<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Allinmedia</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/macau-receives-over-1-million-visitors-in-week-long-national-day-holiday/</link><description>Allinmedia RSS</description><item><title>十一黃金周訪澳日均客量14.3萬升1.9%  10.4單日錄19.1萬創新高</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/%e5%8d%81%e4%b8%80%e9%bb%83%e9%87%91%e5%91%a8%e8%a8%aa%e6%be%b3%e6%97%a5%e5%9d%87%e5%ae%a2%e9%87%8f14-3%e8%90%ac%e5%8d%871-9-10-4%e5%96%ae%e6%97%a5%e9%8c%8419-1%e8%90%ac%e5%89%b5%e6%96%b0%e9%ab%98/</link><description>十一黃金周訪澳旅客共114.4萬人次，按年增加15.3%。(Allin圖片)
內地國慶連中秋節8天假期結束，據澳門治安警察局公佈數據顯示，十一黃金周訪澳旅客共114.4萬人次，相較去年的7天假期增長15.3%；今年日均客量達14.3萬人次，同比去年上升1.9%。而10月4日為入境高峰，訪客量達19.1萬人次，刷新澳門歷來十一黃金周假期的最高紀錄。
今年十一黃金周假期自10月1日起至10月8日結束，澳門總出入境客流量累計553.6萬人次，日均69.2萬人次，同比去年上升2.2%。通關口岸以關閘出入境客流最多，佔全澳50.9%；其後為青茂、橫琴及港珠澳口岸，分別佔15.6%、15.1%及11.3%。
訪澳旅客之中，以內地旅客最多，佔82.4%，此外，香港、台灣及外國旅客則分別佔11.2%、1.4%及5%。
上周六(4日)為入境人數高峰，達19.1萬人次，不過由於颱風麥德姆對澳門的影響，周日的入境入數下跌至11.3萬人次。據早前澳門旅遊局局長文綺華預計，十一黃金周的總客量可達120萬人次，即日均客量15萬人次。</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 16:02:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Three staffers from jewelry store arrested for ‘cashing out credit cards’</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/three-staffers-from-jewelry-store-arrested-for-cashing-out-credit-cards/</link><description>Three staffers from jewelry store arrested for ‘cashing out credit cards’(Allin photo)
Two men and one woman working at a jewelry store in Macau have been arrested for collusion with mainland China money exchange parties to profit from cashing out credit cards, which is a violation of the Anti-Illegal Gambling Crimes Act.
 
According to the judiciary Police, the jewelry store, which is located near a casino at the Cotai Strip, opened for business in February 2024 and has since been disguising its cash-out activities as jewelry sales through fake transactions. The store’s total transactions have exceeded HK$27 million, involving at least HK$540,000 in illicit profits.
 
The case was reported to the Public Security Police on the early morning of October 5 when the police responded to a dispute at a Cotai entertainment venue, revealing that a mainland man had brought customers to a jewelry store in a hotel to cash out using credit cards. The case was then handed over to the Judiciary Police for further investigation as it involved criminal activities related to money exchange.
 
The Judiciary Police arrested three local individuals (two men and one woman) aged between 32 and 48, including a jewelry store manager and two sales staff. The operation seized a cash-checking machine and HK$430,000 in cash, and investigations are ongoing to track down the jewelry store’s owner and other individuals involved in the case.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 15:42:31</pubDate></item><item><title>NBA關懷行動×金沙關懷籃球公益周啟動 藉籃球力量展現關懷</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/nba%e9%97%9c%e6%87%b7%e8%a1%8c%e5%8b%95x%e9%87%91%e6%b2%99%e9%97%9c%e6%87%b7%e7%b1%83%e7%90%83%e5%85%ac%e7%9b%8a%e5%91%a8%e5%95%9f%e5%8b%95-%e8%97%89%e7%b1%83%e7%90%83%e5%8a%9b%e9%87%8f%e5%b1%95/</link><description>「NBA關懷行動×金沙關懷籃球公益周」在威尼斯人綜藝館啟動。(金沙圖片)
全城期待的NBA中國賽2025將於10月10日及12日於威尼斯人綜藝館強勢登場。藉賽事落戶澳門之際，NBA關懷行動(NBA Cares)與金沙關懷攜手於今天(9日)在威尼斯人綜藝館啟動「NBA關懷行動×金沙關懷籃球公益周」，一系列社區活動將邀請多名NBA傳奇球星，包括米治·列治文(Mitch Richmond)、添·夏達威(Tim Hardaway)、姚明、夏恩·馬利安(Shawn Marion)、迪朗·威廉士(Deron Williams)，以及鳳凰城太陽隊及布魯克林籃網隊的現役球員走進社區，以籃球運動為橋樑，促進社區關懷互動，並以關愛傳頌社群。
拉斯維加斯金沙集團總裁兼首席營運總裁Patrick Dumont相信公益周活動將為社區帶來正面影響。(金沙圖片)
在今天的啟動儀式上，拉斯維加斯金沙集團總裁兼首席營運總裁Patrick Dumont表示，「很高興藉着NBA籃球賽事在澳門舉行之際，為大家帶來一連五天的公益周活動，向澳門本地青年及社區有需要的群體予以關懷。我們相信本周活動將為社區帶來正面影響，賽事亦進一步提升澳門作為世界休閒及商務旅遊目的地的地位。」
NBA主席亞當·蕭華期望參加者可享受今次的體育交流，並從中獲得啟發。(金沙圖片)
NBA主席亞當·蕭華(Adam Silver)表示，「今日邀請一眾青年人在威尼斯人綜藝館這個頂尖場館，向NBA傳奇球星及優秀球星學習球技，期望參加者享受今次的體育交流，並從中獲得啟發。」
今次公益周啟動儀式，獲奈史密斯名人堂成員、姚基金理事長姚明親臨現場支持，並邀請了NBA中國賽兩支對陣隊伍鳳凰城太陽隊及布魯克林籃網隊各6名球員及兩名教練參與。期間兩隊的現役球員與一眾與會者分享了他們準備NBA賽季和比賽的實戰經驗和心得，以及對於即將在澳門參與賽事的興奮心情等。
NBA球隊成員為參與活動的澳門學生提供技術指導。(金沙圖片)
今次活動約有100人參與，兩支NBA球隊成員為勞校中學、聖公會(澳門)蔡高中學及澳門粵華中學的澳門學生，以及參與了「NBA關懷行動・女生主場」計劃的鄉村老師及學生逾60人，提供技術指導。
拉斯維加斯金沙集團總裁兼首席營運總裁Patrick Dumont一同參與製作禮品包及健康用品禮包。(金沙圖片)
除此之外，NBA球隊成員更與金沙中國社區義務工作者—金沙中國關懷大使一同為即將舉行的公益周活動，製作禮品包及健康用品禮包。此外，姚明亦即場向所有參與活動的學生送上預先準備的禮品包，為啟動禮劃上圓滿句號。
而公益周首場系列活動「青年校園籃球交流活動」亦已於昨天(8日)率先在勞校中學圓滿舉行，邀請了NBA傳奇球星米治·列治文及NBA教練向澳門及「女生主場」計劃的學生傳授籃球技術，同場上演一場精彩紛呈的五人籃球友誼賽。
公益周於10月8日至12日一連五天舉行，涵蓋一系列多元化社區活動，包括澳門校園籃球交流互動、暖心午餐社區分享活動、籃球社區嘉年華及「女生主場」籃球交流活動，將NBA關懷行動的社區力量延伸至澳門社群，發揮互助互愛精神。</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 18:45:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau hosts first NBA House to warm up for All-Star Game</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/macau-hosts-first-nba-house-to-warm-up-for-all-star-game/</link><description>Macau hosts first NBA House to warm up for All-Star Game(Allin photo)
The NBA, in collaboration with Sands China, is hosting the NBA China Games 2025 presented by Taobao 88VIP, which will take place on October 10 and 12 at the Venetian Macao. The event features a legendary all-star game and a pre-season match between the Brooklyn Nets and the Phoenix Suns.
 
Prior to the games, the organizers have launched a series of side-line activities to engage with the public, including the first-ever NBA House event, which runs for five days starting Wednesday (October 8) at the Venetian Macao’s Cotai Expo A Hall. Admission is free, and the venue will be open from 11 am to 10 pm.
 
This is the first time NBA House is being held in Macau, featuring a theme that includes interactive installations, brand shopping, and a food court, among other elements. Highlights include live basketball activities, an LED basketball fountain, a themed photo area. NBA House has previously been held in Brazil, Canada, France, India, Mexico, the United States, and the United Kingdom. Visitors who entered early expressed that they specially traveled from mainland China to watch the games and were thrilled to learn about the free admission to NBA House, believing that the event enhances fan engagement before the games.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 15:47:40</pubDate></item><item><title>澳娛綜合舉行國慶酒會  盼員工秉承民族奮鬥精神提升自身競爭力</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/%e6%be%b3%e5%a8%9b%e7%b6%9c%e5%90%88%e8%88%89%e8%a1%8c%e5%9c%8b%e6%85%b6%e9%85%92%e6%9c%83-%e7%9b%bc%e5%93%a1%e5%b7%a5%e7%a7%89%e6%89%bf%e6%b0%91%e6%97%8f%e5%a5%ae%e9%ac%a5%e7%b2%be%e7%a5%9e%e6%8f%90/</link><description>澳娛綜合董事和來賓與在場員工舉杯祝酒。(Allin圖片)
澳娛綜合聯同公司的員工福利諮詢委員會、澳娛綜合勞資協商委員會於今天(9日)舉行慶祝中華人民共和國成立76周年國慶酒會，酒會假上葡京禮堂進行，參與的主禮嘉賓包括澳娛綜合董事局主席霍震霆、常務董事何超鳳、董事兼福諮會主席梁安琪、勞資協商委員會顧問黃顯輝，另有逾2,000名員工參與。
澳娛綜合常務董事何超鳳致辭。(Allin圖片)
酒會安排升國旗儀式後，何超鳳上台致辭時表示，澳娛綜合作為澳門經濟及社會發展的重要參與者，秉持「愛國愛澳」初心，積極配合澳門政府「1+4」經濟適度多元策略，以「旅遊+」為核心，推動相關產業跨界深度融合發展；隨着深合區建設全面提速，澳娛綜合積極參與其中，致力把豐富的國際旅遊休閒經驗和創新實力帶到橫琴，助力琴澳一體化，促進區域的「硬聯通、軟聯通、心聯通」。中央政府一直是澳門不斷向前的重要支撑，面向前所未有的發展機遇，她勉勵全體員工以實際行動把握時代脈搏，提升專業技能，培育具澳門特色的新質生產力，以創新思維和優質服務迎接四方賓客，一同講好中國故事、講好澳門故事。
澳娛綜合董事兼福諮會主席梁安琪致辭。(Allin圖片)
隨後，梁安琪在致辭時表示，澳娛綜合一如既往以愛國主題員工活動為載體，推動員工認識祖國，增強員工對國家認同感及民族自豪感，樹立正確的歷史觀、民族觀及國家觀。面對新時代的機遇及挑戰，希望全體員工繼續秉承中華民族的奮鬥精神，不斷提升自身競爭力，將愛國精神同樣用於愛澳、愛崗敬業、奉獻社會的實際行動上，與公司攜手並進，共創美好未來，打造屬於澳門、屬於澳娛綜合的品牌影響力。
澳娛綜合表示，作為澳門首家開展系統化愛國教育課程及紅色之旅的綜合旅遊休閒企業，一直致力透過舉辦各項愛國主題活動，包括全國兩會精神分享會、江西井岡山愛國主義教育培訓課程、「我和我的祖國灣區行」等，深化團隊成員對國家發展的認識，傳承愛國愛澳精神，同時亦體現澳娛綜合對國家發展戰略及澳門政府施政方針的堅定支持。</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 20:14:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau receives over 1 million visitors in week-long National Day holiday</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/09/macau-receives-over-1-million-visitors-in-week-long-national-day-holiday/</link><description>Macau receives over 1 million visitors in week-long National Day holiday(Allin photo))
Macau saw a total of 1.0554 million visitor arrivals during the first 7 days of the National Day Golden Week holiday, representing a year-on-year increase of 7.4%, according to figures released by the Macau Government Tourism Office.
 
Mainland Chinese tourists accounted for 879,700 of total visitor arrivals , with an average of about 125,700 per day, up 7.8% year-on-year. In contrast, Hong Kong visitors totaled 111,100, averaging about 15,900 per day, down 5% year-on-year.
 
UBS released a research report stating that during the first 7 days of the National Day Golden Week Macau received an average of about 151,000 visitors per day, which is a year-on-year increase of about 7%, in line with the expectations of the Macau Government Tourism Office. The growth rate of visitor numbers accelerated further on the 7th day of the Golden Week to about 83%, which is believed to be driven by the 8-day holiday and a low base effect, offsetting the impact of Typhoon Mitag on October 5.
 
Another brokerage firm, Citigroup, indicated that based on industry data, Macau’s gaming revenue during the first 5 days of October is expected to reach about 5.5 billion patacas, which means an average daily gaming revenue of about 1.1 billion patacas during the first 5 days of the National Day Golden Week.
 
Citigroup further noted that on-site observations showed that Typhoon Mitag, which struck on Sunday, had little impact on Macau. They believe that after the Golden Week, Macau’s gaming revenue will be boosted by the NBA China Games and K-pop concerts. They currently maintain their October gaming revenue forecast for Macau at 23 billion patacas, equivalent to 87% of the level in October 2019, representing an 11% year-on-year increase.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 15:39:04</pubDate></item></channel></rss>