<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Allinmedia</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/macau-receives-nearly-790000-visitors-in-first-five-days-of-national-day-golden-week/</link><description>Allinmedia RSS</description><item><title>希爾頓太陽集團加大合作  引進兩大奢華酒店品牌落戶越南</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/%e5%b8%8c%e7%88%be%e9%a0%93%e5%a4%aa%e9%99%bd%e9%9b%86%e5%9c%98%e5%8a%a0%e5%a4%a7%e5%90%88%e4%bd%9c-%e5%bc%95%e9%80%b2%e5%85%a9%e5%a4%a7%e5%a5%a2%e8%8f%af%e9%85%92%e5%ba%97%e5%93%81%e7%89%8c%e8%90%bd/</link><description>希爾頓與太陽集團簽署戰略合作協議，將在廣寧、峴港和富國島建造五家酒店，客房總數超過2,000間。(太陽集團圖片)
外媒報導，美國酒店業巨頭希爾頓(Hilton)與越南開發商太陽集團(Sun Group)簽署戰略合作協議，並確認將在廣寧省、峴港市及富國島開發項目，將引進希爾頓旗下康萊德酒店及度假村(Conrad Hotels &amp; Resorts)與LXR酒店及度假村(LXR Hotels &amp; Resorts)兩大奢華品牌首次落戶越南，屆時將為越南酒店業帶來超過2,000間客房。此次合作是希爾頓針對越南高端旅遊需求增長策略的重要一步。
Chris Nassetta在集團公告中表示：「越南長期以來都是希爾頓在東南亞發展藍圖中的關鍵一環。此次合作集合了希爾頓享譽全球的品牌影響力與太陽集團深厚的本土經驗，旨在打造能夠滿足當代旅客多元化需求的頂級目的地。」
項目位於越南南部的度假勝地富國島，興建一個由康萊德、希爾頓和希爾頓逸林酒店組成的酒店群，提供近2,000間客房，並與新建的會議中心及機場相連，主要為擴大越南的高端旅遊容量，同時為2027年亞太經合組織(APEC)峰會提供支持，屆時越南將接待數以千計的各國代表和國際媒體。
項目是太陽集團整個旅遊與活動綜合區規劃的一部分。太陽集團表示，相關規劃旨在將富國島定位為亞太地區領先的會議及獎勵旅遊(MICE)目的地。此外，整個產業生態圈將得到該開發商旗下新成立的航空公司太陽富國航空(Sun Phu Quoc Airways)的支持。
在越南北部，位於廣寧省的希爾頓度假村(Hilton Quang Hanh Onsen Resort)將以日式溫泉度假村為設計核心，設有216間客房和別墅，提供礦物浴池及康養設施。越南中部則將迎來全國首家LXR酒店及度假村。這家奢華酒店坐落於峴港市漢江沿岸的綠島(Green Island)，其設計將把頂級奢華與在地文化體驗深度融合，進一步擴大希爾頓在東南亞的業務版圖。
繼富國島希爾頓格芮精選酒店(La Festa Phu Quoc – Curio Collection by Hilton)去年開業之後，此次合作標誌着太陽集團與希爾頓集團合作的另一個里程碑。太陽集團董事Dang Minh Truong表示，新一輪項目將有助為融合休閒、娛樂與康養的綜合度假村模式樹立行業新標杆，同時完美融合文化傳承、自然風光與國際化的服務標準。
目前希爾頓旗下擁有25個世界級品牌，在139個國家和地區擁有超過8,800家酒店、近130萬間客房，以及超過2億會員的客戶群。</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 20:47:39</pubDate></item><item><title>珠寶店涉勾結換錢黨誘賭客刷卡套現  三員工被捕涉款至少54萬</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/%e7%8f%a0%e5%af%b6%e5%ba%97%e6%b6%89%e5%8b%be%e7%b5%90%e6%8f%9b%e9%8c%a2%e9%bb%a8%e8%aa%98%e8%b3%ad%e5%ae%a2%e5%88%b7%e5%8d%a1%e5%a5%97%e7%8f%be-%e4%b8%89%e5%93%a1%e5%b7%a5%e8%a2%ab%e6%8d%95%e6%b6%89/</link><description>涉案珠寶店長及兩名銷售員被移交檢察院偵辦。(Allin圖片)
司警偵破一宗涉及「為賭博的不法借貸」和「經營為賭博的不法匯兌」案件。行動先後拘捕3名本地男女，他們任職於路氹賭場附近的珠寶店，包括店長及銷售員，全部涉案人對勾結內地換錢黨刷卡套現賺取差價均知情，自《打擊不法賭博犯罪法》生效至今，店舖交易流水帳總額逾2,700萬港元，涉案金額不少於54萬。
案情指，本周日(5日)凌晨治安警接報到路氹一間娛樂場處理一宗糾紛事件，揭發有內地男子曾招攬客人到酒店內的一間珠寶店刷卡套現，由於內情涉及換錢黨的犯罪行為，轉交司警跟進。
司警調查發現，案件源於姓韋內地高利貸艇仔，疑於賭場中找到內地長者賭客欲借貸博彩，本周一(6日)經其介紹予一名高利貸，雖然借貸事宜最後告吹，但高利貸卻利誘其協助刷卡套現賺取差價，稱聲事成可獲一成回報。長者賭客於是被安排到涉事珠寶店刷卡套現，以約4.15萬人民幣套現4.3萬港元，長者賭客收取6,000元酬勞輸光後，高利貸將5萬元人民幣轉入其內地帳戶，要求再到珠寶店刷卡，惟長者賭客害怕是黑錢而拒絕要求，雙方發生糾紛，繼而驚動治安警介入。
司警接手案件後，發現涉事珠寶店自2024年2月開業至今，以售賣珠寶作掩飾，透過虛假交易替客人刷卡套現，從《打擊不法賭博犯罪法》生效至今，店舖交易流水帳總額逾2,700萬港元，從中涉及不法獲利至少54萬港元。
司警經調查拘捕姓李、姓洪和姓林兩男一女木地疑犯，年齡介乎32至48歲，分屬珠寶店店長及兩名銷售員，行動檢獲驗鈔機及43萬澳門元現金等，司警現正追查涉事珠寶店東主、在逃高利貸和其他涉案人士，案件移送檢察院偵辦。</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 18:57:19</pubDate></item><item><title>黃金周首7天訪澳旅客錄105.5萬  花旗維持10月賭收230億預測</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/%e9%bb%83%e9%87%91%e5%91%a8%e9%a6%967%e5%a4%a9%e8%a8%aa%e6%be%b3%e6%97%85%e5%ae%a2%e9%8c%84105-5%e8%90%ac-%e8%8a%b1%e6%97%97%e7%b6%ad%e6%8c%8110%e6%9c%88%e8%b3%ad%e6%94%b6230%e5%84%84%e9%a0%90/</link><description>十一黃金周首7天訪澳旅客錄105.54萬人次，其中內地客佔83.2%。(Allin圖片)
澳門旅遊局公佈，十一黃金周8日假期中首7日訪澳旅客錄105.54萬人次，日均旅客15.07萬人次，按年增加7.4%。期內內地旅客佔87.97萬人次，日均約12.57萬人次，按年增加7.8%。至於香港旅客則佔11.11萬人次，日均約1.59萬人次，按年跌5%。
瑞銀發表研究報告指，澳門國慶黃金周首7天，平均每日接待約15.1萬名旅客，按年增長約7%，符合澳門旅遊局的預期，其中旅客量增幅在黃金周第7天進一步加快至約83%，相信是由於今年黃金周假期長達8日以及低基數的推動，抵銷了10月5日颱風麥德姆所帶來的影響。
另一券商花旗的研究報告則指，根據行業數據，預料10月首5天澳門博彩收入達到約55億元(澳門元、下同），即國慶黃金周首5天日均賭收約11億元。
花旗又指，實地考察發現，周日吹襲的颱風麥德姆對澳門影響不大，相信黃金周過後澳門博彩收入將受到NBA中國賽及韓星演唱會活動推動，目前維持10月澳門賭收預測為230億元不變，相當於疫前2019年10月水平的87%，即按年增長11%。</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 18:49:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands China’s parent company shuts down online casino business</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/sands-chinas-parent-company-shuts-down-online-casino-business/</link><description>Sands China's parent company shuts down online casino business(Allin photo)
Las Vegas Sands Corporation (LVS), the parent company of Sands China, has confirmed the closure of its online gambling business. The decision to shut down Sands Digital Services was reached earlier this week after company executives determined the project was not a good strategic fit for the company, according to foreign media reports.
 
Sands executives emphasize that the group’s strategic focus remains on core markets in Asia. In Macau, Sands continues to operate several large integrated resorts, including The Venetian and The Londoner, while continuously investing new capital according to new licensing requirements.
 
The closure of the online gambling business will result in the elimination of about 300 to 400 positions, with approximately 150 based in Las Vegas. This project was initially intended to provide live dealer services for legalized online gambling states, including New Jersey, Michigan, Pennsylvania, Connecticut, Delaware, and West Virginia.
 
In 2021, Sands acquired related assets of Qbet (online gambling gaming software) to formally enter the field. Its strategic goal was to seize opportunities in regulated online gambling markets
 
Despite the end of the online gambling experiment, LVS said it will continue to evaluate technology and innovation projects that complement its hotel and gambling operations.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 17:00:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City launches world’s first integrated resort medical center equipped with MRI and CT services</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/studio-city-launches-worlds-first-integrated-resort-medical-center-equipped-with-mri-and-ct-services/</link><description>Studio City launches world's first integrated resort medical center equipped with MRI and CT services
The Studio City Medical Center officially opened on Monday (October 6), becoming the world’s first and Macau’s only integrated resort hospital equipped with MRI and CT services. By creating a comprehensive medical ecosystem, it strategically complements Macau’s existing world-class services and further enhances tourism infrastructure, marking an important milestone in Macau’s journey towards becoming a global leader in medical tourism. 
 
The center offers a first-class experience in medical care, wellness, and entertainment in partnership with Hong Kong’s largest MRI diagnostic service provider, iRad. 
 
Located on the second floor of Studio City and covering more than 12,000 square feet, the new facility will provide world-class health check-ups, diagnostic imaging, medical aesthetics, anti-aging treatments, and medical concierge services. This revolutionary medical concept will usher in a new era of medical tourism in Macau.

The new iRad Hospital aims to meet the growing global demand for quality medical services and capitalize on the continuous increase in the number of visitors to Macau. By offering advanced medical tourism experiences, it seeks to attract regional and international travelers, encouraging them to extend their stay in Macau and increase their spending. Simultaneously, it aims to attract long-term clientele through exceptional medical tourism experiences.
 
The new hospital’s opening ceremony featured dozens of guests of honor including Mr. Lo Iek Long, Director for Department of Health of the Macao SAR; Ms. Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, Director of Macau Government Tourism Office; Mr. Che Weng Keong, President of the Commerce and Investment Promotion Institute of the Macao SAR and Mr. Sun Yaohua, Director of the Economic Affairs Department of the Liaison Office of the Central People’s Government in the Macao SAR.

In his speech, Melco Chairman, Mr Lawrence Ho, stated that by launching the world’s first and Macau’s only hospital located within an integrated resort, equipped with MRI and CT services, Melco aims to contribute to the development of medical tourism in Macau. This initiative perfectly aligns with the Macau SAR government’s “1+4” economic diversification strategy.
 
Additionally, Ho expressed heartfelt gratitude to the Macau government for its support and guidance throughout the project development process. He emphasized that the group’s goal is to provide guests with a world-class destination for integrated entertainment and wellness, reinforcing Macau’s position as a leading center for medical and wellness tourism in the region. This initiative also aims to promote local economic development and create valuable job opportunities for the community.

Mr. Dennis Tam, Honorary Chairman of iRad, expressed his honor in partnering with Melco to launch Macau’s first medical project. He highlighted that this initiative represents a significant contribution to supporting the Macau government’s strategic goal of building a national-level regional medical center.

As a leading private diagnostic medical group in Hong Kong, iRad believes this health project will set a new benchmark for excellence in Macau’s healthcare, attracting patients and visitors from both local and international regions.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 10:57:35</pubDate></item><item><title>勞工局10月續夥6博企辦配對會供546職缺  餐飲房務前線營運為主</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/%e5%8b%9e%e5%b7%a5%e5%b1%8010%e6%9c%88%e7%ba%8c%e5%a4%a56%e5%8d%9a%e4%bc%81%e8%be%a6%e9%85%8d%e5%b0%8d%e6%9c%83%e4%be%9b546%e8%81%b7%e7%bc%ba-%e9%a4%90%e9%a3%b2%e6%88%bf%e5%8b%99%e5%89%8d%e7%b7%9a/</link><description>勞工局10月續辦休閒企業配對會，共546個職缺可供配對。(Allin圖片)
澳門勞工局10月份繼續與6間綜合度假休閒企業合作，推出至少6場配對會，為有就業需求的澳門居民提供合共546個職位空缺，報名日期由10月9日至25日。
是次可供配對的職位空缺合共546個，由6間休閒企業旗下酒店及餐飲場所的前線及後勤多個業務部門提供，崗位主要分佈於「餐飲類」、「房務及清潔類」及「前線營運類」三大類，佔總空缺約七成三。
此外，是次配對會亦涉及部分管理及專業技術類別崗位，包括銷售部助理總監/高級經理、資訊科技部經理/助理經理/高級分析員、市場部分析師、內部審計員和多個不同菜系的副主廚/廚師等。
由10月9日至25日期間，有意應徵的澳門居民可登入勞工局網站或登入一戶通並進入「求職服務」頁面，點擊「休閒企業配對會」，即可瀏覧及應徵崗位，當報名接納後符合條件者將由企業安排約見。
各間企業首場配對會安排如下：10月16日(銀河娛樂集團、美高梅)、10月21日(新濠博亞)、10月23日(金沙中國)、10月27日(永利)和10月31日(澳娛綜合)。除上述安排外，各間企業會因應參與配對的人數作出其他時間的安排，具體場地、面試日期及時間，由企業以電話或短訊通知。</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 16:28:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau receives nearly 790,000 visitors in first five days of National Day Golden Week</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/08/macau-receives-nearly-790000-visitors-in-first-five-days-of-national-day-golden-week/</link><description>Macau receives nearly 790,000 visitors in first five days of National Day Golden Week(Allin photo)
During the first five days of the National Day holiday (October 1 to 5), Macau recorded a total of approximately 3.578 million entries and exits, an increase of 2.1% compared to the same period last year. The total number of travelers visiting Macau during these five days was 789,000.
 
October 4 saw the highest entry peak, with over 191,000 visitors, while due to the typhoon’s impact, only about 112,000 entries were recorded on Sunday (October 5). The average daily passenger volume during this period was over 157,000.
 
From October 1 to 5, there were 678,000 incoming travelers from the mainland, with the highest entry recorded on the fourth day at 164,000. Hong Kong travelers totaled 70,000, with the highest entry on the fourth day at 16,000.
 
During this period, the total entries and exits at the Gongbei checkpoint amounted to approximately 1.859 million, an increase of 0.5% year-on-year, averaging about 372,000 entries and exits daily. At the Qingmao Port, there were about 544,000 entries and exits, a 1% increase year-on-year, averaging approximately 109,000 daily. The Hengqin-Macau Port recorded about 535,000 entries and exits, a 16.6% increase year-on-year, averaging around 107,000 daily. The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge Port saw approximately 398,000 entries and exits, a 4.2% increase compared to the same period last year, averaging about 80,000 daily.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 17:08:13</pubDate></item></channel></rss>