<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Allinmedia</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/27/%e7%be%8e%e9%ab%98%e6%a2%85%e8%8f%af%e5%ba%9c%e9%85%92%e5%ba%97%e6%98%8e%e5%b9%b4%e9%80%b2%e9%a7%90%e9%9d%92%e5%b3%b6-%e6%8e%a5%e6%a3%92%e9%9d%92%e5%b3%b6%e9%87%a3%e9%ad%9a%e5%8f%b0%e6%88%90%e5%93%81/</link><description>Allinmedia RSS</description><item><title>Marina Bay Sands Annual EBITDA Forecast: Expected to exceed $2.5 billion in 2025</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/27/marina-bay-sands-annual-ebitda-forecast-expected-to-exceed-2-5-billion-in-2025/</link><description>Marina Bay Sands Annual EBITDA Forecast: Expected to exceed $2.5 billion in 2025(Allin Photo)
Las Vegas Sands (LVS), parent company of Sands China, has announced its third-quarter results, with Marina Bay Sands in Singapore posting an adjusted property EBITDA of $743 million for the quarter, an 83% year-on-year increase.
According to foreign media reports, LVS Chairman and CEO Rob Goldstein stated during a conference call that the group’s EBITDA forecast for Marina Bay Sands was overly conservative, believing that the property could easily exceed $2.5 billion this year.
Rob Goldstein further noted that the group had previously predicted an annual EBITDA of $2.5 billion for Marina Bay Sands, but results indicated that this was too conservative, as the EBITDA so far this year had already surpassed $2.1 billion, with one quarter still to be accounted for.
Meanwhile the revenue from table games and slot machines in the third quarter reached a record high of $905 million, which is a 122% increase compared to the third quarter of 2019 and a 35% increase from the same period last year. He stated that the group had launched appropriate products under favorable conditions, and the operational performance of Marina Bay Sands was unprecedented in industry history, believing that the current growth of its EBITDA is highly sustainable.
Rob Goldstein remarked, “If two years ago someone had said we would achieve $700 million every quarter by 2025, I would have said that was ambitious. However, looking back, it has gone quite smoothly, and recent quarters have performed exceptionally well.” He also expressed confidence in the long-term sustainability of the Singapore market, adding that increasing the proportion of suites and adjusting the previous configuration dominated by standard rooms was a very wise move.
Furthermore, Rob Goldstein pointed out that the introduction of side bets in Singapore and Macau has transformed baccarat from a game previously described as dull and lacking excitement, bringing it closer to a sports betting model with various themed bets and side bets.
Sands China CEO and President Cheng Junlu also mentioned during the conference call that the types and proportions of side bets in Macau are still lower than in Singapore, but are on the rise, which has contributed to an increase in the banker’s advantage over the past few years.
Management also responded during the call regarding the recent NBA preseason held at the Venetian Macao. Patrick Dumont stated that the specific impact of this event on Sands China’s gaming and entertainment business would be explained at the end of this quarter, at which point the data would be more complete. He added that overall, the event was very successful and they were very satisfied with the results, noting the considerable marketing value it brought.
Regarding overseas development, when asked whether Sands would reconsider the Japanese market or invest in the UAE, LVS President and COO Patrick Dumont stated that the group continues to pay attention to both locations, but currently has no specific plans. He continued that the group’s strategic focus is to direct capital towards high-growth projects, continuously evaluating opportunities and ensuring that they have the appropriate safety margin to secure investment returns.</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 16:36:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau’s visitor arrivals hit 29.67 million in first 9 months</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/27/macaus-visitor-arrivals-hit-29-67-million-in-first-9-months/</link><description>Macau’s visitor arrivals hit 29.67 million in first 9 months
The total number of incoming visitors to Macau in the first three quarters of this year reached 29.671 million, a year-on-year increase of 14.5%, according to data from the Macau Statistics and Census Service.
Mainland visitors accounted for 72.7% of Macau’s total visitor arrivals, while international visitors made up nearly 6.4% of the total, with the remainder being from Hong Kong and Taiwan. In September alone, the number of incoming visitors was 2.775 million, representing a year-on-year increase of 9.8%.
In the first three quarters, the number of same-day visitors was approximately 17.279 million, while overnight visitors totaled about 12.393 million, reflecting increases of 24.9% and 2.5%, respectively, compared to the same period last year. Due to the rise in the proportion of same-day visitors, the average length of stay for visitors decreased by 0.1 days to 1.1 days year-on-year; the average length of stay remained unchanged for same-day visitors (0.2 days) and overnight visitors (2.3 days).
In the first three quarters, international visitors rose by 12.4% year-on-year to 1.886 million. In the Southeast Asian market, the Philippines recorded 383,000 visitors, Indonesia 146,000, Malaysia 121,000, and Thailand 115,000, with year-on-year increases of 10.8%, 14.6%, 3.1%, and 20.8%, respectively. From South Asia, India recorded 81,000 visitors, a year-on-year increase of 5%. In Northeast Asia, South Korea recorded 382,000 visitors and Japan 116,000, with year-on-year increases of 12% and 25%, respectively. Among long-distance travelers, visitors from the United States totaled 112,000, an increase of 8.7% year-on-year.
In September alone, the total number of incoming visitors to Macau was 2.775 million, including 1.562 million same-day visitors, which marked a year-on-year increase of 19.4%, while overnight visitors totaled 1.214 million, showing a year-on-year decrease of 0.5%. The average length of stay for visitors decreased by 0.1 days to 1.2 days year-on-year; the average length of stay remained unchanged for same-day visitors (0.2 days) and overnight visitors (2.5 days).</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 16:32:06</pubDate></item><item><title>衞星場英皇宮殿華都相繼月底提早結業  賭枱博彩機撥歸所屬博企</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/27/%e8%a1%9e%e6%98%9f%e5%a0%b4%e8%8b%b1%e7%9a%87%e5%ae%ae%e6%ae%bf%e8%8f%af%e9%83%bd%e7%9b%b8%e7%b9%bc%e6%9c%88%e5%ba%95%e6%8f%90%e6%97%a9%e7%b5%90%e6%a5%ad-%e8%b3%ad%e6%9e%b1%e5%8d%9a%e5%bd%a9%e6%a9%9f/</link><description>澳娛綜合旗下的英皇宮殿娛樂場(左)本周四將終止營業；銀娛旗下華都娛樂場(右)亦於本周五終止營運。(Allin圖片)
澳門衞星場過渡期年底結束，再有兩間衞星場提前結業。銀河娛樂(27)及澳博控股(880)旗下的澳娛綜合於今天(27日)先後公佈，銀娛旗下華都娛樂場將於本周五(31日)終止營運；而澳博旗下英皇宮殿娛樂場則於本周四(30日)終止營業；兩間娛樂場的賭枱及博彩機將重新調配至所屬公司經營的其他娛樂場運作。澳門博監局亦表示，將嚴格監督相關娛樂場的停運程序，確保過程平穩有序，各項法定程序均妥善執行。
銀娛表示，基於商業考量及經澳門政府批准旗下銀河娛樂場股份有限公司所營運的華都娛樂場將於本月31日晚上11時59分起終止營運。有關華都的終止營運安排，銀娛正與博監局保持緊密溝通，並根據法律規定有序推進相關程序。經博監局批准，華都的博彩桌會調配至銀娛旗下其他娛樂場繼續運作。
此外，銀娛將按營運需要，調派華都娛樂場的本地團隊成員到旗下其他娛樂場或非博彩範疇繼續工作，所有聘用條件維持不變；同時將提供一系列職業培訓，協助相關員工適應新的工作環境，確保其穩定就業。
至於華都娛樂場籌碼的後續安排，自11月1日起，客人可帶同印有銀河華都標誌的有效籌碼，前往澳門銀河娛樂場或星際娛樂場指定櫃枱辦理兌換。
銀娛表示，衷心感謝澳門政府、市民、顧客及各界人士多年來對銀娛的愛戴及支持，並會一如既往，繼續致力為澳門的旅遊休閒事業作出貢獻。華都娛樂場為其旗下「城市娛樂會」三個娛樂場之一，其餘兩間為總統及利澳娛樂場，均於2022年6月16日結業。
另一博企澳娛綜合表示，經與政府部門及相關娛樂場服務提供者協調，英皇宮殿將於本周四(30日)23時59分起終止營運。原設於該場地的博彩桌及博彩機將重新調配至公司經營的其他娛樂場繼續運作。如顧客於英皇宮殿停止營運後，仍持有該娛樂場的未兌換籌碼、存款或積存現金回贈，本月31日起可前往澳娛綜合所經營的其他娛樂場辦理跟進安排。
員工安排方面，所有由澳娛綜合聘用的本地僱員將繼續受僱，並按營運需要妥善調派至公司的其他娛樂場從事博彩相關工作；而在英皇宮殿娛樂場服務的非澳娛綜合聘用的本地僱員，將獲邀申請集團內的相關空缺崗位，並可在相同條件下獲優先聘用，並視乎實際情況提供所需支援。澳娛綜合表示：「將根據法律規定有序推進所需安排，確保各項工作順利銜接，並一如既往履行企業責任，與澳門社會共同推動博彩業的穩健發展。」
澳博旗下原有9間衞星場，早前自7月君怡娛樂場結業後，連同英皇宮殿在內僅有7間衞星場踏入10月仍繼續營運。惟上月底Allin記者曾到英皇宮殿視察，發現二至五樓樓層的賭枱部已關閉，僅剩博彩機仍開放。
澳門博監局今天亦發新聞稿表示，在英皇宮殿及華都娛樂場正式停運時，博監局將派員到場實地監察整個停運程序，確保澳娛綜合及銀娛按照其提交政府的處理方案結束相關衞星場的營運，並有序妥善處理帳房內的現金及籌碼，以及倘有的未兌換現金券、籌碼兌換以及博彩機累積獎金彩池、未兌換博彩機代金券等事宜。在協調英皇宮殿及華都的關場安排中，局方與相關部門保持緊密合作，確保各環節能順利進行。
對於英皇宮殿娛樂場的71名僱員以及華都娛樂場的111名僱員安排，博監局將與勞工事務局繼續保持密切聯繫，確保澳娛綜合及銀娛嚴格履行承諾，按早前提交之方案妥善安置相關僱員，並切實保障有關僱員的薪酬福利及工作條件，提供轉職機會以保障其持續就業。</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 20:13:11</pubDate></item><item><title>美高梅華府酒店明年進駐青島  接棒青島釣魚台成品牌矚目成員</title><link>https://www.allinmedia.com.hk/2025/10/27/%e7%be%8e%e9%ab%98%e6%a2%85%e8%8f%af%e5%ba%9c%e9%85%92%e5%ba%97%e6%98%8e%e5%b9%b4%e9%80%b2%e9%a7%90%e9%9d%92%e5%b3%b6-%e6%8e%a5%e6%a3%92%e9%9d%92%e5%b3%b6%e9%87%a3%e9%ad%9a%e5%8f%b0%e6%88%90%e5%93%81/</link><description>青島釣魚台酒店即將升級為青島美高梅華府酒。(釣魚台美高梅酒店集團圖片)
美高梅國際酒店集團旗下美高梅華府(MGM Reserve)公佈，2026年1月1日青島釣魚台酒店即將升級為青島美高梅華府酒店(MGM Reserve QingDao)，成為美高梅系列品牌又一矚目成員。
美高梅國際飯店集團中國區酒店總裁周鋒(Fred Zhou)表示：「青島是中國極具活力的沿海國際都市，也是集團戰略版圖中的關鍵市場。作為集團佈局青島高端文旅市場的重要項目，青島美高梅華府酒店不僅是品牌定位的有力實踐，更是我們對話青島城市底蘊的重要載體。」
美高梅又指，青島美高梅華府酒店力求成為青島文化的窗口，聚焦山海文化的深度演繹與特色體驗，為青島酒店市場持續打造具有中國文化內涵的優秀標桿，進一步提升美高梅系列酒店在青島的綜合影響。
在酒店的空間與體驗設計中，東方美學與國際脈絡交融，山海意境與當代表達呼應。透過細緻入微的待客禮遇呈現極具個性化的入住體驗，從高品質服務、優雅愜意的居住環境、到以嶗山特色山海食材烹製的精美餐食，皆融匯嶗山的養生文化與自然底蘊，為賓客打造環保健康的生活方式與難忘的旅居時光。
青島釣魚台酒店於2023年6月正式開幕，與青島美高梅酒店同時推出，被喻為「雙品牌」項目，擁有116間客房，屬釣魚台美高梅酒店集團旗下。據官方網站顯示，目前集團發展及經營有7個酒店品牌，分別是寶麗嘉、美高梅華府、釣魚台、美高梅、美高梅美幻、美高梅美薈以及美高梅麥思精選，同是開展品牌住宅業務。</description><pubDate>2025-10-27 21:18:25</pubDate></item></channel></rss>