<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>ASEAN | Malaysia calls for the largest union in the face of US tariffs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/asean-malasia-apela-a-maior-uniao-face-a-tarifas-dos-eua/</link><description>Southeast Asia should accelerate economic integration, diversify markets, and remain united in the face of disturbances in global trade resulting from US tariffs, said the head of Malaysian diplomacy yesterday.
Malaon Foreign Minister Mohamad Hasan spoke during the opening of the first annual summit of heads of state and government of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) in Kuala Lumpur.
"ASEAN countries are among the most affected by US -imposed tariffs. Trade war between the US and China is drastically disturbing production and commerce standards around the world," said Mohamad.
The diplomat even admitted that "it is likely that there is a global economic slowdown." "We must take advantage of this moment to deepen regional economic integration, so we can better protect our region from external shocks," added Mohamad.
ASEAN countries, many of which depend on exports to the US, are suffering from tariffs ranging from 10 percent and 49 percent. Six of the association's ten member countries were among the most affected, with tariffs ranging from 32 percent and 49 percent.
ASEAN has unsuccessfully attempted to mark an initial meeting with the US as a block. ASEAN's unit is crucial, as the region deals with the impacts of climate change and the disturbance caused by the use of artificial intelligence and other unregulated technologies for criminal purposes, Mohamad said.
The diplomat added that Asean, whose rotary presidency belongs to Malaysia, will be tested by external pressure, including a rivalry between superpowers. "External pressures are increasing, and the scope of challenges has never been so big," said Mohamad. "Therefore, it is crucial that we reinforce the bonds that unite us, so that they do not disqual to external pressures. For Asean, unity is now more important than ever," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:09:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | Tai Kin IP took stock of the implementation of Xi speeches</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/pequim-tai-kin-ip-fez-balanco-da-implementacao-de-discursos-de-xi/</link><description>Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, led a delegation on a trip to Beijing to visit ministries and commissions from central authorities. On Friday, the secretary met with the Hong Kong and Macao Work Office director of the China Communist Party Central Committee (CCP) and the Hong Kong and Macao Staff of the Council of State, Xia Baolong.
According to the secretary's office, Tai Kin IP informed Xia Baolong “about the situation of the scrupulous implementation of the spirit consecrated in President XI Jinping's important speeches”, as well as the political objectives in the area of ​​Sam Hou Fai's economy and finance. Among the goals to be achieved, the Government of MSAR emphasizes the proper diversification of the economy, the construction of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin and the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau, as well as "supporting the state to open to the world to a higher level and support the qualitative development of companies and residents."
During his stay in Beijing, the MSar entourage visited the National Commission for Development and Reform, the Ministry of Science and Technology, the Ministry of Industry and Technologies, the Ministry of Finance, the Popular Bank of China, among other bodies of the central authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:26:31</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI | Confirmed suspended arrest of six months to doctoral student</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/tsi-confirmada-prisao-suspensa-de-seis-meses-para-doutorando/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance (TSI) confirmed the sentence to six months in prison to the student at a local university, who tried to corrupt the thesis advisor with 8 thousand patacas. Confirmation of the conviction was released on Friday by the courts of MSAR. The penalty was suspended for two years, due to the payment of 15 thousand patacas to the MSAR.
Despite entering an unidentified local college in August 2020 and having as a deadline for the delivery of the PhD Thesis May 2023, the student only began to discuss the structure of work with the advisor in March 2023. Presenting a project that did not meet the advisor's requirements, and in view of the prospects of not being approved, the student placed an 8,000 -borrowed red envelope inside a book Advisor, leaving this book in the advisor's mailbox.
However, the teacher refused the offer and eventually complained to the authorities. This was not the student's first monetary offer to the teacher. In 2020, the student had offered valleys and money to the tutor, who, in turn, refused the offer and warned the student that the behavior was illegal and possibly constituted the crime of corruption.
With the following case to the courts, the first instance sentenced the student for the crime of active corruption, with a sentence of arrest of six months, suspended for two years, and the payment of 15,000 patacas to the MSAR.
The defendant resorted to the conviction for arguing that the money had been offered to “obtain more academic guidance” and never with the purpose of corrupting the teacher to facilitate the approval of the thesis. However, the TSI declined the arguments and maintained the condemnation of the first instance.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:40:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix Museum | Competition illustrations can be seen until September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/museu-do-grande-premio-ilustracoes-de-concurso-podem-ser-vistas-ate-setembro/</link><description>The winning works of the Illustration Contest of the Gaining Car of Asia's first major award (Macau) are available for public viewing at a Macao Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) museum until September 1st. The contest awards were awarded last Friday, in an organization of the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) and Macau Creatations Limited.
In total, 30 prizes were delivered. The contest had as its main theme the Triumph TR2, the winning car of the first major prize of Macao. In total, 88 works were received, which received more than 10,000 online votes from the public. An evaluation committee also chose the first three classifieds of the group of secondary education candidates and the open group. The contest were also the categories of “most popular internet”, “Merit Awards” and “Finalist Awards”.
In the secondary education group, the winners were Chan Hei Wo, in the first place, followed by Leong Sam U and Ma Nim Ian, as third classified. In turn, in the open group, he won Tam Iok Meng, Lam Si Cheng, in second place and Cheang Ka Ian, in third place.
The exhibition that is now evident in the museum's basement allows “the public to enjoy the award-winning creative and theme artistic works”, and through the illustration, “the public can also feel the precious history of the Macao Grand Prix”, reads in an official note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:01:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Inflation in Macau is 0.23% in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/economia-inflacao-em-macau-fixa-se-em-023-em-abril/</link><description>The consumer price index in Macau rose 0.23 percent in April, in annual terms. The section of leisure, recreation, sport and culture was the one that recorded the largest monthly price increase, 2.47 percent, due to the inflation of the hotel rooms. In the first four months of the year, the price index grew 0.17 percent compared to the same period as 2024
 
Last April the Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 0.23 percentage points compared to April 2024, and 0.16 percent compared to the previous month, according to data released on Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
Prices of the leisure, recreation, sport and culture section increased by 2.47 percent compared to April 2024, mainly driven by the climb of hotel room prices.
The price index of the food products and non-alcoholic beverages grew 0.48 percent in the month under analysis, "thanks to the climbing price of meal acquired away from home and" Take-Away "," the same source added. In monthly terms, the prices of non-alcoholic food and beverages have slightly descended from March (0.04 percent), because the additions of meal prices acquired outside the home and “take-away” did not completely compensate for fresh fish prices, fresh and fruit products and fruit products ”.
Spring-summer fashion
With regard to housing and fuels, DSEC data demonstrates an annual climb was 0.21 percent due to an increase in home rents.
In the section of clothing and footwear, DSEC indicated that prices rose 0.78 percent in April compared to the previous month, "thanks to the launch of summer clothing." Still, in annual terms the clothing and shoe section fell 2.35 percent.
While in transport the monthly climb was 0.42 percent due to “the increase in airplane ticket prices”, although annual comparison, a break of 1.67 percent was verified. On the other hand, in the fourth month of the year, an annual drop in information and communication prices (-3.01 percent) was recorded, a section that also registered a monthly break of 0.07 percent.
DSEC also indicated that in the 12 months ended in April, the IPC rose 0.42 percent over the immediately preceding 12 months. During this period, the sections that “had the most notable additions” were various products and services (+2.47 percent), education (+2.21 percent) and health (+1.62 percent). In the opposite direction, transports fell 3 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:39:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro | Government denies delays in building the east line</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/metro-governo-nega-atrasos-na-construcao-da-linha-leste/</link><description>In the best scenario, the opening of the new Metro line will take place in July 2029. The construction works of the north and southern segments of the East Line are evaluated at 9.3 billion patacas, but infrastructure costs will be borne by 2031
 
The Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) states that the construction of the eastern Metro Line has a “good progress” and that the conclusion in the first quarter of 2028 is provided. In a statement issued on Saturday, DSOP acknowledged that the southern and northern east line works will cost about 9.3 billion patacas, according to the price of adjudication.
"The construction works of the east line of the Light Metro began in the third quarter of 2023, scheduled for the first quarter of 2028," was informed by DSOP. Nevertheless, the opening of the line to circulation should only happen after July 2029, given the need to do the circulation tests of the subway. "Subsequently, commissioning and testing of the circulation system will be performed, and the East Line project is advancing towards the purpose of gathering the conditions for its entry into the second half of 2029," he was explained.
"Like the bar line, the Hengqin line and the Pai Van Seac line that were completed recently, after the construction works were completed, were still subject to the installation of the circulation system and the tests to have conditions of operation," was indicated. "Taking as reference the conclusion, within the expected period and without delays, of the three lines of the light meter, the East Line's work plan is viable," he was added.
41 percent progress
Regarding the works of the southern and northern segments of the East Line, the cost of adjudication was 9,281 million patacas, being “being paid according to the progress of the work”.
Although the works are completed until 2028, DSOP explained that the payments will be extended by 2031, which was justified with the fact that some works are only “performed after the east line operates.
Government communication also served to make a point of situations, indicating that the work is completed at 41 percent. "Currently, the works related to the circulation system have already begun, while the construction work of underground stations, the tunnel using tuning and the linked mud binding viaducts are also underway, and the work of some mandatory goals has been completed in advance," was revealed. "At this stage, the completion of the global project is concluded by about 41 percent and its progress and budget are as expected," he was nominated.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:35:51</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ | Promised helps to students from Macau who study at Harvard</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/dsedj-prometida-ajuda-a-alunos-de-macau-que-estudam-em-harvard/</link><description>Given the hypothesis of Macao students being affected by the conflict between Donald Trump and Harvard University, DSEDJ said it has contacted students and asked local universities to accommodate students to accommodate students
 
The Macao government said it has offered help to young places studying at Harvard University after US President Donald Trump suspending foreign students enrollment at the institution.
The Board of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) said in a statement issued on Saturday that he contacted Macao students at Harvard "to provide permanent counseling and assistance." On Friday, a federal judge in Boston, Massachusetts, temporarily blocked the Trump administration's decision to suspend foreign students at Harvard University.
DSEDJ said it "is closely following the last developments," but stressed that "circumstances are still changing." Still, the Board encouraged Macao universities to provide methods of "convenient transfer" to those affected to "protect students' rights to continue their studies."
"Any concrete measure will be decided by each university in accordance with the actual conditions," said the DSEDJ. On the other hand, the tutelage promised to “continue to promote Macao universities and attract exceptional students from around the world” to promote the internationalization of higher education in the territory.
Example
On Friday, a university in the neighboring region of Hong Kong had already promised to facilitate the registration of students from Harvard University.
Hong Kong University of Science and Technology has promised "unconditional offers, simplified admission procedures and academic support to facilitate a soft transition." The proposed benefits include “accelerated admissions, credit transfers and personalized support” in visa and accommodation assistance, according to a statement.
On Thursday, the US government prohibited Harvard from continuing to enroll foreign students and indicated to those who are already transferred to other universities at risk of losing their immigration status. The university, the most prestigious in the United States, responded to the executive with a judicial action.
Judge Allison D. Burroughs accepted Harvard's temporary suspension of the revocation of permission to welcome international students, representing a quarter of the institution's total students. "Harvard has shown that without a request to temporarily restrict [the Order of Trump], it will suffer immediate and irreparable damage," the judge noted.
The magistrate scheduled an audience about the case for tomorrow, which will be attended by representatives on both sides. Harvard sued the republican government in April to recover his frozen federal financing of $ 2.6 billion for alleged anti-Semite behaviors.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Meeting with 50 consular representatives</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/cooperacao-reuniao-com-50-representantes-consulares/</link><description>The Chief Executive had dinner on Friday with representatives of consulates of about 50 countries and international organizations to those who stressed the mission of establishing an international cooperation platform. Sam Hou Fai stressed the importance of strengthening economic, commercial and cultural ties
 
The Government of MSAR organized a reception and dinner on Friday, which was attended by representatives of consulates generals of about 50 countries and international organizations. In the speech at the reception to the representatives, Sam Hou Fai said that "Macau is committed to building an international cooperation platform", and a "high quality abroad opening platform." The leader of the MSA has indicated that the goal is to make Macau "in an important window for mutual exchange and learning between Chinese civilization and Western civilization."
Addressing the international guests, Sam Hou Fai pointed to economic and commercial cooperation, cultural exchange and the connection of people between Macau and those countries, and ensured that its executive will articulate with the national development strategy, “with the driving force the innovation of legal regimes and the optimization of policies”. The goal is to “coordinate the common progress of the government and the market, from Macao and the world, in favor of building a more inclusive, more convenient, and more effective international exchange platform”.
Sam Hou Fai also linked the commitment of his executive in the “reform of public administration, the constant elevation of the efficiency of governance, the innovation of the concept of serving”, and in the creation of “an environment that further facilitates the lives of people and companies”.
The ruler also indicated that all countries and regions are welcome to take advantage of the role of Macao as an international cooperation platform, and invited "companies and tourists from all countries" to "experience the vitality of the development of Macao and China."
Widen the circle
The chief executive also mentioned some of the typical political concepts of MSAR, such as the idea that the principle "one country, two systems" "demonstrates worldwide notable successes." After highlighting the imperative need to ensure sovereignty and national security, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the importance of ensuring “fully a high degree of macao autonomy, keeping the capitalist system and their way of living, its status of International and Autonomous Customs, and the Continental European Law System in Macau”.
The head of executing said that "Macau is willing to share development opportunities with all countries and regions, widening the" circle of friends "to achieve increasingly comprehensive cooperation."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nanfang Media | Guangdong Group creates platform with Portugal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/nanfang-media-grupo-de-guangdong-cria-plataforma-com-portugal/</link><description>On Friday, a media cooperation platform was launched, promoted by the Nanfang Media group, based in Guangdong and offices in Macau. The “Chinese-Portuguese Platform of Media Contents to the Great Bay” aims to “reform media cooperation and facilitate the exchange of cultural news and content between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”
 
A new platform has just been created to exchange news and cultural content between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. The project is from Nanfang Media Group, based in Guangdong Province and offices in Macau, and calls it "Greater Bay Area Chinese-Sports Media Content Platform." This is an integrated project in the internationalization and expansion of the Chinese group and which was launched last Friday in Lisbon, integrated at the Chinese-Portuguese Culture Festival “Chinese Styles, Portuguese Flavors” [Chinese styles, Portuguese flavors], which took place at Quinta da Marmeleira headquarters in Lisbon.
Nanfang Media Group, which has titles such as GD Today, in English, now wants to reach the Portuguese language universe and a “global audience of about 300 million Portuguese speakers,” wrote this publication. Also there is also describing that the great purpose of this new platform is to “reinforce media cooperation and facilitate the exchange of news and cultural content between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
In his speech, Zhao Yang, chief of wording of the “International South” portal, linked to the Nanfang group, presented the main objectives of this platform, namely “strengthening collaboration with Portuguese media," Think Tanks "and other institutions and presenting, more affordablely, stories about China's business environment, large bay and guangdong."
It is also aiming to show the economic and social modernization that China has known in recent years, as well as showing “sino-Portuguese pragmatic cooperation and friendship between the two peoples”.
Thus, this contact platform also aims to “take advantage of the potential of artificial intelligence in order to promote our media in the digital age”. “I hope this initiative can contribute, with the force of the media, to the dialogue between civilizations and deepening a comprehensive cooperation between China and Portugal,” said Zhao Yang.
The official also explained that "in the last two years, and through the use of journalistic advantages in Macao, South has reinforced collaboration with the Sino-Portuguese platform, Lusa agency or other Portuguese-speaking communication bodies, widely spreading stories about Portuguese to live and work in the great country [China], Hong Kong and economic cooperation between Guangdong and Portugal." It should be noted that the Nanfang group, chaired by Liu Qiyu, currently holds the Portuguese radio Iris FM, based in Samora Correia and Lisbon.
President Words
Liu Qiyu, president of Nanfang Media Group, highlighted the fact that this platform is launched at a time when the 500th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations between China and Europe are celebrated, as well as “the 20th anniversary of establishing a comprehensive strategic partnership between China and Portugal”.
Referring to the group he leads, which has “wide national and international influence and is rooted at China's main economic province in Guangdong,” Liu Qiyu spoke of the idea of ​​internationalizing the group, “striving to build international bridges and promoting dialogue between civilizations”.
"We want to reinforce cooperation with the media around the world in order to promote a global understanding between peoples," he said. The official said he hoped the new platform "can gather the wisdom and strength of the media of both countries to tell stories of the Lusophone world and the stories of Guangdong, the Great Bay and China, and also to take stories from Portugal and Europe to China, especially to Guangdong."
The president of the Nanfang group did not forget the role of Macau in connection with the Hengqin zone, at a time when “the role of the region as an economic and commercial service platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Camões and Ronaldo
Zhao Bentang, China's ambassador in Lisbon, was present at the event, noting that "Chinese and Portuguese civilizations are valued, learn and coexist harmoniously, which benefits people on both sides, also making important contributions to peace and world development."
"Linguistic and cultural cooperation between China and Portugal has suffered a rapid process," he said, noting that in recent years Chinese culture has increasingly popular abroad, while Portugal "was one of the first European countries to communicate with China." It is a story “over 500 years”, having created “a solid basis for common development” and greater cultural exchange, he said.
Zhao Bentang did not forget the highlight that football and literature in Portuguese have had in China. "Cristiano Ronaldo is a well -known name in China, and the excellent works of Portuguese writers such as Camões, Fernando Pessoa or José Saramago can be found in all Chinese bookstores," he recalled.
The Sino-Portuguese Cultural Festival where the launch of this new media platform was part of Chinese cuisine and also macanese and Portuguese dishes, signed by Michael Franco, Macaense Hong Kong that recently opened a new restaurant in Lisbon, Dragon Inn.
Moreover, the event, supported by several entities, such as the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry (CCILC), had wine and demonstrations of Chinese culture, with handwriting and wearing traditional robes.
Bernardo Mendia, CCILC Secretary-General, stressed that China created, 71 years ago, the idea of ​​“mutual respect and peaceful coexistence between nations, the celebrated five principles of peaceful coexistence, which are no more than a manifestation of respect for third party culture, without the pretense of changes or impositions, as if some cultures were superior to others”.
The official stressed that, in economic links, "culture is an essential and even earlier element as a way to enhance the good bilateral relationship and mutually beneficial business realization."
In this sense, Bernardo added, "respect for culture is non -negotiable," because it is "an intangible good, because it is composed of values, beliefs, customs and traditions, transmitted from generation to generation through practices, rituals and expressions that result in the very identity of a people or community."
According to GD Today, Bernardo Mendia said "that media can help us break barriers and facilitate communication", and the new platform could have "huge meaning in the connection between Portugal and China."
Referring to the debate that currently exists in Portugal, about the end of bullfighting, Bernardo Mendia pointed out that “the races of Portuguese bumps” are part of culture, something “prior to the power of the state itself, which is legitimized by the respect of the culture of its people and communities”. Thus, in this context, the Secretary General of Cilc lamented that the state tries to “impose a culture-a phenomenon called the 'state culture'”. In such cases, “chaos is installed, as we recently witnessed in the western world with the attempt to impose Woke culture by some states,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:18:46</pubDate></item><item><title>ASEAN | Malaysia calls for the largest union in the face of US tariffs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/asean-malasia-apela-a-maior-uniao-face-a-tarifas-dos-eua/</link><description>Southeast Asia should accelerate economic integration, diversify markets, and remain united in the face of disturbances in global trade resulting from US tariffs, said the head of Malaysian diplomacy yesterday.
Malaon Foreign Minister Mohamad Hasan spoke during the opening of the first annual summit of heads of state and government of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) in Kuala Lumpur.
"ASEAN countries are among the most affected by US -imposed tariffs. Trade war between the US and China is drastically disturbing production and commerce standards around the world," said Mohamad.
The diplomat even admitted that "it is likely that there is a global economic slowdown." "We must take advantage of this moment to deepen regional economic integration, so we can better protect our region from external shocks," added Mohamad.
ASEAN countries, many of which depend on exports to the US, are suffering from tariffs ranging from 10 percent and 49 percent. Six of the association's ten member countries were among the most affected, with tariffs ranging from 32 percent and 49 percent.
ASEAN has unsuccessfully attempted to mark an initial meeting with the US as a block. ASEAN's unit is crucial, as the region deals with the impacts of climate change and the disturbance caused by the use of artificial intelligence and other unregulated technologies for criminal purposes, Mohamad said.
The diplomat added that Asean, whose rotary presidency belongs to Malaysia, will be tested by external pressure, including a rivalry between superpowers. "External pressures are increasing, and the scope of challenges has never been so big," said Mohamad. "Therefore, it is crucial that we reinforce the bonds that unite us, so that they do not disqual to external pressures. For Asean, unity is now more important than ever," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:09:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | Tai Kin IP took stock of the implementation of Xi speeches</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/pequim-tai-kin-ip-fez-balanco-da-implementacao-de-discursos-de-xi/</link><description>Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, led a delegation on a trip to Beijing to visit ministries and commissions from central authorities. On Friday, the secretary met with the Hong Kong and Macao Work Office director of the China Communist Party Central Committee (CCP) and the Hong Kong and Macao Staff of the Council of State, Xia Baolong.
According to the secretary's office, Tai Kin IP informed Xia Baolong “about the situation of the scrupulous implementation of the spirit consecrated in President XI Jinping's important speeches”, as well as the political objectives in the area of ​​Sam Hou Fai's economy and finance. Among the goals to be achieved, the Government of MSAR emphasizes the proper diversification of the economy, the construction of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin and the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau, as well as "supporting the state to open to the world to a higher level and support the qualitative development of companies and residents."
During his stay in Beijing, the MSar entourage visited the National Commission for Development and Reform, the Ministry of Science and Technology, the Ministry of Industry and Technologies, the Ministry of Finance, the Popular Bank of China, among other bodies of the central authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:26:31</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI | Confirmed suspended arrest of six months to doctoral student</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/tsi-confirmada-prisao-suspensa-de-seis-meses-para-doutorando/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance (TSI) confirmed the sentence to six months in prison to the student at a local university, who tried to corrupt the thesis advisor with 8 thousand patacas. Confirmation of the conviction was released on Friday by the courts of MSAR. The penalty was suspended for two years, due to the payment of 15 thousand patacas to the MSAR.
Despite entering an unidentified local college in August 2020 and having as a deadline for the delivery of the PhD Thesis May 2023, the student only began to discuss the structure of work with the advisor in March 2023. Presenting a project that did not meet the advisor's requirements, and in view of the prospects of not being approved, the student placed an 8,000 -borrowed red envelope inside a book Advisor, leaving this book in the advisor's mailbox.
However, the teacher refused the offer and eventually complained to the authorities. This was not the student's first monetary offer to the teacher. In 2020, the student had offered valleys and money to the tutor, who, in turn, refused the offer and warned the student that the behavior was illegal and possibly constituted the crime of corruption.
With the following case to the courts, the first instance sentenced the student for the crime of active corruption, with a sentence of arrest of six months, suspended for two years, and the payment of 15,000 patacas to the MSAR.
The defendant resorted to the conviction for arguing that the money had been offered to “obtain more academic guidance” and never with the purpose of corrupting the teacher to facilitate the approval of the thesis. However, the TSI declined the arguments and maintained the condemnation of the first instance.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:40:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix Museum | Competition illustrations can be seen until September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/museu-do-grande-premio-ilustracoes-de-concurso-podem-ser-vistas-ate-setembro/</link><description>The winning works of the Illustration Contest of the Gaining Car of Asia's first major award (Macau) are available for public viewing at a Macao Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) museum until September 1st. The contest awards were awarded last Friday, in an organization of the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) and Macau Creatations Limited.
In total, 30 prizes were delivered. The contest had as its main theme the Triumph TR2, the winning car of the first major prize of Macao. In total, 88 works were received, which received more than 10,000 online votes from the public. An evaluation committee also chose the first three classifieds of the group of secondary education candidates and the open group. The contest were also the categories of “most popular internet”, “Merit Awards” and “Finalist Awards”.
In the secondary education group, the winners were Chan Hei Wo, in the first place, followed by Leong Sam U and Ma Nim Ian, as third classified. In turn, in the open group, he won Tam Iok Meng, Lam Si Cheng, in second place and Cheang Ka Ian, in third place.
The exhibition that is now evident in the museum's basement allows “the public to enjoy the award-winning creative and theme artistic works”, and through the illustration, “the public can also feel the precious history of the Macao Grand Prix”, reads in an official note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:01:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Concert | Bruno Pernadas in Macau and inland in June</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/concerto-bruno-pernadas-em-macau-e-no-interior-em-junho/</link><description>June will be filled for Portuguese multi-instrumentalist and composer Bruno Penadas, who, in partnership with the Noyb Association (None of Your Business), star in several concerts in Macau, Hong Kong and other stops from southern China. Lush sounds can hear in Shenzhen on the 12th; in Macau the next day, and then in Zhuhai and Hong Kong
 
The Noyb Association (None of Your Business) is preparing to bring, next June, the tour of Bruno Pernadas, “The Greatest Bay Area Tour 2025”, with concerts in Shenzhen, Macau, Zhuhai and Hong Kong. Thus, the Portuguese, Chinese and other nationalities can listen and closely see the creations of the Portuguese multi-instrumentalist and composer, presenting a journey of sound mergers that wanders between “jazz, futuristic pop, folk, electronics and psychoadelical rock”.
According to a Noyb press note, Bruno Pernadas is a "master of sound alchemy, creating vibrant and immersive landscapes that challenge categorizations, making their concerts an unforgettable experience." “Your fluid approach between genres, combining intricate arrangements with global influences, will take the audience on a musical trip where retro-futurizing melodies meet hypnotic rhythms, and where each note tells a story. More than a series of concerts, this event is a cultural bridge between Portugal and the big bay,” says Noyb.
Highlight for the fact that the concert in Macao will take place two days after June 10 - Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese Communities, and the whole month is dedicated to celebrating Portuguese culture and language.
All songs in one
The raid of Bruno Penas into the music world was through the real Lisbonense Combo and groups such as the "Julie &amp; The Carjackers" or "Minta &amp; The Brooktrout". The first album was titled "How Can We Be Joyful In A World Full of Knowledge?" And was released 11 years ago. This was followed by “Those Who Throw Objects at the Crocodiles Will Be Asked To Retrieve Them” in 2016, and since then it has been added success. Highlight for the release, in 2021, of the album work “Private Reasons”, which ends the sound trilogy created in 2014 and 2016. Later this year, Bruno Pernadas released “Worst Summer Ever”, also creating several sound bands for dance, theater and cinema.
Speaking to the Lisbon Cultural Agenda, Bruno Pernadas spoke of the diversity of musical styles that are present at the work he does. “There is no genre that describes the song I make. There's jazz, there's pop music, a lot of exotic music, some rock, world music… When I make music I don't think so much about it, where genre fits.”
The musician also said, to the same publication, that he does not consider himself a singer. “No, I don't feel singer, at all [laughs]. In other records I sang, but in this corner more, it's a fact. It was hard for me because it's not natural, I don't have tools for that. I sing like anyone, the only difference is that I know the notes I'm singing, but I don't have it. I prefer to play instruments much more.”</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:57:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Israelite attacks have been 52 dead since Saturday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/gaza-ataques-israelitas-fazem-52-mortos-desde-sabado/</link><description>At least 52 people have died in the Gaza range since early Saturday morning due to Israelite air strikes, Palestinian news agency Wafa said. On Saturday night, an Israeli Defense Forces Drone (IDF) attacked a family business in the Al Hakr neighborhood of Deir Al-Balah in the center of the Gaza Strip, killing five Palestinians.
At night, the Israelite Air Force also launched attacks on communities east of Khan Yunis in the south of the Gaza Strip, where several IDF helicopters have also opened fire. In the north of the enclave, air strikes and “intense shots” were reported by the Israeli forces in various places, including Beit Lahia and the northeast of Jabalia. Local and doctors had already advanced the deaths of at least eight more people in the city of Gaza and seven more in Rafah, in the south of the track, where about 60 people were also injured.
The worst nightmare
The attacks appear after the Hamas Government Ministry of Health, in the Gaza Strip, registered 79 dead on Friday, including nine children of a pediatrician who was working at the hospital when the bodies arrived.
According to Hamas, pediatrician Alaa Al Najjjjaros was working at Nasser Hospital in Khan Youis (southern Gaza) when the bodies of nine of his 10 children (Yahya, Rakan, Raslan, Jibran, Eve, Rivan, Luqman, Sadeen and Sidra) arrived after being killed in an attack on their home.
Pediatrician's husband, Hamdi Al Najjar, and the only surviving son, Adam, both seriously injured, are being treated in the intensive care unit. The images released after the attack by QDS News Network show Hamdi on the stretcher with bass burns.
The oldest of the deceased children was 12 years old, according to the director general of the Ministry of Health of Gaza, Munir Al-Bursh. The rescue video of the bodies shows the Gaza Civil Defense agents and the Crescent Palestinian red to remove the children's charred bodies from the house, one after another.
"She left them to do their duty and mission to all children who do not find another place at the Nasser Hospital, which is full of innocent screams and weakened by the disease, hunger and tiredness," wrote the doctor, Youssef Abu Al Rish, in a note released yesterday by health services.
Updated data yesterday, by the Ministry of Health they raise to more than 53,900 the number of people killed in Gaza since Israel launched an offensive. The war broke out in Gaza after an unprecedented attack by the Palestinian Islamite group Hamas on Israeli soil on 7 October 2023, which caused about 1,200 dead and more than two hundred hostages.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:06:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Traffic | Tourist crosses road off the treadmill and is run over</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/transito-turista-atravessa-estrada-fora-da-passadeira-e-e-atropelada/</link><description>A interior tourist had to be transported to the Conde São Januário Hospital Center, after crossing Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro off the treadmill. The accident happened around 11:30 am, when the wife and a friend decided to cross the road, ending one of them for being hit by a TCM bus.
As a result of the accident, the woman was transported to the hospital with head injuries, although she had kept conscious. The bus got the cracked front glass.
Despite the injuries, both the injured tourist and the friend, were eventually fined by the authorities, for crossing the road off the treadmill.
The accident led to the TCM company to issue a statement to explain the situation. According to the company's version, the driver was surprised by two women who appeared behind other vehicles that followed the road, which did not have enough time for the driver to lock. The company also indicated that after the accident the response mechanisms were activated for these situations, with the driver calling the rescue teams and the police.
The accident became viral, with several images online, including the victim bleeding on the road. Some of the images were altered using artificial intelligence, to show the two tourists dance in the middle of the road, which did not correspond to reality.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:37:13</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Liu Yuxi (772-842), Luoyang's poet (Henan), contemplating the heavens noticed in certain birds who liked to dwell with families and indicated a permanence within the constant change of stations. Observing the habits of the swallows and the decay of the high classes in Jinling, he wrote in the last two verses of the poem to Rua das Mansions of Black Village:
Under the eaves of the powerful Wang and Xie
before they were swallows,
Now flying, they seek so many times
our humble dwellings.
This proximity that speaks, for example, the founding legend of the first dynasty that there are written records and that is the origin of the Shang lineage (c. 1500-1050 A. C.) it was long recognized with the first.
Then, according to historian Sima Qian, a woman named Jiandi would have eaten a swallow egg (Yan), previously called simply Xuanniao, "black bird", then giving birth to a man named Xie, who was the ancestor of the founders of the dynasty. Over time, in various arts such as architecture, painting or poetry, repeated references were unfolded to this relationship of perceived friendship with black birds.
In times of uneasiness, such as those who followed the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition in which painters identified with the losers and belonging to the previous reigning family, such as Zhu da (1626-1705) known as Bada Shanren, found new, expressive forms of the fluidity of the caleigraphic brush trace along the Tang and Song Dynasties and Song and Song Qichang would make an ideal.
In the epitome of its speed, this trait was designated Feiba, the "flying white", which left only the traces of the brush passage. A painter from Xinghua (Yangzhou, Jiangsu) admirer of Bada Shanren showed in several paintings the same independent attitude of canons that would lead to one of the Yangzhou Baguai, "the eight eccentrics of Yangzhou."
Li Shan (1686- C.1756) who would use the stage name Futang, which can be translated as a "recovery of family relationships", in the vertical roll swallows (paint and color on paper, 134.9 x 33 cm, metmuseum) painted slowly, carefully two swallows in a branch made with the spontaneity of the speed of the trace used to write with the pinl.
And as in many paintings by Bada Shanren, the words in Him are written in harmony with the figuration, and just like the swallows in the branch depend on each other. In this roll Li Shan wrote: «As soon as the fall does salguels begin to wither cruelly wither,/ how do they compare to the spring brisa and the corner of the swallows?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Southeast Asia should accelerate economic integration, diversify markets, and remain united in the face of disturbances in global trade resulting from US tariffs, said the head of Malaysian diplomacy yesterday.
Malaon Foreign Minister Mohamad Hasan spoke during the opening of the first annual summit of heads of state and government of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) in Kuala Lumpur.
"ASEAN countries are among the most affected by US -imposed tariffs. Trade war between the US and China is drastically disturbing production and commerce standards around the world," said Mohamad.
The diplomat even admitted that "it is likely that there is a global economic slowdown." "We must take advantage of this moment to deepen regional economic integration, so we can better protect our region from external shocks," added Mohamad.
ASEAN countries, many of which depend on exports to the US, are suffering from tariffs ranging from 10 percent and 49 percent. Six of the association's ten member countries were among the most affected, with tariffs ranging from 32 percent and 49 percent.
ASEAN has unsuccessfully attempted to mark an initial meeting with the US as a block. ASEAN's unit is crucial, as the region deals with the impacts of climate change and the disturbance caused by the use of artificial intelligence and other unregulated technologies for criminal purposes, Mohamad said.
The diplomat added that Asean, whose rotary presidency belongs to Malaysia, will be tested by external pressure, including a rivalry between superpowers. "External pressures are increasing, and the scope of challenges has never been so big," said Mohamad. "Therefore, it is crucial that we reinforce the bonds that unite us, so that they do not disqual to external pressures. For Asean, unity is now more important than ever," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Southeast Asia should accelerate economic integration, diversify markets, and remain united in the face of disturbances in global trade resulting from US tariffs, said the head of Malaysian diplomacy yesterday.
Malaon Foreign Minister Mohamad Hasan spoke during the opening of the first annual summit of heads of state and government of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) in Kuala Lumpur.
"ASEAN countries are among the most affected by US -imposed tariffs. Trade war between the US and China is drastically disturbing production and commerce standards around the world," said Mohamad.
The diplomat even admitted that "it is likely that there is a global economic slowdown." "We must take advantage of this moment to deepen regional economic integration, so we can better protect our region from external shocks," added Mohamad.
ASEAN countries, many of which depend on exports to the US, are suffering from tariffs ranging from 10 percent and 49 percent. Six of the association's ten member countries were among the most affected, with tariffs ranging from 32 percent and 49 percent.
ASEAN has unsuccessfully attempted to mark an initial meeting with the US as a block. ASEAN's unit is crucial, as the region deals with the impacts of climate change and the disturbance caused by the use of artificial intelligence and other unregulated technologies for criminal purposes, Mohamad said.
The diplomat added that Asean, whose rotary presidency belongs to Malaysia, will be tested by external pressure, including a rivalry between superpowers. "External pressures are increasing, and the scope of challenges has never been so big," said Mohamad. "Therefore, it is crucial that we reinforce the bonds that unite us, so that they do not disqual to external pressures. For Asean, unity is now more important than ever," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 2025
In Chinese proverbial lessons I discovered great affinities between spontaneous Chinese popular philosophy, which runs from mouth to mouth, and the Christian proverbial wisdom, also made so that believers, in every corner of the globe, could memorize, repeat and disseminate.
Nothing like the other's knowledge to bring and dispel prejudice, being one of the most usual that Chinese are extremely pragmatic and cold. But when we come across proverbs such as “love others as yourself,” in a direct translation and faithful to the original “爱人如己” (ài Rú Rú Jǐ), such leads us to think twice, it seems not to be here just a matter of respect, uncharged and formal, but rather a strong feeling for the other, not any, only a deep affection, of those we understand well that we are good, we will be well, we will be well, we will be well, we will be better. Then he runs a love of the Christian way for China without Christ ever been. Such finding can lead us to the assumption of the existence of universal structures, not only logical, including as regards affections, therefore sentimental. After all, selfishness may not be a dominant tendency, there is everything: selfish, aggressive and competitive people, as others will be naturally altruistic, compassionate and cooperatives, ready to recognize the universality of the feeling of love, which crosses borders rather than erecting them, bringing people closer to the most diverse social classes, ethnic groups, geographies, as in "love has no borders", in a direct translation "" (Àiqíng wú jiējí zhī fēn), here is particularly emphasized social borders.
The content of the message gains full sense when one realizes that love to oneself takes place in a culture that many consider wrong and prejudiced only to focus on the whole, in the community.  Attention to the person, the particular and the style and feeling of each, lives, in philosophies such as Taoist for centuries with the valorization of the collectivity, this ultimate tendency manifestly inculcated and worked by Confucianism.  Love to itself, care for the individual body and mind, is emphasized in the so -called Proverbial “well -understood love and virtue must begin with us”, which has the following correspondence in Chinese “爱德从己起” (to Cong Jǐ qǐ).
Anyone who imagines that in proverbial wisdom there is only place to praise and sing relational love, since the Chinese have no religious philosophy that chant spiritual love above all, in the Christian way of St. Augustine, will be surprised to find the following proverb "where there is no other gentleman", that in a direct translation of the Chinese is "the love above all" 爱情至上 爱情至上 爱情至上ZHì Shàng).
If in doubt, there is another saying of complementary meaning and in which the idea of ​​the integrity and unity of this powerful affection, which moves mountains in the Christian sense, when it reads 爱情专一 （（（（iqíng zhuān yī）, in a possible translation "love cannot be broken", "one person cannot have a heart in two parts at the same time."
From a psychological point of view, the acceptance of the other in loving terms will have to be complete, so their tastes, affections, relationships, and objects cannot be rejected, as it follows from the lesson “Who loves Beltrão, loves his dog”, in a relative correspondence for “爱屋及乌” (ài wū jí wū), which in a literal translation would be “love the house and the crows”.
As it is known, proverbs are susceptible to various interpretations, so they say polysemic, but if they are perspective as a whole and only after as pieces of a puzzle, there seems to be many doubts with regard to the viabial philosophy and psychology of Chinese love, which is echoed in the country's scholarly philosophies.
In Chapter 67 of the Book of the road and virtue (《道德经》), also known by the name of the Patriarch of Taoism, Lazi (老子), is the first of the three guiding virtues of the Wise Way, Love, as you can read in the translation of Claudia Ribeiro (2004, 139):
I have three treasures
What entesouro and retains:
The first is love (CI),
The second frugality,
The third is not daring to be the vanguard of the world.
(…)
For love,
In combat, it triumphs,
And in defense it is firm.
The sky will come to aid
And, with love, will protect
(我有三寶/寶而持之/一曰慈/二曰儉/三曰不敢為天下先 (……) 夫慈以戰則勝//以守則固/以慈衛之 1)
It is noted that while in proverbial philosophy the synogram used for love is 爱/愛 2 (AI), in the scholarly philosophy of the Patriarch of Taoism the term employment is 慈 (CI), that is, love with a strong relational and spiritual burden; Although they are different words, both refer to love, the first concerns the most physical and concrete feeling, centered on the heart of the person and the clutches that hold it;  The second to that most relational and general indicates that love comes from inside the heart (内心 nèixīn), where it has the roots, emerging like any plant. However, the truth is that both terms focus on people, or rather in their hearts, affectionate connection with others, such a strong connection that draws the attention of heaven (天 tiān), maximum impersonal power, it ensures victory on all battle fronts, whether in the forefront or rear, when fighting and defended itself for love.
Already the patriarch of Confucianism, Confucius (孔子), in the Chapter Twelve, later entitled the deep face, of the Analects (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 22) defines the main virtue of the school, benevolence or humanity, (仁 Rén) as an act of love to others, maintaining the term of the traditional vernacular 爱 (AI): “Fan Chi asked what was the benevolence was what answered, "love people". " (樊遲問仁 ， 子曰 「愛人 3。 ”) It is in this context of love of neighbor, that one of the main maxims of Confucian philosophy must be understood, which arises in the same chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 2)“ Do not make the others what they do not want for you ”(己所不欲勿施於人 jǐ suǒ bù yù shunk yú rén).
The essentials in Confucian philosophy will then guarantee love of others in terms of respect or humanity towards others, in order to ensure the normal functioning of society, without extreme sacrifices or exaggerated explorations, given to the proverb containment of confusion in relation to feelings, they are important and useful but should not extravate the boundaries of rationality, that is, even the best of them, will have to be measured, controlled and ritualized in the name of harmony collective. Therefore, the love that moves friendships, especially intellectuals, is the most praised, as we remembered at the end of this chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 24):
Zeng Zi stated: “A gentleman resorts to knowing to make friends and friends to cultivate benevolence4” (曾子曰：君以文會友 ， 以友輔仁。)
Finally, also the Buddhist philosophy, especially from the Chan (禅 Chán) or Zen meditation line, praises the love of humanity, but indirectly, drawing attention to the heart and the identification of Buddha with the heart, the way of the Daoxin Patriarch (道信) and its maximum proverbially known “the heart is Buddha and Buddha is the heart” (非心不问佛 ， 问佛不非心 fēi xīn bùwèn fu, wèn fi bù fēi xīn). Here you come to love indirectly, only an enlightened heart can love the Buddha, as it is not surprising in the picture of this philosophy, after all what is Buddha but the very love that expresses itself not in a selfish, sick, self -centered heart, but in a heart capable of establishing relationships, healthy, altruistic and without empty, but not indifferent to the other?  This confirms it the social and humanitarian actions of Via Mahayana Buddhism, which was accepted in China and unfolds in collective works such as the construction of educational institutions, hospitals, centers of social solidarity, in a proselytist action at all similar to the history of the Christian Church and its missionaries around the world.
Bibliographic references
Lansheng, Jiang (Comp.) 1997. 100 Excerpts from Zen Buddhist Texts. Hong Hong Kong: Commercial Press.
NGAN, António André. 1998. SINE-SHORE CONGRELLANCE OF PROVERBS AND IDIOMATIC PHRASES. 中葡對照成語集. Macau: Macao Adult Association.
RIBEIRO, Claudia (Trad). 2004. 《道德經》 The Book of Road and Power. Bilingual edition. Mem-Martins: European American Publications.
Xin Guanjie (辛冠洁) (org. And trad.) 1994. 《論語》 .Tradument for contemporary Chinese falls xiqin (蔡希勤) and English translation of Lai Bo (赖波) and Xia Yuhe (夏玉和). Beijing: Sinolingue.
References:
Text in classic Chinese.
Love in simplified and traditional Chinese.
Text in classic Chinese.
A gentleman in ancient Chinese times was a gentleman and a potential ruler.
“This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors” https://www.cccm.gov.pt</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Liu Yuxi (772-842), Luoyang's poet (Henan), contemplating the heavens noticed in certain birds who liked to dwell with families and indicated a permanence within the constant change of stations. Observing the habits of the swallows and the decay of the high classes in Jinling, he wrote in the last two verses of the poem to Rua das Mansions of Black Village:
Under the eaves of the powerful Wang and Xie
before they were swallows,
Now flying, they seek so many times
our humble dwellings.
This proximity that speaks, for example, the founding legend of the first dynasty that there are written records and that is the origin of the Shang lineage (c. 1500-1050 A. C.) it was long recognized with the first.
Then, according to historian Sima Qian, a woman named Jiandi would have eaten a swallow egg (Yan), previously called simply Xuanniao, "black bird", then giving birth to a man named Xie, who was the ancestor of the founders of the dynasty. Over time, in various arts such as architecture, painting or poetry, repeated references were unfolded to this relationship of perceived friendship with black birds.
In times of uneasiness, such as those who followed the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition in which painters identified with the losers and belonging to the previous reigning family, such as Zhu da (1626-1705) known as Bada Shanren, found new, expressive forms of the fluidity of the caleigraphic brush trace along the Tang and Song Dynasties and Song and Song Qichang would make an ideal.
In the epitome of its speed, this trait was designated Feiba, the "flying white", which left only the traces of the brush passage. A painter from Xinghua (Yangzhou, Jiangsu) admirer of Bada Shanren showed in several paintings the same independent attitude of canons that would lead to one of the Yangzhou Baguai, "the eight eccentrics of Yangzhou."
Li Shan (1686- C.1756) who would use the stage name Futang, which can be translated as a "recovery of family relationships", in the vertical roll swallows (paint and color on paper, 134.9 x 33 cm, metmuseum) painted slowly, carefully two swallows in a branch made with the spontaneity of the speed of the trace used to write with the pinl.
And as in many paintings by Bada Shanren, the words in Him are written in harmony with the figuration, and just like the swallows in the branch depend on each other. In this roll Li Shan wrote: «As soon as the fall does salguels begin to wither cruelly wither,/ how do they compare to the spring brisa and the corner of the swallows?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>CCCM | Launched bilingual edition of book on human science</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/cccm-lancada-edicao-bilingue-de-livro-sobre-ciencia-humana/</link><description>Human science, which aims to “integrate all areas of human knowledge”, was the subject of a book by Maria Burguete and Lui Lam released in 2015. Now the bilingual edition of “Science Matters - Human Science, a unified perspective on humanities and sciences”, edited with the support of the University of Macau. The work was presented on Wednesday at the Scientific and Cultural Center of Macau
 
There was a time when philosophy was the basis of knowledge before other areas of knowledge emerge. However, the exact sciences from the humanities, the art of philosophy, as completely different areas, are now separated. Maria Burguete, scientist and president of the Science Matters Association, established in Portugal, launched on Wednesday the book Bilingual “Science Matters-Human Science, a unified perspective on humanities and sciences”, written with Chinese scientist Lui Lam. The work seeks to demonstrate how all areas of knowledge can live and live together, in a kind of complementarity, without forgetting philosophy.
The book was presented at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) and was supported by various entities, namely the University of Macau and the Rocha Cabral Institute.
First launched in 2015, the work is now edited in a bilingual version, in Portuguese and Chinese, in order to gather the work that has been developed by Maria Burguete, a doctorate in science stories in Germany and with biochemistry base formation, and scientist Lui Lam. It is at the Science Matters Association, which has been linked, since 2018, the Center Science Matters, which Maria Burguete gives courses on the concept of “human science”, while Lui Lam is dedicated to the same work in China.
At Wednesday's session, Maria Burguete explained that human science, Portuguese translation of the concept “Science Matters”, aims to “integrate all areas of human knowledge, including natural, social and human sciences, under the scientific paradigm”. Thus, "the idea is that all aspects related to humans can be scientifically studied, breaking with the traditional divisions between the natural and human sciences", promoting "the unification of all the knowledge produced by the human species in a single multidiscipline." Therefore, the areas of humanities and the arts with the social sciences, or the humanities with the medical sciences, are included.
According to the author, human science brings a "unifying vision of knowledge", being "a new multidiscipline that is like a new philosophy of the 21st century." It is a “new approach to knowledge, where common patterns are recognized” to all areas, he explained.
Maria Burguete says she had contact with the concept from the ideas of English nuclear physicist Charles Percy Snow, who in a Cambridge lecture in 1959 presented the idea of ​​the “two cultures”, a separation between the exact sciences and the humanities, as two opposite poles.
“My basic formation is biochemistry and chemical engineering. Therefore, I am very linked to the natural sciences. And there was a time when C.P. Snow, when I was a teacher in Cambridge, gave a conference where he spoke of the existence of two cultures. This was a scandal at the time, because it seemed that there was scientific culture and all who were not within this scientific culture. of the rest, and that has to end. ”
For Maria Burguete, “it makes no sense to create barriers” because “all areas complement each other”. "All areas, one way or another, are subject to a very similar paradigm of knowledge. How do you form, where they come from and where they go? They all go through these steps. Of course, the approaches are different, as is literature, arts or chemistry, but they continue to be areas of knowledge development," he added.
The Role of Philosophy
Maria Burguete's contact with Lui Lam was at the time of the 20th World Congress of the History of Science, which took place in Beijing in 2005. “Then I presented a new epistemology, and my physical colleague, who is physically, was enchanted and came to me, proposing a new multidiscipline, because I said, how I know is transverse,” he said to HM.
Moreover, this bilingual work is born from a six -volume editorial project, and this edition is only the first volume. The conferences promoted by Maria Burguete and Lui Lam related to the theme of human science scored in 2007 and several editions took place in 2009, 2011, 2013, 2015, 2017 and 2019. What was said in these conferences was compiled in English, editing now, in the book presented on Wednesday.
The academic believes that “everything came up with philosophy”, referring to the period of classical antiquity. "Philosophy was the main milestone of knowledge, and only then did the areas of knowledge begin to diverge."
Álvaro Rosa, Macaense and professor at ISCTE - University Institute of Lisbon, left some of the themes that can be found on the work, namely the history of science in China. "For those interested in China's problems, this book helps us understand how China faces and sees the history of sciences, and how science communication is done," he said.
"China is not exactly the same as the West, it has its characteristics, and this book helps us understand how China sees this and other issues. It is a book that is worth reading, made for open minds, so that one can discuss knowledge without a vocabulary or approach too technical," added Álvaro Rosa.
Álvaro Rosa launched the refers to the CCCM audience with the example of how the beauty or the ugliness of something is viewed. “We often say that tastes are not discussed. The scientist begins by classifying which things are beautiful and ugly and then performs an inquiry, starting to observe whether or not there is ugliness, putting everything into categories. There is a completely different approach from the humanist. Therefore, the idea of ​​Maria Burguete is to cover all the themes related to humanity within what we call science, in the sense that we can put, in the same way we can put it in the same way as we can put Hat, the study of all topics and their interpretation. I find it very interesting, ”said Álvaro Rosa.
“An integrated perspective”
Ana Cristina Alves, coordinator of the CCCM Educational Service and formed in the area of ​​Chinese philosophy and culture, argued that the book of Maria Burguete and Lui Lam presents “a holistic and integrated perspective” of knowledge.
"Western philosophy looks at Chinese philosophy as not being philosophy, staring at it as poorly scientific, because it does not start and does not end in logic," he said, speaking of the example of integrating existing knowledge in traditional Chinese medicine.
"Traditional Chinese medicine is all supported by philosophy, its substrate is philosophy. When there is no integrated and holistic philosophical perspective, what is done in medicine is to receive patients in five minutes and ready. And what is important for a good diagnosis is to realize the ills that afflict the patient. This is only possible from an integrated perspective," he said.
In this sense, Maria Burguete argued that a doctor should not end her formation without "having at least three years of philosophy, because treating people is not only to treat the body physically, but also to realize the person in front of him."</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:18:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Foreign language students increasingly use AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/19/estudo-alunos-de-linguas-estrangeiras-usam-cada-vez-mais-a-ia/</link><description>A study by academics at Macao Polytechnic University concludes that 80 percent of a sample of 25 Portuguese students “regularly uses” artificial intelligence as a study tool. The authors of the study warn of the need for combination with traditional teaching and teacher education methods
 
To what extent is Artificial Intelligence (AI) being used by Chinese students to learn foreign languages, and how is this use done? A study developed by academics and teachers at Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) Vanessa Amaro and Manuel Pires concludes that the use is growing.
The work, entitled “Artificial and Natural: Interconnections and Balances in Ple”, published in the scientific journal “Millenium - Journal of Education, Technologies and Health”, concludes that, from a sample of 25 undergraduate students in UPM, “80 percent uses the AI. Lusophone ”.
Students concerned attend the third and fourth year of the course and were chosen because they have “a more advanced level of dominance of the Portuguese language and greater experience with different pedagogical approaches, including the use of technologies in teaching”.
In addition, "most participants were aged between 21 and 24 years, from various provinces in the interior of China (about 70 percent) and Macao", and "had prior experience in the use of AI tools for linguistic learning."
In general terms, the work points out that AI is increasingly important “in the learning of PLE [Portuguese as a foreign language]”, and that “the analysis of student interactions with AI for foreign languages ​​is critical to ensuring that technological solutions are worked based on their needs and expectations”.
It also states that the 25 students interviewed assume "a positive attitude towards the integration of AI in the learning of Portuguese, recognizing both significant advantages and its limitations." "A recurring theme was the need to maintain the balance between the use of AI and human interaction, highlighting the desire for language teaching open to new technologies, but without compromising the benefits of interpersonal relationships," the authors point out.
Tongue
If 80 percent of the students often resort to AI, what are the purposes of this use? The study points out that AI can support “the training of pronunciation, especially in the context of autonomous learning”. "Many have highlighted the neutrality of generated voices, which avoids regional influences, as an effective resource for developing correct habits in oral production." One student referred to the authors of the study that "the AI ​​voice is adjusted, there is no accent of any region and, therefore, it is good for students to train oral understanding with various types of texts beyond the materials given by the teacher in class."
In addition to pronunciation training, AI tools are also widely used for information research on Portuguese -speaking countries. “Students have recognized that these tools save time and allow more direct access to relevant content,” says the work, which highlights a student's response: “Help me to look for information about current trends in Brazil or Portugal, because books and information on the internet are dispersed and require many more time and much more time.”
However, it is stressed, based on the experience of both teachers, "that excessive use of AI tools has contributed to the significant reduction in the development of critical skills between students."
"More and more work, both written and oral, lack analytical depth, presenting advanced lexical and grammatical structures that do not correspond to the actual level of students' proficiency. This disadvantage suggests a superficial relationship with study materials, where reflective effort and autonomous thinking are often replaced by AMA automatically generated answers," he concludes.
Complementarity is needed
According to Vanessa Amaro and Manuel Pires, the study allows us to conclude that “the integration of AI in foreign language teaching is an irreversible trend, but it requires a structured and careful pedagogical approach”.
"Most students [interviewed] recognized the importance of adapting language teaching into current technological reality, stressing the need to incorporate the AI ​​in a planned way. The balance between traditional methods and the use of new technologies is critical to ensuring effective learning," is concluded.
One of the students even defended that it is necessary to have a balance between AI and traditional methods, ”because“ language learning can be better and more interesting through AI, but it lacks the ability to create ideas and imagination, as well as the intercultural aspects of language learning ”.
Thus, for the students inquired, “the presence of the teacher, as a mediator of knowledge, is seen as essential, especially in the specific context of Macao, where there is no linguistic immersion during the learning process of Portuguese”.
Human interaction is, in addition to the “transmission of linguistic content, the ability to interpret cultural, social and emotional aspects, something that was going, despite its technical efficiency, cannot replicate”.
Vanessa Amaro and Manuel Pires also highlight the fact that “AI ethical and pedagogical challenges in teaching are complex and multifaceted”. This is because "data privacy is a central concern, as many AI tools collect personal information that can be used for purposes that users are unaware of." Moreover, “the risk of algorithmic bias can be a pertinent issue, because if the algorithms produce results that are systematically incorrect, biased or unfair, it can accentuate difficulties and inequalities in learning and require extra care in its use and regulation,” is indicated.
The authors also consider that "the excessive dependence of AI can compromise human interaction, essential for the development of social and cultural skills present in educational processes."
Given that "in the teaching of foreign languages ​​there seems to be several speeds in the integration of AI, with higher education institutions that do so gradually and even with enough reservations, as well as those that are most developed and proactive in the way they embrace these technologies," it is necessary to "foster dialogue and cooperation between the various teaching agents to understand the potential of AI".</description><pubDate>2025-05-19 02:27:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Leo XIV offers Vatican mediation to “silence the weapons”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/leao-xiv-oferece-mediacao-do-vaticano-para-silenciar-as-armas/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday exhorted world leaders to sit down and negotiate to “silence the weapons” and offered the Vatican's mediation to all belligerent parts. "The Holy See is available for enemies to meet and look in their eyes," Leo XIV told Vatican to speak at the representatives of the 23 Catholic churches of the East.
The Pope said it is necessary that "peoples can rediscover the hope and dignity to which they are entitled," the dignity of peace. "The people want peace and I, with my heart, say to the leaders of the people: We find, we speak, negotiate! War is never inevitable, weapons can and should be silenced, because they do not solve problems, but increase them," he said.
The US Pope's appeal appears on the eve of possible negotiations in the Turkish city of Istanbul about the Russian War against Ukraine. It is also unknown if today's conversations can include a meeting between Russian presidents, Vladimir Putin, and Ukrainian, Volodymyr Zelensky. Other wars have caused suffering in other latitudes, such as the Middle East, Africa or Asia.
First-hand
Leo XIV said in the Paul VI room, before thousands of people who moved to the jubilee of countries such as Syria, Ukraine, Lebanon and Iraq, which the oriental churches know "firsthand the horrors of war."
"To the point that Pope Francis has called martyrs to your churches," he said, quoted by the Spanish news agency Efe. "It is true: from the Holy Land to Ukraine, from Lebanon to Syria, from the Middle East to Tigray [Ethiopia] and to the Caucasus, so much violence," he lamented.
The Pope, applauded by the hearing, said the horror of war and "of the massacres of so many young lives" should cause indignation, "because in the name of military conquest people die."
He asked him to pray for peace, which he described as "reconciliation, forgiveness, courage to turn the page and start over." “For this peace to differ, I will do everything within my reach,” he promised. "The church will not get tired of repeating:" May weapons shut up, "he said.
Leo XIV said that others are not enemies, but human beings, "they are not bad people to hate, but people to dialogue." The Pope has asked to escape "from the typical manichaeist visions of violent narratives, which divide the world between good and bad."
Leo XIV prayed for the oriental and Latin Christians, who, especially in the Middle East, "resist their lands, stronger than the temptation to abandon them." He also launched a new appeal to be given to Christians the opportunity to remain where they live "with all the rights necessary for a safe existence."
Robert Prevost, 69, born in the United States, but with double American and Peruvian nationality, leads the Catholic Church since May 8, under the name of Leo XIV. It succeeded the Argentine Pope Francis, who died on April 21, 88 years old.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:21:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Nanfang Media | Guangdong Group creates platform with Portugal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/nanfang-media-grupo-de-guangdong-cria-plataforma-com-portugal/</link><description>On Friday, a media cooperation platform was launched, promoted by the Nanfang Media group, based in Guangdong and offices in Macau. The “Chinese-Portuguese Platform of Media Contents to the Great Bay” aims to “reform media cooperation and facilitate the exchange of cultural news and content between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”
 
A new platform has just been created to exchange news and cultural content between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. The project is from Nanfang Media Group, based in Guangdong Province and offices in Macau, and calls it "Greater Bay Area Chinese-Sports Media Content Platform." This is an integrated project in the internationalization and expansion of the Chinese group and which was launched last Friday in Lisbon, integrated at the Chinese-Portuguese Culture Festival “Chinese Styles, Portuguese Flavors” [Chinese styles, Portuguese flavors], which took place at Quinta da Marmeleira headquarters in Lisbon.
Nanfang Media Group, which has titles such as GD Today, in English, now wants to reach the Portuguese language universe and a “global audience of about 300 million Portuguese speakers,” wrote this publication. Also there is also describing that the great purpose of this new platform is to “reinforce media cooperation and facilitate the exchange of news and cultural content between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
In his speech, Zhao Yang, chief of wording of the “International South” portal, linked to the Nanfang group, presented the main objectives of this platform, namely “strengthening collaboration with Portuguese media," Think Tanks "and other institutions and presenting, more affordablely, stories about China's business environment, large bay and guangdong."
It is also aiming to show the economic and social modernization that China has known in recent years, as well as showing “sino-Portuguese pragmatic cooperation and friendship between the two peoples”.
Thus, this contact platform also aims to “take advantage of the potential of artificial intelligence in order to promote our media in the digital age”. “I hope this initiative can contribute, with the force of the media, to the dialogue between civilizations and deepening a comprehensive cooperation between China and Portugal,” said Zhao Yang.
The official also explained that "in the last two years, and through the use of journalistic advantages in Macao, South has reinforced collaboration with the Sino-Portuguese platform, Lusa agency or other Portuguese-speaking communication bodies, widely spreading stories about Portuguese to live and work in the great country [China], Hong Kong and economic cooperation between Guangdong and Portugal." It should be noted that the Nanfang group, chaired by Liu Qiyu, currently holds the Portuguese radio Iris FM, based in Samora Correia and Lisbon.
President Words
Liu Qiyu, president of Nanfang Media Group, highlighted the fact that this platform is launched at a time when the 500th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations between China and Europe are celebrated, as well as “the 20th anniversary of establishing a comprehensive strategic partnership between China and Portugal”.
Referring to the group he leads, which has “wide national and international influence and is rooted at China's main economic province in Guangdong,” Liu Qiyu spoke of the idea of ​​internationalizing the group, “striving to build international bridges and promoting dialogue between civilizations”.
"We want to reinforce cooperation with the media around the world in order to promote a global understanding between peoples," he said. The official said he hoped the new platform "can gather the wisdom and strength of the media of both countries to tell stories of the Lusophone world and the stories of Guangdong, the Great Bay and China, and also to take stories from Portugal and Europe to China, especially to Guangdong."
The president of the Nanfang group did not forget the role of Macau in connection with the Hengqin zone, at a time when “the role of the region as an economic and commercial service platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Camões and Ronaldo
Zhao Bentang, China's ambassador in Lisbon, was present at the event, noting that "Chinese and Portuguese civilizations are valued, learn and coexist harmoniously, which benefits people on both sides, also making important contributions to peace and world development."
"Linguistic and cultural cooperation between China and Portugal has suffered a rapid process," he said, noting that in recent years Chinese culture has increasingly popular abroad, while Portugal "was one of the first European countries to communicate with China." It is a story “over 500 years”, having created “a solid basis for common development” and greater cultural exchange, he said.
Zhao Bentang did not forget the highlight that football and literature in Portuguese have had in China. "Cristiano Ronaldo is a well -known name in China, and the excellent works of Portuguese writers such as Camões, Fernando Pessoa or José Saramago can be found in all Chinese bookstores," he recalled.
The Sino-Portuguese Cultural Festival where the launch of this new media platform was part of Chinese cuisine and also macanese and Portuguese dishes, signed by Michael Franco, Macaense Hong Kong that recently opened a new restaurant in Lisbon, Dragon Inn.
Moreover, the event, supported by several entities, such as the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry (CCILC), had wine and demonstrations of Chinese culture, with handwriting and wearing traditional robes.
Bernardo Mendia, CCILC Secretary-General, stressed that China created, 71 years ago, the idea of ​​“mutual respect and peaceful coexistence between nations, the celebrated five principles of peaceful coexistence, which are no more than a manifestation of respect for third party culture, without the pretense of changes or impositions, as if some cultures were superior to others”.
The official stressed that, in economic links, "culture is an essential and even earlier element as a way to enhance the good bilateral relationship and mutually beneficial business realization."
In this sense, Bernardo added, "respect for culture is non -negotiable," because it is "an intangible good, because it is composed of values, beliefs, customs and traditions, transmitted from generation to generation through practices, rituals and expressions that result in the very identity of a people or community."
According to GD Today, Bernardo Mendia said "that media can help us break barriers and facilitate communication", and the new platform could have "huge meaning in the connection between Portugal and China."
Referring to the debate that currently exists in Portugal, about the end of bullfighting, Bernardo Mendia pointed out that “the races of Portuguese bumps” are part of culture, something “prior to the power of the state itself, which is legitimized by the respect of the culture of its people and communities”. Thus, in this context, the Secretary General of Cilc lamented that the state tries to “impose a culture-a phenomenon called the 'state culture'”. In such cases, “chaos is installed, as we recently witnessed in the western world with the attempt to impose Woke culture by some states,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:18:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Church | Victims of sexual abuse want Leo XIV to assume theme</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/igreja-vitimas-de-abuso-sexual-querem-que-leao-xiv-assuma-tema/</link><description>One of the movement spokesmen that represents victims of sexual abuse in the Catholic Church yesterday asked Pope Leo XIV to put the theme as a priority and defines global rules to deal with cases.
"Now that we have a new Latin American Pope should be given an example in all Latin American episcopades that, by decision and by the Pope, there can be no double standard" among the various Catholic hierarchies around the world, "said Argentine Sebastián Cuattromo, from the adult collective for the rights of the child.
On the day the Pope made the first Sunday greeting in St. Peter's Square, praying Regina Caeli, a group of victims joined the square to ask the Vatican to impose common rules on the whole church.
Cuattromo, 42, set an example of what is happening "in the first world societies and Latin America that acts as a Vatican backyard, where the same [repair] demands are not felt, such as they are felt before European public opinion."
"As a survivor of childhood sexual abuse within the Catholic Church, with other fellow survivors of this crime, we hope that the Pope will make an explicit mention of this question and an explicit reference to what he intends to do in this regard to pay off very large debts that, in our opinion, the Catholic Church still has to the victims," ​​said Cuattromo.
“We victims broke the taboo, silence, denial, concealment, with our struggles, with a huge sacrifice, and reached a level of visibility in public opinion,” which forced the church to face the problem.
Therefore, the global group of victims subscribed to a petition already delivered, in which they require “a true zero tolerance law that is established as canonical law”, which would “imply the immediate expulsion of the religious life of anyone involved in these acts”.
Moreover, they propose a “Truth Commission that should not be directed by the Vatican, but by international human rights organizations with the United Nations standards and with which the Vatican would have to fully cooperate, freeing all the archives he has on the subject”.
Finally, the victims intend a “justice process for the victims, where, among other things, there are concrete actions of reparation and justice for survivors around the world”, with the costs supported by the Church's own goods.

In the first person
In his particular case, Sebastian Cuattromo filed an action against a religious from a Catholic school of Buenos Aires for sexual abuse and won the process in 2012, even before the election to the Pope of then Cardinal Bergoglio, archbishop of the Argentine capital. "Then the city's Catholic hierarchy was against the victims and supported the school, which intended to silence the victims of this offense through a private economic agreement," he recalled.
"They made us feel a profound underestimation of the severity of the crime we were talking about," because, at that moment, "I was a young man who was fighting in solitude, with many doubts, with a lot less, with much anguish and felt an absolute lack of empathy and, instead, deep arrogance," he explained.
After Francis' election, "I invited him publicly and privately to meet with the victims of his country, especially those who had bad experiences," but the Pope "never had the courage or sensitivity to summon us."
For the new Pope, who is also accused of having ignored abuse complaints when he was a prior of the Augustinhos, Cuattromo expects Leo XIV to “assume this theme personally” and to be willing to “go to the last consequences”. Cardinal Robert Francis Prevost, 69, was elected Pope on Thursday after two days of Conclave, in the Vatican City, and took the name of Leo XIV.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Osaka 2025 | Japanese architect Kengo Kuma considers it to be friendly with architecture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/osaka-2025-arquitecto-japones-kengo-kuma-considera-ia-amiga-da-arquitectura/</link><description>Japanese architect Kengo Kuma states in an interview with Lusa that she wanted to show the uniqueness between Portugal and Japan in the Portuguese Pavilion project at Expo 2025 Osaka and considers AI (artificial intelligence) friendly to architecture.
Asked if Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a friend or enemy of architecture, Kengo Kuma opts for the first option. "Yes, it's a friend", because in fact in the design process "we are working with AI".
Artificial intelligence “is a very strong team between us” and “we like to work” with this technology, he says. “We wanted to show the relationship with the ocean in Portugal,” says Kengo Kuma, when asked what was the project's inspiration. Portugal participates in Expo Osaka with the theme “Ocean, Blue Dialogue” and is located in the “Empowering Lives” zone, in a lot with 1,836.75 square meters, being close to the Japan Pavilion.
The Kuma Kuma project expresses the dynamics of the ocean moment, using 9,972 suspended cables weighing more than 60 tons, and recycled networks to create a perennial effect and exposed to natural elements such as sun and wind, according to the organization.
Sea connections
The life of Portugal and Japan is “very linked to the ocean”, in the sense that “we eat fish, we travel a lot through the oceans and history and life are closely linked to the ocean,” adds the architect. There is this “uniqueness of Portugal and Japan and we want to show” this similarity between the two countries.
The volume of the Portugal Pavilion is characterized by a scenic facility that symbolizes the upper square suspended as a wave.
"This design is very, very new to the history of art. We have long tried to use lines as a resource for navigation. With these lines, we try to show the beauty of natural phenomena," in the sea "we see natural light and breeze," he explains.
“We tried to bring this kind of natural phenomenon to the Expo, perhaps the first attempt in the history of the expo to bring its own nature to the pavilion,” says the architect. About what will happen to the pavilion after finishing the Expo, the architect says he wants to bring the diversity of the project (which includes cables of various diameters and lengths) to different places.
“I want to bring this diversity to different places” and “now we are planning to work with some artists” about it. Kengo Kuma said that the Slaughterhouse Project in Porto is completing and has two more projects in Portugal.
The architect says he loves the side of the big cities in Portugal, but also the mountainous side and the ocean of the country. “We want to enjoy the diversity of Portugal,” he says.
Create Memories
Asked how can the more sustainable architecture become currently become, Kengo Kuma considers that "the most important for sustainability is to leave the memory of architecture forever." That is, "architecture, life, basically, are not so permanent."
However, “we can leave the memory of architecture forever, which is the connection between architecture and humanity” and this “is the most important for sustainability,” he says. Used to comment on the controversy around his choice to project the Portuguese pavilion, the architect points out that he has an international office working in Portugal.
"Maybe that's why we were invited," he concludes. Regarding the challenges that architecture currently faces, Kengo Kuma states that its cost is increasing “dramatically” and that everyone wants to reduce it.
"But at the same time, people want to create a new monument" for this pillar. "And the cost and monumentality must walk together" today. Expo 2025 runs since April 13 and runs until October 13 on the artificial island of Yumeshima, located on the edge of Osaka, Kansai, Japan.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:03:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Startups | Portugal interested in the SINO-LUSOPHONE TECHNOLOGY FUND</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/startups-portugal-interessado-no-fundo-sino-lusofono-de-tecnologia/</link><description>A delegation from Macao, with government representatives and local startups, is in Portugal to meet with leaders of Portuguese companies and participate in the SIM conference, which ends today in Porto. During the visit, a protocol was signed that signs the Portuguese interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund, managed by Heng Qin Group's state-owned company Zhuhai
 
Several macao startups are represented on a trip to Portugal this week, and whose delegation also includes representatives of the Directorate of Economics and Tourism Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries Association (AEIMCP). The objective is to strengthen ties with the entrepreneurship ecosystems of Lisbon and Porto and reinforce Portugal's interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund designed to support startups, which will be managed by Heng Qin Group's Zhuhai state company.
In this sense, a protocol between AEIMCP and the nascent Value, “Portuguese company with extensive investor capture” and also “accelerating small business growth (SME) and startups in Portugal and in Portuguese-speaking countries” was signed on Monday, in Lisbon on Monday, with a focus on innovation and state-of-the-art technology ”, is highlighted in a joint statement of AEIMCP and Rising Value sent to HM.
The protocol signed on Monday signs the highest Portuguese access to the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund. The document was signed as part of a visit from the Macau Group to Lispolis - Lisbon Technological Pole.
The nascent Value thus becomes a “exclusive agent for investor capture services in Portugal, focusing on the involvement of investors in the background” SINO-LUSOPHONE, whose official name is “from Heng Qin Sino-Maluso Technology and Innovation Investment LPF”. This “promotes investments in high quality science and technology innovation companies in Portuguese -speaking countries”, explains the same note.
Thus, this protocol will allow AEIMCP, as a connecting entity between Portugal and the Fund via Macau, and the nascent Value, “reinforce its commitment to support startups, promote transfronhoring investment and create new opportunities for collaboration between Macau, Portugal and other Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Quoted by the same note, AEIMCP's Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said this new agreement shows how the entity, which also organizes the “929 Challenge” contest, is committed to “creating bridges for the global startup growth, facilitating the entry of Portuguese startups into the Chinese market through Macao, as well as the expansion of Chinese startups to Portugal and Europe”.
In turn, Rui Ferreira said that “the signing of this protocol is an important milestone for connecting innovation ecosystems and promoting synergies between macao startups and Portuguese investors”. "We are confident that this partnership will bring significant results for both sides," he added.
At HM, Rui Ferreira explained that the signature of the protocol represents the culmination of a work of about a year.
"We want to promote a model of host of startups and companies from Macao that want to enter Europe through Portugal, and also in the countries of Portuguese expression, and vice versa, that is, to place, through Macau, companies of these territories, but always through Portugal, in the East, in order to obtain easier connections with the Chinese market."
Thousand Visits
Macao's group visited several essential points of the Portuguese entrepreneurship sector. In addition to the visit to Lispolis, considered the “key moment to foster dialogues between Deep Tech startups and potential investors, consolidating Macau's vision as an innovation and entrepreneurship hub with global range”, the entourage passed through the unicorns factory in Lisbon, and the PWC consultant.
Marco Duarte Rizzolio explained to HM the benefits to Macao from the journey through Portugal. “In addition to the interest in the Sino-Lusophone Fund and its preparation, as it will be released soon, our focus has also been the startups. On the visit to Lispolis macao startups made a pitch [attempted investment tarning], presented their products and had a networking session with other startups. Immersion in the Entrepreneurship Ecosystem in Portugal. ”
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, Macao's entourage only took to Portugal to startups with a more advanced business phase, namely Zence Object, founded by Calvin Sio and obtained a $ 2.5 million financing from the Alibaba Group entrepreneurs to the Great Bay area. Zence Object uses patented technology to transform organic waste, namely tea leaves, into alternative plastic and paper products. The idea is that these recycled and transformed products can be used on a daily basis, such as home or decorating utensils.
"There are startups in Macau who are very advanced in terms of business and we have brought to Portugal. We want to explore new opportunities for internationalization, so that they explore other markets, as these startups already have some development. We want to create partnerships, so that these representatives realize what the market is like and explore possible customers," said the representative of AEIMCP.
By unbeaten paths
Macao's entourage is today in Porto to participate in “SIM Conference” [Startups &amp; Investment Matching], where “it will have its own stand to present projects and connect with investors and possible customers”. This event was organized by the Entity Startup Portugal, which invited to be present.
Also today will be signed another protocol, this time between the association that organizes the contest “929 Challenge” and Startup Portugal. The idea is, according to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, “stimulate the connection of the Portugal ecosystem with Macau and help in the process of internationalization of the startups on both sides, both the Portuguese who are intended for the great bay, through Macau, both the macao startups that go to Portugal”.
The official has no doubt that what is lacking in knowledge is left in interest. “There is a great interest in China, but at the same time there is a great ignorance. The startup ecosystem in Portugal is much more linked to Europe. When we talk to the unicorns factory for months, we were told that there was a great interest in the Macao and China market, but that these visits to Portugal were lacking. It is growing a lot in technology and artificial intelligence, with the launch of DeepSeek, for example. ”
According to Rui Ferreira, the presence of the delegation of Macao in “Yes Conference” will allow access to “privileged and wider contacts”, as it is a national event. "With this visit we have been able to do two things: starting the relationship with AEIMCP more formally and helping Macao companies know of partners and investors. We also want to bet on the work for the future Sino-Musso fund, to prepare companies with investment potential," he said.
For Rui Ferreira, the Macao market has the potential “to be used as a business exchange platform, thanks to linguistic connection, and there is conditions in the territory to establish all the part of reception, support and exchange with China entities and create an ecosystem”. In addition, “it will be interesting Macao to make a specialized innovation hub in strategic areas”, which in this case is technology. Highlight for the fact that the visit also had the organization of the Macao Sino-Lusophone Platform Association for sustainable development.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>DSEDJ | Promised helps to students from Macau who study at Harvard</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/dsedj-prometida-ajuda-a-alunos-de-macau-que-estudam-em-harvard/</link><description>Given the hypothesis of Macao students being affected by the conflict between Donald Trump and Harvard University, DSEDJ said it has contacted students and asked local universities to accommodate students to accommodate students
 
The Macao government said it has offered help to young places studying at Harvard University after US President Donald Trump suspending foreign students enrollment at the institution.
The Board of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) said in a statement issued on Saturday that he contacted Macao students at Harvard "to provide permanent counseling and assistance." On Friday, a federal judge in Boston, Massachusetts, temporarily blocked the Trump administration's decision to suspend foreign students at Harvard University.
DSEDJ said it "is closely following the last developments," but stressed that "circumstances are still changing." Still, the Board encouraged Macao universities to provide methods of "convenient transfer" to those affected to "protect students' rights to continue their studies."
"Any concrete measure will be decided by each university in accordance with the actual conditions," said the DSEDJ. On the other hand, the tutelage promised to “continue to promote Macao universities and attract exceptional students from around the world” to promote the internationalization of higher education in the territory.
Example
On Friday, a university in the neighboring region of Hong Kong had already promised to facilitate the registration of students from Harvard University.
Hong Kong University of Science and Technology has promised "unconditional offers, simplified admission procedures and academic support to facilitate a soft transition." The proposed benefits include “accelerated admissions, credit transfers and personalized support” in visa and accommodation assistance, according to a statement.
On Thursday, the US government prohibited Harvard from continuing to enroll foreign students and indicated to those who are already transferred to other universities at risk of losing their immigration status. The university, the most prestigious in the United States, responded to the executive with a judicial action.
Judge Allison D. Burroughs accepted Harvard's temporary suspension of the revocation of permission to welcome international students, representing a quarter of the institution's total students. "Harvard has shown that without a request to temporarily restrict [the Order of Trump], it will suffer immediate and irreparable damage," the judge noted.
The magistrate scheduled an audience about the case for tomorrow, which will be attended by representatives on both sides. Harvard sued the republican government in April to recover his frozen federal financing of $ 2.6 billion for alleged anti-Semite behaviors.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | Tai Kin IP took stock of the implementation of Xi speeches</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/pequim-tai-kin-ip-fez-balanco-da-implementacao-de-discursos-de-xi/</link><description>Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, led a delegation on a trip to Beijing to visit ministries and commissions from central authorities. On Friday, the secretary met with the Hong Kong and Macao Work Office director of the China Communist Party Central Committee (CCP) and the Hong Kong and Macao Staff of the Council of State, Xia Baolong.
According to the secretary's office, Tai Kin IP informed Xia Baolong “about the situation of the scrupulous implementation of the spirit consecrated in President XI Jinping's important speeches”, as well as the political objectives in the area of ​​Sam Hou Fai's economy and finance. Among the goals to be achieved, the Government of MSAR emphasizes the proper diversification of the economy, the construction of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin and the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau, as well as "supporting the state to open to the world to a higher level and support the qualitative development of companies and residents."
During his stay in Beijing, the MSar entourage visited the National Commission for Development and Reform, the Ministry of Science and Technology, the Ministry of Industry and Technologies, the Ministry of Finance, the Popular Bank of China, among other bodies of the central authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:26:31</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM | Construction and Infrastructure Forum in June at Venetian</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/ipim-forum-de-construcao-e-infra-estruturas-em-junho-no-venetian/</link><description>It runs from June 10 to 12, at Venetian, the 16th edition of the International Investment and Investment Investment and Construction Exhibition, organized by the Institute for Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM) and the China International Civil Construtors Association.
The event will have as its central theme “enhanced connectivity for mutually beneficial cooperation”, integrating four areas of exchange between companies, exhibitions, official launches and business promotion, intended for representatives of Fortune 500 companies, national companies, industrial chain leading companies and international organizations.
According to a note from IPIM, it is intended, with this event, to “promote cooperation in the field of infrastructure between China and the international community, leading it to a new level”. At this stage, the organization has already welcomed 13 projects that will make its market debut, linked to areas such as “smart construction, digital intelligence technology, new materials, environmental protection and low carbon”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:25:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Meeting with 50 consular representatives</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/cooperacao-reuniao-com-50-representantes-consulares/</link><description>The Chief Executive had dinner on Friday with representatives of consulates of about 50 countries and international organizations to those who stressed the mission of establishing an international cooperation platform. Sam Hou Fai stressed the importance of strengthening economic, commercial and cultural ties
 
The Government of MSAR organized a reception and dinner on Friday, which was attended by representatives of consulates generals of about 50 countries and international organizations. In the speech at the reception to the representatives, Sam Hou Fai said that "Macau is committed to building an international cooperation platform", and a "high quality abroad opening platform." The leader of the MSA has indicated that the goal is to make Macau "in an important window for mutual exchange and learning between Chinese civilization and Western civilization."
Addressing the international guests, Sam Hou Fai pointed to economic and commercial cooperation, cultural exchange and the connection of people between Macau and those countries, and ensured that its executive will articulate with the national development strategy, “with the driving force the innovation of legal regimes and the optimization of policies”. The goal is to “coordinate the common progress of the government and the market, from Macao and the world, in favor of building a more inclusive, more convenient, and more effective international exchange platform”.
Sam Hou Fai also linked the commitment of his executive in the “reform of public administration, the constant elevation of the efficiency of governance, the innovation of the concept of serving”, and in the creation of “an environment that further facilitates the lives of people and companies”.
The ruler also indicated that all countries and regions are welcome to take advantage of the role of Macao as an international cooperation platform, and invited "companies and tourists from all countries" to "experience the vitality of the development of Macao and China."
Widen the circle
The chief executive also mentioned some of the typical political concepts of MSAR, such as the idea that the principle "one country, two systems" "demonstrates worldwide notable successes." After highlighting the imperative need to ensure sovereignty and national security, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the importance of ensuring “fully a high degree of macao autonomy, keeping the capitalist system and their way of living, its status of International and Autonomous Customs, and the Continental European Law System in Macau”.
The head of executing said that "Macau is willing to share development opportunities with all countries and regions, widening the" circle of friends "to achieve increasingly comprehensive cooperation."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Restoration | Law that regular licensing will be reviewed</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/restauracao-lei-que-regula-licenciamento-sera-revista/</link><description>The government intends to review various legal diplomas in the area of ​​commerce and business, and the 1996 law review, regarding the licensing of food and beverage and bars establishments, will be one of the first to be reviewed, together with the 1998 law that “regulates administrative conditioning of certain economic activities”.
In addition, the 2013 cultural heritage safeguarding law will also be reviewed in order to “guarantee the interests of consumers, the values ​​of cultural heritage, the safety in construction and fire safety”.
The information is in response to Deputy NGAN Iek Hang's written interpellation signed by the Director of Services for Justice Affairs, Leong Weng In. The director states that the review of these diplomas aims to “reduce the negative impacts that relevant legislation can cause to the business environment, namely regarding the start of business activity”.
The executive also wants to bet on the electronization of services for companies, namely the “constitution of commercial companies”, “certificate of admissibility of firm” and “initial registration of commercial entrepreneur and singular person”. This system is in the test phase and should be launched “gradually on the platform for companies and associations [in the single account] in the second and third quarter of this year”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:28:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Insurance sector with higher wages and vacancies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/trabalho-sector-dos-seguros-com-salarios-mais-altos-e-vagas/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) confirm that the insurers 'sector is on the rise, both in the number of vacancies and the average workers' salary. At the end of the first quarter of this year, there were a total of 821 workers in insurance companies, plus 1.1 percent compared to the same period last year, and in March the average remuneration was 34,480 patacas, plus 3.3 percent.
The increase in average remuneration, within the financial sector, was higher for financial intermediation activities, in the order of 5.5 percent. Thus, in March, a worker in this segment earned an average of 30,270 patacas. In global terms, the average remuneration of workers in full time of the financial activities sector was 32,020 patacas, plus 2.7 percent, in annual terms.
At the end of the first quarter there was a 0.7 percent break in the number of bank workers, which had a total of 7,193 employees. This is a reduction of 53 people. In terms of the number of vacancies available at banks, there were 202, eight minus less terms. However, in the insurance segment, the number of vacancies increased by seven, totaling 41.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:25:41</pubDate></item><item><title>One | Investment company in the interior pays 3 million by study</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/um-empresa-de-investimento-no-interior-paga-3-milhoes-por-estudo/</link><description>The University of Macao's investment arm will build the new campus on Mountain Island and before obtaining the license to use the land must have to conduct soil studies. The price of this contract is 3.3 million patacas
 
Guangdong Hengqin A Higher Education Development will pay 2.95 million Renminbis (3.3 million patacas) for soil studies to build the future campus on Mountain Island. This amount adds to the 946 million renminbis paid before the Zhuhai authorities, by granting the land.
According to the information shared by the University of Macao subsidiary (one) at the Portal of the Directorate of Supervision and Management of Public Assets (DSSGAP), studies are a requirement to receive the permanent license of land use on Mountain Island. Only after these works are finished will advance with the works that should have a cost of the thousands of millions of Renminbis.
The study in question was commissioned to the Zhuhai representation of the China Nonferrous Metal Industry Changsha Reconnaissance Design &amp; Research Institute, a multinational from China, which also has activity in countries such as United States, Japan or Germany.
Among the 2.95 million Renminbis, the company of UM admits that a first payment of 2.17 million has been made and that the remaining amount of 780,000 Renminbis will be paid "when conditions are gathered."
In the report, the amount declared with investment in land and construction of assets is 976 million renminbis, although these expenses are not discriminated against, so they may take into account other costs, in addition to the previously announced 946 million Renminbis through the newspaper or Mun.
In terms of operational spending, the company spent 359,000 renminbis on seal tax in the interior of China, and paid 84,000 land use tax renminbis for a total of 443.2 thousand renminbis.
Previous costs are added 80 thousand renminbis paid to intermediates, defined as management expenses, in addition to the payment of financing of 576 thousand Renminbis. At the level of the expense recognized by Guangdong Hengqin, a Higher Education Development are also given donations of 100,000 Renminbis, although the recipient is not indicated.
About 10,000 students
According to the plans previously announced by one, the land of the future campus is divided into nine lots, of which six will be used to build laboratories, colleges, and other university facilities.
The mission is to build an international campus on Mountain Island, with the seal of the Government of MSAR, facing teaching and research in the areas of science, engineering, agriculture and medicine. At least 10,000 students are expected on the campus that is expected to be completed by 2028, the year they will start operations with 8,000 students, including 4,000 to attend undergraduate degrees. The campus is also expected to need about 500 employees to operate, and it is not yet clear whether one will choose local residents or give Chinese residents priority.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:24:47</pubDate></item><item><title>The gravedigge of democracy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/o-coveiro-da-democracia/</link><description>Here he is! Of hand on the chest and neck. To faint. With the televisions all covering all day the route of the ambulances that carried it. Appearing in the Lisbon Square of Ligasures in the Fist and Penses in his arms, pretending to cry in good scholarship and tricky way.
This is, the poor thing, who deserved the illiterate vote of politics, or rather all those who did not think if not in a messiah who will save Portugal from the corrupt, immigrants and Gypsies. From his name André Ventura, he managed to capture the disgruntled to the parties of governance in 51 years of democracy and obtain an unbelievable vote that no polls ever alviped. Ventura is in the largest. On the gravedigge path of democracy.
The arrival will certainly be as the main opposition party, as it seems that the votes of emigrants in Europe and outside Europe will offer two deputies to AD and two at the arrival. The elections have effectively showed everything we have written here over the years: the discontent of the middle class, the low wages, the pensions of misery, the schools with rain entering, the young people without home and emigrates, the poorly paid doctors and nurses, the more likely, the elderly without dignified homes, the poor non -power to buy their medicines. Ruled, transportation to crack and with expensive passes, IRS increasing, income subsidies to be removed to more than 80,000 poor, pregnant women to have their children in ambulances, consultations and surgeries to delay months and, a few years, the absence of social housing or affordable income, domestic violence to be increased and the prevarickers to be sent in freedom. All of these facts have been highlighted in these chronicles and all of these reasons have led to the increase in vote in a neo -fascist party. How was it possible for the always socialist and communist algarve possible to stop at the hands of the arrival? For the discontent that is raising in the Portuguese population.
The arrival even won in Algueirão-Mem Martins, on the outskirts of Lisbon, where the vast majority of residents are made up of maids and lower hierarchical civil servants who get up every day at five o'clock to catch a train for work when there is no strike. It was this phenomenon of discontent with the rulers of the PSD and PS that took many people who are not racist, not xenophobic, not pedophile, does not steal bags, to vote for the arrival. They voted voters who once put the cross on the PSD, the PS, the PCP and even in the Left Block. A friend of ours of the BE conveyed to me that he voted for arrival because he will never forgive Mariana Mortágua had failed party employees who were pregnant. And therefore, we watched the huge fall of the BE that is deadly in Parliament and symptoms of upcoming elections disappear from the hemiciclo.
As for the “Hecatombo” of the Socialist Party was already expected. A party that chose to forget the young people, who has become an anti António Costa feud, who has more than six factions inside to swallow themselves, obviously it would have to fall into disgrace. With more or less reflection, with a new secretary general, it will take many years to get up from the ground, if it does not happen to him the same as the French Socialist Party. Socialist vows with family members living with difficulties went to the arrival. Votes Socialist Anti Pedro Nuno Santos went to the free.
As for AD, who was taken to the lap for televisions, is singing a great victory. Which victory? The number of votes has increased a little and can not even have normal stability to govern. Of the two, one. Either it combines with the arrival, or awaits the small socialist parliamentary group to take advantage of the government program and the state budget. The voices have already been sadly listened to the pepêdist hosts. Hugo Soares and Paulo Rangel have already given the motto that in many proposals there will be a coexistence with the arrival.
The Portuguese did not think twice. They got intoxicated with the promises of Ventura that he could never fulfill, in the face of Portugal, they had no money so that their desiderates were forward and voted for a creature that already had the disappointment of saying that “they have not seen anything” and “I will be the future Prime Minister”.
Ventura is undemocratic, just wants to alter the Constitution, remove the word “socialism” from the Constitution, want to remove all subsidies and houses from the Gypsy communities, to remove, to Laia de Passos Coelho, the vacation and Christmas allowance, to prohibit that in schools there are sexual education, that the police are preferably black because it is a pure racist and, essentially, that the immigrants who are to “hold” to "who are" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are to" who are to be "who are to" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are to" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are to" who are to "to be" to be "who are to" who are to "to" to be "to" Social Security are expelled from Portugal, in a good trumpper way.
Portuguese democracy is in danger. Not now. But in the next legislative elections, if democratic parties are not convinced that they have to come together to defend a regime won with much struggle, arrests and deportations of anti -fascist men. Ventura only has in mind to change the regime and be the gravedigger of democracy, so that it can continue to receive the congratulations from all the far right of Europe and the US. Ventura -If the Portuguese do not open their eyes well and if the rulers do not start solving the survival problems of the majority -will go to the executive head and the neo -fascist tragedy will be a reality in Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:04:36</pubDate></item><item><title>How can Macau be saved?</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/como-e-que-macau-se-pode-salvar/</link><description>The dead have no voice, but the act of suicide talks about misfortune. We cannot cover our ears and pretend we don't hear, nor to cover our eyes and pretend we don't see. The life of each person is precious and unique and one case of suicide is too much.
In response to recent suicide cases and the discovery of corpses, the MSAR Social Action Institute (IAS), together with the competent government departments and social service organizations, has held the “exchange meeting - let's play the role of life guardian, cherishing people around us”. At this meeting, the president of IAS reported that 18 cases of suicide had occurred in the first quarter of 2025, a decrease of four compared to the same period last year. Without a decrease in suicide cases, IAS would not have hurried to hold this meeting. Statistics does not explain everything, but it is in reality that the best explanation is found. To tell a beautiful story about Macau just have some skill, but being able to identify the problems and find a solution is what really matters. If the RAE government does not take practical measures to improve citizens' living conditions and thus restore their trust in the future, tragedies will continue to happen. Even though the coverage of suicides made by the media is an echo of the guidelines “six things to do and eight to avoid” of the IAS, or even if nothing is mentioned, it is believed that cases of unnatural deaths continue to increase.
Polishing the golden image of Macao and releasing the city from misfortune is no difficult task. Just have the same consideration for the lives of the residents that are held by the members of our family, to face their concerns as if they were ours, and to work consciously and responsibly to protect the subsistence of the people, promoting employment. At that time, all problems will be solved. Only when social and survival conditions are guaranteed can the country be safe.
Macau's economy is currently affected by various factors and the situation is not favorable. Among them, there are several social problems that were not effectively communicated or resolved through the appropriate means. Maintaining stability through the use of high -pressure tactics and a chimerical prosperity are mere illusions. When they fall to the ground, illusions naturally lead to a dead end. In fact, as long as the RAE government shows determination and take the necessary measures, Macau can save itself.
Since the game's recipes fell short of expectations and a lot of large -scale construction projects are underway, it is true that the RAE government is facing some financial pressure; Otherwise, this year civil servants would not have had frozen salaries. But with financial reserves accumulated over the years, the RAE government can concentrate capital investment in the development of various projects. And with the synergy effect, Macao's economic problems can be solved. When the economic situation and living conditions improve, Macau residents will naturally prosper and find joy in their lives.
In order to improve people's subsistence conditions and create more job opportunities for residents, I throw the following suggestions. For example, transforming the space of the old Jockey Club into the "Jockey Club Fun Land", taking the land of "Oceanis Park" in the mud, left to abandon, for an "Ocean tea house" or an "Ocean night market" with typical Chinese and Portuguese elements, creating a "Integrated Activities Center" in Seac Pai Van and their surroundings, with services daytime. Also, interconnecting the schools in zone A of new urban landfills to create a “school city”, expedite the transformation of the place of the Galgos de Macao Race Company (Yat Yuen) into a “sports garden for citizens”, introducing a one -year subsidies program for young residents and encouraging free schools and governmental schools to provide job opportunities for the younger ones.
If the Macao government is concerned with its citizens, and scrupulously respect the principle that foreign workers should only be welcomed to supply the lack of labor, reinforce the promotion of the responsible game and minimize all negative factors that affect citizens' mental health, will become the best “guardian of life”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:44:38</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great America (IV)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/a-grande-america-iv/</link><description>“America Great Again with Trump? NO. America Under Trump Previously Was a joke but this time America is fast becoming a train crash. For President who's proud good Was That Never Started any Wars is pulling out all fingers to make up for lost time. Four Years But the Damage He has Created Already Will Take Decades to Repair. ”
Stephen Leader
The founding father, Thomas Paine, to which Trump alludes when he exalts common sense, decreed that "we have the power to begin the world again." The quintessence of the American is (was it?) Look up and beyond, to find out if the European was inserted in the group. The certainty of having no alternative. Manifestly, its destiny is the decline, confused with an eternal gift. America's risk is not the decline, it is the collapse. Because, fixed in itself, it is alienating the world. While compulsively monitoring fever, you forget that your health is always relative to that of rivals that follow your own trajectory. Consider technological supremacy, a parameter based on which America determines the classification of the powers. American elites are unanimously obsessed with the fact that the Chinese surpass America in artificial intelligence (IA).
Trump has just launched, among trumpets, the Stargate public-public colossus, with a declared (inflated) capital of five hundred billion dollars, when he comes to the news that an municipal Chinese company developed capabilities similar to OpenAi and associates, spending a fraction than the confidence of the “trustees” expects, through lateral innovation techniques. Panic in the bag, not even a virtual Pearl Harbor. Patetic are the Beijing charges of technology theft and exploration of the low cost of its, enviable, economic engineers. What other indiscipline have been dedicated to competitors during technological revolutions for example, two centuries ago, from Americans to British?
And when I would take jobs to qualified engineers, what will Trump say to its worshipers? When America accepts that it does not negotiate with itself, it will understand that bullying generates resistance because there are different cultures and interests from its. The great Andrew Marshall Aka Yoda, director of the United States Department of Defense's Office of Net Assessment ”from 1973 to 2015, was aware of that when he insisted on the comparative method in conflict analysis. One who considers himself so superior that he does not have to integrate the cultures and interests of others in the evaluation of power relations, while self -proclaiming absolute lord of his own destiny, prepares the ground for defeat. Marshall left no heir. And Trump has no resemblance to him.
But the “terrible simplifier” risks reaching the same conclusions that Yoda may have arrived regardless of her analytical course. America's salvation does not reside in a return to the super order on the normal system of power. In this effort she would crumble, and all of us with her. It is better, while there is time to satisfy first (not exactly) equal. Revolution that would imply a poignant self-analysis. In turn, only conceivable with an inconceivable “I” distance in Trump, even less in Musk. Fortunately, the heterogenesis of the ends, the old Archimedes slip into the bath and discovers the eponymous principle, disturbs the boredom of determinisms. The stable genius of agreement applies his art to practical geopolitics without extracting it from mathematical models that unnerved Marshall, just because "this is how I have fun." But the agreement is exchange for definition. You may feel and perhaps be a hundred times superior to the rival with whom it negotiates, but by negotiating it accepts it as it is. Legitimizes it. And of course vice versa. So the best or the smartest will win.
Recalling John Fitzgerald Kennedy's (private) reaction to the construction of the Berlin Wall “a thousand times a wall than the war! We would dare to paraphrase“ a thousand times better a negotiation than Revelation! ”.
The frenzy of changing everything so that everything changes before it is too late obscures the beginning of the second Trump and can make it derail. It does not invalidate the fact that, from so much chaos, a principle of new order may arise. More than imperfect, we agree. Nothing to do with Kantian perpetual peace. Something suggests that a big confrontation is not impossible between the United States, China and Russia. Adjust the past and limit the risk of apocalypse. When Trump announces that he wants to take all North America by force, he is not just updating Monroe. You are declaring a moment voucher.
(continues)</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:37:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Princess Mononoke 520 (i)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/20/princess-mononoke-520-i/</link><description>In the last scene of the movie “Princess Mononoke” (“幽灵公主”), performed by Japanese animator Hayao Miyazaki, San chooses to stay in the forest and Ashitaka decides to return to the village. Although they are loved, the moral of history is the mutual respect and liberation of the other so that it can freely live their choices.
The end of this relationship reminds me of a television series broadcast on mainland China called “the story of my best friend” (“流金歲月”). The protagonist is a successful middle-aged businessman and the protagonist is a university student who has just graduated. A casual meeting provoked a love story. Due to the difference in ages, the hero ends up let the heroine go freely behind his dreams.
Later, the heroine married and had a son. When her husband's business was on the verge of bankruptcy, the hero took the initiative to abandon his own business and offered to work with the executive director for his beloved's husband and save the company. He also promised to form his husband to become an excellent boss in three years. In the end, the heroine divorced, but the hero continued not to want to marry her. Once again, he let her go in freedom. The heroine eventually left for Beijing to invest in her career and the story ended here.
The Princess Mononoke and the story of my best friend coincidentally express two points of view about love. Firstly, loving truly means being happy with the happiness of the other. When he is sad, we also sadden, and we sincerely want the best to our beloved. Secondly, true love is free. Lovers do not kidnap themselves or restrict each other in the name of love, because this kind of love is not true, but a kind of control to satisfy self-love. This kind of love ends up imprisoning the other on a cage. Therefore, Princess Mononoke's famous makes it “I come to see you when you miss me.”
Love implies mutual companionship, care and attachment. Companionship means that the two are together and that they accompany themselves mutually. Beware means that we are available to each other whenever you need us. Attachment is loyalty to love. Companionship and care requires time and living in communion is a good foundation. We only take care and follow the people who are dear to us, do not do it for each other. This is attachment.
Mutual companionship, care and attachment are important elements that constitute love. Once these elements are established, they integrate the lives of lovers. When we get sick, the other takes care of us unconditionally. This is careful. If the disease is prolonged and your love continues to take care of you unconditionally, this is companionship. Don't leave you when you are sick. This is attachment. Lovers need time to obtain these three elements. Today you can walk and speak, you are not sick or suffering, so you cannot understand the importance of these three elements.
When do people get more susceptible to the disease? The answer, of course, is when they get older, with age we are contracting various health problems. In the days they run, how many couples are they together in this way? Only with true companionship, care and attachment, we cry and laugh together and wish each other's good. As we mentioned in last week's article, one of Sean Lau Ching Wan's iconic phrases about love is: “One day you will realize that you do not want to live a passionate love, but to have someone who never gives up or ever abandoning you.”
Next week we will continue to analyze the messages of Princess Mononoke and the story of my best friend.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-05-20 02:01:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix Museum | Competition illustrations can be seen until September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/museu-do-grande-premio-ilustracoes-de-concurso-podem-ser-vistas-ate-setembro/</link><description>The winning works of the Illustration Contest of the Gaining Car of Asia's first major award (Macau) are available for public viewing at a Macao Grand Prix Museum (MGPM) museum until September 1st. The contest awards were awarded last Friday, in an organization of the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) and Macau Creatations Limited.
In total, 30 prizes were delivered. The contest had as its main theme the Triumph TR2, the winning car of the first major prize of Macao. In total, 88 works were received, which received more than 10,000 online votes from the public. An evaluation committee also chose the first three classifieds of the group of secondary education candidates and the open group. The contest were also the categories of “most popular internet”, “Merit Awards” and “Finalist Awards”.
In the secondary education group, the winners were Chan Hei Wo, in the first place, followed by Leong Sam U and Ma Nim Ian, as third classified. In turn, in the open group, he won Tam Iok Meng, Lam Si Cheng, in second place and Cheang Ka Ian, in third place.
The exhibition that is now evident in the museum's basement allows “the public to enjoy the award-winning creative and theme artistic works”, and through the illustration, “the public can also feel the precious history of the Macao Grand Prix”, reads in an official note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:01:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Concert | Bruno Pernadas in Macau and inland in June</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/concerto-bruno-pernadas-em-macau-e-no-interior-em-junho/</link><description>June will be filled for Portuguese multi-instrumentalist and composer Bruno Penadas, who, in partnership with the Noyb Association (None of Your Business), star in several concerts in Macau, Hong Kong and other stops from southern China. Lush sounds can hear in Shenzhen on the 12th; in Macau the next day, and then in Zhuhai and Hong Kong
 
The Noyb Association (None of Your Business) is preparing to bring, next June, the tour of Bruno Pernadas, “The Greatest Bay Area Tour 2025”, with concerts in Shenzhen, Macau, Zhuhai and Hong Kong. Thus, the Portuguese, Chinese and other nationalities can listen and closely see the creations of the Portuguese multi-instrumentalist and composer, presenting a journey of sound mergers that wanders between “jazz, futuristic pop, folk, electronics and psychoadelical rock”.
According to a Noyb press note, Bruno Pernadas is a "master of sound alchemy, creating vibrant and immersive landscapes that challenge categorizations, making their concerts an unforgettable experience." “Your fluid approach between genres, combining intricate arrangements with global influences, will take the audience on a musical trip where retro-futurizing melodies meet hypnotic rhythms, and where each note tells a story. More than a series of concerts, this event is a cultural bridge between Portugal and the big bay,” says Noyb.
Highlight for the fact that the concert in Macao will take place two days after June 10 - Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese Communities, and the whole month is dedicated to celebrating Portuguese culture and language.
All songs in one
The raid of Bruno Penas into the music world was through the real Lisbonense Combo and groups such as the "Julie &amp; The Carjackers" or "Minta &amp; The Brooktrout". The first album was titled "How Can We Be Joyful In A World Full of Knowledge?" And was released 11 years ago. This was followed by “Those Who Throw Objects at the Crocodiles Will Be Asked To Retrieve Them” in 2016, and since then it has been added success. Highlight for the release, in 2021, of the album work “Private Reasons”, which ends the sound trilogy created in 2014 and 2016. Later this year, Bruno Pernadas released “Worst Summer Ever”, also creating several sound bands for dance, theater and cinema.
Speaking to the Lisbon Cultural Agenda, Bruno Pernadas spoke of the diversity of musical styles that are present at the work he does. “There is no genre that describes the song I make. There's jazz, there's pop music, a lot of exotic music, some rock, world music… When I make music I don't think so much about it, where genre fits.”
The musician also said, to the same publication, that he does not consider himself a singer. “No, I don't feel singer, at all [laughs]. In other records I sang, but in this corner more, it's a fact. It was hard for me because it's not natural, I don't have tools for that. I sing like anyone, the only difference is that I know the notes I'm singing, but I don't have it. I prefer to play instruments much more.”</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:57:27</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Debate on technology use next Wednesday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/frc-debate-sobre-uso-de-tecnologia-na-proxima-quarta-feira/</link><description>It will take place next Wednesday, at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC), the session “Screen Generation: Navigating Without Limits” [Blue Wave Generations: Surfing Without Limits]. The event aims to discuss the impact of navigation, without limitations, on digital screens, especially in mobile phones and new technologies.
The session, a joint organization of the Association of Young Macanese (AJM), University of São José (USJ) and the Rui Cunha Foundation, will focus on the way excessive time in digital screens affect health and well-being, especially the younger generation, and how it can affect the educational system in Macau, as well as what can be done to balance and manage time (with or without screen), including Introduction of Artificial Intelligence in our near future.
Jacky Ho, director of USJ's Faculty of Health Sciences and “Macao Observatory for Social Development”, is the guest speaker of this event, who will present the theme in this session, moderated by Jerusa Antunes, Vice President of AJM. The lecture, starting at 6.30 pm, is open to the public and will be conducted in English.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:43:20</pubDate></item><item><title>HK / Alliance Française | Session about Mark O'Neill's new book</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/hk-alliance-francaise-sessao-sobre-novo-livro-de-mark-oneill/</link><description>The Alliance Française de Hong Kong will feature, next Wednesday, at 6.30 pm, the event dedicated to talking about the latest book by writer and journalist Mark O'Neill, entitled “Europeans in Hong Kong” [Europeans in Hong Kong].
The session, named “Rencontre Avec Mark O'Neill:‘ Europeans in Hong Kong ”. According to the official presentation of the event, it will talk about how the communities of European nationalities, including members of the Macanese community, shaped local society and developed various community and social support initiatives.
“In nineteenth-century Hong Kong social pressures led to the abandonment of many women, the vulnerable. The Les Soeurs of Saint-Paul Congregation, arrival in Hong Kong in 1848, offered refuge [to poor people],” and between 1848 and 1897 supported more than 34,000 children, mostly Chinese and girls. "This act of compassion represents one of the most significant European contributions to Hong Kong," he describes.
Mark O'Neill was born in London, UK, and has been living in Hong Kong for many years. He was a journalist and since 2006 he has been dedicated to writing full time, having already launched 12 books on social and cultural issues in the region and China, including biographical works.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:42:10</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI | Confirmed suspended arrest of six months to doctoral student</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/tsi-confirmada-prisao-suspensa-de-seis-meses-para-doutorando/</link><description>The Court of Second Instance (TSI) confirmed the sentence to six months in prison to the student at a local university, who tried to corrupt the thesis advisor with 8 thousand patacas. Confirmation of the conviction was released on Friday by the courts of MSAR. The penalty was suspended for two years, due to the payment of 15 thousand patacas to the MSAR.
Despite entering an unidentified local college in August 2020 and having as a deadline for the delivery of the PhD Thesis May 2023, the student only began to discuss the structure of work with the advisor in March 2023. Presenting a project that did not meet the advisor's requirements, and in view of the prospects of not being approved, the student placed an 8,000 -borrowed red envelope inside a book Advisor, leaving this book in the advisor's mailbox.
However, the teacher refused the offer and eventually complained to the authorities. This was not the student's first monetary offer to the teacher. In 2020, the student had offered valleys and money to the tutor, who, in turn, refused the offer and warned the student that the behavior was illegal and possibly constituted the crime of corruption.
With the following case to the courts, the first instance sentenced the student for the crime of active corruption, with a sentence of arrest of six months, suspended for two years, and the payment of 15,000 patacas to the MSAR.
The defendant resorted to the conviction for arguing that the money had been offered to “obtain more academic guidance” and never with the purpose of corrupting the teacher to facilitate the approval of the thesis. However, the TSI declined the arguments and maintained the condemnation of the first instance.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:40:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Inflation in Macau is 0.23% in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/economia-inflacao-em-macau-fixa-se-em-023-em-abril/</link><description>The consumer price index in Macau rose 0.23 percent in April, in annual terms. The section of leisure, recreation, sport and culture was the one that recorded the largest monthly price increase, 2.47 percent, due to the inflation of the hotel rooms. In the first four months of the year, the price index grew 0.17 percent compared to the same period as 2024
 
Last April the Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 0.23 percentage points compared to April 2024, and 0.16 percent compared to the previous month, according to data released on Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
Prices of the leisure, recreation, sport and culture section increased by 2.47 percent compared to April 2024, mainly driven by the climb of hotel room prices.
The price index of the food products and non-alcoholic beverages grew 0.48 percent in the month under analysis, "thanks to the climbing price of meal acquired away from home and" Take-Away "," the same source added. In monthly terms, the prices of non-alcoholic food and beverages have slightly descended from March (0.04 percent), because the additions of meal prices acquired outside the home and “take-away” did not completely compensate for fresh fish prices, fresh and fruit products and fruit products ”.
Spring-summer fashion
With regard to housing and fuels, DSEC data demonstrates an annual climb was 0.21 percent due to an increase in home rents.
In the section of clothing and footwear, DSEC indicated that prices rose 0.78 percent in April compared to the previous month, "thanks to the launch of summer clothing." Still, in annual terms the clothing and shoe section fell 2.35 percent.
While in transport the monthly climb was 0.42 percent due to “the increase in airplane ticket prices”, although annual comparison, a break of 1.67 percent was verified. On the other hand, in the fourth month of the year, an annual drop in information and communication prices (-3.01 percent) was recorded, a section that also registered a monthly break of 0.07 percent.
DSEC also indicated that in the 12 months ended in April, the IPC rose 0.42 percent over the immediately preceding 12 months. During this period, the sections that “had the most notable additions” were various products and services (+2.47 percent), education (+2.21 percent) and health (+1.62 percent). In the opposite direction, transports fell 3 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:39:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Traffic | Tourist crosses road off the treadmill and is run over</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/transito-turista-atravessa-estrada-fora-da-passadeira-e-e-atropelada/</link><description>A interior tourist had to be transported to the Conde São Januário Hospital Center, after crossing Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro off the treadmill. The accident happened around 11:30 am, when the wife and a friend decided to cross the road, ending one of them for being hit by a TCM bus.
As a result of the accident, the woman was transported to the hospital with head injuries, although she had kept conscious. The bus got the cracked front glass.
Despite the injuries, both the injured tourist and the friend, were eventually fined by the authorities, for crossing the road off the treadmill.
The accident led to the TCM company to issue a statement to explain the situation. According to the company's version, the driver was surprised by two women who appeared behind other vehicles that followed the road, which did not have enough time for the driver to lock. The company also indicated that after the accident the response mechanisms were activated for these situations, with the driver calling the rescue teams and the police.
The accident became viral, with several images online, including the victim bleeding on the road. Some of the images were altered using artificial intelligence, to show the two tourists dance in the middle of the road, which did not correspond to reality.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:37:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro | Government denies delays in building the east line</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/metro-governo-nega-atrasos-na-construcao-da-linha-leste/</link><description>In the best scenario, the opening of the new Metro line will take place in July 2029. The construction works of the north and southern segments of the East Line are evaluated at 9.3 billion patacas, but infrastructure costs will be borne by 2031
 
The Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) states that the construction of the eastern Metro Line has a “good progress” and that the conclusion in the first quarter of 2028 is provided. In a statement issued on Saturday, DSOP acknowledged that the southern and northern east line works will cost about 9.3 billion patacas, according to the price of adjudication.
"The construction works of the east line of the Light Metro began in the third quarter of 2023, scheduled for the first quarter of 2028," was informed by DSOP. Nevertheless, the opening of the line to circulation should only happen after July 2029, given the need to do the circulation tests of the subway. "Subsequently, commissioning and testing of the circulation system will be performed, and the East Line project is advancing towards the purpose of gathering the conditions for its entry into the second half of 2029," he was explained.
"Like the bar line, the Hengqin line and the Pai Van Seac line that were completed recently, after the construction works were completed, were still subject to the installation of the circulation system and the tests to have conditions of operation," was indicated. "Taking as reference the conclusion, within the expected period and without delays, of the three lines of the light meter, the East Line's work plan is viable," he was added.
41 percent progress
Regarding the works of the southern and northern segments of the East Line, the cost of adjudication was 9,281 million patacas, being “being paid according to the progress of the work”.
Although the works are completed until 2028, DSOP explained that the payments will be extended by 2031, which was justified with the fact that some works are only “performed after the east line operates.
Government communication also served to make a point of situations, indicating that the work is completed at 41 percent. "Currently, the works related to the circulation system have already begun, while the construction work of underground stations, the tunnel using tuning and the linked mud binding viaducts are also underway, and the work of some mandatory goals has been completed in advance," was revealed. "At this stage, the completion of the global project is concluded by about 41 percent and its progress and budget are as expected," he was nominated.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:35:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Startup transforms tea residues into paper, packaging and furniture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/startup-transforma-residuos-de-cha-em-papel-embalagens-e-mobiliario/</link><description>A Macao-based 'start-up' has created a business based on tea plantations in China, which recycles on paper, shopping bags, glasses, toothbrushes, electronic and even furniture sheets. Zence Object Holding already has more than 20 active projects in areas such as interior decoration, beverage packaging, among others, which develops with various customers, who are also partners, namely restaurants, hotels and conference centers.
Every year, China produces about 100 tons of tea waste, which end in the trash, according to the China's annual report of China in 2023. On the other hand, the country produces about 200 million tons of plastic waste annually, according to a UN report by 2023.
Zence has seen in the need to “solve global waste problems” an opportunity, seeming perfectly the idea of ​​turning tea waste into recycled ecological materials.
The company founded in 2023, with a capital of six million patacas, expects to reach the return on investment next year and be profitable in 2028. "A ton of tea residues can give rise to ten tons of tea-based bioplastic, flexible and versatile like plastic," the company's co-founder Bob Hou Keung told Lusa.
The same weight of tea residue can make 150 table tops, or cluster panels with size 120x60x1.8cm, which can be used in the “direct replacement of the majority of wood panels”, with the “triple of the hardness of cement”, added the entrepreneur.
Cooperation with neighbors
About a ton of tea waste per month, coming directly from a tea plantation from Fujian province, one of China's largest tea -producing provinces, is sent to two Zence factories in Guangdong province, Lei said.
The industrial process integrates technologies of modification of biological -based plastics and mixture of vegetable fibers, biomaterial modification, production and manufacture.
"After gathering the tea residues, we process them, sterilize them, we begin to turn them into a grain-shaped tea-based bioplastic, which after melting is shaped by a machine," the businessman explained. Law stressed that tea residues “can be decomposed 100 percent natural”, “without formaldehyde” and “neutral in terms of carbon”.
A cup of coffee, for example, contains 10 percent pure tea leaves with vegetable polymers and polyhydroxialcanoates (PHA)-natural biodegradable polymers, “buried in the ground, and can completely decompose within 60 to 90 days,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:34:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Number of doctors and nurses per inhabitant without increases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/saude-numero-de-medicos-e-enfermeiros-por-habitante-sem-aumentos/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) disclosed by Health Services (SS) show that between 2023 and 2024 there was no increase in the number of health professionals in the territory in terms of the average of doctors or nurses per number of inhabitants.
Thus, at the end of last year there was an average of 3 doctors (2.9) per thousand inhabitants; 1 doctor (1,1) of traditional Chinese medicine (MTC) for every thousand people; Less than one dentist or dentist (0.4) for every 1,000 people and still about 4 nurses per thousand inhabitants (4.44). These are “data similar to those of 2023,” says DSEC.
Still, and in global terms, Macau registered 50 more doctors enrolled in annual terms, totaling 2,030; plus 732 traditional Chinese medical doctors or registered traditional Chinese medicine masters, an increase of only four, in annual terms; and a reduction of two registered dentists, in a total of 304. In turn, the territory gained another 78 nurses within one year, with 3,058 registered in late 2024.
In terms of the number of beds there were, at the end of last year, 1,779 beds in the five local hospitals, a reduction of 103 in annual terms “mainly due to the transfer of beds to sick”. Inpatient beds increased by 96 units compared to 2023, but their 71.5 percent use rate recorded a homologous decrease of 2.3 percentage points. Noteworthy, in these statistics, for a light rise of 0.5 percent, between 2023 and 2024, of the care in the emergency services of all hospitals, in a total of 463 thousand.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:36:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Zape | Seized 651 tobacco packs in convenience stores</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/zape-apreendidos-651-macos-de-tabaco-em-lojas-de-conveniencia/</link><description>Following a complaint, the Office for prevention and control of smoking and alcoholism of health services seized 651 cigarette packs in two convenience stores in the Zape area.
According to a statement released yesterday by the services DER HEALTH, it was found that the stores had a large amount of cigarettes whose labeling was not in accordance with the legal provisions of Macao. In one of them, 159 packs were found (totaling 3180 cigarettes) and the other 492 packs (totaling 9840 cigarettes). Those responsible for the convenience stores in question did not show import documents.
Tobacco was seized by customs services and health services will follow the case and, if the offense is confirmed, those responsible for stores can be punished with a fine up to 200,000 patacas.
Health services have reiterated that "to ensure residents' health, Macau law rigorously regulates the circulation of tobacco products, appealing to traders not to risk luck or challenging the law, otherwise they are severely punished."</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:34:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim committed himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my rank of hatter at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over the referected zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>ASEAN | Malaysia calls for the largest union in the face of US tariffs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/asean-malasia-apela-a-maior-uniao-face-a-tarifas-dos-eua/</link><description>Southeast Asia should accelerate economic integration, diversify markets, and remain united in the face of disturbances in global trade resulting from US tariffs, said the head of Malaysian diplomacy yesterday.
Malaon Foreign Minister Mohamad Hasan spoke during the opening of the first annual summit of heads of state and government of the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean) in Kuala Lumpur.
"ASEAN countries are among the most affected by US -imposed tariffs. Trade war between the US and China is drastically disturbing production and commerce standards around the world," said Mohamad.
The diplomat even admitted that "it is likely that there is a global economic slowdown." "We must take advantage of this moment to deepen regional economic integration, so we can better protect our region from external shocks," added Mohamad.
ASEAN countries, many of which depend on exports to the US, are suffering from tariffs ranging from 10 percent and 49 percent. Six of the association's ten member countries were among the most affected, with tariffs ranging from 32 percent and 49 percent.
ASEAN has unsuccessfully attempted to mark an initial meeting with the US as a block. ASEAN's unit is crucial, as the region deals with the impacts of climate change and the disturbance caused by the use of artificial intelligence and other unregulated technologies for criminal purposes, Mohamad said.
The diplomat added that Asean, whose rotary presidency belongs to Malaysia, will be tested by external pressure, including a rivalry between superpowers. "External pressures are increasing, and the scope of challenges has never been so big," said Mohamad. "Therefore, it is crucial that we reinforce the bonds that unite us, so that they do not disqual to external pressures. For Asean, unity is now more important than ever," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:09:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Israelite attacks have been 52 dead since Saturday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/gaza-ataques-israelitas-fazem-52-mortos-desde-sabado/</link><description>At least 52 people have died in the Gaza range since early Saturday morning due to Israelite air strikes, Palestinian news agency Wafa said. On Saturday night, an Israeli Defense Forces Drone (IDF) attacked a family business in the Al Hakr neighborhood of Deir Al-Balah in the center of the Gaza Strip, killing five Palestinians.
At night, the Israelite Air Force also launched attacks on communities east of Khan Yunis in the south of the Gaza Strip, where several IDF helicopters have also opened fire. In the north of the enclave, air strikes and “intense shots” were reported by the Israeli forces in various places, including Beit Lahia and the northeast of Jabalia. Local and doctors had already advanced the deaths of at least eight more people in the city of Gaza and seven more in Rafah, in the south of the track, where about 60 people were also injured.
The worst nightmare
The attacks appear after the Hamas Government Ministry of Health, in the Gaza Strip, registered 79 dead on Friday, including nine children of a pediatrician who was working at the hospital when the bodies arrived.
According to Hamas, pediatrician Alaa Al Najjjjaros was working at Nasser Hospital in Khan Youis (southern Gaza) when the bodies of nine of his 10 children (Yahya, Rakan, Raslan, Jibran, Eve, Rivan, Luqman, Sadeen and Sidra) arrived after being killed in an attack on their home.
Pediatrician's husband, Hamdi Al Najjar, and the only surviving son, Adam, both seriously injured, are being treated in the intensive care unit. The images released after the attack by QDS News Network show Hamdi on the stretcher with bass burns.
The oldest of the deceased children was 12 years old, according to the director general of the Ministry of Health of Gaza, Munir Al-Bursh. The rescue video of the bodies shows the Gaza Civil Defense agents and the Crescent Palestinian red to remove the children's charred bodies from the house, one after another.
"She left them to do their duty and mission to all children who do not find another place at the Nasser Hospital, which is full of innocent screams and weakened by the disease, hunger and tiredness," wrote the doctor, Youssef Abu Al Rish, in a note released yesterday by health services.
Updated data yesterday, by the Ministry of Health they raise to more than 53,900 the number of people killed in Gaza since Israel launched an offensive. The war broke out in Gaza after an unprecedented attack by the Palestinian Islamite group Hamas on Israeli soil on 7 October 2023, which caused about 1,200 dead and more than two hundred hostages.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:06:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Pyongyang | Three leaders after accident with war ship</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/pyongyang-detidos-tres-dirigentes-apos-acidente-com-navio-de-guerra/</link><description>The launch of a new war ship was marked by an accident that affected the boat's hull, allowing the water to enter, and which led to the cancellation of the ceremony
 
North Korea detained three leaders under an investigation into an accident on Wednesday during the release ceremony of a new war ship. "The authorities detained Kang Jong Chol, chongjin shipyard engineer, Han Kyong Hak, head of the hull building workshop, and Kim Yong Hak, vice-director of administrative affairs," said the group that is analyzing the incident, quoted on Saturday by KCNA.
The North Korean official news agency said leader Kim Jong-un, who was present at the release ceremony of the five thousand tons in the port city of Chongjin, described the accident as a "criminal act."
On Friday, the KCNA had said that an underwater and internal inspection of the war ship "confirmed that, contrary to what was initially announced, there was no gap in the bottom of the ship." However, "the stroke hull was scratched and a little sea water entered the stern section by the emergency exit," the agency added, ensuring that the damage suffered by the "not serious" war ship.
"No more damage to the war ship" and "the rehabilitation plan is advancing as scheduled," KCNA said on Saturday. According to the US and South Korea information services, the “side launch attempt” of the ship has failed.
The Fatherworthy is currently inclined in the water, the South Korean military said. Satellite images from the site showed the ship lying on the side, with most of the submerged hull and covered by blue covers.
In search of balance
Hong Kil-ho, the shipyard director where the accident occurred, was summoned by a military commission on Thursday, KCNA added.
North Korean experts estimate that “two or three days to restore the balance of the war ship that pumps water from the flooded section,” the agency said. The repair of the hull of the Freemaker should take about ten days, he added.
The name of the boat was not specified. In April, Pyongyang released images of a five thousand tonword -filed ship, called Choe Hyon. At the time, state media transmitted Kim images to participate in a ceremony with their daughter, Kim Ju-AE, that many experts believe it will be the successor in power.
North Korea claimed that the ship was equipped with the "most powerful weapons" and "would enter service early next year."
According to some experts, Choe Hyon may be equipped with short -range tactical nuclear missiles, although North Korea has not yet proven to develop small nuclear weapons. Public recognition of technical or administrative failures is highly unusual in North Korea.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:53:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazil | Chinese company GAC starts sales of electric and hybrid vehicles</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/brasil-empresa-chinesa-gac-inicia-vendas-de-veiculos-electricos-e-hibridos/</link><description>Chinese car manufacturer GAC wants to sell up to eight thousand electric and hybrid vehicles in Brazil this year and 29,000 by 2026, as well as establishing a production line that has described as comprehensive.
GAC, the sixth largest car builder in China, said on Friday, at an event in Sao Paulo, which will start selling four models in 83 dealers, although the goal is to reach 120 points of sale by the end of the year.
The models range from price from 169 thousand reais (26,300 euros), the cheapest, up to 350 thousand reais (54,500 euros), the most expensive.
GAC President Feng Xingya said in a statement that they will produce cars “with the most modern technologies in the world” and that Brazil is now a “priority market” for them. Xingya added that the company's mission is to make the sector more competitive and align it with the principles of green mobility and energy efficiency.
The company, which operates in approximately 70 countries and produces more than two million cars annually, has promised to create an innovation and development center in the South American country to support operations. The company's executives announced last week during a meeting with Brazilian President Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, who will invest $ 1.3 billion in the country, without specifying a deadline.
Chinese rival Byd announced in late 2024 that it planned to start producing electric vehicles in Brazil from March, with the purpose of manufacturing 150,000 units throughout the year, a number that would double by 2026. The Brazilian government has sought to increase investment in the production of less polluting vehicles through a tax incentive program.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:52:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Patriots at a party from 1 to 5 June</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/hong-kong-patriotas-em-festa-de-1-a-5-de-junho/</link><description>Hong Kong's patriotic groups will hold a party a party for the third consecutive year, supported by the territory government, which coincides with another anniversary of the events of 1989 in Beijing in Tiananmen. The event takes place from June 1st to 5th in Parque Victoria, which for more than three decades, until 2019, was the place of annual vigils to mark Tiananmen.
Rock Chen, from the Zhejiang United Residents Association, told the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper that the program and the place are “the same as in previous years”, stressing that “there is no intention to overshadow the birthday” of June 4, 1989. This year, Carnival will include “experiences of innovation and technology, a sports competition, as well as traditional culinary delights and cultural shows of cultural shows several Chinese provinces ”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Commerce | Beijing and Berlin want stable economic relations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/comercio-pequim-e-berlim-querem-relacoes-economicas-estaveis/</link><description>Xi Jinping and Friedrich Merz spoke on the phone to hit needles about trade between the two nations and reinforce the economic connections between China and the European Union
 
China and Germany defended Friday the establishment of “stable and predictable” ties between Beijing and Berlin, involving the European Union (EU), with the German chancellor stressing the importance of “loyal competition” in economic relations.
According to a spokesman for Friedrich Merz's government, and in the first telephone conversation with Xi Jinping, the German chancellor insisted on “loyal competition”, but also in “reciprocity” between the two powers, at a time when the intense trade between China and Germany is full of geopolitical and economic tensions.
For his part, Chinese President Xi Jinping, created by the state -owned news agency Xinhua, appealed to Merz to establish “stable and predictable” ties between Beijing and Berlin, as well as with the European Union.
"The correct status on relations between China and Germany and between China and the European Union is that of partners," said XI, adding that "a stable and predictable political environment is an important guarantee of bilateral cooperation."
Xi Jinping also appealed to Germany to open more bilateral investments between the two countries. "I hope Germany will provide more political support and facilities for bilateral investment cooperation, as well as a fair, transparent and non -discriminatory business environment for Chinese companies," said Xi Jinping.
Merz, for his part, also urged Beijing to support peace efforts in Ukraine, underlining the "desire to work in partnership to face global challenges."
"The two leaders discussed the War of Russian aggression against Ukraine. The chancellor reported on joint efforts from Europe and the United States to reach a quick ceasefire. He asked these efforts to be supported," according to a German government press release.
On Thursday, after a telephone conversation with Xi, French President Emmanuel Macron assured the Chinese counterpart that he shared "the same goal regarding the war led by Russia": "A lasting and solid peace [which] begins with an immediate and unconditional ceasefire."
Exchange of materials
At a time when the intense trade between China and Germany is full of geopolitical and economic tensions, Merz stressed the importance of “loyal competition” and “reciprocity” between the two powers during his meeting with XI.
Many subsidized Chinese products are flooding Europe, and the German market in particular, raising concerns about impact on local industry. These products range from electric cars, supported by state subsidies, to cheap Chinese solar panels, as well as the current iron arm on steel.
For his part, Xi asked Germany to give more support for bilateral investment, according to Chinese state press.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timor-Leste | Permanent prohibition permanent martial arts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/timor-leste-admitida-proibicao-permanente-artes-marciais/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Timor-Leste, Xanana Gusmão, admitted yesterday the possibility of permanently banning the practice of martial arts in the country, considering that they continue to divide young Timorese.
"It's all going well, although there is still problems in some places. That's why today (yesterday) I proposed that, in the Council of Ministers, we look at the best way, that it may really end it, because this issue is dividing young people," said Xanana Gusmão.
"We are both siblings [direct cousins], but only because we belong to different martial arts groups, we have to get away and we are no longer well," lamented the prime minister. The head of the Timorese government spoke to journalists after a meeting with President José Ramos-Horta at the Presidency Palace in Dili, before the meeting of the Council of Ministers.
Xanana Gusmão also showed concern for young people's behavior, noting that security reports indicate that problems continue to occur, including physical aggression, and argued that there is therefore a decision to make a decision.
On Tuesday, during the National Flag Içar ceremony, under the celebrations of the 23rd anniversary of the Restoration of Independence, confrontations between young people caused a dead at the CAILACO Administrative Post, in the municipality of Bobonaro.
According to the Timor-Leste National Police, the young people involved in the clashes belonged to two martial arts groups, who have been in conflict since Monday, having also attacked the home of a veteran.
In early April, the government of Timor-Leste decided to extend the suspension of teaching, learning and practice of martial arts by the end of 2025 to continue to consolidate social peace and ensure that in the future the practice of martial arts stems exclusively in sports.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:47:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul | Pyongyang fired cruise missiles to the sea</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/seul-pyongyang-disparou-misseis-de-cruzeiro-para-o-mar/</link><description>The South Korean army said North Korea yesterday fired unidentified cruise missiles to the sea, hours after Pyongyang admitted a "serious accident" with a new war ship.
The South Korean joint staff said it had detected the missiles near the Southern Hamgyong Province in eastern North Korea, which were fired towards the Japan Sea.
The launch took place hours after the official North Korea press had advanced with a "serious accident" that occurred during the release ceremony of a war ship. During the release ceremony of a five-ton-ton setback in the port city of Chongjin, “a serious accident occurred,” said the North Korean official news agency KCNA.
North Korean leader Kim Jong-un was present at the ceremony, held on Wednesday in the northeast of the country, and said it was a "criminal act caused by absolute neglect" that "could not be tolerated," KCNA said.
Pointing to the "inexperience of command and operational negligence" during the launch, the agency said "some sections of the war ship's background were crushed" and that the accident "destroyed the battle ship's balance."
Kim said the "irresponsible errors" of the culprits would be "approached at the Plenary Meeting of the Party Central Committee, to be held next month." The name of the boat was not specified. In April, Pyongyang released images of a five thousand tonword -filed ship, called Choe Hyon.
At the time, state media transmitted Kim images to participate in a ceremony with their daughter, Kim Ju-AE, that many experts believe it will be the successor in power. North Korea claimed that the ship was equipped with the "most powerful weapons" and "would enter service early next year."</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:46:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | President requires government resignation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/filipinas-presidente-exige-demissao-do-governo/</link><description>The president of the Philippines, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., demanded yesterday the resignation of all members of the government, after having obtained a worse result than expected in the interchange elections of May 12.
Marcos Jr. “requested the dismissal by courtesy of all office secretaries,” said the presidential palace in a statement, a measure that aims to give the president “the margin of maneuver necessary to evaluate the performance of each department and determine who will continue to serve”.
The order was taken after the candidates supported by Marcos Jr. to the Senate, the Alta Chamber of the Philippines Parliament, had fewer places than expected in the interchange elections held on May 12.
"The people spoke and expect results, no political maneuvers or excuses. We hear them and we will act," said the president. The elections were marked by the dispute between the candidates of Marcos Jr. and those supported by the vice president and former Alleada Sara Duterte.
The vote came months after the father, former President Rodrigo Duterte (2016-2022), was extradited to be tried for crimes against humanity by the International Criminal Court due to war against drugs. Despite being detained in The Hague, Rodrigo Duterte was reelected as Mayor of Davao, in Mindanao, in southern Philippines, a position he held before running the head of state.
The presidency said yesterday that government services “will remain uninterrupted” during the transition, during which it will evaluate the performance of the current secretaries before deciding whether or not they will be replaced.
Falling
The son of the late dictator Ferdinand Marcos (1917-1989) is three years old until the end of his term and, according to the statement, ministerial renewal represents "a new phase totally focused on the most urgent needs of the population."
To date, more than a dozen of the 23-time secretaries have dismissed or announced their intention to abandon the position, together with agency leaders under the control of the president, such as Manila's Metropolitan Development Authority.
Among them was Finance Secretary Ralph G. Recto, who, in a statement, praised the “bold decision” made “with the desire to give priority to people and the country”. Energy Secretary Raphael Lotilla noted that the order of resignation is "an excellent opportunity to take stock and invigorate the government."
The measure was taken after the president recognized on Monday that the bad results of the elections were due to the disappointment of the Philippines with the government's performance. Marcos Jr.'s approval rate fell to 25 percent, according to a survey held in March, a sharp drop from the 42 percent rate in February.
The interviewees pointed to the government's failure to control inflation, unbridled corruption in the country and the lack of measures to combat poverty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:45:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, mapping those that were written during the remainder of his Asian designer would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the appropriate place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account] to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
What other projects are in this book?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Yes. The idea of ​​publication, with Barcelona's Actar Books, has to do with putting the work, and more than that, its message, which is very specific to Macau and our way of working in the international and architects community, and this goes a lot through the Biennial. It was also in Europe that a consensus was built on the level of descriptions [in architecture] for a few centuries, and where there is a discussion, national and international, around the issues of the profession. We want our work to be present, either through the book and through acting Books, in this international community, to be part of the world.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through the space narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will lead lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and see as soon as I was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the guide circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of copies produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos further underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major goal will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name in Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao's historicals get a GP clearance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/20/historicos-de-macau-conseguem-apuramento-para-gp/</link><description>The Guangdong International Circuit welcomed, last weekend, the second and decisive double journey of Macao - Macau Road Sport Challenge cars, proof of finding for the most important motor racing of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. In a journey with few celebration reasons for the colors of the sinters, the veterans Jerónimo Badaraco and Rui Valente managed to ensure the qualification.
With a list of 68 subscribers, the grill was divided into two groups, A and B, with all the pilots competing with Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) models. This year, with only one race scheduled for the Grand Prix Program - due to the inclusion of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup - the number of riders was reduced to 36, which placed a supplementary pressure for both missing races. To complicate, the rain came, changing the turns to teams and riders.
In Group A, where Rui Valente faced a complicated weekend on the track around Zhaoqing, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão failed to qualify, in a series dominated by Hong Kong pilots. In Saturday's race, the podium consisted of Wong Chuck Pan, Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping. On Sunday, these three repeated the feat, but with a new order: Lo Pak Yu, Chan Ka Ping and Wong Chuck Pan.
In difficult atmospheric conditions on Saturday, Rui Valente ended only 25th, due to an error in tuning, improving to 15th on Sunday, with the track dry. A penalty after the second race fired him to the 27th place. Still, the 7th place obtained on the first round was enough to secure a place in the Macao Grand Prix.
On the contrary, Maximiano Mannão, behind the wheel of a Toyota with the colors of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended on 26th and 14th, a result below the finding, but it turns out to be positive given that it was Jove Pilot's debut in these wanderings. Célio Alves Dias, with difficulties in his car since the first race, was 24th and 28th, far from the usual level of this experienced Macaense pilot.
Badaraco with final sprint '
On a weekend, where the lively races were broadcast on live streaming in Group B, Hong Kong riders stood out again. On Sunday, Adrian Chung won, with Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin completing the podium. In the second confrontation, Cheang Kin Sang reached a deserved victory, followed again by Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin.
Jerónimo Badaraco came to this challenging weekend without the assured clearance. A modest qualification and 11th Saturday place maintained the open outcome. However, a solid race on Sunday and an excellent 4th place assured veteran Macanese the much desired place on the grid of the Macao Grand Prix, along with countrymen Cheng Kin San, Leong Keng Hei, Lou Check In and Carson Tang.
Also outside the Grand Prix was Dionísio Albino Pereira, who finished 23rd in Saturday's race, but closed the time more forcefully, cutting the line of goal in 13th place in the second race.
At the end of the races, competitors provisionally calculated had an extra technical verification, being forced to open engines and gearbox, to verify the legality of these two decisive organs of their vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-05-20 01:57:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Council of Motorsport approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and an enthusiast of the MSAR test, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The potential for growth and development in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into detail, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula cup last year, says that “this big step will undoubtedly benefit local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSar pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSAR VICTORY AND TOP-10 to Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite Safety Car's entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet beginning, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, third in the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item></channel></rss>