<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>India/Accident | Pilot declared “Mayday” seconds after take off</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/india-acidente-piloto-declarou-mayday-segundos-apos-descolagem/</link><description>The Ministry of Civil Aviation of India revealed Saturday that the AI171 Air India Flight pilot, which fell with 242 people on board, declared an emergency Mayday seconds after offspring, and that the aircraft fell almost exactly a minute later.
In the first official statement of the Indian government since the accident on Thursday, the Secretary of Civil Aviation, Samir Kumar Sinha, made a minute report of the final moments of the flight. "The plane took off at 13:39, local time, and in seconds, after reaching an altitude of about 650 feet (almost 200 meters), began to sink, that is, to lose altitude," said Sinha.
The official added: "At 1:39 PM, the pilot reported the Air Traffic Control (ATC) in Ahmedabad that it was a Mayday." According to the secretary, when the ATC tried to contact the plane again after the emergency call, it did not get any response.
"Exactly a minute later, at 1:40 pm, the plane dumped in Meghaninar, a zone about two kilometers from the airport," he added. The ministry also confirmed that 242 people were on board the plane: 230 passengers, two pilots and 10 crew.
About the previous state of the device, the secretary said that before the accident, the plane had made the Paris-Delhi-Ahmedabad route without incident. The number of dead in the AI171 flight tragedy of Air India rose to at least 279.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:34:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Education | Lam regrets Vong Fong Va's death</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/educacao-o-lam-lamenta-falecimento-de-vong-fong-va/</link><description>Tomorrow is the funeral of Professor Vong Fong VA, who died on June 4 with 94 years. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, issued a statement on Saturday to regret the death of the man who devoted almost half a century to education, highlighting the time of the time as deputy director of Hou Kong Secondary School.
Lam stressed Vong Fong Va's dedication to teaching and patriotism, a work that earned him the silver lotus medal of honor awarded by the Government of MSAR.
Vong Fong VA has occupied prominent places in various local associations. He was vice-president of the General Association of Chong Wa de Macau Students, vowel of the Macao's Return of the Return of Macau, President of the Macao Education Association, President of the Friendship and Coordination Association of former National Popular Assembly and former Member of the Chinese Political Conference of Macao, “uniting the forces of associations in the love of Macao and Macao, promoting the Macao,”, promoting prosperity and macao stability ”,” He pointed out Lam.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:00:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice | TSI maintains a sentence of 9 months in prison for the theft necklace</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/justica-tsi-mantem-pena-de-9-meses-de-prisao-por-furto-de-colar/</link><description>The second instance (TSI) court refused to suspend a 9 -month prison sentence, applied to a tourist who stole a jewelry store necklace in Macao. The decision was announced last Friday, through a statement from the office of the president of the last court.
The case happened on March 11, 2023, when the criminal brought a fake necklace to Macao, in order to go to a store and exchange it for an original, getting the most valuable. In the store he frequented, after entering Macao, the necklace from which he was intended to appropriate was evaluated 37,300 patacas.
With the excuse that he intended to buy the necklace, the man managed to change it for the other who brought inside the coat. With the exchange made, eventually left the store without making the purchase. Initially, the store workers did not detect the original necklace change for the fake, but at the end of the day, when the cleaning before the closure realized the had happened, so the authorities called.
The man was eventually tried and sentenced to 9 months in prison for the crime of qualified theft. However, the detainee contested the first sentence to the second instance court because he understood that once the facts had confessed to the penalty should be suspended. However, the TSI has refused the claim, so the detainee will have to serve the sentence.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:13:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Museum | Gansu culture exposed until July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/museu-de-macau-cultura-de-gansu-exposta-ate-julho/</link><description>Until July 13, the Macao Museum will be exhibited entirely dedicated to Chinese culture. This is “Genesis and Spirit-Show of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Gansu”, which “presents the culture of Longyuan and the charm of the Silk Rota”, according to the description of the Cultural Institute
 
The exhibition “Genesis and Spirit-Show of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Gansu” was inaugurated on the weekend, patent at the Macao Museum until July 13. The show is part of the celebrations of the Cultural Institute (IC) of the “China's Cultural and Natural Heritage Day” of 2025.
According to a note issued by the IC, it is intended to “deepen the exchange and cooperation between the interior of China and Macau in the field of intangible cultural heritage”, and it shows Macau helps “actively play the role of 'a base' in promoting excellent traditional Chinese culture”.
Inaugurated on Saturday, the cultural initiative has the support of several entities, namely the IC and the Gansu Province Department of Culture and Tourism, and is also co-organized by the Intangible Cultural Heritage Protection Center of Gansu Province and the Gansu Province Music and Dance Group, with so many other supports.
Located in the Yellow River Higher Course, the province of Gansu is an important stretch of the old silk route, where several cultures converged and mixed, giving rise to a rich variety of intangible cultural heritage, with strong regional characteristics and ethnic diversity. This heritage, which has been continually accumulated, transmitted and developed, “has become a treasure for the Chinese nation,” says the IC.
Many activities
Until July 13, various activities are held around the exhibition, namely performances, demonstrations of handcrafted techniques and experimental workshops, intending to display “the rich and diverse intangible cultural heritage of the province of Gansu, so that the public can experience the Longyuan culture and the charm of the Silk Route”.
Today the demonstrations of handcrafted techniques and sales of intangible cultural heritage products at the Macau Museum, where Gansu transmitters have the essence of the techniques incorporated into the intangible cultural heritage of their province, allow the public to experience the inheritance and creativity of this intangible cultural heritage.
Regarding the show itself, it presents' qingyang fragrance sachets, linxia brick sculptures, Dunhuang's colorful sculptures, sculpted bright glasses and other works in four sections, namely 'Longyou Ballads',' turbulent rivers', 'Dunhuang Flowers' and' eternal breeze along the silk route '.
It is intended, with the exhibition “to show the unique charm of the artisanal techniques of the intangible cultural heritage of the province of Gansu”, as well as the “acts of the intangible cultural heritage of Gansu 2025”, at 7:30 pm at Senate Largo and, at the same time, in the garden of Iao Hon. Hua'er, corner accompanied by Longouqin (Chinese -headed dragon -headed harp), and Kongtong school martial arts. ”</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:25:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | Elderly displeased with dinner kills wife to stab</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/crime-idoso-desagradado-com-jantar-mata-esposa-a-facada/</link><description>Police suspect that displeasure before dinner may have led a 74 -year -old man to murder his 71 -year -old wife after about 50 years of marriage. The victim will have suffered at least 16 cleaver blows, most of them in the head and neck. The man is indicted for the crime of qualified homicide, which may imply a sentence up to 25 years in prison
 
Around 5 pm on Friday, a woman found a macabre scenario when she returned home in the Lakes Nam Van. Between the living room and the kitchen, his parents were on the floor in an authentic blood pool. The mother would eventually lose her life following multiple stab wounds and her father would be arrested on suspicion of qualified homicide.
According to the Judicial Police, dissatisfaction with what dinner would have been at the source of a contempt that ended in tragedy, with her husband, a 74 -year -old retired to murder her 71 -year -old wife with whom she had been married for about 50 years.
When the authorities arrived at the apartment, they found a cleaver and kitchen scissors in the lady's washing and signs of fighting in the kitchen, with blood everywhere.
The suspect also presented blows to the head and multiple lacerations that did not need suture and appeared to be in a stable mental state. After receiving medical treatment, he was taken to the Judicial Police for interrogation. The gun of the crime was a cleaver, discovered in the lava-laryl, with which the suspect will have, at least 16 blows to the victim, most in his head and neck.
Crime and punishment
At a press conference on Saturday, the Judicial Police indicated that it was often for the couple to have discussions for trivial reasons, but without registration of police intervention requests to resolve disputes.
The case was referred to the Public Prosecution Service and the man is suspected of the crime of qualified homicide. According to the Penal Code, "if death is produced in circumstances that reveal special censorship or wickedness of the agent, it is punished with prison sentence of 15 to 25 years."</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:11:14</pubDate></item><item><title>IIICF | Signed agreements of $ 10.1 billion US dollars</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/iiicf-assinados-acordos-de-101-mil-milhoes-de-dolares-americanos/</link><description>The 16th Forum and International Exhibition on Investment Investment and Construction (IIICF) was marked by the signing of 31 cooperation protocols in areas such as transport, construction, electricity, water resources and renewable energy
 
Thirty-one cooperation protocols, worth US $ 10.1 billion, were signed during an infrastructure forum in Macao. One third involve lusophone and mashed companies, it was announced yesterday.
The agreements established during the 16th International Forum and Exhibition on Investment and Construction of Infrastructure (IIICF), with a value of “about $ 10.1 billion US, predict cooperation in domains such as transport, construction, electricity, water resources and renewable energy in 22 countries and regions”, reads in a statement from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macau. (Ipim).
About one third of the signed projects, between Tuesday and Thursday, involve companies from Portuguese and Macao countries.
Over the three days, Ipim indicates, more than 200 contact scholarship sessions were organized, with more than 70 counted with the presence of companies from Macao and Hengqin, “which represents an increase of more than 30 percent”, compared to the 52 sessions of the previous year.
“These results further highlight the role of Macao as a sino-sirophone platform, as well as the efforts of this region in the proactive joint with national development strategies, especially the construction of the great bay,” writes Ipim.
In this sense, the note continues, representatives of Portuguese -speaking countries “recognized the effective role of Macao” as a bridge to establish contacts between companies and institutions in China and Lusophone.
“They even revealed that during the IIICF they obtained cooperation agreements with companies in the interior of China in the areas of Information Technology and Electric Engineering, underlining their satisfaction,” reads the IPIM note. In 2003, Beijing established Macao as a platform for the reinforcement of economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries and that same year created the Macao Forum.
Great Bay Numbers
The Great Bay is a Beijing project that aims to create a worldwide metropolis from the Special Chinese administrative regions of Macao and Hong Kong and nine other cities of the neighboring province of Guangdong, where they inhabit more than 80 million inhabitants.
Also launched by Beijing in 2021, the initiative of the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin encompasses an area of ​​about 106 square kilometers.
More than 3,500 infrastructure professionals from more than 70 countries and regions participated in this forum, which recorded “a new record in terms of the presence of high-level guests, specifically with almost 70 ministerial level leaders”.
During these days the infrastructure development rate “a track, a route”, led by Saudi Arabia, Indonesia and Malaysia, was also released, in which Brazil is the Portuguese-speaking country with the best score.
The initiative, announced by Chinese leader Xi Jinping in 2013, involves more than 80 countries in Beijing's International Strategic Strategic Plan to develop maritime, bus and rail connections, but also investment in energy resources.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:07:13</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS | New drugs are 16% of positive tests</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/ias-novas-drogas-sao-16-dos-testes-positivos/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action believes that last year there were 148 drug consumers, about 0.02 percent of the population, based on the number of people who are serving time for consumption or who is in rehabilitation. Still, the 148 consumers represent an increase of 25 percent compared to 2023
 
The Institute of Social Action has once again betting on a pilot project to test the use of new drugs, such as ethomyidate (known as Space Oil), metcatinone and synthetic cannabinoids. Last year, authorities collected about 1,600 samples that revealed a positivity rate of 9 percent. Among the positive tests, 16 percent concerned the new drugs referred to, Cheang Io Tat, head of the IAS department of dependence on the game and drug, in statements quoted by TDM's Macao channel.
Despite the media and stresses provoked by Space Oil, which even led to the amendment of the law, the IAS responsible states that the “traditional drugs” continue to be predominant.
Cheang Io Tat spoke on Saturday on the sidelines of the launch of a series of IAS organized activities to mark International Day against Drug Abuse and Trafficking.
During the ceremony, IAS delivered “diplomas of recognition to schools that have participated in the Sadia Life Education course over the years, as a way of thanking their contribution to the promotion of the education of healthy life. In addition, the same day was the inauguration ceremony of the scientific exposure on the fight against the Great Bay, performed for the first time this year”.
Fantasy world
The United Nations Office against Drugs and Crime published in October the World Drug Report that indicated that in 2022, there were almost 292 million consumers of narcoty around the world, about 1 in 18 people. The number advanced by the United Nations pointed to a proportion of about 5.5 percent of the world population that had consumed drugs in the year under analysis. The percentage at the global level is sprayed by the numbers advanced by the Institute of Social Action (IAS), which last year indicated that last year the number of consumers in Macau was 148, or about 0.02 percent of the population of MSAR.
In a highly punitive panorama, which pushes pathological or occasional consumers for obscurity, which authorities call “hidden consumption”, IAS numbers represent the only people who in Macao for certainty do not consume drugs: those who are serving time for use or are in rehab.
Despite the statistics that do not reflect reality, the authorities indicate that the 148 drug consumers last year represented an increase of about 25 percent compared to 2023. However, the 2024 record was 6 percent lower compared to the period before the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:01:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | List of the “hand soldier” target of CCAC due to corruption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/eleicoes-lista-do-soldado-de-mao-alvo-do-ccac-devido-a-corrupcao/</link><description>When trying to gather the missing signatures to participate in the elections, the list helps Mutual Grassroots, linked to Wong Wai Man, was the target of another operation of the authorities, with new arrests. The two operations within two days, with several arrests, will even have prevented participation in the elections
 
The potential list candidate for elections Mutual Help Grassroots, linked to Wong Wai Man, the “Mao Soldier”, will have failed the deadline for delivering missing signatures, after being the target of a commissioned operation against corruption (CCAC), justified with corruption suspicions. This was the second operation of the authorities against members of the potential list within two days, and the exclusion of the elections must be confirmed today by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal).
CCAC's operation was announced by the body led by Ieong Seong on Friday without identifying the list of the list. In a statement, about the operation that took place on Thursday, the authorities just stated that they had discovered “a case suspected of offering advantages, including pecuniary advantages, to entice the signing of the form for recognition of the application committee.”
Before a candidate for the Legislative Assembly is formed, members need to constitute the so -called application committee and collect between 300 and 500 support signatures. At the time of CCAC's operation, Mutual aid Grassroots was in a race against time to get 77 more valid signatures after some of the signatures originally presented were considered invalid.
"CCAC has found that there are at least five individuals involved in the case. These individuals will have enlisted others to sign filing forms with pecuniary advantages or other advantages or will have offered proposition forms already signed," was reported by the authorities. "One of the suspects confessed to the practice of their suspicious criminal act while another suspect confessed to falsifying voter signatures, signing forms of proposition," he was added.
Almost confirmed deletion
To the All About Macau, Sou Weng, a member of the Iron and Steel Association that serves as the basis for the potential list Mutual Grassroots, acknowledged that the latest operation of CCAC resulted in the detention of the person in charge of collecting missing signatures.
The detainee, who was not identified, was in a meeting with a friend when he was taken by the authorities. This person was in charge of collecting the signatures, after Wong Wai Man was arrested the day before by the Judicial Police, allegedly for the crime of exploitation of Mah-Jong, in another judicial case.
Given the arrests of the association's latest members, I am Weng admitted as soon as the signatures are most likely to deliver, which excludes from the elections to the list. To All About Macau, the association member refused the existence of any corruption case involving the Association of Iron and Steel shipowners.
Cash prison
On Saturday, the Public Prosecution Service (MP) issued a statement informing that members of the association involved are appointed by the crime of electoral corruption, punished with a sentence of one to five years in prison. According to the MP, if they are considered guilty, the targets have to serve effective prison sentence, since the electoral law does not allow suspension, without replacement for other punishment measures, as a fine. The targets are also indicted for the crime of falsifying a document that can be punished with a fine or prison penalty up to 3 years, which may be suspended.
The MP also informed that the criminal instruction judge "applied to the two main measures to coercive security, periodic presentation, prohibition of absence and prohibition of contacts and the other three defendants of security coercion.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:52:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Entrepreneurship | Event for local companies wants to capture “angel investors”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/empreendedorismo-evento-para-empresas-locais-quer-captar-investidores-anjo/</link><description>Macau today hosts an event designed to capture the so -called “angel investors” for local entrepreneurship projects. Macao Angel Investor Network takes place at “The Macao Young Entrepreneur Incubation Center” and aims to support emerging business projects or simply startups that are taking the first steps
 
It's called “Macau Angel Investor Network”, anything like “Angel Investor Network in Macao” and aims to bring residents closer who want to be successful entrepreneurs and create their own business in an economy that wants to diverse. The event is scheduled for today at Hengqin Development Center, at 517 Avenida da Praia Grande, Nam Tung commercial building, between 11h and 12h30, and has several personalities linked to the local economy, but not only. They are Raphael Chan, Deputy Director of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Paulo Andrez, Emeritus President of the “European Business Angel Network” and also figures such as Emanuel Soares, Legal Consultant, U Man Fai, angel investor for the Great Bay and Founder/founder of “Esenia Fund” and even Ung Choi Kun, former deputy to the Legislative Assembly and president of Kun Cheong Holding Ltd and also an “angel investor”. The event is developed by the Association for Entrepreneurship and Innovation for Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries, which is linked Marco Duarte Rizzolio.
To HM, this explained the main objectives that are behind this initiative. "We want to connect an angel investors to startups and small and medium enterprises (SMEs), fostering the entrepreneurial ecosystem and promoting the economic diversification of Macao." In turn, Alvin Fong, also linked to the organization of this event and president of Direch International, argued that it is intended to “create a platform that brings together knowledge about angel investments, helping in the diversification of Macao's economy”.
According to Rizzolio, "Investors Angel, who invest capital in emerging companies, are fundamental to support startups in early stages where financing possibilities are more scarce in the traditional financial sector."
“In addition,” he said, the contact network that now runs on Praia Grande Avenue “seeks to bring investors closer to Portuguese -speaking and China countries, creating mutual access to the best projects developed in these regions and reinforcing Macao as a strategic link between the East and the West”.
For Alvin Fong, this is the "opportune moment" for the holding of such an event, given that "the world is going through many changes and new opportunities are emerging."
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, in Macao have already occurred in previous events in an attempt to capture angel investments, "but this is the first time a" Business Angels "network has been created in Macao with Chinese investors and Portuguese -speaking countries."
"The conditions to hold this event now arise from various factors, such as the accelerated growth of innovation and technology, the greater digitization and the use of software in business, the need to diversify the local economy, the growing focus on the great bay as a pole of innovation," he said.
At issue, there are also factors such as “the joint effort of public and private entities in creating an environment favorable to entrepreneurship”, something that has been greatly enhanced by the pandemic years, defended, having brought Macao and the authorities “a new understanding of the importance of supporting local and regional businesses, making this moment particularly strategic”.
Who is who
For today's session were invited “Successful Entrepreneurs and Entrepreneurs, some of whom are leaders in their areas”, and their “experience and intelligence add a lot to this event,” said Alvin Fong.
Already Marco Duarte Rizzolio, stressed that will be present “people interested in technology and innovation, including some angel investors, representatives of risk capital funds, renowned entrepreneurs and specialists in innovation and business development”.
Today's session is an “opportunity to obtain valuable knowledge and expand the network of contacts”, and Marco Duarte Rizzolio highlights personalities such as Paulo Andrez, “recognized international expert in entrepreneurship, innovation and angel investment”, or Ung Choi Kun, “prominent figure in Macao in real estate and education sectors, as well as an angel investor in several companies”.
Asked about the main areas in which this initiative is focused on, Rizzolio adds that the event is focused on “startups and SMEs that act on sectors such as technology, intelligent tourism, green economy, health, digital education, logistics or finance”, because they are “sectors with high growth potential and that are aligned in local needs”, namely in the “1+” economic diversification strategy or “1+4” strategy global trends ”.
"We want to identify innovative companies that can thrive not only in Macao, but also in the big bay and in international markets," added this official who is also linked to the organization of the startups and entrepreneurship contest, the "929 Challenge".
Right moment
For Alvin Fong, Macao currently presents potentialities for the connection of business projects to the cities of the Great Bay, all located in Guangdong Province.
"Macau has a lot of freedom and flexibility to experience new ideas. In addition, we have received many tourists from around the world. Being one of GBA's eleven cities, Macau is, in fact, an excellent platform," he said. In turn, Marco Duarte Rizzolio speaks of “unique characteristics” of the territory, “like their position as a bridge between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, a stable regulatory environment and tax and financial incentives that can attract investors and startups”.
There is also “the increase in the focus on the diversification of the economy beyond the game sector”, with “a fertile ground for innovation and new business”.
"In a global scenario of low interest rates, capital markets with some geopolitical friction, investment in technology has presented multiple incomparable from other assets. In this context, the creation of more financial incentives and the strengthening of startup support programs are crucial steps," said the event co-creator.
Great competition
Despite the potential, the challenges persist, given that “Macao does not have many advantages beyond the game sector,” there is “intense competition in the big bay,” warned Alvin Fong.
For Marco Duarte Rizzolio "Challenges are significant," because "the transition from an economy so dependent on the game sector to a more diverse model takes time and requires coordinated efforts."
It is also necessary to take into account the opportunities that arise with the integration of MSar on Hengqin Island, Rizzoolio said, which recalls, however, “the challenges related to competitiveness and regulatory adaptation”.
"In addition, housing and commercial remodeling requires balance between economic growth and the preservation of local social fabric. It is essential to create policies that encourage entrepreneurship and investment, minimizing the negative impacts of these transformations," he said.
Asked whether the authorities have been enough to capture angel investors, both argue that there is more work to do. "This is a good start, but more can be done in the future," said Alvin Fong.
Already Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said that "the Government of MSAR has made important efforts", as well as mentioning "several times the need to create a" Business Angels "network."
“Macau has supported many initiatives that aim to stimulate investment. It is true that the creation of more financial incentives and the strengthening of startup support programs are crucial steps. It is also necessary to promote Macau more actively as an attractive destination for investors, highlighting its competitive advantages on the international scene. This event is an example of good collaboration between the public and private sector to stimulate ecosystem”, defended Rizzolio.
Also noteworthy is that today's close connection with 369, an entity that aims to become “an international hub of science and technology in Macau, giving new generations a greater stage of exploration” of opportunities, ”said Alvin Fong, president of this entity. Marco Duarte Rizzolio stressed that we are facing “an incubator of the Macao ecosystem that has organized several events”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:50:29</pubDate></item><item><title>India/Accident | Pilot declared “Mayday” seconds after take off</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/india-acidente-piloto-declarou-mayday-segundos-apos-descolagem/</link><description>The Ministry of Civil Aviation of India revealed Saturday that the AI171 Air India Flight pilot, which fell with 242 people on board, declared an emergency Mayday seconds after offspring, and that the aircraft fell almost exactly a minute later.
In the first official statement of the Indian government since the accident on Thursday, the Secretary of Civil Aviation, Samir Kumar Sinha, made a minute report of the final moments of the flight. "The plane took off at 13:39, local time, and in seconds, after reaching an altitude of about 650 feet (almost 200 meters), began to sink, that is, to lose altitude," said Sinha.
The official added: "At 1:39 PM, the pilot reported the Air Traffic Control (ATC) in Ahmedabad that it was a Mayday." According to the secretary, when the ATC tried to contact the plane again after the emergency call, it did not get any response.
"Exactly a minute later, at 1:40 pm, the plane dumped in Meghaninar, a zone about two kilometers from the airport," he added. The ministry also confirmed that 242 people were on board the plane: 230 passengers, two pilots and 10 crew.
About the previous state of the device, the secretary said that before the accident, the plane had made the Paris-Delhi-Ahmedabad route without incident. The number of dead in the AI171 flight tragedy of Air India rose to at least 279.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:34:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Education | Lam regrets Vong Fong Va's death</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/educacao-o-lam-lamenta-falecimento-de-vong-fong-va/</link><description>Tomorrow is the funeral of Professor Vong Fong VA, who died on June 4 with 94 years. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, issued a statement on Saturday to regret the death of the man who devoted almost half a century to education, highlighting the time of the time as deputy director of Hou Kong Secondary School.
Lam stressed Vong Fong Va's dedication to teaching and patriotism, a work that earned him the silver lotus medal of honor awarded by the Government of MSAR.
Vong Fong VA has occupied prominent places in various local associations. He was vice-president of the General Association of Chong Wa de Macau Students, vowel of the Macao's Return of the Return of Macau, President of the Macao Education Association, President of the Friendship and Coordination Association of former National Popular Assembly and former Member of the Chinese Political Conference of Macao, “uniting the forces of associations in the love of Macao and Macao, promoting the Macao,”, promoting prosperity and macao stability ”,” He pointed out Lam.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:00:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice | TSI maintains a sentence of 9 months in prison for the theft necklace</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/justica-tsi-mantem-pena-de-9-meses-de-prisao-por-furto-de-colar/</link><description>The second instance (TSI) court refused to suspend a 9 -month prison sentence, applied to a tourist who stole a jewelry store necklace in Macao. The decision was announced last Friday, through a statement from the office of the president of the last court.
The case happened on March 11, 2023, when the criminal brought a fake necklace to Macao, in order to go to a store and exchange it for an original, getting the most valuable. In the store he frequented, after entering Macao, the necklace from which he was intended to appropriate was evaluated 37,300 patacas.
With the excuse that he intended to buy the necklace, the man managed to change it for the other who brought inside the coat. With the exchange made, eventually left the store without making the purchase. Initially, the store workers did not detect the original necklace change for the fake, but at the end of the day, when the cleaning before the closure realized the had happened, so the authorities called.
The man was eventually tried and sentenced to 9 months in prison for the crime of qualified theft. However, the detainee contested the first sentence to the second instance court because he understood that once the facts had confessed to the penalty should be suspended. However, the TSI has refused the claim, so the detainee will have to serve the sentence.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:13:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Museum | Gansu culture exposed until July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/museu-de-macau-cultura-de-gansu-exposta-ate-julho/</link><description>Until July 13, the Macao Museum will be exhibited entirely dedicated to Chinese culture. This is “Genesis and Spirit-Show of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Gansu”, which “presents the culture of Longyuan and the charm of the Silk Rota”, according to the description of the Cultural Institute
 
The exhibition “Genesis and Spirit-Show of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Gansu” was inaugurated on the weekend, patent at the Macao Museum until July 13. The show is part of the celebrations of the Cultural Institute (IC) of the “China's Cultural and Natural Heritage Day” of 2025.
According to a note issued by the IC, it is intended to “deepen the exchange and cooperation between the interior of China and Macau in the field of intangible cultural heritage”, and it shows Macau helps “actively play the role of 'a base' in promoting excellent traditional Chinese culture”.
Inaugurated on Saturday, the cultural initiative has the support of several entities, namely the IC and the Gansu Province Department of Culture and Tourism, and is also co-organized by the Intangible Cultural Heritage Protection Center of Gansu Province and the Gansu Province Music and Dance Group, with so many other supports.
Located in the Yellow River Higher Course, the province of Gansu is an important stretch of the old silk route, where several cultures converged and mixed, giving rise to a rich variety of intangible cultural heritage, with strong regional characteristics and ethnic diversity. This heritage, which has been continually accumulated, transmitted and developed, “has become a treasure for the Chinese nation,” says the IC.
Many activities
Until July 13, various activities are held around the exhibition, namely performances, demonstrations of handcrafted techniques and experimental workshops, intending to display “the rich and diverse intangible cultural heritage of the province of Gansu, so that the public can experience the Longyuan culture and the charm of the Silk Route”.
Today the demonstrations of handcrafted techniques and sales of intangible cultural heritage products at the Macau Museum, where Gansu transmitters have the essence of the techniques incorporated into the intangible cultural heritage of their province, allow the public to experience the inheritance and creativity of this intangible cultural heritage.
Regarding the show itself, it presents' qingyang fragrance sachets, linxia brick sculptures, Dunhuang's colorful sculptures, sculpted bright glasses and other works in four sections, namely 'Longyou Ballads',' turbulent rivers', 'Dunhuang Flowers' and' eternal breeze along the silk route '.
It is intended, with the exhibition “to show the unique charm of the artisanal techniques of the intangible cultural heritage of the province of Gansu”, as well as the “acts of the intangible cultural heritage of Gansu 2025”, at 7:30 pm at Senate Largo and, at the same time, in the garden of Iao Hon. Hua'er, corner accompanied by Longouqin (Chinese -headed dragon -headed harp), and Kongtong school martial arts. ”</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:25:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Comedy | Jimmy O. Yang acts for the first instead Macau in Broadway</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/comedia-jimmy-o-yang-actua-pela-primeira-em-vez-macau-no-broadway/</link><description>July 4th, 5th and 6th deserve to be reserved on the Calendar of Macao Stand-Up Comedy fans. Jimmy O. Yang, Hong Kong comedian who enters series such as “Silicon Valley” and “Space Force”, will act on Broadway Theater. Tickets are on sale today and cost between 480 and 880 patacas
 
“I have something big to announce: Macao, or Mun, I'm going to be from July 4th to 6th to three shows. It will be my first shows in Macau. The tickets will be for sale on June 13th. Until now, Macao!” This is how comedian Jimmy O. Yang announced on social networks that he will bring his stand-up comedy show for the first time to Macao. The shows are marked for the Broadway Theater. On July 4th and 5th, start at 8:30 pm and on July 6, Sunday, the session starts at 15h.
Tickets are on sale today and cost between 480 and 880 patacas.
Prior to the shows in Macau, Jimmy O. Yang will act in his homeland, Hong Kong, with five shows already sold out at the neighboring city's coliseum, between today and Sunday, with two matins in the middle.
At the age of 38, the comedian already has a long career, not only in stage comedy, but especially in a television series and cinema. The popularity of HBO comedy “Silicon Valley” introduced Jimmy O. Yang to the World, playing a member of a computer programming team that tries to luck in the billionaires of mobile applications.
Another recurring role in Jimmy O. Yang's curriculum, was on the Netflix series "Space Force", where he contracted with actors such as Steve Carell, John Malkovich, Ben Schwartz, Diana Silvers, Lisa Kudrow and her father Richard Ouyang.
Hong Kong comedian has still entered series such as "The Simpsons", "It's Always Sunny in Philadelphia", "American Dad", among others.
In seventh art
In about 12 years, Jimmy O. Yang has entered more than two dozen movies. In his filmography there are some unavoidable feature films such as "Crazy Rich Asians", "Love Hard", "Like a Boss" and animations such as "The Monkey King", where he gives voice to the protagonist, "Minions: The Rise of Gru", "The Lego Movie 2" and "Wish Dragon".
In the middle of a career on stage and the big and small screens, Jimmy O. Yang still had time to write a book: "How to American: An Immigrant's Guide to Disappointing Your Parents." Not only does the work describe your life a little, but someone who moves from Hong Kong to California, where he already had a family, but also unravels the themes he usually addresses in stand-up comedy shows.
In the introduction of the book, the comedian gives some clues about his journey and the impact he had on his family. “I refused a job in the financial area to dedicate myself to my stand-up comedy career. My father thought I had crazy. But I realized that it was more worth disillusioned for my parents for a few years, than to disappoint my life. I had to dedicate them so I could do it. That was the only way I got to be able to eat my chinese cake and the chinese cake American at the same time. ”
Jimmy O. Yang was born in Hong Kong in the summer of 1987, after his parents moved from Shanghai to the neighboring region. In 2000, when the comedian was a 13-year-old, the family moved to Los Angeles, where he lived an aunt and a young man from the young man.
In 2009, he graduated from Economics at the University of California, San Diego. At the ceremony of delivery of diplomas in the year in which he completed the degree, the main speaker was Mike Judge, the author of the series "Silicon Valley".</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tehran | New explosions heard yesterday in the Iranian capital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/teerao-novas-explosoes-ouvidas-ontem-na-capital-iraniana/</link><description>New explosions were heard yesterday in Tehraão, the capital of Iran, on the third day of an Israeli attack on a large scale against the Islamic Republic, an AFP journalist has advanced at the site.
Iranian media, Khabar Online and Ham Mihan reported that air defense systems in the west and northwest of Tehran had been activated “to counteract new attacks”, while the Iranian Diary Shargh broadcast a video that showed smoke columns in the east of the capital. The Israelite army guaranteed to have reached more than 80 targets yesterday in Tehran, in night air attacks involving "about fifty fighters."
"Throughout the night, the Air Force fighters flew over Tehran and reached infrastructures and targets of the Iranian nuclear project," according to a military statement, quoted by AFP.
Israel has reached "more than 80 targets, including the Ministry of Defense [and what Israel describes as] the headquarters of the Iranian [military] nuclear project [the organization of defensive research and innovation, or separate, according to the acronym Persian], as well as targets where the regime hid nuclear files."
In turn, the Iranian government announced yesterday that the meter and mosques of Tehran will remain open 24 hours a day for the population to take refuge from Israelite attacks, which resumed the bombing against the Iranian capital at noon.
Iranian government spokesman Fatemeh Mohajerani has announced that “mosques, schools and the subway will be available to the public as shelters”, when national media began reporting new Israeli bombing in the neighborhoods of Saadat Abad and Punak, northwest of the capital. The Iranian Portal Khabar Online reported that the Niroo Research Institute in the northwest region of Teerão was attacked by Israel.
According to the Young JournaLists Club agency, near the Iranian government, the city's air defenses have already been activated to repel the attack.
Between dead and injured
The Iranian government spokesman appealed to calm. "Service centers, such as banks and medical centers, are at the service of the public and other centers also have the possibility of some employees to work at a distance," he explained to the media, according to the Iranian official news agency Irna.
The war between Israel and Iran, triggered at dawn on June 13 for Israelite bombings that aimed at Iranian military and nuclear facilities, has already caused more than 100 dead and 800 injured in Iran, including military leaders, scientists and civilians.
The Israelite attacks, made by 200 aircraft against a hundred targets, reached mainly Tehran (North) and the uranium enrichment centers of Fordow and Natanz (Center), Mehrabad National Airport and various military bases.
Iran retaliated with hundreds of missiles directed to the cities of Telavive and Jerusalem, who made at least 13 dead and 150 injured.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:30:31</pubDate></item><item><title>G Dragon | 12 tickets in ticket purchase</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/g-dragon-12-burlas-em-compra-de-bilhetes/</link><description>A total of 12 people were circumvented in 87,000 patacas when they sought to buy tickets on the black market for the concerts of singer G Dragon, which took place between June 6 and 8. The case was revealed yesterday by the Judicial Police (PJ), and quoted by the newspaper or Mun.
Although the identity of the show artist was not revealed, the South Korean singer was the only one with concerts in Macau in those three consecutive days. According to Modus Operandi, the burns promised to sell tickets to the different days and after receiving the payment were unmistakable.
In 10 cases, the burles were made over the internet and in two other occurrences the scores were in person, as the alleged sellers did not attend the time of handing over the tickets. Ticket losses ranged from 1,000 patacas and 25,000 patacas for a total of 87,000 patacas.
Online Sales | Burlas generate losses of 25 thousand patacas
The Judicial Police (PJ) announced the 19th online sales registration that resulted in losses of 25,000 patacas. According to police information, quoted by the newspaper or Mun, the slips were made through the online sale of shellfish, buffets in local restaurants, amusement parks or local hotel packages.
PJ is investigating all cases, which have affected a total of 19 victims, 11 women and 8 men. Regarding the profile of the victims, it was also announced that 16 are middle age and three are young.
The victims were deceived after accessing online advertising and paid by bank transfer between June 7 and 11. However, although they made payments never received the goods they bought. In individual terms, the burles ranged from the 320 patacas and 3,800 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:12:37</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Lu Dongbin, the Immortal, waited sitting in a Handan inn, the city of Hebei at Hanshan's term, the reddish purple mountain. He had a porcelain pillow and expected, he would know later, to demonstrate the possibilities offered in the finitude of the flow of the days.
Unknowingly, he came to a luminous encounter, Lu Sheng was immersed in obscure thoughts raised by repeated setting of fortune, but would come with the accuracy of the road that would place him face to face with the immortal patient. Having a brief exchange of words, Lu Sheng realized that the lovely man, who was in front of him with the robes of a daoist priest, was available to listen to his complaints. And the disappointed traveler told how he had narrowly disapproved of the Jinshi exam that would allow him a quiet life in the service of the Empire and now even admitting to imagine a future.
After listening to him, Lu Dongbin reached out for the pillow he brought and told him to rest a moment while a comforting yellow sorghum porridge cooked to the heat. Soon the traveler fell asleep. And he dreamed the most comforting dream: that passed the imperial exam, knew the most beautiful and intelligent wife, who would give him many children, with whom he would live many years in a well paid and quiet imperial post. Suddenly but awakened from the dream that seemed to have lasted a lifetime. Asking the Master of theist how long he had slept, he replied that the sorghum Pope had not yet bought it yet.
The ancient account in which an immortal allows a mortal to live, in fact, another life for a short time to show him the illusory and transitory character of ambitions for himself to deduce another path, would be resumed in 1601 by playwright Tang Xianzu (1550-1616). But it was well known as one of Handan's many proverbs, reduced to four short characters: 黄粱美梦 Huangliang Meimeng, "a good dream, yellow sorghum."
Huang Ding (c.1650-1730), a changzhou painter, made a series of paintings "in the way of" augustes painters of the past such as Wang Meng, Dong Yuan or even Nizan's unmistakable style landscapes (vertical roller, ink on paper, 92.7 x 35.1 cm, at the Minneapolis Art Institute) as wanting to embark on his push Long history of painting made for a wide time.
At that time a small album was circulated with notes of the influential Dong Qichang, but which is attributed to Wang Shimin (1592-1680) entitled Xiaozhong Xianda, "Revelation of Large Things In Small", which contained, in a small format, recreations of works by great masters. Can you see something too big can be done in a small shape, but a lifetime in a short time? Because what travels is the Spirit, Lu Dongbin made him in less than an hour, the time it takes to cook the yellow sorghum.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Lu Dongbin, the Immortal, waited sitting in a Handan inn, the city of Hebei at Hanshan's term, the reddish purple mountain. He had a porcelain pillow and expected, he would know later, to demonstrate the possibilities offered in the finitude of the flow of the days.
Unknowingly, he came to a luminous encounter, Lu Sheng was immersed in obscure thoughts raised by repeated setting of fortune, but would come with the accuracy of the road that would place him face to face with the immortal patient. Having a brief exchange of words, Lu Sheng realized that the lovely man, who was in front of him with the robes of a daoist priest, was available to listen to his complaints. And the disappointed traveler told how he had narrowly disapproved of the Jinshi exam that would allow him a quiet life in the service of the Empire and now even admitting to imagine a future.
After listening to him, Lu Dongbin reached out for the pillow he brought and told him to rest a moment while a comforting yellow sorghum porridge cooked to the heat. Soon the traveler fell asleep. And he dreamed the most comforting dream: that passed the imperial exam, knew the most beautiful and intelligent wife, who would give him many children, with whom he would live many years in a well paid and quiet imperial post. Suddenly but awakened from the dream that seemed to have lasted a lifetime. Asking the Master of theist how long he had slept, he replied that the sorghum Pope had not yet bought it yet.
The ancient account in which an immortal allows a mortal to live, in fact, another life for a short time to show him the illusory and transitory character of ambitions for himself to deduce another path, would be resumed in 1601 by playwright Tang Xianzu (1550-1616). But it was well known as one of Handan's many proverbs, reduced to four short characters: 黄粱美梦 Huangliang Meimeng, "a good dream, yellow sorghum."
Huang Ding (c.1650-1730), a changzhou painter, made a series of paintings "in the way of" augustes painters of the past such as Wang Meng, Dong Yuan or even Nizan's unmistakable style landscapes (vertical roller, ink on paper, 92.7 x 35.1 cm, at the Minneapolis Art Institute) as wanting to embark on his push Long history of painting made for a wide time.
At that time a small album was circulated with notes of the influential Dong Qichang, but which is attributed to Wang Shimin (1592-1680) entitled Xiaozhong Xianda, "Revelation of Large Things In Small", which contained, in a small format, recreations of works by great masters. Can you see something too big can be done in a small shape, but a lifetime in a short time? Because what travels is the Spirit, Lu Dongbin made him in less than an hour, the time it takes to cook the yellow sorghum.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 20, 2025
Cultural Introduction and Comparison
What is the implicit popular philosophy in Wu Cheng´en's West Pilgrimage (吴承恩) 1500 - 1582? This was written during the Ming Dynasty and published in 1570, about the time when the Lusíadas de Luís Vaz de Camões, the Camonian epic, would be edited in 1572.
In the western pilgrimage, we are looking for an imaginary recreation of a group of pilgrims, headed by the monk of the Tang Xuanzang Dynasty (唐玄奘 Xuánzàng), to conquer a new spiritual world, that of Buddhist religion, to which the Chinese should adhere to a better ethical-moral conduct for a much-diverted population of good teachings and conduct.
Those who lead the initiative to free the Chinese from suffering is, of course, the deity of compassion, Guanyin (观音 Guānyīn), always attentive to all distressed souls, ready to launch their help.
Already in the case of Os Lusíadas, composed by Luís Vaz de Camões (1524/5-1580), a journey is also narrated, but it is real, inseparable from spiritual and religious aspects, because made in the name of the universality of the Christian faith, but being inseparable from the concrete journey, which implies the very human and Renaissance conquest of a better world for people, in which the Portuguese can not the Portuguese Just survive, but command and imperate, because they are worthy of an old history and very valuable warriors. Therefore, the heroism of the discoveries, living in the Christian faith, but accompanied and protected by the Renaissance Belling that recovers the classic spirit and deities, such as the protective Venus, a loving deity that sails for the Portuguese, and the aggressive and jealous Bacchus, the god of wine who wants to lose them.
The west pilgrimage by the Chinese is performed in the name of collective liberation and salvation, through contact with Buddhist sutras; The Portuguese “pilgrimage” to the east is also in the name of a collectivity, saves souls and extends to the whole land, given the proselytist vocation of Christianity and globalizing merchants, as well as the navigators, Camões his poetic herald desires the spread of faith by a great empire built by Portuguese heroes, as read in the first resort of singing first:
The weapons and the barons marked
That of the western Lusitana beach,
By seas never of before navigadas
Also passed beyond TAPROBAN,
In hardworking dangers and wars,
More than promised human strength,
And among remote people built
New kingdom, which so sublimated;
That would be translated into Chinese by Zhang Weimi 张维民 in 19981 as follows:
威武的船队 ， 强悍的勇士 ，
驶离卢济塔尼亚西部海岸 ，
越过自古茫无人迹的海崖 ，
甚至跨越塔普罗瓦那海角 ，
经历千难万险、无穷战争 ，
超出人力所能承受的极限 ，
在那荒僻遥远的异域之帮 ，
将灿烂辉煌的新帝国拓建。
张维民 (译) 《卢济塔尼亚人之歌 • 第一章 ， 一》
Both pilgrimages are true poetic adventure novels, the Lusíadas in poetry, the west pilgrimage in poetic prose and poetry. In the latter, Bodhisattva Guanyin will subdue 4 monsters who will be the companions of the monk Xuanzang. Bodhisattva takes an embroidered accent and a nine -lap ring to deliver to the monk. The latter, if effectively fulfilling his 14 -year mission, escapes the wheel of reincarnation (Jenner, 1994: 60), and his disciples, disobedient divine forces falling into the human world, will be able to return to heaven, where they will again occupy divine positions.
Guanyin also delivers a band, which causes terrible headaches to the disobedient King Monkey (Jenner, 1994: 60).
The monsters and indomitable spirits are presented.
First Sun Wukong (孙悟空 Sūn Wǔkōng), by King's disobedient monkey transits the obedient guardian of the Buddhist religion. Guanyin will free this indomitable spirit, prisoner in the mountain of the five elements (五行山 wǔxing shān), as punishment for the disobediences they have no account.
Then a heavenly marshal who will pass the pig. He is Marshal Tian Peng (天篷 Tiān Péng) of the Milky Way, tried to seduce the Divinity of the Moon, was punished by the emperor of Jade with axes and condemned to exile on earth. Bodhisattva baptized him with the nickname of Zhu Bajie (猪八戒 Zhū Bājiè), which means "Pig of the eight abstinences," and gave him the name Buddhist of Zhu Wuneng (猪悟能 Zhū Wǔnéng), ie "awakening pork for power" (1994: 63).
There will be an ogre that will be dominated and transformed into a sand monk. He was punished for being a distracted heavenly general. He paid the distraction with 800 whipping, having been exiled to Earth, where he devours travelers hidden in the waters of the floating river. Guanyin frees him, baptizing him with the nickname "sand" (沙 shā), and the Buddhist name of Wujing (牾净 Wǔjìng), which means "awake to purity."
Follows is the son of the West Sea Dragon King who will be metamorphosed on a white horse. He was denounced by his own father for burning the bright pearls of the palace. Jade emperor punished him, suspending him in the air. He gave him 300 whips, letting him wait for death. Prince Dragon is freed to turn into the white horse of the Xuánzàng monk, or as he is known in Chinese, on the white-dragon horse, (白龙马 白龙马 Lóng Mǎ).
In the term of the pilgrimage, Zhu Wuneng spiritualized, ascends to heaven, being rewarded with the heavenly position of cleans. But there are more honors to the group of victorious pilgrims who led the Sutras to China: the sand monk will receive the title of Golden Holy (Arhat), the monkey will be named Buddha of the victorious fight and the Sanzang monk will receive the title of Buddha do Merit (Buddha Candana-Punya.) As well as the white horse will rise the heavenly dragon.
Proverbial popular philosophy
Among the pilgrims are, as is well known, the monkey and the pig that escorts the great monk and Buddhist translator Xuanzang [唐玄奘 Xuánzàng (c. 602-664) or Sanzang (三藏 Sānzàng), the monk of the three Buddhist treasures (Buddha himself, teachings or Dharma, the monastic order or Sangha), the monastic order), Mandated by Emperor Emperor Táng Tàzōng (唐太宗, R. 626-649) to go to the Holy Scriptures from India. These will be delivered by the historic Buddha that resides in the Pico do Vulture, because "there are many greedy and evil creatures in the east, which are bought to cause suffering to others, killing and fighting nonstop." (Jenner, 1994: 58). Therefore, Buddha wanted to distribute the Scriptures through the Chinese world.
In popular and proverbial philosophy, which today rushes from mouth to mouth, it is drawn to the existential duel, between two of the five pilgrims, very similar to that of the work Don Quixote, by Miguel de Cervantes (1547-1616), composed between 1605 and 1615, in which the author puts in dialogue two opposing and complementary characters, Don Quixote and Sancho Pança: Romantic, dreamer and even utopian, almost only skin and bone, as it is like an incarnate spirit; The second, materialist, realistic, pragmatic, a very strong and plump "feet".
Mutatis Mutandis Zhu Bajie, the eight abstinence pig, and Sun Wugong, the west -west -awake to emptiness, have many of the opposite and complementary characteristics we find in D. Quixote and Sancho Pança. To confirm it, be aware of some of the said proverbials associated with King Monkey:
1) The seventy -two transformations of the monkey king (七十二变 qī shí èr bàn)
2) endless mutations (千变万化 qiān biàn wàn huà)
3) great confusion in the heavenly palace (大闹天宮 大闹天宮 nao tiān gōng)
4) Infinite Magic Powers (神通广大 Shéntōng-Guǎnggdà)
5) Appears and mysteriously disappears (神出鬼没 Shénchū-guǐmò)
He has an infinite spiritual ability, which allows him to accompany the universal movement and be in permanent transformation. It has numerous magical powers, learned from the best of Taoist masters, which enables him to successfully interfere in both the heavenly and earthly order, which is why he will be punished and only subjugated by the Buddha himself, which, tame it reveals it belongs to a superior spiritual and religious order.
After a five hundred -year -old punishment, inflicted by the Buddhism patriarch, will be able to join the group of pilgrims that will successfully introduce sutras and Buddhist teachings in China. Sun Wugong reveals to be a complex and multifaceted character, retaining and enhancing the best and worst of human nature in his portentous intelligence, challenging and disobedient. It has a lot of difficulty in dealing with Zhu Bajie, for the stupidity and lust of the partner, always ready to sloth out and surrender to exclusively carnal pleasures.
Zhu Bajie embodies some of the typical defects of human nature that are well revealed in the popular proverbial philosophy, as can be seen by some of the said mentioned:
1) Zhū Bájiè fails and never assumes his responsibilities (豬八戒上陈 Zhū Bájiè Shàng Chén)
2) Zhu Bajie is adorned with flowers (豬八戒戴花 Zhū Bájiè dài huā).
3) Zhū Bájiè is the mirror (CZHū Bájiè Kàn Jìngzi)
4) Zhū Bájiè departed by plane (豬八戒坐飞机 Zhū Bájiè Zuò Fēijī).
In the first proverb, there is the difficulty of the pig to assume guilt whenever it makes mistakes, and how to make mistakes is human, there are no accounts at the times when shaking responsibilities; Already in the second is denounced a very characteristic defect between the people, the vanity, that is, the constant need for ornaments, and not only from the physical point of view, because here not only counts the clothing but also the titles, positions and honors, in a total inability to strictly self -evaluate. In the third said, the physical and moral fealade, which attracts complaints from others, for the lack of composure and, finally, this expression is used when someone goes to the best, but in a worse way, that is, without dignity.
Finally, here are some more generally meaningful proverbs, taken from the west pilgrimage, who draw attention to the general evils of the world through the adventures of pilgrims, since, except Sun Wugong, others are very easily fooled by all kinds of monsters, demons, seductive spirits, etc., having great difficulty unraveling hypocritical behaviors in which they stumble through Journey, where they find “many guys to which they cannot see their hearts” or, in other words, abundant hypocrisy, as said (虚情假意 xū qing jiǎ yì).
Therefore, they are constantly involved in sarilhos or situations that “have no feet or head”, which is literally translated into Chinese by “unequal sizes” (七长八短 qīm tea bā duān). Now in a misleading world, pilgrims are those who with good intentions go with the greatest goal of saving China, so the group finds itself in the situation of “big ship, great storm”, or as it is said in Chinese, “great tree that attracts the wind” (树大招风 shūo fēng) in a world where when virtue grows a few centimeters, so wickedness increases several meters (， ， ， ， ， ， ， Give gāo yī chǐ, mó gāo yī zhàng).
Despite all the warnings, coming from popular wisdom and Romanesque adventures, the west pilgrimage and the Lusíadas end with the success of its protagonists, as the Portuguese expand around the world, Buddhism is introduced in China and all the characters in the poetic soap opera give rise to a proverbial source pedagogical.
Bibliographic references
ALVES, Ana Cristina.  2022. Chinese culture, a western perspective. Coord. Carmen Amando Mendes. Coimbra: Almedina and Macau Scientific and Cultural Center.
蔡志忠 (编绘) 2014 《西游记》北京: 现代出版社.
CAMões, Luís de. 1971. The Lusíadas. Lisbon: National Press of Lisbon.
CAMões, Luís de. 1998. 《卢济塔尼亚人之歌》. Beijing: East Foundation and Federation of China Artistic and Literary Associations.
JENNER, W.J.F. 1994. Wu Cheng'en. Journey to the West. «西遊記». Hong Kong: The Commercial Press.
吴承恩 2015 《西游记》. 全三册. 长沙: 岳麓书社.
“Proverbial stories related to Zhu Bajie”: 《描写猪八戒的成语》
http://wenwen.soso.com/z/q314030363.htm
“Proverbial stories related to Sun Wukong”: 《关于孙悟空的成语》 http://zhidao.baidu.com/question/95335747.html
This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors ”https://www.ccccm.gov.pt
Beijing: East Foundation and Federation of China Artistic and Literary Associations.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Lu Dongbin, the Immortal, waited sitting in a Handan inn, the city of Hebei at Hanshan's term, the reddish purple mountain. He had a porcelain pillow and expected, he would know later, to demonstrate the possibilities offered in the finitude of the flow of the days.
Unknowingly, he came to a luminous encounter, Lu Sheng was immersed in obscure thoughts raised by repeated setting of fortune, but would come with the accuracy of the road that would place him face to face with the immortal patient. Having a brief exchange of words, Lu Sheng realized that the lovely man, who was in front of him with the robes of a daoist priest, was available to listen to his complaints. And the disappointed traveler told how he had narrowly disapproved of the Jinshi exam that would allow him a quiet life in the service of the Empire and now even admitting to imagine a future.
After listening to him, Lu Dongbin reached out for the pillow he brought and told him to rest a moment while a comforting yellow sorghum porridge cooked to the heat. Soon the traveler fell asleep. And he dreamed the most comforting dream: that passed the imperial exam, knew the most beautiful and intelligent wife, who would give him many children, with whom he would live many years in a well paid and quiet imperial post. Suddenly but awakened from the dream that seemed to have lasted a lifetime. Asking the Master of theist how long he had slept, he replied that the sorghum Pope had not yet bought it yet.
The ancient account in which an immortal allows a mortal to live, in fact, another life for a short time to show him the illusory and transitory character of ambitions for himself to deduce another path, would be resumed in 1601 by playwright Tang Xianzu (1550-1616). But it was well known as one of Handan's many proverbs, reduced to four short characters: 黄粱美梦 Huangliang Meimeng, "a good dream, yellow sorghum."
Huang Ding (c.1650-1730), a changzhou painter, made a series of paintings "in the way of" augustes painters of the past such as Wang Meng, Dong Yuan or even Nizan's unmistakable style landscapes (vertical roller, ink on paper, 92.7 x 35.1 cm, at the Minneapolis Art Institute) as wanting to embark on his push Long history of painting made for a wide time.
At that time a small album was circulated with notes of the influential Dong Qichang, but which is attributed to Wang Shimin (1592-1680) entitled Xiaozhong Xianda, "Revelation of Large Things In Small", which contained, in a small format, recreations of works by great masters. Can you see something too big can be done in a small shape, but a lifetime in a short time? Because what travels is the Spirit, Lu Dongbin made him in less than an hour, the time it takes to cook the yellow sorghum.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Lu Dongbin, the Immortal, waited sitting in a Handan inn, the city of Hebei at Hanshan's term, the reddish purple mountain. He had a porcelain pillow and expected, he would know later, to demonstrate the possibilities offered in the finitude of the flow of the days.
Unknowingly, he came to a luminous encounter, Lu Sheng was immersed in obscure thoughts raised by repeated setting of fortune, but would come with the accuracy of the road that would place him face to face with the immortal patient. Having a brief exchange of words, Lu Sheng realized that the lovely man, who was in front of him with the robes of a daoist priest, was available to listen to his complaints. And the disappointed traveler told how he had narrowly disapproved of the Jinshi exam that would allow him a quiet life in the service of the Empire and now even admitting to imagine a future.
After listening to him, Lu Dongbin reached out for the pillow he brought and told him to rest a moment while a comforting yellow sorghum porridge cooked to the heat. Soon the traveler fell asleep. And he dreamed the most comforting dream: that passed the imperial exam, knew the most beautiful and intelligent wife, who would give him many children, with whom he would live many years in a well paid and quiet imperial post. Suddenly but awakened from the dream that seemed to have lasted a lifetime. Asking the Master of theist how long he had slept, he replied that the sorghum Pope had not yet bought it yet.
The ancient account in which an immortal allows a mortal to live, in fact, another life for a short time to show him the illusory and transitory character of ambitions for himself to deduce another path, would be resumed in 1601 by playwright Tang Xianzu (1550-1616). But it was well known as one of Handan's many proverbs, reduced to four short characters: 黄粱美梦 Huangliang Meimeng, "a good dream, yellow sorghum."
Huang Ding (c.1650-1730), a changzhou painter, made a series of paintings "in the way of" augustes painters of the past such as Wang Meng, Dong Yuan or even Nizan's unmistakable style landscapes (vertical roller, ink on paper, 92.7 x 35.1 cm, at the Minneapolis Art Institute) as wanting to embark on his push Long history of painting made for a wide time.
At that time a small album was circulated with notes of the influential Dong Qichang, but which is attributed to Wang Shimin (1592-1680) entitled Xiaozhong Xianda, "Revelation of Large Things In Small", which contained, in a small format, recreations of works by great masters. Can you see something too big can be done in a small shape, but a lifetime in a short time? Because what travels is the Spirit, Lu Dongbin made him in less than an hour, the time it takes to cook the yellow sorghum.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>June 10 | Alexandre Leitão highlights the end of the waiting lists at the Consulate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/11/10-de-junho-alexandre-leitao-destaca-fim-das-listas-de-espera-no-consulado/</link><description>Yesterday was held at the consular residence in Bela Vista, the usual celebration ceremony of June 10-Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese Communities. Alexandre Leitão, Consul, highlighted the end of the waiting lists in the consulate and the modernization of some services, noting that Portugal is ready to promote stronger economic ties with the MSAR
 
After years when renewing the citizen card or passport could be a small major problem for Portuguese citizens to reside in the MSAR, since this subject seems to be solved. Alexandre Leitão, Portuguese consul-general in Macao and Hong Kong, proved yesterday to be a satisfied man to talk about the last achievements achieved in the operation of the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macau and Hong Kong, this regards the June 10th, Portugal, Camões and Portuguese Communities celebrations.
"After two years of intense concentration in the normalization of consular services, we eliminated waiting lists in the field of issuing citizen cards and passports," he said.
According to Alexandre Leitão, "users have returned access to 90 percent of services without prior appointment, we introduced electronic payment, we drastically reduce response and referral times after the admission of processes, and reorganize human resources and procedures."
The consul did not forget the consulate's team, "which is constituted, almost in full, by Macanese who have positively reacted to the successive challenges that have been presented to them", also noting that "in 15 months were emitted or renewed 55 thousand cards of citizen and passports, which also demonstrates the dimension of the Portuguese community of Macau and Hong Kong."
Portugal with value
Thus, the official said he could “safely say that the essential, from the strictly consular point of view, is done”, but intends to bet on the “deepening of Portugal's diplomatic, economic and cultural relations with the special administrative regions” of Macao and Hong Kong.
Addressing the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, Alexandre Leitão recalled that the ruler “has defended the acceleration of the opening and diversification of the economy” and that from this point of view Portugal has a privileged role to fulfill.
"Portugal has the same purpose, which makes us, once again, bridged in a common purpose: to grow and diversify our economies, internationalizing them for the benefit of our peoples. Portuguese companies are prepared to take advantage of the" most open and inclusive posture to intensify international ties and increase global projection and attractiveness and the renowned Macao as an international metropolis "," Since, they are aware of the contribution of Portuguese companies and workers to the growth and quality of Macao economy services ”.
The consul was still clear in saying Sam Hou Fai that "he can count on the Portuguese community to actively participate in the ambitious design of economic diversification of Masters."
Alexandre Leitão did not forget the last major Chinese investment in Portugal, namely in Sines, by Calb - China Aviation Lithium Battery, being “the largest of the decade”, which “demonstrates the confidence of large Chinese companies and the quality and capacity of Portugal as the preferential investment destination”.
Camões, the Great
Given that there are numerous celebrations of the 500th anniversary of the birth of Luís Vaz de Camões, Sam Hou Fai brought the Portuguese poet to his speech at yesterday's ceremony in Bela Vista. “The strong and deep historical ties between Portugal and Macau are already known to all, and are reflected on this day, because today is also celebrating the largest Portuguese poet who lived a few years in Macao and was part of the first moments of this historical meeting of two peoples.”
"It is never too much to remember that it is because of this centenary meeting of cultures, in this" outdoor window "of China, that the" uniqueness "of Macao arises as" the only place in the world whose official languages ​​", as expressly underlined by President XI Jinping," said the chief executive.
Sam Hou Fai has not yet forgotten the “commitment and commitment of the Government of MSA in the concentration of efforts to build a higher level opening platform”, as well as the “reinforcement of bilateral opening with Lusophony and promoting comprehensive mutual benefits cooperation that enriches and further widen the role and functions of Macao as a sino-illusion platform”.
The chief executive's words also referred to the defense “Macao's multicultural characteristics” and promoting “development in all strands, seeking to continually ensure and improve the well-being of all residents of Macao, including Portuguese communities in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:30:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Casinos | Government says that closing impact will be controlled</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/casinos-satelite-governo-diz-que-impacto-de-encerramento-sera-controlado/</link><description>It is official: the 11 satellite casinos will even end doors until December 31 this year, and Melco and the Macao Game Society have already announced the restructuring plans. Regarding the affected workers, the government presents numbers lower than those already mentioned by deputies and associations: 5,600. An impact on SMEs is still expected, but without a major consequence for banks
 
After much speculation, here is finally the authorities and operators have announced what will actually happen to the 11 satellite casinos operated in the territory. They all will close, and the Macau Game Society (SJM) Resorts and Melco have already defined the plans for what follows [see secondary text], which includes acquisitions of L'ARC and Bridge 16, as well as the transfer of workers and game machines.
The executive presented yesterday, at a press conference, numbers of workers affected with the closing of the satellite casinos below those already referred to by sector associations. It will, after all, will be 5,600 and no more than ten thousand as some deputies said to these entities, and from this cake, 4,800 workers were directly hired by the operators of the game, so if the satellite casino, they can be integrated into their paintings. The rest, 800, were contracted directly by the satellite casinos themselves. There are still 400 non -resident workers (TNR) involved in this process. With regard to Mocha Clubs, 300 local workers and 50 TNR.
Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, said that "the data were collected by different means", but that the government calculations "are official". "As the other means came to this data, I don't know," he added.
Asked about the support of these 800 workers, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, explained that "the owners of the satellite casinos have the responsibility to ensure the work relationship of these people."
"In the case of the 4,800 hired by the dealers, such as Croupiers or Treasury Employees, they can return to work in these dealers' casinos. In relation to 800, the concessionaires have guaranteed the government that if they have employment problems they can absorb them and provide adequate jobs on the properties of the dealers," he said.
Representative Song Pek Kei even talked about the possibility of about 15,000 unemployed, while Nick Law, in a plenary intervention, said that among the satellite casinos and associated stores, there were "13,500 workers", representing "4.6 percent of the total macao work force".
POSSIBILITY OF CONVERSION
Regarding small and medium-sized companies (SMEs) located in the neighborhoods that will no longer have these satellite casinos, namely in areas such as the Inner Port, Zape, Nape or Fishermen's Dock, the government predicts some impact but controlled. There are, in total, 320 stores that operate in the vicinity with 800 workers, and “about 400 workers will have another employment situation according to the reconversion of stores,” said Secretary Tai Kin IP.
Essentially, and after the government's surveys, half of the 320 stores "will be affected directly by the satellite casinos closure, such as the pledge houses, mobile phones, restaurants and jewelery." However, Tai Kin IP pointed out that there will be others that will not have a great impact on depending on sales to residents.
Above all, the ruler pointed out that this scenario may even constitute an opportunity. "It will be a challenge and an opportunity for the reconversion of stores. Traditional stores that have a close relationship with satellite casinos customers have to reconvert.
Highlight that Hospitality Consultant Savills referred in March that the satellite casinos closure would devalue the hotels in 60 percent and cause more non-compliance with the SMEs, with bank credit obligations valued between 25 and 39 billion.
Tai Kin IP devalued this scenario. “From the knowledge we have, the loans granted to satellite casinos involve less than 1 percent of all bank loan activity, and we find that the risks are very limited to the operation of banks. In terms of risk supervision indicators in the financial industry, such as capital flow and others, banks' behavior will be safe and stable.”
Regarding the SMEs, Tai Kin IP said that the monetary and currency of Macao is “closely monitoring the situation with the banks to mitigate the recovery of customers”, and the secretary in advance that in April, “ten billion patacas were injected to loans to the SMEs, attenuating their pressures”.
Asked about the timing of these measures, André Cheong said it is the right time. "It all depends on the dealerships' decisions and we now officially receive the decision. This is a problem that has to do with several casinos and a considerable number of workers, and we did not want that only at the end of the year they knew about their situation. With six months to finish the transition period we understand that this is the indicated phase to advertise," he said.
No impact on recipes
Given the budgetary revision for this year with 12 billion Patacas in the forecast of game revenues, André Cheong assured that the satellite casinos closure will not have a major impact on the overview of revenues.
"We made the budgetary review with less 12 billion patacas due to lack of consumption. We believe that the closure of satellite casinos does not have great impact on the game's recipes," he said.
The secretary also stressed that, as for the intention of SJM Resorts to purchase the enterprises Ponte 16 and L'ARC, the concessionaire "has to conclude this acquisition procedure until December 31, and if they cannot buy these satellite casinos [who operate in the projects] have to end."</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 23:32:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Pecunaries Checks | Former Beneficiaries defend better assignment criteria</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/cheques-pecuniarios-ex-beneficiarios-defendem-melhores-criterios-de-atribuicao/</link><description>Given the changes to the pecuniary reimbursement plan, HM has heard three permanent residents who will no longer receive the check because they do not reside permanently in Macao, including a macanese born in the territory. Arnaldo Gonçalves, academic and former Beneficiary, defends a better distribution of support depending on the income of families
 
The rules for the attribution of pecuniary checks will change and now it is really necessary to be 183 days a year in the territory. The exceptions are some and arrest with students from Macau who are attending courses abroad or residents to work remotely to Macau and who are enrolled in the Social Security Fund, among other situations.
However, many people will be left out, even though they have lived for several decades in the territory or even macanese born in Macau, that is, many of the members of the Macanese diaspora.
In the case of Arnaldo Gonçalves, a permanent resident resident in Lisbon, he lived several decades in Macau, having worked for the government and was a university professor in the area of ​​political science. Six years ago, he returned to Portugal, being renovated, and told HM that he was already waiting for the day he was going to stop receiving the ten thousand dates annually.
"This measure aims to give people a counterpart, given the difficulties existing in consumption and the characteristics of life. I don't live in Macau, and I think from the point of view of equity, the government has never been able to make a fairer regime from the distributive point of view, because there is no system of attribution from the income, and deep down there are multimillionaires that gain the subseck, like the pensioners, all," he said. This is what Arnaldo Gonçalves says "lament". "It is hard work to make an assessment of people's economic possessions, and so everyone receives the same as it is more practical in administrative terms," ​​he said.
Maria João Ferreira, macaense of gem, daughter of the famous poet Adé, will also fail to receive the pecuniary check. He says he understands, but also criticizes the executive's positions. "I was already waiting and accepted with all the tranquility. It is fair, since I do not live there and I have the chance to be 183 days. I thank the time of checks that was dismissed. I lived in Macau until I was 16, but I was born there and still have family. Even the pandemic was there every year of vacation. mentioned.
Maria João Ferreira, currently in the direction of Macao's house in Lisbon, says she was “shocked” with a very concrete case. "A few years ago, when he was doing his doctorate, he learned of a civil servant who did two service committees in Macao and was a contemplated BIR money and even told me, not just me, that I thought it was funny as he was there so recently, he was entitled to such a benefit," he said.
"This is what I think is bad. It is one thing to go to do a service committee in public administration, or two or three, but it was never, in fact, resident. It is, as it were, an immigrant, because it will only work. This is how I see things," he added.
Patacas Amealdas
For Arnaldo Gonçalves, the ten thousand annual patacas served as a “Management Fund” for trips to the territory, where he still has family and where he travels frequently. "I've never used this money for personal purposes, you know? But I think these changes are a good measure, justifiable, and I even think it's selfish, that I've been entitled to this support for so many years. There are other people who need it," he said.
In the case of Maria João Ferreira, the cash of the pecuniary check was also used for expenses in Macao and with trips to the territory. "I have an account in Macao, and when I went there, if I needed to buy the plane ticket, my sister said the money here, or this money served to fund my stay in Macao," he explained.
Sofia Mota, a permanent resident and former Maradora in Macao, regrets the absence of explanations for these changes. "It depends on what the pecuniary check is for, whether it is a way of distributing the wealth or profits of casinos to the people who are part of the territory, or have already done; either if it is a condition to be part of the territory. I do not realize the premise in which the pecuniary check measure is based, and depending on the premise these changes may be more or less acceptable."
The teacher considers that "it makes no sense that those who contribute to social security at their own initiative, as is my case, are not covered." "It seems that there is a first and second and second social security system. People who come to Portugal to provide family care seem not to be covered and yet are out of the territory for reasons of force majeure. What is meant by providing subsistence to family members, is not realizing the function of the check and the coherence of exceptions," he said.
Sofia Mota confesses that she also used money to "a management fund to go to Macau, or to invest in formation."
The first reactions
The changes to the pecuniary reimbursement program were presented at the end of May and report that three groups will be exempt from the obligation to be 183 days a year in Macao and thus receive the check. They are the residents under 22 in 2024 and where one parent meets the requirements for receiving the check; the beneficiaries of the disability pension and the beneficiaries of disability allowance.
There are eight other situations where residents may have access to the check. This is what happens when residents attend higher education outside the territory; When they are hospitalized in a hospital outside the sons, those who are over 65 and live in the interior of China or, even under 65, have health reasons that justify the permanence inside China. Residents who work outside Macao are also covered by the exceptions to an employer registered at the MSAR Social Security Fund and residents outside the MSAR who are responsible for the family aggregate subsistence.
These are also attached to the exercise of official functions outside Macao; the registration of domicile, work or study in the deepened cooperation zone; And yet the work done in the cities of large bay except Hong Kong that is left out.
Deputy Pereira Coutinho manifested against the changes to the pecuniary check referring to violate the Macao Basic Law, namely in article 25, which guarantees the equality of the residents of Macao before the law and prohibits discrimination. The article determines that "the residents of Macao are equal before the law, without discrimination due to nationality, ancestry, race, gender, language, religion, political or ideological convictions, economic instruction and situation or social condition."
More recently, the Macao Synergy Association publicly stated that changes to the pecuniary reimbursement plan in economic development are not in accordance with the wishes of the population. Ron Lam also criticized the executive for applying the changes “in a hurry” which only came to cause more controversy: “the government was in a hurry and applied a sudden measure, without making any public consultation, with only behind -the -scenes movements leading to the population to question governance,” he said. "Consultations with local associations were simulated, which only generated more criticism and caused more unnecessary controversy," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:15:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Entrepreneurship | Event for local companies wants to capture “angel investors”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/empreendedorismo-evento-para-empresas-locais-quer-captar-investidores-anjo/</link><description>Macau today hosts an event designed to capture the so -called “angel investors” for local entrepreneurship projects. Macao Angel Investor Network takes place at “The Macao Young Entrepreneur Incubation Center” and aims to support emerging business projects or simply startups that are taking the first steps
 
It's called “Macau Angel Investor Network”, anything like “Angel Investor Network in Macao” and aims to bring residents closer who want to be successful entrepreneurs and create their own business in an economy that wants to diverse. The event is scheduled for today at Hengqin Development Center, at 517 Avenida da Praia Grande, Nam Tung commercial building, between 11h and 12h30, and has several personalities linked to the local economy, but not only. They are Raphael Chan, Deputy Director of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Paulo Andrez, Emeritus President of the “European Business Angel Network” and also figures such as Emanuel Soares, Legal Consultant, U Man Fai, angel investor for the Great Bay and Founder/founder of “Esenia Fund” and even Ung Choi Kun, former deputy to the Legislative Assembly and president of Kun Cheong Holding Ltd and also an “angel investor”. The event is developed by the Association for Entrepreneurship and Innovation for Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries, which is linked Marco Duarte Rizzolio.
To HM, this explained the main objectives that are behind this initiative. "We want to connect an angel investors to startups and small and medium enterprises (SMEs), fostering the entrepreneurial ecosystem and promoting the economic diversification of Macao." In turn, Alvin Fong, also linked to the organization of this event and president of Direch International, argued that it is intended to “create a platform that brings together knowledge about angel investments, helping in the diversification of Macao's economy”.
According to Rizzolio, "Investors Angel, who invest capital in emerging companies, are fundamental to support startups in early stages where financing possibilities are more scarce in the traditional financial sector."
“In addition,” he said, the contact network that now runs on Praia Grande Avenue “seeks to bring investors closer to Portuguese -speaking and China countries, creating mutual access to the best projects developed in these regions and reinforcing Macao as a strategic link between the East and the West”.
For Alvin Fong, this is the "opportune moment" for the holding of such an event, given that "the world is going through many changes and new opportunities are emerging."
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, in Macao have already occurred in previous events in an attempt to capture angel investments, "but this is the first time a" Business Angels "network has been created in Macao with Chinese investors and Portuguese -speaking countries."
"The conditions to hold this event now arise from various factors, such as the accelerated growth of innovation and technology, the greater digitization and the use of software in business, the need to diversify the local economy, the growing focus on the great bay as a pole of innovation," he said.
At issue, there are also factors such as “the joint effort of public and private entities in creating an environment favorable to entrepreneurship”, something that has been greatly enhanced by the pandemic years, defended, having brought Macao and the authorities “a new understanding of the importance of supporting local and regional businesses, making this moment particularly strategic”.
Who is who
For today's session were invited “Successful Entrepreneurs and Entrepreneurs, some of whom are leaders in their areas”, and their “experience and intelligence add a lot to this event,” said Alvin Fong.
Already Marco Duarte Rizzolio, stressed that will be present “people interested in technology and innovation, including some angel investors, representatives of risk capital funds, renowned entrepreneurs and specialists in innovation and business development”.
Today's session is an “opportunity to obtain valuable knowledge and expand the network of contacts”, and Marco Duarte Rizzolio highlights personalities such as Paulo Andrez, “recognized international expert in entrepreneurship, innovation and angel investment”, or Ung Choi Kun, “prominent figure in Macao in real estate and education sectors, as well as an angel investor in several companies”.
Asked about the main areas in which this initiative is focused on, Rizzolio adds that the event is focused on “startups and SMEs that act on sectors such as technology, intelligent tourism, green economy, health, digital education, logistics or finance”, because they are “sectors with high growth potential and that are aligned in local needs”, namely in the “1+” economic diversification strategy or “1+4” strategy global trends ”.
"We want to identify innovative companies that can thrive not only in Macao, but also in the big bay and in international markets," added this official who is also linked to the organization of the startups and entrepreneurship contest, the "929 Challenge".
Right moment
For Alvin Fong, Macao currently presents potentialities for the connection of business projects to the cities of the Great Bay, all located in Guangdong Province.
"Macau has a lot of freedom and flexibility to experience new ideas. In addition, we have received many tourists from around the world. Being one of GBA's eleven cities, Macau is, in fact, an excellent platform," he said. In turn, Marco Duarte Rizzolio speaks of “unique characteristics” of the territory, “like their position as a bridge between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, a stable regulatory environment and tax and financial incentives that can attract investors and startups”.
There is also “the increase in the focus on the diversification of the economy beyond the game sector”, with “a fertile ground for innovation and new business”.
"In a global scenario of low interest rates, capital markets with some geopolitical friction, investment in technology has presented multiple incomparable from other assets. In this context, the creation of more financial incentives and the strengthening of startup support programs are crucial steps," said the event co-creator.
Great competition
Despite the potential, the challenges persist, given that “Macao does not have many advantages beyond the game sector,” there is “intense competition in the big bay,” warned Alvin Fong.
For Marco Duarte Rizzolio "Challenges are significant," because "the transition from an economy so dependent on the game sector to a more diverse model takes time and requires coordinated efforts."
It is also necessary to take into account the opportunities that arise with the integration of MSar on Hengqin Island, Rizzoolio said, which recalls, however, “the challenges related to competitiveness and regulatory adaptation”.
"In addition, housing and commercial remodeling requires balance between economic growth and the preservation of local social fabric. It is essential to create policies that encourage entrepreneurship and investment, minimizing the negative impacts of these transformations," he said.
Asked whether the authorities have been enough to capture angel investors, both argue that there is more work to do. "This is a good start, but more can be done in the future," said Alvin Fong.
Already Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said that "the Government of MSAR has made important efforts", as well as mentioning "several times the need to create a" Business Angels "network."
“Macau has supported many initiatives that aim to stimulate investment. It is true that the creation of more financial incentives and the strengthening of startup support programs are crucial steps. It is also necessary to promote Macau more actively as an attractive destination for investors, highlighting its competitive advantages on the international scene. This event is an example of good collaboration between the public and private sector to stimulate ecosystem”, defended Rizzolio.
Also noteworthy is that today's close connection with 369, an entity that aims to become “an international hub of science and technology in Macau, giving new generations a greater stage of exploration” of opportunities, ”said Alvin Fong, president of this entity. Marco Duarte Rizzolio stressed that we are facing “an incubator of the Macao ecosystem that has organized several events”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:50:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Environment | Macau registers a new maximum temperatures in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/ambiente-macau-regista-novo-maximo-de-temperaturas-em-2024/</link><description>The direction of environmental protection services yesterday launched new data on the environmental landscape in the territory, in the Macao Encounters of the Macao 2024. The data is not encouraging: last year a new record of maximum temperatures, more rain and typhoons were recorded. More electricity and water was spent, more garbage was produced and fewer recyclable waste was collected
 
Lusa
The Macao Government, through the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) announced yesterday that 2024 reached a maximum temperature record in the territory, and there was also an increase in typhoons and precipitation.
According to the Macau 2024 state report, the average temperature last year was 23.6 ° C, precisely the value that had been reached in 2019, the highest since the records began, in 1952. The average temperature of 2024 was 0.8 ° C higher than the average climacteric (average of 30 years, between 1991 and 2020), according to the document prepared by DSPA.
In addition, Macau registered 42 days considered to be hot last year, more 10.7 days than the climacteric average, 29 hot nights, more 17.5 than the average, and 29 cold days, less 10.1 days than the average.
Meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) classify as hot days when the maximum temperature is equal to or greater than 33ºC and the nights at which the minimum temperature is at least 28ºC. As for the days considered cold, they are those at which the minimum temperature does not exceed 12ºC.
"With global warming, the occurrence of extreme weather phenomena is increasingly frequent," said DSPA in the report.
In 2024, Macau was affected by seven tropical cyclones, known as tuffons, and for the first time three tropical cyclones affected Macao in November, the last month of the Typhoons, which begins in May.
According to the report, the region last year received a total precipitation of 2,029.2 millimeters, "slightly higher than the climacteric average." DSPA also said that since 1970, sea level in Macao has risen at an average rate of about 3.5 millimeters per year.
Also worldwide, 2024 was the hottest year that there are records and exceeded for the first time the 1.5 ° C above the pre-industrial level, in January the copernicus European service advanced in January. Last week, the world weather organization predicted that temperatures should continue to reach record values ​​by the end of the decade.
More people, more expenses
The DSPA report also tells that with the arrival of more tourists to Macau, there were also more waste and spending on water consumption, for example. "With the improvement of the economy, the number of visitors in 2024 increased 23.8 percent in annual terms for almost 35 million, having recovered about 90 percent of the pre-pound level. Tourist intensity also registered a certain increase, with GDP [Gross Domestic Product] climbed 8.8 percent. In addition, there was a slight increase in the population at the end of the year."
Thus, it is added, "in relation to environmental indicators, economic and population growth led to the rise of estimated local emissions of greenhouse gases, invoiced water volume, electricity consumption and the amount of urban solid waste, compared to 2023". "During the pandemic, there was a decrease in the various economic and environmental indicators. However, with the constant improvement of the economy, most of these indicators rose again," is explained.
With regard to the volume of invoiced water, in thousands of cubic meters, by 2023 the record was 89,164 and last year, 94.123, which constitutes an increase of 5.6 percent. Regarding electricity consumption, in millions of kW/h, in 2023 it was 5,740, while in 2024 consumption went to 6,030, plus 5.1 percent. The report also highlights the tons of urban solid waste produced, which in 2023 was 501,512, rising 5.1 percent last year to 526,979 tons.
Another worrying fact of waste level was the fall, for the third consecutive year, the volume of recyclable waste collected, which went from 24.5 percent at 2021 to 21.7 percent last year. Changed for kids, of all recyclable waste generated in Macao, only about one fifth are collected for recycling.
In the report, IP Kuong Lam, director of DSPA, indicates that last year, "with the ongoing economic recovery, there was greater pressure on various environmental indicators, while climate change became more severe." Despite the results, the official said that the objectives are "to encourage greater participation of the population in environmental initiatives and together to achieve the view of building a macao with low carbon emissions."
A question of gases
The report released yesterday by DSPA also accounts for the panorama of greenhouse gases (GHG) gases, and last year, a global increase of “about ten percent, including carbon dioxide (C02), which represented 90 percent”.
It also highlights DSPA that “the estimated emissions of GHE from the various sources have registered upon the same period (2023), except for landfill residues, and the most significant increases were verified in estimated emissions from local electricity production and air transport”.
In addition, it is stated that, in 2024, the main source of Emission of GHG and CO2 was land transport, followed by local electricity production, waste incineration, trade, domestic consumption and services. "The main sources of CH4 emissions [methane] were the waste deposited in landfills and the treatment of wastewater, while the latter was also the main source of N2O emission [nitrous oxide]," he stresses in the document.
DSPA clarifies, regarding the tendency of GHG emissions, that "after reaching the peak in 2017, local Emissions of GHG showed a decreasing tendency, year after year, having reached its lower value during the pandemic." However, with the recovery of economic activities and the great movement of people, especially "in the last two years, the estimated emissions of these gases has gradually rise again."
The air we breathe
Also as regards air quality data is not encouraging, because in 2024 “the number of days with the average quality of the air classified as 'Moderate' registered in the six Macao air quality monitoring stations reached 88 percent, slightly lower than 2023”.
There was, in a total of the year, 15 to 34 days with “unhealthy” classification, and only two days obtained the classification of “very unhealthy”.
According to DSPA, “the pollutants detected in the air monitoring stations were mainly ozone (O3) and thin particles suspended (PM2.5)”, while “at Berma da Estrada station (Ká-Hó), the highest index detected all year round, classified as 'very unhealthy', was the O3 the main pollutant”.
Last year, July was the best air quality month, while October to December obtained the worst qualification according to data from Macao air monitoring stations.
The report also reveals that “in terms of compliance with atmospheric pollutant concentrations in 2024, the average annual concentrations of PM10 and PM2.5 registered in the various monitoring stations were lower than the standard values”, while “the average annual concentrations of nitrogen dioxide (NO2) were also below standard values, except for the stem station station. (Macao) and at the High Density Areas station (Macau) ”.
More optimistic data is also revealed “daily averages of sulfur dioxide concentrations (SO2) and the maximum averages of eight hours of carbon monoxide concentrations (CO) verified in the various stations throughout the year”, as “both were below standard values”.
“In all seasons there was a record of the maximum averages of eight hours of O3 concentrations to exceed standard values ​​in some days. In relation to atmospheric pollutant concentrations recorded in the monitoring stations, generally the average annual concentrations of PM2.5 and NO2, while PM10 and CO descended”, and “as in the road station season (Macao) Only in 2024 did SO2 and O3 begin to be monitored, no comparisons were made. ”</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:16:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | A look at the approach to Spanish -speaking countries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/cooperacao-um-olhar-sobre-a-aproximacao-aos-paises-de-lingua-espanhola/</link><description>The MSAR was already approaching Spain, but the chief executive began to refer to official speeches the importance of cooperation between Macao and Spanish -speaking countries, as well as the usual Lusophone world. Analysts relate these words to the current panorama of relations between China and Spain
 
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, has expressed in some discourses the importance of having to establish economic and commercial relations not only with Portuguese -speaking countries, but also with Spanish -speaking ones. Last month, on a public occasion, the government leader stated that the territory has to "welcome foreign friends to invest in Macau and also to realize his dreams in Macao." Sam Hou Fai highlighted the area of ​​advanced technology, stressing that “they can come from Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries” because “as long as they are in favor of economic diversification, they are always welcome,” he added.
Moreover, after the inauguration of the new government, Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, made, in March, a visit to several European countries, leading a delegation that passed through Spain, Portugal, Belgium and Monaco to deepen “international links and explore opportunities for cooperation”, according to official information released at the time.
This approach to the Spanish -language universe, in addition to the usual connection already established between China and the Lusophone world, can have several origins: the growing relationship between China and Spain, as well as the desire to diversify the economy by MSAR, say analysts contacted by HM.
“The interpretation of Sam Hou Fai Declaration is very objective and pragmatic and can be summed up to the Macao economy diversification project, for which companies and investors are not only in Macao, but also from Portuguese-speaking countries. But the fact is that companies and institutions in Portuguese-speaking countries are not being effective in response to this need for Macao. For cooperation it seems logical to me, ”said economist Maria Fernanda Ilhéu, former resident of Macao and president of the Friends Association of the New Seda Route (ARS).
According to the leader, “Macau is a pure market economy, is classified by the World Trade Organization as a free port with its own international agreements both in the economic, commercial, investment, financial, health, sports, sports, international relations agreements with various organizations. Therefore, the business in Macau is very free, and the part of the government of Macau is to promote and frame this opening”. "As Sam Hou Fai says, all companies and investors who bring Macao economy diversification solutions are welcome," he added.
To Cátia Miriam Costa, professor at ISCTE - University Institute of Lisbon, and specialist in Chinese foreign policy and Macao, considered the HM that “this connection to the Spanish stems from the high -level official visits made by the Spanish government to China, that is, there is certainly one of the consequences of the repeated presence of Spanish diplomacy on a very high level, reinforcing the ties between the two. countries ”.
THE IMPORTANCE OF GLOBAL SOUTH
It is true that Beijing, in the words of President XI Jinping, has shown great interest in the approach of the countries of the so -called “global south”, where Portuguese and Spanish speaks, essentially. For Cátia Miriam Costa, here also resides another explanation for the change of paradigm in the field of commercial and economic cooperation.
"It seems to me that recent meetings with high Spanish political representatives have influenced this decision, along with a growing political investment in China in the global south where Portuguese and Spanish are, in fact, the most spoken languages."
For Académica, "the strategy of using Macau as a convergence point may be historically justified by its cosmopolitanism, but also by its traditional role in including the routes that connected Asia to Latin America." In addition, "adds to a historical perspective, a contemporary view for a region that needs economic diversification and benefits from this proximity to distant spaces, whether historical or culturally." Cátia Miriam Costa understands, therefore, that "Spanish can be seen as an additional value to Portuguese, without distorting the paradiplomacy strategy defined for Macao early on."
The inclusion of Equatorial Guinea in the Macao Forum cannot be ignored, as a result of its entry to the CPLP - community of Portuguese -speaking countries. However, Cátia Miriam Costa believes that this change has little or nothing to do with the inclusion of Spanish -speaking countries in the official commercial approach discourse.
"The inclusion of Equatorial Guinea in the Macao Forum stems from another circumstance, that of his participation as a member of the CPLP. In this sense, it was a logical step in the dynamics of the Forum. However and although it can count as a positive element in this approach, the leverage that Equatorial Guinea has in the Hispanic or Hispanic speaking world," he pointed out.
ASES BY ARE
Maria Fernanda Ilhéu also highlighted the fact that the only direct air connection between Macao and Europe will be for Madrid and not to Lisbon. “By chance, TAP or the Portuguese government have contacted Air Macau or the Macao government expressing interest in resuming this airline? I don't know, but I know that this connection will greatly contribute to strengthening the Spanish presence in Macao, whether in tourism, commerce or investment.”
The guardian highlights the complementarity factor of the air route. "Is it incompatible with the Portuguese and Spanish presence in Macau? It doesn't seem to me, but it's competitive, it may even be beneficial if they know how to collaborate and gain scale in the Great Bay area, but Portugal has to work harder for their presence in Macau not a historical relic."
Moreover, the economist does not forget the role that Portuguese foreign policy may play in this issue, with the removal of Huawei in Portugal and a closer approach to Beijing in recent times.
“Portugal's decision banning the use of Huawei equipment says mainly respect for the economic relations of Portugal with mainland China and it is framed by a fearful diplomatic relationship that the Portuguese government followed from 2019 to 2024, contrary to the Spanish diplomatic relationship. It should be noted that the Spanish Prime Minister visited China several times during this period and the Portuguese government alone was represented by the foreign business minister. At the Boao Forum in Hainan, with a brief pass for Beijing. ”
Thus, Maria Fernanda Ilhéu understands that between 2019 and 2024 “the Portuguese government and the Portuguese civil society were very conditioned by the American narrative of cold war and the formation of two antagonistic blocks, not knowing how to keep the line followed by 2019 to proceed with a relationship with China supported by the friendship and confidence of nearly 500 years of cooperation in Macau”.
The necessary work
For the economist and president of ANSRs, it is necessary to take into account the investments and business movements made in recent times to perceive the position of Portugal and Spain in this domain.
“The last major investment of a large Chinese company in Portugal was registered in 2020, and only now is this type of investment with Calb investment [SINE Battery producer] that is in the implementation and licensing phase. If we see the same type of investments in Spain from 2020 to 2024 we can record five major energy investments, by China Three Gorges and Huadian; Transport, Geely, Chery Auto and Envision Group; a major investment in agriculture by Yankuang Beijing Energy and also a major investment in the health sector by Worg Pharmaceuticals. ”
For the official, “a lot of work will have to be done by the new Portuguese government to develop Portuguese economic cooperation with mainland China and MSAR, but it will also have to be accompanied by Portuguese business fabric”, he summarized.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Budget 2025 | Government removes 12 billion from the estimates of the game's revenues</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/orcamento-2025-governo-retira-12-mil-milhoes-as-estimativas-das-receitas-do-jogo/</link><description>The advanced forecast in November by the executive, which pointed to 240 billion casinos gross revenues in 2025, was reviewed. The government now predicts that revenues have a break of 12 billion patacas, forcing the budgetary review yesterday by André Cheong yesterday
 
Yesterday were released by the Executive Council, the data on the budget review for this year, which happens due to the low forecast of the amount of gross revenues of the game, which depend, on large scale, the local economy and public revenues.
Thus, if the executive initially estimated that the game's gross gross revenues would be, this year, from 240 billion patacas, this value now drops to 228 billion, or 12 billion. Regarding the average monthly estimate, 19 billion patacas in gross revenues are now foreseen, because "the situation is not like the one planned."
In yesterday's presentation, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, and also spokesman for the Executive Board, said that “after study and analysis of the current global economic conjuncture and the effective situation of exploitation of the game sector from the beginning of this year to the present moment, it is proposed that the annual estimate of gross revenues of the game will be reduced from 240 billion to 228 billion, thus serving as to Main base of the financial budget financial revenues, and that relevant budgetary revenue rules are properly adjusted. ”
In November last year, when Ho Iat Seng was about to leave the position of Chief Executive, predictions for gross revenues were 240 billion, taking into account the initial version of the budget proposal for 2025. At the time, the forecast represented an increase compared to what had been estimated to 2024, which situated the gross revenues of casinos by 216 billion Patacas, an increase of 11.1 percent. Given the gross game recipes in 2023, the estimate for 2025 was a 31.1 percent increase.
It is important to highlight that the new forecast below expected is an annual increase of only 0.5 percent in gross revenues, when the initial numbers translated into annual growth of 5.8 percent. In the first five months of this year, the game's revenues rose only 1.7 percent annually to 97.7 billion patacas.
Balance Guarantee
In response to journalists, the subdirector of finance services, Ho Silvestre in Mare, said the new calculations were based on the data provided by the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination Services (DICJ) in contrast to the first semester public expenses.
“In this proposed budget law we made an analysis of the global conjuncture and took into account a different model regarding the consumption of tourists in Macau. We made general considerations for these estimates and, according to DICJ, from January to April this year, an average of 19 billion and there was an increase to 21.1 billion (gross revenues). reaching the 20 billion [ragous game revenues, on average], so in the second half of the year there will be uncertainties. ”
"In this budget we intend to take a balance in expense and revenue. After an evaluation at the first half of the year, we can make an assessment taking into account the amount of 19 billion Patacas, and according to the current expense of the MSAR, we were able to get a more balanced budget," he added.
In general terms, and according to the explanatory note presented by André Cheong, the total amount of the ENGRICIAN INTEGRATED ORDINARY BUDGET for the 2025 economic year is 116.5 billion, when a revenue of the 121 billion patacas was expected to be expected to be expected to be expected to be expected to reduce the DSF's gross revenue revenue. The cut is 4.56 billion patacas.
In addition, the official said, only the reduction in the tax raised on the game, due to the break in gross revenues, translates into 450 million patacas for the administration. It should also be noted that budgetary expense within the PIDDA [Administration Development Investment and Development Plan] is reviewed to about 19.587 billion Patacas.
Budgetary expense rises 2.5 percent due to education and social support
The government ensures that, in the proposal for a budget for this year, the construction of a new campus of the University of Macau (one) on the island of Hengqin will contribute, in part, to the increase of expense, around 2.5 percent, as well as “the increase in budget in relation to subsidies attributed to vulnerable groups and investment in research and scientific and technological development”.
In the budget proposal presented yesterday, there is a approximate amount of 1.7 billion Patacas for the construction of the new UM campus, said the subdirect of Finance Services (DSF). In addition, at the level of scientific and technological investment was added the amount of 340 million patacas “for investments in the scope of science and technology, such as the acquisition of laboratory devices, to satisfy the measure and policies of the Government of Masters,” said Ho Silvestre in Mais.
"For construction is expected an expense of about eight billion patacas. As the campus is built on Hengqin Island, the cost must be calculated in Renminbis, which is about seven billion. This is the data we can have at this time," said the official.
Support for support
With regard to social support, the budget proposal for this year reveals an increase of 2.86 billion of Patacas in the expected expenses, as a way of reinforcing these supports. In total, the rise in expenses is 2.5 percent, to 116.2 billion patacas.
As for the preparation of the budget for next year, it is being prepared and the watchword is containment. "We are already elaborating the budget for the year 2026, and all services of the Government of MSAR need to consider more about their expenses, especially given the current conjuncture. In the budgetary elaboration phase we take a prudent and rigorous attitude towards the expenses," said the subdirector of DSF.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 00:29:05</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS | New drugs are 16% of positive tests</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/ias-novas-drogas-sao-16-dos-testes-positivos/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action believes that last year there were 148 drug consumers, about 0.02 percent of the population, based on the number of people who are serving time for consumption or who is in rehabilitation. Still, the 148 consumers represent an increase of 25 percent compared to 2023
 
The Institute of Social Action has once again betting on a pilot project to test the use of new drugs, such as ethomyidate (known as Space Oil), metcatinone and synthetic cannabinoids. Last year, authorities collected about 1,600 samples that revealed a positivity rate of 9 percent. Among the positive tests, 16 percent concerned the new drugs referred to, Cheang Io Tat, head of the IAS department of dependence on the game and drug, in statements quoted by TDM's Macao channel.
Despite the media and stresses provoked by Space Oil, which even led to the amendment of the law, the IAS responsible states that the “traditional drugs” continue to be predominant.
Cheang Io Tat spoke on Saturday on the sidelines of the launch of a series of IAS organized activities to mark International Day against Drug Abuse and Trafficking.
During the ceremony, IAS delivered “diplomas of recognition to schools that have participated in the Sadia Life Education course over the years, as a way of thanking their contribution to the promotion of the education of healthy life. In addition, the same day was the inauguration ceremony of the scientific exposure on the fight against the Great Bay, performed for the first time this year”.
Fantasy world
The United Nations Office against Drugs and Crime published in October the World Drug Report that indicated that in 2022, there were almost 292 million consumers of narcoty around the world, about 1 in 18 people. The number advanced by the United Nations pointed to a proportion of about 5.5 percent of the world population that had consumed drugs in the year under analysis. The percentage at the global level is sprayed by the numbers advanced by the Institute of Social Action (IAS), which last year indicated that last year the number of consumers in Macau was 148, or about 0.02 percent of the population of MSAR.
In a highly punitive panorama, which pushes pathological or occasional consumers for obscurity, which authorities call “hidden consumption”, IAS numbers represent the only people who in Macao for certainty do not consume drugs: those who are serving time for use or are in rehab.
Despite the statistics that do not reflect reality, the authorities indicate that the 148 drug consumers last year represented an increase of about 25 percent compared to 2023. However, the 2024 record was 6 percent lower compared to the period before the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:01:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Education | Lam regrets Vong Fong Va's death</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/educacao-o-lam-lamenta-falecimento-de-vong-fong-va/</link><description>Tomorrow is the funeral of Professor Vong Fong VA, who died on June 4 with 94 years. The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, issued a statement on Saturday to regret the death of the man who devoted almost half a century to education, highlighting the time of the time as deputy director of Hou Kong Secondary School.
Lam stressed Vong Fong Va's dedication to teaching and patriotism, a work that earned him the silver lotus medal of honor awarded by the Government of MSAR.
Vong Fong VA has occupied prominent places in various local associations. He was vice-president of the General Association of Chong Wa de Macau Students, vowel of the Macao's Return of the Return of Macau, President of the Macao Education Association, President of the Friendship and Coordination Association of former National Popular Assembly and former Member of the Chinese Political Conference of Macao, “uniting the forces of associations in the love of Macao and Macao, promoting the Macao,”, promoting prosperity and macao stability ”,” He pointed out Lam.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:00:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Sam received president of the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/cooperacao-sam-recebeu-presidente-da-academia-chinesa-de-ciencias-sociais/</link><description>The chief executive met on Friday with the president and secretary of the Chinese Academy Party Leadership Group of Social Sciences, and director and secretary of the Chinese Academy Party Committee of History, Gao Xiang. According to the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai "said the Government of MSAR guidance the" four expectations "requested by President XI Jinping," and has as a priority "the construction of" a center, a platform and a base ".
The ruler will have said that the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences, as a “superior institution of the country in the area of ​​Social Sciences Study and Research”, conducts exchange and cooperation broadly with Macao Higher Education Institutions in the areas of Social, Cultural and Human Sciences Studies and Research ”. As such, the head of the Executive has praised the“ constant ”contribution of the National Academy to the“ development of masters ”.
Sam Hou Fai also suggested that the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences and the Higher Education Institutions of MSA take advantage of the Macau platform, "to promote opportunities and spread the excellence of traditional Chinese culture and thus tell the stories of Macao and China well."</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:53:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | List of the “hand soldier” target of CCAC due to corruption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/eleicoes-lista-do-soldado-de-mao-alvo-do-ccac-devido-a-corrupcao/</link><description>When trying to gather the missing signatures to participate in the elections, the list helps Mutual Grassroots, linked to Wong Wai Man, was the target of another operation of the authorities, with new arrests. The two operations within two days, with several arrests, will even have prevented participation in the elections
 
The potential list candidate for elections Mutual Help Grassroots, linked to Wong Wai Man, the “Mao Soldier”, will have failed the deadline for delivering missing signatures, after being the target of a commissioned operation against corruption (CCAC), justified with corruption suspicions. This was the second operation of the authorities against members of the potential list within two days, and the exclusion of the elections must be confirmed today by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal).
CCAC's operation was announced by the body led by Ieong Seong on Friday without identifying the list of the list. In a statement, about the operation that took place on Thursday, the authorities just stated that they had discovered “a case suspected of offering advantages, including pecuniary advantages, to entice the signing of the form for recognition of the application committee.”
Before a candidate for the Legislative Assembly is formed, members need to constitute the so -called application committee and collect between 300 and 500 support signatures. At the time of CCAC's operation, Mutual aid Grassroots was in a race against time to get 77 more valid signatures after some of the signatures originally presented were considered invalid.
"CCAC has found that there are at least five individuals involved in the case. These individuals will have enlisted others to sign filing forms with pecuniary advantages or other advantages or will have offered proposition forms already signed," was reported by the authorities. "One of the suspects confessed to the practice of their suspicious criminal act while another suspect confessed to falsifying voter signatures, signing forms of proposition," he was added.
Almost confirmed deletion
To the All About Macau, Sou Weng, a member of the Iron and Steel Association that serves as the basis for the potential list Mutual Grassroots, acknowledged that the latest operation of CCAC resulted in the detention of the person in charge of collecting missing signatures.
The detainee, who was not identified, was in a meeting with a friend when he was taken by the authorities. This person was in charge of collecting the signatures, after Wong Wai Man was arrested the day before by the Judicial Police, allegedly for the crime of exploitation of Mah-Jong, in another judicial case.
Given the arrests of the association's latest members, I am Weng admitted as soon as the signatures are most likely to deliver, which excludes from the elections to the list. To All About Macau, the association member refused the existence of any corruption case involving the Association of Iron and Steel shipowners.
Cash prison
On Saturday, the Public Prosecution Service (MP) issued a statement informing that members of the association involved are appointed by the crime of electoral corruption, punished with a sentence of one to five years in prison. According to the MP, if they are considered guilty, the targets have to serve effective prison sentence, since the electoral law does not allow suspension, without replacement for other punishment measures, as a fine. The targets are also indicted for the crime of falsifying a document that can be punished with a fine or prison penalty up to 3 years, which may be suspended.
The MP also informed that the criminal instruction judge "applied to the two main measures to coercive security, periodic presentation, prohibition of absence and prohibition of contacts and the other three defendants of security coercion.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 00:52:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Casinos | Closure affects real estate and bank</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/casinos-satelite-fecho-afecta-imobiliario-e-banca/</link><description>The President of the General Association of Macao Real Estate Sector warns that poorly stopped credit can reach 100 billion patacas, due to the closing of satellite casinos and businesses around these fun spaces
 
The announcement about the closing about nine satellite casinos in the outer port landfills (Zape) resulted in the freezing of at least 10 real estate business in just two days. The scenario was drawn by the president of the General Association of Macao Real Estate Sector, IP Kin Wa, in statements to the newspaper or Mun.
According to IP Kin Wa, with confirmation of the closing of nine satellite casinos in that area, several interested in buying real estate, or lease, immediately chose to postpone business, and even those who gave up the investment.
IP revealed that in many cases the freezing of potential businesses have been justified with the need to wait to see what happens in the future and realize what will be the new value of real estate. With the closure of the satellite casinos, around which several businesses, such as pledge, restaurants or convenience stores, are expected to devalue these spaces.
The president of the association also explained that some renewals of leasing of commercial spaces in that area, which were practically completed, were suspended and may not advance. Given this scenario, IP Kin Wa is very concerned about what has considered the direct impact of the advertising of the closing of the casinos of that zone.
As a consequence of the closure, the associative leader fears that the crisis with which the real estate market has been discussed for some years ahead with the breach of the value of real estate and the reduction of sales prices.
Feet shots
In the statements made to the newspaper with greater circulation in the territory, IP Kin Wa also warned that the closure of satellite casinos represents a risk to the health of the banking system much higher than officially recognized by the government.
According to the president of the association, the government indicated that credits related to the satellite casinos only represent 1 percent of the total credits of the bank. However, according to IP, the numbers of the bank itself point out that the value linked to these casinos is greater than 10 billion patacas.
In addition, IP indicated that the government, by choosing not to take steps to save satellite casinos, is ignoring the indirect impact of the closure of these casinos on other businesses that turn around the game spaces. Previously, Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, estimated that there would be about 320 stores that could be affected by the closing of the casinos.
However, the Association's president now warns that loans were requested during the pandemic for these businesses, to meet revenue reduction, and that there was no time to recover financially, which makes them not capable of returning money to banks. To these loans, the mortgages are added to be paid by the landlords who lease the spaces where businesses are explored. According to IP, when business loans and mortgages are taken into account, the amount of credit directly and indirectly linked to the satellite casinos rises to at least 70 billion patacas, in the case of 70 percent of businesses lose their ability to pay their loans.
Based on these accounts, IP Kin Wa estimated that poorly-paved credit can rise to 100 billion patacas, a rate of 10 percent. According to the data cited by IP, from the Macao monetary authority for April, this month, the lending failure rate was 5.4 percent, equivalent to 55 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:28:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Government renews contract with slot but requires TNR reduction</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/jogo-governo-renova-contrato-com-slot-mas-exige-reducao-de-tnr/</link><description>The government renewed the instant exploitation exploration agreement with Macau's SLOT-Bills and Mutual Better, but required the company to priority for local residents in access to employment and formulating proposals to reduce non-resident workers' quotas.
According to the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination (DICJ), among the human resources of SLOT, 15 percent are TNR. In view of the Executive's requirements, the company proposed to reduce by 35 percent TNR's current quotas to a total of 26 quotas for non -specialized workers until the end of the first quarter of next year.
The DICJ stressed yesterday that "the Government of MSAR will continue to evaluate the situation of execution of SLOT with regard to the guarantee of priority of access to the employment of local residents and in the fulfillment of their social responsibilities, in order to ensure the healthy development of the local labor market and, together, safeguard social stability."</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:27:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Aviation | Market opening starts in February 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/aviacao-abertura-do-mercado-arranca-em-fevereiro-de-2026/</link><description>The law that aims to end Air Macau's monopoly in Civil Aviation is expected to enter February in February next year. The estimate was left by Vong Hin Fai, deputy and president of the 3rd Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly yesterday, after the discussion in the specialty was finalized.
At this stage, the law will still have to be voted in the plenary of the Legislative Assembly, which should happen as late until 15 August this year, and no difficulty in approving the diploma.
Once the law comes into force, in theory, any airline can try to get a license to operate in Macao. However, the number of licenses is controlled by the Chief Executive, which means that the market is not possible to be effectively liberalized.
In addition to passenger transport aviation, the concession system is also effective for the transportation of goods and mail.
The law will not impose a service obligation on the new companies that enter the Macao market, but if after the authorization, companies will pass two years without any activity, the authorization will expire.
Authorizations to operate in Macau can be distributed by public tender. No entanto, Chefe do Executivo tem poderes para dispensar esse procedimento e entregar a licença directamente a uma empresa, se considerar que essa opção é aquela que melhor defende o interesse público.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:26:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Violence to increase under Nazi greeting</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/violencia-a-aumentar-sob-a-saudacao-nazi/</link><description>Facts: At the celebrations of April 25 a group of neo -Nazis insulted and assaulted the Democratic protesters and police officers with dicks and iron chairs of a tergo in São Domingos, Lisbon; In the Alto Lisboeta neighborhood four neo-Nazis after giving Nazi greeting before three blacks, two South African tourists and one Portuguese, they beat and kicked until the blacks became unconscious; In a restaurant next to the 'The Tent' Theater, a Neonazi Group joined a meeting/lunch and leaving the transfer went to the door of the theater where some employees and actors were talking about. Wearing nightgowns of a neo -NaIzi group began to insult one of the gifts that wore a nightgone with a red star and Che Guevara's silhouette "ah is Guevara, we too, but it's to kill you all."
However, the well-known actor Adérito Lopes arrived and tried to appease the discussion and one of the neo-Nazis with an iron soothed in his hand punched the actor on his face, making him severely injured in a view and having to be hospitalized; Next to the Sporting Sports Pavilion, after a roller hockey meeting, a hooded group of sportinguist supporters, two of them already identified as connoted with an far right group, attacked and burned the car where five portist supporters were going to be seriously injured; In Porto, two ladies of the home association who supported the homeless people were surrounded by neo-Nazi individuals who after doing the Nazi greeting began to assault the homeless, insult and assault the volunteer ladies, saying, "You stop with this shit to help foreigners!".
Police arrived shortly after and one of the attackers, as they asked the identification, punched the police officer; At the celebrations of June 10 next to the Monument of the Old Combatants, in Belém, an individual after extending his arm to the style of Nazi greeting, began to shouts the magnet of the Muslim community, who for over 17 years participates in that celebration with the Catholic chaplain of the Armed Forces, saying, "O traitor goes away, go to your land that this is the Portuguese." Those present at the ceremony immediately dismissed the individual who insulted and some had to contain themselves not to give them a slob; An African homeless lying next to the door of a house of Alcântara was completely painted black and left the drawing of a swastatic cross in the sheet that covered the homeless.
Violent, unpunished and revolting facts. To the point that the judicial power sent the aggressor of the actor Adérito Lopes and the perpetrators of the police officer and the volunteer ladies of the house. Violence by neo-Nazi groups is generalizing in a way that in most cities there is no old man who leaves the street without fear of being attacked and stolen, especially if not white. The phenomenon is naturally a sad reality of this party that tends to increase. And why? Because these neo -Nazi groups began to feel their backs hot.
If not, let's see. Since André Ventura and his party supporters arrived began to start speeches of racism, xenophobia, hatred and insults to other deputies of the Assembly of the Republic, social networks have filled with messages of hatred, xenophobia, racism and incentive to aggression to all who were immigrants. André Ventura is the main culprit of this wave of violence that is generated in the country by neonazis groups and even some elements of arrival. But the fault is not only of venture. We shamefully watched that Prime Minister Luís Montenegro neither a word of disapproval uttered about the case of aggression to actor Adérito Lopes.
The new Minister of Internal Affairs came to public with a simple statement, where what he said meant zero, about the violence that begins to be weekly. How did the information services of the Republic and PSP not become aware of the gathering of many neo -Nazi elements in a restaurant next to the theater a tent? How was it possible that they were not controlling their movements? And that these elements could leave the restaurant going through the streets, armed in owners of the world and could get to the aggression to an actor?
Much has been said since the last election campaign for the Legislative Elections of the past 18, safely. We hear that the country is the safest in Europe. Bullets. When the people are already afraid to leave home, do we live in a safe country? Police associations are tight to claim better conditions in their activity, to point out that they arrest criminals and that the judicial power sends them free. Even police officers are already afraid of patrolling on foot. At night, don't even think. Patrol and “Vivó Velho Old!” Pass. The safety of populations is a theme that has to be taken very seriously by the new government. The situation we assist extreme violence from neo -Nazi groups has only one solution: as soon as they are detained after an act of violence must be sent in court to prison.
And what is the Minister of Justice, especially with a non-existent reform in the paintings, when it is known that a large number of judges are sympathizing by André Ventura? The government has announced that financial support to Ukraine will increase and that the investment in defense will be many million euros. Was it no longer logical than if you first thought about the safety of the people and that the number of police officers increased substantially? Real and worrying is the increase in cases of violence under Nazi greeting.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:28:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Rum</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/rumi/</link><description>The ancient Persia has for us the charm of legends and we resort to it when around the dreams and silence the rules of civilization that makes us dive daily in tangible facts, and without realizing there is an inner voice that takes us out and puts us in the way where the poem helps to rise, that to fall, we are instigated under any circumstance.
But this Persia, where was it? What is the reason for giving us the best of human condition when we deal with spirituality and poetry? It is a Western Asia territory and the place of the oldest civilizations in the world, and we focus on it to better understand this overwhelming front called geopolitics.
It has now been going since 1935, and it is here that Rumi was born in one of its provinces, Afghanistan, under the sultanato of Rum, Turkey, in the thirteenth century, backwards we left the largest empire in the world, and the successive vacancies of achievements and reconquisers that made it so powerful.
In this Persia peoples prayed to poets, therefore, there was no differentiation between their status and the spirituality in force in the lands of zoroastrianism, the first monotheistic religion that would give the bases to the Abumi, which produced a Rumi, as it had already given an Omar Khayyam - Rumi, can be considered a Sufi, the most spiritual side of Islam, and the expression “science” cannot be fairer or more suggestive, when we read your poems.
He is a mystical poet who launched himself in his divine project by studying philosophy, theology, law, who gave him a great ability to look at injustices and make laws (let us not forget one of the first milestones of Persia, free the slaves. Greece followed their steps) and their main work, the greatest mystical work of the world poetry that puts it in the legendary voice of a prophet, but immense And it encompasses prose, sermons, and a hundred number of notes from its disciples who can guide those who perspective it as the most achieved exercise to prevent the shadows that are so vertically fall upon us.
Poets also serve this: to stop fascism! The filth of these societies and the programmatic artificial links of insane policies need Rumi. It is also needed that teaching guides for a different and more solemn context in the pursuit of other sources, that is, they need not to be widely in the “creative” artifacts ”and climb from step so that we can throw themselves from the predestined abyss that we all have to face. The legislator should seek by all means to introduce the cultures where the poem was law, and the spiritual strength, its link, and if two of these Earth navigators have an effect on the minds in formation, the effort was gained to have been implemented. Also his world has never been calm, having to escape the arrival of the Mongols, becoming a Dervixe (Turkish Name) on the ascetic path of the Tariqah: his order called Mevlevi, who are those who dance around with men dressed in white.
Union, love, concord, and harmony were the themes that composed, so that we meet the "immortal beloved" and almost ended in Ramon Llull's "friend and beloved".
Friends, return to the source of the pure essence,
that nothing else can be the same. Remember,
We are pearls in the ocean of the Spirit. If not;
Why are constant waves sprout in our hearts?
The Primeva Wave created the bowl of this body,
And as we break, we will be in union with our friend.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:45:36</pubDate></item><item><title>The Star Door (I)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/12/a-porta-das-estrelas-i-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the June 5th edition)
To understand Trump's project, it is essential to watch the Stargate presentation video. The tycoon begins to speak almost in bureaucratic, stating that the purpose of the project is to build "the physical and virtual infrastructure to strengthen the next generation of artificial intelligences." Then he pauses, takes a deep breath and proceeds with the fatal statement that "for this we will build colossal data centers." This passage, if the tycoon had chosen to publish it in the "Truth Social" instead of announcing it in world broadcast, would certainly have been written in Trumpian capital letters "we will build colossal data centers."
The stars door, in short, is something very ground. It is not about writing some software lines, but building huge industrial warehouses where storing a gigantic amount of data needed to train the IAS to match and perhaps overcome human intelligence. It is about diverting whole water courses to cool the machines, given the incredible energy consumption of these infrastructures. AI consumes a lot of energy and is certainly not "green". Trump realized this, and therefore the 2008 Republican Campaign slogan «Drill, Baby, Drill!» It also adapts to the development of AI. It is not cruelty or disinterest regarding the ecological destination of the planet. It is pure principle of reality. Typical, before the president, the businessman. Because Altman can hire all the best computer engineers in the world and collect all the data they want, but without the Jensen GPUs and the Donald ChatgPT land can be at most a brilliant calculator.
In a recent interview, Jake Sullivan, a former US National Security Gate, explained that now the state can no longer exert real control over technological development, especially when it comes to AI. Is that so. Regulating OpenAi and similar companies is impossible. Innovation is very fast and cannot be softened without creating threats to national security. However, as AI does not exist in nature, but it has to be produced, Trump reasoning, if I want to exercise power in this process, a power, not a European -style governance that is equivalent to industrial suicide, I have to insert myself into value chains. How to do this? Sometimes the most trivial solutions are also the most effective. Certainly, the state cannot compete with Altman in software, Jensen in hardware or Ellison and Microsoft in the cloud. But it remains the only subject that has the soil, which exercises the monopoly of legitimate violence and which can grant authorization to "build colossal data centers".
Only the state can decide to divert watercourses to direct them to the cooling facilities and provide data centers for the energy needed to feed the computing capacity. Neither Jensen's GPUs, nor OpenAi software, nor the cloud of Oracle can do so. In this world, only Donald Trump can do so. In economic terms, it is about occupying a strangulation point in a value chain.
At the moment, the president and three musketeers of Stargate (Ellison, Masa and Altman) are aligned. Therefore, the tycoon promises a flood of executive orders and emergency statements to ensure the water and energy supply needed to feed the colossal data centers that are now part of the American landscape. However, in doing so, Trump also intends to signal to his traveling companions that the star door still depends on the state, at least until the words of Max Weber "the last fossil fuel backyard is burned."
Perfo. So and summarizing, through Stargate, Trump intends to consolidate the primacy in Ia in relation to China and maintain some form of control over innovation. The financial liability of the operation ie the task of finding the 100 billion dollars to start and then quintuplycling it is up to softbank, while operational responsibility is from OpenAi.
Oracle will make the clouds available and the GPUs, while the government is to ensure the necessary energy supply to feed the entire process. Stargate is, first of all, an infrastructure project, which is materialized in the construction of colossal data centers and the future creation of one hundred thousand jobs. As Trump said at the Davos Forum, the star door should indeed be inserted into the country's broader industrial strategy, which consists of 'making the United States an industrial superpower.'</description><pubDate>2025-06-12 00:43:10</pubDate></item><item><title>In the month of sexual diversity, who do we preach?</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/11/no-mes-da-diversidade-sexual-a-quem-pregamos/</link><description>My intuition tells me that we are on the wrong way. We are entering a complex dark tunnel system, in a labyrinthine mountain, with little possibility to see points of light. These warmths are still far from our reach - not before we cross the darkness and the winding curves that the rock naturally forms.
In the game between light and shadows, we lose ourselves in dichotomies that deluded us, judging us on the way to progress, unity, diversity and respect. Given what is happening in the world, socially and politically, empty theories arise - theories of those who think it understands the complex development system that is ours: the human. We are fish in the ocean trying to make sense of water, without ever having a state outside it.
June is the month of LGBTQIA+celebration, and the tension is palpable. Pinkwashing, i.e., marketing that takes advantage of social causes and civic for profit-proves to be fragile. The colors of the rainbow are no longer seen as seen last year or two years ago. Now defending the LGBTQIA+ cause can cause damage. In addition, social networks are filled with complaints, as if the celebration of homosexual pride required an opposite celebration of "heterosexual pride." As if being heterosexual were not already celebrated around the corner of the world, with full rights in love and union. What we see, instead, is a misunderstanding that only feeds more hatred, more prejudice - and in many cases more death.
We live in a schizophrenic world: on the one hand, illusion; on the other, the disguised rot. Both sides suffer from the same evils. Develop spaces to talk about sexuality-so that people better understand themselves and others-it seemed to me a natural mechanism for the normalization of the subject. However, the confusing and hateful information paths overpassed. How does Elon Musk's absurd theory come about? What empathy destroys civilizations? And love - also destroys them? Is this natural act that leads to sex and procreation is not based on this intimate and simple relationship of empathy? We are lost.
Resting in the trenches of the battle of ideas, there is still hope - hope that certain ideas do not have to be defeated by others. In Thailand, in January this year, same-sex marriage was legalized. In Hong Kong, news agencies celebrate homosexual unions - impossible in China, Macao or Hong Kong - that find in other Southeast Asian countries the possibility of acceptance.
I have reflected a lot on how to reach those who need to review in a friendly word, and to understand that the freedom to be is a human right. There are many lives at this time, whose value is minimized - as if one life was worth less than another. In the month of sexual and gender diversity, where the sense of the right to existence reigns, I want to honor the decreasing people, who are erased, raped and killed for the worst reasons. From Palestine to the rest of the world.
I don't know if I'm preaching to fish, converts, or simply to anyone. But if these words come to the eyes of those who need it, I am satisfied. There are no revolutionary fantasies here - just the belief that one must be on the side of understanding and empathy. The mechanism that has allowed the progress of societies to this day.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 03:00:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Museum | Gansu culture exposed until July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/museu-de-macau-cultura-de-gansu-exposta-ate-julho/</link><description>Until July 13, the Macao Museum will be exhibited entirely dedicated to Chinese culture. This is “Genesis and Spirit-Show of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Gansu”, which “presents the culture of Longyuan and the charm of the Silk Rota”, according to the description of the Cultural Institute
 
The exhibition “Genesis and Spirit-Show of the Intangible Cultural Heritage of Gansu” was inaugurated on the weekend, patent at the Macao Museum until July 13. The show is part of the celebrations of the Cultural Institute (IC) of the “China's Cultural and Natural Heritage Day” of 2025.
According to a note issued by the IC, it is intended to “deepen the exchange and cooperation between the interior of China and Macau in the field of intangible cultural heritage”, and it shows Macau helps “actively play the role of 'a base' in promoting excellent traditional Chinese culture”.
Inaugurated on Saturday, the cultural initiative has the support of several entities, namely the IC and the Gansu Province Department of Culture and Tourism, and is also co-organized by the Intangible Cultural Heritage Protection Center of Gansu Province and the Gansu Province Music and Dance Group, with so many other supports.
Located in the Yellow River Higher Course, the province of Gansu is an important stretch of the old silk route, where several cultures converged and mixed, giving rise to a rich variety of intangible cultural heritage, with strong regional characteristics and ethnic diversity. This heritage, which has been continually accumulated, transmitted and developed, “has become a treasure for the Chinese nation,” says the IC.
Many activities
Until July 13, various activities are held around the exhibition, namely performances, demonstrations of handcrafted techniques and experimental workshops, intending to display “the rich and diverse intangible cultural heritage of the province of Gansu, so that the public can experience the Longyuan culture and the charm of the Silk Route”.
Today the demonstrations of handcrafted techniques and sales of intangible cultural heritage products at the Macau Museum, where Gansu transmitters have the essence of the techniques incorporated into the intangible cultural heritage of their province, allow the public to experience the inheritance and creativity of this intangible cultural heritage.
Regarding the show itself, it presents' qingyang fragrance sachets, linxia brick sculptures, Dunhuang's colorful sculptures, sculpted bright glasses and other works in four sections, namely 'Longyou Ballads',' turbulent rivers', 'Dunhuang Flowers' and' eternal breeze along the silk route '.
It is intended, with the exhibition “to show the unique charm of the artisanal techniques of the intangible cultural heritage of the province of Gansu”, as well as the “acts of the intangible cultural heritage of Gansu 2025”, at 7:30 pm at Senate Largo and, at the same time, in the garden of Iao Hon. Hua'er, corner accompanied by Longouqin (Chinese -headed dragon -headed harp), and Kongtong school martial arts. ”</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:25:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Comedy | Jimmy O. Yang acts for the first instead Macau in Broadway</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/comedia-jimmy-o-yang-actua-pela-primeira-em-vez-macau-no-broadway/</link><description>July 4th, 5th and 6th deserve to be reserved on the Calendar of Macao Stand-Up Comedy fans. Jimmy O. Yang, Hong Kong comedian who enters series such as “Silicon Valley” and “Space Force”, will act on Broadway Theater. Tickets are on sale today and cost between 480 and 880 patacas
 
“I have something big to announce: Macao, or Mun, I'm going to be from July 4th to 6th to three shows. It will be my first shows in Macau. The tickets will be for sale on June 13th. Until now, Macao!” This is how comedian Jimmy O. Yang announced on social networks that he will bring his stand-up comedy show for the first time to Macao. The shows are marked for the Broadway Theater. On July 4th and 5th, start at 8:30 pm and on July 6, Sunday, the session starts at 15h.
Tickets are on sale today and cost between 480 and 880 patacas.
Prior to the shows in Macau, Jimmy O. Yang will act in his homeland, Hong Kong, with five shows already sold out at the neighboring city's coliseum, between today and Sunday, with two matins in the middle.
At the age of 38, the comedian already has a long career, not only in stage comedy, but especially in a television series and cinema. The popularity of HBO comedy “Silicon Valley” introduced Jimmy O. Yang to the World, playing a member of a computer programming team that tries to luck in the billionaires of mobile applications.
Another recurring role in Jimmy O. Yang's curriculum, was on the Netflix series "Space Force", where he contracted with actors such as Steve Carell, John Malkovich, Ben Schwartz, Diana Silvers, Lisa Kudrow and her father Richard Ouyang.
Hong Kong comedian has still entered series such as "The Simpsons", "It's Always Sunny in Philadelphia", "American Dad", among others.
In seventh art
In about 12 years, Jimmy O. Yang has entered more than two dozen movies. In his filmography there are some unavoidable feature films such as "Crazy Rich Asians", "Love Hard", "Like a Boss" and animations such as "The Monkey King", where he gives voice to the protagonist, "Minions: The Rise of Gru", "The Lego Movie 2" and "Wish Dragon".
In the middle of a career on stage and the big and small screens, Jimmy O. Yang still had time to write a book: "How to American: An Immigrant's Guide to Disappointing Your Parents." Not only does the work describe your life a little, but someone who moves from Hong Kong to California, where he already had a family, but also unravels the themes he usually addresses in stand-up comedy shows.
In the introduction of the book, the comedian gives some clues about his journey and the impact he had on his family. “I refused a job in the financial area to dedicate myself to my stand-up comedy career. My father thought I had crazy. But I realized that it was more worth disillusioned for my parents for a few years, than to disappoint my life. I had to dedicate them so I could do it. That was the only way I got to be able to eat my chinese cake and the chinese cake American at the same time. ”
Jimmy O. Yang was born in Hong Kong in the summer of 1987, after his parents moved from Shanghai to the neighboring region. In 2000, when the comedian was a 13-year-old, the family moved to Los Angeles, where he lived an aunt and a young man from the young man.
In 2009, he graduated from Economics at the University of California, San Diego. At the ceremony of delivery of diplomas in the year in which he completed the degree, the main speaker was Mike Judge, the author of the series "Silicon Valley".</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Consulate | Sara Augusto presents book and exhibition about Camões</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/12/consulado-sara-augusto-apresenta-livro-e-exposicao-sobre-camoes/</link><description>“Vast Empire of the Heart” is the title of the book Sara Augusto presents next Wednesday. The work, accompanied by an exhibition focused on the presence of Camões in Macau, is part of the June 10th celebrations poster - Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese Communities
 
Macao continues to celebrate the Portuguese Portuguese and the largest poet of the Portuguese language, Luís de Camões, with various events and protagonists. This time the focus is, again the poet, but the initiative is born from Sara Augusto, Academic, Portuguese professor at the City of Macau and also photographer.
“Vast Empire of the Heart” is the verse of António Couto de Viana that names the book and exhibition will be presented next Wednesday, 18 at the Stanley Ho Auditorium, at the Portuguese General Consulate in Macau and Hong Kong. The show consisting of 12 images of Sara Augusto, is also evident in the same place.
At HM, Sara Augusto explains that the choice of name for the work and exhibition "has to do with the sound of the verse." “The poem to which it belongs is a tormented poem, which contains the immensity of Camões's work as a country that does not live up to the expectations of the poetic subject. But it was not the meaning of the poem that interested me, it was this particular verse that seems to be relating to the vocation for maritime travels and above all with the expansion of the Portuguese language. Language, capable of expressing different latitudes and cultures as shown by the richness of Lusophone literature, ”he explained.
“Vast Empire of the Heart” results from the work developed by Sara Augusto for a congress. "This work was then more developed and presented in a colloquium in Beijing, also organized by the Portuguese Institute of the East, under the celebration of the 500th anniversary of the birth of the poet. From this presentation came the idea of ​​publishing a volume with an anthology of texts, a study and photographic record, both of my own."
Poetic testimonies
The work in question is an anthology that “collects poetic records of visitors, Portuguese writers who lived in Macau some time and writers born in Macao, revealing ties that celebrate, identify themselves and who inscribed Camões in collective memory”.
Sara Augusto said that “the set of texts covers just over two centuries” and the starting point is Almeida Garrett's poem “Camões”, “who became the model of the lonely poet's romantic image, writing her verses in the cave scenario”.
“This model was brought to the letter in the nineteenth century and in much of the twentieth century. The book 'The Cave of Camões' by Monsignor Manuel Teixeira was an important source, such as the consultation of the five volumes of the anthology 'from far to China', as well as a long survey in the Public Library of Macao. Portuguese poets visited and lived some time in Macau, such as António Manuel Couto Viana, José Valle de Figueiredo, or Alice Vieira and Eugénio de Andrade, ”explained Sara Augusto.
Adé's place
The author points out that “it was very important the Camonian inspiration poetry of José dos Santos Ferreira, Adé, who even translated poems from Camões to Patuá, or the poetry of José Joaquim Monteiro, Leonel Alves, Maria do Rosário Almeida, António Correia, Josué da Silva, António Boondoso, José Maria Bartolo”.
Then, already in the 21st century, “the Camonian theme continued, taking different and more elaborate forms, as with Fernando Sales Lopes, Jorge Arrimar, António Mil-Homens and Carlos Morais José”, the latter a name that Sara Augusto considers “unavoidable”, taking into account the novel “The Archive of Confessions”.
The images on the exhibition are black and white and focus on “in the garden and cave of Camões”, intending to “accompany the poetic record”. With both projects, the official wanted to “participate in the celebration of the 500th anniversary of the birth of Camões and present a collection in an organized way, accompanied by a study”.
In addition, “it was intended to gather poetry that speaks of Camões, but also the subjective image of a photographic record,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-12 00:41:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Docomomo brings Macau Session on Nepal Architecture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/11/docomomo-traz-a-macau-sessao-sobre-arquitectura-do-nepal/</link><description>Next Monday, 16, the Conference “Modern Encounters in Architecture: Challenges for Documentation of Modernist Buildings in Nepal”, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, from 18:30. The event is organized by the Docomomo Research Center in Macao and the conversation will be starred by architect and teacher Jharna Joshi, being moderate by architect João Nuno Marques.
Jharna Joshi is an architect, graduated from the University of Tsinghua, in Beijing, having specializations in historical conservation and cultural landscapes. Recently completed a doctorate in management (Tourism) at Victoria University of Wellington, New Zealand, with the dissertation “Aesthetics of Landscape, Tourism and Change: Case Studies in Nepal”, where he analyzes how residents and tourists perceive the aesthetic changes of the landscape in Ghandruk, Bandipur and Sauraha.
A Larga Experience
With over twenty years of experience in architecture, conservation, cultural landscapes, tourism and teaching, Jharna worked at Nepal, China, Hong Kong, USA, Vietnam, Greece and New Zealand. Leaded restoration and adaptive reuse projects throughout Nepal, with emphasis on local materials, traditional knowledge and creative reuse. It collaborates with national and international professionals in architectural projects and heritage conservation, and teaches as a guest teacher, focusing on urban conservation, vernacular architecture, resignation and cultural landscapes.
Regarding Nepal's architectural panorama, there has been a focus on heritage buildings, which need to be at least 100 years old to obtain official recognition. As a consequence, the initial modern architecture - structures built between 1945 and 1985 - remains undervalued, unoccumented and vulnerable to demolition or abandonment.
The absence of a consolidated tradition of archiving of architectural materials makes it even more difficult to understand and teach this period, leaving students and teachers with few resources.
The recent initiative of the Kathmandu Institute to document initial modern buildings highlighted this gap. These constructions symbolized the impulse of Nepal modernization, transforming agricultural zones into urban spaces. However, accelerated development and marketing put them at risk of disappearing.
Documentation has proved difficult due to the scarcity of files and the diversity of formats, obtained from private collections, online institutions and files. According to a note from Docomomo, this lecture presents the initial conclusions of the project, aiming to promote the dialogue and appreciation of this neglected era of Nepalesa architecture. In addition to historical preservation, the project also has an educational and public sensitization aspect, launching the foundations for future initiatives for legal protection and continuous investigation.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 19:19:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice | TSI maintains a sentence of 9 months in prison for the theft necklace</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/justica-tsi-mantem-pena-de-9-meses-de-prisao-por-furto-de-colar/</link><description>The second instance (TSI) court refused to suspend a 9 -month prison sentence, applied to a tourist who stole a jewelry store necklace in Macao. The decision was announced last Friday, through a statement from the office of the president of the last court.
The case happened on March 11, 2023, when the criminal brought a fake necklace to Macao, in order to go to a store and exchange it for an original, getting the most valuable. In the store he frequented, after entering Macao, the necklace from which he was intended to appropriate was evaluated 37,300 patacas.
With the excuse that he intended to buy the necklace, the man managed to change it for the other who brought inside the coat. With the exchange made, eventually left the store without making the purchase. Initially, the store workers did not detect the original necklace change for the fake, but at the end of the day, when the cleaning before the closure realized the had happened, so the authorities called.
The man was eventually tried and sentenced to 9 months in prison for the crime of qualified theft. However, the detainee contested the first sentence to the second instance court because he understood that once the facts had confessed to the penalty should be suspended. However, the TSI has refused the claim, so the detainee will have to serve the sentence.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:13:39</pubDate></item><item><title>G Dragon | 12 tickets in ticket purchase</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/g-dragon-12-burlas-em-compra-de-bilhetes/</link><description>A total of 12 people were circumvented in 87,000 patacas when they sought to buy tickets on the black market for the concerts of singer G Dragon, which took place between June 6 and 8. The case was revealed yesterday by the Judicial Police (PJ), and quoted by the newspaper or Mun.
Although the identity of the show artist was not revealed, the South Korean singer was the only one with concerts in Macau in those three consecutive days. According to Modus Operandi, the burns promised to sell tickets to the different days and after receiving the payment were unmistakable.
In 10 cases, the burles were made over the internet and in two other occurrences the scores were in person, as the alleged sellers did not attend the time of handing over the tickets. Ticket losses ranged from 1,000 patacas and 25,000 patacas for a total of 87,000 patacas.
Online Sales | Burlas generate losses of 25 thousand patacas
The Judicial Police (PJ) announced the 19th online sales registration that resulted in losses of 25,000 patacas. According to police information, quoted by the newspaper or Mun, the slips were made through the online sale of shellfish, buffets in local restaurants, amusement parks or local hotel packages.
PJ is investigating all cases, which have affected a total of 19 victims, 11 women and 8 men. Regarding the profile of the victims, it was also announced that 16 are middle age and three are young.
The victims were deceived after accessing online advertising and paid by bank transfer between June 7 and 11. However, although they made payments never received the goods they bought. In individual terms, the burles ranged from the 320 patacas and 3,800 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:12:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | Elderly displeased with dinner kills wife to stab</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/crime-idoso-desagradado-com-jantar-mata-esposa-a-facada/</link><description>Police suspect that displeasure before dinner may have led a 74 -year -old man to murder his 71 -year -old wife after about 50 years of marriage. The victim will have suffered at least 16 cleaver blows, most of them in the head and neck. The man is indicted for the crime of qualified homicide, which may imply a sentence up to 25 years in prison
 
Around 5 pm on Friday, a woman found a macabre scenario when she returned home in the Lakes Nam Van. Between the living room and the kitchen, his parents were on the floor in an authentic blood pool. The mother would eventually lose her life following multiple stab wounds and her father would be arrested on suspicion of qualified homicide.
According to the Judicial Police, dissatisfaction with what dinner would have been at the source of a contempt that ended in tragedy, with her husband, a 74 -year -old retired to murder her 71 -year -old wife with whom she had been married for about 50 years.
When the authorities arrived at the apartment, they found a cleaver and kitchen scissors in the lady's washing and signs of fighting in the kitchen, with blood everywhere.
The suspect also presented blows to the head and multiple lacerations that did not need suture and appeared to be in a stable mental state. After receiving medical treatment, he was taken to the Judicial Police for interrogation. The gun of the crime was a cleaver, discovered in the lava-laryl, with which the suspect will have, at least 16 blows to the victim, most in his head and neck.
Crime and punishment
At a press conference on Saturday, the Judicial Police indicated that it was often for the couple to have discussions for trivial reasons, but without registration of police intervention requests to resolve disputes.
The case was referred to the Public Prosecution Service and the man is suspected of the crime of qualified homicide. According to the Penal Code, "if death is produced in circumstances that reveal special censorship or wickedness of the agent, it is punished with prison sentence of 15 to 25 years."</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:11:14</pubDate></item><item><title>MPay | Application will allow calling taxis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/mpay-aplicacao-vai-permitir-chamar-taxis/</link><description>The Macau Pass company announced that the MPay application started to include a function to call taxis, which emerges as a gauge, the phonetics of the characters in Mandarin.
According to the information released by Macau Pass, which is currently controlled by Alibaba, currently the taxi call service only covers the normal taxis, identified by the black color, so it leaves out the taxis reserved by telephone.
If users travel inside China, the gate function can be used not only to call it taxis, but also offer services like Uber and Didi, ie transport services that are not provided by taxis. In Macao, this type of service is considered illegal as vehicles do not have the necessary licenses.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:08:50</pubDate></item><item><title>IIICF | Signed agreements of $ 10.1 billion US dollars</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/iiicf-assinados-acordos-de-101-mil-milhoes-de-dolares-americanos/</link><description>The 16th Forum and International Exhibition on Investment Investment and Construction (IIICF) was marked by the signing of 31 cooperation protocols in areas such as transport, construction, electricity, water resources and renewable energy
 
Thirty-one cooperation protocols, worth US $ 10.1 billion, were signed during an infrastructure forum in Macao. One third involve lusophone and mashed companies, it was announced yesterday.
The agreements established during the 16th International Forum and Exhibition on Investment and Construction of Infrastructure (IIICF), with a value of “about $ 10.1 billion US, predict cooperation in domains such as transport, construction, electricity, water resources and renewable energy in 22 countries and regions”, reads in a statement from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macau. (Ipim).
About one third of the signed projects, between Tuesday and Thursday, involve companies from Portuguese and Macao countries.
Over the three days, Ipim indicates, more than 200 contact scholarship sessions were organized, with more than 70 counted with the presence of companies from Macao and Hengqin, “which represents an increase of more than 30 percent”, compared to the 52 sessions of the previous year.
“These results further highlight the role of Macao as a sino-sirophone platform, as well as the efforts of this region in the proactive joint with national development strategies, especially the construction of the great bay,” writes Ipim.
In this sense, the note continues, representatives of Portuguese -speaking countries “recognized the effective role of Macao” as a bridge to establish contacts between companies and institutions in China and Lusophone.
“They even revealed that during the IIICF they obtained cooperation agreements with companies in the interior of China in the areas of Information Technology and Electric Engineering, underlining their satisfaction,” reads the IPIM note. In 2003, Beijing established Macao as a platform for the reinforcement of economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries and that same year created the Macao Forum.
Great Bay Numbers
The Great Bay is a Beijing project that aims to create a worldwide metropolis from the Special Chinese administrative regions of Macao and Hong Kong and nine other cities of the neighboring province of Guangdong, where they inhabit more than 80 million inhabitants.
Also launched by Beijing in 2021, the initiative of the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin encompasses an area of ​​about 106 square kilometers.
More than 3,500 infrastructure professionals from more than 70 countries and regions participated in this forum, which recorded “a new record in terms of the presence of high-level guests, specifically with almost 70 ministerial level leaders”.
During these days the infrastructure development rate “a track, a route”, led by Saudi Arabia, Indonesia and Malaysia, was also released, in which Brazil is the Portuguese-speaking country with the best score.
The initiative, announced by Chinese leader Xi Jinping in 2013, involves more than 80 countries in Beijing's International Strategic Strategic Plan to develop maritime, bus and rail connections, but also investment in energy resources.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:07:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Auto-Silos | 12 proposals for exploration received</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/auto-silos-recebidas-12-propostas-para-exploracao/</link><description>The public tender for granting the exploitation of the parking lot of the Comendador Ho Yin Jardim SILO, the self-solo of Malaca Street, the self-solo of the Mong Sin building, the self-solo of the Mong In building, the self-solo of the tranquility street and the self-solo of Rua do Almirante Sérgio received 12 proposals. However, only 11 proposals ended up meeting the required requirements, so one was excluded, and there was yet another withdrawal, which was not even taken into account.
Admitted proposals range from 1.068 million patacas, which came from the NAM property administration company or, and 3,500 million patacas, proposed by management and cleaning.
The deadline for granting the exploitation of the public parking service of the six self-siles is six years, covering 1119 parking places for light car and 1772 for motorcycles and mopeds. The concessionaire will be responsible not only for the management and daily exploitation of the auto-silos, but also for the optimization of the electronic payment system and without contact of the auto-sign, the reinforcement of safety surveillance systems, the implementation of ecological and energetically efficient equipment, and the improvement of existing facilities.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:05:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Take-Away | Distributor detained for driving drunk</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/take-away-distribuidor-detido-por-conduzir-embriagado/</link><description>A Take-Away distributor was arrested after a road accident and an alcohol rate of 2.95 grams per liter of blood on Tuesday. According to the newspaper or Mun, the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) received the call from the suspect himself, who asked for help and claimed that his left foot had been injured in one of the motorcycle parking bars.
When the police officers arrived, they found that the suspect smelled of alcohol and suspected that he had been driving with excessive alcohol in the blood. Also before the call, the CPSP had received a complaint from a road accident, where a motorcycle driver had fallen alone, without damage, and fled from the site.
Using video surveillance CPSP confirmed that it was the same suspect and that after the accident it still continued to distribute food. After taking the balloon test, an alcohol rate of 2.95 grams per liter of blood was discovered in the driver. The case was referred to the Public Prosecution Service for the crime of driving in a state of drunkenness.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:33:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed with scholastic rigor stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club Narrative Prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>India/Accident | Pilot declared “Mayday” seconds after take off</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/india-acidente-piloto-declarou-mayday-segundos-apos-descolagem/</link><description>The Ministry of Civil Aviation of India revealed Saturday that the AI171 Air India Flight pilot, which fell with 242 people on board, declared an emergency Mayday seconds after offspring, and that the aircraft fell almost exactly a minute later.
In the first official statement of the Indian government since the accident on Thursday, the Secretary of Civil Aviation, Samir Kumar Sinha, made a minute report of the final moments of the flight. "The plane took off at 13:39, local time, and in seconds, after reaching an altitude of about 650 feet (almost 200 meters), began to sink, that is, to lose altitude," said Sinha.
The official added: "At 1:39 PM, the pilot reported Air Traffic Control (ATC) in Ahmedabad that it was a Mayday." According to the secretary, when the ATC tried to contact the plane again after the emergency call, it did not get any response.
"Exactly a minute later, at 1:40 pm, the plane dumped in Meghaninar, a zone about two kilometers from the airport," he added. The ministry also confirmed that 242 people were on board the plane: 230 passengers, two pilots and 10 crew.
About the previous state of the device, the secretary said that before the accident, the plane had made the Paris-Delhi-Ahmedabad route without incident. The number of dead in the AI171 flight tragedy of Air India rose to at least 279.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:34:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Tehran | New explosions heard yesterday in the Iranian capital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/teerao-novas-explosoes-ouvidas-ontem-na-capital-iraniana/</link><description>New explosions were heard yesterday in Tehraão, the capital of Iran, on the third day of an Israeli attack on a large scale against the Islamic Republic, an AFP journalist has advanced at the site.
Iranian media, Khabar Online and Ham Mihan reported that air defense systems in the west and northwest of Tehran had been activated “to counteract new attacks”, while the Iranian Diary Shargh broadcast a video that showed smoke columns in the east of the capital. The Israelite army guaranteed to have reached more than 80 targets yesterday in Tehran, in night air attacks involving "about fifty fighters."
"Throughout the night, the Air Force fighters flew over Tehran and reached infrastructures and targets of the Iranian nuclear project," according to a military statement, quoted by AFP.
Israel has reached "more than 80 targets, including the Ministry of Defense [and what Israel describes as] the headquarters of the Iranian [military] nuclear project [the organization of defensive research and innovation, or separate, according to the acronym Persian], as well as targets where the regime hid nuclear files."
In turn, the Iranian government announced yesterday that the meter and mosques of Tehran will remain open 24 hours a day for the population to take refuge from Israelite attacks, which resumed the bombing against the Iranian capital at noon.
Iranian government spokesman Fatemeh Mohajerani has announced that “mosques, schools and the subway will be available to the public as shelters”, when national media began reporting new Israeli bombing in the neighborhoods of Saadat Abad and Punak, northwest of the capital. The Iranian Portal Khabar Online reported that the Niroo Research Institute in the northwest region of Teerão was attacked by Israel.
According to the Young Journalists Club, near the Iranian government, the city's air defenses have already been activated to repel the attack.
Between dead and injured
The Iranian government spokesman appealed to calm. "Service centers, such as banks and medical centers, are at the service of the public and other centers also have the possibility of some employees to work at a distance," he explained to the media, according to the Iranian official news agency Irna.
The war between Israel and Iran, triggered at dawn on June 13 for Israelite bombings that aimed at Iranian military and nuclear facilities, has already caused more than 100 dead and 800 injured in Iran, including military leaders, scientists and civilians.
The Israelite attacks, made by 200 aircraft against a hundred targets, reached mainly Tehran (North) and the uranium enrichment centers of Fordow and Natanz (Center), Mehrabad National Airport and various military bases.
Iran retaliated with hundreds of missiles directed to the cities of Telavive and Jerusalem, who made at least 13 dead and 150 injured.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:30:31</pubDate></item><item><title>FIA | Extraordinary General Assemblies in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/fia-assembleias-gerais-extraordinarias-em-macau/</link><description>The Extraordinary Assemblies of the International Automobile Federation (FIA) held in Macao last week. Organized by the FIA ​​member club at MSA, the Macao-China General Association (AAMC), with the support of Galaxy Entertainment Group, the event took place so well that the maximum organ that rules the motor rating intends to return to the Galaxy International Convention Center in 2026 and 2027
 
The FIA ​​is the regulator of car sport worldwide and the Federation of Global Mobility Organizations. It is a non -profit organization, dedicated to boosting innovation and defending safety, sustainability and equality in motorized sport and mobility. Founded in 1904, with offices in Paris, London and Geneva, FIA brings together 245 member organizations on five continents, representing millions of road users, as well as professionals and volunteers of motorized sport. Among many other functions, it develops and applies regulations for motorized sport, including the seven FIA world championships.
The Extraordinary General Assemblies of the FIA ​​result under the Annual Conference of the International Federation and usually have a rotating character between countries. However, after this year's excellent reception in the territory, the Paris-based organization is preparing to return to Macau again in the next two years.
It is possible to read in the press release of the International Federation that “after the success of the FIA ​​conference of 2025, organized in Macao by the Macau-China General Association Member (AAMC), with the support of Galaxy Entertainment Group, the members of the FIA ​​voted in favor of holding the 2026 and 2027 Extraordinary Assemblies in Macao. will take place at Galaxy Macau. ”
Set goals
At the end of this year's edition, FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulayem recalled that “our mid -year conference is a valuable opportunity to interact with our members clubs, celebrate our successes and set goals for the future. It is a time to reinforce connections and boost our strategy with a new dynamism, continuing to fulfill our commitments.”
The event received more than 500 FIA senior delegates, in the areas of mobility and sports, from 149 countries, offering the opportunity to address key initiatives in road safety, sustainable mobility, regional growth of sports and transportation in transportation.
Also during the event, on the eve of election for the presidency, the FIA ​​presented and approved its accounts and the 2024 activities, detailing the success of FIA's financial recovery during the presidency of Mohammed Ben Suulayem. Earlier this year, the FIA ​​announced that it recorded an operating result of 4.7 million euros, about 40.42 million patacas, its best financial result since 2018.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:21:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Transport | Tested in real high speed train that can reach 400 km/h</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/transportes-testado-em-linha-real-comboio-de-alta-velocidade-que-pode-atingir-400-km-h/</link><description>China began last week the first real-line tests of the new high-speed CR450 train, fully developed in the country and designed to reach 400 kilometers per hour, local press reported Friday.
The tests, with a scheduled duration of about 15 days, take place in the Wuhan-Yichang section of the newly settled Wuhan-Chongqing-Chongdu line in Hubei's central province, considered adequate to validate technical performance without interfering with regular rail traffic.
The train left on Thursday of Yichang Norte station, having traveled the route to several speeds to collect data on acceleration, braking, stability and energy consumption, within the scope of what is designated as a “type test”.
Although the maximum speed in commercial operation is 400 km/h, the CR450 is designed to reach up to 450 km/h in test conditions, in an attempt to exceed the current technical limits of the Chinese high speed network, set at 350 km/h.
The CR450 represents an evolution of the fuxing model, the first high -speed train fully developed in China without resorting to foreign technology. It is part of an innovation program started in 2018, supported by the current five -year development plan of the Chinese government, which defines the country's strategic and economic priorities to five years.
Among the technical objectives of the project is the maintenance of energy consumption levels and noise similar to those of the models currently in operation, despite the increase in speed. If the tests are successfully completed, the new train will be able to go into commercial service from 2026, according to experts from the China Institute of Rail Sciences.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:19:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Aviation | Xi Jinping sends condolences to India by the victims of the accident in Ahmedabad</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/aviacao-xi-jinping-envia-condolencias-a-india-pelas-vitimas-do-acidente-em-ahmedabad/</link><description>China President Xi Jinping sent messages of condolences to the Indian counterpart Friday, Doupadi mutter, and to Prime Minister, Narendra Modi, for the plane crash in Ahmedabad, which caused at least 279 dead, including seven Portuguese citizens. "I am deeply saddened to learn of the Air India flight accident, which caused numerous victims," ​​said Xi, in a message cited by the official news agency Xinhua.
In the name of the Government and the Chinese people, the head of state expressed “the most felt condolences” to the families of the deadly victims and wished rapid improvements to the injured. Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang also sent a message similar to Narendra Modi, associating with official manifestations of solidarity with the government and the people of India.
During a press conference held Friday in Beijing, the spokesman for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs Lin Jian also revealed that Xi Jinping addressed condolence messages to King Charles III and that Li Qiang did the same with British Prime Minister Keir Strmer, given the presence of British citizens among the victims.
The aircraft, a Boeing 787 bound for London, drew shortly after taking off from the Indian city of Ahmedabad on Thursday morning. The accident, already considered one of the worst air tragedies in recent India history, caused 268 dead, including several people on land, and only one survivor.
According to the Indian authorities, the plane lost power shortly after offspring and clashed in a residential complex, causing a large explosion fueled by the fuel on board. The plane carried 230 passengers - 169 Indians, 53 British, seven Portuguese and one Canadian - and 12 crew members.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:18:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran | China condemns and calls for an end to the attacks of Israel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/irao-china-condena-e-pede-fim-dos-ataques-de-israel/</link><description>Israel continues to take the war to the medium-orient. After the ongoing genocide in Gaza, and attacks on Lebanon and Syria, the radical government of Netanyahu now turns to Iran
 
China condemned Israeli attacks on Friday Friday and appealed to Israel to stop military activity against the Islamic Republic during an emergency meeting of the UN Security Council. "Increasing tensions in the region will not benefit anyone and we appeal to Israel to stop the attacks on Iran," said China Ambassador to the Security Council, Fu Kong, quoted by Iranian IRNA official news agency.
China's permanent representative in the United Nations said Israel "caused massacres in Iran and damaged nuclear facilities in the country." Fu referred to the attacks launched by Israel against military and nuclear facilities in Iran that caused at least 78 dead and 320 injured, according to the authorities of Tehran.
In the attacks, according to IRNA, the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, Major-General Mohammad Bagheri, the commander of the central headquarters of Khatam-AL ANBIYA, Major-General Gholam Ali Rashid, and the commander of the guards of the Revolution, Major General Hossein Salami. Physicist Mohammad Tehranchi and nuclear scientist Fereydoon Abbasi, as well as civilians were also killed.
"According to the Israelite authorities, these attacks will continue. China condemns these actions that violate Iran's safety and territorial integrity," said Chinese diplomat.
Fu warned that the attacks “will have serious consequences”, which did not specify, and that the aggravation of tensions in the region “will not benefit anyone”. "We appeal to Israel to end the attacks and that all parties respect international law," he insisted.
Climbing
Fu Kong said China was "very concerned" about the direct effects of the attacks on Iran's diplomatic process. "China has always supported diplomacy and opposed unilateral actions," he said.
Fu also defended respect for the right of Iran, as a signatory to the non -nuclear non -proliferation treaty, to use nuclear technology for peaceful purposes.
"There have been conflicts for a long time in the Middle East and the situation remains critical. The international community should seek to obtain a ceasefire in Gaza, a crumbling in the region and the prevention of tensions and conflict climbing," he said.
Fu Kong appealed to "countries with influence on Israel," an allusion to the United States, to play "a constructive role." "The UN Security Council must play the role of Guardian of Peace," he added, according to the Iraqi agency. Following Israelite attacks, Iran launched hundreds of missiles and drones against Israel.</description><pubDate>2025-06-16 01:17:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Vatican | Beijing says that agreement on bishops was applied without setbacks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/vaticano-pequim-diz-que-acordo-sobre-bispos-foi-aplicado-sem-contratempos/</link><description>China said yesterday that the provisional agreement with the Vatican about the appointment of bishops "has been implemented without setbacks" after the appointment of Joseph Lin Yuntuan as auxiliary bishop of the city of Fuzhou in the southeastern country.
"In recent years, China and Vatican have maintained fluid communication and reinforced mutual trust through a constructive dialogue," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said at a press conference in Beijing.
The official stressed that both parties have cooperated in implementing the provisional agreement signed in 2018 - and renewed twice - which provides for the consensualization of the appointment of bishops in China, a matter historically sensitive to both states. "China is willing to work with the Vatican to continue to promote the progress of relationships," added Lin.
The Vatican confirmed on Wednesday that Pope Leo XIV appointed Joseph Lin as auxiliary bishop of the Diocese of Fuzhou on June 5, under the agreement, and that the appointment was formalized after civil recognition by the Chinese authorities.
The bilateral pact allows the joint choice of bishops - a competence traditionally reserved for the Pope - but that Beijing considered an internal affairs of the country. The appointment of Lin - who was ordered bishop in 2017 as a member of the so -called clandestine church, faithful to Rome - represents a new step in the complex relationship between the two states, which have not maintained diplomatic ties since 1951.
Since the signing of the agreement, about a dozen episcopal appointments in China have been held, with different levels of coordination between the parties.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:49:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Alibaba | Jack Ma defends restructuring and bets on AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/alibaba-jack-ma-defende-reestruturacao-e-aposta-na-ia/</link><description>Alibaba founder Jack Ma reaffirmed yesterday the strategy of transforming the Chinese giant electronic trade with an investment of $ 52 billion in Artificial Intelligence (AI).
In an internal message for employees and released yesterday by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post Journal, Jack Ma responded to a 15 -year -old dismissal letter, who pointed to "flaws in acquisitions, unfast strategies, questionable signings and unfair performance evaluations."
At 60 and removed from executive functions since 2019, MA stressed that the company is evolving into a “more agile and customer -centered” structure following the reorganization started in 2023, which divided Alibaba into six independent units.
Also considered the group's “spiritual leader”, the entrepreneur argued that AI is a fundamental strategic axis and that Alibaba must lead technological development to “maintain its relevance in the global market”.
The intervention of MA also seeks to reinforce the confidence of the company's approximately 250,000 workers, at a time when Alibaba faces the growing competition of PDD Holdings, operator of the rival Pindumo platform, which registered a 94 percent revenue growth in 2023, against the 9 percent of Alibaba.
In the quarter ended on March 31, Alibaba announced a 7 percent increase in revenues to 236.5 billion Yuan, and a net profit of 12.4 billion Yuan, which represents an increase of 279 percent compared to the same period.
The Cloud Intelligence Group unit, a pillar of the group's AI strategy, has a growth of 18 percent in revenues, which reached 30.1 billion yuan.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:48:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Air India | Plane crashed over buildings with 242 people on board</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/air-india-aviao-despenhou-se-sobre-edificios-com-242-pessoas-a-bordo/</link><description>The plane that fired yesterday in Ahmedabad, west of India, was from Air India and carried 242 people on a flight to London, reported the Indian news agency Press Trust of India (PTI). Seven Portuguese followed on board.
"Flight AI171, which operated Ahmedabad-Londres Gatwick, was involved in an incident today (yesterday), June 12, 2025," the airline said, according to PTI. The plane, a Boeing 787, crashed into a locality near Ahmedabad airport shortly after taking off, police said.
At the time of the closing of this edition, at least 290 dead were confirmed, including passengers and inhabitants of the buildings on which the plane crashed, with only one survivor. The images of local television channels showed smoke leaving the scene of the accident, near Ahmedabad airport.
The plane crashed into a residential area called Meghani Nagar, five minutes after taking off at 1:38 pm, Civil Aviation Director Faiiz Ahmed Kidwai told the US Associated Press (AP) news agency.
Following 230 passengers on board, seven of which Portuguese who are supposed to be dual nationality, and 12 crew members, and emergency teams were activated at the airport, Kidwai said. The 787 Dreamliner is a large twin -engine plane.
Shock
It is the first accident of a Boeing 787, according to the Aviation Safety Network database, added AP. Indian Aviation Minister Ram Mohan Naidu Kinjarapu said he was “shocked and dismayed,” according to France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
"Rescue services are being mobilized and all efforts are being made to ensure that medical teams (…) are sent quickly to the scene," the minister said in a statement. He added that he prayed for "all people on board and their families."
The previous air crash in the country occurred in 2010, when an India Air flight from Dubai drew upon landing in Mangar, southern India, killing 158 people. In 1996, Saudi Flight 763 Airlines collided in full air with the 1907 flight from Kazakhstan Airlines near Nova Delhi. All 349 people aboard the two planes died, becoming the deadliest air collision in history, according to AFP.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:47:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the appropriate place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account] to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
What other projects are in this book?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Yes. The idea of ​​publication, with Barcelona's Actar Books, has to do with putting the work, and more than that, its message, which is very specific to Macau and our way of working in the international and architects community, and this goes a lot through the Biennial. It was also in Europe that a consensus was built on the level of descriptions [in architecture] for a few centuries, and where there is a discussion, national and international, around the issues of the profession. We want our work to be present, either through the book and through acting Books, in this international community, to be part of the world.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through the space narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and I see soon that AI was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
What do you talk about is economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MOTOR EMBALISM | Project for new track in Zhuhai emerges</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/30/automobilismo-surge-projecto-para-nova-pista-em-zhuhai/</link><description>With a very black cloud to turn to the future of the Zhuhai International Circuit, there is a potential good news for the great bay of motoring: a project for a new permanent circuit in the Chinese city adjacent to the MSAR.
According to Hong Kong's Ta Kung Pao newspaper, Guangdong's provincial government recently published the document “Measures to promote high quality tourism and accelerate the construction of a strong tourist province”, which proposes, for the first time, the creation of an “industrial circle of culture and tourism of the Great Bay”, offering political support to the integrated development of culture and tourism in the region. With this, the first industrial and tourist complex of motorized sports in the Great Bay may emerge.
The project of the Zhuhai Chaoyue international circuit was recently presented at the Zhuhai Ocean Spring Resort, located in Doumen, not far from the city's airport, with an initial investment of 250 million Renminbis.
According to the first information, the project of this circuit provides for welcoming evidence such as Formula 3 and foster collaborative development between motorized sports sectors, cultural events and exhibition industry. The plan includes the holding of several international tests per year and foresees collaboration with Hong Kong and Macau to connect cities such as Jiangmen and Zhongshan, promoting “Multiple stops” and boosting the innovative development of “Event Economics + Cultural Tourism”.
According to Zhou Jian, China Travel Service (Zhuhai) Executive Director General Ocean Spring Resort Co., the FIA ​​grade certification-will also include a karting track, drift track and an interior space of 2,400 m² for exhibitions and events related to the automobile sector. With more than 50 international events projected annually, the goal is to become a "super IP" that joins running, leisure and tourism under the same concept.
The first phase of the Zhuhai Chaoyue International Circuit project will include international certification professionals, as well as support facilities. This project aims not only to fill “a gap in the high -end motorized sports sector in Zhuhai, but will also promote the modernization of the Great Bay's cultural, sports and tourist industries by conducting international racing and themed cultural events linked to motorsport.”
Uncertainties in the air
Last summer, the company Malay LBS Bina Group BHD announced that it sold its participation in the Zhuhai International Circuit (ZIC) - the first permanent circuit built in the interior of China - by 124.7 million ringits (about 214.15 million patacas). In a statement to Bursa Malaysia Securities BHD, the group reported that their subsidiary, Dragon Hill Corporation Ltd, sold all his participation in Lamdeal Investments Ltd (Lil) to Huafa Urban Operation (HK) Ltd, a well -known real estate operator. Lil Detinha 60 percent of Zhuhai International Circuit Limited (ZICL), circuit operator.
Raised in 1996 in order to receive the first major award from China from Formula 1 - something that never materialized - ZIC was still the initial motor of motoring in the country and a reference in Asian motorsport. Since its opening, it has welcomed several international evidence, such as the FIA ​​GT, A1 GP or the Intercontinental Le Mans Series. In recent years, track administration has chosen to organize its own events, abdicating the most costly international evidence.
Despite having received, in the past, auto competitions from MSAR, ZIC has been losing protagonism in local motorized sport, due to high prices, limited availability and reducing sports activity in favor of the most profitable commercial activities. The future of the circuit remains uncertain: it is only known that lease agreements between resident teams and the circuit have been frozen and are not being renewed. The track approval will also be about to expire, requiring a new certification to continue to receive competitions in the future.
However, on the weekend of June 14 and 15, the still only circuit of Zhuhai will host the third race of the Formula 4 China Championship season.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 01:53:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao's historicals get a GP clearance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/20/historicos-de-macau-conseguem-apuramento-para-gp/</link><description>The Guangdong International Circuit welcomed, last weekend, the second and decisive double journey of Macao - Macau Road Sport Challenge cars, proof of finding for the most important motor racing of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. In a journey with few celebration reasons for the colors of the sinters, the veterans Jerónimo Badaraco and Rui Valente managed to ensure the qualification.
With a list of 68 subscribers, the grill was divided into two groups, A and B, with all the pilots competing with Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) models. This year, with only one race scheduled for the Grand Prix Program - due to the inclusion of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup - the number of riders was reduced to 36, which placed a supplementary pressure for both missing races. To complicate, the rain came, changing the turns to teams and riders.
In Group A, where Rui Valente faced a complicated weekend on the track around Zhaoqing, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão failed to qualify, in a series dominated by Hong Kong pilots. In Saturday's race, the podium consisted of Wong Chuck Pan, Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping. On Sunday, these three repeated the feat, but with a new order: Lo Pak Yu, Chan Ka Ping and Wong Chuck Pan.
In difficult atmospheric conditions on Saturday, Rui Valente ended only 25th, due to an error in tuning, improving to 15th on Sunday, with the track dry. A penalty after the second race fired him to the 27th place. Still, the 7th place obtained on the first round was enough to secure a place in the Macao Grand Prix.
On the contrary, Maximiano Mannão, behind the wheel of a Toyota with the colors of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended on 26th and 14th, a result below the finding, but it turns out to be positive given that it was Jove Pilot's debut in these wanderings. Célio Alves Dias, with difficulties in his car since the first race, was 24th and 28th, far from the usual level of this experienced Macaense pilot.
Badaraco with final sprint '
On a weekend, where the lively races were broadcast on live streaming in Group B, Hong Kong riders stood out again. On Sunday, Adrian Chung won, with Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin completing the podium. In the second confrontation, Cheang Kin Sang reached a deserved victory, followed again by Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin.
Jerónimo Badaraco came to this challenging weekend without the assured clearance. A modest qualification and 11th Saturday place maintained the open outcome. However, a solid race on Sunday and an excellent 4th place assured veteran Macanese the much desired place on the grid of the Macao Grand Prix, along with countrymen Cheng Kin San, Leong Keng Hei, Lou Check In and Carson Tang.
Also outside the Grand Prix was Dionísio Albino Pereira, who finished 23rd in Saturday's race, but closed the time more forcefully, cutting the line of goal in 13th place in the second race.
At the end of the races, competitors provisionally calculated had an extra technical verification, being forced to open engines and gearbox, to verify the legality of these two decisive organs of their vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-05-20 01:57:43</pubDate></item><item><title>FIA | Conference helped perceive future of motorsport</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/fia-conferencia-ajudou-a-perceber-futuro-do-automobilismo/</link><description>For the first time in its history, in 2025, Macau welcomed the Extraordinary General Assemblies and Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). Organized in partnership with the Macau-China General Association (AAMC), the FIA-affiliated sports territory, and Galaxy Entertainment Group, this event brought together more than five dozen FIA senior delegates from 147 countries in the field.
 
In the Galaxy International Convention Center, to this day, the future of motoring and mobility worldwide is discussed. However, some details about the future of sport in the territory have already been revealed between the lines. Focused on obtaining information about the growth of motorsport and promoting safe, sustainable and accessible mobility to everyone in the Asia Pacific region, the FIA ​​conference opening session highlighted the importance of communication and collaboration, as well as the region's ability to innovate and create solutions that respond to specific questions it faces.
Roberto Carlos Osório, president of the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), said the association has a strong tradition in motor racing and that following FIA's guidelines is being able to grow rapidly competition at the base level in the region.
“We organized the first GT Macau Cup in 2008,” said the AAMC leader. "Currently, we also have the GT Cup - Great Bay Race for GT4 cars. In addition, in 2008, we created Road Sport Challenge," he explained. “And today, in 2025, we are proud to announce that we have 68 tourism cars in the region to compete in the qualification race to enter the 72nd Macao Grand Prix.”
In a year when AAMC celebrates 30 years of existence - was born as Macao Automobile Club - we also learned that the association's bet for the future will be in the basic disciplines of motor sport. Roberto Carlos Osorio also revealed a curious fact: Macau has 135 pilots with sports license from the territory.
“This growth was achieved following FIA's guidelines to promote grassroots motorsport and create accessible races for riders in the region,” added the manager of the territory. “With the interest of pilots, teams and promoters in developing state-of-the-art activities in Macau, we will focus even more on base competitions and affordable races, not only to support tourism, but also to make Macau in a Karting international center of international events, where champions can be selected for F4 and, later, for regional formula.”
Confirmed GP program
The Macao Grand Prix Organizing Committee (COGPM) held a press conference on June 8 at the Macao Grand Prix Museum to confirm the 72nd Macao Grand Program races, which will take place from November 13 to 16 this year.
As last year, there will be seven races in total, respectively, the Macao Grand Prix - FR da Fia World Cup, the GT Macau Cup - GT da Fia World Cup, the Macau Guide Race - Kumho Fia tcr World Tour Event of Macau, the Formula 4 Formula 4 World Cup, the 57th Macao Motor Motor Prize, GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4) and Macao Roadsport Challenge. For the first time, the guide circuit receives four different cups under the FIA ​​seal on the same weekend.
Other news
Between meetings and communications, other information was revealed about the November edition of the Macao Grand Prix. The FIA ​​World Council approved in Macao that the winner of the first Formula 4 World Cup of the FIA ​​will receive two points for the super license. We have also noticed that Pirelli will equip all the monologes that participate in both the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup and the FIA ​​regional formula World Formula Cup. In turn, the supply of tires and fuel to the FIA ​​GT World Cup remains in the contest phase.
Registration for the Formula 4 World Cup will be open until July 30. The final selection of 20 pilots will be confirmed by the FIA ​​through an official invitation letter, taking into account the current classification of the pilots in the respective championships.
In the case of the FIA ​​Regional Formula World Cup, registrations will also remain open until July 30, and the grill will be able to host a maximum of 27 Tatuus regional formula -equipped with alpha Romeo engines built by the autotechnic. As with Formula 4, participation will be by invitation, with priority assigned to pilots who have reached the best positions in the five regional formula championships of 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:43:57</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Jaguar that won in Macau in 1984 returned to the tracks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/gp-jaguar-que-venceu-em-macau-em-1984-regressou-as-pistas/</link><description>The more than seventy years of history of the Macau Grand Prix are people, machines and great moments. We were in 1984, when Tom Walkinshaw won Jaguar's only victory in the guide race. After years away from the audience, for the affected man, this same car returned to the tracks at the hands of an enthusiast of the MSAR MOTOR EVENT
 
Richard Meins, an English maritime transport entrepreneur who lived many years in Hong Kong, who participated on several occasions at the Macao Grand Prix, led this Jaguar XJs of Group A in the Historic Touring Car Challenge race, a competition for classics during the Donington Historic Festival. This “Big Cat”, Chassis No. 5 and one of the four original XJs still existing, is practically as it was in 1984, but given the limitations of tobacco advertising, today boasts the colors used in the European Tourism Championship, instead of the iconic black and gold decoration of John Player Special (JPS) that marked the ticket through the guide circuit.
Interestingly, this return to the clues, from a car that has been still in New Zealand and Japan, was scheduled for the Algarve International Race Track, but the Historic Touring Car Challenge canceled its race in early April in Portimão. So it was in lands of his majesty that Richard Meins made his first race with the British car.
“The car won in Macao in 1984, so I'm a big fan of this model,” Ricard Meins told the English magazine Motorsport News. “I still have the photographs I took this weekend in Macao,” said this avid classic competition car collector who, besides driving, supported several riders at the Macao Grand Prix.
In Donington Park, Richard Meins shared the imposing Jaguar XJS, equipped with a 5.3 -liter V12 engine with Jack Tetley, and ended in sixth place, winning in his class. Richard Meins had only guided the car once or twice, but plans to participate in more historic touring car challenge rounds with XJS 1984. “Let's try to put it on track more often now,” Ricard Meins said, who revealed that he was a stake in the Silverstone Festival in August with this very rare and striking copy of the 1980s tourism cars history.
Premiere of an iconic decoration
In the summer of 1984, Tom Walkinshaw accepted the challenge of the Portuguese organization of the Grand Prix to travel later this year to Macau. With the European title in his pocket, the English driver and team boss was accompanied by one of his usual riders, German Hans Heyer. The guide race was a BMW fiefdom and the controversial English wanted to put an end to the Bavarian domain in the race. To this end, it had the precious support of JPS, which was relaunching the brand, decorating its cars with the famous black and gold colors that would later be eternalized in Ayrton Senna's Lotus. At the time, the guide race took place three weeks before 1000 km from Bathurst, another important race on the worldwide calendar of tourist racing, and so TWR made a "two in one."
The 100 -mile race on the streets of Macau would not have much history, such as the cars built in the Kidlington workshops against the competition headed by the two BMW 635i Schnitzer officers, guided by Hans Stuck and Dieter Quester, and painted by rival Marlboro. Tom Walkinshaw ended first and Hans Heyer and m second.
At the end of the race, quoted by the Portuguese newspaper Autosport, Tom Walkinshaw said: “The circuit is fantastic. Tight, but with many curves, climbs and descents, which made the race become difficult. But I like difficult things and, for me, the race was great from beginning to end.
The Jaguar were again invited by the Macao Grand Prix committee to run in 1985, but Tom Walkinshaw had other plans for his cars. Fortunately, thanks to Richard Meins we will continue to see this beautiful car on the tracks.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Council of Motorsport approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and a MSAR test enthusiast, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The growth and development potential in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into detail, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula cup last year, says that “this big step will undoubtedly benefit local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item></channel></rss>