<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>South Sea | Beijing discovers large oil deposit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/mar-do-sul-pequim-descobre-grande-jazida-de-petroleo/</link><description>Chinese oil company Cnooc discovered an important oil field in the east of the Southern Sea of ​​China, with proven reserves of over 100 million tons, the state press said yesterday.
According to Chinese official news agency Xinhua, the identified field, Huizhou 19-6, is about 170 kilometers from the city of Shenzhen in the south of the country. Test drilling produced 413 barrels of raw and 68,000 cubic meters of natural gas per day, according to the same source.
Proven reservations of the oil field, ie the amount of hydrocarbons whose recovery can be almost certainly estimated using current techniques, ascend to more than 100 million tons, according to the information cited by Xinhua.
Southern China's underground is largely sub-pitched due to territorial disputes, but most known oil and gas deposits are in non-contested areas, according to the US energy information administration.
Beijing claims the sovereignty of almost the whole sea, over which the Philippines, Malaysia, Vietnam, Indonesia and Brunei also have claims.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Litiges | Deputies want more transparency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/litigios-deputados-querem-mais-transparencia/</link><description>The 3rd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly was discussing the future conciliation regime for family causes, which aims to create a mechanism to avoid the appellates in the event of divorce disputes, exercise of paternal power, food provision or issues related to the family home.
After the working meeting, the committee chairman, Deputy Vong Hin Fai, indicated, based on the executive's explanations, that family conciliators will belong to private institutions and will be chosen by the Institute of Social Action (IAS). In the IAS current list, about 30 community service centers of local associations and 2,000 social workers can be chosen for conciliation.
According to the statements cited by the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, during the working meeting, the committee deputies were concerned about the IAS criteria, as they argue that it is necessary to ensure independence, transparency and rationality not only of the conciliator but also the selection process. Therefore, they expect this aspect to be clarified.
On the other hand, in relation to the litigious divorce, the law defines that the party that intends to request divorce has a period of three years to advance to the courts, after the facts that justify the request. Deputies consider that the count of this period must be suspended, while the conciliation period takes place.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:12:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Tui reduces resident sentence for fatal crime in Zhuhai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/tui-reduz-pena-de-residente-por-crime-fatal-em-zhuhai/</link><description>The last court (TUI) decided to reduce the penalty of a 44 -year -old resident in August 2023 for killing another resident in Zhuhai. It all happened on a night of night fun that ended the worst way, in the Gongbei area, and the two men began to argue on the street when the murderer decided to attack the other resident with two scissors blows.
The Base Judicial Court (TJB) sentenced the resident to an effective 15 -year prison for the practice, in material authorship and in a consummate form, of a crime of homicide. In addition, the resident was ordered to pay compensation of more than two million patacas to the widow, with interest. It was then that the murderer decided to appeal to the court of second instance, because he did not agree with the sentence, and Tui has now reduced this sentence to 13 years and nine months.
Unintentionally “direct”
According to the TUI judgment, the murderer requested the reduction of the sentence claiming that it was under the influence of alcohol and did not know that scissors could effectively kill the other resident. In addition, the applicant claimed that the police had been called before assaulting the man with the scissors. However, Tui understands that "such circumstances are not valid and effective to exclude their guilt as to conduct and its responsibility."
Tui understands that a situation of "eventual deceit" is at stake and not a "direct" intention of killing the other, so it was possible to be possible "a moderate reduction in the penalty".
The details of the case are described in the ruling: the two men were, around 12:02 am on July 31, 2023 eating with the deceased's wife and seven friends, and the murderer drank “three to four beer bottles”, some of them gone to play Mahjong to follow. The discussion between the two men took place around 3:50 am "for trivial reasons", becoming "increasingly serious."
Friends tried to separate them unsuccessfully. Around four in the morning, the murderer “abandoned Mahjong's establishment, running, took a scissors from a fruit store with which he gave several blows to the left side of his left -handed chest, arm and forearm and thumb of the left hand” of the deceased. The death was declared at 4:15 am by the Zhuhai Public Security Police. The perpetrator was arrested at the entrance of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinematheque | “Flow”, Oscar winner, prominently in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/cinemateca-flow-vencedor-do-oscar-em-destaque-no-mes-de-abril/</link><description>“April charms” is there, with a new movie selection to see this month at Cinemateca Paixão. Highlight for “Flow - to Deriva”, which won the Oscar for Best Animation Movie this year, as well as “Dog on Trial” or “Four Trails”, among others
 
A bright black kitten tries to survive the flood of the world he knows. Suddenly, you have to share the space of a boat with other animals of completely different species, and ensure they live. “Flow - to Deriva” is a lesson of humanity and, perhaps, a reflection on climate change, depending on their eyes. It can now be seen at Cinemateca Paixão, starting this Friday, having three other sessions scheduled.
Gints Zilbalodis's “Flow - Flow” is a production of Latvia that surprised the half world and the Hollywood Academy, having won the Oscar for best animated film. The film's initial budget was US $ 3.6 million and its success surprised even the author of the film.
"We thought that at best we would be selected for some festivals and would have a good season of festivals," Zilbalodis, 30, told France-Presse (AFP). For Latvia, the two Oscar nominations were historical, as no movie in the Baltic country of only 1.8 million inhabitants had played an Oscar.
But "April charms" continues with other stories, already outside the world of animation. One of them is “dog on trial”, which can be seen from this Thursday. It is an out-of-vulgar story in which an Avril lawyer defends a dog in the court bar. The film eventually reveals comic and at the same time dramatic episodes around issues such as the judicial system, the rights of women and the animals themselves.
Adventures in Paris
Following is “Grand Maison Paris”, a Japanese movie spent in the French capital. The first session takes place today at 7:30 pm, followed by two more display dates. The story revolves around the opening of a Paris restaurant called "Grand Maison Paris", after the success obtained with the three -star Michelin winner "Grand Maison Tokyo."
Natsuki Obana and Rinko Hayami then ventured in Paris, wanting to be the first Asian bosses to get Michelin stars in the light city, but the challenges they face make adventure a much harder task than they thought. The protagonists must also deal with the pressure of a city full of well -known chiefs of French cuisine.
Another film, of the genre documentary, which can be seen from tomorrow is "Four Trails", although all the screening sessions are already sold out. This is a real story, that of Andre Blumberg, who left alone to run the four long distance iconic tracks from Hong Kong in just 72 hours. It's 298 kilometers, and over 14,500 meters unevenly later, one of the most difficult marathons in the world, with the name "Hong Kong Four Trails Ultra Challenge" was created. The documentary thus portrays the 2021 edition of this competition.
Inside the Asian films list is “Montages of A Modern Motherhood,” a Hong Kong movie this year, which will be screened on April 15 and 27. It is the story of Suk-Jing, which welcomes a baby daughter in your life, and that will never be the same. Speak Suk-Jing realizes that the day is too small for everything she has to do, complaining that her husband does not help her in this new maternity task. Family family dramas and reflections on the need for better days begin.
Within another section, “Ater Style-Double functionality”, the British director Mike Leigh's film on family ethics is also presented this Friday. The story revolves around the nervous pansy, with contrasting psychological behavior in the face of his sister, younger and more relaxed. In this movie, one can explore family relationships and the difficulties that exist to sometimes maintain harmony in these connections.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:24:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Takeaway | Up to 50% tariffs threaten restoration</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/takeaway-tarifas-de-ate-50-ameacam-restauracao/</link><description>Home food delivery applications touched the restoration sector to the wall, imposing high delivery rates and changing customer habits. The Macao Catering Industry Association says APPs threaten business survival and calls for government intervention
 
When the COVID-19 pandemic forced social isolation and distancing, the mere act of taking a meal away from home became a nightmare. From this time, it became common to see the Macao roads full of MFood and Aomi scooters, and later to Tikbee. Finding the restrictions on combating pandemic, remained the habit of asking for meals, drinks and desserts through these platforms, and complaints from the restoration sector began to emerge.
The president of the Macao Catering Industry Association, Aeson Law, has been one of the critical voices of how applications have changed the industry and forced restaurants to pay high delivery fees or abdicate a popular way to do business.
"When there were no Takeaway platforms, if we faced 100 patacas, this value entered the box. Nowadays we even delivered 50 of these 100 patacas to applications, as well as the operating costs of a restaurant. It is difficult to survive in this scenario," said the representative, quoted by the citizen newspaper.
The associative leader recalls that meal delivery platforms began by charging more than 20 percent of the amount charged to the customer as a distribution tariff, which considered reasonable. However, "apps also started charging distribution or delivery tariff to customers," he said, raising prices. As such, they ended up “asking traders to pay the slice that should be paid by the consumer,” he said.
Do something
Aeson Law does not realize why applications have been charging twice distribution rates. The fact is that restaurants are required to pay twice if they want to occupy a summit place in the ranking of applications.
With the double collection, the applications are about 40 percent of the online sales of restaurants, a slice that grows to 50 percent during discount campaigns. Aeason Law considers that the only way to control excessive charges is through government intervention, as restaurants do not have negotiating power to cope with the prevalence of online platforms.
Thus, the representative of the sector expects the executive to elaborate a law that will introduce a mechanism for supervising the online platform action and complaint presentation.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:17:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Islands Hospital | Extended aesthetic and vaccine services</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/hospital-das-ilhas-alargados-servicos-de-estetica-e-de-vacinas/</link><description>The director of health services, Alvis Lo, states that throughout this year will be expanded the aesthetic services and external vaccination consultations of the islands hospital. The future also undergoes cooperation with dealers to bet on more health tourism services
 
The availability of aesthetic and vaccine services abroad at Hospital das Ilhas will be extended throughout this year. The confirmation of the new services came from Alvis Lo, director of health services, and is the response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U.
The availability of these services is part of the government's strategy to bet on health tourism, presented as Big Health. As part of this strategy, Alvis Lo explains that the Islands Hospital will “take full advantage of the notoriety of the Peking Union Medical College Hospital brand”, which explores the services available, not only at the level of services provided, but also to collaborate in terms of research and health partnerships.
Regarding the services provided, Alvis Lo points out that aesthetics and external vaccines services are currently available. Regarding the area of ​​aesthetics, the doctor points out that "the initial focus lies in facial rejuvenation" is being performed with "resort to the most advanced medical equipment of Hong Kong and Macau". In this service, it is also indicated that “16 therapeutic projects” are being implemented, including using “Picosecond laser” technologies and “radio -ferotement microagulating”.
Regarding vaccination, it is indicated that the islands hospital offers five types of vaccines abroad among which the Nanavalent Vaccine against Human Papillomavirus (HPV), the zoster herpes vaccine and the pneumococcal vaccine.
Expansion of services
Throughout this year, Alvis Lo also points out that the Islands Hospital will “further expand the supply of aesthetic and vaccination medicine projects” and create “new specific external consultation services”, such as “weight loss consultations and cancer prevention”.
In the future, Alvis Lo indicates that the path will progressively implement “private ward services” and “Individual Health Management Projects” to achieve “constant progress in medical tourism and Big Health industry”.
On the other hand, the doctor indicates that the islands hospital is “attracting more and more tourists to visit Macau” to receive “medical care and health care”.
In addition, in response to Chan U law it is indicated that tourism services will launch other “medical tourism services, actively promoting cooperation between the Macao tourist sector and the various integrated tourism and leisure companies for the development of tourist products focused on medical care, well-being and therapeutic food”. Alvis Lo points out will also be “launched several accommodation promotions and the promotion [of medical services] will be intensified with the target markets”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:15:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Song Pek Kei asks for subsidies to pay interest</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/habitacao-song-pek-kei-pede-subsidios-para-pagar-juros/</link><description>The deputy linked to the Fujian community wants the “healthy development” of the real estate market and asks the government to provide more land to build quality houses, and counteract the recent trend
 
Representative Song Pek Kei argues that the government must make a subsidy available to residents who ended up in the purchase of housing to help them pay interest on the contracted loans. The measure arises in a written interpellation of a deputy linked to the community of Fujian.
In the logic of the legislator, it is necessary to finance the payment of loans from those who buy home because the real estate market has a “weak development”, while “consumer power has weakened even more”. "The real estate market in Macau is still relatively slow and the Malparado credit ratio has reached a record level, which affected the stable development of the financial market," he warns.
The deputy considers that the reduction in housing prices in recent years should be a concern of society, because it is happening at a time when there is still demand, especially among the younger ones. Therefore, Song wants the government to subsidize the payment of interest on loans, when their amount does not exceed 4 percent.
The interest bonus measurement in the purchase of housing in force in Macao in the past, especially in the 1990s and at the beginning of the establishment of the MSAR. In 2001, the measure covered dwellings that were bought for a value of less than 750 thousand patacas. Song Pek Kei considers that this measure was “very successive” and asks for repetition.
In an interpeação in which the focus of the deputy is the youngest, the deputy close to Ung Choi Kun, former deputy for the Fujian community and one of the main local voices of real estate interests, also calls for changes in the exemption from the payment of the Seal Tax.
Poor housing
Song Pek Kei also acknowledges that the construction of latest housing at MSA has created a problem of lack of habitability conditions. According to the deputy, the latest buildings, built as studios or as apartments where there are no divisions demarcated by walls between the living room and the only room, offer decent conditions for residents. "Although there is a certain amount of residential apartments in Macao, there are structural problems in offering good apartments, which is due to the small dimension," he says.
Song Pek Kei also recognizes that old housing is more quality than the recent and asks the executive to use the land reserve to allow more construction, this time with the quality that has not been guaranteed in recent years. “The Government of MSAR has a certain land reserve, will management accelerate its planning and adjust the relationship of the supply structure to provide better apartments that satisfy market demand and improve the quality of life of residents?” He asks.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:13:59</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | Government Action Lines presented on April 14</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/al-linhas-de-accao-governativa-apresentadas-a-14-de-abril/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai presents to 14 April the first lines of governing action of its Executive. The next day, the Chief Executive returns to the Legislative Assembly to answer the questions of the deputies. Between April 17 and 30, will be discussed the sectoral governing directions, starting with administration and justice and ending in transport and public works
 
After several months of collecting suggestions between local associations, the President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, the deputies called the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for the Chief Executive for the Financial Year of 2025 on April 14, at 15h. Shortly after the presentation to the Plenary, follows the press conference at 5:30 pm at the Government headquarters, during which Sam Hou Fai will respond to the questions of the Social Communication.
The call signed by Kou Hoi In adds that the next day, as is tradition, Sam Hou Fai returns to Al to answer the deputies' questions about the LAG report, between 15h and 18h. Deputies have to deliver questions to the Question and Answer Session until 6:30 pm on April 14, that is, scarce hours after the first lag of the executive led by Sam Hou Fai.
Let's go by parts
Also, as is tradition, the presentation of the LAG report in the Plenary, the press conference that follows at the Government headquarters and the return of Sam Hou Fai to AL the next day to the deputies' questions and answers session will be broadcast live on TDM, both on television and on the radio.
The public will also be able to attend the broadcast through the internet in real time, the official portals of the government, the office of the Chief Executive, the al, the media of Social Communication (GCS) and in a thematic portal created for the purpose. In addition to the various apps of the executive, sessions can also be seen in the exclusive YouTube channel of the Chief Executive and GCS's Office and on the GCS Facebook page.
The Executive's General and Sectorial Program for the Fiscal Year 2025 will still be published online, as well as in Social Communication.
Following the presentation of the general guiding lines of the governance work, the sectoral debates are followed in the AL, between April 17 and 30. André Cheong is the first secretary to debate the LAG of the Administration and Justice area on April 17. On April 23, Tai Kin IP debuts to present the lag to the economy and finance. Two days later it is Wong Sio Chak's turn to debate with deputies the governing direction of the security area, something that has been doing annually since 2015.
The last two debates have as protagonists two newcomers, on April 28 LAM discusses the LAG of the Social and Culture Affairs area and on April 30, closing, Raymond Tam will debate in the plenary as the LAG of the transport and public works sector.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:10:19</pubDate></item><item><title>José Paulo Esperança, Associate Rector of the City of Macau University: “Languages ​​cannot be controlled”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/jose-paulo-esperanca-reitor-associado-da-universidade-cidade-de-macau-as-linguas-nao-podem-ser-controladas/</link><description>Co-author of the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with Luís Reto and Fernando Luís Machado, José Paulo Esperança reveals to HM that the work edited in 2016 and 2018 is being updated, especially due to the growing global value of the language. The Associate Rector and Professor of the City of Macao University suggests partnerships with Macau under the Editorial Project
 
Launched the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, in co-authorship, about the global value of the language. Plan a new edition or update?
Undoubtedly. We are working in this regard, there was a recent conference in Macao and Professor Luís Reto, former Rector of ISCTE, presented some more current elements that were developed. He has worked on a very important issue, which is the role of Portuguese as a frank language, which was for a few centuries in Asia. The exchange between Dutch and the kingdom of Zion was made in Portuguese, because it was the common language used at that time, before English became the contemporary frank language. Therefore, there is a whole interesting story of Portuguese and the role it had in the first pinyins that existed, with the Chinese and the use of the [Roman] alphabet in Vietname. There are a number of elements that are not, therefore, very publicized, and the work of Atlas is the same, to disclose some economic dimensions of the language.
What are these dimensions?
One is the exchange of foreign trade and investment, which is very facilitated by the language. We also talk about migrations, tourism, students' exchange that is greatly influenced by linguistic proximity. Therefore, today we have a set of elements that are very interesting, and we hope to develop some more important partnerships with Macau.
As?
More at work, Professor Luís Reto is doing, which maintains an investigation team about the value of Portuguese. He has collaborated with the Portuguese Language Museum of São Paulo, for example. It is a museum space that was renewed after the fire that destroyed it. In addition, there is a project with Cascais City Council to develop such a structure, and we hope to do some works with Macau, in order to create three poles for the projection of the Portuguese language. As for Atlas' materials, we would like to have a continued update model, as this data is out of date very quickly. The work was edited in many languages, including Mandarin. This is the moment when we would like to give the book a more historical and deep dimension, with more knowledge about the teaching of Portuguese in the world.
What balance does this teaching do today?
Portuguese is developing a great deal of mother tongue and is effectively one of the most expanding languages ​​due to demographic growth in Africa, with countries such as Angola and Mozambique, which around 2050 will have populations of over 100 million inhabitants, each. The Portuguese thus consolidates itself as a language of the southern hemisphere, but much more from Africa, supplanting Brazil itself as the place of largest number of speakers of the language. All of this generates enormous potential, and this also occurs due to the great exchange of universities and internationalization of teaching. Today there is the possibility of Portuguese being a language of science, there is more publications in this language. This is a great challenge because English is the contemporary language of scientists. We want to contribute to all these dimensions, and Macau can also play an important role there. Macao is indeed a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and can play a significant role.
Is Macao an ideal place to train Portuguese teachers who do not have Portuguese as a mother tongue? Do you fear that the territory loses relevance in this matter before the offer of courses in the interior of China?
I see this question more as complementarity than competition. We have identified about 60 higher education institutions in China that have Portuguese courses, but I think Macau has very interesting conditions to start teaching from primary to secondary education so that children have been able to have learning from an early age. It does not mean that there are no young Chinese who began to learn their tongue in adolescence that they speak fantastically, which surprises me, but it is easier to start earlier and earlier. This will be easier in Macau. What is important is to create conditions for greater economic collaboration to many levels, such as joint research. In this respect, Macau has a very interesting opportunity. At the City of Macau University we are very interested in increasingly collaborating with researchers who visit us and work with our teams.
Can you give me examples?
Brazil is today one of China's great business partners. There is a lot of exchange in both directions, but one of the themes that is little studied, and in which I work hard, is the internationalization of Chinese companies. To what extent do these companies follow a model of internationalization similar to that of other countries that started this process earlier? I speak of the United States of America, the European countries, but also of Japan and others. China has, in fact, different models of presence in countries that are not yet well known, and this is important to realize, so that we know how to facilitate this process of exchange in a world that lives periods of some setback. It is very sad. I always remember a great economist of Portuguese origin, David Ricardo, who clearly explained how world trade is beneficial to everyone and how countries can take advantage of this situation. Therefore, applying tariffs, making such commercial barriers harms countries that are major exporters, such as China or Germany, and countries that today have a cultural export capacity, for example, and are not just importers.
In relation to the new Orthographic Agreement. It continues without a standardization in Macau. Does it worry it?
Languages ​​are dynamic and cannot be controlled. We think today in English, and we realize that there are almost incomprehensible ways to each other, such as the English one in Nigeria or Australia. Americans have difficulty realizing the Australians. In the nineteenth century, Portuguese from Portugal and Brazil were closer, then some disagreement emerged. There was an effort in Brazil to propose an orthographic agreement, and the Portuguese joined, resulting in a series of negotiations. There have always been resistances. I remember that Fernando Pessoa suggested the famous phrase “My homeland is the Portuguese language”. It was curiously a manifestation of some conservatism, because he thought Pharmacy had to continue writing with pH [Pharmacia]. In fact it did not make much sense. Portugal ended up seeking to impose a certain standardization based on the most genetic changes in the spelling agreement. It is not a process that has been running a hundred percent well, and has been universally adopted. African countries have become more defenders of Portuguese from Portugal. There is sometimes some confusion, but I understand that intercomprehension still remains, achieving a homogeneous language, more perhaps than English.
 
Between words and numbers
José Paulo Esperança is a doctorate in Economics from the European University Institute and was president of the ISCTE Department of Finance and Accounting - University Institute of Lisbon. The “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with editions in 2016 and 2018, contains “a large set of indicators that reinforce the idea of ​​the growth of teaching, speakers and the written use of Portuguese in the world”, having been the target of a series of recent initiatives in Macao.
One of them took place on March 17, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, with a session of the “Roda de Ideas” cycle, entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, which was attended by the former ISCTE Rector, Luís Reto, and José Paulo Hope himself. In addition to the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, José Paulo Esperança is the author of other works in the financial area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:08:41</pubDate></item><item><title>South Sea | Beijing discovers large oil deposit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/mar-do-sul-pequim-descobre-grande-jazida-de-petroleo/</link><description>Chinese oil company Cnooc discovered an important oil field in the east of the Southern Sea of ​​China, with proven reserves of over 100 million tons, the state press said yesterday.
According to Chinese official news agency Xinhua, the identified field, Huizhou 19-6, is about 170 kilometers from the city of Shenzhen in the south of the country. Test drilling produced 413 barrels of raw and 68,000 cubic meters of natural gas per day, according to the same source.
Proven reservations of the oil field, ie the amount of hydrocarbons whose recovery can be almost certainly estimated using current techniques, ascend to more than 100 million tons, according to the information cited by Xinhua.
Southern China's underground is largely sub-pitched due to territorial disputes, but most known oil and gas deposits are in non-contested areas, according to the US energy information administration.
Beijing claims the sovereignty of almost the whole sea, over which the Philippines, Malaysia, Vietnam, Indonesia and Brunei also have claims.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Litiges | Deputies want more transparency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/litigios-deputados-querem-mais-transparencia/</link><description>The 3rd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly was discussing the future conciliation regime for family causes, which aims to create a mechanism to avoid the appellates in the event of divorce disputes, exercise of paternal power, food provision or issues related to the family home.
After the working meeting, the committee chairman, Deputy Vong Hin Fai, indicated, based on the executive's explanations, that family conciliators will belong to private institutions and will be chosen by the Institute of Social Action (IAS). In the IAS current list, about 30 community service centers of local associations and 2,000 social workers can be chosen for conciliation.
According to the statements cited by the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, during the working meeting, the committee deputies were concerned about the IAS criteria, as they argue that it is necessary to ensure independence, transparency and rationality not only of the conciliator but also the selection process. Therefore, they expect this aspect to be clarified.
On the other hand, in relation to the litigious divorce, the law defines that the party that intends to request divorce has a period of three years to advance to the courts, after the facts that justify the request. Deputies consider that the count of this period must be suspended, while the conciliation period takes place.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:12:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Tui reduces resident sentence for fatal crime in Zhuhai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/tui-reduz-pena-de-residente-por-crime-fatal-em-zhuhai/</link><description>The last court (TUI) decided to reduce the penalty of a 44 -year -old resident in August 2023 for killing another resident in Zhuhai. It all happened on a night of night fun that ended the worst way, in the Gongbei area, and the two men began to argue on the street when the murderer decided to attack the other resident with two scissors blows.
The Base Judicial Court (TJB) sentenced the resident to an effective 15 -year prison for the practice, in material authorship and in a consummate form, of a crime of homicide. In addition, the resident was ordered to pay compensation of more than two million patacas to the widow, with interest. It was then that the murderer decided to appeal to the court of second instance, because he did not agree with the sentence, and Tui has now reduced this sentence to 13 years and nine months.
Unintentionally “direct”
According to the TUI judgment, the murderer requested the reduction of the sentence claiming that it was under the influence of alcohol and did not know that scissors could effectively kill the other resident. In addition, the applicant claimed that the police had been called before assaulting the man with the scissors. However, Tui understands that "such circumstances are not valid and effective to exclude their guilt as to conduct and its responsibility."
Tui understands that a situation of "eventual deceit" is at stake and not a "direct" intention of killing the other, so it was possible to be possible "a moderate reduction in the penalty".
The details of the case are described in the ruling: the two men were, around 12:02 am on July 31, 2023 eating with the deceased's wife and seven friends, and the murderer drank “three to four beer bottles”, some of them gone to play Mahjong to follow. The discussion between the two men took place around 3:50 am "for trivial reasons", becoming "increasingly serious."
Friends tried to separate them unsuccessfully. Around four in the morning, the murderer “abandoned Mahjong's establishment, running, took a scissors from a fruit store with which he gave several blows to the left side of his left -handed chest, arm and forearm and thumb of the left hand” of the deceased. The death was declared at 4:15 am by the Zhuhai Public Security Police. The perpetrator was arrested at the entrance of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinematheque | “Flow”, Oscar winner, prominently in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/cinemateca-flow-vencedor-do-oscar-em-destaque-no-mes-de-abril/</link><description>“April charms” is there, with a new movie selection to see this month at Cinemateca Paixão. Highlight for “Flow - to Deriva”, which won the Oscar for Best Animation Movie this year, as well as “Dog on Trial” or “Four Trails”, among others
 
A bright black kitten tries to survive the flood of the world he knows. Suddenly, you have to share the space of a boat with other animals of completely different species, and ensure they live. “Flow - to Deriva” is a lesson of humanity and, perhaps, a reflection on climate change, depending on their eyes. It can now be seen at Cinemateca Paixão, starting this Friday, having three other sessions scheduled.
Gints Zilbalodis's “Flow - Flow” is a production of Latvia that surprised the half world and the Hollywood Academy, having won the Oscar for best animated film. The film's initial budget was US $ 3.6 million and its success surprised even the author of the film.
"We thought that at best we would be selected for some festivals and would have a good season of festivals," Zilbalodis, 30, told France-Presse (AFP). For Latvia, the two Oscar nominations were historical, as no movie in the Baltic country of only 1.8 million inhabitants had played an Oscar.
But "April charms" continues with other stories, already outside the world of animation. One of them is “dog on trial”, which can be seen from this Thursday. It is an out-of-vulgar story in which an Avril lawyer defends a dog in the court bar. The film eventually reveals comic and at the same time dramatic episodes around issues such as the judicial system, the rights of women and the animals themselves.
Adventures in Paris
Following is “Grand Maison Paris”, a Japanese movie spent in the French capital. The first session takes place today at 7:30 pm, followed by two more display dates. The story revolves around the opening of a Paris restaurant called "Grand Maison Paris", after the success obtained with the three -star Michelin winner "Grand Maison Tokyo."
Natsuki Obana and Rinko Hayami then ventured in Paris, wanting to be the first Asian bosses to get Michelin stars in the light city, but the challenges they face make adventure a much harder task than they thought. The protagonists must also deal with the pressure of a city full of well -known chiefs of French cuisine.
Another film, of the genre documentary, which can be seen from tomorrow is "Four Trails", although all the screening sessions are already sold out. This is a real story, that of Andre Blumberg, who left alone to run the four long distance iconic tracks from Hong Kong in just 72 hours. It's 298 kilometers, and over 14,500 meters unevenly later, one of the most difficult marathons in the world, with the name "Hong Kong Four Trails Ultra Challenge" was created. The documentary thus portrays the 2021 edition of this competition.
Inside the Asian films list is “Montages of A Modern Motherhood,” a Hong Kong movie this year, which will be screened on April 15 and 27. It is the story of Suk-Jing, which welcomes a baby daughter in your life, and that will never be the same. Speak Suk-Jing realizes that the day is too small for everything she has to do, complaining that her husband does not help her in this new maternity task. Family family dramas and reflections on the need for better days begin.
Within another section, “Ater Style-Double functionality”, the British director Mike Leigh's film on family ethics is also presented this Friday. The story revolves around the nervous pansy, with contrasting psychological behavior in the face of his sister, younger and more relaxed. In this movie, one can explore family relationships and the difficulties that exist to sometimes maintain harmony in these connections.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:24:39</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean artist Shin Min wins first edition of “MGM Discoveries”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/artista-sul-coreana-shin-min-vence-primeira-edicao-do-mgm-discoveries/</link><description>Shin Min, South Korean artist, was the winner of the first edition of the MGM Discoveries Art Award, awarded together by MGM and Art Basel de Hong Kong. According to a MGM statement, the artist, represented by Seoul's P21 gallery, won with an “innovative installation”, named “Ew! There is Hair in the Food !!!”, in which he used “a powerful symbolism and personal experiences to confront social norms and systemic injustices”.
According to the same note, Shin Min "expects this work to serve as a powerful tool to sensitize society and ultimately improve the working conditions of the population." The prize includes a monetary value of $ 50,000 and the "opportunity to be invited by MGM to hold an exhibition and participate in artistic exchanges in Macao."
The objective of the “MGM Discoveries” award is “to promote artistic diversity and connect Hong Kong, Macau and the world through iconic cultural events”, and this initiative “recognizes the originality and innovation of emerging international artists”, as well as “expanding their visibility in the global art world”.
Shared views
Kenneth Feng, president and executive director of MGM China Holdings Limited, said “MGM and Art Basel Hong Kong share the common vision of promoting global artistic and cultural development”, and this joint award “is a commitment to discovering emerging artists and celebrating its originality and creativity, offering a platform to develop its potential and grow”.
"In addition, through international cultural efforts, Macau is closely united with Hong Kong and the global stage, expanding the global network and the exchange of Macao," said the official.
Angelle Siyang-Le, director of Art Basel Hong Kong, said that the jury chose "Shin Min from a remarkable set of artists presented in the" Sector Discoveries ", which highlights emerging artists and galleries through individual presentations of recent projects."
MGM also organized a guided tour of Art Basel de Hong Kong, one of the most important art fairs in the world, for about 50 Macao's cultural and educational representatives. With this award, the game operator says she wants to “bring new artistic perspectives to Macau and the Great Bay”, as well as “a variety of international artistic and cultural activities”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 06:02:45</pubDate></item><item><title>XI Jinping stimulates investment in meeting with foreign entrepreneurs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/xi-jinping-estimula-investimento-em-encontro-com-empreendedores-estrangeiros/</link><description>On the morning of Friday, March 28, XI Jinping met with “representatives of the international business community” at the Great People's Hall in Beijing. “The reason I have invited all present is to hear your ideas, respond to your concerns and support the development of foreign companies in China,” explained the president in the initial words of his intervention, paying tribute to the numerous benefits that foreign companies brought to the country.
"China's impressive achievements are not only due to the Communist Party and the Chinese people, but also to the support and help of the international community, including the contribution of foreign companies operating in China," said XI.
"Foreign companies represent a third of China's total imports and exports, a quarter of their industrial value added and a seventh of their tax revenues, creating more than 30 million jobs," he explained.
For Xi, foreign companies are “important participants in Chinese modernization, the country's renovation, opening and innovation, and their interconnectivity with the world and integration into economic globalization”. Therefore, “here I would like to express my sincere gratitude to all the foreign companies that participated and supported the development of China!” He concluded.
Many will say that the Chinese president is, in the background, to respond to the growing pessimism of multinational companies in relation to the Chinese market, evidenced by the fall in foreign direct investment. Xi acknowledged, although diplomatically, that "in recent years, foreign companies have indeed found some difficulties in their development in China." Facing the problem directly is undoubtedly better than pretending it does not exist.
But it was more detailed than ever, for example, by recognizing that multinationals often cannot access business opportunities despite role market openings. “We will work to resolve the issue of 'large open doors, but small closed doors' in market access, ensuring that companies with foreign investment are not only able to go into open sectors, but also enjoy full and fair access to operations.”
The president acknowledged that multinationals are often discriminated against, stressing that it has long been that “foreign companies in China should benefit from national treatment, with equal application of laws, equal status and equal treatment. We will ensure that foreign companies have fair and legal access to production factors”, admitting that multinationals cannot often benefit from public contracts in China, promising: promising: "We will ensure that products manufactured in China by foreign companies can participate in public contracts on an equal foot, according to the law."
Trump a and the WTO
Many will say that Xi is taking advantage of Trump's shock. Their comments are normal for Chinese standards, including "many foreign companies, especially multinational companies, have a substantial global influence. We hope to speak right, act with pragmatism, firmly oppose retrograde movements that retreat the clock of history, reject zero -sum and promote cooperation and mutual benefit."
While Trump suspends US financing for the World Trade Organization (WTO), Xi reinforces the WTO: “The multilateral trade system, with the World Trade Organization at its core, is the cornerstone of international trade… We must defend the principles and rules of the WTO, continue to advance the liberalization and facilitation of trade and investment and encourage all countries to expand the development of shared development through greater opening.
Xi also promised greater internal opening: “The reduction of the market access threshold will be a key priority in the next opening phase. I specifically stressed that opening measures should be completed earlier than later. This year, we will widen the opening programs in selected areas and accelerate opening in sectors such as culture and education.”
XI has promised that China is not interested in any military conflict, stating that "it will be unobailably a path of peaceful development, it will actively promote the resolution of important international and regional issues and will strive to create a favorable environment for foreign companies."
On Friday night, Beijing promptly announced the full comments of Xi, beyond his usual reading. This is a sign of the emphasis given to meetings with foreign companies. Complete comments also help, as they serve as a reference, more officially and conveniently, for cunning political operators, including, expecting, experts in governmental matters and public relations of multinationals, who should use them as a valuable tool in their transactions in China.
Of the foreign participants at the meeting with XI, 14 of the 38 were Americans, 10 Germans, 6 British, 3 French, 2 Japanese, 2 Koreans and one from Switzerland, Denmark, Sweden, Brazil and Saudi Arabia. Despite BRICS and Global South, when it comes to foreign and multinational investment, the West continues to play a central role. Foreigners gathered are officially described by China as “representatives of the international business community”.
“Security Oasis”
FedEx Corporation President Raj Subrmaniam, Mercedes-Benz Group AG chairman, hello Källenius, Sanofi SA executive director Paul Hudson, HSBC Holdings PLC executive director, Georges Elhedery, Hitachi Ltd. Tosiaki Executive President SK Hynix Inc. Kwak Noh-Jung, and the President of Saudi Aramco Amin Nasser were some of those who intervened at the meeting.
Os representantes das empresas estrangeiras “elogiaram a China por ter alcançado um crescimento económico estável através de uma reforma profunda e abrangente e de uma abertura de alto nível sob a liderança do Presidente Xi”, refere a Xinhua.
From “Made in China” to “new quality productive forces”, China has enhanced industrial transformation and modernization through innovation, being prepared to perform a higher quality and more sustainable development.
The perspectives of the Chinese economy are strong, because in the midst of growing protectionism, China has continually expanding its opening, injecting stability in the global economy, and has become a "oasis of certainty" for investment and entrepreneurship. "China's development is the main driving force of the world economy and offers vast and exciting opportunities and growth potential," he was mentioned.
According to Xinhua, foreign representatives “applauded Chinese government efforts to create a fair and favorable environment for foreign companies and expressed their availability to expand investment cooperation with China, cultivate the Chinese market, actively participate in the modernization of China and build bridges for the exchange and cooperation of China with the world, and also expressed their availability to support an open world market, defend international free trade and contribute to the development of the world economy. ”</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:21:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Portsmouth will investigate maritime energy transition in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/portsmouth-vai-investigar-transicao-energetica-maritima-em-macau/</link><description>Macao was one of the places selected by the University of Portsmouth to study the inheritance of the energy transition in the coastal communities of the global southern and how they cross the age of decarbonization, the project officer told Lusa.
After the Port of Callao, in the center of Peru, Macau was the choice of the University of Portsmouth in the United Kingdom to investigate as maritime communities from the so -called global south crossed one of the milestones of the Industrial Revolution, the transition from sail to steam.
Relief commercial warehouse, Macao has a very rich story linked to the sea, a factor that weighed on the center's decision and maritime cultures (PCMC, British acronym) at the British University. "It is probably one of the first European enclaves in East Asia and has a long history of international travel by the sea from 1500," Melanie Bassett researcher Lusa told Lusa.
The creation of a doctoral research scholarship will bring to the territory an academic, whose mission is still to understand how these communities can adapt to a sustainable future. "We then want to look at the new energy transitions, to decarbonization, how Macau is making this transition and if people are aware of the changes," added Bassett, who leads the project "From Steam to Green to Green: Empower port communities in the global south [Sail to Steam, Carbon to Green: Empowering Port Communitiesin The Global South]" Portsmouth.
The project, which extends for a period of six and a half years, started in February, with the investigation to focus on the Peruvian Port of Callao, but should later expand to two other regions “somewhere in the Indian subcontinent and West Africa”.
Understand the past
Only the investigation will bring tangible results, but Bassett points out that, with the primacy of the steam vessel, the travel of communities and industries were generally away from the sea waterfront. Changes have also occurred in several businesses linked to the sector, from the fishing industry to naval construction. “We anticipate seeing this kind of changes, but also with the advent of European colonization, we see changes in cultures and architecture and how it affects the population, and then how, over time, these cultures merge and hybridize to create new cultures and new understandings of the world,” he said.
“It's part of Lloyds Register Foundation's financing to learn from the past,” Bassett added, referring to the project's funder who, in the case of Macao, will have the collaboration of the University of Macao and the local Maritime Museum.
It is also expected to have the communities active in research. Therefore, the recruitment of the academic that will lead the investigation requires language skills to ensure communication with the population. Recruitment for this research that is divided between Portsmouth and Macau is expected to be completed in April, and the project starts in October.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:18:44</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Wang Jian (c.767-C.830), Henan's poet of humble origins who lived in the Tang dynasty, was very attentive to the life of the palace, a theme on which he wrote about a hundred poems. As one reads in one of them, which is an outburst of a neglected lady of the palace of the palace that with words away, as shaking, a contradiction. Using her voice, writes:
«I gave up using all my jewelry and secretly we ticked a daoist robbery with the intention of joining the temple of Jinxian. However, recently, the sovereign found that I could read. I was then taken to your secretary to help with clerical work. »
The poem was transcribed into a Tuanshan, the 'round fan' of silk also designated Gongshan, the 'fan of the palace', used by the ladies of the Tang Dynasty Palace, accompanying the painting Sentido (paint and color, 25.9 x 26 cm, at the Ashmolean Museum of the University of Oxford) Delta of the Pearl River, Li Jian (1747-1799).
In addition to boasting his scholarship and ingenuity, the painter showed in several paintings a often figurative independence in a literate walking alone in the landscape. A freedom wants visual materials in Europe, which since about 1720 began to circulate in Canton (Guangzhou), either against the orthodoxy inspired by Dong Qichang (1555-1636) in the northeast cities.
This original view is quite evident in a 1788 vertical roller entitled White Clouds, Red Trees (Ink and Color on Silk, 126 x 52.7 cm, at the Cleveland Art Museum) in which, among the surprising color of green and blue rocks, he finds himself in a house elevated by bars, a literate sitting at the window playing a Qin. The red leaves of the treetops indicate that they are senescence in the fall, underlining change. It would be said that the painting rhymes with Qin's music notes in a visualization of the emotions aroused by the melody.
Li Jian wrote a poem to accompany the painting:
«White clouds surround red trees,
The fog has already returned to the valley,
Why not rest
and leave the Spirit alone with the world.
With the solidarity of Qin,
I sit at the Rio Pavilion.
An old friend is expected
But it doesn't come.
The day is cold and fall
The leaves of the fields. »
In the way painting is expressed is the knowledge of the lesson of painters made remarkable for their attitude towards painting and marked it with the pulsatile sensitivity of the art of calligraphy. Especially Shitao (1642-1707) who in her vagabond will have left in the region where I read Jian, many admirers. An echo of the unique trace of the all-inclusive brush, of which the painter spoke, is noted in paintings of the one who sometimes signed with the name Kuang Jian, "Jian, the wild" in the way he reacted to the unexpected.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Chinese oil company Cnooc discovered an important oil field in the east of the Southern Sea of ​​China, with proven reserves of over 100 million tons, the state press said yesterday.
According to Chinese official news agency Xinhua, the identified field, Huizhou 19-6, is about 170 kilometers from the city of Shenzhen in the south of the country. Test drilling produced 413 barrels of raw and 68,000 cubic meters of natural gas per day, according to the same source.
Proven reservations of the oil field, ie the amount of hydrocarbons whose recovery can be almost certainly estimated using current techniques, ascend to more than 100 million tons, according to the information cited by Xinhua.
Southern China's underground is largely sub-pitched due to territorial disputes, but most known oil and gas deposits are in non-contested areas, according to the US energy information administration.
Beijing claims the sovereignty of almost the whole sea, over which the Philippines, Malaysia, Vietnam, Indonesia and Brunei also have claims.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Wang Jian (c.767-C.830), Henan's poet of humble origins who lived in the Tang dynasty, was very attentive to the life of the palace, a theme on which he wrote about a hundred poems. As one reads in one of them, which is an outburst of a neglected lady of the palace of the palace that with words away, as shaking, a contradiction. Using her voice, writes:
«I gave up using all my jewelry and secretly we ticked a daoist robbery with the intention of joining the temple of Jinxian. However, recently, the sovereign found that I could read. I was then taken to your secretary to help with clerical work. »
The poem was transcribed into a Tuanshan, the 'round fan' of silk also designated Gongshan, the 'fan of the palace', used by the ladies of the Tang Dynasty Palace, accompanying the painting Sentido (paint and color, 25.9 x 26 cm, at the Ashmolean Museum of the University of Oxford) Delta of the Pearl River, Li Jian (1747-1799).
In addition to boasting his scholarship and ingenuity, the painter showed in several paintings a often figurative independence in a literate walking alone in the landscape. A freedom wants visual materials in Europe, which since about 1720 began to circulate in Canton (Guangzhou), either against the orthodoxy inspired by Dong Qichang (1555-1636) in the northeast cities.
This original view is quite evident in a 1788 vertical roller entitled White Clouds, Red Trees (Ink and Color on Silk, 126 x 52.7 cm, at the Cleveland Art Museum) in which, among the surprising color of green and blue rocks, he finds himself in a house elevated by bars, a literate sitting at the window playing a Qin. The red leaves of the treetops indicate that they are senescence in the fall, underlining change. It would be said that the painting rhymes with Qin's music notes in a visualization of the emotions aroused by the melody.
Li Jian wrote a poem to accompany the painting:
«White clouds surround red trees,
The fog has already returned to the valley,
Why not rest
and leave the Spirit alone with the world.
With the solidarity of Qin,
I sit at the Rio Pavilion.
An old friend is expected
But it doesn't come.
The day is cold and fall
The leaves of the fields. »
In the way painting is expressed is the knowledge of the lesson of painters made remarkable for their attitude towards painting and marked it with the pulsatile sensitivity of the art of calligraphy. Especially Shitao (1642-1707) who in her vagabond will have left in the region where I read Jian, many admirers. An echo of the unique trace of the all-inclusive brush, of which the painter spoke, is noted in paintings of the one who sometimes signed with the name Kuang Jian, "Jian, the wild" in the way he reacted to the unexpected.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Wang Jian (c.767-C.830), Henan's poet of humble origins who lived in the Tang dynasty, was very attentive to the life of the palace, a theme on which he wrote about a hundred poems. As one reads in one of them, which is an outburst of a neglected lady of the palace of the palace that with words away, as shaking, a contradiction. Using her voice, writes:
«I gave up using all my jewelry and secretly we ticked a daoist robbery with the intention of joining the temple of Jinxian. However, recently, the sovereign found that I could read. I was then taken to your secretary to help with clerical work. »
The poem was transcribed into a Tuanshan, the 'round fan' of silk also designated Gongshan, the 'fan of the palace', used by the ladies of the Tang Dynasty Palace, accompanying the painting Sentido (paint and color, 25.9 x 26 cm, at the Ashmolean Museum of the University of Oxford) Delta of the Pearl River, Li Jian (1747-1799).
In addition to boasting his scholarship and ingenuity, the painter showed in several paintings a often figurative independence in a literate walking alone in the landscape. A freedom wants visual materials in Europe, which since about 1720 began to circulate in Canton (Guangzhou), either against the orthodoxy inspired by Dong Qichang (1555-1636) in the northeast cities.
This original view is quite evident in a 1788 vertical roller entitled White Clouds, Red Trees (Ink and Color on Silk, 126 x 52.7 cm, at the Cleveland Art Museum) in which, among the surprising color of green and blue rocks, he finds himself in a house elevated by bars, a literate sitting at the window playing a Qin. The red leaves of the treetops indicate that they are senescence in the fall, underlining change. It would be said that the painting rhymes with Qin's music notes in a visualization of the emotions aroused by the melody.
Li Jian wrote a poem to accompany the painting:
«White clouds surround red trees,
The fog has already returned to the valley,
Why not rest
and leave the Spirit alone with the world.
With the solidarity of Qin,
I sit at the Rio Pavilion.
An old friend is expected
But it doesn't come.
The day is cold and fall
The leaves of the fields. »
In the way painting is expressed is the knowledge of the lesson of painters made remarkable for their attitude towards painting and marked it with the pulsatile sensitivity of the art of calligraphy. Especially Shitao (1642-1707) who in her vagabond will have left in the region where I read Jian, many admirers. An echo of the unique trace of the all-inclusive brush, of which the painter spoke, is noted in paintings of the one who sometimes signed with the name Kuang Jian, "Jian, the wild" in the way he reacted to the unexpected.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Wang Jian (c.767-C.830), Henan's poet of humble origins who lived in the Tang dynasty, was very attentive to the life of the palace, a theme on which he wrote about a hundred poems. As one reads in one of them, which is an outburst of a neglected lady of the palace of the palace that with words away, as shaking, a contradiction. Using her voice, writes:
«I gave up using all my jewelry and secretly we ticked a daoist robbery with the intention of joining the temple of Jinxian. However, recently, the sovereign found that I could read. I was then taken to your secretary to help with clerical work. »
The poem was transcribed into a Tuanshan, the 'round fan' of silk also designated Gongshan, the 'fan of the palace', used by the ladies of the Tang Dynasty Palace, accompanying the painting Sentido (paint and color, 25.9 x 26 cm, at the Ashmolean Museum of the University of Oxford) Delta of the Pearl River, Li Jian (1747-1799).
In addition to boasting his scholarship and ingenuity, the painter showed in several paintings a often figurative independence in a literate walking alone in the landscape. A freedom wants visual materials in Europe, which since about 1720 began to circulate in Canton (Guangzhou), either against the orthodoxy inspired by Dong Qichang (1555-1636) in the northeast cities.
This original view is quite evident in a 1788 vertical roller entitled White Clouds, Red Trees (Ink and Color on Silk, 126 x 52.7 cm, at the Cleveland Art Museum) in which, among the surprising color of green and blue rocks, he finds himself in a house elevated by bars, a literate sitting at the window playing a Qin. The red leaves of the treetops indicate that they are senescence in the fall, underlining change. It would be said that the painting rhymes with Qin's music notes in a visualization of the emotions aroused by the melody.
Li Jian wrote a poem to accompany the painting:
«White clouds surround red trees,
The fog has already returned to the valley,
Why not rest
and leave the Spirit alone with the world.
With the solidarity of Qin,
I sit at the Rio Pavilion.
An old friend is expected
But it doesn't come.
The day is cold and fall
The leaves of the fields. »
In the way painting is expressed is the knowledge of the lesson of painters made remarkable for their attitude towards painting and marked it with the pulsatile sensitivity of the art of calligraphy. Especially Shitao (1642-1707) who in her vagabond will have left in the region where I read Jian, many admirers. An echo of the unique trace of the all-inclusive brush, of which the painter spoke, is noted in paintings of the one who sometimes signed with the name Kuang Jian, "Jian, the wild" in the way he reacted to the unexpected.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MNE | BIR OF PORTUGUESE AND EPM are topics to discuss with Paulo Rangel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/28/mne-bir-de-portugueses-e-epm-sao-temas-a-discutir-com-paulo-rangel/</link><description>During the visit to Macao of Portuguese Foreign Minister, Amelia António and Miguel de Senna Fernandes want to discuss the end of access to BIR access by Portuguese. The president of the House of Portugal in Macau associates this article with the position of Lisbon in the issue of 5G
 
It is another visit of a Portuguese ruler to Macau, but Paulo Rangel's first as Minister of Foreign Affairs of the executive of Luis Montenegro, at a time when the country is preparing to go to votes in May after the dissolution of the Assembly of the Republic.
After a journey through China, Paulo Rangel will meet with local associative leaders in order to perceive existing problems related to the Portuguese community.
At HM, Amelia António, president of the House of Portugal in Macau (CPM), argues that the difficulties of obtaining residence by Portuguese should be one of the pressing matters. “My expectation is not high. I would like the Minister, after visiting China, to say something friendly, as relationships have been very loose. I would like to see this relationship resumed as usual and also that we were not as followers of the positions of the European Union (EU) so fierce, because we have very special interests and we have a very large Portuguese community. of the EU, and this should not be lost sight of. ”
Amelia António highlights the position that Portugal adopted in the case of Rede 5G and Huawei, but also “the development that occurred in relation to the coming of Portuguese to Macau, subject to Blue Card”. “I have the feeling that everything comes following this EU policy against China. Portugal must have a position to safeguard these interests.”
Speaking to Lusa, the official made similar complaints. "We are here, we suffer the consequences of these relationships [between Portugal and China], good or bad. We had very close relations for a long time, which changed with Covid. I have not seen things again as they were, and I think it was important that Mr. Minister explains what is the position," he said that Portugal does not have to "align faithfully with everything in Europe and, above all,"
Before the pandemic, he recalled the official, there was “permanent communication” and “much exchange” between the Portuguese and Chinese authorities.
Today is noticeable a “hardening regarding the Portuguese” in macao immigration, Maria Amelia António declared, but not being able to affirm categorically whether the position is related to “this removal” between China and the West.
Macao authorities have not accepted new requests for residence in the territory for Portuguese for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing for justification of family reunion or previous connection to the territory.
Also Miguel de Senna Fernandes, lawyer and president of the Macanese Association, regrets the situation of the assignment of the BIR. "I would like the government of the Portuguese Republic to take into account the Portuguese community in the territory, which faces some difficulties regarding the possibility of obtaining the residence. It is a topic that may be addressed between the Portuguese State and the MSAR, to be greater flexibility to allow the Portuguese community to have greater accessibility to the right of residence, as existed before."
For the causal, "Misrere does not have to randomly assign more homes, but it is something that corresponds only to my desire." "Of course, that Mand has its reasons and Macau is different, and there are other communities that are interested in staying in the territory. The Portuguese community, due to greater historical connection that has to the territory, is still another community, among others. As Portuguese we are, we would like to have greater flexibility," he admitted.
The EPM case
Another point that Amelia António and Miguel de Senna Fernandes want to see approached on Paulo Rangel's visit is the situation at the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) and the lack of teachers. "I think you should see the school and make a little more awareness of the situation, although the EPM is not from its area. As a member of the government it is important to realize that this situation has been poorly conducted, because in Portugal has been gone after some conversations that have little to do with reality and only harm. If he realized a little more of the situation, it would not be bad," said Amelia António.
Already Miguel de Senna Fernandes says that it is time for the Portuguese executive to stop looking at the school as another Portuguese educational institution abroad. “EPM is always a recurring question, and it all depends on how the Portuguese state looks at school: if you look like any Portuguese school spread around the world, this is a mistake. There is no possible comparison, because the EPM emerged in a very special context.”
However, to Lusa agency, Jorge Neto Valente, president of the EPM foundation, was categorical: the school “has nothing to peddling” to Paulo Rangel. "There is no whimper, we have nothing to do, we have nothing to demand, everything is normal," he said.
The lawyer and president of the founding of the EPM said Rangel hoped "take a correct perception of the school, what it is for, the goals he has." “It's always good to have direct knowledge, it's much better than in papers,” said Neto Valente. "We have to account that the school is fulfilling the role that is expected to play," added the leader, recalling that the Portuguese State holds the majority of the capital of the EPM foundation.
Still on the EPM universe, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, who also leads the Macanese Instruction Promoting Association (Apim), suggested a close look at the Chinese teaching in the EPM.
"I have always advocated that Cantonese must have status. Because students, when they leave school, are in a singing world. This with all the merit that can have teaching in Mandarin," he said. "It is an issue that should be posed. It is a delicate question, because we are talking about an official language," he added, referring to Mandarin, an official language in China.
The official, also vice president of the EPM foundation, admits that this is not a question that generates consensus -"many parents do not agree with this view" -but stresses that the learning of Cantonese "is a vehicle of integration", as it is the dominant language in the territory.
Yes to the electronic vote
Also to Lusa several associative leaders defended the transition to electronic vote, stressing embarrassment in the current options for emigration. "As long as it is not advanced without being tested, I am fully in agreement. The future is this and we have to point out," said the president of the CPM.
In legislative elections, the Portuguese abroad have the possibility of exercising the right to vote in person or by post, while in presidential and European, the vote is in person.
In choosing correspondence, the government sends the address indicated in the census notebook the voting report and two envelopes, one of green and one white, which must be returned to the Ministry of Internal Affairs after filling.
The electronic option “can offer greater security”, defended Maria Amelia António. "With the consulates to work poorly, in order to have few employees, with their work, and in countries where they are far from the places where people live, it is very difficult for people to vote personally. There has also been a lot of failures in the guarantees of receiving vote [via mail]," he added.
The electronic choice is a longstanding claim of the Portuguese Communities Council (CCP). Rui Marcelo, president of the Regional Council of the Portuguese Communities of Asia and Oceania, who has a meeting scheduled with the Portuguese Foreign Minister, said that the “theme is already part of the CCP agenda“ a few years ago and has been approached several times and with several governments ”.
"With the advancement of technology and the possibility of implementing security systems that can ensure vote safety - which happens today through the provision of services in other areas of the government also - the conditions are created so that we can eventually evolve into a situation where it can obviously be a complement, but not a substitute," he noticed.
In February, the Portuguese Parliament approved a resolution proposed by the PSD to test the electronic vote in emigration. The President of the Portuguese Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, suggested in December a pilot electronic voting experience in the circles of emigration.
The head of Portuguese diplomacy arrives in Macau today after passing by Beijing and Haikou, in the province of Haião, where he was present at the Boao Forum.
In Macao, Paulo Rangel has scheduled meetings with the head of local government, Sam Hou Fai, as well as the counselors of the Portuguese communities, associative representatives, educational institutions and entrepreneurs. Visit the EPM and the Consulate General of Portugal in the territory.
In the late afternoon, MNE goes to Hong Kong to visit “Lusas Stories”, an exhibition dedicated to the Portuguese community at the Hong Kong History Museum. Lame</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:02:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Apomac | Jorge Fão regrets lack of people to manage association</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/apomac-jorge-fao-lamenta-falta-de-pessoas-para-gerir-associacao/</link><description>APOMAC - Macao's retirees, retired and pensioners association goes to elections tomorrow with a unique list. Francisco Mannão competes again for president, Jorge Fão for the General Assembly and Daniel Mendonça to the Fiscal Council. Mannão suggests the creation of a “satellite city” only for the elderly and calls for pensions update
 
Increasing the elderly pensions would be "gold on blue." In the meantime, Francisco Mannão continues to fight for this and other flags designed to improve the lives of older residents, again leading the candidate list for the management of Apomac - Macao's retirees, retirees and pensioners association, which take place tomorrow.
The list is unique and the faces have little or nothing difference from previous years: Jorge Fão continues to lead the General Assembly, while Daniel Mendonça competes for the Fiscal Council. There is only one new name in the position of Member of the Fiscal Council.
"It is very difficult to find people available to do this volunteer work. Jorge and I would like to find someone who could replace us, because we are for a long time in this association. We are elderly, but we have energy. As long as we have strength on the legs to walk, we are walking and trying to do our best by Apomac," Francisco Mannhão told HM.
Jorge Fão highlights the fact that Apomac has been about to celebrate 25 years since the foundation, noting that there is, in fact, a leadership problem that if not solved can culminate in the disappearance of the association. "We are not seeing the emergence of another list of younger and younger people, so that we offer our services for another term and so on, as far as possible. There is a leading problem at Apomac and in other associations. The Apomac issue is more serious, because we have been standing for 24 years, we will celebrate in May."
Satellite city and pensions
In a list that will lead the association by 2028, the motto is “we are elderly but energetic”, reads in the action program.
At the first point, it is indicated that the team's objective is "to monitor the government's policy and the Macau Foundation, with a view to adjusting the needs of our action program throughout this three -year term." In addition, they intend to "provide the necessary support to members so that they can enjoy the benefits awarded by the Government of MSAR and other official entities."
One of the requests on the list to the government led by Sam Hou Fai is the increase in pensions, which is currently 3,740 patacas. It would be for the association would be the update to four thousand monthly patacas.
"It would be good for the government of MSar to pay the pension monthly to the elderly, the pecuniary compensation and the old age, instead of having to wait every three months to receive the pension for the elderly, seven months to receive the pecuniary compensation and ten months to receive old age. Hm.
Another idea left by Francisco Mannão is from the construction of a satellite city only for elderly dwellings, in what would be a larger project against residence for the elderly already built by the executive, in the area of ​​sand black.
"I liked the Government of MSA to build a satellite city for the elderly. I worry a lot because there are many living alone, and with the construction of this satellite city they no longer have problems of loneliness, and could live with each other, and can provide services common to all. The construction of high buildings is good, but for the elderly it is not that good," he defended.
Still, Mannão assures that being elderly in Macau is much easier than in Hong Kong. “Nowadays, in Macau, the elderly live quite well, because there are many social support attributed to this group of people.
Sufficient resources
Asked about the essential points to make Apomac a larger association, Francisco Mannhão says that “they have enough”, however, the closure of the clinic where they were provided to the elderly health care.
"Of course we had the plan to be able to develop our headquarters more, but due to the lack of the allowance we had to end our clinic. In this context, we had a program to develop this area that had to be abandoned, and that would benefit our associates. We tried to organize more lectures about health, because the senior group needs to know more about disease and health affairs, something that can generate great concerns."
In political terms, Francisco Mannhão, who was even a candidate for deputy to the Legislative Assembly, says that Apomac is an advocate of the principle of “one country, two systems”, thought by Beijing to the regions of Macau and Hong Kong. "We agree with the national policy of 'a country, two systems', so that Macau can be a paradise for us. So far we have been quite well in Macau, we have no problems, but we would like this principle to continue."
A lot of bureaucracy
One of the services provided by Apomac goes through bureaucratic support to the elderly in communication with the General Retirement Caixa (CGA), in the case of former civil servants who receive the reform of Portugal, or the Macao Pension Fund.
"The communication with the CGA has improved a little, but the bureaucratic part is still very difficult to deal with on the part of our associates. Not long ago one of our associates waited more than three years for an amount of an amount that has been improperly charged," said Francisco Mannão.
Jorge Fão, in turn, stressed that Apomac is also popular with non -partners, including from the Chinese community, to treat various issues, such as requests for subsidies or funeral -related paperwork.
Still looking at the Action program, Apomac's list also aims to “organize more sightseeing tours to mainland China, making known its culture and success of the country”, as well as the promotion of “more coexistence, so that members join periodically”. Much sought after by the dining service, since in Apomac some dishes of macanese gastronomy can be eaten, the list wants to "improve the management of the canteen whenever possible."
Asked if many elderly from Macau want to pass the renovation in China one day, at a time when regional integration is increasingly a reality, Francisco Mannão admits yes, although many “prefer to stay in the territory, as they have their life rooted here, being used to the uses and customs of Macao”. "The Government of MSA has been doing a lot of work so that they can join the great bay," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>BOAO FORUM | Ia, globalization and sustainability in discussion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/forum-boao-ia-globalizacao-e-sustentabilidade-em-discussao/</link><description>Another edition of the Boao Forum began in Haião, where topics such as artificial intelligence, globalization, current economic issues and sustainable development will be discussed. The head of the Executive of Masters departs today for the event, whose theme is “Asia in the world in transformation: towards a shared future”
 
Posters to announce another edition of the Boao Forum can be seen everywhere in Haião, the Chinese island that hosts the International Forum promoted by Beijing to discuss, with other countries, issues of economic, commercial and cooperation at various levels.
The MSAR will be represented by an official delegation led by Sam Hou Fai, chief executive, who will be on the island between today and tomorrow. Liu Xianfa, commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China in the MSAR, continues to join the delegation of MGA as a guest advisor.
The official delegation of the MSAR is also composed by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, and the chief executive chief of the cabinet, Chan Kak. During the absence of Sam Hou Fai, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, will interim the functions of Chief Executive.
The Boa Goveal Forum for Asia 2025 ends on Friday and has as its theme “Asia in the world in transformation: Towards a shared future” [Asia in the Changing World: Tows a Shared Future], and, according to a statement released by the chief executive's office, focuses on four essential areas, one of them “rebuilding confidence and promoting cooperation in a rapid transformation world”.
Objectives are followed by "encouraging growth and rebalanced globalization for inclusive development" or "modeling the future and rapidly implementing the objectives of sustainable development to respond more effectively to global challenges." In turn, the fourth objective concerns a very current area: Artificial Intelligence (AI).
It is thus intended to “explore potentialities and intensify AI's application and governance for development motivated by innovation”.
According to the People's Daily Journal, this year are expected for more than two thousand participants from 60 countries and regions, being held 50 forums, or discussion groups, around the above objectives. 1,140 journalists are expected to coverage the event.
The forecasts of a forum
The main conferences of the Boao Forum include discussions about the Chinese and World Economy, namely in "High-Level dialogue: China's reform and economic predictions" and "construction of an open world economy: challenges and solutions." Following is “Improvement of the construction of digital capacity &amp; conforming the gap between digital”, as well as “unlock the great potential of regional free trade agreements”.
Among the remaining panels are also conversations about the potential of AI in "AI: how to ensure a balance between application and governance." Countries will also address the issue of global governance in the relationship with the United Nations (UN), in "high-level dialogue: global governance after the UN summit of the future."
But the discussion forums start with some predictions made in the report released in the context of the Boao Forum, entitled "Asian Economic Outlook and Integration Progress". One of the forecasts is that the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) of the Asian continent should grow 4.5 percent this year, reported Xinhua. "Despite growing global economic uncertainty, Asia remains a key growth engine for the world economy," the report says.
In addition, in terms of parity of purchasing power, the Asia GDP ratio, within the world total, is expected to increase from a registration of 48.1 percent last year to 48.6 percent this year. In turn, the report describes that the general situation of employment and wages “is improving in Asia”, with an unemployment rate of 4.39 percent for this year, below the global rate of 4.96 percent.
The Asian Economic Outlook and Integration Progress also highlights foreign investments in Asia, describing that China and Asean-Association of Southeast Asia nations "are the most appealing economies in Asia." In addition, it refers that the dependence on the internal and external foreign direct and external investment of Asian economies in the region itself reached 49.15 percent by 2023.
From the point of view of the bidirectional dependence of IDE in Asia, China continued to be the most dependent economy of the Asian IDE flows, followed by Indonesia, with its dependence rates over 80 percent and 75 percent, respectively.
The report also pointed out that China remains the center of global production value chains, and since 2017, global trade in intermediate goods has been more dependent on China than in North America.
In 2023, China's global dependence on intermediate goods was 16 percent compared to 15 percent to North America. The commercial friction caused by the United States in 2018 did not raise their position in the global value chains of the transforming industry, the report added.
Thus, the advance of Asia is also described in the level of emerging green technologies, since this is "driven by strong industrial capabilities and political support." Thus, the continent seems to be positioning itself "as a potential leader in advanced materials related to batteries or production of biodegradable plastics."
China, Japan, and the Republic of Korea dominate the Lithium Battery Battery Technology Global Supply Chain, a factor considered crucial for the electrification of transport, the report underlines. However, China is at the forefront of the expanding green hydrogen industry in Asia, being the region responsible for almost 70 percent of the worldwide capacity of hydrogen electrolisters, also reveals the same report.
An ecological island
According to an Xinhua report, Haião Island, which welcomes the Boao Forum, is “a pioneer in development with low carbon emissions”, namely the use of photovoltaic energy.
"On Dongyu Island, in Hainan province, southern China, the almost null carbon emissions demonstration zone is redefining harmony between humanity and nature-remodeling modern life through the integration of cutting-edge technology with sustainable development," he describes.
But there are more technological news, such as the use of "a simple QR code that unlocks a coffee carbon emissions experience, and where a robotic arm prepares coffee using clean energy." There is also the bet on recycling, as "an advanced recycling cube separates the materials, converting them into" carbon points ", which can be changed to ecological awards."
The area that welcomes the Boao Forum has a total area of ​​190 hectares, where a bet on “three key strategies” was made, namely the “renewal of ecological buildings, use of renewable energy and ecological transport”. The renewal of the zone for more sustainable bets will have begun in 2022, being proof of “how technological innovation and urban renewal can shape a future with low carbon emissions, paving the way for sustainable development, particularly in the tropical regions of the world,” says Xinhua.
Also according to the same report, "one of the main strengths of the area lies in energy production capacity", currently producing "about 32 million kWh of green electricity, almost double its search for 17 million kWh". In turn, "surplus energy is introduced into the network, contributing to an annual savings of 7 720 tons of negative carbon resources," he said to Xinhua Ouyang Qinglun, deputy director of the Cosco Shipping Boao Co. Department of Engineering.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>EPM | Paulo Rangel guarantees increased financial support after 11 years of cuts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/epm-paulo-rangel-garante-aumento-de-apoio-financeiro-apos-11-anos-de-cortes/</link><description>On a lightning visit to Macao, Portugal's Foreign Minister argued that the position that the country maintains in the European Union does not affect the relationship with China. During Paulo Rangel's visit, it was also announced that Sam Hou Fai should visit Portugal during the summer
 
He met with Sam Hou Fai, with counselors from the Portuguese communities, associative representatives, Portuguese educational institutions and entrepreneurs. Thus was the visit of Paulo Rangel, Minister of Foreign Affairs of Portugal, in the short visit to the MSAR, which took place on Friday. There are no passages in the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) and the Consulate General of Portugal in the territory. In the late afternoon, Paulo Rangel also moved to Hong Kong to visit the exhibition “Lusas Stories”, dedicated to the Portuguese community of the territory, patent at the Hong Kong History Museum. In China, Paulo Rangel was present at the Boao Forum in Haião.
In an interview with TDM, the minister assured that Portugal's relations with China remain good, denying that the country's position in the European Union's position (EU) can represent some kind of obstacle.
"Anyone who thinks that Portugal's presence in the EU is harmful to Portugal's relationship with China, does not realize Portugal's relationship with China and does not realize the role of Portugal in the international picture. I realize that some people do not understand, but honestly we have to see it as more value. And this is seen like this," he said.
One of the voices that criticized Portugal's position in relation to stories such as the issue of Huawei and Rede 5G was Amelia António, lawyer and president of the House of Portugal in Macau.
“My expectation is not high. I would like you minister, after visiting China, to say something friendly, as relationships have been very loose. I would like to see this relationship resumed as usual and also that we were not as followers of the EU positions, so fiercely, because we have very special interests and we have a very large Portuguese community. It should not be lost sight of, ”he told Paulo Rangel to Macao.
The EPM question
In the interview given to TDM, Paulo Rangel also commented on the issue of EPM, stressing the points that were not on the agenda, namely the works of expansion of the facilities.
"This question has not yet been addressed. There are, in fact, several issues that have to be detailed and resolved, and one or the other that have not yet been put on the table. We know that there is search for it, but and I am being totally transparent, it is a question that is not yet on the table."
According to Lusa, Paulo Rangel also announced that the government increased financial support to the EPM, returning to the legally expected level after 11 years of cuts.
"We just replaced the Portuguese contribution to the Portuguese School of Macao, which (…) had suffered a huge cut," Rangel said on Friday.
The Portuguese State holds the majority (51 percent) of the capital of the EPM foundation, but since 2014 that Lisbon only contributed with 10 percent of school expenses, a decision taken under the Portuguese financial rescue program. EPM financing “is now at legal levels again and is the first time at the end of 11 years,” he said.
Shortly thereafter, the chief of Portuguese diplomacy told reporters that "there was no reason, honestly, to have this cut and he remained." "We have increased five times this value [of EPM financing], so this is something that is highly significant from the commitment we have."
"There are governments that really give importance to Macau and China and there are others who do not give, this is something that has to be said," lamented the minister, pointing his finger at the previous executive of the Socialist Party. The replacement of financing “is undoubtedly an important help” for EPM, which Rangel described as having a key role for Portugal in Macau.
"We also have pleased ... that there have never been so many Portuguese students - and now I speak of students from the Chinese community - as there are today in multiple schools," added the leader. "It means that also the special administrative region [of Macau] has encouraged Portuguese teaching and knowledge of Portuguese, and this is something that can only bring good relations between the two sides," added Rangel.
SAM in Portugal
From the meeting with Sam Hou Fai, which also took place on Friday, some ideas and opinions on “bilateral exchange and cooperation in the judicial, economic-commercial, education, among others,” says an official note from the Social Communication Office.
Sam Hou Fai led to the meeting topics such as “the most current development of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Henqing”, and remembered that “Paulo Rangel is the first foreign ministerial guardian he receives after the executive's head of the executive, a fact that reflects the good relations between Macao and Portugal with a longtime history”.
The head of the executive also pointed out that after December 20, 1999, Macau, "with strong support from the central government, has insisted on maintaining the principle of" a country, two systems ", preserving the continental legal system, traditional culture and customs, as well as actively maintaining the connection and foster relations with Portugal."
The ruler also said that "Macao has deepened the role of bridge and platform between China and Lusophone countries, continuously boosting the establishment of friendly relationships in the various areas of bilateral cooperation."
Another novelty of this meeting was the information, advanced by Sam Hou Fai himself, which “expects to visit Portugal in the near future” without, however, a concrete date has been announced.
Rangel announced that the chief executive of Macao is expected to visit Portugal "immediately before August or in September." "There is clearly here also an alignment of the priorities that is highly symbolic," said the diplomat, on the fringes of a meeting with the Portuguese community in Macau.
Asked about the restrictions to Portuguese in accessing the resident status, Rangel said he spoke with Sam Hou Fai "on all the issues that are relevant to the relationship between Portugal and the MSAR." "But, as it is a dialogue that is underway, I have a duty to give the opportunity we can, with the questions that have been raised from one part and the other, now we have space and time to build solutions," he added.
Rangel said that the "follow -up of dialogue" with Sam Hou Fai will take place at a meeting of the Portugal -Raem Joint Commission, "which will be organized in principle in the second semester here in Macao."
Paulo Rangel also said, in an interview with TDM, that the visit of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, president of the Portuguese Republic, “will happen a little later”, precisely due to the marking of new elections in the country. Initially, the aim was that Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa came to Macao in June to commemorate Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities. The visit should take place in the following months of summer, predicted Paulo Rangel.
Encounters and mismatches
Paulo Rangel also had a meeting with local associative representatives, including with the Portuguese communities counselor. Francisco Mannhão, president of the Macao Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners Association (Apomac), took the opportunity to talk about the bureaucracy that still exists in the relationship with the Caixa Geral de Retirement (CGA).
"To dispatch a survival pension process takes six months and then the correspondence goes back and forth. Macao benches do not have Iban, and this, for example, delays the whole process. Whenever a process goes to CGA, they insist that they do not have the number of IBAN and NIF [Fiscal Identification Number], that most of the widows receiving survival pensions, do not have in Portugal." exemplified.
Mannão also compliments to the Portuguese politician. "For a short time he was here, he showed concern. I liked the presence of the minister." In addition, Francisco Mannão stressed that “in a good time the Portuguese government appointed Alexandre Leitão to Consul”, also recalling the good work of the previous Portuguese consul, Vítor Sereno. "The consulate has never been as well functioned as now. The criticism made to our consul are unfair. There were our associates who told me to have been admired for making a marking and was attended the next day," he said.
More bet on the language
Another important point of Rangel's visit was the promise of the reinforcement of Mandarin teaching in Portugal. "With the Chinese authorities I made a point of saying that we will be very committed to teaching Chinese in Portugal."
In the Chinese capital, Rangel met with Chinese counterpart, Wang Yi, before meeting with Chinese vice-minister, Ding Xuexiang, on Hailão Island, where the Boao Forum took place.
"The situation today is much better than it was 20 years ago ... We have, in fact, a formation that we did not have at all," said Paulo Rangel. The formation of fluent people in Mandarin “is also decisive for our future”, but “it is not enough for the challenges we have ahead,” he warned. Lame</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:28:19</pubDate></item><item><title>History | Lara Reis, Professor of Macao High School, remembered in Lisbon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/historia-lara-reis-professor-do-liceu-de-macau-recordado-em-lisboa/</link><description>The former teacher of the Macao High School Fernando Lara Reis was remembered in the “Spring Conferences”, from the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center, by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira. A native of Leiria, Lara Reis fought in the 1st World War and lived on Avenida da República, in the villa that today houses the Macau Red Cross house
 
Fernando Lara Reis was born in 1892 and died in 1950. Throughout a life filled with historical events and testimonies, the natural man of Leiria was a military man and a teacher at Macao High School, eventually making the territory his home.
Lara Reis's life was recently remembered at the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira, herself to her former teacher in the territory.
At the session, the historian, who won the 2024 Macao International Institute Identity Award (IIM), recalled the “teacher, meritorious, driving of the arts”, and owner of “unusual knowledge”.
“He was a native of Leiria and lived in Macao until his death. He attended Leiria High School, the Military College, then joined the Army School. In World War I was in Elvas, and then left to Angola in 1915 when he faced the German threat over Portuguese colonies in Africa. Observer-Aviator. ”
Lara Reis was never a pilot as she wanted, having dedicated much of her life to teaching and Macao. “In 1919, Lara Reis went to Macao High School. He took a long circum-gap trip, leaving Portugal from Lisbon, going to the United States of America, crossed the entire territory and then went to Japan, down to Hong Kong and even Macau. He was a teacher in Macao, drawing, handicrafts and gymnastics until the end of his life,” said Celina Veiga de Oliveira.
The historian took to the session some written testimonies left by other Macao figures who wrote about Lara Reis, namely Monsignor Manuel Teixeira in the book “Macao Lyceu”. He said he never found "no teacher who had served the High School with greater dedication."
“He was a rigorous methodical teacher, whose military formation was certainly not oblivious to these characteristics. What was truly standing out was his artistic vein, because Lara Reis was always concerned with ascertaining the aesthetic meaning of the students and opening their mental horizons. This at the time when Macau was a small town. that he organized and also exhibitions by Portuguese and foreign artists he sponsored, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira also highlighted the words left by the writer Henrique de Senna Fernandes in an interview on "one of the greatest qualities of Lara Reis", which "besides rigor and discipline, was the consideration by the students, not distinguishing rich from the poor."
Professor Lara Reis was "a party prosecutor who served to obtain tuition fees for needy students," and "he is due to the initiative of the creation of the High School Association, of which he was the first president." This association organized in the former canhydrome “sports parties of the end of the year when students performed the most difficult exercises”.
Work done in Macau
The historian also highlighted “another aspect of dedication to territory” by Lara Reis. The Leiriense "participated in the First World War and this led him to interest all those who were incorporated into this conflict, having founded the League of the Great War fighters and had built in the cemetery of St. Miguel Archangel the monument where the bodies of combatants rest."
Moreover, "another facet of his personality was a taste for travel, because he had no family and thus left for the world." "I visited museums, art schools and photographed everything I saw, having created a estate with 32 volumes that is now a heritage of Leiria."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira did not forget the old “Sol Pente” villa, located in the middle-leaf zone, namely the Avenida da República, which was the house of Lara Reis, later donated to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao to “an anti-cancer clinic that was the first institution of the genre in the Portuguese colonial space”. Today this villa serves as a house to the Red Cross of Macao, and on its walls you can find a stone with the following message: “In this building legacy by the Rotary Fernando Reis to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao, it was installed at the initiative of the Rotary Club of Macao the first anti-cancer fighting center on April 15, 1951.”
“Change of Ares”
When Fernando Lara Reis goes to Macao, political times are troubled, with the political agitation to be lived in China after the fall of the Empire and the Republican Revolution of 1911.
"In the 1920s the nationalist shock waves lived in the Canton, which sometimes haunted the Portuguese enclave quiet, but never moved with everyday life. The Portuguese administration guaranteed a standard appearance, and the parties at Christmas, Chinese New Year, the religious festivities of the Catholic community and the Chinese population were habitual."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recalled that in the late 1920s, Lara Reis decided to transfer to Goa, a trip that would only accentuate her belonging to Macau.
“In the late 1920s, he felt he was time to change his air and asked to be transferred to the Afonso de Albuquerque High School in Pangim, and was there between 1941 and 1945, taking the opportunity to know India, and met the whole country. Instead, with a graceful and already sick license, choosing Macau to be his last address, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recordou também as palavras de Orlando Cardoso, que no artigo “Macau e o Oriente na vida de Lara Reis” falou do homem que se deslumbrou com Macau “a partir do momento em que, às 8 horas da noite de 23 de Outubro de 1919, avistou pela primeira vez o Farol da Guia, um pouco antes de se instalar no ‘New Macao Hotel’ e sorver de sentidos atentos os sons, os cheiros e as luzes desta porta of an immeasurable and fantastic Asia that he would describe to exhaustion. ”
These Lara Reis testimonies are “in a remarkable set of travel books that lay virtually unexplored in all their research potentialities on the shelves of the Leiria District Archive”, and were investigated by Orlando Cardoso himself.
In the same article, this one refers to a text from the newspaper “News of Macau” of January 17, 1950, about Lara Kings: “The Auster and Worsen Teacher; the tenacious and thorough tourist; the military who fought and consecrated the memory of those who fell in the field of struggle; the honest and firm friend; the lovely and humorous companion; social celibate that, despite this, did not disdain any opportunity to undo its gallants, always kind and inconsequential to any palm with a face that in the goto ”.
Given the few studies that exist about Lara Reis and the estate he left, Celina Veiga de Oliveira left a suggestion: "May the CCCM get the detailed index of the Leiria Archive, so that the research is possible for any interested researchers."</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:57:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Public Hiring | New regime “is on the good way,” says lawyer</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/contratacao-publica-novo-regime-esta-no-bom-caminho-diz-advogado/</link><description>Marco Caldeira, a lawyer and auxiliary teacher at the University of Lisbon Faculty of Law, argues that the proposed public hiring law, under analysis in the specialty in Hemiciclo, is “on the good way” regarding the attempt to “promote transparency and competition and bet on digitization”. The theme was discussed last week at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
 
The proposal of public hiring, currently under analysis in the specialty in the First Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly (AL), was one of the topics addressed in the “Spring Conferences”, at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) last week. The author of the lecture, the lawyer and teacher Marco Caldeira, made praise for the diploma for his attempt to reform and innovation in many respects.
"Although not perfect, the bill under discussion is justified by the need to update legislation that was approved four decades ago. It is a proposal that seems to point in the good way, with an effort to codify the regime, promote transparency and competition and bet on digitization," said the professor at the University of Lisbon Law School (FDUL) to HM.
In addition, Marco Caldeira understands that the diploma, and the content proposed by the government, aims to "follow what are good practices adopted in Europe and the West in general."
"It is also very commendable that the proposal was prepared following a serious and participated procedure of public consultation, which gave the opportunity to economic operators and contracting entities to identify deficiencies in current legislation and make suggestions," added Marco Caldeira.
At the CCCM session, the FDUL professor also pointed out that the concern [demonstrated, in the diploma] with the competition and transparency of the procedures ”, as well as“ the focus on training in the use of databases, as well as the focus on centralization ”.
The teacher also understood that, in this bill, the Portuguese regime "can help, because the practice followed in Portugal, and legislative evolutions, have useful teachings that, with proper adaptations, can be transposed to Macao."
Positive points
In the presentation at CCCM, Marco Caldeira highlighted several positive aspects of the current law proposal, namely “the express determination of inapplicability to certain contracts”, or the fact that “fundamental principles of public hiring” are established.
It is also required with the new law “qualifications to candidates and competitors” of public tenders, and there is also “the clarification and standardization of the types of public hiring procedures”.
Thus, a “centralized hiring regime” is created, as well as regulating “award criteria” in competitions, and the creation of an exclusive website for the public hiring area is also foreseen.
Marco Caldeira also drew attention to the real need of this diploma, as public hiring was legislated with various diplomas, including two decrees of 1984 and 1985, which established, respectively, the expenditure regime with works and service acquisitions, and the process of acquisition of goods and services. Such diplomas were “undone of reality” of Macao, even though the 1984 decree was reviewed in 2021, the teacher considered.
Marco Caldeira also considered that the process of revision of this diploma has been “slow”, as the public consultation took place between November 6, 2018 and January 4, 2019, and a later report was prepared, but the truth is that the proposal has been under analysis since December 2023, having been voted generally on January 11 last year.
What has to change
In the same session, the causal and university professor also highlighted the points already addressed by the first Standing Commission of AL regarding the necessary changes to legislate in the area of ​​public hiring. It was imposed “expressly consecrating fundamental legal principles, such as economy, efficiency and effectiveness, as well as publicity and transparency”, and there is also “a lack of regulation of public hiring policies”.
There was also the “need to promote transparency in public hiring procedures” and ensure “greater protection of loyal competition”. There was also “lack of rigorous and explicit regulation on the composition and operation of the proposals evaluation committees” submitted to a public tender, and there is “lack of explicit demands on the qualifications and capabilities of candidates and competitors in hiring procedures”.
Other gaps point to “insufficient regulation and transparency in the evaluation and adjudication procedures”, or “lack of explicit regulation on proposals presentation with an abnormally low price”. It was still necessary to “improve the sanctioning and inspection regime”, as well as bet on “regulation that promotes the development of electronic hiring”.
Says the executive
Looking at the justification of the law proposal, submitted by the Executive to AL, it is read that one of the great reasons for his presentation was even the legislative dispersion that was verified and the misfit over the current reality.
"The nuclear part of these diplomas was prepared in the mid-1980s, and has been in force for over 30 years. A significant part of the provisions of other legal diplomas already has an obvious divergence regarding the needs of Macao's current socioeconomic development, the efficiency of public administration management and the reinforcement of transparency and supervision," he reads.
According to the executive, "given that public hiring involves the use of the public purse, it is essential to review these regimes in order to meet the needs of the society of our day." Thus, in this law proposal, “the process and regime of expenses and acquisitions of goods and services” are regulated, with some provisions of a 1999 law, as “the provisions related to the public works contract regime have a high degree of specialization and are still effective”.
It is intended, with the new law of public hiring, to “guarantee justice, impartiality in the evaluation of proposals”, and expressly defining criteria of aid and determining the rules of conduct of workers and members of the opening and evaluation of proposals submitted to competition, so that “excerpt their functions impartially and entirely”.
Thus, it is foreseen that “contracting entities must adequately publicize the informative elements related to public hiring procedures”. They are “those related to the public tender, the clarifications provided, the rectification of documents, the extension of the deadline for the presentation of proposals, the causes for non -adjudication, the decision to annul the procedure and the award decision”.
In order to guarantee loyal competition, the government wants to ensure that all entities interested in participating in a competition have “the broader access” to all procedures, prohibiting “all acts, agreements or practices that can prevent, false or restrict competition”. Moreover, there is the “principle of impartiality”, which determines that “the program of procedures, book of charges or other documents, made by the contracting party, cannot contain any clause designed to favor or harm a particular interested party”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:18:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Aviation | Maria José de Freitas regrets removal of panels from the airport</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/20/aviacao-maria-jose-de-freitas-lamenta-retirada-de-paineis-do-aeroporto/</link><description>The first attempts to establish in Macao airlines in the early twentieth century were approached by historian Célia Reis in the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center. The architect Maria José de Freitas regretted the removal of panels from Macao International Airport that told this same story
 
Between the departure of the plane and the entrance to Macao International Airport (AIM) was a corridor that told the history of civil and military aviation from the territory of the early twentieth century. The project of this area of ​​the airport is by the studio of architect Maria José de Freitas, which regrets the removal of the panels and historical information that were installed in 2013.
The architect left this idea in an intervention after the presentation of historian Célia Reis about the history of civil and military aviation in Macao on Monday, on the occasion of the “Spring Conferences” that take place at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon.
“We decided to tell the story of Aviation in Macao in this corridor, with a great extent, although at the time there was little documentation about it. I discovered some information in a work by Luís Andrade de Sá. We collected texts and images and put it all on the walls of this corridor, and that was there for a while.”
"With a new direction [at AIM], I was asked how I could prove that all these events had happened. I had documentation in Portuguese, but I had nothing in Chinese and English, and at a time when I moved to Portugal on vacation, I saw, when I returned to Macau, who had removed all the information and images from this corridor. This story is unfortunate," he added.
The architect added that she would like the history of the early days of Aviation in Macao to be told in these same walls. "It would be important to realize where there is more information, so that they realize the history of aviation in Macao, which was a pioneer. There was, for example, an aviation hangar near the mud houses, and there are a series of references linked to the history of this land that should be made visible at the airport, in the rooms, for example. This story should be told and things should be placed in the right place," he said.
Ricou plans
Célia Reis, historian and teacher, is developing an investigation project around the early days of aviation in Macao and this was the theme that led to the “spring conferences” on Monday, with the session “Aviation and Air Navigation in Macao in the 1920s-a process of colonial innovation”.
Célia Reis spoke of a time when aviation began to be important to China for security reasons, and also begins to be thought to Macau. In this process, there is a personality whose name is important, a Hong Kong -born Frenchman: Charles William Ricou, a engineering and aviation pilot. From November 1919 the possibility of “establishing an air career between Macao, Hong Kong, Shanghai, Philippines, Java, India” began to equate, from November 1919, the possibility of Macaoi, Shanghai, Java, India, "contacting local government entities to obtain facilities and agreements.
Célia Reis explained that Ricou intended to form two airlines, the “Far East Aviation Company”, with “a much wider connection, reaching Manila”, and another to connect Macau, Hong Kong and Cantão, named “Macau Aerial Transport Company”.
This company "was constituted in Hong Kong, with a capital of $ 50,000, and had as founding partners personalities from Macau, such as Humberto de Avelar, Rodrigues dos Santos, Francisco Nolasco and Francisco da Silva". The historian also said in the presentation that the idea "was to complete the rest of the capital necessary with low value actions so that they could be bought by all [the inhabitants] in Macao."
"There is even the appeal of the company's board of directors for the Macanese to subscribe to capital, showing that the company was extremely important for the inhabitants of Macao, highlighting its patriotic value, of solidarity with progress," he added.
"Several voices have shown at that time that the company's commercial success, at first, could be little or none, although it was thought that the company could have some profits, having the ability to transport the air mail. However, this transportation capacity would be extremely limited, as the number of mail objects transporting from Macau was 24 letters a day," said Célia Reis.
At the time it was thought that Macau would be a pioneer, because "it would be the first territory to the East to have an aviation company", something that would "bring more visitors and increase trade." The Government of Macao, then led by Governor Correia da Silva, "gives in to the company's appeals, granting various facilities, such as the permission to build a provisional hangar on public ground that was vacant or from sea access infrastructure." In addition, “exemption from payment of the fuel storage tax” was allowed.
Thus, Macao even had hydroavião and 21 American airmen hired by the company. "It was considered that it was the largest load of air material exported by the United States of America (USA), all brought to Macao." Then the company tries to organize itself, "even asking for space on Taipa Island, designed to have definitive hangars, although provisional concessions have existed." In this context, he recalled the historian, "there were subsidies, a contract for the transportation of postal bags", to "allow a development of air navigation."
Impasses to the end
In May 1920, a new worldwide aviation convention emerged, to which Portugal adheres, which causes the “Macau Aerial Transport Company” to be nationalized. The project comes to advance, but quickly retreats.
“The airline therefore accesses the condition of obtaining a subsidy, and having four aircraft available for military service in Macau, if necessary. The issue of defense was always present. There was then some disagreement between the conditions required by the company and those that the governor understood were necessary. In addition, the government of Macao needed the Lisbon authorization for the operation of the airline. Advance, and this one begins to negotiate with the company. But voices begin to emerge in Lisbon that will make things change. ”
This is the idea that the US would be showing hidden interests through the establishment of the company. "[In Lisbon] it is fear that this is the found form of an American aviation company to settle in Macao, Portuguese territory, by different ways."
First, Lisbon forbids, retreating in the negotiations, and the next governor, Rodrigo Rodrigues, "is not in accordance with the company, understanding that it will not be viable," which leads to the entire project and dialogue to be suspended.
Célia Reis also pointed out that "the government of Correia da Silva has undergone several difficulties in these years, in terms of security", having occurred "very serious incidents in the relationship between Portugal and China".
“For this reason, the governor considered that having airplanes was extremely important because, at this moment, China was also resorting to aviation. The authorities of Portugal, however, considered that the planes of Macao would be of no importance, comparing with the set of aircraft that would have China or even Japan. When permission for the constitution of the airline in Macao, Lisbon understands that the territory could have in a worrying situation and planes could have functions with planes Military, even if there were few, ”explained the historian. The project would fall, however, by land.</description><pubDate>2025-03-20 01:43:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Song Pek Kei asks for subsidies to pay interest</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/habitacao-song-pek-kei-pede-subsidios-para-pagar-juros/</link><description>The deputy linked to the Fujian community wants the “healthy development” of the real estate market and asks the government to provide more land to build quality houses, and counteract the recent trend
 
Representative Song Pek Kei argues that the government must make a subsidy available to residents who ended up in the purchase of housing to help them pay interest on the contracted loans. The measure arises in a written interpellation of a deputy linked to the community of Fujian.
In the logic of the legislator, it is necessary to finance the payment of loans from those who buy home because the real estate market has a “weak development”, while “consumer power has weakened even more”. "The real estate market in Macau is still relatively slow and the Malparado credit ratio has reached a record level, which affected the stable development of the financial market," he warns.
The deputy considers that the reduction in housing prices in recent years should be a concern of society, because it is happening at a time when there is still demand, especially among the younger ones. Therefore, Song wants the government to subsidize the payment of interest on loans, when their amount does not exceed 4 percent.
The interest bonus measurement in the purchase of housing in force in Macao in the past, especially in the 1990s and at the beginning of the establishment of the MSAR. In 2001, the measure covered dwellings that were bought for a value of less than 750 thousand patacas. Song Pek Kei considers that this measure was “very successive” and asks for repetition.
In an interpeação in which the focus of the deputy is the youngest, the deputy close to Ung Choi Kun, former deputy for the Fujian community and one of the main local voices of real estate interests, also calls for changes in the exemption from the payment of the Seal Tax.
Poor housing
Song Pek Kei also acknowledges that the construction of latest housing at MSA has created a problem of lack of habitability conditions. According to the deputy, the latest buildings, built as studios or as apartments where there are no divisions demarcated by walls between the living room and the only room, offer decent conditions for residents. "Although there is a certain amount of residential apartments in Macao, there are structural problems in offering good apartments, which is due to the small dimension," he says.
Song Pek Kei also recognizes that old housing is more quality than the recent and asks the executive to use the land reserve to allow more construction, this time with the quality that has not been guaranteed in recent years. “The Government of MSAR has a certain land reserve, will management accelerate its planning and adjust the relationship of the supply structure to provide better apartments that satisfy market demand and improve the quality of life of residents?” He asks.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:13:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Litiges | Deputies want more transparency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/litigios-deputados-querem-mais-transparencia/</link><description>The 3rd Permanent Committee of the Legislative Assembly was discussing the future conciliation regime for family causes, which aims to create a mechanism to avoid the appellates in the event of divorce disputes, exercise of paternal power, food provision or issues related to the family home.
After the working meeting, the committee chairman, Deputy Vong Hin Fai, indicated, based on the executive's explanations, that family conciliators will belong to private institutions and will be chosen by the Institute of Social Action (IAS). In the IAS current list, about 30 community service centers of local associations and 2,000 social workers can be chosen for conciliation.
According to the statements cited by the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, during the working meeting, the committee deputies were concerned about the IAS criteria, as they argue that it is necessary to ensure independence, transparency and rationality not only of the conciliator but also the selection process. Therefore, they expect this aspect to be clarified.
On the other hand, in relation to the litigious divorce, the law defines that the party that intends to request divorce has a period of three years to advance to the courts, after the facts that justify the request. Deputies consider that the count of this period must be suspended, while the conciliation period takes place.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:12:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Courts | Notices will be published online</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/tribunais-editais-vao-ser-publicados-online/</link><description>Since yesterday, the public notices published by the courts and are usually posted outside the spaces, the headquarters of the Institute for Municipal Affairs and in local newspapers, they can also be disclosed through the website of courts on the Internet.
The information was transmitted in a statement from the office of the president of the last court, which ensures that the amendment aims to implement the changes to the law of sending procedural pieces, payment of costs and practice of other acts by electronic means.
"With a view to promoting the development of the digitization of the courts, from March 31, 2025, the notices published by the courts of the three instances of the Special Administrative Region of Macau will be disclosed, through electronic means, at the Court of Courts, with the objective of replacing the form of public notices in the courts and headquarters of the Institute for Municipal Affairs," was indicated.
"The legal provisions that require the posting of public notices outside the courts and the headquarters of the Institute for municipal matters and the publication of advertisements in newspapers continue to be applied," he was added.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:11:27</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | Government Action Lines presented on April 14</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/al-linhas-de-accao-governativa-apresentadas-a-14-de-abril/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai presents to 14 April the first lines of governing action of its Executive. The next day, the Chief Executive returns to the Legislative Assembly to answer the questions of the deputies. Between April 17 and 30, will be discussed the sectoral governing directions, starting with administration and justice and ending in transport and public works
 
After several months of collecting suggestions between local associations, the President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, the deputies called the presentation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for the Chief Executive for the Financial Year of 2025 on April 14, at 15h. Shortly after the presentation to the Plenary, follows the press conference at 5:30 pm at the Government headquarters, during which Sam Hou Fai will respond to the questions of the Social Communication.
The call signed by Kou Hoi In adds that the next day, as is tradition, Sam Hou Fai returns to Al to answer the deputies' questions about the LAG report, between 15h and 18h. Deputies have to deliver questions to the Question and Answer Session until 6:30 pm on April 14, that is, scarce hours after the first lag of the executive led by Sam Hou Fai.
Let's go by parts
Also, as is tradition, the presentation of the LAG report in the Plenary, the press conference that follows at the Government headquarters and the return of Sam Hou Fai to AL the next day to the deputies' questions and answers session will be broadcast live on TDM, both on television and on the radio.
The public will also be able to attend the broadcast through the internet in real time, the official portals of the government, the office of the Chief Executive, the al, the media of Social Communication (GCS) and in a thematic portal created for the purpose. In addition to the various apps of the executive, sessions can also be seen in the exclusive YouTube channel of the Chief Executive and GCS's Office and on the GCS Facebook page.
The Executive's General and Sectorial Program for the Fiscal Year 2025 will still be published online, as well as in Social Communication.
Following the presentation of the general guiding lines of the governance work, the sectoral debates are followed in the AL, between April 17 and 30. André Cheong is the first secretary to debate the LAG of the Administration and Justice area on April 17. On April 23, Tai Kin IP debuts to present the lag to the economy and finance. Two days later it is Wong Sio Chak's turn to debate with deputies the governing direction of the security area, something that has been doing annually since 2015.
The last two debates have as protagonists two newcomers, on April 28 LAM discusses the LAG of the Social and Culture Affairs area and on April 30, closing, Raymond Tam will debate in the plenary as the LAG of the transport and public works sector.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:10:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | Wong Wai Man confesses difficulty collecting signatures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/eleicoes-wong-wai-man-confessa-dificuldade-na-recolha-de-assinaturas/</link><description>Wong Wai Man revealed that until Saturday he had managed to collect 80 signatures to propose the candidacy for the upcoming direct legislative elections.
The eternal former deputy candidate, also known as the “Mao Soldier”, confessed to All About Macau being having difficulty collecting signatures, but is confident in the possibility of reaching 300 signatures required by law.
It is recalled that Wong Wai Man, also president of the Iron and Steel Association, could not gather all the signatures enough to formalize his candidacy for legislative elections of 2021. About the political program, Wong Wai Man highlighted the need to solve problems related to employment, especially due to the importation of non-residential labor.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:38:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Macau Negoceia Agreement on the delivery of convicts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/filipinas-macau-negoceia-acordo-sobre-entrega-de-condenados/</link><description>Between March 25 and 27, a MGI delegation was in Manila to negotiate an agreement on the transfer of convicted persons and an agreement of delivery of escape. The information was released on Friday by the Directorate of Justice Affairs Services (DSAJ), through a statement.
"In a friendly environment, the two parties came to consensus on the text of the project according to the transfer of convicted persons, the negotiation of some parts of the content of the escape offenders were concluded," he was reported.
The next meeting is expected to take place in Macao, "in the second half of this year", with the "Escape Infrastial Delivery Agreement" and a third agreement, the "Mutual Judicial Assistance Agreement in criminal matters".
The MSAR delegation was headed by the subdirector of the Directorate of Justice Services (DSAL), IAO Hin Chit, and included representatives of the office of the president of the last court, the office of the office, the secretary for administration and justice, and the Secretary for Security Office.
The Philippine delegation was headed by the National Chief Councilor of the Ministry of Justice, Dennis Arvin L. Chan, with representatives of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Ministry of Justice of the Philippines.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:37:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Budget | Public revenues fall 14% until February</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/orcamento-receitas-publicas-caem-14-ate-fevereiro/</link><description>The current revenue of the MSAR budget was 15.9 billion patacas in the first two months year, indicating a downward movement. The amount of tax charged on the game followed the trend and presented a 3.8 percent reduction
 
Macao Current Revenue fell 14 percent in the first two months of 2025, in annual terms, especially due to a drop in financial revenues and a deceleration in the game's recipes. Current revenue between January and February was 15.9 billion patacas, according to published "online" data by territory finance services on Thursday.
The main reason for the decrease was the financial revenues, which went from billion in the first two months of 2024 to just two thousand patacas this year. This heading corresponds to the results of the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), including investment and interest and dividends revenues.
On the other hand, the data also reveal a drop of 3.8 percent to 14.2 billion patacas in tax revenues, which still represented 89.3 percent of the total.
The six city game operators pay a 35 percent direct tax on the game's revenues, 2.4 percent for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development and 1.6 percent delivered to the Macao Foundation for cultural, educational, scientific, academic and philanthropic purposes.
Taxes on the game fell despite the Macao casinos registered total revenues of almost 38 billion patacas in the first two months of the year, more 0.5 percent than in the same period as 2024.
Above estimates
In January and February, Macau collected 14.2 percent of the current revenue projected for 2025 in the region's budget, which is 112.6 billion patacas. In early December, the Macao Study Center and the University of Macao Economics Department foresaw that revenues should be smaller than the government's estimated: 111.8 billion patacas.
With falling revenues, Macao ended February with a surplus in public accounts of six billion patacas, 24.8 percent less than in the same period of 2024. Macau closed last year with a surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than double the recorded in 2023.
In addition, it was the first year since 2020, at the beginning of the pandemic, that the territory was able to keep accounts on positive land, something required by the basic law, without transfers from the financial reserve.
The surplus shrunk despite the public expense descended 6.1 percent in January and February, to 9.99 billion patacas, mainly due to the lower investment in infrastructure. The government spent 2.48 billion patacas under the Administration Investment and Expenses Plan (PIDDA), minus 24.9 percent compared to the first two months of 2024.
On the contrary, the current expense increased 3.1 percent to 7.51 billion patacas, mainly due to a 5.7 percent increase in social support and subsidies given to the population.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:35:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Bidourado whistle</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/apito-bidourado/</link><description>We all remember the case 'Golden whistle' involving the former president of Football Club do Porto, Jorge Nuno Pinto da Costa. The case was serious and the accusation to the portist leader involved several suspicions, the main corruption to the referees, so that the rivals did not win championships.
The case was news for months and one of the witnesses in court was the former president of the Portuguese Football Federation (FPF), Gilberto Madail. This one said nothing could incriminate Pinto da Costa because he also had glass roofs. We are perfectly recalled from the Euro 2004 organization in Portugal, where the president of the FPF was precisely Gilberto Madail.
Povinho was atonyred with the construction and renewal of ten football stadiums to hold Euro'04. Four stadiums were owned by Benfica, FC Porto, Sporting and Boavista, while public investment was inserted in the stadiums of Braga, Guimarães, Aveiro, Coimbra, Leiria and Algarve.
At the time, the very exaggerated investment was debated in the social communication for such a small and poor country and was convinced that corruption would have been around the investment. Today, the stadiums of Leiria, Aveiro and Algarve are practically abandoned.
Corruption has always been linked to football, not only institutionally but through the numerous businesses that take place in clubs with the purchase and sale of players. As for arbitration it is better not even to emphasize the scandals we watched almost weekly.
On December 17, 2011, Fernando Gomes took office as president of the FPF and his responsibilities were immense over all these years, as he recently spent the ball to former referee Pedro Proença, who in turn was already president of the soccer league. Fernando Gomes was a controversial president and we must not forget that seriousness did not impede when Fernando Santos was the national team coach.
Last week, the country was atonymous because at the end of so many years, a team of 65 Judicial Police inspectors (PJ), 15 PJ Scientific Police experts, five criminal instruction judges, six prosecutors, and four representatives of the Bar Association began the megaoperation to the name of the name “added value”. The suspicion of corruption in the Portuguese Football Federation was concerned, and 20 search and seizure warrants were triggered in households, banking institution and law firm in the districts of Lisbon, Setúbal and Santarém.
So what was in question? Nothing more, nothing less than the suspicion of large committees received by FPF leaders and intermediaries in the sale of the Old FPF headquarters in April 2018, for 11 million and 250 thousand euros and that this business may have exceeded two million euros.
The period under investigation is between 2016 and 2020, during Fernando Gomes' second term as president of the FPF. However, magistrates and inspectors have failed to have access to all documents about selling the old headquarters and that some information will be disappeared.
What was confirmed is that the intermediary in the business of selling the FPF building, António Gameiro, former deputy of the Socialist Party, received from FPF 249 thousand euros, and 492 thousand euros from those who bought the building. In the end and by hand, the imbroglio is huge because it involved more suspects both inside the FPF and abroad and investigations are being very complex.
But, as we have never seen everything, which was not the biggest surprise, scandalous and shameful for the PJ, when journalists who were preparing to report the inauguration of Fernando Gomes as president of the Portuguese Olympic Committee, here comes the National Director of PJ, Luís Neves - recently reappointed in office - with Fernando Gomes next to him and begins to fire an absurd way of clarifying that he immediately clarifies that he immediately clarifies that he immediately clarifies that he immediately that he immediately that he immediately that he immediately that he immediately that he immediately that he immediately that of clarify that he immediately that he immediately that he immediately that of clarify that he immediately There are investigations of suspicion of corruption in the FPF, but there is always one but, that former President Fernando Gomes is unlawful of any suspicion and consequently innocent.
Did they read well? How could the PJ director ensure Fernando Gomes's total innocence when investigations were still underway in the city of Football, where computers, mobile phones and documentation were collected? When were the inspectors still requesting access to Fernando Gomes's email? Well, expensive readers, what we know was that it was the first time a PJ director has been publicly suspected of investigations that still took place, putting his head in the blind of suspicious potential.
Obviously our sources with the Public Prosecution Service transmitted us that the attitude of the PJ director caused immense discomfort within the "surplus" judicial investigation. A case never seen. After all, is corruption everywhere and that instead of a bidourado whistle will we have a trouted whistle?</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 06:06:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Ambush</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/28/emboscada/</link><description>When danger lurks is the body that speaks. We are able to decipher in record time our powerful transmitters that we will never know exactly where they come from. The impressive accuracy capacity is perhaps the hallmark of thought to adjust to the unlikely, a genius network of components that add themselves before any analysis: we can designate as prescience, strong angle, innate talent to survive. However, it will always be supernatural, for nature does not need in its constancy of such tears, to live, after all, it is not even a great danger, but there are times.
Just as the behalf of life are open, also in our favor, resources are added, and in this succession we call miracle, this arithmetic that we must not ask too much so that it always constitutes its own atmosphere.
Cultural Europe of constant and almost legendary ramifications does not gather its daily life roles in the lives of nations, and has been in an offensive entertainment in these hosts, often from a difficult to interpret, and not to be east and west, to the center, or within its periphery. The dogmas launched fell asleep their cultural charm that no clairvoyance can already awaken, that a certain base hedonism has crossed everything so that no one else feels empty times in the many enthusiasts, and this begins as we are seeing, crumbling in various ways. Looking better (far forever any conspiracy theory, emphatic, superficial, delirious model…) when we only have a certain and incisive observation of events, we know that there is much more not revealed. There is now no analysis that overcomes René Char's great conclusion: "The dangers always come from an angle that we were not waiting."
For those who entertain in this amalgam of sudden changes, for those who are sheltering in the nations' head hat, which are unaware of the initial purpose is so great that they run the danger of an ambush. It's like the Silk Route, China brought a product that reaching Mediterrane, people of the desert and other Damascus roads, found, never seeing the real faces they made of a larger art. Mongolia climbed up there with some affinities with these nomadic tribes, and no one also concluded that this whole region below had not been in the domain of the great seda. More: that outside it pioneer. And now make our superlative friends who disdain Europe as who hides a slave? This, no one knows.
But after all, what would they want Europe? For nothing. The fact that we are being reduced in this way is already extremely perfidious even compared to that majestic Roman phrase "the gods drive those who want to lose". If we are thinking that we are of unquestionable attractiveness, the problem beyond pathetic, it will be still tragic, laughable. Ultimately, and not to saturate the world of strategies further, who tells us that they are human who represent the factors of these abrupt changes? Artificial intelligence may be much further, and never exclude extraterrestrial participation in the domains of the now.
In our personal lines things are no better either; We are full of ambushes, addictive, delusional complexities that such a old continent of people, and so atonitious in the face of its presumption, is now unable to react with the prerogatives that make any defensive organism. We are paralyzed. We go and saw at tea time, we squeezed our hands, future skeletons, and smiled as if we didn't want to understand anything else. However, we were only an ordinary market. Our modern condition is nothing more, and as we should calculate, the market is always very little. We shared the ordinary goods, deluded the war, made the sports frames of former armies, only none of this now matters, nor the atomic French incentive, that these defensive people must understand them only as an added danger. Zelensky is a Jewish struggle outside of a non -promised land, but there was a time when Crimea could have been his state. All this is over and it's over time, but we all behaved like a reality. China gently says nothing until we fall all inanimate in our words.
There is anything much wider than all these positions. When all begins to run away as a destination, we must have the circumspection that can make us understand this new modified world.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:32:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence in Macao Culinary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/inteligencia-artificial-na-culinaria-de-macau-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the March 20 edition)
As the food industry adapts to new technologies, bosses take on new roles as curators of experiences rather than mere producers. The combination of human creativity with AI capabilities can lead to unparalleled gastronomic offers.
The impact of AI on consumer behavior cannot be ignored. The emergence of mobile applications that use AI algorithms to predict gastronomic preferences can change the way residents and tourists experience food in Macao. Food delivery services, such as FoodPanda and Uber Eats that do not yet operate in Macao, use AI to suggest restaurants based on users' habits and preferences.
This personalization increases customer satisfaction by presenting options that closely align with individual tastes. In addition, food sustainability is another critical area to which AI can contribute positively.
In Macao, like in other regions, there is increasing sensitization for the environmental impact of food production and waste. AI can optimize supply chain logistics, predict demand and reduce excesses, leading to more sustainable practices. For example, algorithms can analyze seasonal trends to suggest menus that align with available ingredients, reducing waste and ensuring that customers receive fresh offers.
Collaboration between food brands and AI development companies is also becoming predominant. Partnerships may arise with the aim of creating innovative culinary products that capitalize on AI data and knowledge.
For example, collaborations between chefs and technology companies can result in products designed specifically for Macanese cuisine, combining traditional recipes with AI -generated recommendations for the purchase and use of ingredients. The future of AI in the gastronomic landscape of Macau is promising. With continuous advances in automatic learning and data analysis, we can expect even greater AI integration into kitchens. For example, kitchen robots that may replicate the accuracy of human heads may become common.
These robots will be able to improve techniques such as cooking and precise emphasis, improving the consistency of food production. In addition, virtual reality and AI can join to revolutionize gastronomic experiences in Macao.
Imagine that customers can participate in virtual cooking classes guided by top chiefs, learning how to prepare traditional dishes while exploring the integration of Ia in real time. These experiences would promote culinary education, maintaining the essence of heritage. In the light of such advances, the ethical considerations surrounding AI in the culinary arts should also be carefully analyzed.
The question of the displacement of jobs due to automation is a pressing concern. As AI assumes tasks traditionally performed by humans, bosses and kitchen staff can see their functions evolve.
The formation and improvement of competences will become fundamental to ensure that cooking professionals can prosper in an IMI environments. Educational institutions in Macao must respond to this need, incorporating culinary technology courses in their curricula. This initiative will prepare aspiring bosses not only to dominate traditional cooking techniques, but also to understand the role of AI in modern kitchen.
By combining the traditional teaching of culinary arts with technology, the next generation of bosses can enjoy the best of both worlds. The use of AI in Macau cuisine means an important turning point in the way food is prepared, served and experienced.
By improving operational efficiency and customizing gastronomic experiences, AI brings a new era of culinary possibilities. Influential heads like André Chiang are leading the process, demonstrating how technology can coexist with tradition. However, the authenticity of Macanese cuisine should be preserved as we adopt these innovations.
By addressing this weighted integration, Macau can remain a vibrant gastronomic center, balancing the richness of his heritage with the exciting possibilities of the digital age.
The interaction between AI and traditional macao cuisine is a reflection of broader trends in the cooking arts globally. The trip of mixing the AI ​​with Macau's cultural heritage is just starting, but has a vast potential to shape the future of food. Resistance to embrace it can mean stagnation, while opening to innovation can lead to a prosperous and dynamic culinary scenario in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:53:47</pubDate></item><item><title>LIMITS OF WORK</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/limites-do-trabalho/</link><description>On March 17, the Hong Kong Census and Statistics Department released data showing that approximately 12,900 people worked on digital food delivery platforms and other goods over the past year.
52.5 percent of these workers are between 15 and 39 years old, more than half are less than 40 and 24.2 percent over 50 years. 64.7 percent of respondents stated that this work is their main source of income, 61 percent receives less than $ 5,000 from Hong Kong (HKD) per month and 37.1 percent earns more than 15,000 hkd a month.
53.9 percent work less than 44 hours a week, 24.9 percent over 44 hours per week and 21.2 percent of these workers claim not to have a fixed time. 68.6 percent work only for a delivery platform every day.
91.3 percent of respondents say they have started working in this business because it is easy to enter, having a flexible working method and having great control over methods and procedures. 98.2 percent claim to have more maneuver field to balance work with personal life. 45 percent are attracted to this work due to salary.
Other data previously issued by the Hong Kong government show that the average salary of these workers was 22,000 USD between October and December 2024. By comparison, only 37.1 percent earn more than 15,000 USD, showing that they usually receive wages below average.
Office employees in Hong Kong usually work from 9am to 6pm during the week and another four hours on Saturdays, which means a total of 49 hours of weekly work. Excluding the break from an hour for lunch from Monday to Friday, exactly 44 hours. Since 53.9 percent of distributors work less than 44 hours per week, it is reasonable that their salaries will be lower than the market average.
98.2 percent of people who make deliveries say they do this service by giving them more room to balance their work with family life. This demonstrates that the new generation pay more attention to the balance between work and personal life, a different phenomenon from the “tele-work” that emerged during the epidemic. The “tele-work” means working from home because it is difficult to evaluate the limit between work and family life.  As people working on delivery platforms can control their working hours, the problem of defining the border between work and leisure is very small.
The three main limits that define the exercise of labor functions are psychological, temporal and physical. Psychological boundaries are rules created by individuals who determine specific thoughts, behaviors and emotions, which means that one should have a rational attitude when working and an emotional attitude when one is in family. Time limits mean defining working hours, turning off duties outside this time, and dedicating this extra labor time to home and family. The physical limit is defined by the workplace. When you go to the office you will work, when you leave the work ended. The statistical data of delivery platforms show that people choose to collaborate with them mainly because they have more room to control their hours and work model. This phenomenon indicates that the new generation values ​​the existence of boundaries to work time and, in terms of psychological limits, seeks to have more control over their work.
In the post-epicide era, it is given greater importance to the balance between professional and family career. Limits theory helps companies understand and better manage work and family boundaries, thus achieving better balance and allowing workers' quality of life to improve.
In Hong Kong, delivery platform distributors earn less. Although it has a better notion of the limits of work and a happier family life, material goods that can give to the family are limited. These workers need to achieve balance between family life and material goods. From a business point of view, giving workers more space and flexibility, as well as broader borders, will help recruit a new generation of employees.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:26:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinematheque | “Flow”, Oscar winner, prominently in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/cinemateca-flow-vencedor-do-oscar-em-destaque-no-mes-de-abril/</link><description>“April charms” is there, with a new movie selection to see this month at Cinemateca Paixão. Highlight for “Flow - to Deriva”, which won the Oscar for Best Animation Movie this year, as well as “Dog on Trial” or “Four Trails”, among others
 
A bright black kitten tries to survive the flood of the world he knows. Suddenly, you have to share the space of a boat with other animals of completely different species, and ensure they live. “Flow - to Deriva” is a lesson of humanity and, perhaps, a reflection on climate change, depending on their eyes. It can now be seen at Cinemateca Paixão, starting this Friday, having three other sessions scheduled.
Gints Zilbalodis's “Flow - Flow” is a production of Latvia that surprised the half world and the Hollywood Academy, having won the Oscar for best animated film. The film's initial budget was US $ 3.6 million and its success surprised even the author of the film.
"We thought that at best we would be selected for some festivals and would have a good season of festivals," Zilbalodis, 30, told France-Presse (AFP). For Latvia, the two Oscar nominations were historical, as no movie in the Baltic country of only 1.8 million inhabitants had played an Oscar.
But "April charms" continues with other stories, already outside the world of animation. One of them is “dog on trial”, which can be seen from this Thursday. It is an out-of-vulgar story in which an Avril lawyer defends a dog in the court bar. The film eventually reveals comic and at the same time dramatic episodes around issues such as the judicial system, the rights of women and the animals themselves.
Adventures in Paris
Following is “Grand Maison Paris”, a Japanese movie spent in the French capital. The first session takes place today at 7:30 pm, followed by two more display dates. The story revolves around the opening of a Paris restaurant called "Grand Maison Paris", after the success obtained with the three -star Michelin winner "Grand Maison Tokyo."
Natsuki Obana and Rinko Hayami then ventured in Paris, wanting to be the first Asian bosses to get Michelin stars in the light city, but the challenges they face make adventure a much harder task than they thought. The protagonists must also deal with the pressure of a city full of well -known chiefs of French cuisine.
Another film, of the genre documentary, which can be seen from tomorrow is "Four Trails", although all the screening sessions are already sold out. This is a real story, that of Andre Blumberg, who left alone to run the four long distance iconic tracks from Hong Kong in just 72 hours. It's 298 kilometers, and over 14,500 meters unevenly later, one of the most difficult marathons in the world, with the name "Hong Kong Four Trails Ultra Challenge" was created. The documentary thus portrays the 2021 edition of this competition.
Inside the Asian films list is “Montages of A Modern Motherhood,” a Hong Kong movie this year, which will be screened on April 15 and 27. It is the story of Suk-Jing, which welcomes a baby daughter in your life, and that will never be the same. Speak Suk-Jing realizes that the day is too small for everything she has to do, complaining that her husband does not help her in this new maternity task. Family family dramas and reflections on the need for better days begin.
Within another section, “Ater Style-Double functionality”, the British director Mike Leigh's film on family ethics is also presented this Friday. The story revolves around the nervous pansy, with contrasting psychological behavior in the face of his sister, younger and more relaxed. In this movie, one can explore family relationships and the difficulties that exist to sometimes maintain harmony in these connections.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:24:39</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean artist Shin Min wins first edition of “MGM Discoveries”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/artista-sul-coreana-shin-min-vence-primeira-edicao-do-mgm-discoveries/</link><description>Shin Min, South Korean artist, was the winner of the first edition of the MGM Discoveries Art Award, awarded together by MGM and Art Basel de Hong Kong. According to a MGM statement, the artist, represented by Seoul's P21 gallery, won with an “innovative installation”, named “Ew! There is Hair in the Food !!!”, in which he used “a powerful symbolism and personal experiences to confront social norms and systemic injustices”.
According to the same note, Shin Min "expects this work to serve as a powerful tool to sensitize society and ultimately improve the working conditions of the population." The prize includes a monetary value of $ 50,000 and the "opportunity to be invited by MGM to hold an exhibition and participate in artistic exchanges in Macao."
The objective of the “MGM Discoveries” award is “to promote artistic diversity and connect Hong Kong, Macau and the world through iconic cultural events”, and this initiative “recognizes the originality and innovation of emerging international artists”, as well as “expanding their visibility in the global art world”.
Shared views
Kenneth Feng, president and executive director of MGM China Holdings Limited, said “MGM and Art Basel Hong Kong share the common vision of promoting global artistic and cultural development”, and this joint award “is a commitment to discovering emerging artists and celebrating its originality and creativity, offering a platform to develop its potential and grow”.
"In addition, through international cultural efforts, Macau is closely united with Hong Kong and the global stage, expanding the global network and the exchange of Macao," said the official.
Angelle Siyang-Le, director of Art Basel Hong Kong, said that the jury chose "Shin Min from a remarkable set of artists presented in the" Sector Discoveries ", which highlights emerging artists and galleries through individual presentations of recent projects."
MGM also organized a guided tour of Art Basel de Hong Kong, one of the most important art fairs in the world, for about 50 Macao's cultural and educational representatives. With this award, the game operator says she wants to “bring new artistic perspectives to Macau and the Great Bay”, as well as “a variety of international artistic and cultural activities”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 06:02:45</pubDate></item><item><title>IPOR | Literary Festival “Letras &amp; Companhia” starts this week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/ipor-festival-literario-letrascompanhia-arranca-esta-semana/</link><description>This Friday begins another edition of the Children's Festival “Letters &amp; Companhia”, organized by the Portuguese Institute of Oriente (IPOR), which brings a very current theme: the use of artificial intelligence in education. Highlight for the presence of Portuguese singer and writer Luísa Sobral and the presentation of the book illustrated “The Adventurous Journey of the Fatherland”, by Filipa Brito Pais
 
Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Education. This complex relationship, but increasingly present in our daily lives, is the central theme of this year's edition of the Literary and Cultural Festival for parents and children “Letras &amp; Company”, organized by the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) in partnership with the Portuguese Consulate General in Macau and Hong Kong. The event, which starts this Friday, April 4, and ends on May 6, also has a series of institutional support.
This year's theme is thus "artificial intelligence in education - the robot and me." One of the highlights of the poster is the presence of author and songwriter Luísa Sobral who launches the bilingual edition (Portuguese and Chinese) of her latest book, “The Weight of Words”.
According to a statement from IPOR, Luísa Sobral will “promote a set of workshops in local schools, as well as a concert open to the public” that takes place this Saturday, April 6.
Another highlight of the poster is the presentation of Joana Morgado Bento's book “The Seed of Love”, a work written in verse that has as its theme positive parenting. "The author's starting point for the writing of this book was the recognition of the inevitable imperfection of parents, of which a recognized difficulty is born: how to educate a child so that the child today is a happy adult tomorrow? Joana Morgado Bento will answer this and other questions, in a session directed to parents and children," writes Ipor.
In a collaboration with the Somos Association! - Portuguese Language Communication Association, will also be presented the book “Once upon a time… my language”, which resulted from a literary contest promoted by the entity. It is a work that brings together written tales of purpose for this contest, and all texts are translated and adapted to Chinese. The release of the book will be held through a shadow theater.
Remember the Fatherland
After a launch in Portugal, Filipa Brito Pais prepares to launch, at this festival, the book aimed at the youngest in Chinese language, “The Adventurous Trip of the Fatherland-from Portugal to Macao on plane (1924)”, which marks the 100th anniversary of the first Portuguese air trip-Macau. The author, a niece of aviator António Brito Pais, will make known to the younger ones the extraordinary feat of the three aviator and dreamers, António Brito Pais, José Manuel Sarmento de Beires and Manuel Gouveia, who at the time managed, with little financial support, to do what no one had been able to do until then.
The “Letras &amp; Company” also provides two workshops developed and boosted by Catarina Mesquita, founder of children's book publisher “Mandarina Books”, directed to children and young people. The two workshops, entitled “Usually…” and “Real or Artificial?”, Will aim to stimulate the creativity of the younger ones, either through a creative mechanism that involves the valorization of everyday and banal, either through an attitude that finds in doubt and sensory distrust a way to promote imagination.
Meditation and Training
Yoga instructor Ana Júlia Sampaio will be responsible for conducting two meditation sessions. “Happy Kids” will be an activity divided into two workshops, properly thought and adapted taking into account the age of the participants. These two sessions will help develop children's body, mental and emotional awareness.
The poster also features Macau Adelina Moura, a trainer of training courses and continuous training of teachers in the field of technologies in the classroom, as a member of the “Gilt-Games, Interaction and Learning Technologies” research group from Porto Engineering Institute.
At the festival, Adelina Moura will give teachers a training and teach the workshop “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions online”, where participants will be invited to reflect on topics such as application of strategies to protect digital identity and personal data online, the creation and responsible information sharing, the application of methods that can encourage online research and critical analysis of digital sources.
The festival also features a conference open to the general public, entitled “A AI in Education”, which takes place on April 16 with Adelina Moura, psychologist Nuno Gomes and researcher Min Yang of United Nations University Institute in Macau.
The theater is also present in “Letras &amp; Companhia” with two pieces, one of which is in charge of the company “Disrupt” that presents the show “Peripeças - The History of Portugal with Artificial Intelligence”, a comic piece about the power that narratives and stories take on this predominantly digital age.
The second theatrical representation, “The Peakture”, will be a nonverbal show developed by the local company “Stone Commune”, in which the body movements of the actors, puppets and some live video projections will be at the service of a moving story about the unthinkable obstacles that a simple trip can raise.
Also noteworthy is the initiatives “One Night in… Library”, which aims to stimulate the taste for reading through dramatized tales reading sessions, and the exhibition “The Robot and Me”, inaugurated on Friday. This show will present the works developed by artists from the region and students from local schools, with the special participation of artist José Nyögeri, who will expose a set of works of his own on the subject.
The festival was created in 2021 and revolves around the concept of the “three l's”: language, book and reading. For this edition, we seek to “address the introduction of technologies not only in teaching, but also in the lives of children”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 06:00:36</pubDate></item><item><title>SOAGAO | “Year 3” exhibition inaugurated today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/28/amagao-exposicao-ano-3-inaugurada-hoje/</link><description>It is today inaugurated, at Galeria Amagao, at Artyzen Grand Lapa, a new collective exhibition that marks the third anniversary of the gallery.
This is a show with 30 works by 29 artists, local and not only, with names such as Alexandre Marreiros, Abílio Febra, Clara Leitão, João Palla, Ieong Man Fai, Nuno Calçada Bastos or Suzy Bila, among others.
"This exhibition has the uniqueness of all artists have received an equal screen of 30 x 30 cm," he stands out in the same note. The inauguration of the show begins at 18:30. The Amagao Gallery is a project of Lina Ramadas and Victor Hugo Marreiros.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:29:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Tui reduces resident sentence for fatal crime in Zhuhai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/tui-reduz-pena-de-residente-por-crime-fatal-em-zhuhai/</link><description>The last court (TUI) decided to reduce the penalty of a 44 -year -old resident in August 2023 for killing another resident in Zhuhai. It all happened on a night of night fun that ended the worst way, in the Gongbei area, and the two men began to argue on the street when the murderer decided to attack the other resident with two scissors blows.
The Base Judicial Court (TJB) sentenced the resident to an effective 15 -year prison for the practice, in material authorship and in a consummate form, of a crime of homicide. In addition, the resident was ordered to pay compensation of more than two million patacas to the widow, with interest. It was then that the murderer decided to appeal to the court of second instance, because he did not agree with the sentence, and Tui has now reduced this sentence to 13 years and nine months.
Unintentionally “direct”
According to the TUI judgment, the murderer requested the reduction of the sentence claiming that it was under the influence of alcohol and did not know that scissors could effectively kill the other resident. In addition, the applicant claimed that the police had been called before assaulting the man with the scissors. However, Tui understands that "such circumstances are not valid and effective to exclude their guilt as to conduct and its responsibility."
Tui understands that a situation of "eventual deceit" is at stake and not a "direct" intention of killing the other, so it was possible to be possible "a moderate reduction in the penalty".
The details of the case are described in the ruling: the two men were, around 12:02 am on July 31, 2023 eating with the deceased's wife and seven friends, and the murderer drank “three to four beer bottles”, some of them gone to play Mahjong to follow. The discussion between the two men took place around 3:50 am "for trivial reasons", becoming "increasingly serious."
Friends tried to separate them unsuccessfully. Around four in the morning, the murderer “abandoned Mahjong's establishment, running, took a scissors from a fruit store with which he gave several blows to the left side of his left -handed chest, arm and forearm and thumb of the left hand” of the deceased. The death was declared at 4:15 am by the Zhuhai Public Security Police. The perpetrator was arrested at the entrance of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Portsmouth will investigate maritime energy transition in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/portsmouth-vai-investigar-transicao-energetica-maritima-em-macau/</link><description>Macao was one of the places selected by the University of Portsmouth to study the inheritance of the energy transition in the coastal communities of the global southern and how they cross the age of decarbonization, the project officer told Lusa.
After the Port of Callao, in the center of Peru, Macau was the choice of the University of Portsmouth in the United Kingdom to investigate as maritime communities from the so -called global south crossed one of the milestones of the Industrial Revolution, the transition from sail to steam.
Relief commercial warehouse, Macao has a very rich story linked to the sea, a factor that weighed on the center's decision and maritime cultures (PCMC, British acronym) at the British University. "It is probably one of the first European enclaves in East Asia and has a long history of international travel by the sea from 1500," Melanie Bassett researcher Lusa told Lusa.
The creation of a doctoral research scholarship will bring to the territory an academic, whose mission is still to understand how these communities can adapt to a sustainable future. "We then want to look at the new energy transitions, to decarbonization, how Macau is making this transition and if people are aware of the changes," added Bassett, who leads the project "From Steam to Green to Green: Empower port communities in the global south [Sail to Steam, Carbon to Green: Empowering Port Communitiesin The Global South]" Portsmouth.
The project, which extends for a period of six and a half years, started in February, with the investigation to focus on the Peruvian Port of Callao, but should later expand to two other regions “somewhere in the Indian subcontinent and West Africa”.
Understand the past
Only the investigation will bring tangible results, but Bassett points out that, with the primacy of the steam vessel, the travel of communities and industries were generally away from the sea waterfront. Changes have also occurred in several businesses linked to the sector, from the fishing industry to naval construction. “We anticipate seeing this kind of changes, but also with the advent of European colonization, we see changes in cultures and architecture and how it affects the population, and then how, over time, these cultures merge and hybridize to create new cultures and new understandings of the world,” he said.
“It's part of Lloyds Register Foundation's financing to learn from the past,” Bassett added, referring to the project's funder who, in the case of Macao, will have the collaboration of the University of Macao and the local Maritime Museum.
It is also expected to have the communities active in research. Therefore, the recruitment of the academic that will lead the investigation requires language skills to ensure communication with the population. Recruitment for this research that is divided between Portsmouth and Macau is expected to be completed in April, and the project starts in October.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:18:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Takeaway | Up to 50% tariffs threaten restoration</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/takeaway-tarifas-de-ate-50-ameacam-restauracao/</link><description>Home food delivery applications touched the restoration sector to the wall, imposing high delivery rates and changing customer habits. The Macao Catering Industry Association says APPs threaten business survival and calls for government intervention
 
When the COVID-19 pandemic forced social isolation and distancing, the mere act of taking a meal away from home became a nightmare. From this time, it became common to see the Macao roads full of MFood and Aomi scooters, and later to Tikbee. Finding the restrictions on combating pandemic, remained the habit of asking for meals, drinks and desserts through these platforms, and complaints from the restoration sector began to emerge.
The president of the Macao Catering Industry Association, Aeson Law, has been one of the critical voices of how applications have changed the industry and forced restaurants to pay high delivery fees or abdicate a popular way to do business.
"When there were no Takeaway platforms, if we faced 100 patacas, this value entered the box. Nowadays we even delivered 50 of these 100 patacas to applications, as well as the operating costs of a restaurant. It is difficult to survive in this scenario," said the representative, quoted by the citizen newspaper.
The associative leader recalls that meal delivery platforms began by charging more than 20 percent of the amount charged to the customer as a distribution tariff, which considered reasonable. However, "apps also started charging distribution or delivery tariff to customers," he said, raising prices. As such, they ended up “asking traders to pay the slice that should be paid by the consumer,” he said.
Do something
Aeson Law does not realize why applications have been charging twice distribution rates. The fact is that restaurants are required to pay twice if they want to occupy a summit place in the ranking of applications.
With the double collection, the applications are about 40 percent of the online sales of restaurants, a slice that grows to 50 percent during discount campaigns. Aeason Law considers that the only way to control excessive charges is through government intervention, as restaurants do not have negotiating power to cope with the prevalence of online platforms.
Thus, the representative of the sector expects the executive to elaborate a law that will introduce a mechanism for supervising the online platform action and complaint presentation.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:17:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Islands Hospital | Extended aesthetic and vaccine services</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/hospital-das-ilhas-alargados-servicos-de-estetica-e-de-vacinas/</link><description>The director of health services, Alvis Lo, states that throughout this year will be expanded the aesthetic services and external vaccination consultations of the islands hospital. The future also undergoes cooperation with dealers to bet on more health tourism services
 
The availability of aesthetic and vaccine services abroad at Hospital das Ilhas will be extended throughout this year. The confirmation of the new services came from Alvis Lo, director of health services, and is the response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U.
The availability of these services is part of the government's strategy to bet on health tourism, presented as Big Health. As part of this strategy, Alvis Lo explains that the Islands Hospital will “take full advantage of the notoriety of the Peking Union Medical College Hospital brand”, which explores the services available, not only at the level of services provided, but also to collaborate in terms of research and health partnerships.
Regarding the services provided, Alvis Lo points out that aesthetics and external vaccines services are currently available. Regarding the area of ​​aesthetics, the doctor points out that "the initial focus lies in facial rejuvenation" is being performed with "resort to the most advanced medical equipment of Hong Kong and Macau". In this service, it is also indicated that “16 therapeutic projects” are being implemented, including using “Picosecond laser” technologies and “radio -ferotement microagulating”.
Regarding vaccination, it is indicated that the islands hospital offers five types of vaccines abroad among which the Nanavalent Vaccine against Human Papillomavirus (HPV), the zoster herpes vaccine and the pneumococcal vaccine.
Expansion of services
Throughout this year, Alvis Lo also points out that the Islands Hospital will “further expand the supply of aesthetic and vaccination medicine projects” and create “new specific external consultation services”, such as “weight loss consultations and cancer prevention”.
In the future, Alvis Lo indicates that the path will progressively implement “private ward services” and “Individual Health Management Projects” to achieve “constant progress in medical tourism and Big Health industry”.
On the other hand, the doctor indicates that the islands hospital is “attracting more and more tourists to visit Macau” to receive “medical care and health care”.
In addition, in response to Chan U law it is indicated that tourism services will launch other “medical tourism services, actively promoting cooperation between the Macao tourist sector and the various integrated tourism and leisure companies for the development of tourist products focused on medical care, well-being and therapeutic food”. Alvis Lo points out will also be “launched several accommodation promotions and the promotion [of medical services] will be intensified with the target markets”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:15:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Earthquake | Macao with alert to Thailand and CE expresses condolences</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/sismo-macau-com-alerta-para-a-tailandia-e-ce-expressa-condolencias/</link><description>The executive issued a travel alert signal to Thailand following the magnitude 7.7 earthquake on the Richter scale and received a request for assistance and seven information. Sam Hou Fai sent a message of condolences to the population of Myanmar, where the dead of the dead yesterday exceeded 1,600
 
On Saturday night, Sam Hou Fai addressed “a message of condolences to Myanmar's leader, Min Aung Hlaing, following the earthquake that shook the region,“ expressing its senses condolences, condolences and attention and solidarity with the victims' wounded and relatives ”.
At 2:50 pm, Macao's time, a lattice of magnitude 7.7 on the Richter scale, and with epicenter near the Myanmar capital, shook the Earth, and 11 minutes later a 6.7 replica was followed by Richter scale. The earthquake felt in Thailand and several Chinese provinces, with greater intensity in Yunnan, but also in Gizhou, Guangxi and Sichuan, in Laos, Vietname, Bangladesh and India. However, Myanmar was the most affected country, with fatal counting yesterday to 1,644 dead.
In the note published Saturday night, the chief executive demonstrated the grief and stressed the strong bonds of friendship between the peoples of Macau and Myanmar.
"It was with great dismay that I received the information of the occurrence of strong intensity earthquake in Myanmar. (…) In the name of the government of Masters and the population, we address our most senses condolences, condolences and solidarity, to the entire population of Myanmar, with special attention to the families of the deceased, the injured and residents in the most affected areas."
Sam Hou Fai also stated that "Macao residents have empathy and are solidary," and "available to provide, within our abilities, all the necessary support for rescue and later reconstruction work."
Full attention
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) reacted just over an hour to the first shake, noting that people who are traveling should “pay attention to their personal security, be vigilant and carefully follow the evolution of the situation”.
Still on Friday night, the MSar issued to Thailand the travel alert level 1, the lowest of a total of three levels, which was already in force for Myanmar, but due to the civil war in the country. According to STD, this level "represents the emergence of a threat to personal security."
STD also revealed that it had received a request for help from a resident of Macao who lost a flight due to the closure of roads that prevented him from reaching the airport, and seven requests for information.
Although there are no organized excursions from Macau either in Thailand or Myanmar, STD has sent messages to 1,475 mobile phones registered in the territory that were accessing roaming services in both countries or neighboring Laos.
No excursions
After Friday's earthquake, which had an epicenter at Myanmar, the president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association, Andy Wu, confirmed that there was no Macao excursion at Myanmar, Thailand nor in the Chinese province of Yunnan at the time of shaking.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, the official revealed that the direction of tourism services immediately contacted the travel agencies of the territory to find out if they took excursions in the affected regions.
However, Andy Wu stressed the inevitability of residents in the affected areas and revealed that, despite the significant volume of the information request, there was no dropouts to the areas affected by the earthquake, which will be made during Easter holidays and Cheng Ming.
Replica of 5.1
A 5.1 magnitude earthquake on Richter scale yesterday shook Mandalay in downtown Myanmar (former Birmania), being a replica of the 7.7 magnitude earthquake that caused more than 1,600 dead and 3,400 wounded.
The United States Geological Service (USGS) stated that yesterday's tremor had its epicenter 28 kilometers northwest of Mandalay and a hypotrocemine at a depth of 10 kilometers. Until the closing of this edition, there was no record of victims or material damage to this latest earthquake. Lame</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:47:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal leads European delegation to the International Tourism Fair</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/portugal-lidera-delegacao-europeia-a-feira-internacional-de-turismo/</link><description>Professionals from the tourist sector and Portuguese journalists will lead a European delegation to the Macao International Tourism Fair, from 25 to 27 April, Lusa told the region's authorities.
The Directorate of Macao Tourism Services (STD) has revealed that a European delegation will participate in the 13th International Tourism Expo (Industry) of Macau (Mite). In a written response, STD added that the delegation is being organized by the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies (APAVT).
Macao will host in June the semi -sectional meeting of the European Confederation of Travel Agency Associations and Tour Operators (ECTAA). “I think it's a good start,” said STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes on January 17.
"Although it will have less than 100 people, they represent 80,000 travel agencies from all over Europe in all," said the leader. "This is also a result of good collaboration between us and APAVT, because it was through APAVT that we were introduced to Ectaa," said Senna Fernandes.
Lusitanian aid
Senna Fernandes added that Portugal can help the region attract more visitors from the rest of Europe. “Portugal is not just about reaching Portugal. Portugal also serves to help us reach the European market,” said Senna Fernandes.
In April 2024, Ectaa Vice President Heli Mäki-Fränti told Lusa during the 12th Mite that the meeting in the territory happens “at initiative” of APAVT. It will be the second time that Ectaa has gathered outside Europe after Kuala Lumpur in Malaysia. The Confederation also chose Macau as a favorite destination for 2025.
The territory wants to attract more international visitors and this year alone, participated in the Madrid International Tourism Fair in January and at ITB Berlin, the largest travel fair in the world, between March 4, as well as seminars in the United Arab Emirates and Saudi Arabia.
Macau was not present at the Lisbon Tourism Stock Exchange (BTL), which took place between March 12 and 16, but STD assured that Portugal remains “a priority market”.
STD recalled that Macau will host, between December 2 and 4, the 50th APAVT Congress, “considered the largest annual meeting of the Portuguese tourist industry and which is expected to gather between 700 and 800 participants”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:43:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Legend | Confirmed losses of 667.2 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/macau-legend-confirmadas-perdas-de-6672-milhoes/</link><description>Given the announced loss and the accumulated debts of $ 2.51 billion from Hong Kong, Macau Legend Development admits that its future is concerned
 
Macao Legend Development (MLD) announced on Friday that the damage of the game operator fired in 2024, in part due to the decision of the Government of Cape Verde to recover an unfinished hotel in the capital. The results confirm the losses that had been anticipated early last week.
According to a report sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, MLD lost $ 667.2 million from Hong Kong last year. By 2023, the company had registered a loss of less than three million dollars from Hong Kong.
MLD estimated a loss of Hong Kong's $ 45.9 million after the Cape Verdean government on November 18, formalizing the reversal of the company's Hotel and other unfinished works of the company, at Santa Maria Island and Gamboa's waterfront, in Praia.
The operator reiterated on Friday that she is "taking the necessary measures to safeguard the interests of the group (..), including exploring all available options to contest the decision." On the other hand, MLD admitted to “significant doubts about the group's ability to continue in activity” due to total debt of $ 2.51 billion from Hong Kong.
Bad investments
In 2015, the then MLD leader, David Chow Kam Fai, signed an agreement for an investment of 250 million euros. After revisions, five and a half years ago, the conclusion of the first phase was scheduled for 2021.
In recent years, there are only guards at the venues of the venue, an area of ​​about 160,000 square meters, which includes the partially sulved Santa Maria islet and, a paved bridge of a few meters that connects it to a building of about eight floors, empty and sealed with Taipal.
The government said it gave Macao Legend "all opportunities for the resuming of works or to negotiate the sale of actions or the assignment of its contractual position to a potential interested in the continuation of the project," but no alternatives were presented.
“Given that the MLD has violated, flagrant and repeatedly, the obligations (…) there is no other way out of the State of Cape Verde, other than to resolve” the contracts, reads a decision of the Council of Ministers. According to the executive, the company "also violated" the legal regime of exploitation of games, "by transferring, without authorization from the Government of Cape Verde, the ownership of more than 20 percent of the capital capital."
In late 2023, in an interview with Hong Kong TVB television, Macau Legend's president and executive director, Li Chu Kwan, said the group intended to end the projects in Cape Verde and Cambodia by 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:41:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us his wife and daughter (cf. Recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: High there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails about sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim committed himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>South Sea | Beijing discovers large oil deposit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/mar-do-sul-pequim-descobre-grande-jazida-de-petroleo/</link><description>Chinese oil company Cnooc discovered an important oil field in the east of the Southern Sea of ​​China, with proven reserves of over 100 million tons, the state press said yesterday.
According to Chinese official news agency Xinhua, the identified field, Huizhou 19-6, is about 170 kilometers from the city of Shenzhen in the south of the country. Test drilling produced 413 barrels of raw and 68,000 cubic meters of natural gas per day, according to the same source.
Proven reservations of the oil field, ie the amount of hydrocarbons whose recovery can be almost certainly estimated using current techniques, ascend to more than 100 million tons, according to the information cited by Xinhua.
Southern China's underground is largely sub-pitched due to territorial disputes, but most known oil and gas deposits are in non-contested areas, according to the US energy information administration.
Beijing claims the sovereignty of almost the whole sea, over which the Philippines, Malaysia, Vietnam, Indonesia and Brunei also have claims.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>XI Jinping stimulates investment in meeting with foreign entrepreneurs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/xi-jinping-estimula-investimento-em-encontro-com-empreendedores-estrangeiros/</link><description>On the morning of Friday, March 28, XI Jinping met with “representatives of the international business community” at the Great People's Hall in Beijing. “The reason I have invited all present is to hear your ideas, respond to your concerns and support the development of foreign companies in China,” explained the president in the initial words of his intervention, paying tribute to the numerous benefits that foreign companies brought to the country.
"China's impressive achievements are not only due to the Communist Party and the Chinese people, but also to the support and help of the international community, including the contribution of foreign companies operating in China," said XI.
"Foreign companies represent a third of China's total imports and exports, a quarter of their industrial value added and a seventh of their tax revenues, creating more than 30 million jobs," he explained.
For Xi, foreign companies are “important participants in Chinese modernization, the country's renovation, opening and innovation, and their interconnectivity with the world and integration into economic globalization”. Therefore, “here I would like to express my sincere gratitude to all the foreign companies that participated and supported the development of China!” He concluded.
Many will say that the Chinese president is, in the background, to respond to the growing pessimism of multinational companies in relation to the Chinese market, evidenced by the fall in foreign direct investment. Xi acknowledged, although diplomatically, that "in recent years, foreign companies have indeed found some difficulties in their development in China." Facing the problem directly is undoubtedly better than pretending it does not exist.
But it was more detailed than ever, for example, by recognizing that multinationals often cannot access business opportunities despite role market openings. “We will work to resolve the issue of 'large open doors, but small closed doors' in market access, ensuring that companies with foreign investment are not only able to go into open sectors, but also enjoy full and fair access to operations.”
The president acknowledged that multinationals are often discriminated against, stressing that it has long been that “foreign companies in China should benefit from national treatment, with equal application of laws, equal status and equal treatment. We will ensure that foreign companies have fair and legal access to production factors”, admitting that multinationals cannot often benefit from public contracts in China, promising: promising: "We will ensure that products manufactured in China by foreign companies can participate in public contracts on an equal foot, according to the law."
Trump a and the WTO
Many will say that Xi is taking advantage of Trump's shock. Their comments are normal for Chinese standards, including "many foreign companies, especially multinational companies, have a substantial global influence. We hope to speak right, act with pragmatism, firmly oppose retrograde movements that retreat the clock of history, reject zero -sum and promote cooperation and mutual benefit."
While Trump suspends US financing for the World Trade Organization (WTO), Xi reinforces the WTO: “The multilateral trade system, with the World Trade Organization at its core, is the cornerstone of international trade… We must defend the principles and rules of the WTO, continue to advance the liberalization and facilitation of trade and investment and encourage all countries to expand the development of shared development through greater opening.
Xi also promised greater internal opening: “The reduction of the market access threshold will be a key priority in the next opening phase. I specifically stressed that opening measures should be completed earlier than later. This year, we will widen the opening programs in selected areas and accelerate opening in sectors such as culture and education.”
XI has promised that China is not interested in any military conflict, stating that "it will be unobailably a path of peaceful development, it will actively promote the resolution of important international and regional issues and will strive to create a favorable environment for foreign companies."
On Friday night, Beijing promptly announced the full comments of Xi, beyond his usual reading. This is a sign of the emphasis given to meetings with foreign companies. Complete comments also help, as they serve as a reference, more officially and conveniently, for cunning political operators, including, expecting, experts in governmental matters and public relations of multinationals, who should use them as a valuable tool in their transactions in China.
Of the foreign participants at the meeting with XI, 14 of the 38 were Americans, 10 Germans, 6 British, 3 French, 2 Japanese, 2 Koreans and one from Switzerland, Denmark, Sweden, Brazil and Saudi Arabia. Despite BRICS and Global South, when it comes to foreign and multinational investment, the West continues to play a central role. Foreigners gathered are officially described by China as “representatives of the international business community”.
“Security Oasis”
FedEx Corporation President Raj Subrmaniam, Mercedes-Benz Group AG chairman, hello Källenius, Sanofi SA executive director Paul Hudson, HSBC Holdings PLC executive director, Georges Elhedery, Hitachi Ltd. Tosiaki Executive President SK Hynix Inc. Kwak Noh-Jung, and the President of Saudi Aramco Amin Nasser were some of those who intervened at the meeting.
Representatives of foreign companies “praised China for achieving stable economic growth through deep and comprehensive reform and a high -level opening under the leadership of President XI,” says Xinhua.
From “Made in China” to “new quality productive forces”, China has enhanced industrial transformation and modernization through innovation, being prepared to perform a higher quality and more sustainable development.
The perspectives of the Chinese economy are strong, because in the midst of growing protectionism, China has continually expanding its opening, injecting stability in the global economy, and has become a "oasis of certainty" for investment and entrepreneurship. "China's development is the main driving force of the world economy and offers vast and exciting opportunities and growth potential," he was mentioned.
According to Xinhua, foreign representatives “applauded Chinese government efforts to create a fair and favorable environment for foreign companies and expressed their availability to expand investment cooperation with China, cultivate the Chinese market, actively participate in the modernization of China and build bridges for the exchange and cooperation of China with the world, and also expressed their availability to support an open world market, defend international free trade and contribute to the development of the world economy. ”</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:21:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine | Lula da Silva will talk to Putin and Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/ucrania-lula-da-silva-vai-falar-com-putin-e-zelensky/</link><description>Brazilian President Lula da Silva said Saturday that he will have separated conversations with leaders from Russia and Ukraine, Vladimir Putin and Volodymyr Zelensky, respectively, about the need to negotiate an eventual end of the war.
During a press conference in Hanoi at the end of an official three-day visit to Vietnam, the South American leader said that bringing peace back to Ukraine, invaded by Russia since February 2021, would be "the best thing" to both countries, but also for Europe and the rest of the world.
“In a conflict, both sides have to be willing to negotiate,” said Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, who intends to visit Putin in Moscow on May 9 on the occasion of the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II.
"Peace destroys and peace builds ... I will discuss this with Putin again," he added. The President of the Republic also said that he will talk to Zelensky by telephone, "this week" without specifying the day.
Brazil has repeatedly condemned the Russian invasion, but has raised skepticism of much of the West and Ukraine itself for the peace proposal in 2024, in partnership with China. This week, the United States issued two separate statements about their contacts with Russia and Ukraine in Riade, a Saudi capital, under the negotiations for a possible end of the conflict.
The parties, which continue to attack each other, have agreed to ensure safe navigation, eliminate the use of force and prevent the use of commercial ships for military purposes in the Black Sea, as well as developing measures to ban attacks on energy facilities in both countries.
Despite the huge costs of the Russian invasion, most Ukrainians are in favor of resistance and not surrender in case of full withdrawal of Washington's support, since Europe remains by its side, according to a poll from the Kiev International Institute of Sociology (Kiis).</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 06:07:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Earthquake / Myanmar |  Xi Jinping expresses “condolences” and sends aid</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/sismo-myanmar-xi-jinping-expressa-condolencias-e-envia-auxilio/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping expressed on Saturday the "condolences" to the leader of the Burmese Board, Min Aung Hlaing, after the earthquake that shook the country of Southeast Asia the country, leaving more than 1,600 dead.
The Armed Forces of Burma, which have power since the 2021 coup d'etat dived the country in a semi-Annarch and a wide conflict, declared the state of emergency in six zones: Sagaing, Mandalay, Magway, Shan, Naipyidó and berry.
A team of 37 Chinese rescuers arrived on Saturday at Myanmar, according to the official news agency Xinhua. The group, which departed this morning of Yunnan, a Chinese province bordering the Burma, is equipped with emergency relief material such as life detectors, early warning systems of earthquakes and drones, and it is expected to help with “medical care and care work,” he added.
Seen other members of Blue Sky Rescue (BSR), one of China's leading non-governmental humanitarian organizations, set out to Ruili's Burmeania in Yunnan province, at 9:30 am on Saturday, transporting first aid kits, power generators and demolition tools in five vehicles.
"We are the first team and we will be followed by a second and third group," said Gao Hengyi, head of the BSR Ruili Branch, in a statement also released by Xinhua. A spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry said on Friday night that China is prepared to "do everything possible" by Burma, which Beijing considers a "neighbor friend."</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:57:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing asked Lisbon reciprocity in the exemption of visas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/pequim-pediu-a-lisboa-reciprocidade-na-isencao-de-vistos/</link><description>China has asked Portugal to facilitate the entry of its citizens, as there is an exemption from visas since October 2024 to Portuguese who moves to the Asian country, Chinese ambassador Zhao Bentang said on Friday.
"China has already asked Europe, Portugal, which facilitates the entry to Chinese citizens. If the Portuguese can go very easily to China to do business, their partners in China want to come and they can't or it's very difficult," he said.
In an interview with Lusa, the Chinese diplomat in Portugal said that the “Chinese government expects the Portuguese government, European governments to also make it easier for tourists, traders and Chinese businessmen on the subject of visas”.
"We always talked to the Portuguese government. I spoke many times. I believe that during the visit of the minister [Portuguese foreign business, Paulo Rangel] also the Chinese part spoke of this theme," added the ambassador, referring to the trip of the chief of Portuguese diplomacy to the Asian country, which ended on Friday, with a visit to Macau and Hong Kong (see big plan).
Zhao Bentang recalled that since October 2024 the Portuguese can travel to China without the need for seen, under certain conditions, following a “unilateral policy” and whose final is scheduled for December.
"But [the continuity of the exemption] depends on the appreciation, the demand. I believe that when it comes to height, if necessary, the Chinese part may consider some extension, some renewal. But it has not yet come to evaluate," he said.
At the end of September 2024, China announced the extension of the visa exemption policy to Portuguese citizens, in stay up to 15 days, thus inserting Portugal into a list that covered another 16 European countries.
The enlargement, which was confirmed in a statement by the Chinese Foreign Ministry, appears after Beijing included Norway, Slovenia, Greece, Denmark and Cyprus on the list of countries whose citizens can remain in the Asian country for tourism, business or traffic for 15 days, exempt from visa. The measure came into force on October 15, 2024 and in force until December 31, 2025.
Reopened doors
Beijing tries to stimulate international tourism and foreign investment, paralyzed by the Covid-19 pandemic, during which China imposed an almost total closure of the borders.
In November 2023, the Asian country announced that the nationals of France, Germany, Italy, the Netherlands and Spain would benefit from a unilateral visa exemption. In March 2024, he extended policy for stay of up to 15 days to six other European countries - Switzerland, Ireland, Hungary, Austria, Belgium and Luxembourg.
When the 20th anniversary of the global strategic partnership between Lisbon and Beijing marks, the visit of the china's head of Portuguese diplomacy, which “gives a very important sign” because it is said about “good cooperation in all areas,” said Zhao Bentang.
“The return of Macao [China] is an example of how to solve problems through peaceful negotiations between countries” and in the Portuguese support “one country, two systems, supports Macao to develop and maintain in stability and adapt to new realities”, as well as foster the quality of bilateral relations.
Zhao Bentang also noticed the “importance” of Paulo Rangel's visit as it was the “first” of a European diplomacy leader after the recent annual session of the National Popular Assembly.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:56:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Beijing, Tokyo and Seoul respond to Trump with acceleration of agreements</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/31/comercio-pequim-toquio-e-seul-respondem-a-trump-com-aceleracao-de-acordos/</link><description>China, Japan and South Korea respond to US administration attacks and place mechanisms to accelerate free trade agreements
 
Japan, South Korea and China announced yesterday that they intend to reinforce cooperation and provide a “predictable environment” to companies and “accelerate” negotiations on a free trade agreement that responds to US uncertainties.
The ministers of industry and commerce of the three countries yesterday held an emergency meeting in Seoul, designed to settle policies to respond to the acceleration of tariff increases imposed by Washington - a tripartite emergency meeting and the first in this format since 2020.
South Korean Industry Minister Ahn Duk-Geun, his Japanese counterpart, Yoji Muto, and Chinese trade minister Wang Wenta agreed to “pursue discussions to accelerate negotiations for a comprehensive trilateral trade agreement” and “fair” according to a joint statement.
Discussions about this agreement began in 2013 and continued until 2019, when they stagnated. They were relaunched in 2024, in a special tripartite summit, which brought together the leaders of the three countries in Seoul.
For now, “we will continue to work to ensure equitable competition conditions at the world, in order to promote a predictable, free, fair, non -discriminatory, transparent and inclusive commercial, free, non -discrimination environment,” adds the joint statement.
For the three countries, the objective is to “gradually intensify their cooperation” in order to “create a predictable commercial environment, stabilize supply chains and improve communication on export controls”, insisted Seoul in a separate statement.
More generally, Seoul, Beijing and Tokyo yesterday agreed to “work closely” to promote the Reform of the World Trade Organization (WTO) and encourage new members to join the vast Economic Economic Partnership (RCEP), which brings together China and 14 Asian countries.
Among them, China, Japan and South Korea represent about 20 percent of the world's population, a quarter of the world economy and 20 percent of global trade.
Under "fire"
The tripartite meeting arises after the US Administration of Donald Trump, in mid-March, 25-percent customs rights on steel and aluminum, a few days before the imposition, from April 2, of 25-percent customs of customs on the United States.
Japan and South Korea represent, respectively, 16 percent and 15 percent of total US imports from the United States, an important sector for their national economies.
China, for its part, faces a total of a total of 20 percent over all its exports to the United States. There is also the spectrum of “reciprocal” customs rights, which Washington also threatens to impose from next week.</description><pubDate>2025-03-31 05:55:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Lula says Trump “is not the sheriff of the world” and threatens reciprocal tariffs in Brazil</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/28/lula-diz-que-trump-nao-e-o-xerife-do-mundo-e-ameaca-tarifas-reciprocas-do-brasil/</link><description>Brazilian President Lula da Silva yesterday criticized his US homologist Donald Trump, who "is not the sheriff of the world," according to Lula, threatening to react with "reciprocity" to US tariffs on Brazilian steel imports.
At a press conference yesterday in Tokyo, during his state visit, Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva said that Brazil has "two decisions to make" in response to 25 percent rates that came into force this month: the first is to resort to the World Trade Organization (WTO) and, if it does not work, "resort to other tools".
Lula specifically mentioned the option of “increasing tariffs on American products” imported by Brazil, which defined as “putting into practice the law of reciprocity”. "What we can't do is be silent, thinking that only they can impose tariffs," he said.
"I am very concerned about US government policy because of these rates on all products from all countries," Lula told the press in Tokyo at the end of his visit when asked about the new 25 percent tariffs on all US imported cars from April 2, announced the day before Trump.
"I am concerned because free trade is being harmed, because multilateralism is being defeated, and I am concerned because the American president is not the sheriff of the world, he is only the president of the United States," said the Brazilian leader.
Instead of imposing “unilateral measures”, Lula considers that it would be more appropriate to “talk to other leaders” to reach a beneficial price policy agreement for all parties.
"Honestly, I don't know the benefit of increasing tariffs on the cars bought in Japan," said the Brazilian leader of Asian country, one of the most affected by new commercial measures in the United States, given the weight of his automotive industry.
"The only thing this is going to do is to make cars more expensive for US consumers and increase inflation," said Lula, who also pointed out the risk of higher prices leading to economic contraction.
Leaders according to
Lula arrived in Japan on Monday for a four-day state visit, which ended yesterday, before going to Vietname, where he is expected to meet Vietnamese Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh, and Vietnamese President Luong Cuong.
In a summit held the day before Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba, the two leaders agreed to launch joint decarbonization initiatives and reinforce commercial ties, with a future free trade agreement between the Asian country and Mercosur on the horizon and the current context of commercial war and climate negationism.
During the visit, the Brazilian president stressed the message that democracy, free trade and multilateralism are in danger worldwide in the face of increased protectionism, authoritarianism, and the “new cold war” between the United States and China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:33:17</pubDate></item><item><title>BOAO FORUM | Beijing asks Asian countries to oppose protectionism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/28/forum-boao-pequim-pede-aos-paises-asiaticos-que-se-oponham-ao-proteccionismo/</link><description>Chinese vice-master-master, Ding Xuexiang, yesterday asked “resolute opposition to protectionism” at the Forum dedicated to economic cooperation in the Asia-Pacific region.
"Asia has become the world's most dynamic region in terms of development and growth potential," said Ding Xuexiang, deputy Chinese-prime minister, in his intervention at the event, which was attended by Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel.
"Asia has actively opened its doors and took the initiative to integrate into the world," said the Chinese official, in a period of growing commercial frictions the United States and the rest of the world.
Ding Xuexiang stated that the region should “work together to protect free trade, adhere to open regionalism and resolutely oppose commercial and investment protectionism”. He appealed to the “resolution of differences and differences through dialogue and consultation” and defended “opening, cooperation and economic globalization” as “inevitable choices” for the region.
The deputy minister said China's economic performance “remains stable” and that “industry growth rates, consumption, investment and other indicators in the first two months of this year were higher than those last year”.
Ding said authorities “will implement more pro-active macroeconomic policies” and “expand internal demand on all fronts” at a time when weak internal consumption raises deflationary pressures in the world's second largest economy.
The leader added that the Chinese government will "promote the healthy development of real estate and scholarship more vigorously." The forum, which runs until Friday under the theme “Asia in a change world: towards a shared future,” said the resilience of the region in a global environment marked by geopolitical tensions.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tiktok | Beijing rejects Trump's offer to reduce rates</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/28/tiktok-pequim-rejeita-oferta-de-trump-de-reduzir-taxas/</link><description>China yesterday refused the offer of US President Donald Trump to grant customs relief in exchange for an agreement on the sale of Tiktok video sharing application.
"On the Tiktok issue, China has expressed its position on several occasions. China's position against the imposition of additional customs rates is also consistent and clear," said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Guo Jiakun.
Donald Trump said on Wednesday that he is prepared to reduce some of the rates on imports from China if the owner of Tiktok, Chinese Bytedance, agreeing to alienate her US operations.
"China will have to play a role in selling the application, it will possibly have to approve it and, if you do, you may grant you a small reduction in customs rates," said the US president, from the White House. On January 20, as soon as he took office, Trump gave Bytedance 75 days to sell his operations in the US, ie until April 5.
At the end of this period, if not, the platform is expected to be prohibited in the United States, where it has 170 million users, pursuant to a law passed last year in the name of protection of national security.</description><pubDate>2025-03-28 00:25:04</pubDate></item><item><title>José Paulo Esperança, Associate Rector of the City of Macau University: “Languages ​​cannot be controlled”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/jose-paulo-esperanca-reitor-associado-da-universidade-cidade-de-macau-as-linguas-nao-podem-ser-controladas/</link><description>Co-author of the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with Luís Reto and Fernando Luís Machado, José Paulo Esperança reveals to HM that the work edited in 2016 and 2018 is being updated, especially due to the growing global value of the language. The Associate Rector and Professor of the City of Macao University suggests partnerships with Macau under the Editorial Project
 
Launched the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, in co-authorship, about the global value of the language. Plan a new edition or update?
Undoubtedly. We are working in this regard, there was a recent conference in Macao and Professor Luís Reto, former Rector of ISCTE, presented some more current elements that were developed. He has worked on a very important issue, which is the role of Portuguese as a frank language, which was for a few centuries in Asia. The exchange between Dutch and the kingdom of Zion was made in Portuguese, because it was the common language used at that time, before English became the contemporary frank language. Therefore, there is a whole interesting story of Portuguese and the role it had in the first pinyins that existed, with the Chinese and the use of the [Roman] alphabet in Vietname. There are a number of elements that are not, therefore, very publicized, and the work of Atlas is the same, to disclose some economic dimensions of the language.
What are these dimensions?
One is the exchange of foreign trade and investment, which is very facilitated by the language. We also talk about migrations, tourism, students' exchange that is greatly influenced by linguistic proximity. Therefore, today we have a set of elements that are very interesting, and we hope to develop some more important partnerships with Macau.
As?
More at work, Professor Luís Reto is doing, which maintains an investigation team about the value of Portuguese. He has collaborated with the Portuguese Language Museum of São Paulo, for example. It is a museum space that was renewed after the fire that destroyed it. In addition, there is a project with Cascais City Council to develop such a structure, and we hope to do some works with Macau, in order to create three poles for the projection of the Portuguese language. As for Atlas' materials, we would like to have a continued update model, as this data is out of date very quickly. The work was edited in many languages, including Mandarin. This is the moment when we would like to give the book a more historical and deep dimension, with more knowledge about the teaching of Portuguese in the world.
What balance does this teaching do today?
Portuguese is developing a great deal of mother tongue and is effectively one of the most expanding languages ​​due to demographic growth in Africa, with countries such as Angola and Mozambique, which around 2050 will have populations of over 100 million inhabitants, each. The Portuguese thus consolidates itself as a language of the southern hemisphere, but much more from Africa, supplanting Brazil itself as the place of largest number of speakers of the language. All of this generates enormous potential, and this also occurs due to the great exchange of universities and internationalization of teaching. Today there is the possibility of Portuguese being a language of science, there is more publications in this language. This is a great challenge because English is the contemporary language of scientists. We want to contribute to all these dimensions, and Macau can also play an important role there. Macao is indeed a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and can play a significant role.
Is Macao an ideal place to train Portuguese teachers who do not have Portuguese as a mother tongue? Do you fear that the territory loses relevance in this matter before the offer of courses in the interior of China?
I see this question more as complementarity than competition. We have identified about 60 higher education institutions in China that have Portuguese courses, but I think Macau has very interesting conditions to start teaching from primary to secondary education so that children have been able to have learning from an early age. It does not mean that there are no young Chinese who began to learn their tongue in adolescence that they speak fantastically, which surprises me, but it is easier to start earlier and earlier. This will be easier in Macau. What is important is to create conditions for greater economic collaboration to many levels, such as joint research. In this respect, Macau has a very interesting opportunity. At the City of Macau University we are very interested in increasingly collaborating with researchers who visit us and work with our teams.
Can you give me examples?
Brazil is today one of China's great business partners. There is a lot of exchange in both directions, but one of the themes that is little studied, and in which I work hard, is the internationalization of Chinese companies. To what extent do these companies follow a model of internationalization similar to that of other countries that started this process earlier? I speak of the United States of America, the European countries, but also of Japan and others. China has, in fact, different models of presence in countries that are not yet well known, and this is important to realize, so that we know how to facilitate this process of exchange in a world that lives periods of some setback. It is very sad. I always remember a great economist of Portuguese origin, David Ricardo, who clearly explained how world trade is beneficial to everyone and how countries can take advantage of this situation. Therefore, applying tariffs, making such commercial barriers harms countries that are major exporters, such as China or Germany, and countries that today have a cultural export capacity, for example, and are not just importers.
In relation to the new Orthographic Agreement. It continues without a standardization in Macau. Does it worry it?
Languages ​​are dynamic and cannot be controlled. We think today in English, and we realize that there are almost incomprehensible ways to each other, such as the English one in Nigeria or Australia. Americans have difficulty realizing the Australians. In the nineteenth century, Portuguese from Portugal and Brazil were closer, then some disagreement emerged. There was an effort in Brazil to propose an orthographic agreement, and the Portuguese joined, resulting in a series of negotiations. There have always been resistances. I remember that Fernando Pessoa suggested the famous phrase “My homeland is the Portuguese language”. It was curiously a manifestation of some conservatism, because he thought Pharmacy had to continue writing with pH [Pharmacia]. In fact it did not make much sense. Portugal ended up seeking to impose a certain standardization based on the most genetic changes in the spelling agreement. It is not a process that has been running a hundred percent well, and has been universally adopted. African countries have become more defenders of Portuguese from Portugal. There is sometimes some confusion, but I understand that intercomprehension still remains, achieving a homogeneous language, more perhaps than English.
 
Between words and numbers
José Paulo Esperança is a doctorate in Economics from the European University Institute and was president of the ISCTE Department of Finance and Accounting - University Institute of Lisbon. The “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with editions in 2016 and 2018, contains “a large set of indicators that reinforce the idea of ​​the growth of teaching, speakers and the written use of Portuguese in the world”, having been the target of a series of recent initiatives in Macao.
One of them took place on March 17, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, with a session of the “Roda de Ideas” cycle, entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, which was attended by the former ISCTE Rector, Luís Reto, and José Paulo Hope himself. In addition to the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, José Paulo Esperança is the author of other works in the financial area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:08:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Vera Lúcia Raposo, jurist and teacher: “It was propagated today as a virus”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/vera-lucia-raposo-jurista-e-docente-ia-propaga-se-hoje-como-um-virus/</link><description>Vera Lúcia Raposo presented on Wednesday at the University of Macao the new regulatory framework of the European Union for Artificial Intelligence, in a session promoted by the Institute of European Studies of Macao. The former Macao University officer argues that China is gaining the race in an area that has never been so present in our lives
 
 
Spoke on Wednesday of “Ai Act” approved by the European Union (EU). Specifically, what are the main points of this document?
This is the Artificial Intelligence Regulation (IA) published last year in the EU official newspaper. It is a European law, but it is also, so far, the most detailed legal regime about the products surrounding AI.
Is it difficult to legislate on the AI ​​at this preliminary phase?
Maybe we will never stop being at this stage. Notice, AI did not come up with ChatgPT or anything that looks like. Since the middle of the last century, and even before, but especially since Alan Turing's 'Paper' that Ia exists, first in the laboratory, girded with a group of researchers. Then it began to be released into the world and to be part of our lives, but never as now. We are currently in a kind of pandemic, where AI propagates in our existence as a virus, but not a bad virus, because I understand that the AI ​​often propagates with positive effects. Of course, although it is not a completely new thing, it is a very mysterious reality for us jurists. The problem begins that we can't even get a definition mostly accepted by experts of what AI is. First of all, we don't know what it is, because it is a moving entity that constantly changes. What we thought was ten years ago, today it will be an algorithm.
In the areas of private life defense, or personal data, for example, or copyright, what does European legislation tell us in concrete terms?
The AI ​​regulation [of the EU] is part of what we call “Data Package” [Data Package], it is inserted in the group of regulations that concern product security. But this is understood in very comprehensive terms, not only security as we are used to thinking about it, as something that calls into question physical integrity, but covers environmental issues, respect for fundamental values ​​and technology rights and data protection. It is true that the regulation has these practical aspirations and realization in some standards, but the idea is to develop with other existing regulations on data protection and intellectual property, and that does not conflict with them.
We currently have ChatgPT on the American side, and DeepSeek on the Chinese side. Do you think China positions itself as a leader in the AI ​​area?
China is found to be a colossus in the digital world. The way the world has been evolving has differentiated. 100 years ago we had war conflicts, and today we have wars where we continue to kill people, but we also have commercial wars and these technological wars. And I say that more than a war is a race to reach the new invention. The old blocks of countries have different strategies. For example, in the case of the United States of America (USA), this strategy has changed a lot with the presidency of Trump, but was always more liberal and "Laissez-Faire". This has also been the form of US action, but with Trump is more in the line of "Vale Tudo", what matters is to arrive first. There is a great promotion of technological companies, as you see with the great support they gave to Trump's presidential campaign. Then we have China, with a state policy, which is not so much in the hands of the private. There is a great focus on technological advancement, but it is visible that the country is already in a position that will hardly be achieved by others. Europe is not exactly well positioned.

Why?
Europe has made the decision that the best way to develop technological progress and foster innovation is through hyper-regulation. There is no centimeter that is not regulated or not being regulated by the EU. Of course, it may have some advantages, and the aspirations can be in the face of controlled and sustainable development, and respect our fundamental rights and the rule of law. But I have some doubts. First, that this is achieved, because the protection of fundamental rights does not go through this hyper-regulation either. Then it seems to me that we are doing this at the expense of a value that seems to me, which is innovation. This idea comes, by the way, in the report of Mario Draghi, who warned the EU to the ability to mortgage future generations because we are leaving innovation behind. I don't see that any of these three technological models [US, China and EU] be particularly fruitful because they have benefits and disadvantages. We have an interesting model, which is the British.
In what sense?
The United Kingdom maintains the legal framework it inherited from the EU, and has not yet changed it. The United Kingdom will not adopt AI regulation [Europe's Ai Act], because it is no longer part of the EU, it seems that it will not create such a regulatory framework, but have an approach that is having a very generic picture that fixes the main points and limits, but then there will be a sectoral regulation. This regulation, which is still being created, is to establish the 'guidelines' for each area of ​​activity, so that there is autonomy in each sector and always respecting the particularities of each. In theory, it is more interesting, but everything is at first and I have not seen cases applied in practice.
How do you comment on the use of AI in the legal and judicial area?
Using sources that are not desirable to do our work was not something that came with ChatgPT. Speaking of something I know well, such as academic theses or scientific papers, it is not unprecedented that some less scrupulous authors quote sources in which they have never put their eyes, and then quote the wrong way, or quote sources that do not exist. There are situations in which unafable sources are cited, such as blogs, or papers that have not been subject to the peer review system. This is not new. We have the chatgpt beside it helps a lot and the temptation is great. I don't think it's the end of the world. Literacy was fundamental to the academy and any citizen. We all have to understand the benefits of Generative AI and risks as well. Research on Wikipedia pages can also generate errors. It is impossible to tell students not to use chatgPT, because this ban would be hollow. I can't know how people do their job. There may be situations of scientific dishonesty and situations where information is not true, but if someone tells me who wrote something with ChatgPT support, I have no problem with that. I have if the person is considered to be the author's author. ChatgPT works a lot as a Google search, it's not completely new. But I have to realize that the information that ChatgPT gives me has to be very analyzed and again investigated. ChatgPT can only give me clues where I can go, and then it can be useful and make us think. It is a source like any other, but it is not very credible. Chatgpt never deals with things in detail, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 16:42:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby Hui, President of the Macao Autism Association: “Autism differs from person to person”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/ruby-hui-presidente-da-associacao-de-autismo-de-macau-autismo-difere-de-pessoa-para-pessoa/</link><description>Created in 2012, the Macao Autism Association continues to fight for more care for children and young people with this development disturbance. But the association's president, Ruby Hui, warns of the need for more incisive policies for adolescents and their specific needs, especially in access to employment
 
 
What balance does the work done by the association in recent years?
My work is above all to establish a connection with all the entities and resources made available by the government and also the game industry, as the authorities have started to [the context of the new game concession contracts] that develop more social support activities. Therefore, we have gathered all these resources to organize recreational activities for children and youth. In addition, we organize therapy sessions for our members. Usually, we request financial support from private companies and the government, covering 30 to 50 percent of these expenses.
The support of the game sector is therefore quite important.
Yes, but it has not really been a great support. For example, the government covers part of our monthly expenses, about 40,000 patacas. But this amount comes only to hire two full -time employees and one part -time employee. They are the ones who organize all activities, deal with the bureaucratic part, which includes the presentation of many reports to the government, because we ask for subsidies for almost half of our expenses.
Therefore, do you consider that they need more support from the executive to be able to hire more professionals?
Yes, it would be ideal. Associations like ours are getting bigger and the children we support are growing. I would say that 60 percent of our members are 11 or more, and about 20 percent are even larger, over 14 years old. We have to think about their future and the needs of therapy and treatment for adolescents, as it is not only small kids who need therapies such as speech or occupational therapy. They are young people who are still in high school and need to acquire different types of social skills, boys need to know how to deal with girls and vice versa. Then, when they become adults, they need to know how to deal with bosses in jobs. There are many valences to explore, but at this moment I would say that the supports are not enough.
Are schools not yet prepared to receive these students, for example?
Autism may be different from person to person. Students with autism, but who have better learning skills, are in normal schools. But parents tell me that there are not enough teachers with certain skills to deal with and teach these children. There are teachers who still have a very traditional mindset to treat these young people, who often have to deal with alone with bullying, for example. I would say that there are many children and young people with autism with psychological problems because of the school.
When it speaks of the traditional mindset, what does this mean in concrete?
In the case of my son, for example, he is obliged to always be sitting at school, but often likes to move and get up from his chair. From the point of view of parents who have children with this problem, there would be no problem, as long as it did not bother others, but for teachers it cannot be, and complain. They say things of the genre: "He will beat the table, he will move the painting, makes a lot of noise." Every day I receive complaints from parents to connect with the school, and for small situations like this.
What are the main difficulties or challenges that Macao families face when they deal with an autistic child?
In my case, my family is middle class, and we are financially well. But when my son was younger needed to do therapy and it was very expensive. Now these therapies cost even more. At the time my son was in primary education, 600 to 700 patacas was paid for each therapy session, but there are days a father told me that the sessions now cost about 1000 patacas per class, which is very expensive. Families of lower social classes cannot afford. Therefore, this support is one of the great objectives of our association, raising money so that we can provide explanations, therapy sessions or other type of support. All so that our members can attend classes with 50 percent discount, where the association pays half the amount.
When the association was created, what were its main objectives?
In 2012 autism was not a very spoken theme. Therefore, we joined [some parents and families] and we started to ask for support from the government and try to draw attention to the subject. We got some things because the government now gives more support to these young people, at least for those under 12. The problem we feel is that these young people are growing and adolescents need other types of supports that do not exist.
What is necessary to change in mindsets and society in relation to autism?
In Macao there are not many companies willing to hire young people with autism. Situation that is not seen in Hong Kong, where there are several hiring programs with social companies. Macau needs to follow this path.
One day in Rio
World Autism Consciousness Day is celebrated on April 2 and, in this context, the Macao Autism Association joined Sands China for a series of activities with children and parents, which took place last March 10th. Through the program “Sands Care”, the game operator provided a visit to the exhibition “Coastal Fantasia”, with the figure of “King Lobster”, a creation of Philip Colbert artist ” A boat trip through the Delta of the Pearl River.
In total, 70 people participated. Quoted by a game operator statement, Ruby Hoi said the tour "allowed children to enjoy the maximum of the trip." "Thank you for all the support provided to people with autism in Macau, and I hope that all sectors of society can continue to support the development of these people and promote their inclusion in society," he said.
For the game operator, this type of events can help “reinforce the cohesion of families dealing with autism, but also promote the awareness of society and support for the community of people with autism fostering a more inclusive and supportive social environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul French, writer: Looking for Wallis Simpson in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/paul-french-escritor-a-procura-de-wallis-simpson-na-china/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival, which starts on Friday, will feature the presence of writer Paul French, who launched last year a new biographical book, "Her Lotus Year", which describes Wallis Simpson's experience in China before being a Duchess of Windsor. The British author will also talk about “Destination Macau”, a nostalgic and almost cinematic account of the city's history
 
How did you come to the history of Wallis Simpson's life experience in China?
I lived in Shanghai for many years and many visitors knew that Wallis Simpson had spent time in the city. Rumors ran on what he had done, and visitors always wanted to know if the rumors were true, such as the idea that she had learned esoteric sexual techniques or had posed naked for photographs. It was also said that he had belonged to a group of opium smuggling, or a group of bets that combined horses races. For me, as an author and expert in foreign experiences in Shanghai in the first half of the twentieth century, none of this made sense. So I thought this was the ideal time to really find out what Wallis had done in China. The fact that she was in the country in 1924 and 1925, two of the most fascinating years in the history of modern China, helped a lot.
How do you describe the life of the duchess in the country during that specific political period?
China was in total chaos when she was there, because Puyi, the last emperor, had been expelled from the forbidden city and occurred the biggest strikes ever in Hong Kong history. In addition, political fractions were recorded in Guangzhou, warlords of war in Shanghai and northern China. These were also the most wet years that there is a record in China, with crop production breaks and the occurrence of tiphoid and cholera fever outbreaks. He fired the number of bandits and pirates. Then, in March 1925, Sun Yat-Sen, leader of the Republican Revolution of 1911, died without leaving an obvious successor. Wallis came across all this, as he was retained on the island of Shamian, Guangzhou, while the city struggled; In Shanghai, he saw corpses to be brought to the city from the battles of the warlords; He saw victims of typhus and anger in Tianjin; and troops of the warlords threatening Beijing. But he was also largely in a foreign protective bubble that protected her from foreign soldiers and her white skin. He could delight in China's culture and aesthetics, while around him the whole country threatened to explode.
How was the personality of Wallis Simpson, a controversial figure in the context of the marriage to the Duke of Windsor?
It is very important not to confuse Wallis of 1924 with the later Wallis, from the long years of exile and controversy as Duchess of Windsor. In 1924 Wallis was only 28 years old, fleeing from a physically abusive husband (her first husband, Win Spencer, an American Navy commander) and was not yet particularly sophisticated or cosmopolitan. These were characteristics that would learn in China, mixing in the “colonies” [concessions] international international and bohemiums of Shanghai and Beijing. In fact, it was in Beijing that it first mixed with ambassadors, high -level Chinese politicians, high -ranking military officers and a stretch, and from them learned everything from playing Bridge and enjoying Jade to how to behave in high society. Obviously, this was useful a decade later when he met the Prince of Wales in England. Admittedly, the posterior Wallis, the Duchess, is a more difficult figure to like. Perhaps she and the Duke have made some bad political decisions and made some friendships, perhaps Wallis became a little bitter for not being accepted by the British royal family. But the truth is that in 1924 she was young, free of a bad husband and was in one of the most fascinating countries in the world.
What can readers perceive this figure and about China of that time, with "Her Lotus Year"?
China in 1925 was on the brink of potential explosion, as the whole country could have fallen into total chaos, dividing into the size of Portugal managed by warlords with private armies, or a resurgent Qing Dynasty supported by Japan in the North [China], the South and, of course, the foreign powers-England, America, France and Japan-who had Chinese lands like colonies. Ultimately, this did not happen, but no one knew this in 1925. Wallis herself oscillated between feeling incredibly comfortable and happy in what was her "year of lotus," as he described him, quoting Homer's Sopoifers who never want to return home; and feel terrified of the violence of the warlords or those who were against foreigners.
What are the biggest challenges, as a writer, in the process of researching the history of Wallis?
Wallis probably became the most photographed and spoken woman in history, more than Marilyn Monroe, more than Queen Isabel II. But in 1924 she was not famous at all. So it left a very difficult trail to follow. He wrote his memories, but these were "disinfected." A big problem was also the rumors that the British government and secret services circulated in 1936 in an attempt to destroy the idea of ​​a marriage between King Eduardo VIII and Wallis. The attempt failed because he abdicated the throne and they married, but these sexual rumors and insinuations, many of them racist and misogynists, have remained to this day, and they continue to be regularly recycled in the British and American Tabloid Press. I found the real Wallis a much more friendly character than I expected, and I hope readers will feel that too.
Is invited to another edition of Rota das Letras. How do you feel for being part of the festival?
I love to be part of the Macao Literary Festival. Although he had spoken before in Macao, namely in the Portuguese bookstore and other places, he had never participated in the festival. I look forward to being able to talk about Wallis Simpson and also about my new collection of rehearsals about Macau, entitled "Destination Macau". Some stories of Macao that have pleased me over the years, some of them presented with a more English look, as it were, may be interested and will be new to the local public.
Book | “Destination Macau”, the city between “The Imaginary and the Real”
Paul French has just launched the third volume of the “Destination” collection, which had editions of Shanghai or Beijing, and is now dedicated to telling stories of the ancient macao, a “place as imaginary as real”, as described the synopsis of the work. The work of the British author presents "The Macao by artists George Chinnery and George Smirnoff, the writers Deolinda da Conceição and Maurice Dekobra, to the fantasies of" Pulp Fiction "and febrile dreams of Josef Von Sternberg and Jean Delannoy."
There is still no shortage of Paul French, stories around historical figures such as Pedro José Lobo and Ian Fleming, author and creator of James Bond. Macao of the time of World War II, those who “came to Macao in search of gold, and those who sought war refuge” is described, not forgetting “the combatants looking for a secret passage through the 'neutral' macao”.
Paul French unveil mysteries or tells forgotten stories to many, such as the idea that Japan had tried to buy Macau in 1934 or the person who sailed with the Macau pirates queen, Lai Choi San. There are, in all, 18 stories “true of fascinating people who lived or visited Macau in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Iame Asia finals of Karting back in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/finais-da-iame-asia-de-karting-voltam-em-dezembro/</link><description>The Macao Karting International Award will receive again, from December 11 to 14, the Iame Asian finals. Like last year, the coloane karting race will give invitations to the very coveted world end of Iame in 2026.
Organized by the Institute of Sport, Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Otk Kart Asia and Iame Asia, the 2024 event brought back the international spirit to one of the largest competitions of the sport on the Asian continent. Coloane's karting received several races and different categories of Iame Series Asia, recovering the international prestige of an event that has been the scene of the Cik-Fia World Championship events.
Pilots from the interior of China, Singapore, Philippines, Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Japan, India, Sri Lanka, Australia, New Zealand, Sweden, Italy, France, Austria, the United States of America, Brazil, Hong Kong, and, of course, Macao, filled the track from the mashes in 2024 for four days of intense Competition, something that has not been seen for several years.
After the success of the previous edition, the formula is repeated this year. Singapore's organization again chooses Coloane's karting for its biggest event of the season, confirming the presence of the usual categories: Cadet, Junior, Senior and Master.
Thank you Macau!
The Iame (Italian American Motor Engineering) is one of the world's leading engine manufacturers for Karting. Founded in 1968 by Bruno Grana, the company is headquartered in Italy and is one of the references in Karting Internacional, having bet strongly in the Asian market in recent years. The presence in Macau is part of this strategy of growth and expansion.
The announcement of the return to the territory was made on social networks: “After an incredible debut in 2024, we are back with the Macao International International Award and the Iame Asia final for another epic confrontation! The city of emotions at high speed and legendary races will be the stage for the best pilots in Asia and the world!
Satisfied with the reception in 2024, Iame Asia organizers took the opportunity to leave a "huge thanks to AAMC and the Macao government for their continuous support and confidence to make it possible!"
In addition to the Macao test, the 2025 calendar of Iame Series Asia includes three events in Malaysia and three events in Thailand. However, for the first time, last weekend of March, the Iame Asia Cup will be held at the International Shanghai Circuit Karting.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 01:04:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to GIC | Local tests return to Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/regresso-ao-gic-provas-locais-voltam-a-zhaoqing/</link><description>The dates for the Macao of Tourism Car Championship (MTCs in the English acronym) were made known on the past Friday by the General Automóvel Association of Macau-China (AAMC) through a newsletter. The competition for local pilots and decides to find out the Macao Grand Prix in November will again return to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC).
After a year when the MTCS headed to the Zhuzhou International Circuit in Hunan province, AAMC listened to most of the territory pilots and chose to make these important races closer to the main interveners' house - the pilots. In recent years, the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing has been the preferred stage for the realization of these races, due to the proximity and the fact that it serves as an operational basis to most teams.
The first of the two events scheduled for the 2025 MTCS is scheduled from 18 to 20 April, while the second round is scheduled from 16 to 18 May. The AAMC newsletter says that "all riders must go through a selection process before they can participate in the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix - Macau Touring Car Challenge."
Registration, for the competition that joins Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and Subaru BRZ (ZD8), are open until March 29 and after the registration period, "all applications will be subject to AAMC approval, which reserves the final right to accept or reject any registration."
The technical regulation was also published, as was officially confirmed the use of tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, which belongs to the Chinese conglomerate Sinochem, as had already happened on the last edition of the Macao Grand Prix.
Confirmation of the Great Bay
AAMC also confirmed the two findings for the GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4), which will be concomitant with the new Chinese Championship Sro GT Cup. The first race will be played from March 21 to 23, at the International Circuit of Shanghai, in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix. Zhuhai International. Also here Pirelli will be the only tire supplier.
These two tests will be determined for the big holiday party on the guide circuit, and it is defined that only 28 cars will be accepted on the starting grid in the mashed race. The 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix runs from November 13 to 16.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 04:17:32</pubDate></item><item><title>FIRST RALENT PROOF FOR THE MACAU GP took place in Shanghai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/primeira-prova-de-apuramento-para-o-gp-macau-decorreu-em-xangai/</link><description>The first determination test for the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix took place last weekend at the International Shanghai Circuit. Integrated in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix Program, Chen Weian and Lichao Han won the two races that will serve to select competitors entitled to participate this year in the GT - Great Bay Cup -
 
The GT Cup-Great Bay Race joined the newly created SRO GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macao Grand Prix. Thirty-three cars, six of them driven by Macau pilots, signed up for this debut-a record number of participants in a GT4 category in Asia category.
According to the organizer's statement, Sro Motorsports Group, “the total number of cars and the variety of builders have even exceeded the organizers' expectations for a championship that only began to be discussed in late November 2024. Since then, the Sro Asia team and their partner AAMC (Macau-China General Automobile Association) have worked tirelessly to make the series a reality before their debut.”
The event started in a troubled way. Due to a customs problem that affected several cars, more than a dozen competitors was unable to participate in the free training session on Friday. Fortunately, for this group of pilots, among which were included the drivers of the Kevin Leong Ian Veng, Kim Hou Lao and Un Hou IP, the cars arrived at the circuit in time for Saturday's qualification.
Animated races and decision in Zhuhai
With three dozen cars, from ten different brands, on track, all with very balanced tasks, was attended by two animated races in the imposing Shanghai track. In the first 12 -lap race, the two Lotus Emi GT4 Officials, by Daniel Lu and Luo Kailuo, who departed from the first line of the grill, were overcome on track by the Chen Weian Audi R8 LMS GT4. In the second match of the weekend, Lichao Han, behind the wheel of the same Toyota GR GT4 who beat the GT Cup - Great Bay Race in 2024, triumphed ahead of Chen Weian and Lotus de Liu Kai Shun.
Macao pilots had no easy life on a track where they had little or no experience. The most rewarded of all, Kelvin Leong, abandoned in the second round of the first race, while Miguel Law, in Audi R8 LMS GT4, was the best of the riders of MSAR, ending in 19th place. In Sunday's race, Leong took his BMW M4 GT4 F82 to 11th place.
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, at the end of the season, on the streets of Macau. The places will be attributed based on the classification after the second round of the championship, scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit, on a date yet to be announced.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:20:30</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Fia introduces costly measure to GT world cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/gp-macau-fia-introduz-medida-onerosa-para-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) announced on Tuesday afternoon a technical measure for the GT3 cars participating in the GT World Cup of the Macao Grand Prix, which will certainly have an impact on a race that is the event's headlord
 
To improve the Balance of Performance (BOP) - the method that balances the progress between all cars in the GT3 category - the FIA ​​decided to force the use of torque sensors, like what you already do in their championships, such as resistance worlds (WEC) and Rally Raid or Formula E. Torque sensors offer a very high precision in power measurement, allowing FIA ensures that the power of each car does not exceed the values ​​assigned by BOP and that external factors, such as atmospheric conditions, do not influence performance.
Although Sro Motorsports Group is co-organizer of this race, and having a bop recognized worldwide, in the last two years, the Macao Bop has been provided by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA ​​BOP was worth a series of criticisms, with teams and pilots-particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main impaired-to publicly express their natural discontent with the difference in progress.
These sensors are installed in car transmission veins and represent the most effective tool for measuring wheel power, being individually attributed by the BOP process to each car model that participates in the world's most prestigious “sprint” race for GT3 class machines. According to FIA, the decision to make torque sensors mandatory after consultations with the brands involved in the GT3 technical working group.
Costs will shoot
For a race that has several private teams, this measure will be expensive, as these sensors exceed half a million patacas per car, and the teams need to have another same spare reserve system. This, given that most teams that participate in the MSar test do not use torque sensors in their cars in any competition, and cannot amortize the brutal investment.
"From the experience I had in Qatar, it is noted that there is a difference between several builders in the way it generates this technology. An extra support team is needed to monitor and maximize performance without exceeding the stipulated limits," he told HM Duarte Alves, the experienced track engineer in the territory who was with the official Ford team in the first WEC season in the Arab country.
"A good example is the difficulty and time needed for a builder who enters as a newcomer. An illustrative case is Mercedes-AMG, which is facing growth pains while developing its own systems," said Duarte Alves. “In more flat circuits, the management of these systems is simpler. In places like Macau, where 'torque peaks' will always be frequent, it will be a real challenge for the engineers of these systems!”
Confident
Immune to all this, the FIA ​​chooses a speech directed to builders, forgetting that most of the starting grid is made up of private competitors.
Lutz Leif Linden, chairman of the FIA ​​GT commission, said the institution that represents “made this decision in consultation with the builders”, adding that, to the International Federation, “this means even more justice and improved control of BOP values, which is particularly important in such a prestigious and media event, in such a demanding circuit, where long -speed long -speed straight lines and narrow ”.
Fabrice Van Ertvede, FIA speed technical manager, stressed the idea that "our goal, as a regulatory entity, is to ensure total equity for all participants." The implementation of torque sensors “is an extremely effective tool for achieving this goal, allowing us to align very different cars in parameters such as pure power, but also at full speed, a crucial factor in a circuit like the guide circuit.”
Despite the difficulties that Mercedes-AMG encountered with this system last month, Fabrice Van Ertvede praises that “the builders we hope to see in Macau this year are already familiar with this innovation, through their experience in the FIA's LMGT3 LMGT3 class, and the decision to adopt torque sensors resulted from the dialogue we kept with them.”
This is the second news that the FIA ​​introduces in the mashed race, having announced last month that the second qualification segment will have a super pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification laps. The eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will take place from November 13 to 16, as part of the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 17:11:10</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | FIA confirms GT World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/gp-macau-fia-confirma-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The World Council of last Wednesday has confirmed the expected, that the eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be held as part of the Macao 72nd Grand Program, from November 13 to 16. However, there is a big news for this year's edition
 
The International Federation, which co-organizes this race in partnership with Sro Motorsports Group and the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), took the opportunity to announce a new qualification model for the race. In addition to the 30 -minute qualification session equal to the previous editions (Q1), a second qualification segment (Q2) was added, reserved for the top ten pilots of the first session.
The Q2 session will be held in Super Pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification turns, and each pilot is also allowed to use a new tire set at this session. This novelty will allow qualification to be decided without interference from third parties.
The remaining program of the Queen of GT will remain the same as the previous editions, with the free training session, the traditional 12-lap classification race on Saturday afternoon, followed by the 16-lap main race that will decide the world's Cup winner on Sunday.
Veterans compliments
These measures introduced by the FIA ​​were very well received by the most experienced GT riders. This is because traffic has always been a huge obstacle in obtaining a good qualification return on the guide circuit, something essential for those who aim to win this title.
"It's an excellent idea to introduce the Super Pole session in Macao," said German Maro Engel, the winner of the World Cup last edition by Mercedes-AMG. This will be one of the most spectacular and exciting sessions of the season and should also secure sports justice.
Raffaele Marciello, for two occasions winning of this trophy, and one of the BMW factory riders, also reacted positively, adding: “In Macao, it was always complicated to make a clean lap. With this new format, you will not hear the excuse of traffic or a red flag. Having only two laps will be very challenging, but now the fastest pilot will probably be in pole.”
This is an opinion shared by Laurens Vanthoor, the World Cup winner in 2016, who said there will no longer be “apologies” in the qualification. Porsche's experienced Belgian pilot believes that “there will be an added pressure because you only have these two turns”, because in a difficult circuit like this, “if you make an error, there is nothing more to follow. In a normal qualification, you have more opportunities. Personally, a shootout is always something that I appreciate a lot. For pilots like this, it will be almost the highlight of the weekend.”
And the younger ones too
Chinese pilot Yifei Ye premiered at the Grand Prix last November at the World Cup. Ferrari's official pilot, which is up to the Endurance Fia World Championship (WEC), has left a good impression on the guide circuit, and he also welcomes the measurements now introduced.
“It's good to eliminate these red flag interventions and yellow flags, so that in the end, the one that really is the fastest to get pole position,” said Yifei Ye that she could return to the race this year. "In Macao, everyone is very close in terms of times, so it will be extremely difficult for pilots to try to get to 'Super Pole'. I think it will also be great for viewers."</description><pubDate>2025-02-28 01:03:51</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Célio Alves Dias will continue to run this season</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/gp-celio-alves-dias-vai-continuar-a-correr-esta-temporada/</link><description>Macaense pilot Célio Alves Dias was one of the long -term returns of the 2024 car.
 
The Macao Cup winner of Macau in 2021 was removed from motorsport at the time of 2023 for personal reasons, but last year made his debut in the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8). Despite the vast experience in tests of the specialty, having conducted several generations of tourism cars, Célio Alves Dias had never managed the new bobbinns that the Macao-China General Association (AAMC) introduced in its competition in 2023. Last time turned out to be of learning, with some difficulties in the tuning and behavior of the Japanese car.
Participation in races at the Zhuzhou International Circuit and the Macau Grand Prix made Célio Alves Dias realize that his Toyota GR86 was not at the strongest competition level. Based on the conclusions drawn from these experiences, he decided to start preparing for the new season.
"The car had to be all dismantled. My car was bought in Monday, and the chassis and the security arc, for me, were not well done," explained Fu Lei Racing Team pilot to HM. "This, I made the car too hard and very difficult to bow. I tried a well -mounted China car, and there is a difference. I had a long time in January, in China, with this car. Our cars, made in the same workshop, were very hard, which made it difficult to get around quickly."
If in the Macao Grand Prix, the house riders, excellent guide circuit, managed to equate the progress to their hong Kong opponents and the interior of China, in the initial races on the Zhuzhou track in Hunan province, it wasn't quite like that. "There are many differences between cars, but especially in chassis, because the engines, in terms of power and horses, are almost all at the same level. Our opponents have also experienced many pieces, many engines, even speed boxes, and chassis. Competition cars are always the same.
Silver Jubilee in November
Being a usual Portuguese name in the Macao Grand Prix in recent decades, Célio Alves Dias debuted at the Guide Circuit in 2000 and from then was a frequent presence and no faults in the race until 2023. This year, its objective is to account for its twenty-fifth participation in the biggest sports event of RAEM, but will have to align in the findings.
While awaiting the announcement of the 2025 calendar by AAMC, Célio Alves Dias details details to start his test program, because his Toyota, after being reviewed, "is ready to test" in the interior of China, something that will happen "very soon," says the pilot.
In the last edition of the Grand Prix, Célio Alves Dias qualified in 12th place for the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. However, his participation was short and unhappy: at the wheel of Toyota with dorsal No. 11, was forced to give up after being immobilized on the climb of San Francisco. The Macanese pilot was out of the race on the first lap, in an incident that caused the Safety Car.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:50:53</pubDate></item></channel></rss>