<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Brazil | China suspends imports of beef of three factories</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/brasil-china-suspende-importacoes-de-carne-de-bovino-de-tres-fabricas/</link><description>China temporarily suspended imports of beef from three Brazilian factories, announced yesterday the government of Brazil, ensuring that the decision will not affect bilateral trade relations.
China's General Customs Administration has performed a series of “video audits” in the affected units and found that they do not comply with all the import requirements established by the Asian country, explained the Brazilian Ministry of Agriculture and Livestock in a statement.
The companies, whose names were not disclosed by the folder, have already been notified and are “taking corrective measures” to meet the demands of the Chinese body, according to the Brazilian government. China is the main destination of Brazilian beef exports and the largest commercial partner in the South American country.
Brazil, one of the world's largest animal protein suppliers, ended 2024 with a record production of 31.57 million tons of beef, pork and chicken, as well as record exports of 10.26 million tons, according to official data.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:22:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Press | All About Macau prevented from covering elections</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/imprensa-all-about-macau-impedido-de-cobrir-eleicoes/</link><description>The Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly, led by Seng Ioi Man, president of the Court of Second Instance, is blocking the All About Macau newspaper to cover the press conferences of the committee that organizes the September 14 legislative elections.
Following the election of Sam Hou Fai as Chief Executive, and during the term of Ho Iat Seng, the All About Macau newspaper began to be excluded from virtually all press conferences linked to local authorities, justifying that there are not enough vacancies for media professionals. According to this criterion, which is discretionary, the priority is attributed to publications with daily or weekly periodicity. However, several monthly local agencies, published in non -Chinese languages, can access events without embarrassment, although theoretically do not meet the required requirements.
It is also frequent to block access to the All About Macau newspaper, with the justification of lack of space, when the rooms where the conferences are held have several places available.
According to Article 27 of the Basic Law, MSar protects freedom of the press in the territory. According to Article 5 of the Press Law, this freedom implies the guarantee of the right to access the sources of information, which means contact with rulers and the possibility of questioning them.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:50:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Government launches new alert about Covid-19</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/governo-lanca-novo-alerta-sobre-covid-19/</link><description>Macao health services (SS) indicate a decrease in influenza cases, with the current situation “below the alert level”. However, in the case of COVID-19 infections, “the Sars-Cov-2 virus is becoming active,” therefore an appeal to vaccination, especially for chronic and elderly patients. The SS advance, however, that no death caused by Covid-19 has not yet been registered since the beginning of the year.
According to a note released yesterday, which cites laboratory data from the ninth week of the year, that is, from late February, “the Covid-19 detection positivity rate was 13.7 percent”, and this value “represents a significant increase compared to the previous week, 3.8 percent”.
In general terms, SS believe that “flu activity will remain active in the coming weeks”, but the attention, but for a certain stability. The number of patients served in the emergency service in the ninth week of 2025, that is, February, “decreased from the previous week”, having been attended a daily average of 1,190 people, 282 of them children.
Thus, “the descent trend of the influenza virus detection rate, from 10.5 percent in the eighth week of the year (below the alert level of 13.1 percent), to five percent in the ninth week”.
RISE IN DAILY AVERAGE
However, the SS warns that it is not yet time to ward off attention from flu, as it is “an average of about 83 [sick] people per day, which represents an climb compared to previous data”. Of these 83 people, 31 are adults and 52 children. Thus, SS understand that "the propagation of the respiratory tract virus in Macau is still active."
With regard to collective influenza cases, since January 46 occurred in the territory, as well as 25 cases caused by influenza A and five virus by influenza B virus.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:21:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Architecture | Seminar with Marco Imperidori takes place on the 20th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/arquitectura-seminario-com-marco-imperadori-decorre-dia-20/</link><description>The CAC - Circle of Macao Culture Friends organizes, on the 20th, a Seminar with Marco Imperidori, with sessions entitled “Architecture of Care” and “Arte Sella: a balance between architecture and nature”. Events take place at Macao University of Science and Technology, between 15h and 6:15 pm, and the registration deadline ends on the 19th.
Marco Imperradori is a full -seated professor and researcher at Milan Polytechnic, where he tends the technology design and innovation chair. Its work focuses on high energy efficiency buildings, construction/envelope construction systems and sustainability.
With a master's degree and a doctorate in construction engineering, it combines knowledge of architecture and engineering. It has been taught worldwide, including as a visiting professor at the University of St. Joseph in Macau from 2015 to 2023. As a delegate of the Rector to the Far East, it represents the Milan Polytechnic in Asia. Active researcher has published extensively on architectural innovation, sustainability and energy conservation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:10:27</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM | Return to profits after four years of damage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/sjm-regresso-aos-lucros-apos-quatro-anos-de-prejuizos/</link><description>SJM made a $ 3 million profit from Hong Kong last year, and managed to reduce the accumulated debt by 6 percent to Hong Kong's $ 26.5 billion
 
SJM Holdings game concessionaire announced a $ three million profit from Hong Kong in 2024 after unprecedented losses for four consecutive years. In a statement sent on Tuesday to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the company founded by the late game tycoon Stanley Hung Sun recalled that he had a loss of $ 2.01 billion from Hong Kong in 2023.
The SJM casinos raised $ 28.8 billion from Hong Kong, 35.9 percent than the previous year, while the revenues did not play 22.9 percent to Hong Kong's $ 1.92 billion.
With revenues to rise, the company registered an operating profit of Hong Kong's $ 3.76 billion, more than twice than by 2023. During last year, SJM was able to reduce the total debt to Hong Kong at 26.5 billion in late December.
On January 22, the Fitch Ratings Financial Notation Agency maintained the SJM debt rating thanks to the recovery of tourism in Macau. Fitch said the Grand Lisboa Palace, a game development and hotel opening opened in July 2021, in full pandemic, forced SJM to accumulate a high level of debt.
New recipes
The company said on Tuesday that Grand Lisboa Palace went from losses by 2023 to Hong Kong's $ 499 million operating profit last year. The revenues of the new SJM venture more than doubled, reaching $ 6.58 billion from Hong Kong.
The mass market represented 82.4 percent of the company's casinos revenues, while the VIP game was a 9.3 percent slice. The big bets, which in 2019 represented 46.2 percent of the revenues of Macao Casinos, were affected by the detention of the leader of the world's largest VIP betting company in November 2021.
Former Suncity Executive Director Alvin Chau Cheok Wa, was sentenced in January 2023 to 18 years in prison, in a case that dropped from 85 to 18 the number of licenses of game promoters issued in Macao.
The SJM said it will completely renew every room of Grand Lisboa, one of the company's most important casinos, as well as increasing the number of rooms “through the conversion of old areas reserved for junkets”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Security | Firefighters appeal caution in the use of gas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/seguranca-bombeiros-apelam-a-cautela-na-utilizacao-de-gas/</link><description>Faced with a fire that made five injured and suspected was caused by a gas escape, the Fire Department came to public through a statement indicating several inspections to buildings and houses in recent years
 
After an explosion followed by a fire that caused five injuries, the Fire Department (CB) appealed to the population to pay “high attention to safety in the use of gas stove appliances”. The statement, in Portuguese, was issued yesterday morning, since it is suspected that at the origin of the flames it was a “liquefied oil gas escape”.
“CB stresses again that the risk of gas safety cannot be neglected, whether at home, restaurants and other spaces,” can be read in the message. "Citizens and sectors are expected to reinforce surveillance, prevention and to deal with safety matters relating to the use and installation corrects of gas stove devices, in order to jointly ensure the safety of life and goods," he was added.
The message also served the CB to defend any accusations of failure to the inspections made. "Since 2019, the CB has begun to move to communities to continually inspect the gas stoves at home, together with residents' associations and organizations and community security heads against fire," he was nominated. “Until February of this year, 1,742 home inspections were made,” was complemented.
According to the CB, during the inspections there were “safety specifications, the place of installation [of the appliances] and the expiration date of the gas stove pipe”, and as a result there were problems such as gas binding pipes to the expiration, defective connections to exit the gas from the water pitches.
More security
In the last two weeks there have been two fires in residential buildings, which has led to the maintenance of fire safety equipment to be questioned.
The first fire took place in the lake building, it is believed that due to a short circuit with a television, and caused controversy, given that the alarm to alert the residents did not fired. As a result, Deputy Lo Choi In made a written interpellation asking for better inspection inspections.
In the fire on Monday, still on site, the CB ensured that safety equipment worked as expected. However, due to the explosion with a gas leak in the centralized supply system, the impact has just reached larger, five injured, including two children with burns in at least 20 percent of the body, and there was a projection of the 19th floor of various objects to the public road, including a washing machine.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:52:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumption | Exchange of elderly cards available</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/consumo-troca-de-cartoes-de-idosos-disponivel/</link><description>From today, more than 60 posts are open to replace Macau Pass cards that allow the discounts of the great consumption award. Until March 20, residents over 65, or their representatives, can exchange cards free of charge in social service institutions and civic associations spread across the territory
 
With the initiative to incentive the local consumption award to be pulled on March 24, the government today takes the first step in preparing for the distribution of discounts. Today they open more than 60 posts for replacing the “Macau Pass Card for the Elderly”, which allows a new modality of participation compared to previous rounds of the support program for residents over 65 years.
Spread out all over the territory, between social service institutions and civic associations, more than 60 posts will allow you to exchange cards free of charge by March 20. The direction of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) explains that exchange is required “since the chip used in the old version of Macau Pass for elderly to the loading of the card for immediate discount”.
Residents over 65 years old will benefit from two types of discounts, through Macau cards to the elderly and the electronic payment platforms. The inclusion of a physical card with direct discounts was one of the news of the new benefit round, after criticism of previous programs regarding the exclusion of the older population that does not know how to use, or have, online payment platforms.
Practical guide
To change the cards, the holder or a representative must go to one of the replacement posts bringing the old card, which will be collected by the services, in exchange for a lifting bead. This bead indicates the date to raise the new card, which the government estimates taking between 6 to 10 business days, with the balance of the old card to be automatically transferred to the new. The new card can be raised by the elderly or a representative by signing a power of attorney and presentation of their BIR.
The request for a duplicate of Macau Pass for the elderly implies the same steps for the exchange of cards, as well as similar deadlines.
Those who have never required Macau Pass for the elderly can do so at Macau Pass stores, the Jardim Fu Tat building on Paris Street, and at Macau Pass Centers on the Black Areia Marginal Road and Kwong Tung Avenue in Taipa. To request the card you need to present the BIR and a recent Pass type photograph. Cards can be raised within an estimated eight business days.
The holders of the “Macau Pass Card for the elderly” “will be able to participate in the program, with benefits at various levels, such as an immediate discount for consumption of 300 patacas by loading the card”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:47:41</pubDate></item><item><title>“Two Sessions” | Li Qiang highlights “Macau governed by patriots”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/duas-sessoes-li-qiang-destaca-macau-governada-por-patriotas/</link><description>The Chinese prime minister has repeated the principles and goals set in recent years to Macao and pointed out that China's gross domestic product will grow 5 percent throughout this year. The intervention was praised by the deputies of Macao in the National Popular Assembly
 
In the presentation of the annual work report of the central government, Prime Minister Li Qiang defended the application “unshakable” the principles “a country, two systems”, “Macau ruled by their people”, and the high degree of autonomy and safeguarding the constitutional order. The speech was given yesterday morning at the Great People's Hall in Beijing during the opening ceremony of the 3rd session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (APN).
Li Qiang has also indicated that the central government will support the territory to develop the economy, improve the population's living condition, deepen international cooperation, and promote a “better integration in global national development and the maintenance of prosperity and long -term stability”.
Li Qiang's speech did not truly have innovations towards Macao, and the repetition of policies set in the latest years. The same objectives were defined for Hong Kong, with the situation of the two special administrative regions to be presented together.
Li Qiang's speech was still marked by the forecast that the gross domestic product in the interior of China will grow five percent throughout this year, in what is always one of the most anticipated aspects of the central government's annual work report.
Macao applause
The Prime Minister's speech received several compliments from Macao deputies at the National People's Assembly, who promised to work “dedicated” to achieve the goals set.
Chui Sai Peng, quoted by Radio Macau's Chinese channel, highlighted the work done last year by the central government, indicating that all defined goals were achieved, despite the various challenges created by the economic environment. For this reason, the deputy considered that the prospects for the future are encouraging and that the population has reasons to be more confident, especially with regard to the development of high technology.
Kevin Ho, another of Macao members at APN, preferred to underline the various works foreseen in Li Qiang's speech to promote economic growth throughout this year, stressing that they will stabilize real estate and scholarship markets. Ho also stated that this year will show the resistance capacity of the economy of the country.
Ng Siu Lai considered that the central government report was quite realistic and will allow the country to continue progressing, while implementing measures to increase the pensions of urban and rural residents. According to NG, with the implementation of this report, the Chinese population will be more protected and improve the living level.
Already the former deputy of the Legislative Assembly Chan Hong chose to highlight the attention given to education issues, and the plans to progressively implement free education in preschool education.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:39:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Bernardo Mendia, Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong: “Portugal should extend your hand”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/bernardo-mendia-camara-de-comercio-e-industria-portugal-hong-kong-portugal-deve-estender-a-mao/</link><description>The Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry of Hong Kong, Sun Dong, arrives today, accompanied by entrepreneurs from digital areas, online trade and technology. Bernardo Mendia, Mayor of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong, highlights the importance of visiting Portuguese companies and Raehk as a complement to Portuguese contacts in Macau
 
 
Last year, Portugal was visited by Christopher Hui Ching-Yu, Secretary of Hong Kong Financial Affairs and Treasury, and now another Hong Kong ruler passes through Portugal. Is it a visit with added meaning?
As a Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong we consider this visit extremely important, valuing the attention that is being given to Portugal. It is important, above all, because it is such a specific area as innovation. This is an area where Hong Kong bets a lot and has been a priority for the region's authorities, and this is something that exists in common with Portugal, which has also bet on technological and scientific development. What Portugal should do is take this opportunity, extend your hand to the secretary and work in partnership. Technological and economic development is only done with international partnerships, opening markets and collaborations. This is also what we promote as a Chamber of Commerce. We have been involved in organizing this trip, something that started months ago. We will lead Portuguese companies to identify potential synergies with the entities that come here, so that they know each other and then do their work.
Hong Kong has been present in all editions of Websummit in Lisbon. Does this visit give the idea that the region intends to expand and establish more concrete partnerships with Portugal?
Yes, no doubt. This has evidenced in official speeches of the most important members of the Hong Kong government, including the executive's own head. This is the region's strategy at this time, being a bridge for the rest of the world to be able to enter Asia. Then the territory competes with other platforms, as Hong Kong, Singapore and Tokyo are perhaps the three territories with the greatest expression in this [technological] area in Asia. But Hong Kong presents the best conditions, not only for the support it gives [to companies], but also for being part of China, despite having a different legal system and a different currency. There is a system completely open at the level of capital circulation and internet access. I think Hong Kong is better positioned in this field, but this is a competition that the territory has to do, such as Portugal when it will perform in Asia, competing with Spain and other European countries in attracting foreign direct investment.
Macao is usually the main connection to Portugal, for historical reasons and the presence of the Portuguese language. Can Hong Kong also be a binding territory between Portuguese companies and Asia?
Macau and Hong Kong are very complementary in this regard. Macao has this historical connection with Portugal and has very important companies based in the territory, some of them for over 100 years, namely the National Bank Overseas. This experience, and the fact that the Portuguese language is still official, is undoubtedly an advantage for Portuguese companies. If it is necessary to enter the capital market, Portuguese companies will opt for a number of services provided by Hong Kong. But Macau has its own advantages and I consider it two very complementary markets. The geographical proximity of Macau and Hong Kong also acts as an attractive point.
During Christopher Hui Ching-Yu's visit last year, Hong Kong's position as Fiscal Paradise was addressed. How do you look at this question?
This visit is organized by the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Office and the tax issues will now be set aside. But our position, as a Chamber of Commerce, is that it makes no sense Hong Kong being on the list of tax havens, and makes no sense or from a legal point of view. None of the markets we compete with Hong Kong as a fiscal paradise, nor the European Union itself. We just have to lose with it, because we create barriers to trade and foreign direct investment in Portugal, and also the investment that is made by Portuguese companies in Macao, which are eventually affected by it. It makes no sense to this designation from a legal point of view, because Hong Kong does not gather the conditions to be part of the list of tax havens, and from the political point of view because no other European country puts the territory in this category.
China is present in the Portuguese market through various investments. Hong Kong is trying to create its own way?
Not in these terms. The overwhelming majority of Chinese investment that is made in Portugal is through Hong Kong. Then, in this respect, Hong Kong and China work in a quite complementary way. Hong Kong acts as a "aircraft carrier" from China in terms of foreign investment, and there is no competition between the two, working, together.
Encounters in Oeiras | Taguspark today hosts exchange sessions and seminars
Dong Sun is accompanied by Portugal by Hong Kong's most important companies and entities in the areas of innovation, technology and digital media, either government, with Hong Kong Science and Technology Park and “Cyberport”, technology park with budget projects in two billion Hong Kong; either academic and research, attending the entourage of the Hong Kong Applied Science and Technology Research Institute and “Hong Kong Microelectronics Research and Development Institute”.
Exchange sessions and seminars take place today from 4 pm at Taguspark, Oeiras, where Oeiras Valley Investment Agency is located, whose representatives have already been present in Macao for commercial contacts.
In the afternoon there will be the opportunity for dialogue between the Secretary of Hong Kong, representatives of the Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong and leaders of Raehk's technological parks and institutes, and in total 24 companies are represented.
In the Catalan road
In a statement issued by the Hong Kong executive, it is read that the program includes “meetings and exchanges with leaders of local political, business and innovation and technology sectors”, as well as visits to infrastructure, technological parks, research institutes and businesses.
The aim is to “reinforce ties and cooperation” with Portugal in this sector, “promoting the advantages of Hong Kong innovation and technology and exploring business opportunities abroad,” according to the statement.
Before passing through Lisbon, the delegation was in Barcelona to participate in the “Mobile World Congress”, considered one of the most influential technological events worldwide.
This is the second visit to Portugal of a member of the Hong Kong government within a year, after the secretary for financial services and treasure had passed through Lisbon in June. At the time, Christopher Hui Clay-Yu asked Portugal to remove Hong Kong from the list of tax havens and argued that it already fulfills the European Union standards to combat tax dropout.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Brazil | China suspends imports of beef of three factories</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/brasil-china-suspende-importacoes-de-carne-de-bovino-de-tres-fabricas/</link><description>China temporarily suspended imports of beef from three Brazilian factories, announced yesterday the government of Brazil, ensuring that the decision will not affect bilateral trade relations.
China's General Customs Administration has performed a series of “video audits” in the affected units and found that they do not comply with all the import requirements established by the Asian country, explained the Brazilian Ministry of Agriculture and Livestock in a statement.
The companies, whose names were not disclosed by the folder, have already been notified and are “taking corrective measures” to meet the demands of the Chinese body, according to the Brazilian government. China is the main destination of Brazilian beef exports and the largest commercial partner in the South American country.
Brazil, one of the world's largest animal protein suppliers, ended 2024 with a record production of 31.57 million tons of beef, pork and chicken, as well as record exports of 10.26 million tons, according to official data.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:22:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Press | All About Macau prevented from covering elections</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/imprensa-all-about-macau-impedido-de-cobrir-eleicoes/</link><description>The Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly, led by Seng Ioi Man, president of the Court of Second Instance, is blocking the All About Macau newspaper to cover the press conferences of the committee that organizes the September 14 legislative elections.
Following the election of Sam Hou Fai as Chief Executive, and during the term of Ho Iat Seng, the All About Macau newspaper began to be excluded from virtually all press conferences linked to local authorities, justifying that there are not enough vacancies for media professionals. According to this criterion, which is discretionary, the priority is attributed to publications with daily or weekly periodicity. However, several monthly local agencies, published in non -Chinese languages, can access events without embarrassment, although theoretically do not meet the required requirements.
It is also frequent to block access to the All About Macau newspaper, with the justification of lack of space, when the rooms where the conferences are held have several places available.
According to Article 27 of the Basic Law, MSar protects freedom of the press in the territory. According to Article 5 of the Press Law, this freedom implies the guarantee of the right to access the sources of information, which means contact with rulers and the possibility of questioning them.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:50:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Government launches new alert about Covid-19</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/governo-lanca-novo-alerta-sobre-covid-19/</link><description>Macao health services (SS) indicate a decrease in influenza cases, with the current situation “below the alert level”. However, in the case of COVID-19 infections, “the Sars-Cov-2 virus is becoming active,” therefore an appeal to vaccination, especially for chronic and elderly patients. The SS advance, however, that no death caused by Covid-19 has not yet been registered since the beginning of the year.
According to a note released yesterday, which cites laboratory data from the ninth week of the year, that is, from late February, “the Covid-19 detection positivity rate was 13.7 percent”, and this value “represents a significant increase compared to the previous week, 3.8 percent”.
In general terms, SS believe that “flu activity will remain active in the coming weeks”, but the attention, but for a certain stability. The number of patients served in the emergency service in the ninth week of 2025, that is, February, “decreased from the previous week”, having been attended a daily average of 1,190 people, 282 of them children.
Thus, “the descent trend of the influenza virus detection rate, from 10.5 percent in the eighth week of the year (below the alert level of 13.1 percent), to five percent in the ninth week”.
RISE IN DAILY AVERAGE
However, the SS warns that it is not yet time to ward off attention from flu, as it is “an average of about 83 [sick] people per day, which represents an climb compared to previous data”. Of these 83 people, 31 are adults and 52 children. Thus, SS understand that "the propagation of the respiratory tract virus in Macau is still active."
With regard to collective influenza cases, since January 46 occurred in the territory, as well as 25 cases caused by influenza A and five virus by influenza B virus.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:21:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Architecture | Seminar with Marco Imperidori takes place on the 20th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/arquitectura-seminario-com-marco-imperadori-decorre-dia-20/</link><description>The CAC - Circle of Macao Culture Friends organizes, on the 20th, a Seminar with Marco Imperidori, with sessions entitled “Architecture of Care” and “Arte Sella: a balance between architecture and nature”. Events take place at Macao University of Science and Technology, between 15h and 6:15 pm, and the registration deadline ends on the 19th.
Marco Imperradori is a full -seated professor and researcher at Milan Polytechnic, where he tends the technology design and innovation chair. Its work focuses on high energy efficiency buildings, construction/envelope construction systems and sustainability.
With a master's degree and a doctorate in construction engineering, it combines knowledge of architecture and engineering. It has been taught worldwide, including as a visiting professor at the University of St. Joseph in Macau from 2015 to 2023. As a delegate of the Rector to the Far East, it represents the Milan Polytechnic in Asia. Active researcher has published extensively on architectural innovation, sustainability and energy conservation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:10:27</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | IAT PO PORCELAINS EXPOSED UNTIL THE 14th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/frc-porcelanas-de-lei-iat-po-expostas-ate-dia-14/</link><description>It is called “Return to Navigation” and is the latest display patent in the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery available for free visit since Tuesday. This is the opportunity to see Porcelain pieces of IAT PO from Cantão, an area known for the traditional ceramic industry
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) inaugurated this Tuesday the Macao Porcelain and Guangzhou “Return to Navigation” exhibition, by artist Lei Iat Po (李溢坡). In the gallery, 40 pieces of color porcelain in the Cantão region will be available, a traditional industry originating from the Qing Dynasty and developed mainly for export. This industry gained popularity between European courts and western aristocracy, having been an important factor in promoting Chinese culture abroad from the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
According to a FRC note, Canton's porcelain - also known as Guangcai - is famous for the strong and vibrant colors, complex and intricate patterns, and gold -painted golden and richly decorated applications.
Being a typical southern industry of China, he also gained vitality in Hong Kong and Macao in the past twentieth century, namely from the 1930s invasions and during the political instability of the continent. Many factories moved to Macau and Hong Kong which fired production in southern China, namely in the 1950s, thanks to greater international demand of these oriental exoticism pieces growing in the postwar phase.
Canton's porcelain has been a successful example of a fusion between the east and the West over the centuries, contributing to the advantageous cultural exchange. In Macao, at the height of the 1960s, there were dozens of factories. But in the 1980s production returned to the continent, much more competitive in labor and costs, in the aftermath of the cultural revolution.
Family art
IAT PO Law was born in Macao in 1954, having revealed an interest in the art of color porcelain due to the family business. This was influenced since childhood by the father, who produced and exported pieces for European and American markets. Law IAT PO worked at your father's Guangcai Wooden Basis Factory and, later, at the Guangcai Colorful Porcelain factory.
Under the parent's guidance, he followed the famous Master Zhao Zhuo to learn burn control technology in the oven. Later, I would learn about artisanal painting techniques and porcelain color.
Curated by Margareth Lei Siu Heng, the collection available at the FRC presents invaluable pieces, for the quality and degree of complexity in execution, revealing the years of improvement and dedication to this centenary technique by the artist, who intends to continue to disseminate his art and preserve the important historical past. The works will be exhibited until March 14.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:08:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Panama Channel | China denies control and avoids commenting on ports</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/canal-do-panama-china-nega-controlo-e-evita-comentar-venda-de-portos/</link><description>China yesterday classified as “completely false” the allegations that controls the Panama Canal and avoided commenting on the recent sale of two ports on the navigable road by a Hong Kong group.
"China supports Panama's sovereignty about channel operations and is committed to maintaining it as an permanently neutral international river way," Lin Jian Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman said. The spokesman stated that the idea that China has full control over the channel is "completely false."
Asked about the sale of the ports of Balboa and Cristobal by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison conglomerate to a consortium led by American Blackrock, Lin refused to comment and recalled that the government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region has already spoken on the issue.
The agreement, valued at $ 22.8 billion, also includes the transfer of CK Hutchison's participation in 43 other ports from 23 countries, although it excludes terminals in China and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:05:47</pubDate></item><item><title>IPOR | Bai Li Group is the new shareholder</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/ipor-grupo-bai-li-e-o-novo-accionista/</link><description>The Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) has a new shareholder by decision made on January 24 this year at the 74th General Assembly of the Portuguese Teaching Institution as a foreign language.
This is the Bai Li Li Lda Lda Company. Thus joins the associative structure already composed by the Oriente Foundation, as a founding associate, Camões-Institute of Cooperation and Language, I.P., the National Bank Overseas, Quinta da Marmeleira and the Macao Tourism and Tourism Society (STDM).
According to an IPOR statement, the Bai Li group is recognized “for excellence in the area of ​​international trade, especially in the wine distribution sector”, and sought to position itself as a Sino-Portuguese commercial platform in Macao, investing over the years in a series of projects and activities in the Syno-Portuguese Commercial Cooperation Services platform ”.
The purpose of these actions, according to IPOR, is to help make Macau “a connection vehicle for the placement of Portuguese products in the Popular Republic of China, a strategy complemented with actions to promote tourism, culture and Portuguese language, thus aligning with the principles and objectives of IPOR”.
Also according to the same note, the entry of the new shareholder "demonstrates not only the recognition of the work developed by IPOR in the preservation and diffusion of Portuguese language and culture in the Asia-Pacific region, but also the identification and commitment of the company in reinforcing the mission that the institute ends."
Thus, "this cooperation is another step towards the affirmation of the role of IPOR not only as a disseminating agent of the economic and global value of the Portuguese language, but also of cultural and promoting intercultural cooperation."</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:01:05</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Yuanzhang (1328-1398), when he had not yet become Emperor Hongwu (1368-98), founder of the Ming Dynasty and was only a rebel that did not belong to the nobility, came down a large river when a rijo wind broke the mast of the ship carrying him.
Looking at the bank, he noticed in a large tree that rose from a temple and soon wished to use it to replace the broken mast. As he approached, however, the abbot of the monastery advised him that, before he did, he consulted the spirit of the temple by removing a tray of guessing. As he removed it, he read: "Everything under heaven has a master,/ an honorable man takes nothing to himself. Soon gave up on the intention.
The story illustrates the character of the future monarch that, being an orphan still very young, was welcomed in a Buddhist monastery as a novice monk, realizing the value of chance that since then has worked to peer. In the choice of his counselors, obeying this concern, themselves were committed to planning the following steps.
Among them was Liu Ji (1311-1375) also known as Liu Bowen, the 'Sincere Old' Military Stratega, statesman and poet, to whom works that responded to this desire to predict the succession of the days, such as the book of prophecy Shaobing Gene Quan Wen, 'The Full Song of the Shabing Ball, or the' Master's Philosophical Treaty ' From the brilliant trigram Li, the Fire », to clarify the world and the decision makers.
Among its short chapters is the edifying account of a Qin builder, the musical instrument of the literati, which was presented at the court was refused because it did not have the prestige of being ancient. Then he added some risks, buried him for a while and again introduced him, being very well received. Contrary to the contrary, the imperial counselor sought to clarify himself. As on a trip he made, in the fall of 1343, with a companion for the huangshan mountain range, the yellow mountain.
Leng Qian (c.1310-c.1371), this friend who was also scholarly in the arts and musical instruments, accompanied him in a way to an elevation, which from the time of Emperor Jiajing (r.1521-67) was designated Qiyun, 'tall as the clouds', being part of the way by sea, packed in the rhythm of the waves. This rhythm that Leng Qian, versed in the secrets of alchemy, sought to convey in the Painting Monte Baiyue (vertical roll, ink on paper, 84.4 x 41.4 cm, at the National Palace Museum in Taipei) who made Liu Ji's request to memorize the journey.
From the bank of the Hengjiang River, he made a painting free of options for styles or schools, taking advantage of chance, as Emperor Hongwu wanted.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves - Coordinator of the CCCM Educational Service
Zhuangzi, the Taoist philosopher, who will have lived between the fourth and 3rd century BC, possibly between 369 and 268 BC, left us in the homonymous work 《莊 (庄) 子》, as was customary at the time, the possibly transmitted teachings in the first person in the interior chapters (1-7), in the second person in the external chapters (8-21) and in the third person of other intellectuals in the chapters of miscellany (22-33).
It is an extremely motivating philosophy that rests, from my point of view, in three fundamental principles: the acceptance of spontaneous nature (道 giving); The Principle of Transformation (物化 Wùhuà), which leads to the postulate of an essential uniformity; and the non-acting (無為/无为 wuwéi), which presupposes the acceptance of a pre-established harmony and destination. We are facing the best order possible, so it is not right to interfere with what is given to us, letting us lead by a necessarily tension rhythm of life, but whose challenges should be viewed without negative reactions, following the existential bamboo model, when confronted with gigantic winds, such as those of tuffons in China.
Chapters 17 and 18, which now bring themselves allegedly belong to their closest disciples, who faithfully transmit the philosophy of the great Taoist master, and Taoism is the most devoted philosophy to develop a personal project, which will therefore exemplary from the existential point of view.
Completing Chapter XVII, that of the Full Full (Qiū Shuǐ Dìshiqī), is assisted at a symbolic dialogue between the philosopher Zhuangzi and his great friend Huizi (惠子), known in the synological tradition, of which Father Thomas Merton is a good herald in The Via de Zhuangzi (1999, 126-127) Joy of fish ”, whose guideline principle is that of communicating connectivity among all living beings, the same that guides another episode, reported at the end of Chapter II, that of the philosopher dreams of being a butterfly (Zhuangzi, 1999,38-40).
In Chapter XVII, Zhuangzi affects the unbelieving friend Huizi to realize, or rather perfectly intuit the joy of fish, since when looking at them on the Hao River bridge recognizes the signs that in themselves manifest when they feel happy. Friend Huizi, following a rationalizing and separatist philosophy, opposes that this is impossible, being silenced by the logical assumption of communication between all nature. Zhuangzi appeals to the argument that it is possible to extend the intelligent dialogue of humans to all living beings. The philosopher, winning the debate, widened the mastery of language, which now includes the verbal, but also the visual, much closer to silent and intuitive communication, highly valued by the Taoist school, always suspicious of excessive and discursive profanity. And at the same time, guarantees the primacy of the connection, sometimes visible, sometimes invisible, among all nature, rooted in Tao, after all this viable connection of a flow of feelings among all beings, which leads to true joy, against the sad and solipsist cosmos defended in some rationalist philosophical traditions, whose primacy is based on a reason to establish the connection with the body, whether individual or whether it is individual or Collective, as António Damásio had the opportunity to denounce in the error of Descartes (2011).
In fact, what matters so that joy is guaranteed, including humans, goes through a widening of the sphere of sensitivity, the feeling of oneself, still thinking of Damásio, the feeling of others, the recognition of the satisfaction coming from the profound connection between all nature.
Then move on to the translation of dialogue, the traditional Chinese to the contemporary and the contemporary to Portuguese:
原文 Classic Chinese1
莊子與惠子遊於濠梁之上。莊子曰： “鯈魚 2 出遊從容 ， 是魚之樂也。”
惠子曰： “子非魚 ， 安知魚之樂？”
莊子曰： “子非我 ， 安知我不知魚之樂？”
惠子曰： “我非子 ， 固不知子矣；子固非魚也 ， 子之不知魚之樂 ， 全矣。”
莊子曰： “請循其本。子曰‘ 汝安知魚樂 ’雲者 ， 既已知吾知之而問我 ， 我知之濠上也。”
今译 Contemporary Chinese
庄子和惠子在濠水桥上游玩。庄子说： “白鲦鱼从容不迫地游来游去 ， 这是鱼的快乐啊！”
惠子说： “您不是鱼 ， 怎么知道鱼是快乐的？”
庄子说： “您不是我 ， 怎么知道我不晓得鱼的快乐？”
惠子说： “我不是您 ， 固然不知道您；您本来也不知道鱼 ， 那么您不知道鱼的快乐 ， 是完全可以肯定的了。“
庄子说： “请回到原来的话题吧。您说‘ 您怎么知道鱼的快乐 ’这句话 ， 就是您已知道我晓得鱼的快乐而来问我的 ， —— 我是在濠水桥上知道的啊！”
(ZHUANGZI, 1999, 282-3)
Note that the translation I propose to Portuguese has some adaptation to our language, for example, I use conjunctions and conjunctive phrases to join prayers and avoid the repetition of certain verbs, with non-philosophical sense, to make reading more fluid:
Zhuangzi and Huizi were strolling on the Hao River bridge, when Zhuangzi said, "The fish swim calmly and carelessly from side to side, this is your joy!"
Huizi replied, "If it's not fish, how can you know the joy of fish?"
Zhuangzi replied, "You're not me, how can you know that I don't know about the joy of fish?"
Huizi continued: “I am not my friend, which is why I do not know him, and the Lord does not know the fish either, so it is more than certain that they do not know their joy.”
Zhuangzi concluded: “Let's go back to the root of the question. He said the following prayer: 'How can you know the joy of the fish', so you already realized that I knew their joy, so I asked me about me, I met her on the Hao River bridge! ”
This spontaneous and natural connection to all that exists is a source of great joy and happiness, as explained to us in chapter XVIII, entitled “Perfect Happiness”. Here the principle of non-acting (無為/无为 wúwéi) is defended, rather, of agreement with nature, inner and exterior, without seeking to interfere with the world around us, because if the goal is to achieve happiness, it is not acquired by any of our actions that have in view of material or social values, as well as wealth, honors, abundance or even health; We arrived at this world without being consulted and will leave when it is our time, as well illustrated the episode of the death of Zhuangzi's wife, reported in this same chapter. When Huizi visits his friend to introduce him to his condolences, he finds him crouching to drum into a basin and singing, in a clear acceptance of fate: yes, the woman had made her very good company over decades, she had to accept the law of nature and not revolt against the pre-established order, which tells us there is health and illness, wealth and poverty, life and death in an eternal transformation cycle.  "Genuine happiness is derived from the absence of happiness, just as perfect fame derives from the absence of fame." (至樂無樂 ， 至譽無譽, in the contemporary version of simplified Chinese, 最大的快乐在于 ‘无乐 '最高的荣誉在于‘ 无誉 ’(Zhuangzi, 1999, 286).
By non-acting, or rather, as we do not follow the existential models of the light/clairvoyant sky and the quiet earth, thus achieving perfect happiness and immense joy in living:
原文 Classic Chinese
天下是非果未可定也。雖然 ， 無為可以定是非。至樂活身 ， 惟無為幾存。請嘗試言之。天無為以之清 ， 地無為以之寧 ， 故兩無為相合 故兩無為相合 萬物皆化生。芒乎芴乎 無從出乎？芴乎芒乎 ， 而無有象乎！萬物職職 ， 皆從無為殖。故曰天地無為也而無不為也
今译 Contemporary Chinese
天下的是非确实还难以下定论。尽管如此 ， “无为” 可以定是非。最大的快乐能存活身心 ， 而只有清静无为才几乎可以存活身心。请让我说说试试看：天 “无为” ， 因而清虚; 地 “无为” ， 因而宁静 ， 天与地这两个无为的合一 ， 才孕育出万物的存在。恍恍惚惚 才孕育出万物的存在。恍恍惚惚 ， 不知道它们从哪里生出来！恍恍惚惚找不出一点迹象来！万物繁多 “天地无心作为 ， 却没有一样东西不是从它们之中产生出来的。”
(ZHUANGZI, 1999, 286)
Translation proposal for Portuguese
It is very difficult to distinguish right from wrong in our world, even though it “not acting” can do so, which is the greatest happiness. Allow me to say it, the sky is clairvoyant because of its "not acting"; The earth is quiet because of its "not acting." Not acting conjugates from heaven and earth leads to pregnancy and existence of all that lives indistinctly, without realizing where they came from! Indistinctly, without traces, the myriads of beings arise, all created from a vital non-report. That is why it is said that, "Heaven and Earth create unintentionally, but nothing is generated."
And it is added in conclusion that it does not interfere with the heaven of the earth with the natural order of the "ten thousand beings" brings great joy and even supreme happiness following what is defended by the founder of Taoism, in chapter VII of the book of the road and virtue 《道德经 • 七》 3, in the translation of António Graça de Abreu (2013):
天長地久
天地所以能長且久者
以其不自生
故能長生
(……)
Eternal, heaven and earth.
Why eternal?
Do not exist for themselves,
So they remain forever.
(…)
(Abreu, 2013, 40-41)
Bibliography
ABREU, António Grace of (trad.). 2013. Book of the road and virtue. Tao Te Ching. 道德经. Lisbon: Nova Vega.
Damásio, Antonio. 2011. The error of Descartes. Emotion, reason and human brain. Lisbon: Themes and Debates.
MERTON, Thomas. 1999. The Chuang Tzu Via. Petrópolis: Vozes Publisher.
Qin Xuqing (秦旭卿), Sun Yongchang (孙雍长) (contemporary Chinese trad), Wang Rongpei () (汪榕培 汪榕培 English). 1999. Zhuangzi 庄子. Vol I and II. Hunan, Beijing, Hunan People's Publishing House, Foreign Languages ​​Press.
This space has the collaboration of the Scientific and Cultural Center of Macau, in Lisbon, and the opinions expressed in the article are the entire responsibility of the authors. https://www.ccccm.gov.pt/
The texts of this edition maintain the classic structure, but in simplified Chinese, however, for the sake of temporal coherence, the texts of this article will have traditional Chinese to follow the classic structure, while those of contemporary structure will be presented in simplified Chinese, following the edition without any changes.
A very common type of fish in the waters of the rivers of China, whose scientific name is Leuciscus macropus.
The synograms of the text presented by Graça de Abreu were converted to traditional Chinese, as happened with the Zhuangzi edition.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Yuanzhang (1328-1398), when he had not yet become Emperor Hongwu (1368-98), founder of the Ming Dynasty and was only a rebel that did not belong to the nobility, came down a large river when a rijo wind broke the mast of the ship carrying him.
Looking at the bank, he noticed in a large tree that rose from a temple and soon wished to use it to replace the broken mast. As he approached, however, the abbot of the monastery advised him that, before he did, he consulted the spirit of the temple by removing a tray of guessing. As he removed it, he read: "Everything under heaven has a master,/ an honorable man takes nothing to himself. Soon gave up on the intention.
The story illustrates the character of the future monarch that, being an orphan still very young, was welcomed in a Buddhist monastery as a novice monk, realizing the value of chance that since then has worked to peer. In the choice of his counselors, obeying this concern, themselves were committed to planning the following steps.
Among them was Liu Ji (1311-1375) also known as Liu Bowen, the 'Sincere Old' Military Stratega, statesman and poet, to whom works that responded to this desire to predict the succession of the days, such as the book of prophecy Shaobing Gene Quan Wen, 'The Full Song of the Shabing Ball, or the' Master's Philosophical Treaty ' From the brilliant trigram Li, the Fire », to clarify the world and the decision makers.
Among its short chapters is the edifying account of a Qin builder, the musical instrument of the literati, which was presented at the court was refused because it did not have the prestige of being ancient. Then he added some risks, buried him for a while and again introduced him, being very well received. Contrary to the contrary, the imperial counselor sought to clarify himself. As on a trip he made, in the fall of 1343, with a companion for the huangshan mountain range, the yellow mountain.
Leng Qian (c.1310-c.1371), this friend who was also scholarly in the arts and musical instruments, accompanied him in a way to an elevation, which from the time of Emperor Jiajing (r.1521-67) was designated Qiyun, 'tall as the clouds', being part of the way by sea, packed in the rhythm of the waves. This rhythm that Leng Qian, versed in the secrets of alchemy, sought to convey in the Painting Monte Baiyue (vertical roll, ink on paper, 84.4 x 41.4 cm, at the National Palace Museum in Taipei) who made Liu Ji's request to memorize the journey.
From the bank of the Hengjiang River, he made a painting free of options for styles or schools, taking advantage of chance, as Emperor Hongwu wanted.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>China temporarily suspended imports of beef from three Brazilian factories, announced yesterday the government of Brazil, ensuring that the decision will not affect bilateral trade relations.
China's General Customs Administration has performed a series of “video audits” in the affected units and found that they do not comply with all the import requirements established by the Asian country, explained the Brazilian Ministry of Agriculture and Livestock in a statement.
The companies, whose names were not disclosed by the folder, have already been notified and are “taking corrective measures” to meet the demands of the Chinese body, according to the Brazilian government. China is the main destination of Brazilian beef exports and the largest commercial partner in the South American country.
Brazil, one of the world's largest animal protein suppliers, ended 2024 with a record production of 31.57 million tons of beef, pork and chicken, as well as record exports of 10.26 million tons, according to official data.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Yuanzhang (1328-1398), when he had not yet become Emperor Hongwu (1368-98), founder of the Ming Dynasty and was only a rebel that did not belong to the nobility, came down a large river when a rijo wind broke the mast of the ship carrying him.
Looking at the bank, he noticed in a large tree that rose from a temple and soon wished to use it to replace the broken mast. As he approached, however, the abbot of the monastery advised him that, before he did, he consulted the spirit of the temple by removing a tray of guessing. As he removed it, he read: "Everything under heaven has a master,/ an honorable man takes nothing to himself. Soon gave up on the intention.
The story illustrates the character of the future monarch that, being an orphan still very young, was welcomed in a Buddhist monastery as a novice monk, realizing the value of chance that since then has worked to peer. In the choice of his counselors, obeying this concern, themselves were committed to planning the following steps.
Among them was Liu Ji (1311-1375) also known as Liu Bowen, the 'Sincere Old' Military Stratega, statesman and poet, to whom works that responded to this desire to predict the succession of the days, such as the book of prophecy Shaobing Gene Quan Wen, 'The Full Song of the Shabing Ball, or the' Master's Philosophical Treaty ' From the brilliant trigram Li, the Fire », to clarify the world and the decision makers.
Among its short chapters is the edifying account of a Qin builder, the musical instrument of the literati, which was presented at the court was refused because it did not have the prestige of being ancient. Then he added some risks, buried him for a while and again introduced him, being very well received. Contrary to the contrary, the imperial counselor sought to clarify himself. As on a trip he made, in the fall of 1343, with a companion for the huangshan mountain range, the yellow mountain.
Leng Qian (c.1310-c.1371), this friend who was also scholarly in the arts and musical instruments, accompanied him in a way to an elevation, which from the time of Emperor Jiajing (r.1521-67) was designated Qiyun, 'tall as the clouds', being part of the way by sea, packed in the rhythm of the waves. This rhythm that Leng Qian, versed in the secrets of alchemy, sought to convey in the Painting Monte Baiyue (vertical roll, ink on paper, 84.4 x 41.4 cm, at the National Palace Museum in Taipei) who made Liu Ji's request to memorize the journey.
From the bank of the Hengjiang River, he made a painting free of options for styles or schools, taking advantage of chance, as Emperor Hongwu wanted.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Economy | Trips to China increase due to diversity and low prices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/03/economia-viagens-a-china-aumentam-devido-a-diversidade-e-precos-baixos/</link><description>Going to China has never been so easy, fast and cheap. Two residents of Macao of Portuguese nationality reveal to HM which leads them to cross the border frequently, especially the weekend. Cultural diversity, low prices and higher quality of service in bars and restaurants make all the difference
 
Macao Small and Medium-sized (SME) have faced, since the reopening of borders in the postpandeia period, huge difficulties to recover the business, especially those that are further away from the tourist areas. At a time when traveling to China has become extremely easy and cheap, two residents explain why they prefer to move often to the neighboring city of Zhuhai, or even Shenzhen, and consume there instead of being in Macao. Options like dinner outside, catching a taxi or drinking a glass are much cheaper, and the possibility of driving outside the territory has made this option more frequent. But electronic trade has also contributed to the fall of local consumption, they ensure.
Nelson Moura, journalist and resident of Portuguese nationality, goes to Zhuhai whenever he has a free weekend or holidays. It even goes between three to four times a month. “Costs are lower inside China, and then there is the novelty factor. It has never been easy for a non -Chinese resident of Macau to go to China. I previously needed to ask for a visa, had a reduced deadline, and this greatly limited my trips, and always chose more distant places in a context of tourist travel. Local residents could go to China before, but the current convenience, with organized and developed borders, especially Hengqin, with the connection to the light meter, allows for easier connections, ”he told HM.
Since China has flexed the policy of visas and increased the offer of border circulation, traveling to the country is no longer seen as a great trip. “As a foreigner residing in Macao, going to China was a bit like going traveling to another Asian country. In the pandemic we did not go practically from Macau, but now since the policy of visas to Portuguese has been flexible, it is possible to go to China whenever we want, ”said Nelson Moura.
“I am as easily as a Chinese resident, and it has become a viable option to go to the weekends and holidays to China, knowing different sites. The food is a third of the price of what is practiced in Macau, has more quality, with fresh products, the reception offers are better. Macao is a great city, but after three years of pandemic knows very well to get out of here whenever we want. It is a more convenient option now than before. ”
Nelson Moura also considers that "for the Chinese community of Macao and Hong Kong there is a greater convenience of travel," as "there are many residents leading all weekends to China just to go to large commercial surfaces, which allows you to buy large amounts of food."
“Traffic near the border of the HKZM siege or bridge is at a level never seen before. There is the option of being able to drive in the large bay zone which is good for small and expensive cities like are Macau and Hong Kong, ”he said.
PME, the eternal problem
On the side of Macau, associations linked to the Chinese community's commercial sector call for help, asking for more measures such as the great consumption award, or even consumer cards, that is, more campaigns and initiatives so that residents can buy more in Macao with discounts or support.
One of the last voices showing concern about this scenario was Stanley Au, president of the Macao SME association. To TDM Canal Macau, the official argued that in the next lines of government action the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, has to show effective measures to avoid closing and, consequently, more unemployment. “The most urgent and current situation is the closure of companies. I believe the population saw many stores closed in different neighborhoods of the territory. Sometimes, on the same street, there are more stores closed than opened. In addition, the biggest problem is that Macau is facing continuous economic slowdown. If we do not solve this problem, society does not improve, ”he added.
However, according to Nelson Moura, it will always be difficult to combat the attraction of the consumption of Greater China. “Macao's local commerce is a complicated issue. There is a major reduction in consumers, especially on weekends and days when people have time to leave the city. ”
Electronic trade also enhances a reduction in local consumption. “Residents know they find more and cheaper out there. There are Chinese electronic trade companies such as TAOBAO, which allow purchases from all over China to Macau without transportation charges, which has reduced domestic consumption. People go to stores to see what they want to buy and then do it at Taobao. I don't know how this trend can be circumvented. It's capitalism to work, ”explained Nelson Moura.
The resident also draws attention to the fact that it is now easier to use online payment platforms in China with foreign cards or Macao banks, namely through MPay.
Nelson Moura believes that local SMEs have only endured so much time because they were in a kind of closed economic circuit. “Local businesses lived a little in an island economy, and they survived the fact that the Macao market is in the territory, without people could leave so much. Now that there has been competition with what China has to offer, companies suffer because they often don't offer the service so much quality and at such an attractive price. I know the situation in Hong Kong is similar. ”
“Like” in China
Macaense Miguel Rosa Duque has always worked in Macau and spent in the territory most of the days of the week, but since he started teaching in Zhuhai his life has become more across the border. Highlights the much cheaper night exits as well as the restoration offer. “Macao has no variety and people are filled with the fact that the territory is small. We have hotels and restaurants, but they are expensive because the lace are expensive. Faced with China, in terms of price, the difference is like between heaven and earth. I give an example: To take a taxi from the siege gates to the university where I teach it is 40 minutes of travel, 28 kilometers, and paid about 60 to 80 Renminbis. It's very cheap. In Macao, from the doors of the siege to Coloane we pay 150 patacas or more, the price difference is huge. ”
Miguel Rosa Duque says that the trips to China in her circle of friends have become so frequent that they even created a group on the WhatsApp social network to facilitate group walks. “I prefer to go to China a thousand times just for fun. I have a lot of variety of bars and nightclubs and in Macau everything is dead. A two -person massage costs 600 Renminbis in Macao costs twice. I don't talk about hotel massage. Customer service is much better in China, with more attention to customers, more attentive, and it's all cheaper. If we spend 1000 patacas on a night in Macao, China we spend 400 Renminbis and we are treated like kings. The variety is infinite in terms of restaurants. Macau can't compete, ”he said.
Miguel Rosa Duque says he has friends who, even with a car in Macau, eventually acquired another Chinese enrollment car who are parked in the border parking park because it is cheaper to rent a place to park.
Macaense understands that between local SMEs and trade in China “there is no possible competition”, especially with online sales platforms. “People no longer go to stores here, there are a thousand choices and you can buy it from home. My girlfriend rarely goes to the supermarket, does everything online, for example, ”he added.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Teaching | Chinese universities rise in ranking by disciplines</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/25/ensino-universidades-chinesas-sobem-em-ranking-por-disciplinas/</link><description>Chinese universities have risen at the “World University Rankings by Subject 2025” in various areas, although in arts and humanities Asia remains short of other continents. In 11 disciplines analyzed, such as Law, Management and Economics, China and Singapore are in the 50 best, while Hong Kong stands out in Education Studies
 
The latest world ranking of Higher Education areas of Times Higher Education, the “World University Rankings by Subject 2025”, concludes that universities in the interior of China have risen for top positions, although Asia continues to position themselves in the areas of arts and humanities.
In total, 11 academic areas were analyzed. “Arts and Humanities”, “Business and Economics”, “Computer Sciences”, “Education Studies”, “Engineering”, “Law”, “Life Sciences”, “Medicine and Health”, “Physical Sciences”, “Psychology” and “Social Sciences”.
It is concluded, according to an official note from Times Higher Education (The), that “China and Singapore appear among the 50 best in all 11 subjects”, especially the University of Beijing and Tsinghua University, respectively, for fourth and sex places in “business and economy” disciplines. In fact, “Asia's best performance is registered in the areas of management and economics”, with “its main universities to continue to have difficulty competing worldwide in the field of arts and humanities”. "Concerns about the 'crisis' in humanities seem to be designed to continue this year, but the analysis of The reveals the continuous importance to elite institutions."
Given the analysis of 11 academic areas, the neighboring region of Hong Kong stands out in nine, especially in the area of ​​education, where the University of Beijing and Tsinghua also achieved good results. “The National University of Singapore again occupies the ninth position in Engineering, entering the top 10 of the physical sciences-the first institution in Asia to achieve it-in 10th place,” is also read.
Quoted by the same grade, Simon Marginson, professor at Oxford University, an institution that usually leads rankings worldwide, said that Asia's performance in this classification shows “the multipolar world of higher education” existing today, with greater amplification “national academic capacity”.
"In this context, over time, the relative position of Anglosfera and Western European countries has to decrease, not because its absolute quality is decreasing, but because the field of comparison is more filled with other countries to emerge," he said.
The same responsible also pointed out that "East Asia and Southeast Asian higher education systems have improved over the past two decades due to the growth in the number of students, increased public funding, more performance -oriented organization and management and selective internationalization policies."
One of the areas where there is a better position of Asian universities is in education studies, showing “a remarkable force, with three universities in the top 10, with the University of Hong Kong in sixth place, the University of Tsinghua in seventh place and the university of Beijing in eighth place”. In addition, The Show that the Chinese University of Hong Kong has made “significant progress” from 19th to 11th position. On the other hand, the Taiwan National University of Science and Technology (Taiwan Tech) obtained "the highest score in terms of research quality."
However, global leadership goes to Stanford University, "surpassing the University of California, Berkeley, demonstrating exceptional performance in both teaching and research environment."
China rises in law
Looking at the area of ​​law, there is currently, according to the ranking of The, the best place to study than Stanford University, which has achieved “excellence in teaching and research environment”, followed by Harvard University, with “exceptional performance” and, thirdly, the University of New York, “with the highest score in terms of research environment”.
Highlight, in this area, for the entrance of the University of Beijing in 14th position, in part due to the good classification “in teaching and the research environment”. It should be noted that, as regards the law, 389 institutions from 48 countries and territories were classified, using 18 “strict performance indicators”.
In the area of ​​law, specialties are analyzed such as constitutional and administrative law and examination to structures and frameworks of governance, or international law, which includes global legal systems and treaties.
Capital Knowledge
China also stands out in business and economy, led by Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT). The University of Beijing rose to fourth place, accompanied by 20 other Chinese universities that improved their positions in the table. In this area were analyzed 990 institutions from 85 countries and territories, with the attention focusing on the quality of teaching and research in disciplines such as strategic leadership, international business and organizational development, as well as business finances or economic.
With regard to the social sciences, China actually comes below the list of the top 20, again with the University of Beijing in 16th and the University of Tsinghua in 20th. Here, the lead is up to MIT, passing Stanford University for the third to call Oxford, with "exceptional performance in teaching and research environment." The London School of Economics and Political Science remains an integral institution of the top 10, now occupying ninth place.
1,093 institutions from 100 countries and territories were analyzed in disciplines such as media communication and studies, politics and international studies, including development studies, sociology, geography and anthropology.
China also rose in the discipline of Computer Science with the University of Beijing to move from 16th to 12th place. In this area, leads the University of Oxford, reaching its highest score ever.
MIT Leads in Arts
The MIT has been at the head of Stanford University, assuming “first place in arts and humanities, as well as business, economy and social sciences”, even if it is first recognized “by specialization in the fields of science, technology, engineering and mathematics”. According to the ranking, it is now “the best place to study arts - with high scores in each of the five pillars underlying the methodology, especially the quality of the investigation and the international perspective”.
In the 11 disciplines of the ranking, "Stanford ranked first in education, law and psychology studies, Harvard University ranked first in engineering and life sciences."
The only local institution in the ranking of The Disciplines is the University of Macao (one), but in places far below top 10: in the area of ​​computational sciences, it is in the 126-150 best in the world, a similar position occupied in the area of ​​education and engineering. In the area of ​​law, for example, one is in the best group of 176-200, while in life sciences is among the 151-175 best.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 04:59:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Digital insomnia treatment can combat depression</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/estudo-tratamento-digital-de-insonia-pode-combater-depressao/</link><description>An unprecedented study developed by several universities, including the Chinese Hong Kong University and the University of Beijing, concluded that cognitive behavioral therapy through mobile phone applications can help combat young people by monitoring insomious. The rate of disease reduction is about 40 percent
 
The study “Effectiveness of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy Based on insomnia for insomnia in the prevention of Major depressive disorder in insomnia and subclinical depression: a random clinical trial” [Effectiveness of App-Based Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Insomnia on Preventing Major Depressive Desorder Inorder Whit Insomnia and Subclinical Depression: Randomized clinical trial] promises answers to the treatment of cases of depression in the younger ones.
The work, published by PLOS MEDICINE magazine and developed by academics from various universities in Hong Kong and China, including the University of Hong Kong, Chinese Hong Kong University or the University of Beijing, concludes that it is possible to reduce, by about 40 percent, cases of depression in young people with the use of a mobile phone application that monitors insoponies, a habitual symptoms, a symptom in the one who suffers from the sufferers illness. The data were presented at the end of last week in Hong Kong.
To reach the results, a random sample of more than 700 young Chinese from the interior of China and Hong Kong with insomnia disturbance and depressive symptoms, aged 15 to 25 years, who underwent testing with application for six weeks, was chosen.
Thus, “this controlled and random study evaluated the efficacy of cognitive behavioral therapy for application based on application (TCC-I) in preventing the future appearance of Major Depressive Disturbance (MDD) in young people” can be read. This at a time when "more and more evidence suggests that insomnia plays an important role in the development of depression," in this investigation "intervention in insomnia as a promising approach to prevent depression in young people."
Thus, “applications based TCC-I is effective in preventing the future appearance of major depression and improving the results of insomnia among young people with insomnia and subclinical depression”. The study also concludes that "these results underline the importance of aiming at insomnia to prevent the appearance of DMG [a type of depression] and enhance the need for greater dissemination of digital TCC-I to promote sleep and mental health in the young population."
It is also concluded that the TCC-I based on applications "not only improved nightly symptoms, but also reduced daytime fatigue and led to greater change to maturity."
More than 700 young people analyzed
After testing the application of TCC-I, base clinical interviews were conducted over a period of six to 12 months to understand the results in participants and monitor symptoms. We spoke, in the period between September 9, 2019 and November 25, 2022, of 708 participants, of which 407 was women (57 percent), with an average ages of 22 years. The study also points out that “37 participants, 10 percent, in the intervention group and 62 participants, 18 percent, in the control group developed new mood disturbances over the 12 months of follow -up”.
In turn, the group that was subject to CBT-I based on mobile phone application, ie cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia, presented “rates of remission of insomnia disturbance higher than post-intervention control groups” within one year. In addition, the same group "reported a greater decrease in depressive symptoms than post-intervention controls and over six months of follow-up." The authors of the study understand that "insomnia was a mediator of the effects of intervention on depression", and no adverse events related to interventions were reported. "
The authors left for this study with some proven ideas that insomnia is one of the main causes for depression. "Emerging data on insomnia intervention, especially cognitive behavioral therapy for insomnia (TCC-I), have shown promising results in insomnia relief and depressive symptoms in patients with insomnia," he reads.
Existing investigations focus on adults and elderly, so it was important to analyze this matter among the younger ones.
"In addition, there are few studies with appropriate statistical power to demonstrate the preventive effect of TCC-I on depression, both at symptoms and disturbances," explains the study authors, stressing that "little is known about whether the digital insomnia intervention can potentially prevent juvenile depression."
Important meanings
The study also points out that cognitive behavioral therapy for applications based on insomnia is a viable and effective intervention to prevent future depression at both symptoms and disturbances in young people. ” However, further studies are recommended to explore “the integration of application-based TCC-I in clinical practice to improve accessibility and prevent depression among the young population”.
It is also mentioned the need for more clinical trials “to explore the potential benefits of adapting digital interventions on sleep in relief and prevention of depression” in order to “move towards personalized and staggered care approaches to the community”.
Limitations are referred to in this study published in “PLOS Medicine”, namely “the inclusion of a mixture of individuals with and without prior depression, and a limited sample of adolescents, although there was an adequate global sample”.
To the Hong Kong press, the study authors spoke of the importance of these results and how they can constitute new tools in future treatments of the disease. Quoted by The Standard HK, Chen Si-Jing, the first author of the Postdoctoral Research and Psychiatry Department of the Chinese University of Hong Kong, said the study "shows that Digital TCC-I is effective in preventing the future appearance of severe depression, with satisfactory effectiveness." Wing Yun-Kwok, director of the Li Chiu Kong family sleep evaluation unit, indicated that future studies will focus on digital intervention on insomnia in clinical practice.
The unprecedented character of this study in Asia still gives him greater importance. According to Lu Lin, an academic at the Chinese Academy of Sciences and president of the PKU Sixth Hospital, to date "no investigation in Asia had been carried out on the effectiveness of this therapy."</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:07:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | “Two sessions” start today focusing on the economy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/pequim-duas-sessoes-arrancam-hoje-com-foco-na-economia/</link><description>The month of March is synonymous with political movements in Beijing, with the political advisory conference of the Chinese people, which begins today, and the session of the National Popular Assembly, which begins tomorrow. At meetings will be discussed goals and political and economic plans for this year, without forgetting the evolution of the International Panorama
 
Today begins another session of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), in Beijing, while for tomorrow is scheduled the start of the National Assembly (APN). The two events are the most important of the Chinese political system, materializing the country's political representativeness system, with the participation of delegations all provinces and regions of China, including the special administrative regions of Macau and Hong Kong. CCPPC has, as the name implies, an advisory character, while APN is the most important legislative body in the country.
The so -called “two sessions”, with annual periodicity, draw the attention from around the world because it is at this time that the Chinese government presents its economic goals and main political measures for the rest of the year.
According to the Xinhua state agency, data related to the country's gross domestic product (GDP) is one of the most attention points attracts, but the "two sessions" will also serve to shed some lights on China's foreign policy, something particularly remarkable in a turbulent global scenario.
Until March 11, the expected date for the end of the work, there are objectives, calendars and essential policies, shaping “the political direction of the country” in a “complex and challenging global environment”, reads in Xinhua.
Let us look, then, to what we can expect in matters of GDP values. “As the Chinese economy is oriented for high quality development, GDP is not the only measure of the economy, but it remains an important indicator. In 2024, China reached its objective of economic growth of about five percent, thanks largely to a number of significant macroeconomic measures, introduced to compensate for the pressure of economic recession, ”he reads.
Thus, "more concrete policies to stimulate economic activity are expected." According to Xinhua, "China has already given signs of change in its macroeconomic orientation." "At the last central conference of economic labor, in December, political officials committed to apply more proactive macroeconomic policies in 2025."
Thus, the adoption of a “moderately flexible 'monetary policy was decided, which represents a significant removal of the' prudent 'approach adopted in the last 14 years,” the agency describes. In this meeting were also defined “nine fundamental priorities”, the first “the increase of consumption”.
Thus, it is expected that in the “two sessions”, “China emphasizes internal demand as the main economic priority”, and this year it is expected “that large-scale equipment updates and consumer exchange programs will be promoted with greater intensity and more extended”.
It is indicated that "China will actively use the maneuver margin for a higher deficit and increase the issuance of special obligations of local administrations", as well as "continuing to issue Special Treasury obligations with a longer term and increase central government transfer payments to local administrations." The "two sessions" will reveal more details in this regard.
Featured
Still on the economic level, Xinhua describes how President XI Jinping underlines on other occasions “the main priorities, such as support for the growth of the private sector”, “the acceleration of the development of the digital economy” and the deepening of the country's opening.
APN members “will analyze the annual budget and government development plan”, and proposals and suggestions related to Artificial Intelligence (AI) ”are also expected to be expected. In fact, this is “one of the main points of interest to China observers”, along with GDP values. It should be noted that, in this field, the country has sought to score points and gain a growing positioning in the market with the creation of the Deepseek platform.
According to the Global Times newspaper, Chinese companies such as Tencent, Baidu and Byd are part of DeepSeek in the products and services they make available, and "some local governments have also announced collaborations with Deepseek IA models to improve public services."
“Many AI-related plans mentioned in work reports of provincial governments [from China] focus on building innovation platforms, promoting industry deeper integration and improving political staff. It is important to note that the rise of platforms such as DeepSeek reflects China's commitment to make leadership in technological advances and a greater strategic focus on talent cultivation and the existence of an innovation conducive environment, ”he reads.
The “two sessions” also constitute “a crucial platform for political legislators and counselors to present suggestions and promote ample consensus on national development” in the AI ​​area, and “some of them are executives of renowned companies and researchers”.
GDP: Maintenance
Still with regard to Chinese GDP, an analysis by Neil Thomas and Jing Qiang of the Asia Society Policy Institute argues that the “two sessions” should reveal “an even more agenda for growth than last year, with approximate objectives of five percent for GDP growth, four percent for the GDP tax deficit and two percent inflation in terms of consumption ”. "Measures should also be introduced to increase consumption and encourage the private sector in innovation," the authors write.
The same analysis of the Asia Society Policy Institute also highlights economic measures to prevent and combat unemployment, a problem that has affected the Chinese economy in recent times.
“China will also announce the annual goals for new jobs in urban areas and the urban unemployment rate. Last year, Beijing settled these objectives in 12 million new jobs and 5.5 percent unemployment rate, and this year's numbers will probably be similar, ”is mentioned.
With regard to domestic consumption, China is intended to be more and more “a hub for product launch, winter tourism and has a 'silver savings' focusing on the area of ​​restoration for an elderly population”. Also according to the analysis of the Asia Society Polycy Institute, "other priorities include rebalancing economic platform regulations, stimulating economic activity in small towns, greater integration into the area of ​​the large bay and expanding investment in maritime industries."
Attention to Investment
The "two sessions" take place with Donald Trump to return to the Presidency of the United States of America and certainly that this point will mark the external agenda of the meetings in Beijing throughout the week.
But still regarding the economy, the Chinese authorities will seek to present and discuss measures that may maintain foreign investment attraction in the country, after the launch of the “Action Plan to stabilize foreign investment”, on February 19.
Here is a “strategic change in Beijing's approach, moving away from tax benefits and subsidies and addressing the liberalization of specific sectors, rationalizing regulation and incentives for re-inbackets,” the same analysts point out.
Therefore, Beijing intends to “frame foreign companies into China's regulatory framework to turn them into long -term stakeholders, making local expansion more attractive than capital reafect to other markets”. Analysts also expect the "two sessions" to reveal concrete policies in this regard.
Sam Hou Fai in Beijing
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, has been in Beijing since yesterday to attend the opening ceremony of the third session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (APN), which takes place tomorrow.
Sam Hou Fai will be in the Chinese capital until Thursday of this week. According to a statement from the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai will be replaced by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, who acts interimly, the functions of Chief Executive.
In the 14th APN, the Government's work report will be reviewed and the analysis of the report on the implementation of the Annual National Economic and Social Development Plan for 2024. The agenda also includes analysis to the National Economic and Social Development Project for this year. The report on the implementation of the central and local budgets for 2024 will also be analyzed, as well as the central and local budget projects for 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:50:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomacy | Macao Platform seen in the context of Chinese foreign policy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/19/diplomacia-plataforma-de-macau-vista-no-contexto-da-politica-externa-chinesa/</link><description>In "Paradiplomacy in China: Macao's role in relations between sino-Portuguese countries," Xu Heng Wang concludes that the role of platform with Lusophony "can be seen with extension of China's foreign policy." However, the MSar presents its own ideas, without a “complete obedience to the central government”, indicates the academic
 
Macao's diplomatic role in the relationship with China and Portuguese -speaking countries was the focus of Xu Heng Wang's doctoral thesis defended in January at the University of Coimbra (UC) Faculty of Economics. In “Paradiplomacy in China: Macao's role in relations between sino-Portuguese countries”, the author argues that, regarding the role of Economic and Commercial Platform of MSA in the connection of Beijing and Portuguese-speaking countries, there is a certain extent of Chinese foreign policy, but at the same time, ideas proper to local authorities.
"Although the role of Macao as an economic and commercial platform can be seen as an extension of China's foreign policy, this does not mean that Macau is in a state of complete obedience to the central government," is referred to in research work.
Although it is stressed that “it is difficult to discern Macao's desire to develop, it must be mentioned that Macau has his own ideas about the course of his development”, namely in relation to the game and the entire economic structure.
“Macao has long foresaw that the structure of his economy would be unbalanced and that the game would be dominant. Authorities and academics have also made many debates on the issue of unsustainable development based on the game industry. At the same time, Macau is also very aware of its advantages in terms of cultural integration, having carried out the construction of a historic and cultural city, becoming a tourist attraction. ”
Between the own ideas and what is defined in the field of foreign policy by Beijing, there is "a direction of the development of Macao which, basically, is consistent with the role that the central government has conceived to Macao."
In this context, the author concludes that “the interests of Macao and the Central Government are basically the same”, being “a special case of paradiplomacy in China”, due to the implementation of politics “a country, two systems” in the territory and the high degree of autonomy it provides in various areas.
THE ROLE OF THE MACAU FORUM
Xu Heng Wang took a different approach on this issue, not resorting to traditional international relations theories, because “Macao interactions involve both state and non-state actors,” so these theories “do not provide an accurate explanation of Macao's role”. Thus, and to understand the role of Macau in the relations between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries, the idea of ​​paradiplomacy with Guanxi theory, a term used to describe social, economic or political relationships that can enhance business or other benefits, was combined.
Thus, it is said that "the creation of the Macau Forum can be considered one of the prominent paradiplomatic activities," with "Macao playing a role that mixes its development with the strategic objectives of the Chinese central government, especially with regard to Portuguese -speaking countries."
Macao has performed some relevant activities in the relations between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, ”although it is assumed that“ the results have been limited so far ”.
The academic states that these activities are "mainly concentrated in the fields of economics, education, tourism, culture and technology, with political effects that are not yet so evident." In addition, it is pointed out that "the influence of Macau on the relations between China and the different Portuguese -speaking countries has varied in intensity." Still, "much of the interaction and cooperation between Macao, China and the Portuguese -speaking countries occurred through the Macao Forum."
Help with objectives
In general terms, the “paradiplomacy of Macao is a complex and fluid process”, and the territory “shows its identity as a world tourism and leisure center and a characteristic financial center with international activities”, with the aim of “improving economic structure” and making diversification beyond game.
The author highlights fundamental areas such as services for small and medium enterprises, exchange-cultural and formation of bilingual talents. In addition, it is explained that “the central government provides political support to Macau based on its foreign policy needs, with the reinforcement of cooperation” with Portuguese -speaking countries. In these actions, include the Great Bay project, as well as the idea of ​​Macao's establishment as the Renminbi Compensation Center (RMB).
“On the one hand, the central government provides conveniences to Macau and helps [the territory] to establish its identity, 'supported by the mainland China market'. On the other hand, it helps Macau to develop the activity of RMB compensation center for transactions that occur on the Macao negotiation platform. ”
Thus, it denotes the author, "the role of Macao in paradiplomacy, but as an assistant to the implementation of central foreign policy, is also evident." However, "the paradiplomacy of Macao does not only reflect the diplomatic objective of helping the Chinese government to establish relations with Portuguese -speaking countries, but also the improvement of Macau's own international influence."
The doctoral thesis also presents a practical case analysis of Macau's relationship with the most striking Portuguese -speaking countries in the economic relationship with China, namely Angola and Brazil. "For Angola, Macao has played an approach role to China," as the African country needs "foreign investment for the hydroelectric power, infrastructure and agriculture sector." Thus, the binding axis is made at the Macao Forum, where "Angola can establish relations with the Chinese central government and cooperate on investment, in addition to the oil sector."
In addition, "most of China's investment in Angola comes from large companies, while small and medium -sized companies still depend mainly on Macau for commercial cooperation."
In the case of Brazil the situation is slightly different, because “in sino-Brazilian relations, the role of Macao is not obvious”, more “centered around the BRICS”, a group of emerging economies initially founded by Brazil, Russia, India and China, which today has ten member countries.
“Although the first ministerial meeting of the Macao Forum (2003) preceded the first meeting of the BRICS (2009) leaders, the impact of the Macao Forum on Sino-Brazilian Relations is not obviously as good as the influence established through direct meetings. Therefore, in the early days of the establishment of diplomatic relations between China and Brazil, relations between the two countries developed more at national level. ”
It is also highlighted that "although the role that Macao has in the opening of a door to the mainland China market has been established in Brazil's eyes, the impact of Macau on sino-Brazilian relations has not yet become obvious."
It is certain, however, that in recent years "the continuous development of the Macao Forum and the continuous improvement of organizational activities, its attraction to Brazil has become increasingly evident." “As Brazil tries to expand trade, commercial cooperation and investment with China will no longer be concentrated only in national business giants and will be increasingly targeted at private companies,” is still completed.
Regarding Portugal, the “attitude is very positive”, to the existing historical connection. “In many memos and statements signed with China, Macau has been stated to play an increasingly important role as a link between China and Portugal. Portugal and China have great technical cooperation in the domains of new energies, aerospace industry and other technological innovations. There is also a profound relationship of cooperation in the field of education. ”
It is also noteworthy that Portugal “not only signed cooperation agreements in the field of teaching with universities in the interior of China, but also signed several cooperation and exchange agreements with the main universities of Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 00:24:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Vocational Education | Alert Study for Human Resources Failures in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/18/ensino-profissional-estudo-alerta-para-falhas-em-recursos-humanos-na-china/</link><description>A study published in The China Quarterly concludes that there are still many questions to resolve so that technical-professional education in China can respond to human resources needs. The work warns of the “rapid massification” of this type of education, with priority for “number of enrollment over quality”
 
Technical-professional education in China has been popularized, but a recently published study in Cambridge University Press's “The China Quarterly” magazine, concludes that there are still gaps to find that courses can actually respond to the country's needs in the industrial sector.
“More Graduates, Fewer Skills? Vocational Education Expansion and Skilled Labar Shortages in China ”[More graduates, less skills? The expansion of vocational education and qualified labor faults in China] is the name of the study developed by Xinmiao Song of the University of Lingnan, and Duudo XU of the University of Hong Kong Department of Sociology.
Academic work draws attention to the “disturbing tendency” of “rapid massification of vocational education, which gives priority to the number of enrollment over the quality of education” and “does not respond to the search for skills and qualified labor”.
In addition, the authors add to the “adverse consequences for both administrative management and teaching, caused by this scenario. “The development of competences often is up to post-school professional associations and an exclusive group of elite students. However, reform initiatives, such as the Manual Arts Campaign and competency contests, benefit only a few, without improving the prospects of employment of the student population in general. ”
Thus, the two academics argue that “more attention to the tensions inherent to China's teaching and vocational training system”, because “only when there is a deeper understanding of the underlying causes to the ineffective training of competences in professional schools can China achieve its national objective of industrial modernization”.
The study was developed in two vocational schools, and interviews were conducted to 104 students. In addition, ethnographic data of four doctoral projects were used in the area of ​​vocational education, developed between October 2017 and December 2020.
It is also noted that the country needs “increasingly urgent” of qualified workers “due to world economic competition”. However, "despite the massive expansion of the teaching and vocational training system in the last two decades, there is still a significant deficit of qualified labor," there is "debates about the ineffectiveness of vocational education." These focus above all on, “in the absence of institutional synergies between teaching and industry, but they often ignore the conflicts inherent to the vocational education system and the processes of competency training at the micro level”.
Practical difficulties
To the “micro level”, that is, in schools, the authors denote the existence of several difficulties in the effective functioning of these courses in line with the intended results.
In secondary education there is “a delicate balance between the promotion of social equality and the development of skills”. However, "analysis indicates that, in the context of the rapid expansion of secondary education, schools have difficulty effectively harmonizing these objectives."
“In order to maintain a proper student body, schools and teachers are often obliged to compromise the quality of candidates and teaching standards in the classroom. This situation generates a change in daily pedagogy and school administration to preserve discipline and stability, thus attributing the development of competences and the selection of talents-ideally a mission from the whole school-to extra-curricular professional associations, pursued by a few, ”he is added.
It is also concluded that “the acquisition of competences is a multifaceted process, shaped by the dynamic interaction between educators and students”, because “the academic preparation of students and their motivations to learn are equally pertinent for the formation of microcompetence, as are the resources of schools and the capabilities of teachers”.
Thus, “the resolution of the ineffective formation of competencies requires more than top initiatives to the base”, “a approach that recognizes the obstacles that students face in the acquisition of skills, as well as their seizures and uncertainties in the search for employment, is necessary.
The authors also talk about “elitism” in some formations related to handicraft courses and “competency contests”. "These initiatives may inadvertently suggest that handicrafts are reserved for a restricted number of people, as competencies contests often remain inaccessible to most vocational education students, both objective and psychologically."
Thus, the authors emphasize that "there is a significant undoing between this elitist approach to the acquisition of competences and the real conditions faced by vocational education students."
“The superficial promotion of manual labor spirit and the exclusivity of skills failed to truly resolve the challenges associated with the acquisition of skills, the search for employment and the commitment to follow technical professions among vocational education students,” is also mentioned.
Still, limitations in the study are referred to, namely the fact that it focuses only on public schools in higher secondary education, and the results may not completely represent other levels of vocational education, such as the higher institutes of vocational training ”.

Numbers from the “Factory of the World”
In the study is the intense industrial development that China has achieved in the last 40 years, emerging as the "factory of the world," as the authors describe, "taking advantage of their demographic dividends."
“However, the intensive model of labor growth has proved unsustainable due to population aging and intense global competition. To escape the 'medium income trap', the Chinese government has launched a series of industrial modernization actions in the transforming industry and services sectors, ”but“ despite the ambitious agendas for the next decade, the persistent scarcity of qualified workers continues to make these efforts difficult, ”he is mentioned.
By 2020, there were more than 23 million vocational students, so "this scarcity of skilled labor is a surprise," is referred to in the study, which highlights "the substantial efforts and resources that the Chinese government has dedicated to improving vocational education in recent years."
For example, “Free Secondary Professional Education, the expansion of higher vocational facilities in one million students from 2019 to 2021 and the creation of universities of applied technology” emerged. In addition, the vocational education system watched an unprecedented trajectory, with enrollment in secondary professional schools higher than increasing from 4.56 million in 2004 to 7.11 million in 2009 ″.
In terms of the need for human resources, the study cites data from China's Ministry of Human Resources and Social Security for 80 cities in the country. "The ministry's quarterly reports have revealed that the work between work/person looking for qualified labor reached a historical peak of 2.0 in early 2020", and "higher level qualified workers, technicians and higher technicians had a particularly high demand."
It is also noted that the Ministry of Education predicts that the country continues to confront this year “with a deficit of 30 million qualified workers, which represents a 48 percent break in domains such as materials, energy savings and vehicles powered by new energies”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-18 00:25:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Future Ready Talent Program released in Macau and Hong Kong</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/17/108890/</link><description>Wynn and insurer Aia are two of the 14 companies that are part of the “Future Ready” project, launched by LinkedIn on Thursday in Hong Kong. O programa aposta na formação profissional nas duas regiões administrativas especiais, com especial foco para a inteligência artificial
 
The LinkedIn social network, facing the world of work, launched last week in Hong Kong, a talent formation program that has the collaboration of 14 companies from the territory and Macao, namely the Aia insurer and the Wynn game operator. The program, titled “LinkedIn Future Ready”, aims to “equip professionals from Hong Kong and Macau with the skills needed to thrive in a rapidly evolving job market,” is referred to in a note of the organization.
The other participating companies or entities are the Cathay Pacific airline, the Chow Tai Fook jewelry group, the PLC group, the English Schools Foundation, the FWD group, the Hop Lun, the Link Asset Management, the MTR Corporation, the company that manages the hong Kong meter, and the PCCW consultant, without forgetting Prudential, Swire Properties, which operates in the real estate market, and the Hong Kong Jockey Club.
The program includes "initiatives for updating skills, knowledge exchange and [sharing] of data based information." Essentially, “Future Ready” intends to “equip companies with tools and resources needed to navigate a workforce transformation scenario and promote a culture of innovation”.
Given the latest projections of the social network, which published, in January, the report "Work Change Report - Ai Is Coming to Work" [Labor Change Report - Artificial Intelligence (IA) is coming to work], the program "Future Ready" aims to make more training in this area in both territories.
"The" LinkedIn Future Ready "program is a bold initiative that aims to support the work force in Hong Kong and to collect gaps in terms of competences, as well as unlocking new opportunities in growing economy," said Mei NG, director-general of LinkedIn social network in Hong Kong.
The official also added that the social network will work closely with the 14 participating companies, to build “a more resilient workforce” by providing “companies that develop and implement innovative talent strategies and ensure that their employees are equipped with the skills needed to succeed in the future”.
Skills below
According to the same statement, before advancing to this training program, an assessment of markets was made in both territories. It is concluded that “Hong Kong and Macao perform well in cross-cutting skills and innovation-both essential to navigating the dynamic current business landscape”, and by transversal skills, “communication, teamwork and leadership” is understood.
In terms of innovation, another factor analyzed, "Hong Kong exceeds the APAC average [Asia-Pacific countries] in innovation skills, reinforcing its role as a future vision business center that also promotes industry transformation." However, the neighboring region “is behind APAC average in AI proficiency”, so the “Future Ready” program consider that there is “an urgent need for initiatives to improve skills to help enable the workforce to adapt without problems to technological advancement”.
There is, in this domain, a "growing demand for AI -related skills", as "77 percent of Hong Kong business leaders said they would hire a less experienced AI competencies rather than a more experienced candidate without these skills."
In addition, "although transverse skills remain the strongest area of ​​Hong Kong, the region continues to be below APAC average and is late in four of the five domains of critical skills evaluated."
One of the objectives of the program announced on Thursday is to “improve and requalify the labor” of both territories “for a future fueled with AI”, so that there is “a certain combination of technical and human skills”, constituting “a competitive advantage for professionals and organizations”.
The 14 partner companies will have access to more than 23,000 courses available on the “LinkedIn Learning” platform that are based on 41,000 skills sets, namely “curated learning pathways, technology training, AI training and state -of -the -art learning resources”, it is explained.
The future accelerates
According to the same report released by LinkedIn in January, AI's growing adoption worldwide will lead to a "search for new jobs and skills." The social network data show that "more than 10 percent of hired workers currently have positions that did not exist in 2000, including functions such as data scientist, social networking manager, sustainability manager, customer success manager and AI engineer."
In the concrete case of Hong Kong, by 2030, “60 percent of all skills used to do a job will have changed, with the innovations of accelerating this transformation to 80 percent”, is mentioned. Thus, it is concluded that "this rapid pace of change has created a gap of competencies that is difficult to conform in the short term."
In addition to betting on professionals, the “Future Ready” program also wants to promote ideas and debates, promising, for example, “quarterly round tables for executives” and “with sector leaders to discuss the evolution of jobs, skills and learning requirements”. “The program will also provide a platform for the sharing of best practices, influencing the widest development of the workforce in all sectors,” is still added.
Also noteworthy is that the LinkedIn report on changes in work structures describe the most usual forms of AI use, namely communication in human resources or marketing. Thus, "recruiters who use LinkedIn's AI -assisted messages to involve candidates are registering an acceptance rate 44 percent higher compared to the AI ​​-free messages." In addition, “marketers who use LinkedIn's ad campaign creation tool, Accelerate, are presenting a cost per 42 percent lower compared to the classic campaigns” of this social network.
For this report were held several inquiries, namely more than 2,500 entrepreneurs from five countries (United States, United Kingdom, France, Germany and India). The questionnaire focused on executives from various business areas (human resources, operations or marketing) was made in nine country and had 19,991 participants from companies with over 1000 employees. This inquiry was held from 26 November and December 13 last year.
In worldwide terms, in 2030 about 70 percent of each worker's tools and skills will change, with “emerging as a catalyst”, and “IMA investments [by companies] are starting to compensate: in the last two years, 51 percent of businesses that have adopted the general AI reported an increase in revenues of 10 percent or more”. “Unsurprisingly, 88 percent of top executives with top management positions said AI adoption to help accelerate business is something important to develop next year,” one reads.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Press | All About Macau prevented from covering elections</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/imprensa-all-about-macau-impedido-de-cobrir-eleicoes/</link><description>The Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly, led by Seng Ioi Man, president of the Court of Second Instance, is blocking the All About Macau newspaper to cover the press conferences of the committee that organizes the September 14 legislative elections.
Following the election of Sam Hou Fai as Chief Executive, and during the term of Ho Iat Seng, the All About Macau newspaper began to be excluded from virtually all press conferences linked to local authorities, justifying that there are not enough vacancies for media professionals. According to this criterion, which is discretionary, the priority is attributed to publications with daily or weekly periodicity. However, several monthly local agencies, published in non -Chinese languages, can access events without embarrassment, although theoretically do not meet the required requirements.
It is also frequent to block access to the All About Macau newspaper, with the justification of lack of space, when the rooms where the conferences are held have several places available.
According to Article 27 of the Basic Law, MSar protects freedom of the press in the territory. According to Article 5 of the Press Law, this freedom implies the guarantee of the right to access the sources of information, which means contact with rulers and the possibility of questioning them.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:50:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumption | Exchange of elderly cards available</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/consumo-troca-de-cartoes-de-idosos-disponivel/</link><description>From today, more than 60 posts are open to replace Macau Pass cards that allow the discounts of the great consumption award. Until March 20, residents over 65, or their representatives, can exchange cards free of charge in social service institutions and civic associations spread across the territory
 
With the initiative to incentive the local consumption award to be pulled on March 24, the government today takes the first step in preparing for the distribution of discounts. Today they open more than 60 posts for replacing the “Macau Pass Card for the Elderly”, which allows a new modality of participation compared to previous rounds of the support program for residents over 65 years.
Spread out all over the territory, between social service institutions and civic associations, more than 60 posts will allow you to exchange cards free of charge by March 20. The direction of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) explains that exchange is required “since the chip used in the old version of Macau Pass for elderly to the loading of the card for immediate discount”.
Residents over 65 years old will benefit from two types of discounts, through Macau cards to the elderly and the electronic payment platforms. The inclusion of a physical card with direct discounts was one of the news of the new benefit round, after criticism of previous programs regarding the exclusion of the older population that does not know how to use, or have, online payment platforms.
Practical guide
To change the cards, the holder or a representative must go to one of the replacement posts bringing the old card, which will be collected by the services, in exchange for a lifting bead. This bead indicates the date to raise the new card, which the government estimates taking between 6 to 10 business days, with the balance of the old card to be automatically transferred to the new. The new card can be raised by the elderly or a representative by signing a power of attorney and presentation of their BIR.
The request for a duplicate of Macau Pass for the elderly implies the same steps for the exchange of cards, as well as similar deadlines.
Those who have never required Macau Pass for the elderly can do so at Macau Pass stores, the Jardim Fu Tat building on Paris Street, and at Macau Pass Centers on the Black Areia Marginal Road and Kwong Tung Avenue in Taipa. To request the card you need to present the BIR and a recent Pass type photograph. Cards can be raised within an estimated eight business days.
The holders of the “Macau Pass Card for the elderly” “will be able to participate in the program, with benefits at various levels, such as an immediate discount for consumption of 300 patacas by loading the card”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:47:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Science | Mário Évora appointed to Ethics Committee</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/ciencia-mario-evora-nomeado-para-comissao-de-etica/</link><description>Doctor Mário Évora was appointed as a member of the Ethics Committee for Life Sciences, by Sam Hou Fai, according to an order published yesterday in the official bulletin.
The commission will be chaired by Kuok Cheong U, also a doctor, whose replacement is Pang Fong Kuong. Among the other named are the names of Lai Kai Seng, Ren-He Xu, Bernice Lam Nogueira, Wong Io Nam, Yip Tai Ho, Chan Chi Chon and lawyer Vong Hin Fai.
The Commission performs the advisory body tasks and discussion forum on issues raised by the recent development of life sciences. As part of these functions issues recommendations on ethical issues raised by scientific progress in the fields of biology, medicine or health.
In addition, the Commission proposes criteria to define the cerebral death certification rules and follows the execution of measures promoted in the field of biomedicine and international agreements.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:46:12</pubDate></item><item><title>DSF | Surplus of public accounts falls almost a third in January</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/dsf-excedente-das-contas-publicas-cai-quase-um-terco-em-janeiro/</link><description>Macao finished January with a surplus in public accounts 32 percent lower than in the same month of 2024, especially due to the slowdown in the game's recipes.
The excess of MSAR set up at 3.68 billion patacas, according to the latest data published by Finance Services (DSF) on Tuesday. Macao closed last year with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the record in 2023.
In January, Macau collected 7.5 percent of current revenue projected for 2025 in the budget, which is 112.6 billion patacas.
In early December, the Macao Study Center and the University of Macao Economics Department foresaw that revenues should be smaller than the government's estimated: 111.8 billion patacas.
The surplus of the territory shrunk despite the public expense designed 7 percent in January, to 72 billion patacas, mainly due to investment in infrastructure, which fell to less than half. On the other hand, the government spent 594.6 million patacas under the administration's investment and expenses plan, 52.9 percent compared to January 2024.
On the contrary, current expense increased 8.2 percent to 4.12 billion patacas, mainly due to a 12.9 percent rise in social support and subsidies given to the population.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:43:21</pubDate></item><item><title>“Two Sessions” | Li Qiang highlights “Macau governed by patriots”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/duas-sessoes-li-qiang-destaca-macau-governada-por-patriotas/</link><description>The Chinese prime minister has repeated the principles and goals set in recent years to Macao and pointed out that China's gross domestic product will grow 5 percent throughout this year. The intervention was praised by the deputies of Macao in the National Popular Assembly
 
In the presentation of the annual work report of the central government, Prime Minister Li Qiang defended the application “unshakable” the principles “a country, two systems”, “Macau ruled by their people”, and the high degree of autonomy and safeguarding the constitutional order. The speech was given yesterday morning at the Great People's Hall in Beijing during the opening ceremony of the 3rd session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (APN).
Li Qiang has also indicated that the central government will support the territory to develop the economy, improve the population's living condition, deepen international cooperation, and promote a “better integration in global national development and the maintenance of prosperity and long -term stability”.
Li Qiang's speech did not truly have innovations towards Macao, and the repetition of policies set in the latest years. The same objectives were defined for Hong Kong, with the situation of the two special administrative regions to be presented together.
Li Qiang's speech was still marked by the forecast that the gross domestic product in the interior of China will grow five percent throughout this year, in what is always one of the most anticipated aspects of the central government's annual work report.
Macao applause
The Prime Minister's speech received several compliments from Macao deputies at the National People's Assembly, who promised to work “dedicated” to achieve the goals set.
Chui Sai Peng, quoted by Radio Macau's Chinese channel, highlighted the work done last year by the central government, indicating that all defined goals were achieved, despite the various challenges created by the economic environment. For this reason, the deputy considered that the prospects for the future are encouraging and that the population has reasons to be more confident, especially with regard to the development of high technology.
Kevin Ho, another of Macao members at APN, preferred to underline the various works foreseen in Li Qiang's speech to promote economic growth throughout this year, stressing that they will stabilize real estate and scholarship markets. Ho also stated that this year will show the resistance capacity of the economy of the country.
Ng Siu Lai considered that the central government report was quite realistic and will allow the country to continue progressing, while implementing measures to increase the pensions of urban and rural residents. According to NG, with the implementation of this report, the Chinese population will be more protected and improve the living level.
Already the former deputy of the Legislative Assembly Chan Hong chose to highlight the attention given to education issues, and the plans to progressively implement free education in preschool education.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:39:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Change to residence rules for citizens of Macao under study</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/taiwan-alteracao-a-regras-de-residencia-para-cidadaos-de-macau-em-estudo/</link><description>Taiwan is considering imposing more tight rules for the assignment of residence and citizenship on citizens from Hong Kong and Macau, with a view to preventing Chinese influence through immigration, Taiwanese press said.
Unlike other foreign citizens, currently residents of Hong Kong and Macau can apply for permanent residence and get Taiwan identity ticket after a year residing on the island.
Taiwan is now considering implementing changes, establishing that citizens from both administrative regions have to reside on the island four years before becoming eligible for permanent residence, a person familiar with the subject, quoted by the Taipei Times newspaper, said on Monday.
It is intended with the changes to avoid the influence of the Chinese Communist Party in Taiwan through the immigration of Hong Kong and Macau, he said the same source, which he asked not to be identified.
The measure is part of a “safety -related legislative reform,” he added. Another change that is being considered, said the same source, is to end citizenship to people from Hong Kong and Macau with long -term residence.
Also according to the proposed changes, the residence applicants of Hong Kong or Macau who have worked for the CCP, the Chinese Armed Forces or Chinese public institutions will be the subject of rigorous analysis and requests may be refused, he continued.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:43:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Fitch Ratings | Government applauds notation maintenance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/fitch-ratings-governo-aplaude-manutencao-de-notacao/</link><description>The Government of the MSAR issued a statement to highlight the fact that the financial notation agency had maintained the degree of long -term credit notation at AA level, with stable perspectives. This is the third highest level of the financial notation agency scale.
According to government communication, which cites the report, the maintenance of this classification was “to the highly stable situation of public finances and the balance of payment of MSAR, as well as to the government of the Government to continue to adopt prudent financial management, even in periods of economic adjustment”.
The agency will also be foreseen that “the additional growth of the tourism sector and game-related investments, which adds relief in tourism policies for China's interior residents and the continuous optimization of tourist infrastructure” will improve the economic perspectives of the territory.
Credit notations are used as a reference by markets when they buy debt from states or regions. The worse the notation, the higher the interest paid for indebtedness tends to be. In the case of Macao, as there is no debt issuance, since the financial reserve is greater than 600 billion patacas, in practice, the notation turns out to be little relevant.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:42:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Climate change and ocean currents</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/as-alteracoes-climaticas-e-as-correntes-oceanicas/</link><description>To facilitate the study of the complex system which is the climate, it has been considered considering it consisting of five components that interact with each other: atmosphere, hydrosphere, lithosphere, cryiosfera and biosphere.
The first two are the ones that most resent the behavior of a small part of the biosphere, ourselves. It is no longer new to anyone, except for negasters, that climate change is due to anthropogenic activities, which constitute the main cause of the injection of greenhouse gases into the atmosphere.
In these two components there are natural mechanisms that greatly contribute to climate balance: the general circulation of the atmosphere and oceanic circulation. It is up to both the task of distributing the globe the heat received from the sun in the form of radiation. It focuses more intensely in the regions of the low latitudes.
Without these natural mechanisms, the heat would be more concentrated in the equatorial and tropical regions, which would remain indefinitely to warm, while the cooling would not stop in higher latitudes either. General circulation of the atmosphere and oceanic circulation thus contribute to the balance of the climate system. Regarding the first, it is easily understandable that the fact that the air moves causes the heat to be distributed throughout the globe. The wind, in its most varied forms, has an important role in this process.
The jet currents, the wind winds, the monsoons, the breezes, the catabouts and anabetic winds, among other ways in which the wind occurs in nature, are in charge of this distribution of heat. Inserted in this mechanism, tropical cyclones (tropical storms, typhoons and hurricanes), characterized by very strong winds, greatly contribute to the transport of warm energy from the warmer to colder regions, as their trajectories, which start in low latitudes, statistically describe a kind of parable, progressing to higher latitudes.
For example, in western North Pacific, tuffles usually have their beginning in minor disturbances from the field of atmospheric pressure, between the Marian islands and the Philippines, progressing to the west, northwest, north, curving to the northeast and east, turning into extractical depressions. Hurricanes in the North Atlantic have similar behavior, usually beginning in minor pressure from the southern edge of the Azores anticyclone, near Cape Verde, progressing analogously for medium and high latitudes. Regardless of the sometimes catastrophic consequences of tropical cyclones, these meteorological phenomena play an indispensable role in the redistribution of heat, thus contributing to the balance of climate on a global scale.
In addition to the action of atmospheric circulation, oceanic circulation plays an important role in heat redistribution. In addition to the persistent winds, the temperature and salinity of water, and consequently their density, are factors that give rise to ocean currents, the behavior of which is sensitive to the variation of these parameters.
It is undeniable that global warming has caused the ice of the polar and glaciers, at an increasingly faster pace, causing freshwater resulting from the resulting sea to the sea, which could cause changes in current patterns that characterize ocean chains.
And this is where the attention of some scientists is focusing on, considering that the consequences of these changes are worrying, especially in the Atlantic Ocean. One of the recent studies refers to the implications that this process has in the so-called southern reversal circulation in the Atlantic Southern Overporting Circulation-AMOC), which includes the Gulf stream, which progresses from southern to the north, driven by the Azores anticyclone, transporting hot water from the Gulf of Mexico (Sorry, Mr. Trump) to regions to regions) to regions Neighbors on the east coast of the United States and northwestern Europe, positively conditioning the climate in these regions.
AMOC circulation consists of a chain system in the Atlantic, surface and in depth, through which hot and salty water (in the red figure) is transported from the tropical regions of the North Atlantic, from south to north, and which, when cooling, sinks, reversing its displacement to south, in depth. This process may suffer disruption due to the increasing influx of freshwater from the defrost, which causes the surface water dilution, which, thus diluted, would no longer sink due to its lower density, which could weaken the cold branch that flows in depth from north to south.
The pattern of circulation in the Pacific is different from the amoc, due, among others, to geographical factors. Instead of a strong deep return current, the surface -driven currents prevail by the surface.
Oceanic currents greatly contribute to climate balance. Once changed, imbalance in the climate system is generated, with consequences that may be serious for the sustainability of life on the globe. On this subject, studies were recently published, somewhat contradictory in the conclusions regarding the consequences of AMOC changes. According to scientists at the University of Copenhagen, according to a study prepared in 2023 and published in the scientific journal “Nature”, a collapse of Amoc may occur during this century, between the 2025 and 2095, with possible serious consequences for the North Atlantic climate. On the other hand, a work by scientists from the “Met Office” (UK meteorological service) and the University of Exeter in 2024 is not so pessimistic. It argues that Amoc can be weakened, but its collapse is unlikely during this century.
In any case, these studies on ocean currents constitute one more alert with the consequences of global warming on climate system balance.
Meteorologist</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:15:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Geogostronomy and Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/geogastronomia-e-a-inteligencia-artificial/</link><description>“Artificial Intelligence Doesn't have Five Senses. Computers Can't Convey How Foods and Drinks Taste and Smell… Yet ”.
Joshua Lurie
The intersection of geogostronomy and artificial intelligence (IA) presents a unique and transformative exploration of food cultures and culinary practices in various geographies. Geogogogosronomy merges geography and gastronomy, highlighting the impact of the place on the kitchen. It examines the factors that affect food, including climate, soil, culture and local traditions. This concept is not merely theoretical, but it encompasses practical realities. For example, the Mediterranean diet derives its uniqueness of the flora, climate and cultural practices of the region. The combination of food and place provides a basis for understanding how local ingredients shape culinary identities.
The evolution of this field can be tracked to the first anthropological efforts. Scholars like Claude Lévi-Strauss influenced this perspective by associating food with cultural identity. However, modern geogostronomy has expanded to include environmental issues. Topics such as biodiversity, sustainability and local agricultural practices are now essential in debates about food systems. AI refers to the simulation of human intelligence on programmed machines to think and learn. AI applications penetrated various sectors, including health care, finance and transport. In the culinary arts, the influence of AI is multifaceted. Technologies such as automatic learning, natural language processing and data analysis are reshaping the way we understand and produce food.
AI systems can analyze vast data sets to identify trends in food preferences, use of ingredients and nutritional information. This application is particularly valuable for cooking chiefs and food sector companies that intend to elaborate menus that correspond to consumers' preferences. The ability to quickly process and interpret data promotes innovation, as cooking professionals can do proof -based experiences and not just intuition. Modern tools, such as recipe generators and kitchen assistants, demonstrate AI potential. For example, IBM's IBM (Watson is the IBM AI platform that had already shown its expertise in “Jeopardy” and lung cancer treatment, and like Chef Watson, is helping IBM to achieve its mission to “help people discover new ideas” in this case for the kitchen) exemplifies how AI can create new recipes by analyzing thousands of culinary combinations.
When considering factors such as combinations of flavors and cooking techniques, Chef Watson facilitates a new era of cooking experimentation. Several important personalities have had a significant impact on the domains of geogostronomy and AI. Kitchen chief and writer Alice Waters is a prominent personality in promoting the “Quinta to the Table” movement, defending local supply and sustainable practices. Its influence demonstrates how attention given to geography can boost cooking innovation and improve the understanding of food sources and their meaning. In the technological domain, Andrew NG (founded and directed the Google Brain project and was chief scientist in the Chinese Baidu search giant, and directed the AI ​​lab at Stanford University) and Fei-Fe-Li (was vice president of Google and chief scientist of IA/ML on Google Cloud and a member of the board and consultant in several public and private companies and is currently current Cofunder/CEO of World Labs which is an AI company focused on space intelligence and Generative AI).
Its contributions to automatic learning and deep learning have launched the bases for AI applications in various domains, including food technology. These advances allow chefs and food sector companies to adopt innovative approaches that fuse tradition with technology. In addition, several investigators and starting companies are exploring the intersection between AI and geogostronomy. Companies such as FlavorWiki analyze consumer taste preferences using AI -based analysis, helping food brands adapt products to specific regional tastes.
This combination of technology and culinary knowledge reflects a growing trend in recognizing the need for a data -based approach for food production and consumption. The integration of geogostronomy and AI promotes various perspectives, particularly around authenticity, sustainability and ethical considerations. Some critics argue that AI may dilute culinary authenticity. Traditional kitchen methods are often based on intuition and cultural transmission, which can be neglected in favor of data-based decisions. The essence of homemade kitchen, for many, is directly linked to personal stories, cultural meaning and unique rituals.
In addition, the dependence on technology raises questions about sustainability. Although AI can optimize food production, there is a risk of giving priority to efficiency over the preservation of traditional practices. The arguments that advocate a harmonious balance between modern technology and traditional practices suggest that AI should improve and not replace cultural heritage.
On the other hand, advocates of AI integration argue that technology can bring sustainability through data optimization. By predicting crop performance and analyzing soil health, AI can contribute to more efficient agricultural practices and waste reduction.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:12:28</pubDate></item><item><title>The time of the devil</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/a-hora-do-diabo/</link><description>Amazingly, it is a tale of Fernando Pessoa on unnatural loose leaves that in good time arrived at the National Library and was structured and numbered so that we had a attentive and renewed knowledge window of this modeling thinking.
As for the title, it is always a contemporary and permanent nature. We are going through a time with such dynamic characteristics, unequivocal outbreaks lack of lucidity and decreased discernment levels where various dialogues, voices, and concepts of civility to levels that are no more than damnations. In matters of maximum seriousness we always have the great poets, and in this clear source, we can know yesterday, today and tomorrow, as we meet here in successive vacancies of enchantment and blatant repetitions to a too telluric bond that always seems to overlap with a higher level of consciousness.
The gaps that need to be corrected to such a text, make those who worked a true 'chef d´Odo ”some pages are handwritten, some not, the title goes from' night 'to' night 'and unruly leaves require no vigilant framing to avoid any allusion to their message character, not to say that moving from one tongue to considerable archaism, can be This is a process immersed in pure filigree so that nothing is left out. Perhaps these great poets refrain from tidying up and compiling their data, and in the immersion of a creativity that surpasses them, and very well, for others, the bureaucratic work of rectification. If you wake up, you do not wake up, if you become, it is logistical aptitude, but to escape the creative, inventive flow, and in this case, visionally perennial and full of civilizing analogies, it would be a lesser mechanism to be clinging to any metric consequence. Perhaps they are treated, off, operated in the search for the idea in various characters, always imperfect and irregular, and yet, and pass the incongruities, the language to be understood only should be worked by poets.
What most resembles this “bread line” that the devil kneaded, is an old correspondence to the wizard Merlin, which is not alluded to, yet is present throughout this route, an event that is produced in Rua do Carmo where he is distant from any fantastic existence, but where the devil decided not to die of boredom approaching a young Lisbon, who knows, who knows, who knows, who knows, who knows, From the Holy Spirit, she became pregnant without apparently if nothing had passed. At this meeting, the public devil, he believes to have found pregnant, but the embryo had perhaps revolved and would be stripped of a useless husband of this Mary, to be the son of an enigmatic passerby: in fact, this mother had always been as her words uttered him, in the presence of a gentleman. And he also returned to him the traveler. "What man landed on your breasts that hand that was mine?" What kiss gave you it was the same as mine? In the afternoons of dreaming, did you not see, in the background of your dreams, a veiled and quick figure, which would give you all the happiness, which would kiss you indefinitely? It was me »
All this route on a quiet night in a quiet city, we look only at the reflection of the soul of a condemned with an unparalleled labor for enchantment, a vigorous discipline, and a overflowing eroticism. We followed him closely as if a dream turned into the voice of the son who would later remember between worlds of hearing him, as if the verb he had pronounced if he had made flesh.
And because they are splinters
Of being, things scattered
I break the soul into pieces
And in different people.
Um testemunho bem mais requintado que a «Metamorfose» de Kafka, e longamente sentido como estranha confissão. A nossa heroína é no entanto a grande criatura, quando volvendo para ele os olhos marejados lhe disse: – Sabe? Tenho pena de si- Eu também. É de facto uma obra que só um homem pode escrever.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:18:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Improve the economy of Macau (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/aperfeicoar-a-economia-de-macau-ii/</link><description>Last week, we analyzed the issue of directing visitors from traditional tourist attractions to community areas, thus increasing local commerce revenues in areas where residents live their daily lives. Thus, more people could benefit from tourists consumption and the number of stores closed could be reduced.
For this plan to be successful, we must start receiving concerts and create careers of tourist buses between the show rooms and the community tourist areas. Concert organizers will have to sign contracts with the artists. If there is more than an artist to act, contracts should be signed with each of them. The Macao society should decide whether buses will be assigned by local transport companies or other companies. The company that is in charge of this service must decide whether or not the trips will be free.
With tourist buses make the connecting places of concerts and community tourism areas, tourists can easily be transported. As we mentioned, these places are located in the areas where residents live their daily lives. Originally, these places were not considered touristy. Therefore, the first task is to attract tourists to these areas and the second is to take them to shop at local stores. This second question will have to be addressed and resolved by interested traders.
Most of the products in Macau stores come from Zhuhai, Zhongshan and other places. Currently, most tourists visiting Macau and Hong Kong come from the interior of China. If we forward tourists from the Great Bay area to the community zones and expect you to shop at local stores we will not be very successful because the products that are there for sale are available in the cities where they reside.
Also, these products are more expensive in Macau than in the Great Bay area and no one will want to buy at higher prices which can buy cheaper. It should be not to forget that since the movement known as “the cars that go north”, that is, the mass travel of residents of Macao to shop in the cities near the interior of China, local consumption has fallen significantly. This was also one of the reasons for reducing local consumption. It is not surprising that the fall in consumption has resulted in the end of several stores that were unable to pay the rentals.
There is only one way to solve the problem that residents leave the city to shop and also take tourists from the interior of China to consume in community areas, and this has higher quality products, innovating and courage to look for change.
There is a famous hot pot restaurant in mainland China. When it opened, it was just a small unknown store. Later, as the business flourished, they were increasingly opening branches. Hot Pot's restaurant was diversifying its offer and started selling its products in supermarkets, packed in plastic boxes that contained everything that was needed to warm the meals. It was a portable hot pot.
Customers can purchase the meal without having to move to the restaurant. Also, when people go to hot pot restaurants are impregnated with a strong odor from meals. This chain has created a head washing service so that the odor disappears. All of these services have to do with "innovation." In management, there is a theory that advocates the innovation of companies. If our company stagnates, but our competitors evolve, it means that others change until us. If our competitor is better, we will be eliminated.
In addition to bravely looking for change, the type of products sold should also be adjusted. Tourists in the Great Bay area do not easily buy products they can purchase at home. However, if the products sold in Macau stores have Portuguese elements that represent the cultural fusion of Macao, they will become more attractive.
Macao young products such as hand and t-shirts reflect the mindset of local youth and are a symbol of their way of being in life, which is precisely what adherents of immersive tourism are looking for. Many of the Imanes for refrigerators sold in stores represent macao tourist sites. What if instead we would make i imans with specialties from Macau? When tourists see these images in their refrigerators, they will naturally remember the time they have spent in Macao. They will again evoke these flavors and revive their memories, which will always be fresh.
To summarize, creating a special bus career to get the public from the concerts to consume in community zones is a strategy that is worth trying. But it is essential that stores in these zones have the courage to change and provide unique and good quality products and services. Only in this way can trade truly benefit from the visit of tourists.
Tourists consumption in community zone stores is particularly important. This consumption represents recipes for stores. As these revenues increase, taxes that will pay the government will also increase. The Macao government can have more revenues creating new taxes. This way we can enjoy the benefits of "a visa for multiple purposes." In this sense, the whole society of Macau can profit.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the School of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Blog: http://blog.xuite.net/legalpublications/hkblog
Email: LegalpublicationSreaders@yahoo.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 02:05:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Architecture | Seminar with Marco Imperidori takes place on the 20th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/arquitectura-seminario-com-marco-imperadori-decorre-dia-20/</link><description>The CAC - Circle of Macao Culture Friends organizes, on the 20th, a Seminar with Marco Imperidori, with sessions entitled “Architecture of Care” and “Arte Sella: a balance between architecture and nature”. Events take place at Macao University of Science and Technology, between 15h and 6:15 pm, and the registration deadline ends on the 19th.
Marco Imperradori is a full -seated professor and researcher at Milan Polytechnic, where he tends the technology design and innovation chair. Its work focuses on high energy efficiency buildings, construction/envelope construction systems and sustainability.
With a master's degree and a doctorate in construction engineering, it combines knowledge of architecture and engineering. It has been taught worldwide, including as a visiting professor at the University of St. Joseph in Macau from 2015 to 2023. As a delegate of the Rector to the Far East, it represents the Milan Polytechnic in Asia. Active researcher has published extensively on architectural innovation, sustainability and energy conservation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:10:27</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | IAT PO PORCELAINS EXPOSED UNTIL THE 14th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/frc-porcelanas-de-lei-iat-po-expostas-ate-dia-14/</link><description>It is called “Return to Navigation” and is the latest display patent in the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery available for free visit since Tuesday. This is the opportunity to see Porcelain pieces of IAT PO from Cantão, an area known for the traditional ceramic industry
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) inaugurated this Tuesday the Macao Porcelain and Guangzhou “Return to Navigation” exhibition, by artist Lei Iat Po (李溢坡). In the gallery, 40 pieces of color porcelain in the Cantão region will be available, a traditional industry originating from the Qing Dynasty and developed mainly for export. This industry gained popularity between European courts and western aristocracy, having been an important factor in promoting Chinese culture abroad from the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
According to a FRC note, Canton's porcelain - also known as Guangcai - is famous for the strong and vibrant colors, complex and intricate patterns, and gold -painted golden and richly decorated applications.
Being a typical southern industry of China, he also gained vitality in Hong Kong and Macao in the past twentieth century, namely from the 1930s invasions and during the political instability of the continent. Many factories moved to Macau and Hong Kong which fired production in southern China, namely in the 1950s, thanks to greater international demand of these oriental exoticism pieces growing in the postwar phase.
Canton's porcelain has been a successful example of a fusion between the east and the West over the centuries, contributing to the advantageous cultural exchange. In Macao, at the height of the 1960s, there were dozens of factories. But in the 1980s production returned to the continent, much more competitive in labor and costs, in the aftermath of the cultural revolution.
Family art
IAT PO Law was born in Macao in 1954, having revealed an interest in the art of color porcelain due to the family business. This was influenced since childhood by the father, who produced and exported pieces for European and American markets. Law IAT PO worked at your father's Guangcai Wooden Basis Factory and, later, at the Guangcai Colorful Porcelain factory.
Under the parent's guidance, he followed the famous Master Zhao Zhuo to learn burn control technology in the oven. Later, I would learn about artisanal painting techniques and porcelain color.
Curated by Margareth Lei Siu Heng, the collection available at the FRC presents invaluable pieces, for the quality and degree of complexity in execution, revealing the years of improvement and dedication to this centenary technique by the artist, who intends to continue to disseminate his art and preserve the important historical past. The works will be exhibited until March 14.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:08:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Mam | “Above Zobeida: Art of Macau” inaugurated this Friday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/mam-acima-de-zobeida-arte-de-macau-inaugurada-esta-sexta-feira/</link><description>It will be inaugurated this Friday, at the Macao Art Museum (MAM), the show “Above Zobeida: Art of Macao at the 60th International Exhibition of Art of the Venice Biennial”, from 18:30. The exhibition was created by the young Macao artist, Wong Weng Cheong, and curator Chang Chan, and represented Macao at the Italian Biennial, one of the most important in the art scene worldwide.
“Above Zobeida” is inspired by Italo Calvino's novel “As Invisible Cities”, focusing on the fictional city of Zobeida. According to a statement from the Cultural Institute (IC), "Wong Weng Cheong combines digital images and immersive artistic installations to build post-apocalyptic heterotopia," with "mutant herbivorous creatures living in a desert city, with elongated members away from the source of food." This is a symbol “of the imbalance between human civilization”.
The exhibition also has “surveillance cameras installed everywhere in the exhibition, and public members become part of the work when entering space, fluttering the lines that separate reality and fiction”. The central theme of the 60th edition of the Venice Biennial was “foreigners everywhere”, and in the words of curator Chang Chan, “above Zobeida” brings ideas such as “the displacement of spatial identity and alienation, exploring the concept of 'foreign' and the apocalyptic anxiety of contemporary society”, describes in the same note.
Macao participates in the Venice Biennial since 2007. “Above Zobeida”, received about 77,000 visits. The IC describes that "it is of great importance that the exhibition returns to Macau, so that residents and tourists can appreciate the contemporary creations of young artists from Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:56:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Letters Route | Literary festival brings poetry to the inner port</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/rota-das-letras-festival-literario-traz-poesia-ao-porto-interior/</link><description>Lisbon Poetry Orchestra, many Chinese poets and still photographs of Portuguese photojournalist Alfredo Cunha. Here are some of the highlights of the new edition of the Literary Festival Rota das Letras dedicated to poetry, but also recalls the period of Portuguese decolonization. Youth literature also takes place at the event that runs between 21 and 30 this month in the Barra Zone, Porto Interior
 
The main highlights of the 14th edition of the Rota das Letras Literary Festival are already known, scheduled for March 21 to 30, which this year moves to the former Municipal Slaughterhouse, in Barra da Barra, Porto Interior. In a very traditional area of ​​ancient Macau is expected a lot of poetry, concerts and still photography exhibitions.
Highlight for the Lisbon Poetry Orchestra concert, on March 29, which makes its debut in Macao with the show “Os Surrealists”, which is guest vocalist of Macau radio. The first part of the show will be made by Anthony Tao's Poetry &amp; Music band, formerly responsible for organizing the Beijing Literary Festival. The theme of the performance is “the myth of writing”.
It is also noteworthy for the presence of several Chinese poets in Rota das Letras, namely the young Xu Jinjin, an interdisciplinary artist who divides his time between Shanghai and New York, where he has regularly exposed in museums in both cities. His poetic work was recently awarded by the American Society of Poetry.
In the name of poetry, Valério Romão, author and Portuguese translator, who recently launched his first book of poetry, “another disappointment” is brought together. Names such as Beijing's Zang Di and Jia Wei are followed by local authors such as Chan Ka Long and Wang Shanshan. Thus, new books will be presented, and the public will also be able to watch Poetry, lectures and workshops, always with themes around literature.
The festival also serves to remember the hundredth anniversary of the publication “Lin Tchi Fá - Flor de Lotus”, a book of poems by Maria Anna Acciaioli Tamagnini, with the unprecedented release of translations for Chinese and English.
Remember decolonization
This year's Route of Letters also marks the passage of the 50th anniversary of the Independence of the African countries of Portuguese Language through an exhibition of the photojournalist Alfredo Cunha, who covered these historical events. The theme of the end of the colonial war and the process of decolonization that followed is also present in the novel of João Ricardo Pedro, “Your face will be the last”, that the director Luís Filipe Rocha adapted to the cinema.
This is a name linked to the territory, the Portuguese director returns to Macau after filming “love and fingers standing” in the 80s, that is, the film adaptation of Henrique de Senna Fernandes's iconic romance.
Another presence at the festival is António Costa e Silva, who was Minister of Economy and Sea in Portugal between 2022 and 2024, but also dedicated to writing. Costa e Silva comes to Macao to present his novel “Disconsegregated Angola”, about the period of decolonization and consequent civil war that plagued the country for years.
At the level of the Chinese novel, the work of Chen Jining, vice president of the Guangdong Writers Association, and has received numerous literary distinctions, including the Annual Prize for Chinese literature in the category of “Best Novelist”, the People's Literary Prize and China Good Book Award, among others. Chen Jining has two quite award -winning novels, namely “City of Seven Steps” and “Monologue aloud”.
Wallis's life
In the English language, the non-fiction literature is highlighted, namely with the work of British writer Paul French, who brings to the festival two very recent works: “Her Lotus Year”, which tells the passage of Wallis Spencer, Duchess of Windsor, China, in the 20th century; and “Destination Macao”, a collection of stories about some of the most fascinating Macao figures from the nineteenth and twentieth centuries.
Hong Kong's Tony Banham presents the result of his investigation into the sinking of the Lisbon Maru ship, one of the most tragic mistakes made by the Allied forces during the Pacific War. Already Thomas Dubois, author in Beijing, makes known to China in “Seven Banquets”, a deep study of the history of recently published Chinese cuisine.
For smaller
Books for the youngest will be brought to schools by Chen Shige, the first post-Annos 80 writer to gain the highest distinction of children's literature in China. Also André Letria, illustrator and Portuguese editor with several of his works published in Chinese language, and distinguished with several international prizes, will be one of the festival's guest.
Hong Kong's illustrator Sophia Hotung also comes to Macau to share her art with the public. On the eve of the festival's opening, Wang Zhengping, one of the great masters of Chinese photography, inaugurates in the TAP Seac Gallery the exhibition “The Wind blows on the prairie”, a poetic look at the Mongolia in the interior and who inhabits them.
Rao Yongxia, Wang's disciple, followed her footsteps and shows her work days later at the Holy House of Mercy Hostel gallery. Over the course of ten days, the festival proposes a program with two dozen lectures, three exhibitions, a movie cycle and a concert, visits to schools, and photography and creative writing workshops. According to the organization, the most detailed program will be published in the coming days.
Rota das Letras has several support from local companies and the Culture Development Fund of the Government of MSA, being organized by the Arts and Letters Society and Praia Grande Edições.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:55:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government launches new alert about Covid-19</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/governo-lanca-novo-alerta-sobre-covid-19/</link><description>Macao health services (SS) indicate a decrease in influenza cases, with the current situation “below the alert level”. However, in the case of COVID-19 infections, “the Sars-Cov-2 virus is becoming active,” therefore an appeal to vaccination, especially for chronic and elderly patients. The SS advance, however, that no death caused by Covid-19 has not yet been registered since the beginning of the year.
According to a note released yesterday, which cites laboratory data from the ninth week of the year, that is, from late February, “the Covid-19 detection positivity rate was 13.7 percent”, and this value “represents a significant increase compared to the previous week, 3.8 percent”.
In general terms, SS believe that “flu activity will remain active in the coming weeks”, but the attention, but for a certain stability. The number of patients served in the emergency service in the ninth week of 2025, that is, February, “decreased from the previous week”, having been attended a daily average of 1,190 people, 282 of them children.
Thus, “the descent trend of the influenza virus detection rate, from 10.5 percent in the eighth week of the year (below the alert level of 13.1 percent), to five percent in the ninth week”.
RISE IN DAILY AVERAGE
However, the SS warns that it is not yet time to ward off attention from flu, as it is “an average of about 83 [sick] people per day, which represents an climb compared to previous data”. Of these 83 people, 31 are adults and 52 children. Thus, SS understand that "the propagation of the respiratory tract virus in Macau is still active."
With regard to collective influenza cases, since January 46 occurred in the territory, as well as 25 cases caused by influenza A and five virus by influenza B virus.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:21:08</pubDate></item><item><title>IPOR | Bai Li Group is the new shareholder</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/ipor-grupo-bai-li-e-o-novo-accionista/</link><description>The Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR) has a new shareholder by decision made on January 24 this year at the 74th General Assembly of the Portuguese Teaching Institution as a foreign language.
This is the Bai Li Li Lda Lda Company. Thus joins the associative structure already composed by the Oriente Foundation, as a founding associate, Camões-Institute of Cooperation and Language, I.P., the National Bank Overseas, Quinta da Marmeleira and the Macao Tourism and Tourism Society (STDM).
According to an IPOR statement, the Bai Li group is recognized “for excellence in the area of ​​international trade, especially in the wine distribution sector”, and sought to position itself as a Sino-Portuguese commercial platform in Macao, investing over the years in a series of projects and activities in the Syno-Portuguese Commercial Cooperation Services platform ”.
The purpose of these actions, according to IPOR, is to help make Macau “a connection vehicle for the placement of Portuguese products in the Popular Republic of China, a strategy complemented with actions to promote tourism, culture and Portuguese language, thus aligning with the principles and objectives of IPOR”.
Also according to the same note, the entry of the new shareholder "demonstrates not only the recognition of the work developed by IPOR in the preservation and diffusion of Portuguese language and culture in the Asia-Pacific region, but also the identification and commitment of the company in reinforcing the mission that the institute ends."
Thus, "this cooperation is another step towards the affirmation of the role of IPOR not only as a disseminating agent of the economic and global value of the Portuguese language, but also of cultural and promoting intercultural cooperation."</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:01:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Desc | Registered annual increase of TNT</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/dsec-registado-aumento-anual-de-tnr/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) show that, at the end of last year, Macau had 688,300 people, a “light growth” of 0.7 percent, ie a growth of 4,600 people in annual terms. According to DSEC, this should be “mainly to the increase in the number of non-resident workers (TNR) domiciled in Macao”, whose increase was 4,900 people.
Regarding the local population, that is, without TNR and students from abroad, it reached 568,700 people, “lowering” 0.4 percent in annual terms. This should be “mainly that the net emigration of Macao residents, with the exit being higher than the entrance, was higher than natural growth (ie the number of undead is higher than deaths)”.
In terms of population movements, in 2024 there were 3,677 individuals from the interior of the newly arrived China to Macao holders of a safe conduit, which represents 260 more people in annual terms, with 64.8 percent belonged to females.
Last year residence was given to 1,074 people, more than 196 in annual terms, most of these people from Hong Kong, in a total of 364.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:59:51</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM | Return to profits after four years of damage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/sjm-regresso-aos-lucros-apos-quatro-anos-de-prejuizos/</link><description>SJM made a $ 3 million profit from Hong Kong last year, and managed to reduce the accumulated debt by 6 percent to Hong Kong's $ 26.5 billion
 
SJM Holdings game concessionaire announced a $ three million profit from Hong Kong in 2024 after unprecedented losses for four consecutive years. In a statement sent on Tuesday to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the company founded by the late game tycoon Stanley Hung Sun recalled that he had a loss of $ 2.01 billion from Hong Kong in 2023.
The SJM casinos raised $ 28.8 billion from Hong Kong, 35.9 percent than the previous year, while the revenues did not play 22.9 percent to Hong Kong's $ 1.92 billion.
With the revenues to rise, the company registered an operating profit of Hong Kong's $ 3.76 billion, more than twice than by 2023. During last year, SJM was able to reduce the total debt to 6.5 billion Hong Kong at the end of December by 6.5 billion.
On January 22, the Fitch Ratings Financial Notation Agency maintained the SJM debt rating thanks to the recovery of tourism in Macau. Fitch said the Grand Lisboa Palace, a game development and hotel opening opened in July 2021, in full pandemic, forced SJM to accumulate a high level of debt.
New recipes
The company said on Tuesday that Grand Lisboa Palace went from losses by 2023 to Hong Kong's $ 499 million operating profit last year. The revenues of the new SJM venture more than doubled, reaching $ 6.58 billion from Hong Kong.
The mass market represented 82.4 percent of the company's casinos revenues, while the VIP game was a 9.3 percent slice. The big bets, which in 2019 represented 46.2 percent of the revenues of Macao Casinos, were affected by the detention of the leader of the world's largest VIP betting company in November 2021.
Former Suncity Executive Director Alvin Chau Cheok Wa, was sentenced in January 2023 to 18 years in prison, in a case that dropped from 85 to 18 the number of licenses of game promoters issued in Macao.
The SJM said it will completely renew every room of Grand Lisboa, one of the company's most important casinos, as well as increasing the number of rooms “through the conversion of old areas reserved for junkets”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Security | Chan Pou Sam warns that excess zeal harms macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/seguranca-chan-pou-sam-alerta-que-excesso-de-zelo-prejudica-macau/</link><description>The honorary president of the Association for the Promotion of Social Life and Welfare of the Macao population, Chan Pou Sam, argues that society should avoid excess zeal, so as not to harm the image of the territory. The opinion was expressed to the Exmooo newspaper following a road accident during the filming of a movie in Macao.
The accident happened on Rua do Seminar, last month, resulted in the run over 12 people, mostly linked to the production team, and the images captured became viral. Subsequently, both the Public Security Police and the Cultural Institute revealed that the team had not followed the security indications issued, although there was no evidence of illegalities.
In view of the incident, Chan Pou Sam warned that local laws should be applied without the need for zeal excess or outbreaks of situations by residents on social networks. Chan also warned that this kind of situations, with the magnifying way of criticism, can make productions in the future cease to choose Macao as a filming destination, which indicated to be contrary to the interest of the territory.
Chan Pou Sam recalled that over the 30 years, there have been about 50 filming teams in Macao, so he indicated that the territory is able to receive more film and television projects.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:57:17</pubDate></item><item><title>IAO Hon | Would inspect market due to the presence of rat</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/iao-hon-iam-inspecciona-mercado-devido-a-presenca-de-rato/</link><description>Last Tuesday, a video circulated on social networks where you could see a rat crossing the tubes with the ceiling of the Restoration Zone of the Municipal Market of IAO HON.
In response, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) “has proceeded to an exhaustive inspection of the hygiene conditions of the place and the newsstands where the food is made” in the referred space, but also “in all markets and centers of cooked food under its jurisdiction”. In a statement released yesterday, AMI stated that the inspections are intended to "reinforce the control of rodents and sanitary measures in the places in question."
The municipal body has ensured that it “provides great importance” to the hygiene conditions of markets and market restoration zones once again after a video shared on social networks became viral. It is recalled that the same happened after being published on social networks a video that showed a mouse over food products in a Royal jail supermarket, which led to the temporary closure of three commercial surfaces and a restaurant in early January.
Regarding the Restoration Zone of the IAO Hon market, the AMI revealed that no traces of rat was found. The tubes where the rat was spotted were cleaned with diluted bleach and were installed mouse in the zones of traders' stalls.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:54:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Security | Firefighters appeal caution in the use of gas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/seguranca-bombeiros-apelam-a-cautela-na-utilizacao-de-gas/</link><description>Faced with a fire that made five injured and suspected was caused by a gas escape, the Fire Department came to public through a statement indicating several inspections to buildings and houses in recent years
 
After an explosion followed by a fire that caused five injuries, the Fire Department (CB) appealed to the population to pay “high attention to safety in the use of gas stove appliances”. The statement, in Portuguese, was issued yesterday morning, since it is suspected that at the origin of the flames it was a “liquefied oil gas escape”.
“CB stresses again that the risk of gas safety cannot be neglected, whether at home, restaurants and other spaces,” can be read in the message. "Citizens and sectors are expected to reinforce surveillance, prevention and to deal with safety matters relating to the use and installation corrects of gas stove devices, in order to jointly ensure the safety of life and goods," he was added.
The message also served the CB to defend any accusations of failure to the inspections made. "Since 2019, the CB has begun to move to communities to continually inspect the gas stoves at home, together with residents' associations and organizations and community security heads against fire," he was nominated. “Until February of this year, 1,742 home inspections were made,” was complemented.
According to the CB, during the inspections there were “safety specifications, the place of installation [of the appliances] and the expiration date of the gas stove pipe”, and as a result there were problems such as gas binding pipes to the expiration, defective connections to exit the gas from the water pitches.
More security
In the last two weeks there have been two fires in residential buildings, which has led to the maintenance of fire safety equipment to be questioned.
The first fire took place in the lake building, it is believed that due to a short circuit with a television, and caused controversy, given that the alarm to alert the residents did not fired. As a result, Deputy Lo Choi In made a written interpellation asking for better inspection inspections.
In the fire on Monday, still on site, the CB ensured that safety equipment worked as expected. However, due to the explosion with a gas leak in the centralized supply system, the impact has just reached larger, five injured, including two children with burns in at least 20 percent of the body, and there was a projection of the 19th floor of various objects to the public road, including a washing machine.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 02:52:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim committed himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I do not always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained the guts to the dogmas of the "modern". For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
«Ainda criança, roubou dois melros», conta Jacinto do Prado Coelho, roubou-o de um ninho, e palpitou-lhe toda a vida o remorso por isso. A Pessoa, poucas mais travessuras se lhe conhece. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! –/ Masturbam homens de aspecto decente nos vãos de escada.» (Ode triunfal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
Deixei violar as filhas de todos os pais atados a árvores,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazil | China suspends imports of beef of three factories</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/brasil-china-suspende-importacoes-de-carne-de-bovino-de-tres-fabricas/</link><description>China temporarily suspended imports of beef from three Brazilian factories, announced yesterday the government of Brazil, ensuring that the decision will not affect bilateral trade relations.
China's General Customs Administration has performed a series of “video audits” in the affected units and found that they do not comply with all the import requirements established by the Asian country, explained the Brazilian Ministry of Agriculture and Livestock in a statement.
The companies, whose names were not disclosed by the folder, have already been notified and are “taking corrective measures” to meet the demands of the Chinese body, according to the Brazilian government. China is the main destination of Brazilian beef exports and the largest commercial partner in the South American country.
Brazil, one of the world's largest animal protein suppliers, ended 2024 with a record production of 31.57 million tons of beef, pork and chicken, as well as record exports of 10.26 million tons, according to official data.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:22:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Panama Channel | China denies control and avoids commenting on ports</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/canal-do-panama-china-nega-controlo-e-evita-comentar-venda-de-portos/</link><description>China yesterday classified as “completely false” the allegations that controls the Panama Canal and avoided commenting on the recent sale of two ports on the navigable road by a Hong Kong group.
"China supports Panama's sovereignty about channel operations and is committed to maintaining it as an permanently neutral international river way," Lin Jian Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman said. The spokesman stated that the idea that China has full control over the channel is "completely false."
Asked about the sale of the ports of Balboa and Cristobal by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison conglomerate to a consortium led by American Blackrock, Lin refused to comment and recalled that the government of the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region has already spoken on the issue.
The agreement, valued at $ 22.8 billion, also includes the transfer of CK Hutchison's participation in 43 other ports from 23 countries, although it excludes terminals in China and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:05:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing warns that it will resist until the end if they continue with trade war</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/pequim-avisa-que-resistira-ate-ao-fim-se-eua-continuarem-com-guerra-comercial/</link><description>China warned yesterday that it will “resist until the end” if the United States “insists on harming Chinese interests,” in response to the new customs imposed by Washington on Asian country products.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian reiterated at a press conference that Beijing "firmly opposes" the US decision to use Fentanil as an excuse for applying more rates on Chinese exports. "If the US really wants to solve the problem of Fentanil, they should negotiate with China based on equality, respect and mutual benefit," said the spokesman.
Lin Jian said he had not seen the Chinese embassy statements in the United States, which China is "ready for any kind of war," but insisted that Beijing made its position clear.
"We urge the US to abandon its intimidation tactics and to return to the right way of dialogue and cooperation as soon as possible," he concluded. The Chinese executive defended in a white book on the fentanil released the day before, which took rigorous measures against production and fentanyl trafficking and its chemical precursors.
The Chinese government also stated that it has actively promoted the construction of a traceability system using new technologies to monitor any links to production, transportation, importation and exportation of these drugs.
Déjà vu
Trump said 90 percent of death consumption deaths in the US is due to Fentanil. Washington argues that opiates arrive through Mexico and Canada, but whose precursors come from China.
In his first presidency, Trump has already had a tense relationship with Beijing, imposing several rounds of rates, worth about $ 370 billion annually, which China responded with rates on US exports.
Washington announced this week the duplication for 20 percent of Chinese products, which led Beijing to respond at 10 percent and 15 percent rates on US agricultural imports.</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:04:35</pubDate></item><item><title>APN | Beijing has ambitious goal of GDP to 5%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/apn-pequim-apresenta-meta-ambiciosa-do-pib-para-5/</link><description>For the third consecutive year, the Chinese administration has returned to the goal of GDP at 5 percent. The objective was announced yesterday by Prime Minister Li Qiang at the annual plenary session of the National Popular Assembly, the maximum legislative body of China
 
The purpose of growth set by the Chinese authorities for this year, of “about 5 percent”, is ambitious, but the increase in the budgetary deficit will be insufficient to prevent the economy from recurring, warned analysts.
“Chinese politicians have maintained an ambitious goal for the actual GDP growth [Gross Domestic Product], but are more cautious in their predictions for nominal growth and inflation. And although they have announced an increase in fiscal support, the degree of flexibility is more moderate than it seems, ”wrote Julian Evans-Pritchard, an analyst at Capital Economics consultant, in a report.
The expert said he was skeptical about the possibility that the announced measures avoid a slowdown in 2025 growth, marked by "contrary winds in the international scenario and the absence of a more pronounced change in public expenses to support consumption."
After reserving a record percentage of expenses for investment in 2024, Beijing now seems to turn more to consumption, "though nothing extraordinary," equivalent to $ 41.3 billion in obligations to finance the government's "renewal plan" for electrodomatic or electronics, the analyst noted.
Hong Hao of Chinese active manager Grow Investment Group noted that this year's official report is what most often mentions the word 'consumption' in a decade, but Evans-Pritchard pointed out that authorities “are not having a considerable impulse” in the form of reflection.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang said yesterday that the objective of economic growth for the current fiscal year is “about 5 percent” for the third consecutive year, and that the fiscal deficit will be increased at a percentage point to 4 percent as part of the government's efforts to relaunch recovery.
Despite the “largest increase in decades” in the deficit and GDP ratio, Evans-Pritchard estimated that, taking into account other factors, the actual increase in expense will be about 1.5 percent, lower than previous flexibility cycles such as 2015 (2 percent) and 2020 (3.6 percent).
Letters in the sleeve
Cited by Bloomberg Financial News Agency, Charu Chanana of the Saxo Markets Stock Exchange Trading Platform, said the objectives revealed by Li “are within expectations” and show that the authorities are still “keeping ammunition for later”, an analysis that deserved the agreement of Lee Homin, from the Swiss bank Lumbard Odier, who believes Beijing can adjust the objective of the deficit A Mid of the year, when it becomes clear the impact of Washington's customs imposed on goods from China.
The latest projections of the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank point to Chinese GDP growth of about 4.5 percent after growing 5 percent in 2024, driven by extra effort by the authorities at the end of the year.
Evans-Pritchard stressed that the goal for inflation, which went from 3 percent last year to 2 percent, is the lowest since 2003, and noted that "it is unlikely that the Popular Bank of China [Central Bank] does everything necessary to bring" the indicator back to this level: "A lower objective suggests some official acceptance of the current deflating environment."</description><pubDate>2025-03-06 03:03:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Beijing reiterates that he does not give in to pressure from the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/comercio-pequim-reitera-que-nao-cede-a-pressao-dos-eua/</link><description>China warned yesterday that it “will not give way to pressures” and accused the United States of using customs rates as a political instrument in the middle of a climb of trade war between the two powers.
“China does not tolerate hegemony or intimidation. If the US insisted on maximum pressure tactics against China, they chose their wrong opponent, ”Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian told a press conference.
The United States yesterday was in force additional 20 percent rates on all goods from China. Beijing retaliated with rates of up to 15 percent on US agricultural products, including soy, wheat and cow meat (see secondary text).
Lin stated that "the United States imposes fees to divert attention from their own internal problems."
According to the spokesman, these measures "will not resolve US challenges, but will impair bilateral cooperation in key sectors such as technology." Despite the climbing of tensions, the spokesman said Beijing remains committed to dialogue, but stressed that it should be done "based on equality and respect and mutual benefit."
"If the US really wants to solve their problems, they should stress serious negotiations," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:30:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing keeps the goal of placing astronauts on the moon before the end of 2030</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/pequim-mantem-objectivo-de-colocar-astronautas-na-lua-antes-do-final-de-2030/</link><description>The Chinese manned lunar exploration program is progressing and maintains the goal of placing astronauts in the Natural Satellite of Earth before the end of 2030, the Space Agency for Crew Missions from China said yesterday.
In a statement, the agency stated that the main components of the project are progressing according to the scheduled calendar. This includes the heavy "long gear 10" heavy load rocket, the manned space ship "Mengzhou", the lunar land module "Lanyue", the lunar fact "wangyu" and the "Tansuo" space vehicle.
All are in the phase of development of preliminary prototypes, and the conception work is underway according to the scheduled calendar, read in the same note.
At the same time, the authorities began the construction of new infrastructures at the Wechang Space Launch Center in Hainan's island province in the south of the country.
Facilities include test and launch systems as well as land equipment to control the mission. The conception plans have already been approved and the works are about to begin, according to the statement.
China's Crew Lunar Exploration Program foresees two “Long March 10” releases from Wechang to place the “Lanyue” module and the “Mengzhou” spacecraft in the lunar orbit.
Once positioned, the two elements will be attached to space. Two astronauts will then be transferred to the lunar module, which will descend to the lunar surface with a motor -assisted landing.
During its stay on the moon, the crew will use the “Tansuo” tube to perform scientific activities and collect samples. At the end of the mission, they will return to the “Lanyue” module, which will take them back to the “Mengzhou” spacecraft in orbit, after which they will take the return trip to Earth.
Outlined Plan
Space program authorities have selected their fourth generation of astronauts, who are already training for lunar landing and exploration operations, according to the statement.
The Chang'e 7 mission is expected to reach the South Lunar hub in 2026, where it will look for water ice deposits, while Chang'e 8 in 2028 will explore possible uses for the resources discovered by its predecessor and launch the foundations for manned exploration in 2030.
China strongly invested in its space program and was successfully landing the Chang'e 4 probe on the farthest side of the moon-the first time it was achieved-and arrived in Mars for the first time, becoming the third country-after the United States and the former Soviet Union-to "dock" a robot on the red planet.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:28:34</pubDate></item><item><title>China | Additional rates of up to 15% on major US agricultural products</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/china-impostas-taxas-adicionais-de-ate-15-sobre-principais-produtos-agricolas-dos-eua/</link><description>China announced yesterday the imposition of additional customs rates of up to 15 percent on imports from the main agricultural products in the United States, including chicken, pork, soy and cow meat.
The rates, which have been announced by the Ministry of Commerce, are expected to take effect from March 10 and follow the order of US President Donald Trump to increase rates on Chinese product imports to 20 percent on all sectors since yesterday.
Chicken, wheat, corn and cotton imports in the United States will face an extra 15 percent rate, the ministry said. Sorghum rates, soybeans, pork, cow meat, sea products, fruits, vegetables and dairy products will be increased by 10 percent, he added.
Last Friday, the Chinese Ministry of Commerce expressed in a statement the “firm opposition” to US plans, adding that China “repeatedly” that “unilateral rates violate the rules of the World Trade Organization (WTO) and“ harm the multilateral commercial system ”.
Exchange of arguments
Trump pledged to impose an additional 10 percent rate on China-he had announced 10 percent previously-with the argument that the country did not make enough efforts to combat Fentanil entry into the United States.
The Chinese trade ministry has stated that "China is one of the countries with the most strict and comprehensive drug control policies in the world" and has actively cooperated with this issue with all nations in the world, "including the United States."
Trump made the rates of "progress" depend on the fight against fentanyl trafficking, also announcing 25 percent rates against Mexico and Canada. “Drugs are coming from Mexico and many of them are coming from China; Not all, but many of them are coming from China, ”he said.
In the first presidency of Trump, the US head of state maintained a tense relationship with Beijing, imposing several rounds of rates on China's goods, to which the Asian country responded with rates on US exports.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:27:19</pubDate></item><item><title>China | Military Budget is 'strong dish' of the annual session of the maximum legislative agency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/china-orcamento-militar-e-prato-forte-da-sessao-anual-do-orgao-legislativo-maximo/</link><description>The National Popular Assembly starts today, and runs until March 11, with the presence of 3,000 delegates. The reinforcement of the defense budget should gain a new impetus this year, in view of the international developments that increasingly promote the climate of insecurity
 
China should announce today the military budget for 2025, at the opening of the annual session of the country's maximum legislative agency, at a time when the United States proposes an agreement to reduce defense expenses. Analysts consider that the most likely to spend on the Armed Forces continue to increase, like what has happened in recent decades.
Beijing argues that the increases are "appropriate and reasonable" and aim to face "complex security challenges" and insists that their military modernization "does not constitute a threat to any country."
In recent years, Beijing's expenses with his Armed Forces have stabilized in annual growth rates of about 7.2 percent of the Chinese state budget. Last year, this value ascended to 1.67 billion of Yuan.
Analysts believe, however, that China's actual expense with the defense is significantly higher than the announced in the official budget.
"If they significantly deviate from this growth rate of about 7 percent, either above or below it, I think this will be significant," wrote Brian Hart, director-director and member of the North American Reflection Group Center for Strategic and International Studies (CSIS).
“I also think it will be significant if we see the [Chinese] employees to abandon the longstanding statements that defense expenses are linked to GDP growth. I do not foresee that they change these things, but they are certainly aspects to take into account, ”he said.
Protective muscle
In addition to having the world's largest permanent army, China has the largest navy and recently launched its third aircraft carrier. The country has a huge reserve of missiles, fighters, war ships capable of throwing nuclear weapons, advanced surface ships and nuclear -powered submarines.
On the other hand, China has a military base in Djibuti, in the horn of Africa, and modernized the Ream naval base in Cambodia, which offers him a semi -permanent presence in the Gulf of Thailand, facing the disputed Southern China Sea.
Regarding the statements of US President Donald Trump, who proposed a summit with Chinese President Xi Jinping and Russian President Vladimir Putin to negotiate a reduction in defense budgets of the three great powers, Beijing Countertops that Washington is expected to take the initiative.
"Once it appeals to 'America First', Trump should take the initiative to reduce military expenses," replied the spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry, Guo Jiakun, at a press conference.
"China's limited expense with the defense is entirely necessary to safeguard national sovereignty, security and its development interests, as well as to protect world peace," he said.
The National Popular Assembly, whose annual session runs until March 11, consists of about 3,000 delegates, including a representation of the Armed Forces. However, the delegates are not elected by direct suffrage, and the "ruling role" of the Chinese Communist Party is "a heart principle."</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:25:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Busan | Pyongyang condemns a visit from American aircraft carrier</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/busan-pyongyang-condena-visita-de-porta-avioes-norte-americano/</link><description>North Korea yesterday condemned the visit to Busan, in South Korea, US Nuclear Airparts USS Carl Vinson, considering the maneuver a "political and military provocation."
"The cruel maneuvers of the United States for the confrontation [with North Korea] were intensified in March with the appearance of Carl Vinson on the Korean peninsula," said Kim Yo Jong, sister of leader Kim Jong Un, according to official news agency KCNA.
"Since the arrival of the new government this year, the United States has increased political and military provocations against North Korea and" continued the hostile policy of the former government, "added Kim Yo Jong, one of the regime's leading spokesmen.
The USS Carl Vinson, a chief ship of a San Diego-based attack group in California, arrived in Busan on Sunday for a visit scheduled for Sunday, according to the US Navy.
"The visit to Busan demonstrates the commitment of the United States to the region, strengthening relations with the leadership of the Republic of Korea and the local population," said the US force in a statement.
The aircraft carrier should participate in the annual “Freedom Shield” sets with South Korea within a few days. Military cooperation between Seoul and Washington is regularly convicted of Pyongyang, who considers her to invade her territory and often retaliates with missile tests.
Kim Yo Jong criticized "the hostile policy of the United States," which, according to her, is "sufficient justification (for North Korea) indefinitely strengthens her nuclear determination force."
North Korea justifies its nuclear weapons program for the threats it claims to face from the United States and its allies.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:23:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Bernardo Mendia, Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong: “Portugal should extend your hand”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/bernardo-mendia-camara-de-comercio-e-industria-portugal-hong-kong-portugal-deve-estender-a-mao/</link><description>The Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry of Hong Kong, Sun Dong, arrives today, accompanied by entrepreneurs from digital areas, online trade and technology. Bernardo Mendia, Mayor of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong, highlights the importance of visiting Portuguese companies and Raehk as a complement to Portuguese contacts in Macau
 
 
Last year, Portugal was visited by Christopher Hui Ching-Yu, Secretary of Hong Kong Financial Affairs and Treasury, and now another Hong Kong ruler passes through Portugal. Is it a visit with added meaning?
As a Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong we consider this visit extremely important, valuing the attention that is being given to Portugal. It is important, above all, because it is such a specific area as innovation. This is an area where Hong Kong bets a lot and has been a priority for the region's authorities, and this is something that exists in common with Portugal, which has also bet on technological and scientific development. What Portugal should do is take this opportunity, extend your hand to the secretary and work in partnership. Technological and economic development is only done with international partnerships, opening markets and collaborations. This is also what we promote as a Chamber of Commerce. We have been involved in organizing this trip, something that started months ago. We will lead Portuguese companies to identify potential synergies with the entities that come here, so that they know each other and then do their work.
Hong Kong has been present in all editions of Websummit in Lisbon. Does this visit give the idea that the region intends to expand and establish more concrete partnerships with Portugal?
Yes, no doubt. This has evidenced in official speeches of the most important members of the Hong Kong government, including the executive's own head. This is the region's strategy at this time, being a bridge for the rest of the world to be able to enter Asia. Then the territory competes with other platforms, as Hong Kong, Singapore and Tokyo are perhaps the three territories with the greatest expression in this [technological] area in Asia. But Hong Kong presents the best conditions, not only for the support it gives [to companies], but also for being part of China, despite having a different legal system and a different currency. There is a system completely open at the level of capital circulation and internet access. I think Hong Kong is better positioned in this field, but this is a competition that the territory has to do, such as Portugal when it will perform in Asia, competing with Spain and other European countries in attracting foreign direct investment.
Macao is usually the main connection to Portugal, for historical reasons and the presence of the Portuguese language. Can Hong Kong also be a binding territory between Portuguese companies and Asia?
Macau and Hong Kong are very complementary in this regard. Macao has this historical connection with Portugal and has very important companies based in the territory, some of them for over 100 years, namely the National Bank Overseas. This experience, and the fact that the Portuguese language is still official, is undoubtedly an advantage for Portuguese companies. If it is necessary to enter the capital market, Portuguese companies will opt for a number of services provided by Hong Kong. But Macau has its own advantages and I consider it two very complementary markets. The geographical proximity of Macau and Hong Kong also acts as an attractive point.
During Christopher Hui Ching-Yu's visit last year, Hong Kong's position as Fiscal Paradise was addressed. How do you look at this question?
This visit is organized by the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Office and the tax issues will now be set aside. But our position, as a Chamber of Commerce, is that it makes no sense Hong Kong being on the list of tax havens, and makes no sense or from a legal point of view. None of the markets we compete with Hong Kong as a fiscal paradise, nor the European Union itself. We just have to lose with it, because we create barriers to trade and foreign direct investment in Portugal, and also the investment that is made by Portuguese companies in Macao, which are eventually affected by it. It makes no sense to this designation from a legal point of view, because Hong Kong does not gather the conditions to be part of the list of tax havens, and from the political point of view because no other European country puts the territory in this category.
China is present in the Portuguese market through various investments. Hong Kong is trying to create its own way?
Not in these terms. The overwhelming majority of Chinese investment that is made in Portugal is through Hong Kong. Then, in this respect, Hong Kong and China work in a quite complementary way. Hong Kong acts as a "aircraft carrier" from China in terms of foreign investment, and there is no competition between the two, working, together.
Encounters in Oeiras | Taguspark today hosts exchange sessions and seminars
Dong Sun is accompanied by Portugal by Hong Kong's most important companies and entities in the areas of innovation, technology and digital media, either government, with Hong Kong Science and Technology Park and “Cyberport”, technology park with budget projects in two billion Hong Kong; either academic and research, attending the entourage of the Hong Kong Applied Science and Technology Research Institute and “Hong Kong Microelectronics Research and Development Institute”.
Exchange sessions and seminars take place today from 4 pm at Taguspark, Oeiras, where Oeiras Valley Investment Agency is located, whose representatives have already been present in Macao for commercial contacts.
In the afternoon there will be the opportunity for dialogue between the Secretary of Hong Kong, representatives of the Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong and leaders of Raehk's technological parks and institutes, and in total 24 companies are represented.
In the Catalan road
In a statement issued by the Hong Kong executive, it is read that the program includes “meetings and exchanges with leaders of local political, business and innovation and technology sectors”, as well as visits to infrastructure, technological parks, research institutes and businesses.
The aim is to “reinforce ties and cooperation” with Portugal in this sector, “promoting the advantages of Hong Kong innovation and technology and exploring business opportunities abroad,” according to the statement.
Before passing through Lisbon, the delegation was in Barcelona to participate in the “Mobile World Congress”, considered one of the most influential technological events worldwide.
This is the second visit to Portugal of a member of the Hong Kong government within a year, after the secretary for financial services and treasure had passed through Lisbon in June. At the time, Christopher Hui Clay-Yu asked Portugal to remove Hong Kong from the list of tax havens and argued that it already fulfills the European Union standards to combat tax dropout.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Cristina Rocha Leiria, author of the project of the Ecumenical Center Kun Aím: “The work that most filled me”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/cristina-rocha-leiria-autora-do-projecto-do-centro-ecumenico-kun-iam-a-obra-que-mais-me-preencheu/</link><description>Until March 13 can be seen at the Kun Iam Ecumenical Center, the show “Moments of Light With Kun Iam”, an exhibition by Cristina Rocha Leiria, architect, sculptor and author of the center project. At HM, Cristina Rocha Leiria talks about a space created for all, including atheists, and regrets the lack of dissemination of the exhibition
Image: Rui Cunha Foundation
 
Tell me “moment of light”, the exhibition patent at the Kun Iam ecumenical center.
The center was created for silence, because everything is done for majorities, but we have to think about minorities, which have the right to exist. There may be a minority that needs silence. Crystals carried from Portugal can be seen and also acquired in China, chosen by me, and energy stones. Also included are 25 pieces made by Atlantis [Portuguese Company of the Vista Alegre Group] in Cristal, as well as a bazaar with other materials.
The ecumenical center was inaugurated in 1999, 25 years passed. How do you look at the project today? Do you feel that you are properly used?
It is the work that filled me the most. I worked on it at the level of architecture, because this is my training area, and I also worked with the sculpture because it is what I do, although I did not take any course. I sculpture as therapy. I worked at the level of music with Kyao and another conductor, who realized what I wanted and made a composition of such order that plays all day [in the center] and people never get tired. I treated, at the time, everything else, the decoration and what was sold there. Things have been running out and there was almost nothing to sell except for some books and postcards. We created a lot that sold, the tourists went there, made no noise because they realized it was a place of silence, bought and this space had a certain performance. This ecumenical center should be disclosed, which has become a former Macao Libris, with tourists as Macau has and that exists in any other urban place in the world. Therefore, the center works at this time with an exhibition of mine and a bazaar that has products that sell themselves in other places and that have nothing to do with the ecumenical center, but are a gimmick.
How was the start of the construction of this project? Have you ever done anything so much with so much connection with the spirit world?
I lived in Mozambique until I went to Lisbon to study architecture. As a child I know the goddess Kun Age, because my mother had a white statue of Kun ran home, and it was the thing I liked the most in that house. Little did I know that one day I would make a center dedicated to this goddess. When I came to Macau to work in the Leal Senate, as the president's advisor, with the first money I earned I went to Hong Kong to buy a white Abat-Jour with the figure of Kun Iam, which I still have today. Regarding the spiritual part, it comes from a child, I always liked the silence. When I do architecture or sculpture it is always in complete silence. I am only me linked to work and a world that, as it is not tangible, many people do not even realize it, do not believe him. I believe because I feel that when I work two nightsless nights, or three days in a row, in any project, silent, I wake up in the morning and I think of the ideas I had, I am surprised even with them. So the spiritual part is reflected in the sculpture I make. I specialize in housing and spirituality is also reflected in the projects I did in Macao in the area of ​​social housing. Spirituality is a part of me, and the ecumenical center is guided to it. In these guided tours that I have tried to pull for younger people to realize that we can be greatly helped by energies that we do not see. I do not name things and say not to care about it, because the important thing is to become aware that there is more than what we see. The material world is not the only one who interests us, there is more to make contact and thank.
Macao is a territory based on consumption, the game, the excesses. Having a center of this nature in this society has a greater meaning?
This center is ecumenical, but it has nothing to do with the church, referring to something comprehensive. The center was made for atheists, agnostic, religious and non -religious, for all those who need silence. And in the world of Macao, or in large urban media, there is always hearing pollution. This center was made on an island that I asked for the governor of the time, General Vasco Rocha Vieira, who was a very open person to this proposal. This island was created because there was no space in Macau at the time to place a 20 meter high monument. The center became a symbol, many will pray there, but it was not done for it. I must say that I believe that the essence of the divine is in each of us, but not everyone is aware of it. Others are open to this essence.
Returning to the exhibition. What can people learn from her?
I am now in Macao for a period of six months, but I have also dealt with various projects related to projects I have done in Portugal for many years and I have been trying to be recovered. The exhibition itself is there and is not an attractive. It is good to know that the reopening of the ecumenical center did not have the disclosure it should have. No one knows that the ecumenical center has been opened, and who appears there are the people who leave the children in the parks, watch the space, and go there with the children. It is interesting because the little ones go precisely to the energy points identified by me. People who are walking, come in, but will not be on purpose to see my exhibition. Then, as they see the gate that gives the river, they leave soon and the exhibition goes unnoticed.
But regrets that no more dissemination has been made.
It was not done, no. Now I am doing this job and spreading with friendly people. I am finishing an exhibition without, in fact, people have enjoyed when I have sculptures with messages. It takes about a month to sculpture, and I write, thinking, doing poetry, so I have a lot to convey to people about each sculpture. Many people say they get out of there richer. I will ask the exhibition to be prolonged beyond March 13th and it was good to happen, because there have been groups of people, including some that mark time with me and I will make the guided tour.
How did your connection come to Chinese culture?
This connection comes from childhood. Then I deepened this connection a lot because I had to study about the goddess Kun Iam. I had to see many figures of Kun were going to think how it would do one that was suspended there, outdoors subject to taps and strong winds, as well as high temperatures. The spiritual part was easier for me, because since childhood I am interested in oriental philosophies. This part of spirituality [in the construction of the ecumenical center] was easier for me, although it had many difficulties. I gave myself everything, books to the library, and even contributed financially to this center so that many young people could enjoy it.
He told me that some works he has built need recovery. Is this side of the artist ungrateful to see the projects to destroy themselves over time without preservation?
I don't regret anything, I try to understand. But I also try to defend the purposes that existed in the start of each project. I try to understand the way of being of the Chinese who lived so many years limited and with many prohibitions. I would like to understand why they put a bazaar at the exhibition to sell so many products. The same happens in Portugal: I have the work “Candle to the Wind” in Tavira, in a huge roundabout that had a lake, it was something I tried to do poeticly, but then I see that people despise. Now there is no water in space and herbs grow. I feel that there is a lack of respect for the artist.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 23:35:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Jimson Kun Wa Koi, President of the Macau Young Symphony Orchestra: “Macau is a culture space”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/jimson-kin-wa-hoi-presidente-da-orquestra-sinfonica-jovem-de-macau-macau-e-um-espaco-de-cultura/</link><description>The President of the Macao Youth Symphonic Orchestra, Jimson Kin Wa Hoi, defends support for classical music and young people. At the head of the orchestra two decades ago, the official reveals to HM details about the next concerts, including a passage in Portugal and the “24th Concert of the New Generation of Musicians 2025”, scheduled for this Sunday at the Cultural Center of Macau
 
Image: António Sanmfaurl_MacauNews
Let's start talking about the show at the Great Auditorium of the Macao Cultural Center (CCM) this Sunday. It is a great opportunity to reveal your project to the public.
Yes. In fact, the orchestra has existed since 1997, almost 28 years ago. Throughout this time we held about 100 concerts, in what we call Macao signature shows. The new generation of local musicians is indeed quite enthusiastic about the show we will have next Sunday.
Conducting concerts and participation in festivals is the most visible part of your project. But how many musicians are they currently on the orchestra? To what extent is the orchestra important for young people who want to be musicians?
We are indeed the only youth orchestra in Macao that provides specific training in this musical genre. At this stage, young musicians may have the opportunity to show their talent. We really try to build a new generation of musicians. This type of show encourages them to learn and go out more, studying music over the years, so it's really very important to them. In Sunday's show, musicians will have the opportunity to play in orchestra, and this year we organized two auditions to choose the soloists. I am happy to have a total of 33 groups of young people who participated in these auditions this year, where nine soloists were chosen.
He is the director of the only youth orchestra in Macau. How do you describe the panorama of musical formation of younger people? Where do you need to improve?
Yes of course. I started playing from the Macao orchestra from an early age, I'm a violinist. I can tell you that, at the level of training, most teachers are from Hong Kong or Guangzhou, that every week moving to Macau to train our young people. Macau is well known as the city of the game, but it is also a cultural space. You can feel the heritage that exists in Macau, thanks in part to the previous Portuguese administration, and we have to thank the maintenance of this Portuguese culture and a whole western culture mixed with the eastern. Macau is special for that. I think we have to promote this culture and know how to develop it. In the case of classical music, we started to have an orchestra in 1983, still during the government of the Portuguese administration, and there we also organized a series of competitions for the younger ones. The Macao International Music Festival also began to be organized several decades ago, as well as the Macao Arts Festival. Today, Macau has more initiatives of this genre and this is good for enriching our culture, especially the classical music that is made in the territory.
In addition to the Sunday show, what is on the Macao Youth Orchestra Agenda for this year?
I can tell you that we will participate in this year's edition of the Mafra Music Festival “Filipe de Sousa”, scheduled for July. I will visit Mafra and all the places where we will act, have meetings and organize myself with production. It will not be the first time we are, as a group, in Portugal, but I think that for most young musicians will be the first time. Our orchestra has played twice in Portugal, the first time was in 2010.
Do you understand that the Macao government should give more support for classical music training?
I always think that the government should give more support to classical music studies. For this it is not enough to spend money on the organization of festivals, it takes a greater focus on music education. We also have to teach the population how to appreciate classical music, listening to it and consuming it so that they can know what they hear and go to concerts. Macao is a small territory with about 600,000 inhabitants, and has a lot of money because of the game. We have to use this money to build a Macao culture, which includes classical music. We must create a city that shows its culture, so I always encourage the government to support musical formation. Not just for professional orchestras, but for youth orchestras and music associations.
Macao also lacks higher education courses in the music area, having only the Conservatory. Is this also a gap?
It's right. There are several universities in Macao, but there is, in fact, a lack of formative offer in the area of ​​music. The conservatory does not offer this formation at higher level. At this time, students who want to study music professionally have to leave Macau and go to Europe, the United States of America, Hong Kong or even China. But, on the other hand, the population of Macau is very small and maintaining a conservatory with another type of formative offer would cost a lot of money. I think the best you can do is the government financially supporting these excellent students to be accepted in Macao courses.
The young stars that will take the stage of the Cultural Center of Macau
Organized by the Macao Youth Symphonic Orchestra Association, Sunday's show starts at 7:45 pm and has as its motto “Progressing Towards The Future” [progressing towards the future]. The show will be directed by Italian conductor Lorenzo Antonio Iosco, who is also clarinetist and has been working with the Hong Kong Philharmonic Orchestra. Before moving to Asia in 2015, he studied clarinet at the Luigi Cherubini Conservatory in Florence and played in Spain and London.
With regard to the young Macao musicians who take the stage on Sunday, highlighting Zita Ho Nok Chon, born in the territory in 2009, and member of the orchestra since 2021. The young woman attend Pui Ching high school, studies violin and has participated in several contests with distinction. It has played in the orchestra as the first and second violinist.
In the harp stands out Eugenia Wong Hei U, born in 2011 and a student at the Anglican College of Macao. He began playing this instrument with only four years, starting his training at the Conservatory School of Music, which earned his first award when he was only five years old. It currently has classes with Ann Huang, the main harpist at Sinfonietta from Hong Kong.
To HM Eugenia Wong hei u confessed that he feels very pleased by the opportunity provided by the CCM concert. “It has been a great honor to be part of this orchestra, where I met many talented partners and earn a great musical knowledge.”
Another name of Macao on the young orchestra is Brian Mui On Ian, violinist, who also attends Pui Ching Secondary School. In addition to the violin, he began studying piano in 2018. The young man was one of the soloists of last year's edition of the Macao Youth Symphonic Orchestra, the “23rd Macau Music New Generation Musicians Concert 2024”, where he played the composition “Bruch Double Concerto In and Minor”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Cristina Ferreira, jurist and professor at the University of Macau: “The Fatf was in the right place and moment”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/27/cristina-ferreira-jurista-e-docente-da-universidade-de-macau-o-faft-estava-no-lugar-e-momento-certos/</link><description>Cristina Ferreira, an expert in international law, investigated the legal status of the “International Financial Action Group”, which fights money laundering and terrorism financing. In the book “The Legal Status of the Financial Action Task Force in the International Legal System”, the jurist discusses the undefined legal status of the body that got great power worldwide
 
What are the main reasons for the creation of the Financial Action Task Force (FATF)?
The FATF emerges within the scope of the G7 in July 1989, largely at the United States of America (US), to respond to the crime of laundering of capital trafficking and the United Nations Convention against illicit trafficking and psychotropic substances of 1988. Common guidelines and the coordination of preventive measures, especially in the financial scope and international cooperation. 40 international recommendations were elaborated against the laundering of capital ”. Today the FATF has 40 members, 38 jurisdictions, the European Commission and the Gulf Cooperation Council. The last member, Indonesia, entered 2023. These members represent industrialized countries, large financial squares and emerging economies.
How do you evaluate the performance of the FATF over the years?
He played a very important role of leadership after September 11, 2001. Suddenly, the fight against terrorism (FT) became an international obligation and priority on the agenda of all countries. In the international level, the states were urged to be part of the International Convention to suppress terrorism financing, as well as regional or international agreements and actions to combat terrorism and their financing. Internally, countries have been instituted to criminalize the FT, to adopt FLS, prevention and detection measures of the FT in financial entities, such as banks and insurers, and non-finances, such as casinos, real estate agencies or pledge stores. To adopt new international instruments that harmonize or even standardize the practices of various states, and agree on their content, it may take years. But the fatf was in the right place and moment. Given its informal nature and flexibility to adjust your mandate due to the threats that could exist in the financial system and its technical know-how, the FATF incorporated in its mandate the fight against FT and produced recommendations, at a time when this matter was new to most jurisdictions. The FATF acted quickly, useful and efficiently to the international community. It had experienced experts in the financial area and the ability to assist in the application [of the recommendations] and supervise its execution. The same happened in 2009, following the 2008 financial crisis and the G20 request to reinforce measures intended for transparency and combat corruption. Therefore, it has been a positive way.
It argues that the FATF has occurred in a “institutional metamorphosis” in this body. As?
The FATF was created as an informal, technical and temporary group, renewable every eight years, but over 30 years has become an increasingly complex organization, governing 206 jurisdictions today. The extension of the mandate also implied the evolution of its powers and responsibilities, and today the FATF is worldwide recognized as the international authority on this matter. It is endowed with a public power of world governance whose recognition is translated into several resolutions of the UN Security Council.
The study comes to clarify the legal status of FATF. What status is this and what is the connection with other entities also linked to the fight against FT and money laundering?
The FATF is the world authority responsible for setting international standards, rules and policies on these subjects and there is no duplication of functions with other international organizations and entities, including International Monetary Fund (IMF), the World Bank and the European Union. This study argues that the gradual evolution of the mandate, the FATF's institutional structure and 'modus operandi' has changed its 'modus constiti'. That is, an organization can evolve into an international organization of full right, regardless of the initial intention of the members and not being created by a treaty.
How do you explain that, to date, the FATF Legal Statute is lacking clarification?
I think there was never a real interest in analyzing this issue in depth. This theme was addressed between 2016 and 2018, during the Spanish and Argentine FATF Presidencies, but was “Marinar”, with the argument that there would be a advantage of maintaining a flexible entity to more easily be able to respond to emerging challenges and risks against safety, transparency and integrity of the international financial system. But the fact is that the FATF began to stop and exercise enormous power, as it evaluates and identifies non-compliant jurisdictions, naming them in lists ('Blacklisting'). It may also install measures to members and non -members, a power detained by very few international organizations.
To what extent does your recommendations impact and put into practice?
FATF recommendations have impact because countries are regularly evaluated on their application, called the “Technical Compliance”, and the effectiveness of their practical application, with the designation of “immediate outcomes”. This assessment is made according to strict criteria, being given a classification. If the result is disabled, the jurisdiction has to make a high level of resolution political commitment to these deficiencies, becoming part of the 'gray list', subject to an action plan and a term [compliance]. In the absence of political commitment or lack of sufficient progress in the execution of the plan, jurisdiction can be appointed to the 'blacklist', and the FATF may appeal to all FATF network jurisdictions to advise their financial institutions to reinforce diligence measures regarding the risks associated with such a jurisdiction. This is what has been happening to Myanmar since October 2022. If jurisdiction has serious deficiencies or does not comply with the action plan or is not a member of a regional group, it can be appointed to the 'blacklist'. In this case, the FATF may appeal to apply the 'Recommendation 19' measures, ranging from reinforcing the diligence and systematic communication of transactions and operations involving jurisdiction to the limitation or prohibition of financial transactions with jurisdiction.

Are there some concrete examples?
This happens with Iran and North Korea two decades ago. The international reputation [from this measure to a country] is real, has a political and economic cost. A study of the 2021 International Monetary Fund (IMF) reveals that the estimated negative effects of 7.6 percent of gross domestic product on capital flows and a significant reduction in foreign direct investment in the jurisdictions in the 'gray list' and may even have consequences under IMF.
It raises, in the book, the question of the importance of FATF in the global institutional landscape. What importance is this?
FATF serves as an institutional, operational and regime model for other international organizations. This study develops a theoretical model that can be used in any organization that acts on the international scene, gathers the same objective elements and whose legal status is uncommon. In the background, the FATF is a practical case. International law is not static and one has to analyze reality and adjust the models, and they must reflect the objective reality of the international legal order.
China and Hong Kong are members of the FATF. What is the relationship of MSAR and local policies to combat FT and money laundering with this entity?
MSAR is a member of one of the FATF regional groups-the Asia-Pacific group to combat capital bleaching (APG), and obeys the recommendations and mechanisms of FATF supervision, exercised by APG. Macau has had a good performance, obviously fulfilling his recommendations. This happened, for example, with the adoption of the property freezing regime and the law of transmitting control control of cash and negotiable instruments to the bearer. Incidentally, the MSAR was the world's first jurisdiction to obtain the best technical compliance grade compared to the 40 FATF recommendations when it was evaluated in 2017.
What are the main challenges that FATF currently faces in combating this type of crimes?
The use of new technologies, virtual currency and limited access to formal financial services leading to the use of unregulated channels, increasing the risks of capital bleaching and FT. In the book also speak of the economic pit and response or action capacity between FATF's member jurisdictions regarding the member jurisdictions of regional groups. Many of them are fragile or low -income economies, so it is not surprising that they have more disabilities or difficulties in complying with FATF international standards. In APG, by way of example, Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Cambodia, Laos, Myanmar, Nepal, Timor-Leste and Tuvalu are on the World Bank list of 2023 of the least developed countries, which makes the uniform and global application of FATF standards and policies difficult. In addition, the standards, policies, evaluation procedures and recommendations or FATF action plans are poorly flexible or adjustable to the local reality and internal and regional conditionalisms of non -FATF member jurisdictions. A more equitable participation or representation of these jurisdictions in the final decision -making process of the FATF should also be ensured in order to increase its legitimacy and transparency.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP TCR | Australia confirms presence in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/19/gp-tcr-australia-confirma-presenca-em-macau/</link><description>The 2025 season of TCR Australia will end largely when joining the TCR World Tour in the race of the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, which will take place from 13 to 16 November
 
After welcoming TCR China by 2024, the FIA ​​TCR World Tour “worldwide” will have the company of the Australian competitors in the most demanding race of the season, as HM had already foreseen at the end of last year.
This announcement is the second news in the calendar of one of the largest national TCR competitions in the world, after the announcement of a new promoter for the championship.
One pilot who was certainly pleased with the news was Australian Ben Bargwanna, who ran on the streets of Macao in 2023. TCR Australia's first international participation was made possible by the global rights holder, the WSC Group, which will ensure full transportation costs for Australian teams traveling to Macau.
"TCR Australia has always been one of TCR's most important and exciting competitions, rooted in the long tradition of tourism motorsport in the country," said WSC Group president Marcello Lotti. The Italian businessman made it clear that “when logistical issues forced us to cancel the Australian rounds of Kumho Fia TCR World Tour last year, we immediately started working to return in 2025. It is fantastic to extend cooperation for a second event and offer Australian competitors the unique opportunity to finish the season in Macau.”
Other applause
TCR Australia Prosecutor David Sonenscher, an old acquaintance of Macao, highlighted the importance of the moment for the category.
"I am very happy to bring TCR Australia to one of the most iconic circuits in the world and certainly one of the biggest challenges for a pilot," said former Malaysian-based English driver and entrepreneur and co-founder of TCR Asia. “The opportunity to expand our cooperation with the TCR World Tour FIA and to show the talented Australian riders on the highest international stage in Macau demonstrates the unique opportunity that TCR Australia and the TCR Global Platform provide all participants.”
Confirmation of the presence of TCR Australia in the Guide Race should not be impeded to the participation of local pilots and the interior of China in the most celebrated tourist car race on the Asian continent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 01:54:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorcycling | FHO RACING WITH NEW FOCUS IN 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/13/motociclismo-fho-racing-com-novo-foco-em-2025/</link><description>Doubts dissipated this week. Macau's businesswoman Foye Ho's FHO Racing will continue to active in the 2025 season, but without the initially announced riders. Peter Hickman and Davey Todd are leaving and goes to a new team called 8ten Racing
 
According to a statement sent by FHO Racing, BMW Motorrad UK has restructured its training for the 2025 British Superbike Championship, and FHO Racing BMW will compete with a single pilot aboard a BMW M 1000 RR. German 2024 Superbike Champion and Resistance World Cup driver, Ilya Mikhalchik, will make his debut in the British competition, at a time when team owner Faye Ho, realinhas the objectives of his team “to explore new activities in motorized new markets, with the support of BMW Motorrad Motorsport”.
Currently in his fifth year at the British Superbike Championship Paddock, Faye Ho has been a strong presence in the British competition, as well as in the popular road races, such as the Macao Grand Prix, as well as supporting several young female riders, helping them progress in their careers since the lower classes. Faye Ho, Stanley Ho's granddaughter and Clementina Leitão, has supported Kate Walker and Jamie Hanks-Bliott on BMW F 900 R Cup and, it seems, which will continue to support.
To be
Contrary to the rumors that put her from Paddock's departure, Faye Ho made it clear that she is a “great advocate of the British Superbike Championship, one of the world's most exciting and competitive competitions” and will keep her commitment to discipline. However, the territory entrepreneur now has new objectives for herself and its structure. The future will be in Asia and support for young female talents.
"Given my long -term objectives, which include expanding motor sport activities in Asia and continuing to support young women in motorcycling, I realized that I cannot dedicate the same time, to the British Superbike Championship and the road races, which I gave them since I became the owner of the team in 2021, due to additional commitments I have in Macao," Faye Ho said.
Another chapter
This announcement has put an end to a successful partnership, particularly on the island of Man TT, between Peter Hickman, four times winner of the Macao Motorcycle Grand Prix, and Fho Racing. Hickman left some words of thanks to his now former boss.
“I want to leave a huge thanks to Faye [Ho] and Fho Racing for all they have done for me over the past four years,” Hickman wrote in a Facebook social network post. “As it is normal in motorized sport, we had amazing moments and others more difficult, but Fho has always been and always will be a fundamental part of my career. I will be eternally grateful for this opportunity. ”
The new 8Ten Racing team, which will be officially presented on February 26, will be mostly composed of former FHO Racing elements. Hickman and Todd will maintain the important support of BMW Motorrad UK and are expected on the big prize starting grid in November.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 01:30:05</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | FIA confirms GT World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/gp-macau-fia-confirma-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The World Council of the FIA ​​last Wednesday confirmed the expected, that the eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be held as part of the Macao's 72nd Grand Program, from November 13 to 16. However, there is a big news for this year's edition
 
The International Federation, which co-organizes this race in partnership with Sro Motorsports Group and the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), took the opportunity to announce a new qualification model for the race. In addition to the 30 -minute qualification session equal to the previous editions (Q1), a second qualification segment (Q2) was added, reserved for the top ten pilots of the first session.
The Q2 session will be held in Super Pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification turns, and each pilot is also allowed to use a new tire set at this session. This novelty will allow qualification to be decided without interference from third parties.
The remaining program of the Queen of GT will remain the same as the previous editions, with the free training session, the traditional 12-lap classification race on Saturday afternoon, followed by the 16-lap main race that will decide the world's Cup winner on Sunday.
Veterans compliments
These measures introduced by the FIA ​​were very well received by the most experienced GT riders. This is because traffic has always been a huge obstacle in obtaining a good qualification return on the guide circuit, something essential for those who aim to win this title.
"It's an excellent idea to introduce the Super Pole session in Macao," said German Maro Engel, the winner of the World Cup last edition by Mercedes-AMG. This will be one of the most spectacular and exciting sessions of the season and should also secure sports justice. Fans have a lot to yearn. ”
Raffaele Marciello, for two winning occasions of this trophy, and one of BMW's factory riders, also reacted positively, adding: “In Macao, it was always complicated to make a clean turn. With this new format, you will not hear the excuse of traffic or a red flag. Having only two laps will be very challenging, but now the fastest pilot will probably be in pole. ”
This is an opinion shared by Laurens Vanthoor, the World Cup winner in 2016, who said there will no longer be “apologies” in the qualification. Porsche's experienced Belgian pilot believes that “there will be an added pressure because you only have these two turns”, because in a difficult circuit like this, “if you make an error, there is nothing else to follow. In a normal qualification, you have more opportunities. Personally, a shootout is always something I appreciate a lot. For pilots, on a track like this, it will be almost the highlight of the weekend. ”
And the younger ones too
Chinese pilot Yifei Ye premiered at the Grand Prix last November at the World Cup. Ferrari's official pilot, which competes in the Endurance Fia World Championship (WEC), has left a good impression on the guide circuit, and he also welcomes the now introduced measurements.
“It's good to eliminate these red flag interventions and yellow flags, so that in the end, the one that really is the fastest to get pole position,” said Yifei Ye that she could return to the race this year. “In Macau, everyone is very close in terms of times, so it will be extremely difficult for pilots to try to reach Super Pole. I think it will also be great for viewers. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-28 01:03:51</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Célio Alves Dias will continue to run this season</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/gp-celio-alves-dias-vai-continuar-a-correr-esta-temporada/</link><description>Macaense pilot Célio Alves Dias was one of the long -term returns of the 2024 car.
 
The Macao Cup winner of Macau in 2021 was removed from motorsport at the time of 2023 for personal reasons, but last year made his debut in the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8). Despite the vast experience in tests of the specialty, having conducted several generations of tourism cars, Célio Alves Dias had never managed the new bobbinns that the Macao-China General Association (AAMC) introduced in its competition in 2023. Last time turned out to be of learning, with some difficulties in the tuning and behavior of the Japanese car.
Participation in races at the Zhuzhou International Circuit and the Macau Grand Prix made Célio Alves Dias realize that his Toyota GR86 was not at the strongest competition level. Based on the conclusions drawn from these experiences, he decided to start preparing for the new season.
“The car had to be all dismantled. My car was bought on Monday, and the chassis and the security arc, for me, were not well done, ”explained Fu Lei Racing Team pilot to HM. “This, made the car too hard and very difficult to bow. I tried a car from China, which was well assembled, and there is a difference. I had a long time in January, in China, with this car. Our cars, made in the same workshop, were very hard, which made it difficult to make turns fast. ”
If in the Macao Grand Prix, the house riders, excellent guide circuit, managed to equate the progress to their hong Kong opponents and the interior of China, in the initial races on the Zhuzhou track in Hunan province, it wasn't quite like that. “There are many differences between cars, but especially in chassis, because engines, in terms of power and horses, are almost all at the same level. Our opponents also experienced many pieces, many engines, even gearboxes, and chassis. Competition cars are always the same. You have to have engine power, but also chassis. Having only power is not enough. Having better a good chassis is the most important. ”
Silver Jubilee in November
Being a usual Portuguese name in the Macao Grand Prix in recent decades, Célio Alves Dias debuted at the Guide Circuit in 2000 and from then was a frequent presence and no faults in the race until 2023. This year, its objective is to account for its twenty-fifth participation in the biggest sports event of RAEM, but will have to align in the findings.
While awaiting the announcement of the 2025 calendar by AAMC, Célio Alves Dias details details to start his test program, because his Toyota, after being reviewed, "is ready to test" in the interior of China, something that will happen "very soon," says the pilot.
In the last edition of the Grand Prix, Célio Alves Dias qualified in 12th place for the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. However, his participation was short and unhappy: at the wheel of Toyota with dorsal No. 11, was forced to give up after being immobilized on the climb of San Francisco. The Macanese pilot was out of the race on the first lap, in an incident that caused the Safety Car.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:50:53</pubDate></item><item><title>FHO RACING | Peter Hickman denies closing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/07/fho-racing-peter-hickman-nega-encerramento/</link><description>Peter Hickman, four times winner of the Macao Motorcycle Grand Prix, denied the rumors that claimed that the team Racing, from Macau Faye Ho businesswoman, would have closed the doors and would be absent on the British Superbike Championship (BSB) and the Macao Grand Prix in 2025
 
Peter Hickman goes to the fifth season in the British Championship with Fho Racing, however, before the season's start, some rumors came to circulate in Paddock about the team's future. In recent years, FHO Racing has become one of the top teams in the British Superbike Championship and road events, such as the MAN's island TT or the Macao Grand Prix.
Last November, the team announced that they featured Peter Hickman and Davey Todd, winner of the troubled last edition of the Macao Grand Motor Prize in the British Superbike Championship. Faye Ho said at the time that “for 2025 and also for this year's Macao Grand Prix, we have a very strong team, with Davey joining Pete and Michael aboard the BMW. We have two super talented drivers on the roads for next season, and with Davey jumping to the Superbike class, after winning the Superstock Championship for the second time, I think we'll have a strong season. I can't expect my team to return to Macau, I love to share my hometown with the team and show all points of interest, it's such a special place for me. ”
Although Hickman and Todd have been present at the BMW Motorrad Motorsport season in Berlin in mid -January, since November that Fho Racing has no news, which has generated some discomfort and doubts among fans. Hickman was testing his BMW M1000RR from his Phr Performance in Spain, when he responded with a striking "no" to a fan of a fan on Instagram social network about the rumor of FHO Racing activity ceasing, a "no" that had wide repercussion in the specialized British press.
It's not the first time
After a difficult season of his team in 2024 in the British Superbike Championship, Faye Ho, Stanley Ho's granddaughter, had to face similar rumors last September. In Oulton Park, before the opening race of the 2024 showdown, Faye Ho confirmed to journalists that FHO Racing would continue to participate in the 2025 British Superbike Championship, “which is good news, but anything will be announced in time. But I'm happy to be back here and to stay here, it's a big championship and I love to be in this racing environment. ”
To increase speculation between fans, Hickman suggested on social networks a change of direction this year, leaving an announcement about his plans for the North West 200 and TT of the island of Man. In Spain, the British will have tested with his motorcycle without any reference and FHO Racing speakers, while Todd changed his profile photo on social networks, for a photo with a motorcycle from Milwauke BMW by Tas Racing.
Sources of the world of motorcycling tell us that the future of FHO Racing is expected to be known in the coming days, but one thing is that Hickman, regardless of the team, has in his sports program to the trip to masters in November, to try to win the fifth victory in the guide circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 02:20:15</pubDate></item><item><title>GT Cup | Great Bay Race gains impulse from the interior</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/27/taca-gt-corrida-da-grande-baia-ganha-impulso-do-interior/</link><description>The GT Cup-Great Bay Race will be part of this year, the newly created Sro GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macau Grand Prix
 
On the eve of last Christmas, Sro Motorsport Group, the entity responsible for organizing numerous events and championships, including the GT World Challenge Asia and, as the official partner of the FIA, the co-coordination of the FIA ​​GT Cup in Macao, announced the creation of a competition for GT4 vehicles, made up of four events in China. At the time of the announcement, only the inaugural event in Shanghai and the end in Beijing had been confirmed as part of the calendar.
Almost 30 cars, representing an impressive total of ten car builders, participated in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race of 2024, a race that has become an important milestone over the weekend of the Macao Grand Prix in recent years. Indeed, no other GT4 event in Asia brings together such quantity and diversity of cars. The Balance of Performance (BOP), responsible for balancing the performance of the various participating cars, was, at the time, managed by SRO.
In a statement, Benjamin Frannasovici, managing director of Sro Motorsports Asia, said:
“We are enchanted, proud and privileged for adding the GT Cup - Great Bay Race to the inaugural calendar of Sro GT Cup, which begins and ends with the two largest motorized sports events in China. We already have a strong working relationship with the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, which has become the most significant race for GT4 cars in Asia. Its inclusion in the 2025 calendar of the SRO underlines the size of our ambition for this new national series. ”
High interest
The SRO GT Cup debut season begins in March at China's Formula 1 Grand Prix in Shanghai, before moving to the Zhuhai International Circuit - a place previously visited by SRO in BPR times and the FIA ​​GT Championship - where two 30 -minute races are planned. This is followed by the new Citadine Circuit of Beijing, which will host the GT World Challenge Asia on the same weekend, before the big end of the Sro GT Cup season, scheduled for a month later at the Guide Circuit in Macao.
The enthusiasm surrounding this competition is evident. As Benjamin Franassovici said, “This is reflected in the number of consultations and registration for the full season we have received since the release of the championship, just before Christmas. The demand has exceeded our expectations. ”
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete at the season end event on the streets of Macau, with places to be assigned based on the classification after the second round of the championship, which is scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit. All pilots with bronze or “silver” classifications attributed by the FIA ​​are eligible to compete in this competition, as long as they use approved cars from the GT4 class.
To attract brands, the results of SRO GT Cup races will tell the SRO GT4 builders ranking, a title attributed to the brand with better performance in the GT4 category at the end of each season. SRO GT CUP joins its Asian equivalent, Japan Cup, in a list that also includes continental and national competitions in Europe, America and Australia.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 11:13:41</pubDate></item></channel></rss>