<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Palestine | Pope defends two-state solution when receiving Abbas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/palestina-papa-defende-solucao-de-dois-estados-ao-receber-abbas/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday reiterated his defense of a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, when he received the President of the Palestinian Authority, Mahmud Abbas, for the first time in an audience at the Vatican.
This first meeting between Abbas and Leo XIV since the pope's election in May also served to mark the tenth anniversary of the signing of the Global Agreement between the Vatican and the State of Palestine, in 2015, the year in which the Catholic Church recognized the Palestinian State. “During the cordial talks, the urgent need to provide assistance to the civilian population in Gaza and to put an end to the conflict, seeking a two-state solution, was recognized,” the Vatican said in a statement.
On Wednesday, shortly after arriving in Rome, Abbas went to the Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore for a moment of recollection before the tomb of Pope Francis, who died in April. “I came here because I cannot forget everything he did for the Palestinian people,” he told the press.
The President of the Palestinian Authority, in power in the West Bank, visited the Vatican on several occasions during Francis' pontificate, having, in 2014, planted an olive tree in the Vatican gardens alongside former Israeli head of state Shimon Peres and Pope Francis, as a symbol of peace.
In the last months of his pontificate, the Argentine pope toughened his statements against the Israeli offensive, causing diplomatic tensions with the Israeli embassy.
Pope Leo XIV has also expressed solidarity with the “martyred land” of Gaza on several occasions and denounced the forced displacement of Palestinians, but highlighted that the Vatican cannot comment on the alleged genocide in the enclave. On Friday, Abbas will be received in the early afternoon by the Italian Prime Minister, Giorgia Meloni, at the Chigi Palace, the seat of the Government, in Rome.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:29:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment | Calls for measures to improve access in construction and retail</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/emprego-pedidas-medidas-para-melhorar-acesso-na-construcao-e-no-retalho/</link><description>Deputy Leong Pou U argues, in a statement, that measures are necessary to promote employment in the construction sector. Although the latest employment survey by the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC) shows a drop in the unemployment rate, Leong Pou U warns of the poor employment situation in some economic sectors, such as construction and retail sales. Leong Pou U emphasizes that unemployment mostly originated in these two sectors, according to DSEC data.
In this way, the deputy, linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), argues that the Government must launch specific support measures, to provide a situation of full employment in the construction sector. Leong Pou U talks about the underemployment situation for many workers in this sector, taking into account that both public and private work have suffered reductions, in addition to the fact that salaries have been frozen for many years.
For this reason, the deputy suggests that the Government increases the proportion of workers residing in public works awarded, as well as launching more public works projects.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:36:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Rua dos Mercadores | Traffic prohibited until Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/rua-dos-mercadores-transito-proibido-ate-segunda-feira/</link><description>The traffic ban on Rua dos Mercadores, created due to work being carried out at the site, and which should come to an end today, will have to be extended until Monday. At issue is the “need to cure the paving concrete”, with the closure of Rua dos Mercadores to traffic and the reverse measures on Rua das Estalagens and Rua de Camilo Pessanha remaining until 10pm on Monday.
Regarding the bus service, bus route no. 18 (direction to Rua dos Currais) will temporarily continue without making stops at “Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro/Tai Fung”, “Rua dos Mercadores”, “Rua das Estalagens” and “Rua de Cinco de Outubro”. During this period, the “Ponte 16” or “Rua do Tarrafeiro” stops can be used for entrances and exits.
The work is expected to end on November 27th, as defined since the beginning of the project, related to the underground cable network, “greater than initially planned and required better reorganization”. The third, and final, phase of the works takes place between Tuesday and the 27th of this month, “with the intervention area concentrated predominantly on internal roads in the area, not affecting the original direction of traffic”, describes the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT).</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:54:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Success of “book exchange” leads IC to organize more sessions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/sucesso-de-troca-de-livros-leva-ic-a-organizar-mais-sessoes/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) decided to extend the deadline for carrying out the “Book Exchange” initiative, which covers various activities in the territory's public libraries and community neighborhoods, in order to encourage reading.
According to a statement, the extension of the program is due to the fact that “the activity has been widely acclaimed”, so there will be more sessions on weekends during this month and also in December, in order to “further expand the circulation and sharing of books”.
Therefore, this weekend, Saturday and Sunday, new book exchange sessions will take place at Praça de Luís de Camões, and then at Largo do Lilau on the 27th and 28th of December. These two sessions join those previously scheduled for the Lateral Space of Jardim Cidade das Flores, on the 22nd and 23rd of November. The timing of all sessions is from 12pm to 6pm.
For these sessions, IC describes, “participants only need to take the books that comply with the exchange rules to the staff on site, selecting their favorites and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books”.
Standards to comply with
The rules determine that magazines, leaflets, guides for entering a school, school books, event catalogs, children's books, yearbooks published non-locally, legal books, exam preparation books, books with pornographic and/or violent content, religious books, books without a publishing license or with copyright infringements, books with incomplete or damaged pages, volumes of books belonging to an incomplete collection, books with loose binding, with pages that are easy to separate or with missing pages cannot be exchanged. pages, books with written or scribbled pages and books with more than five copies.
In order to maintain the timeliness and usefulness of the books, science and engineering books published more than five years ago, computer books published more than three years ago, tourist guides published more than two years ago are not accepted. Each person can exchange a maximum of 20 books during the event.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 02:08:29</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Race week approaches</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/gp-macau-semana-de-corridas-aproxima-se/</link><description>It already smells like a Grand Prix in the city. On Friday, the containers with the sixteen cars from the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be unloaded in the paddock and, after the official stickers have been placed, they will be transported to Praça do Tap Seac, where they will be on display, along with the bikes from the 57th Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, until Sunday.
This year's edition features no less than thirty-two national flags, which will be raised by competitors from the three FIA ​​World Cups and the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour during the packed program of the 72nd Macau Grand Prix. There could have been thirty-three if Serbian Dušan Borković, winner of the 2024 Guia Race, had not been replaced this week by Spaniard Pepe Oriola in one of GOAT Racing's three Hondas.
The FIA ​​Formula Regional (FR) World Cup, which is being held for the second time after the debut edition in 2024, has fifteen countries or special administrative regions represented, including Macau. In its first edition, the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup features thirteen nationalities on the entry list, while the eighth FIA GT World Cup will be contested by drivers from ten countries or special administrative regions.
Therefore, the flags of South Africa, Germany, Argentina, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, China, South Korea, Denmark, United Arab Emirates, Spain, United States of America, Philippines, France, Hong Kong, Hungary, India, Indonesia, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Macau, Mexico, Poland, United Kingdom, Sweden, Switzerland, Thailand, Chinese Taipei, Turkey, Uruguay and Vietnam will be seen.
Highlight is the absence of the Portuguese flag among the pilots. You have to go back to the beginning of the 1970s to find such a low presence of Portuguese-born pilots at the event. In addition to young Tiago Rodrigues, veterans of the territory Rui Valente and Jerónimo Badaraco will be present, both in the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. The universe of Lusophony is completed with the Brazilian Ethan Nobels, who will make his debut at the Guia Circuit in the F4 race.
Couceiro and Lamy present
After being the Race Director of the first edition of the FIA ​​FR World Cup, Rui Marques is one hundred percent focused on the Formula 1 World Championship, where he has carried out these functions since last year's Macau Grand Prix. In his place will be Simon Gnana-Pragasam, who performs this role in the FIA ​​Formula 2 and Formula 3 Championships. The Briton will also drive the first Formula 4 World Cup in history. Dino Lodola will be the Race Director of the Guia Race, while the Czech Miroslav Bartos will have this role in the GT race and the only motorcycle race, while the experienced Chinese Zhang Tao will be at the helm of the GT Cup – Great Bay Race (GT4) and the Macau Roadsport Challenge.
Two well-known faces from national motorsport will also be present in Macau again, now retired from the tracks, but with other roles on the international scene: Pedro Lamy and Pedro Couceiro. The runner-up in the 1992 Formula 3 Macau Grand Prix, and the first driver to score points in the Formula 1 world championship, Lamy will once again be present as Stewards' Driver Advisor in the FR and Guia Races, a role he has already played in the Guia Circuit and in Formula 1, sharing this role with former F1 driver Vitantonio Liuzzi, who will perform this role in the GT and F4 races.
Pedro Couceiro, who, like Pedro Lamy, competed on the streets of Macau in Formula 3 in the 1990s, will be the driver of the Safety Car in the three FIA ​​World Cups and the Guia Race, which this year will be sponsored by BMW Concessionaires (Macau). The former Portuguese driver takes on this position in the FIA ​​World Endurance Championship (WEC) and was previously in the Macao SAR in these roles.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:22:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Colégio S. José 5th | Teacher accused of humiliating student</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/colegio-s-jose-5a-professora-acusada-de-humilhar-aluno/</link><description>In response to the complaint, the school admits an internal investigation into the case, but warned the complainant to prepare for the consequences, because “the Internet is not a lawless space”. The Government reportedly received a complaint about the case on October 14th, but until now it has remained silent
A teacher at Colégio Diocesano de São José 5ª is being accused of humiliating a student with autism, allegedly using insulting words, after leaving the student waiting more than 80 minutes for a meeting. The complaint was published on social media, on Monday, by an anonymous user, who justifies the use of this medium with the fact that complaints to the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) and the school were ignored.
According to the report presented online, the episode took place on October 10th in the school's teachers' room. The student with autism, who attends secondary school, had an appointment with the teacher. However, the teacher arrived 80 minutes late and reprimanded the student: "But you can never do anything well, except be here waiting? Why didn't you ask another teacher to call me?", the teacher asked. "I taught you so many times, but you never listen! You always act as if I never taught you anything", he added.
The words disturbed the student who raised his voice against the teacher. However, she again admonished the student: "You are not authorized to speak in that tone of voice! Never speak to a teacher in that way", warned the teacher.
After the reprimand, the teacher will have justified, in front of the other teachers present, the arguments used with the fact that the student suffers from autism.
List of complaints
In view of the case, the author of the online comment admits to having filed a complaint about the teacher's conduct with the DSEDJ, the school's management, the Institute of Social Action, and several deputies, including José Pereira Coutinho, for having received the most votes in the last elections, and Ho Ion Sang, elected indirectly by the education sector.
In the complaints presented, an independent investigation into the case was requested, that the teacher be punished due to her conduct and that a review be carried out of the mechanisms for students to defend themselves against teachers when they are targets of abuse.
Although the complaint was made on October 14th, by November 3rd the complainant had not received any response, so he decided to make the complaint public, through social media.
School investigates
With the case going viral, Colégio Diocesano de São José 5ª issued a statement on Tuesday promising an internal investigation, but warning that it will act against defamation attempts.
"Recently, our institution became aware of anonymous online complaints about members of our faculty. These allegations concern issues of professional conduct [...] The school takes these matters very seriously and immediately initiated a rigorous internal investigation," the institution said.
Furthermore, the college revealed that DSEDJ has started to investigate the case: “The school always defends the rights and legitimate interests of staff and students and will actively cooperate with the supervision and investigation work that has already been initiated by the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services”, it was revealed.
Despite this, the school was prepared to target the complainant: “In accordance with the principle of management based on ‘the truth of the facts’, the school […] reserves the right to demand legal responsibility against any fabrications of facts, malicious threats or damage to the reputation of the school and employees — ‘the internet is not a lawless space’!”, it was highlighted.
DSEDJ and Coutinho in silence
In light of the accusations and inaction, HM contacted DSEDJ to confirm the existence of a complaint dated 14 October and to obtain a reaction to the fact that the complaint remained without any response until the beginning of November. However, at the closing time of the HM edition, no response had been received.
As the online publication specifically targeted deputy José Pereira Coutinho, HM tried to get a reaction from the legislator. “I don’t know where this invention came from,” replied the deputy. “I don’t make any comments”, he pointed out. “I am very busy serving dozens of citizens every day in our Citizens Assistance Office”, he added.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:48:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | Revenues grow 14% in the third quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/galaxy-receitas-crescem-14-no-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>In the one-year period, Galaxy's net revenues grew 14 percent. Francis Lui, president of the group, pointed out that the third quarter numbers were achieved, despite the casinos being closed for 33 hours
The Galaxy dealership announced an annual increase in net revenues of 14 percent in the third quarter of this year. The data was released yesterday by the concessionaire through a statement.
Between July and September, the company that manages the casino with the same name recorded net revenues of 12.2 billion Hong Kong dollars, which represented growth compared to the value of 10.7 billion Hong Kong dollars allocated in the third quarter of 2024.
When the comparison is made between the second and third quarters of this year, the growth was less significant, just 1 percent, given that between April and June total net revenue was 12.0 billion Hong Kong dollars.
Still in relation to the third quarter, the bulk of the company's revenue founded by Lui Che Woo was due to gaming, which contributed to net revenue with 9.7 billion Hong Kong dollars, while the non-gaming sector brought the company revenues of 1.7 billion dollars. At the same time, Galaxy's building materials segment generated revenues of $727 million, the only segment showing a negative trend.
Over the three months between July and September, adjusted EBITDA (Earnings Before Interest, Taxes, Depreciation and Amortization) reached 3.3 billion Hong Kong dollars. This amount meant an annual increase of 14 percent, but a reduction of 6 percent, compared to the second quarter of this year.
Limited numbers
Reacting to the numbers, in a statement, the president of Galaxy, Francis Lui, stated that revenues were affected by the fact that September is a month traditionally with low revenues and due to the passage of typhoon Ragasa. "The first factor involved seasonality, given that September is normally a calmer month, with many visitors postponing their trips until October, to coincide with Golden Week. The second event was Typhoon Ragasa", he indicated. "The typhoon led the Government to decree the official closure of all casinos for 33 hours. And 33 hours may not seem like a very long period of time, but it causes potential visitors to cancel their planned visits", he added.
At the same time, Lui also addressed the closure of the Waldo casino, which took place on October 31st: "In accordance with Government policies, the Galaxy Group is committed to safeguarding local employment. In addition to being able to maintain the same positions, employees also had the opportunity to explore a variety of career paths, if they so desired, and received support to transition to a new work environment", he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:42:50</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Association calls for more quality jobs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/lag-associacao-pede-mais-emprego-de-qualidade/</link><description>The Choi In Tong Sam Association talks about economic recovery and greater confidence in the Government, but recognizes that there is still a discrepancy between official data and the population's sentiment
With the Lines of Government Action (LAG) to be presented on November 18, the Choi In Tong Sam Association defends the need for the Government to adopt long-term measures to promote economic growth. The position was taken by vice-president Kou Ngon Fong, in statements to the newspaper Exmoo.
From the association leader's perspective, society needs measures to promote the economy, which stimulate sustained growth, instead of the current measures that are essentially limited to relieving the population of the difficulties experienced in recent years.
According to Kou, the economy has “returned to normal” in recent years and there is greater trust among citizens in the Government. However, support, such as the large premium for consumption in community areas, is not enough to promote economic growth. The association therefore calls for more structural measures and points as an example to the increase in the salary of public servants and the minimum wage, which was recently increased by one pataca per hour.
The official also recalled that the number of visitors and revenue from the game exceeded society's expectations, however, residents still suffer the impact of post-pandemic changes in terms of quality of employment and cost of living, because the economic recovery is uneven.
"People do not feel well, even though the unemployment rate is falling, the room for maneuver to implement salary increases for employees is very limited. People looking for jobs also have difficulty finding suitable vacancies or well-paid jobs", said Kou Ngon Fong.
Unrelevant data
The vice-president of the Choi In Tong Sam Association also warned of the fact that there is a large discrepancy between the data published by the Government, which shows an economy increasingly recovering, and the sentiment of residents.
However, Kou Ngon Fong trusts that the Government knows the real situation in society, because it has just collected opinions to prepare the LAG. Regarding the governance guidelines for next year, Kou warned that it was necessary to increase the value of some subsidies and make the conditions for receiving support clearer.
Regarding the financial contribution plan, Kou Ngon Fong revealed that he had received several complaints about the lack of transparency in the implemented rules that require residents to spend 183 days in Macau. The association leader therefore asked the government to be clearer about the criteria applied and to explain them very well publicly.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:39:07</pubDate></item><item><title>New health post in Zone A opened yesterday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/inaugurado-ontem-novo-posto-de-saude-da-zona-a/</link><description>The inauguration ceremony of the new health post in Zone A of the New Urban Landfills took place yesterday, which officially starts operating today. According to a note from the Macau Health Services (SS), this health post has an area of ​​around 1,066 square kilometers and will provide services from Monday to Friday, from 8:30 am to 1:00 pm and from 2:30 pm to 6:00 pm, closing on Saturdays, Sundays and holidays.
It is a family health unit, which provides “holistic, comprehensive, coordinated and continuous medical services that cover the entire life cycle, including health care for children, women and adults in general, unscheduled outpatient consultations, prevention and treatment of chronic diseases, health promotion, general nursing care, vaccinations and provision of basic medicines”.
The SS estimates that the population in Zone A will be 96 thousand people, so, in the first phase of operation, this health post will be equipped with “six health professionals and administrative staff to provide services to the first batch of inhabitants of that area”, and, “in the future, dynamic adjustment [of professionals] will be carried out according to the actual situation”. These explanations were given by Alvis Lo, director of the SS, at the inauguration ceremony of the new health post.
Comprehensive Services
Alvis Lo also declared that the Health Post of Zone A of Novos Urban Landfills is the first public health institution to be opened in UOPG [Operational Planning and Management Unit] East-2, providing “convenient and comprehensive community medical services to residents of the aforementioned Zone”.
The SS director also recalled the existence, throughout the territory, of nine health centers and four posts, including the space opened yesterday. Alvis Lo also highlighted that “today, more than 80 percent of patients with chronic diseases in Macau opt for health centers to receive treatment, which demonstrates that the objective of global health coverage has preliminarily been achieved”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:33:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestine | Pope defends two-state solution when receiving Abbas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/palestina-papa-defende-solucao-de-dois-estados-ao-receber-abbas/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday reiterated his defense of a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, when he received the President of the Palestinian Authority, Mahmud Abbas, for the first time in an audience at the Vatican.
This first meeting between Abbas and Leo XIV since the pope's election in May also served to mark the tenth anniversary of the signing of the Global Agreement between the Vatican and the State of Palestine, in 2015, the year in which the Catholic Church recognized the Palestinian State. “During the cordial talks, the urgent need to provide assistance to the civilian population in Gaza and to put an end to the conflict, seeking a two-state solution, was recognized,” the Vatican said in a statement.
On Wednesday, shortly after arriving in Rome, Abbas went to the Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore for a moment of recollection before the tomb of Pope Francis, who died in April. “I came here because I cannot forget everything he did for the Palestinian people,” he told the press.
The President of the Palestinian Authority, in power in the West Bank, visited the Vatican on several occasions during Francis' pontificate, having, in 2014, planted an olive tree in the Vatican gardens alongside former Israeli head of state Shimon Peres and Pope Francis, as a symbol of peace.
In the last months of his pontificate, the Argentine pope toughened his statements against the Israeli offensive, causing diplomatic tensions with the Israeli embassy.
Pope Leo XIV has also expressed solidarity with the “martyred land” of Gaza on several occasions and denounced the forced displacement of Palestinians, but highlighted that the Vatican cannot comment on the alleged genocide in the enclave. On Friday, Abbas will be received in the early afternoon by the Italian Prime Minister, Giorgia Meloni, at the Chigi Palace, the seat of the Government, in Rome.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:29:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment | Calls for measures to improve access in construction and retail</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/emprego-pedidas-medidas-para-melhorar-acesso-na-construcao-e-no-retalho/</link><description>Deputy Leong Pou U argues, in a statement, that measures are necessary to promote employment in the construction sector. Although the latest employment survey by the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC) shows a drop in the unemployment rate, Leong Pou U warns of the poor employment situation in some economic sectors, such as construction and retail sales. Leong Pou U emphasizes that unemployment mostly originated in these two sectors, according to DSEC data.
In this way, the deputy, linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), argues that the Government must launch specific support measures, to provide a situation of full employment in the construction sector. Leong Pou U talks about the underemployment situation for many workers in this sector, taking into account that both public and private work have suffered reductions, in addition to the fact that salaries have been frozen for many years.
For this reason, the deputy suggests that the Government increases the proportion of workers residing in public works awarded, as well as launching more public works projects.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:36:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Rua dos Mercadores | Traffic prohibited until Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/rua-dos-mercadores-transito-proibido-ate-segunda-feira/</link><description>The traffic ban on Rua dos Mercadores, created due to work being carried out at the site, and which should come to an end today, will have to be extended until Monday. At issue is the “need to cure the paving concrete”, with the closure of Rua dos Mercadores to traffic and the reverse measures on Rua das Estalagens and Rua de Camilo Pessanha remaining until 10pm on Monday.
Regarding the bus service, bus route no. 18 (direction to Rua dos Currais) will temporarily continue without making stops at “Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro/Tai Fung”, “Rua dos Mercadores”, “Rua das Estalagens” and “Rua de Cinco de Outubro”. During this period, the “Ponte 16” or “Rua do Tarrafeiro” stops can be used for entrances and exits.
The work is expected to end on November 27th, as defined since the beginning of the project, related to the underground cable network, “greater than initially planned and required better reorganization”. The third, and final, phase of the works takes place between Tuesday and the 27th of this month, “with the intervention area concentrated predominantly on internal roads in the area, not affecting the original direction of traffic”, describes the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT).</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:54:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Success of “book exchange” leads IC to organize more sessions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/sucesso-de-troca-de-livros-leva-ic-a-organizar-mais-sessoes/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) decided to extend the deadline for carrying out the “Book Exchange” initiative, which covers various activities in the territory's public libraries and community neighborhoods, in order to encourage reading.
According to a statement, the extension of the program is due to the fact that “the activity has been widely acclaimed”, so there will be more sessions on weekends during this month and also in December, in order to “further expand the circulation and sharing of books”.
Therefore, this weekend, Saturday and Sunday, new book exchange sessions will take place at Praça de Luís de Camões, and then at Largo do Lilau on the 27th and 28th of December. These two sessions join those previously scheduled for the Lateral Space of Jardim Cidade das Flores, on the 22nd and 23rd of November. The timing of all sessions is from 12pm to 6pm.
For these sessions, IC describes, “participants only need to take the books that comply with the exchange rules to the staff on site, selecting their favorites and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books”.
Standards to comply with
The rules determine that magazines, leaflets, guides for entering a school, school books, event catalogs, children's books, yearbooks published non-locally, legal books, exam preparation books, books with pornographic and/or violent content, religious books, books without a publishing license or with copyright infringements, books with incomplete or damaged pages, volumes of books belonging to an incomplete collection, books with loose binding, with pages that are easy to separate or with missing pages cannot be exchanged. pages, books with written or scribbled pages and books with more than five copies.
In order to maintain the timeliness and usefulness of the books, science and engineering books published more than five years ago, computer books published more than three years ago, tourist guides published more than two years ago are not accepted. Each person can exchange a maximum of 20 books during the event.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 02:08:29</pubDate></item><item><title>CCM | Opera performance season runs until March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/ccm-temporada-de-espectaculos-de-opera-decorre-ate-marco/</link><description>It is on the 27th of this month that the first cultural initiative integrated into the “1st Season of Chinese Culture Shows” begins. These are “A Gathering of Heroes, Invoking the East Wind and The Huarong Passage”, Chinese opera pieces written by the Chinese National Peking Opera Company. But there are more shows to see until March next year
This week, Tuesday, the program for the “1st Season of Chinese Culture Shows” was presented, an “artistic banquet” promising “excellent shows with diverse experiences”.
The initiative was created from the previous “Season of Performances of National Art Companies in Macau”, with the first performance taking place on November 27th, with the Beijing opera “A Meeting of Heroes. Invoking the East Wind. The Passage of Huarong”, presented in a three and a half hour show by the Chinese National Peking Opera Company, at the Macau Cultural Center (CCM).
According to the official description of the show, main artists Yu Kuizhi and Li Shengsu take to the stage, leading the cast that presents “the Chinese lyrical tradition in all its expressiveness”.
“Three great plays” and “epics taken from the classic Romance of the Three Kingdoms” are presented, with a “mix of singing and theatrical staging, which highlights a perfect balance between civil and military characters, embodied by a series of historical figures”.  On the 28th of this month, it is time to perform, also at CCM, “The Legend of the White Snake”, written by the famous playwright Tian Han and originally directed by the prestigious director Li Zigui.
"This recognized masterpiece has been meticulously refined on stage for more than 60 years. Considered a fundamental work of the operatic repertoire, the piece has been performed by countless generations of 'dan' (female roles) performers", reads the show's description.
On stage, the artists are Li Shengsu, a distinguished representative and defender of the Mei Lanfang school, who is also a mentor to the talented Zhu Fengyi, an artist with whom she shares the main role of Bai Suzhen (Madam White Snake). “In this re-enactment, the performers magnificently portray the unshakable forbidden love that the legendary character has for a mortal, transporting the audience to a mesmerizing dreamlike scenario”, it also reads.
New interpretations
The program for this initiative also includes theatrical performances such as “Goodbye, My Concubine”, performed by the Beijing People's Theatre. It is an adaptation based on the original creation of Nobel Prize winner for Literature Mo Yan, and which has as its backdrop the historical confrontation Chu–Han.
“The play breaks with the traditional narrative structure of historical drama and explores eternal themes such as power, survival and responsibility through multiple encounters and dialogues that cross time and space between consort Yu and Empress Lü”, it can be read.
The performance of the dance theater piece “Mulan”, by the Ningbo Arts and Entertainment Group, is also scheduled. This “main line is filial piety, loyalty, courage and love, combining dance, martial arts, drama and technological elements”.
Groups such as the Chinese Coal Mine Artistic Troupe and the Chinese National Opera will also be invited to carry out exchange performances in various locations in Macau, namely in schools and community neighborhoods. Also noteworthy is the fact that the National Opera of China will return to performances in Macau in January next year to present “Golden Lotus Flowers – Concert of Vocal Works of the National Opera of China” in several schools.
“The concert brings together masterpieces of Chinese and foreign vocal music, with rich musical pieces and exceptional artists, taking students on a musical journey that crosses East and West”, it is said. In total, this first season includes eight exchange presentations and 50 community activities.
“Using Chinese culture as a connecting link, the event aims to create a cultural event that involves the entire population, promote emotional resonance and cultural transmission, working together to build a happy, beautiful and harmonious circle of life,” it is described.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:59:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Death toll rises to 142 after typhoon hits</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/filipinas-sobe-para-142-numero-de-mortos-apos-passagem-de-tufao/</link><description>The number of deaths and missing people caused by Typhoon Kalmaegi continues to rise in the Philippines. Wind gusts reached 180 km/h
At least 142 people died and 127 are missing following Typhoon Kalmaegi's passage through the central Philippines, according to official data compiled today by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
The Philippines' National Department of Civil Defense confirmed 114 deaths, in addition to 28 fatalities recorded by authorities in the province of Cebu, in the center of the country, AFP reported. The previous balance of civil protection in the Philippines showed 85 dead and 75 missing.
In Cebu, dozens of people were trapped on the roofs of homes and called for help as water rose rapidly. The provincial government declared a state of calamity to allow for the urgent mobilization of emergency funds. The province of Cebu, with 2.4 million inhabitants, was still recovering from a 6.9 magnitude earthquake that occurred in September, which caused 79 deaths.
Most of the victims died by drowning or being hit by debris, following flash floods and landslides caused by the Kalmaegi, which also destroyed houses and swept away vehicles, said on Wednesday the deputy head of the Civil Defense Office, Bernardo Rafaelito Alejandro.
Deadly winds
As it passed through the central Philippines, Kalmaegi brought winds of 130 kilometers per hour (km/h) and gusts of up to 180 km/h. The army indicated that six soldiers died when an Air Force helicopter crashed in the province of Agusan del Sur, during a humanitarian aid mission.
More than 387,000 people were evacuated from risk areas and around 3,500 passengers were stranded in almost a hundred ports due to the navigation ban. Local authorities said years of mining and poor drainage work had worsened the impact of the floods.
After crossing the South China Sea, the storm is expected to hit the coast of Vietnam and cause intense rain in northern Thailand, the region's meteorological services said. Every year, around 20 storms or typhoons hit or come close to the Philippines, with the poorest regions of the country generally being the most affected.
State of emergency
The President of the Philippines, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., yesterday declared a state of emergency in the country, after Typhoon Kalmaegi left at least 142 dead and 127 missing, in the worst disaster to hit the country this year. The declaration of a “state of national calamity” was made by Marcos, during a meeting with disaster response authorities, to assess the consequences of the typhoon. The decision allows the Philippine Government to release emergency funds more quickly and avoid food hoarding and price speculation.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP Macau | Government promises to fight the black market</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/gp-macau-governo-promete-lutar-contra-o-mercado-negro/</link><description>The Grand Prix Organizing Committee admitted having created a task team against the sale of tickets on the black market. The revelation was made by Lei Si Leng, president of the Sports Institute and coordinator of the Grand Prix Organizing Committee.
According to the official's statements, new measures were also adopted in the production of tickets, to prevent counterfeiting, and wristbands will be distributed to prevent tickets from being resold after they have been used. “Reselling even just a penny above the purchase price is illegal,” he said.
Lei Si Leng also clarified that people who buy tickets and are unable to attend the races can sell them, as long as they do so at or below the purchase price.
The statements were made on the sidelines of the Pai San Grand Prix ceremony and Lei Si Leng revealed that at this time around 90 percent of tickets have been sold and that tickets for Saturday and Sunday are sold out. In addition, some tickets will be reserved to be sold on the day of the races.
The person in charge also explained that at this stage the circuit is practically assembled and the organization is now ready to start receiving the cars and motorcycles that will participate in the event.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:35:23</pubDate></item><item><title>José Simões Morais</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/jose-sm/</link><description>In Macau, most commercial establishments have the image of Kuan Tai (Guan Di in Mandarin), who appears with a strong body, red face, long black beard and dressed as a military officer, holding a spear in his right hand.
As a person, he is known as Guan Yu and is related to the fall of the Han dynasty and the struggles to establish the Shu kingdom, in the period that preceded the Three Kingdoms. With the name Chang Sheng (长生), he was born in Xiezhou (today Yuncheng, Shanxi province), on the 24th day of the sixth lunar month in the 60s of the 2nd century.
As an episode from his youth, it is said that one day a nobleman forcibly wanted to possess a girl and Guan Yu, outraged, killed him. Pursued by the authorities, he had to flee and according to legend, in order not to be recognized, Guanyin (known in Macau as Kun Iam) changed the color of his face to red.
Another story says that a rural owner with a lot of power, in order to force everyone to buy water from him, polluted the other sources in the region. Saturated with such infamy, Guan Yu one day killed him and had to flee the city. During this flight, to cross the border (guan), he took the name Guan Yu.
In the late Eastern Han dynasty (25-220), the decadent court in Luoyang was dominated by eunuchs and generals. Guan Yu was wandering as a street vendor in Zhuo Municipality (now Hebei Province) when he met Liu Bei and Zhang Fei. The three swore an oath in the Peach Garden to become brothers in arms, with Guan Yu and Zhang Fei vowing to help Liu Bei, linked to the royal house of Han, in his armed uprising to establish the Shu-Han kingdom.
At that time there were two other different factions that divided the country and thus in the North, the Wei army led by Cao Cao dominated, in the East and South the Wu forces and in the West, the Shu. There were constant battles between them.
Guan Yu, an avid reader of the Classic “Spring-Autumn Annals” (Chunqiu jing) who always accompanied him, had commanded the Shu garrison in Jingzhou for 10 years. In the year 219/220, while engaged in a battle outside the wall against the Wei forces, he was caught in a surprise attack by the Wu army, which was more or less allied with the Shu. The Wu conquered the city and killed Guan Yu, cutting off his head and, as a proof of friendship, handing it over to Cao Cao. Halfway there they learned that the Wei had made a peace agreement with the Shu and so the head was abandoned near Luoyang.
The process of his deification was long. Although he was only God of War during the Ming period, when in 1578 Emperor Wan Li gave him the title of Emperor Guan (Guan Di), already in the Sui dynasty he had a temple dedicated to him in the place where he was buried, with the titles being given by all the following dynasties.
During his life, Guan Yu had the position of Military Officer (Hou). In the Song dynasty he took the place of King (Wang). Due to his loyalty, honesty, piety, benevolence, sense of justice and courage, he became very popular due to the book San Guo Yan Yi, written at the beginning of the Ming dynasty. In this dynasty he was promoted to Emperor (Di) and then, in 1614, to Sage (Sheng) or Military Saint (Wu Di). As a Being so perfect, all professions want him as their patron and thus he is venerated as the God of War, Literature, Wealth and patron of Martial Arts.
In Macau, Guan Di is known as Kuan Tai and the Sam Kai Wui Kun temple, located on Rua Sul of the S. Domingos market, is dedicated to him. There, the image of the God is entirely golden, with no objects in his hands and is accompanied on his left by Chau Chong and on the other side by Kuan Peng. His birthday falls on the 24th of the sixth lunar month, although no festivities are officially held in his honor.
灶神 Zao Shen – the god of the Stove
The god of the Stove, known in Macau as Tchôu-Sân (in Mandarin Zao Shen), is the most important of the domestic deities and twice a month (during the New Moon and the Full Moon) he received offerings, despite his birthday only being celebrated on the third day of the eighth Moon. However, the most important ceremonies performed to this god are those that occur before the week-long journey, when the god leaves home and goes to Heaven to perform the annual report to the Jade Emperor about the family of the residence where he is placed. And that is why this god, also known as the god of the Kitchen, as for simplification he came to be called the god of the Kitchen Chimney, has great power over the lives of the people who form the household. It is in the last week of the lunar year that he ascends to Heaven to meet with the Jade Emperor, where he reports to him the events that took place in the room in his charge, returning on the first day of the year, where he is placed again in the kitchen, behind the stove.
On the eve of the trip, on the twenty-third day of the last lunar month, the inhabitants of the house offer sacrifices to this deity, filling him with sweets so that he only tells good things to the Jade Emperor.
In a ceremony performed only by men, the god of Stove leaves transported on a horse and to make the journey easy and pleasant, one of the male beings in the house takes a candle and burns the image of the god so that it can more easily ascend through smoke to Heaven.
Before being named by the Jade Emperor as God of the Stove, or of the Kitchen, he was a husband who, having spent all his money gambling and selling his wife, years later, while begging on the streets, arrived at his former wife's house. She, recognizing him and taking pity on him, takes him to the kitchen where she gives him something to eat. But her current husband arrives and so she doesn't see him, she hides him in the fireplace. When the maid lights the fire, so as not to compromise the charitable woman, she stays there. The Jade Emperor, seeing his sacrifice, named him the god of the Stove, also known as the god of the Kitchen, or the god of the Home.
There are other versions of both how the man lost the money and how his ex-wife supported him. She, without being recognized by her ex-husband, gave him some cakes and placed a coin in each one. The man, on the way, met another beggar, who, upon seeing the bag with cakes, asked him for one. He discovered the coin in the middle of the cake and, realizing that the other didn't know about the filling, proposed keeping them all, which he managed in exchange for a small amount. When he later found out what he had done, realizing his bad luck, he decided to commit suicide. The Jade Emperor, seeing his kindness, named him god of the Kitchen.
The celebration of this deity's journey to Heaven began in summer, but during the Han dynasty it moved to winter and during the Ming dynasty it was celebrated by the people on the 24th, with sacrifices taking place the day before. Zao Shen is represented in an image containing only his figure, or associated with his consort, or even just characters, which is placed on the first day of the lunar year in the kitchen behind the stove.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Sesshu Toyo (c.1420-1506), the Japanese painter monk who adheres to Chan Buddhism, after years of training in the Hofuku-ji temples and especially in Shokoku-ji, where he studied with the master Tensho Shubun, enters the service of a powerful clan of merchants that allow him to travel to the Celestial Empire.
There you will get to know the centuries-old and exceptional art of painting up close and its sources of inspiration. The Ming dynasty was reigning when he disembarked in the city of Ningbo (Zhejiang) where, since the Song and Yuan dynasties, came many paintings admired in Buddhist temples in Japan. During the three years of his stay between 1467-69, he was allowed to travel to Beijing through the admirable landscapes featured in the works of so many painters.
But he soon found reasons for inspiration in the coastal city of “serene waves” of Ningbo, where professional painters achieved great success in the huaniao hua genre, “painting of flowers and birds”. His knowledge he would display in paintings of meticulous descriptive realism, such as the triptych Flowers and Birds (each ink and color on silk, 55.9 x 53.4 cm, at the Cleveland Museum of Art).
Among these professional painters was one, born in Siming District, who would be immensely recognized named Lu Ji (c. 1429-1505). After being welcomed by a patron, the politician Yuan Zhongche (1377-1459), his talent was recognized, and he was called to the court of Emperor Chenghua (r. 1465-87), but it would be from the following Emperor Hongzhi (r. 1488-1505) that he would receive the qualification of "moral, just and reverent", words that together with those later written by Li Mengyang (1473-1529) in a poem, would reveal the constancy of his upright character: «Lu Ji, with white hair, had a golden incense burner by his side, but at the end of the day he returned home without money to buy wine.»
If posterity kept these words it was because historians of painting have always highlighted the moral character of its cultivators, only then able to relate to the world of Creation.
Lu Ji would carefully study paintings by old masters in the Birds and Flowers category such as Huang Quan (903-65) but also landscapes such as Ma Yuan and Xia Gui, from the Song dynasty. What can be seen in Autumn Landscape with Herons and Ducks (vertical scroll, ink and color on silk, 147.6 x 54.6 cm, at the Metmuseum) in which the monumental scenery overlaps the figures.
In other scrolls, one can notice the taste for symbolic play between figures and words, as in Mandarin ducks and hibiscus rosa sinensis (ink and color on silk, 172.7 x 99.1 cm, at the Metmuseum). By the end of the 15th century, paintings bearing Lu Ji's name appeared in the market by the hundreds. This led some to consider them works “of the hand, not of the heart” but it was necessary to know it like the emperor did or like Sesshu who, to know the art, went to know the people.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ana Cristina Alves</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>By Ana Cristina Alves – Assistant Researcher and Coordinator of the Educational Service of the Scientific and Cultural Center
The image that the Portuguese have of themselves as a whole collective differs internally and externally, according to the thinkers and their ways of being in life, which in turn depend on broader cultural frameworks, their own collectivities. It is not expected that a Frenchman's view of the Portuguese and Portugal will be similar to that of a Chinese person, much less that of a Portuguese person, because their perspectives are conditioned by their historical-cultural development, which will define a specific civilizational stance for each thinker and their personal and collective life history. Furthermore, a foreigner's view of Portugal will always be more distant, for better or for worse, than a Portuguese person's close and committed view to the deepest roots of his being, even if he seeks to be as impartial as possible, as is the case of Miguel Torga, a writer and thinker who loved his country very much, but always in the middle, without letting himself be carried away by romantic and nationalist feelings, for example of Teixeira de Pascoes in The Art of Being Portuguese.
Start with external views, those that reach us from beyond the Portuguese sea. Start with the very recent text Astérix na Lusitânia from October 2025 by Fabcaro with drawings by Didier Conrad, impeccably translated into Portuguese by Maria José Pereira and Paula Caetano.
The compatriots, the “pá” people, who oscillate in the book between slang and the lyrical features of Portuguese fado, in the best that Amália has to offer, are presented in a critical and ironic way, sometimes scathing, in a tone coming from the French comic and rationalist school, which says what it thinks, because that is how it exists without worrying about the consequences that its open, frontal and critical thinking may have on the Portuguese people who will read these lines in band. drawn, many of them truly comical, but which certainly reach the emotional and nervous chords of the great heroes of the Lusitanian sea.
Those in a better mood will take advantage of the pretext to laugh at themselves, while the more serious and sullen will have some difficulty digesting the comic strip, whose main feature is playing around the Portuguese sea, but gastronomically. The Portuguese stand out in the work for their taste for fish and fish sauces, being monotonously excellent in the thousand and one ways of preparing cod, which leads, obviously, to the despair of the illustrious Gallic Obélix, who finds himself surrounded by cod and fish sauce (garum) everywhere. Astérix and Obélix come on a mission to Portugal to help free Malmevês, a Portuguese man sentenced to prison for allegedly trying to poison Caesar with garum. They were called by a Portuguese character, whose name is highly revealing, Tristês. Meanwhile, Malmevês has a daughter, with another symptomatic name, Saudade, with whom Obeléx falls in love.
The Lusitanians are left with sadness, longing and melancholy and are not indebted to their beauty, and it is with great regret that the Gauls will have to disguise themselves as Lusitanians to save Malmevês from prison, with the successful mission aided by Gallic intelligence that unmasks the real poisoner and his accomplice.
Although the Portuguese are not presented as beautiful, intelligent, and some have little ethics, because they betrayed the hero of heroes, Viriato, their most positive aspects include interesting cuisine, with the exception of cod and fish sauce, but which includes pastel de nata and good wine, even green wine. Cuisine is undoubtedly the highlight of the narrative, from all perspectives, even that of the Discoveries, which are reduced and condensed in a reference to Vasco da Gama's Tasco “Oh Man, in Vasco da Gama's Tasco you discover new worlds” (Fabcaro, 2025, 36).
The fact that the Portuguese love fado so much makes the atmosphere very sad for Gallic ears, who weave interesting philosophical considerations throughout the text about it, as it is considered to take away soul strength from Portuguese soldiers and people, who in the heat of the battle are appeased by the doleful and sad song that makes the warriors like this: “I suddenly became so melancholy” (Fabcaro, 2025, 28) or “after all, what do we spend our lives chasing after?” (Ibidem). In short, from this comic we take a look at our collective portrait, a sad and melancholic people, very marked by long years of repression, in which the revolutionaries find themselves in jail, like the one who shouts from behind bars "oh man, listen carefully, damned Romans! The united people will never be defeated." (Fabcaro, 2025, 33).
There are true women in arms like Gama in Lusitânia, when it is said, “it would be impossible to carry out the mission without Gama’s help” (Fabcaro, 2025, 47). Finally, the Gallic heroes leave for Gaul, retaining another characteristic that is usually highlighted in relation to the Portuguese, the smoothness of their relationship: "Ah, these Lusitanians! They are so affable to deal with...it's hard to have to leave, isn't it?" (Fabcaro, 2025, 48).
The comical philosophical image of this comic cannot be generalized to all French people, but what remains for some is that the illustrious and ancient Portuguese history can be summed up in a remarkable gastronomic heroism, represented by a strong woman, Gama, at the head of Tasco Vasco da Gama and as long as she is at the helm, new worlds of flavor will always be discovered. From the Gallic point of view, so much melancholy and sadness are unnecessary, but in the midst of this “strange way of being” there is an affability that leaves us missing the land and wanting to return.
Due to the characteristics of the Chinese mentality, shaped by centuries of Confucian harmony, one cannot expect the same type of open, free, critical record from a Chinese thinker. On the contrary, the descriptions will be carefully chosen so as not to offend other people's sensibilities, as is the case in the work of the thinker and historian Wu Zhiliang (吴志良), Crónicas de Portugal 葡萄牙印象, the result of the author's stay as a student at the country in 1991. Therefore, and recalling an idea with which the article opened, the reflections of a thinker or creative are conditioned by their own way of seeing that is inserted and rooted in their culture.
For Wu Zhiliang, the Portuguese are still the descendants of the sea heroes who arrived in China and Macau, fearlessly crossing the Atlantic, Indian and Pacific oceans and, in our days, they are the great drivers of the cultural dialogue of the 16th century, providing a meeting of cultures that was extremely beneficial for the Chinese, because it opened them to other worlds, awakening them to a way that is complementary to the Chinese, which he describes as submissive and peaceful. What is most valued in the introduction and conclusion of the successive portraits of Portugal provided by these Chronicles are the new characteristics that the Chinese and other Eastern peoples are confronted with in their relationship with the Portuguese, above all, the active, restless and restless spirit, which crossed "the magic of Allah with the Indian Bodhisattvas, the Chinese Tao and Japanese meditation with the totally restless spirit of the West. At the source of the discovering, spiritualized and empty force, East and the West converge into one in this humble and silent “void”, the root of all things that transforms into an immense and infinite freedom.騷動的精神，來發現力的本源，在那裡，神意味着虛無。在這力的源泉中，東西方交融在一處，我們在“無”這個萬物之本的謙卑和寂寞中，變得無比自由。》(Wu, 1991,1/ 2).
Wu Zhiliang emphasizes throughout the work and, also in the final notes, that the various meetings, including academic ones, provided by institutions in the territory of Macau are an invaluable contribution to friendship and cultural dialogue, this being the correct perspective from the author's point of view to evaluate the role of the Portuguese in the world, which in contemporary times still goes back to its great historical past, much like what happens to Portuguese thinkers and writers, even the most impartial, as is the case of Miguel Torga (1907-1995).
This writer born in São Martinho de Anta, a doctor by profession, knows his people well, their joys and sadness, riches, miseries and overcoming. In a very well-executed portrait of the country in Salazar times, Portugal writes, the first edition of which dates back to Coimbra in 1950, assuming very clear perspectives in relation to the Portuguese historical past at home and beyond its borders. Behind the borders dominates the maritime, versatile, cosmopolitan and adventurous capital of Lisbon against the telluric city of Porto, realistic and focused on its roots. Throughout the work, he weaves timely and incisive considerations about the Portuguese mentality, which lead to an image that today perhaps resonates with adventurous people in the character of the soap opera Senhor Ventura, a work dated 1991. This one takes us to China.
Returning to Portugal, the author debuts the work in Minho where he makes considerations about the way in which the impoverished Portuguese relate to the life of the sea and emigration: "From time to time he may have a fit of rage and try to escape from himself. A hopeless illusion. Where he arrives will always be him, dying of homesickness and dreaming of returning to the adventure with a small reform. As a balm, he will be left with the narcissism of his exploits past experiences and the somatic satisfaction of seeing the worlds he discovered and civilized grow and progress.” (Torga, 2003, 17). Many were emigrants from the old regime who left just like today: the difference is that today they are much better prepared and educated. The Portuguese who emigrate are, for the most part, qualified professionals holding various degrees and national diplomas, boasting solid training and a desire for the rest of the world.
But if people have evolved in social terms, their mentality has not changed that much in terms of the way they relate to their historical past, nor in the taste for risk and adventure that drives them out of the country. The hope will always be that of a better life, although the steps to achieve it are not always well measured. When the author describes Trás-os-Montes, his birthplace, he tells us about the emigrants "Haunted by necessity and the love of adventure, at the age of twenty (if it was not earlier), after militancy, some emigrate to the Arabian overseas. Brazil, Africa and Oceania, they put the whole chimera in a bag of scraps and off they go" (Torga, 2003, 50).
This is a trait of the Portuguese mentality that has remained in a constant regime since the Discoveries, the desire and need to leave not only due to lack of opportunities, but also due to the thirst for adventure, as well as the naturalness of miscegenation, which can be seen in the capital of Portugal since the times of “Dona Filipa de Lencastre giving birth on behalf of the Portuguese herd from abroad” (Torga, 2003, 77), or even further, since the very foundation of the land. derived from the energy of a son of a French father and a Spanish mother.
However, the greatest danger for Portugal and the community as a whole is, according to Torga's perspective, wasting the soul strength of the Portuguese and their characteristics on inconsequential adventures that can contribute nothing to their individual life projects and/or the common good, but which we narcissistically insist on reliving. He tells us about Lisbon "Narcissus that we were also one day, a destiny like that of Cephisus's son awaited us. Lisbon is that flower that destiny transformed us into; the Tagus, the river where we lost ourselves contemplating our own image" (Torga, 2003, 136).
It is precisely this mix of pride, vanity and initiative that the work O Senhor Ventura shows. The protagonist is a man from Penedono, in Alentejo, but with multiple resources and capable of taking on any work. With a powerful and bullish constitution, after an adventurous experience of military service that led him to Macau and a short romance with Júlia, the daughter of the Governor's secretary, he deserted the army and joined the world as a sailor aboard a ship doing cabotage in the China Sea. From there he became an employee in a Ford garage in Beijing, where he befriended Pereira, a man from Minho who cooked very well, and he was his companion on adventures until his death. However, Ventura falls into the good graces of Ford's boss, Mr. Hughes, for being “a man of pulse and initiative” (Torga, 2003, 26). In life, he did a bit of everything, trafficking drugs and weapons, being a pirate, kidnapping, driving 200 trucks to Mongolia and, to his misfortune, he fell in love with a Russian woman with an unrecommended life, Tatiana. Although warned, even by himself, because the couple got along very badly, he wanted to marry her, with whom he had a son, Sérgio. It was then that he decided to get rich by getting involved in drug trafficking, more specifically heroin. This new branch of activity went badly for him, he was discovered by the Chinese authorities and he had to return to Portugal, leaving his son in the care of his wife, who betrayed him as soon as she turned her back. He returned to Alentejo within a period of 5 years so that the Chinese authorities would forget about the matter.
Anyway, he was in Portugal and returned to China when he discovered that his wife had cheated on him. He looked for her everywhere until, already dying, she was the one who found him to close his eyes on his deathbed. The word that best characterizes Mr. Ventura is, according to the author, “Action – was his great word.” (Torga, 2003,64).
The writer is careful to warn about this story: “at each stop I do nothing more than try a small meditation on destiny, which is more collective than individual” (Torga, 2003, 70), adding that the fact that the Alentejo native is returning to the land is an imperative call from destiny, to put him back in touch with his roots, in a new opportunity for life. The protagonist rejects the chance, due to the obsession he felt with his Russian passion and which will lead him to death, ending the author with the following reflection: “Strange hands buried the poor adventurer's withered body the next day in the foreign land where he had to pay the price for his adventures.” (Torga, 2003, 100).
Of the two foreign and most distant images from the Portuguese, one critical and playful by the hands of the French artist Fabrice Caro (Fabcaro), another uplifting and very positive transmitted by the Chinese thinker, Wu Zhiliang, to which is added a third, more realistic and closer transmitted by the Portuguese writer, it cannot be concluded that there is just one true one. The collective portrait can only be obtained together and in a kind of Nietzschean perspectivism from the essential traits of the contemporary Portuguese mentality, shaped, as the French artist saw well, by centuries of erasure, but also by the awareness of the glorious exploits of an intercultural past that continues to the present, according to Wu Zhiliang, or even by the thirst for action and adventure which, when not properly structured and rooted in solid individual and collective plans, can lead to a inopportune dead end.
Bibliographic References
Fabcaro, 2025. Asterix in Lusitânia. Translated by Maria José Pereira and Paula Caetano. Drawings by Didier Conrad. Color by Thierry Mébarki. Alfragide: Asa Editions.
Torga, Miguel. 2003. Portugal. Lisbon: Heirs of Miguel Torga José Manuel Rodrigues and Publicações Dom Quixote.
Torga, Miguel. 1991. Senhor Ventura. Coimbra: Circle of Readers
Wu Zhiliang (吴志良). 1991. Chronicles of Portugal 葡萄牙印象Macau: World Association for Cultural and Artistic Exchanges (Macau) with the sponsorship of Fundação Oriente and Fundação Macau.
This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center, in Lisbon, and the opinions expressed in the article are the sole responsibility of the authors. https://www.cccm.gov.pt</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Sesshu Toyo (c.1420-1506), the Japanese painter monk who adheres to Chan Buddhism, after years of training in the Hofuku-ji temples and especially in Shokoku-ji, where he studied with the master Tensho Shubun, enters the service of a powerful clan of merchants that allow him to travel to the Celestial Empire.
There you will get to know the centuries-old and exceptional art of painting up close and its sources of inspiration. The Ming dynasty was reigning when he disembarked in the city of Ningbo (Zhejiang) where, since the Song and Yuan dynasties, came many paintings admired in Buddhist temples in Japan. During the three years of his stay between 1467-69, he was allowed to travel to Beijing through the admirable landscapes featured in the works of so many painters.
But he soon found reasons for inspiration in the coastal city of “serene waves” of Ningbo, where professional painters achieved great success in the huaniao hua genre, “painting of flowers and birds”. His knowledge he would display in paintings of meticulous descriptive realism, such as the triptych Flowers and Birds (each ink and color on silk, 55.9 x 53.4 cm, at the Cleveland Museum of Art).
Among these professional painters was one, born in Siming District, who would be immensely recognized named Lu Ji (c. 1429-1505). After being welcomed by a patron, the politician Yuan Zhongche (1377-1459), his talent was recognized, and he was called to the court of Emperor Chenghua (r. 1465-87), but it would be from the following Emperor Hongzhi (r. 1488-1505) that he would receive the qualification of "moral, just and reverent", words that together with those later written by Li Mengyang (1473-1529) in a poem, would reveal the constancy of his upright character: «Lu Ji, with white hair, had a golden incense burner by his side, but at the end of the day he returned home without money to buy wine.»
If posterity kept these words it was because historians of painting have always highlighted the moral character of its cultivators, only then able to relate to the world of Creation.
Lu Ji would carefully study paintings by old masters in the Birds and Flowers category such as Huang Quan (903-65) but also landscapes such as Ma Yuan and Xia Gui, from the Song dynasty. What can be seen in Autumn Landscape with Herons and Ducks (vertical scroll, ink and color on silk, 147.6 x 54.6 cm, at the Metmuseum) in which the monumental scenery overlaps the figures.
In other scrolls, one can notice the taste for symbolic play between figures and words, as in Mandarin ducks and hibiscus rosa sinensis (ink and color on silk, 172.7 x 99.1 cm, at the Metmuseum). By the end of the 15th century, paintings bearing Lu Ji's name appeared in the market by the hundreds. This led some to consider them works “of the hand, not of the heart” but it was necessary to know it like the emperor did or like Sesshu who, to know the art, went to know the people.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday reiterated his defense of a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, when he received the President of the Palestinian Authority, Mahmud Abbas, for the first time in an audience at the Vatican.
This first meeting between Abbas and Leo XIV since the pope's election in May also served to mark the tenth anniversary of the signing of the Global Agreement between the Vatican and the State of Palestine, in 2015, the year in which the Catholic Church recognized the Palestinian State. “During the cordial talks, the urgent need to provide assistance to the civilian population in Gaza and to put an end to the conflict, seeking a two-state solution, was recognized,” the Vatican said in a statement.
On Wednesday, shortly after arriving in Rome, Abbas went to the Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore for a moment of recollection before the tomb of Pope Francis, who died in April. “I came here because I cannot forget everything he did for the Palestinian people,” he told the press.
The President of the Palestinian Authority, in power in the West Bank, visited the Vatican on several occasions during Francis' pontificate, having, in 2014, planted an olive tree in the Vatican gardens alongside former Israeli head of state Shimon Peres and Pope Francis, as a symbol of peace.
In the last months of his pontificate, the Argentine pope toughened his statements against the Israeli offensive, causing diplomatic tensions with the Israeli embassy.
Pope Leo XIV has also expressed solidarity with the “martyred land” of Gaza on several occasions and denounced the forced displacement of Palestinians, but highlighted that the Vatican cannot comment on the alleged genocide in the enclave. On Friday, Abbas will be received in the early afternoon by the Italian Prime Minister, Giorgia Meloni, at the Chigi Palace, the seat of the Government, in Rome.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Pop Mart, maker of Labubu, falls 10.8% in Hong Kong amid doubts about growth</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/24/pop-mart-fabricante-de-labubu-cai-108-em-hong-kong-entre-duvidas-sobre-crescimento/</link><description>Shares in Pop Mart, the Chinese company responsible for the global phenomenon of Labubu figures, sank 10.8% this Thursday, the biggest drop since April, in a new episode of volatility that contrasts with the good sales results released the day before.
The devaluation reflects investors' growing caution regarding the possibility of a slowdown in the company's growth, after several quarters driven by the popularity of its collectible products.
On Wednesday, Pop Mart shares rose 4.23% on the Hong Kong stock exchange, despite the negative tone of the market, following the announcement that revenue in the third quarter increased between 245% and 250%, driven by Labubu's virality on social media and the company's international expansion.
According to data provided by the company, domestic sales grew 190%, while international sales soared 370%, highlighted by increases of 175% in the Asia-Pacific region, more than 740% in Europe and almost 1,270% in the United States. The strong drop recorded today is largely attributed to profit taking, after appreciation of more than 186% since the beginning of the year, and uncertainty about the sustainability of the current growth rate.
The stock fell 8.1% on Tuesday, its worst performance since April, weighed down by fears of a slowdown in sales after months of euphoria. The preliminary release of results helped to temporarily dispel these concerns, but the absence of an official date for the presentation of the accounts maintains uncertainty regarding the company's future evolution. Executive chairman and founder Wang Ning expressed confidence in the long-term resilience of the Labubu character, arguing that cultural icons continue to generate revenue even after peak popularity.
According to the Bloomberg agency, the explosion in demand forced the company itself to revise its internal goals upwards. If at the beginning of 2024 Pop Mart predicted a turnover of 2,800 million dollars (around 2,400 million euros), in August Wang raised this target to 4,200 million dollars (3,600 million euros), pointing to the brand's global momentum as a key factor.
Founded in Beijing in 2010, Pop Mart has established itself as one of the main Asian references in the toy and collectible figures sector, combining exclusive design, limited editions and collaborations with international brands, artists and franchises.
Its business model is based on so-called “surprise boxes”, which encourage repeat purchases and have created a community of fans willing to pay high premiums for rare pieces. Among its main lines is Labubu, a monster with pointy ears and a mischievous smile inspired by Norse mythology, created by Hong Kong artist Lung Ka-sing in 2015 and integrated into the company's portfolio in 2019.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Louvre | France to reinforce security at cultural sites after theft</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/21/louvre-franca-vai-reforcar-seguranca-de-locais-culturais-apos-roubo/</link><description>The French Minister of Internal Affairs, Laurent Nuñez, will reinforce security measures in all cultural establishments, the press office announced yesterday, following a jewelry theft at the Louvre Museum in Paris. The decision was taken after a meeting with his government colleague in charge of Culture, Rachida Dati, said the same ministerial source, cited by the French news agency AFP.
The institution, in the center of the French capital, remained closed yesterday, one day after a group, still at large, managed to steal multiple works of jewelry art. "The Louvre Museum will remain closed today (yesterday) for exceptional reasons. We apologize for the inconvenience", read a message published on the museum's official website.
A group of four men stole jewelry on Sunday morning, in just a few minutes and when the museum was already open and with visitors inside, using a forklift machine, parked on the respective bank of the River Seine, and raising it to the height of a window on the first floor of the building.
The group took eight pieces “of inestimable heritage value”, including the tiara of Empress Eugenie (wife of Napoleon III, emperor from 1852 to 1870) and two necklaces, the French Ministry of Culture reported on Sunday. That jewel alone has 212 pearls and 1,998 diamonds, according to the Louvre's description, while the pieces belonging to Queen Maria Amélia have multiple sapphires and hundreds of diamonds.
This Parisian museum is the largest and most visited in the world, with nine million people enjoying part of the 35,000 works that the institution houses, in its 73 thousand square meters of space.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 01:53:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuts leave 13.7 million people at risk of extreme hunger</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/16/cortes-levam-137-milhoes-de-pessoas-a-correr-risco-de-fome-extrema/</link><description>Cuts in humanitarian aid funding could expose up to 13.7 million people to extreme hunger around the world, the World Food Program (WFP) warned yesterday. “The humanitarian aid system is under severe pressure as partners withdraw from frontline areas, creating a void,” the Rome-based agency said in a new report titled “A lifebuoy in danger.”
The UN agency said that six of its operations – in Afghanistan, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Haiti, Somalia, South Sudan and Sudan – are “facing major disruptions, which will only worsen”. WFP warned that its financing “has never been so challenging”, anticipating “a 40 percent drop” in 2025, “which will translate into a projected budget of US$6.4 billion, compared to US$10 billion in 2024”.
The report does not name any countries, but points to a study published in the medical journal The Lancet, which found that 14 million additional deaths worldwide from disease, nutritional deficiencies and maternal and perinatal conditions could occur by 2030 as a result of cuts in US humanitarian aid alone.
Returns and records
Since US President Donald Trump's return to the White House, Washington has announced massive cuts in its foreign aid, dealing a huge blow to humanitarian operations around the world. "Program coverage has been significantly reduced and rations cut. Vital assistance to families in food disaster situations [Phase 5 of the Integrated Food Security Phase Classification/IPC] is threatened, while preparedness for future impacts has significantly decreased," warns WFP.
Globally, “WFP estimates that its funding gaps could push 10.5 to 13.7 million people currently in acute food insecurity (IPC Phase 3) into a humanitarian emergency (IPC Phase 4),” the organization added. The UN agency said global hunger has now reached record levels, with 319 million people facing acute food insecurity — including 44 million at emergency levels.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 02:52:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela | Maduro declares that country will never be defeated</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/05/venezuela-maduro-declara-que-pais-jamais-sera-derrotado/</link><description>The President of Venezuela declared yesterday that the country will never be defeated and that the Venezuelan people will respond to what he considered to be a psychological war orchestrated by the United States.
Speaking to the official Venezuelan television station VTV, Nicolás Maduro stated that the authorities and people of Venezuela will respond with work and achievements to the “psychological war”, referring to the North American Administration as “media scoundrels” from Miami. “How do you say ‘imbecile’ in English?” asked Maduro, warning those “who want to do harm” will never be able to defeat Venezuela.
Washington has intensified military operations off Venezuela in recent days, reiterating accusations against Maduro that he promotes drug trafficking.
The North American head of state, Donald Trump, also authorized new attacks against vessels, allegedly belonging to drug trafficking networks, near the Venezuelan coast. Maduro added that Venezuelan security forces have seized 63 tons of drugs since the beginning of the year.
On the other hand, the Venezuelan leader also denounced the attempt to enter Venezuela by two planes linked to drug trafficking. In the same speech, Maduro declared that Venezuela and Russia are making progress in military cooperation, which he described as peaceful and fruitful.
Daily contact
Asked about contacts between Caracas and Moscow in the context of “threats” from the United States, Maduro stated that the government maintains daily communication with Russian President Vladimir Putin on “several developing issues”, including military matters.
On Sunday, the Russian Presidency admitted having maintained contacts with Venezuela regarding a possible request for help from Maduro to Putin. At the same time, the People's Republic of China stated that there is normal cooperation between Beijing and Caracas.
The North American newspaper Washington Post reported that the Venezuelan President asked Russia, China and Iran for help to defend the country from pressure from the United States. Para Pequim, trata-se de uma cooperação entre Estados soberanos e que não é dirigida contra terceiros.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said at a press conference that China supports strengthening international cooperation to combat “transnational crime” and opposes the use or threat of such force in international relations.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:37:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Death | António Coelho dies aged 77, but leaves a legacy in Portuguese gastronomy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/14/obito-antonio-coelho-morre-com-77-anos-mas-deixa-legado-na-gastronomia-portuguesa/</link><description>The founder of Restaurante António died on Sunday in Macau, due to heart problems. Behind him, he leaves a mark and an innovative concept for promoting Portuguese food in Asia
A father, a friend and one of the great ambassadors of Portuguese gastronomy in Asia. Chef António Coelho died on Sunday, aged 77, due to heart problems, but leaves behind a professional career spanning almost 40 years and an influence that can be felt in several restaurants and Portuguese food chefs in Macau.
Born in Portugal in 1948, António Coelho's first contact with Macau took place in 1970, when he had to complete his four-year mandatory military service. After two years, the land remained in his memory, but the future chef chose to return to Europe.
In Portugal, he started working at Social Security, later moving to a clinical analysis laboratory. It was in this area that he developed his taste for gastronomy, not through work, but through various lunches and dinners in different restaurants. Increasingly interested in cooking, António decided to take a job, in 1984, in a restaurant, where he admitted to having learned to cook, according to an interview with the South China Morning Post newspaper, in 2018.
The first years of António Coelho's new career were spent in Portugal, where he performed different roles as manager-administrator of the Botequim do Rei restaurant or director of the catering department at the Grande Hotel da Curia. In 1996, he had his first international experience, as director of the restaurant department at the Hotel Trópico, in Cape Verde. The experience lasts one year.
Creating a legacy
Returning to Macau in 1997, António worked for 10 years in different spaces, such as the restaurants Frol de la Mar, Lusitano, Lisbon, and also had a brief stay in Hong Kong, in 2002, at Restaurante Inn. However, the decisive step towards his affirmation as one of the most influential chefs of Portuguese gastronomy in Asia came in 2007, with the opening of Restaurante António.
And the success that followed was not the result of chance, as said by Edgar Rodrigues, a chef who came to Macau to work on the launch of the project: “The success was based on the recipes, the quality of the food, but also the very professionalism”, says Edgar Rodrigues, to HM. "He was very attentive to his customers. If there was an order for clams à bolhão pato, he would have different recipes adapted to the nationality. For example, Koreans don't like coriander, the recipe for them didn't have coriander. Chinese customers like little salt, they were served with little salt, and locals like the more traditional recipe. In a single dish there were several ways of cooking, just to satisfy different customers", he recalls.
Cristiano Tavares, currently chef at the Macalhau restaurant, also came to Macau to work at the António Restaurant. He believes that the chef found a position for Portuguese food that still influences other restaurants today. “I think his success was due to his way of being, he was a politically correct person, he had a way of working that pleased both Chinese, Korean and Japanese tourists”, explained Cristiano Tavares, to HM. "We were a street restaurant with four or five cooks. He managed to do what many large restaurants still cannot do today. Nowadays there are many restaurants with Portuguese food that open in Macau, but follow the example of what he did", he considered.
Quality and spectacle
In addition to the food, Restaurante António customers were seduced by the “show”. This is the vision of Marcelino Marques, António's friend and musician who for several years livened up the space's nights, with traditional Portuguese music.
"The quality of the food made the space popular. He took great care in choosing the food and drinks served. He went to Portugal to choose wines from various regions, such as Douro or Alentejo, all of high quality, which were bottled under the António brand. People knew they weren't going to pay little, not that it was a space with luxury prices, it wasn't, but the quantity served wasn't small", recalled Marcelino Marques.
However, the musician believes that the success was also due to a concept in which the meal was also a spectacle: "People liked listening to Portuguese music, but also being with António. He was an affable, big person and appeared in that white jacket with the flags of Portugal, China and Macau and people liked his presence and asked him to take photographs", he says. "He also opened a bottle of champagne with a sword. He did a whole ceremony and people really liked it. It was a spectacle and a party to see the cork flying out of the bottle. It worked well", he recalled.
Marcelino Marques recalls that the food and the show made the restaurant very famous, especially among Japanese, Korean and Hong Kong tourists. The musician reveals that Japanese tourists booked days in advance. And this factor also contributed to the fact that António offered a glass of port wine at the end of the meal, which also led to the recognition of the Port Wine Confraternity.
The success of Restaurante António led the chef to sell the space to an investment fund, becoming an ambassador for the space. The break with the fund happened in 2020, when he was fired without just cause. The case ended up in court, with António winning the case. In recent years, António took on the position of executive chef at Angela’s Café and Lounge, at the Hotel Lisboeta.
A father, a friend
Due to his work in Macau, António was distinguished, in 2013, by the Macao SAR Government with the MSAR Tourist Merit Medal. Also in 2015, he received the merit medal for Portuguese communities from the Portuguese Government. However, for those who worked with him the most important thing was the relationship that went beyond the strictly professional field.
"He had a big impact on Macau and for me he was like a second father. When I came to Macau I didn't have an easy life and he always held my hand", confessed Rodrigues. "He was always a person who was there for me. And I always saw him as a man of iron. In everything he did, there was a great will", he pointed out.
This is a feeling shared by Cristiano Tavares. "António is my father in Macau. He worked until the last day, always with seriousness, honesty and integrity. He is an example for all the chefs in this area", he said.
For Marcelino Marques, António's death is the loss of a friend. "António was the person who welcomed me to Macau and was capable of doing the same to everyone. He was strict and demanding, but he was an excellent person", he described. "Everyone knew him. He was an affable person and received people like no one else", he added.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Chemistry | Nobel Prize for the development of metal-organic structures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/quimica-nobel-para-o-desenvolvimento-de-estruturas-metalorganicas/</link><description>The Nobel Prize in Chemistry was awarded to Susumu Kitagawa, from Kyoto University, Richard Robson, from the University of Melbourne, and Omar M. Yaghi, from the University of California, “for the development of metal-organic structures”, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences announced yesterday.
Susumu Kitagawa, Richard Robson and Omar Yaghi have developed a new form of molecular architecture – metal-organic frameworks – that can be used to collect water from desert air, capture carbon dioxide, store toxic gases or catalyze chemical reactions.
The three laureates created molecular constructs with large spaces through which gases and other chemicals could flow. The president of the Nobel Committee for Chemistry, Heiner Linque, highlighted precisely the fact that these “metal-organic structures have enormous potential, bringing previously unforeseen opportunities for personalized materials with new functions”.
The research that led to the discovery of this new form of molecular architecture began nearly four decades ago, in 1989, when Richard Robson tested the use of the inherent properties of atoms by combining positively charged copper ions with a four-armed molecule.
When combined, they bonded "to form a spacious, well-ordered crystal. It was like a diamond filled with countless cavities," the academy explains. Robson immediately realized the potential of his molecular construction, but it was still unstable and crumbled easily. It was chemists Susumu Kitagawa and Omar Yaghi who managed to provide a solid foundation for this construction method.
Notable applications
Following the discoveries of the three laureates, chemists built tens of thousands of different MOFs. Some of them could contribute to solving some of humanity's biggest challenges, with applications including breaking down traces of pharmaceuticals in the environment, capturing carbon dioxide or collecting water from desert air.
The discovery also allows the separation of perfluoroalkylated and polyfluoroalkylated substances (PFAS) from water. PFAS are a group of synthetic chemical compounds known as “forever chemicals” due to their extreme persistence in the environment and in the human body.
PFAS are used in a wide range of industrial and household products, such as stain- and water-resistant textiles, food packaging, non-stick cookware and firefighting foams. Its accumulation in the environment and potential health risks, including liver damage and other problems, have led to concerns and a search for safer alternatives.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:41:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Trump was the main disseminator of disinformation in the USA in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/estudo-trump-foi-principal-disseminador-de-desinformacao-nos-eua-em-2024/</link><description>North American President Donald Trump was the main disseminator of disinformation in the United States of America (USA) in 2024, concluded a study by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ). “US President Donald Trump was the dominant source and distributor of disinformation” in 2024, say the authors of the study “Disarming Disinformation: United States”.
The study highlights that Trump has drawn on the functions of domestic political forces, rather than foreign state actors, as the main source of disinformation narratives in US political discourse. Furthermore, the existence of WhatsApp groups and other closed digital spaces often act as “information cocoons” that encourage rumors and other forms of misinformation.
In this way, "the viral spread of misinformation and the strategic attack on journalists have emerged as interconnected threats to democracy. In an era of increasing authoritarianism and democratic backsliding, falsehoods are often used as a weapon by state actors to influence public opinion, undermine journalism and intimidate journalists."
The study authors state that these factors are increasingly the North American reality, with Donald Trump “promulgating manifestly false narratives” in recent years.
“The American media faces a profound information crisis, at a time of repression of freedom of expression”, the study reads. In this sense, trust in the mainstream press continues to decline in a climate of increasing attacks on the media by the Trump Government.
The study published by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ) was based on the analysis of 10,000 news and media publications during 2024, as well as a survey of 1,020 Americans.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:38:02</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Association calls for more quality jobs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/lag-associacao-pede-mais-emprego-de-qualidade/</link><description>The Choi In Tong Sam Association talks about economic recovery and greater confidence in the Government, but recognizes that there is still a discrepancy between official data and the population's sentiment
With the Lines of Government Action (LAG) to be presented on November 18, the Choi In Tong Sam Association defends the need for the Government to adopt long-term measures to promote economic growth. The position was taken by vice-president Kou Ngon Fong, in statements to the newspaper Exmoo.
From the association leader's perspective, society needs measures to promote the economy, which stimulate sustained growth, instead of the current measures that are essentially limited to relieving the population of the difficulties experienced in recent years.
According to Kou, the economy has “returned to normal” in recent years and there is greater trust among citizens in the Government. However, support, such as the large premium for consumption in community areas, is not enough to promote economic growth. The association therefore calls for more structural measures and points as an example to the increase in the salary of public servants and the minimum wage, which was recently increased by one pataca per hour.
The official also recalled that the number of visitors and revenue from the game exceeded society's expectations, however, residents still suffer the impact of post-pandemic changes in terms of quality of employment and cost of living, because the economic recovery is uneven.
"People do not feel well, even though the unemployment rate is falling, the room for maneuver to implement salary increases for employees is very limited. People looking for jobs also have difficulty finding suitable vacancies or well-paid jobs", said Kou Ngon Fong.
Unrelevant data
The vice-president of the Choi In Tong Sam Association also warned of the fact that there is a large discrepancy between the data published by the Government, which shows an economy increasingly recovering, and the sentiment of residents.
However, Kou Ngon Fong trusts that the Government knows the real situation in society, because it has just collected opinions to prepare the LAG. Regarding the governance guidelines for next year, Kou warned that it was necessary to increase the value of some subsidies and make the conditions for receiving support clearer.
Regarding the financial contribution plan, Kou Ngon Fong revealed that he had received several complaints about the lack of transparency in the implemented rules that require residents to spend 183 days in Macau. The association leader therefore asked the government to be clearer about the criteria applied and to explain them very well publicly.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:39:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment | Calls for measures to improve access in construction and retail</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/emprego-pedidas-medidas-para-melhorar-acesso-na-construcao-e-no-retalho/</link><description>Deputy Leong Pou U argues, in a statement, that measures are necessary to promote employment in the construction sector. Although the latest employment survey by the Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC) shows a drop in the unemployment rate, Leong Pou U warns of the poor employment situation in some economic sectors, such as construction and retail sales. Leong Pou U emphasizes that unemployment mostly originated in these two sectors, according to DSEC data.
In this way, the deputy, linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM), argues that the Government must launch specific support measures, to provide a situation of full employment in the construction sector. Leong Pou U talks about the underemployment situation for many workers in this sector, taking into account that both public and private work have suffered reductions, in addition to the fact that salaries have been frozen for many years.
For this reason, the deputy suggests that the Government increases the proportion of workers residing in public works awarded, as well as launching more public works projects.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:36:49</pubDate></item><item><title>New health post in Zone A opened yesterday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/inaugurado-ontem-novo-posto-de-saude-da-zona-a/</link><description>The inauguration ceremony of the new health post in Zone A of the New Urban Landfills took place yesterday, which officially starts operating today. According to a note from the Macau Health Services (SS), this health post has an area of ​​around 1,066 square kilometers and will provide services from Monday to Friday, from 8:30 am to 1:00 pm and from 2:30 pm to 6:00 pm, closing on Saturdays, Sundays and holidays.
It is a family health unit, which provides “holistic, comprehensive, coordinated and continuous medical services that cover the entire life cycle, including health care for children, women and adults in general, unscheduled outpatient consultations, prevention and treatment of chronic diseases, health promotion, general nursing care, vaccinations and provision of basic medicines”.
The SS estimates that the population in Zone A will be 96 thousand people, so, in the first phase of operation, this health post will be equipped with “six health professionals and administrative staff to provide services to the first batch of inhabitants of that area”, and, “in the future, dynamic adjustment [of professionals] will be carried out according to the actual situation”. These explanations were given by Alvis Lo, director of the SS, at the inauguration ceremony of the new health post.
Comprehensive Services
Alvis Lo also declared that the Health Post of Zone A of Novos Urban Landfills is the first public health institution to be opened in UOPG [Operational Planning and Management Unit] East-2, providing “convenient and comprehensive community medical services to residents of the aforementioned Zone”.
The SS director also recalled the existence, throughout the territory, of nine health centers and four posts, including the space opened yesterday. Alvis Lo also highlighted that “today, more than 80 percent of patients with chronic diseases in Macau opt for health centers to receive treatment, which demonstrates that the objective of global health coverage has preliminarily been achieved”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:33:41</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC / Elections | Cases of corruption and illegal propaganda in the MP</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/ccac-eleicoes-casos-de-corrupcao-e-propaganda-ilegal-no-mp/</link><description>The CCAC reveals that the individual investigated for electoral bribery confessed to the act and is thus practically guaranteed at least one month in Coloane. The electoral law does not allow the suspension of prison sentences
The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) revealed that it had referred a case of electoral corruption and another of illegal propaganda on election day to the Public Ministry (MP). The information was revealed yesterday through a statement, and the cases are related to the September Legislative elections.
According to information from the CCAC, one of those targeted had posted several online publications admitting that he was willing to sell his voting rights, as long as he was paid. “During the inspection of electoral propaganda activities, the CCAC discovered that an individual circulated messages and posted comments on social media with the aim of publicly requesting money from third parties, promising to vote in accordance with the indicated voting direction”, stated in the statement. “The individual in question admitted to committing the crime, claiming that he hoped, in this way, to obtain pecuniary advantages”, it was added.
In this scenario, the person being investigated is indicted for the crime of electoral corruption, for soliciting a bribe, and is therefore guaranteed a stay of at least one month in Coloane prison, in case of conviction. The crime is punishable only with a prison sentence of up to three years and does not allow payment of a fine. Therefore, as the electoral law does not allow the suspension of prison sentences, however short they may be, in case of conviction the defendant will spend at least a month in Coloane.
Promotion platform
Regarding the second case, of illegal propaganda, the CCAC states that it happened on September 14th, when an individual “used social communication software to send propaganda messages for a candidate list, with image and text, in several communication groups with more than a hundred members, appealing to participants in these groups to vote for the respective candidate group”. However, the CCAC statement did not reveal which list benefited from the alleged illegal campaign action.
Despite this, the subject, unlike the corruption case, will be able to avoid Coloane's arrest. According to electoral law, electoral propaganda on election day is punishable by a prison sentence of up to one year or a fine of 240 days. If found guilty and punished with a fine, the suspect avoids prison. However, if you are sentenced to prison, you will always have to go to the Coloane Prison.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:30:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Budget | Economy grew 8.8 percent in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/orcamento-economia-cresceu-88-por-cento-em-2024/</link><description>The 2024 budget execution report, presented this Tuesday by the Executive in the Legislative Assembly, speaks of real economic growth of 8.8 percent in the space of one year
The Macao SAR economy recorded a progressive recovery in 2024, with the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) closing the year with annual growth of 8.8 percent in real terms compared to 2023, it was announced on Tuesday in the Chamber. At current prices, GDP reached 403,310 million patacas, having registered a nominal increase of 9.2 percent, in annual terms, compared to 2023, translating into a recovery in the overall size of Macau's economy to 86.4 percent of the value recorded before the covid-19 pandemic.
According to the 2024 Budget execution report, presented to the Legislative Assembly (AL) by Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, service exports increased by 9.2 percent, driven by the annual growth of 23.8 percent in the number of visitor arrivals in 2024, in the order of 34.929 million.
Exports of gaming services rose by 21.8 percent and exports of other tourist services fell by 6.1 percent due to the relatively high comparison base of the year 2023, but registering an increase of 13 percent compared to 2019.
The gross revenues from the various game items in 2024 grew by 23.8 percent, that is, from 183,700 million patacas in 2023 to 227,420 million patacas in 2024, among which the gross revenues from the game of chance worth 226,780 million patacas stood out, which had a weight of 99.7 percent in revenues global gaming gross, representing an increase of 23.9 percent compared to the same period in 2023.
Right accounts
In 2024, integrated ordinary revenue amounted to 116,060 million patacas, equivalent to 28.8 percent of GDP, representing an increase of 15.5 percent compared to the 100,450 million patacas recorded in 2023.
The Macao SAR's integrated ordinary expenditure stood at 97,950 million patacas, or 24.3 percent of GDP, an increase of 8.1 percent compared to the 90,570 million patacas recorded in 2023. The budget execution balance of 18,110 million patacas represented an increase of 83.4 percent compared to the 9,870 million patacas registered in 2023.
The report highlights the “continuous improvement in the situation of public finances in 2024”, without any public debt burden, on the contrary, “the value of 4,790 million patacas from the execution balance of the Macao SAR's central budget for 2022 was transferred to the financial reserve.
In the year under review, there was also “a positive result in the investment portfolio of 30,950 million patacas, as well as an increase in the financial reserve from 580,470 million patacas at the end of 2023 to 616,210 million patacas at the end of 2024.
In the same AL session, the 2024 General Account Audit Report was also presented, with the audit commissioner, Ao Ieong U, giving importance to the emergence of 57 issues relating to management, operations and institutional development in approximately 18 departments. “Feedback on these issues was provided individually to departmental leaders to reinforce oversight of corrective measures,” he noted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:19:25</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Sam Hou Fai goes to AL on November 18th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/lag-sam-hou-fai-vai-a-al-a-18-de-novembro/</link><description>The Governing Action Lines (LAG) will be presented by Sam Hou Fai on November 18, Tuesday, at the Legislative Assembly. The calendar on the main pillars of governance for next year was released yesterday, through a statement from the Social Communication Office (CGS).
On November 18th, at 3pm, the Chief Executive will go to the Legislative Assembly, to communicate the content of the Lines of Government Action. Two and a half hours later, the traditional press conference takes place at the Government Headquarters. The following day, Wednesday, Sam Hou Fai returns to the chamber to answer deputies' questions about the LAG. Each deputy has the right to ask a question.
A question session in the Administration and Justice area is scheduled for November 21st, in what will be a debut in Wong Sio Chak's new portfolio. The session will take place between 9:30 am and 8 pm, with a break between 1 pm and 3 pm. This is the time for all sectoral sessions.
On November 24th, it is Tai Kin Ip's turn to come to the chamber, to answer questions on Economy and Finance. On November 26th, Chan Tsz King will make his debut in the hemicycle, to address doubts about the area of ​​security. The last sessions are scheduled for November 28th, with questions on Social Affairs and Culture, and for December 1st, with Raymond Tam answering questions about Transport and Public Works.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:12:09</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Academics advocate prudence in spending</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/lag-academicos-defendem-prudencia-nas-despesas/</link><description>Academics Loi Hoi Ngan and Davis Fong argued, according to the Chinese channel Radio Macau, that in the next Lines of Government Action (LAG), relating to 2026, the Executive must be attentive to maintaining public expenditure within revenue limits and support, in a more precise way, vulnerable groups in society.
Loi Hoi Ngan, associate professor at the Faculty of Human and Social Sciences at Macau Polytechnic University, argued that there are external factors causing an impact on Macau, and if fixed financial expenses are too much, this will not bring benefits to the financial health of the territory.
Davis Fong, professor at the Faculty of Business Management at the University of Macau, pointed out that the economic recovery is not yet as strong as the increase in the number of visitors, meaning economic uncertainty from abroad could continue until next year. For this reason, Davis Fong calls for a prudent attitude on the part of the Executive, with policies to support businesses in community neighborhoods that have been recovering more slowly.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:10:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Urgency and Operability of Cross-Border Precautionary Measures in Judicial Disputes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/urgencia-e-operacionalidade-das-medidas-cautelares-transfronteiricas-em-litigios-judiciais/</link><description>By Lei Wun Kong
I. Introduction
With the intensification of economic and cultural exchanges in the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, conflicts in the areas of cross-border trade, investment and financing, intellectual property and family law have increased significantly. Efficient and predictable cross-border enforcement of court judgments and arbitration awards, together with related safeguard measures, plays an irreplaceable role in protecting the legitimate rights of parties, optimizing the regional business environment and strengthening investor confidence.
“Precautionary measures”, as essential judicial guarantee mechanisms, include in mainland China the preservation of assets, the preservation of evidence and the preservation of conduct; in Macau cover urgent and provisional preventive measures to ensure the realization of threatened rights. For example, upon judicial authorization, it is possible to order preventive seizure of the debtor's bank accounts or properties.
However, obstacles persist in requesting cross-border precautionary measures. Even if the creditor has filed the main action in Macau/mainland China, if he does not file the main action at the place of preservation within the legal period (e.g. 30 or 10 days after notification of the precautionary decision in accordance with Article 334 of the Code of Civil Procedure), the precautionary measures granted will be extinguished.
II. Urgency
Statistics from the Guangdong High People's Court reveal that in 2024, the province's courts concluded 2,250 civil and commercial cases involving Macau in the first instance (932 in the Cooperation Zone). On the other hand, a stable growth trend is observed in these cases (2073 in 2023), a pattern that perfectly aligns with the continued economic expansion of the Greater Bay Area and the increase in cross-border investment and trade activities.
However, outside of arbitration, the inability to implement effective cross-border precautionary measures allows debtors to exploit legal loopholes to transfer assets located in another jurisdiction (including Macau). Consequently, even in main actions favorable to creditors, there remains a high risk of frustrated execution due to asset loss.
III. Efficiency and Operability
Cross-border precautionary measures constitute a “preliminary guarantee” for the enforcement of sentences. The absence of mutual recognition mechanisms between the Chinese Mainland and the Macau Special Administrative Region limits judicial effectiveness. Precautionary assistance and cooperation in the execution of sentences are complementary, jointly forming an integral and efficient judicial assistance chain.
In the field of civil and commercial judicial assistance, as stipulated in the Agreement on Reciprocal Confirmation and Execution of Judicial Decisions and the Agreement on Mutual Assistance in the Matter of Preliminary Measures in Arbitration Proceedings, between Mainland China and the Macau Special Administrative Region, their decisions are reciprocally recognized and enforceable.
Additionally, the aforementioned Agreement regarding Mutual Assistance in matters of Precautionary Measures allows applicants to directly request the court of the other region for the preservation of assets before or after initiating arbitration, effectively preventing the alienation of assets by the debtor. However, in practice, as most disputes lack an arbitration agreement, depending exclusively on legal actions, Macau must deepen negotiations with the mainland with a view to extending this cooperation to litigious precautionary measures (pre- and intra-procedural). Such a mechanism, inspired by the existing arbitration agreement, would eliminate time intervals used to transfer assets before or after starting the process of confirming decisions handed down by courts outside Macau.
IV. Conclusions
It is urgent to jointly promote the signing of a regional agreement on precautionary measures in legal disputes between Macau and the mainland. For the same reasons, it is imperative to establish similar arrangements with Hong Kong.
The aforementioned regional Agreements are not “optional”, but “mandatory”. In addition to solving urgent problems in cross-border judicial practice and constituting the most direct path to regulatory convergence (effectively inhibiting fraudulent transfers of assets between jurisdictions), this is a strategic initiative to build a legalized business environment in the Greater Bay Area aligned with international standards. They will provide a solid institutional safeguard for Macau's integration into national development and strengthen judicial credibility.
Note: The above content is based on Lei Wun Kong's speech before the agenda at the Plenary Assembly of the Macau Special Administrative Region in the afternoon of November 4th.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:26:20</pubDate></item><item><title>In search of the golden straw</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/05/em-busca-da-palhinha-de-ouro/</link><description>In the middle of last month, in Zhuji, Zhejiang, China, Mr. Shou manufactured a straw with 100 grams of gold, intended especially to be used for drinking milk tea. The straw was valued at approximately RMB$100,000.
One day, at dusk, Mr. Shou was traveling home on his motorbike. Suddenly, a bump in the road caused the motorcycle to bounce and the straw he was carrying in his pocket fell out. When he couldn't find her, he called the police. The agents, considering the cylindrical shape of the object, realized that it should have rolled off the road and traveled a considerable distance. They ended up finding her next to a sidewalk, about 100 meters from the place where she had fallen.
Although it was recovered, the straw was deformed due to the fall. Mr. Shou decided to melt it down and make another one that will be ready next summer.
Afterwards, Mr. Shou handed over a banner to the police officers to express his gratitude.
This story raises some questions that make us reflect.
First, making everyday objects out of gold is undoubtedly a unique manifestation of a personal lifestyle; However, having the carelessness of putting a gold straw in your pocket and needing to ask the police for help to look for it raises the following question: is it reasonable to ask the police to use their resources to make up for personal negligence? What responsibility should the negligent person bear? Now that the straw has been recovered, let's hope the owner takes more care with his belongings in the future. If these types of cases are avoided, problems can be reduced, there will be no need to spend public resources and everyone benefits.
Second, the police did not stop working to solve the case even though the person was negligent. On the contrary, he demonstrated professionalism and capacity for resolution. The agents analyzed the characteristics of the object, estimated its location and managed to find the straw in the dark; The two agents involved deserve to be praised.
Third, isn't having gold objects for daily use a way of “showing off wealth”, or simply a demonstration that “because you are rich you are willful”? Gold is very valuable and using it to manufacture everyday objects is a unique pleasure. This practical investment is more “realistic” than simply storing it in a box. However, it is not known whether the value of gold will drop if the object is damaged. Gold is valued by weight; Small scratches have little impact on weight, but visible damage can diminish the “artistic” value. The only solution is to remake the straw.
Fourth, offering a banner to police officers as a way of showing gratitude is a gesture of respect. However, these agents are public servants and should not accept gifts. Although offering the banner is a symbolic act, the feeling that accompanies it is profound. It represents Mr. Shou's gratitude, praise and respect for the police. It is believed that the gift of the banner was the best gift Mr. Shou could have given and the best gift the police could have received.
In short, using a “golden straw” to drink tea with milk is an act that combines preference with wealth. Milk tea does not become sweeter if sipped through a straw, but it increases personal satisfaction. Negligence must be prevented to avoid situations of abuse of public resources. The professionalism and resolution capacity of the police deserve praise. The track may be a small gift, but it carries a deep feeling. In today's society that values ​​money above all else, how many people will understand its true meaning?
This news is not particularly relevant to many of our readers, but it can bring a smile to our troubled lives. Whether you are reading us from Portugal, Macau, or anywhere else, I hope this article brings you a moment of relaxation.
See you next week.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor of the Faculty of Management Sciences of the Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:35:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Letter from Rita Santos about the archiving of the investigation process by the Portuguese Public Ministry</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/04/carta-de-rita-santos-sobre-o-arquivamento-do-processo-de-investigacao-pelo-ministerio-publico-portugues/</link><description>Hon. Mr. Dr. Carlos Morais José
M. I. Director of Jornal Hoje Macau
This request for publication serves to confirm that on October 24th, the Public Prosecutor's Office of Portugal issued an order archiving the criminal proceedings brought against me following formal complaints presented by members of the Socialist Party, mostly residing in Macau.
Throughout the process, I have always actively collaborated with the Portuguese authorities in discovering the material truth and, with that, in protecting my good name, honesty and immaculate character, supported by the trust that the Macanese community places in me, which I will never defraud.
It was, from what I was offered to know, a case that was never a case, based only on speculation, defamation and attack on character, a typical case of instrumentalization of justice with political-partisan objectives, but which were not achieved.
And, therefore, as expected, with the Public Prosecutor's Office carrying out a thorough investigation, finding that no illegality had been committed and concluded by the absence of criminal evidence, archiving is the logical corollary and would always be the only and fair solution to this “non-prosecution”.
Values ​​such as respect for the Law and the individual freedom of each citizen are non-negotiable for me and I will never give up on them, which is why I will never stop, as I have always done, being an active voice in defending democratic and humanist principles, and having an active civic participation in defending the interests of the Portuguese community in Macau.
With best regards.
Macau, on October 31, 2025.
Rita Santos</description><pubDate>2025-11-04 01:55:26</pubDate></item><item><title>The drug kills you if you get enough</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/04/a-droga-mata-que-se-farta/</link><description>Gone are the days when opium inspired Camilo Pessanha. In which a goose calmed down and slept well. Today, drugs kill. It kills hundreds of young people who become addicted to heroin, cocaine and psychoactive chemical substances that destroy the brain. Those addicted to the most diverse drugs inject themselves into their veins and when there is no purity in the product, they overdose and die. There were young people in Portugal who, affected by a hangover, beat their parents for not giving them the money they wanted and then committed suicide. Overdose deaths increased by 16 percent in 2023 compared to the previous year, totaling 80, revealed a report from the Institute for Addictive Behaviors and Addictions (ICAD) released last year, with cocaine being the drug most responsible for mortality.
A few days ago, a 14-year-old minor killed his mother with his father's pistol and the Judiciary Police have already added to the file data indicating that the young man was consuming excessive cannabis. And what are drug addicts? Simply dependent on the multi-million dollar organized crime business where the drug lords earn millions of euros.
Last week, we saw two cases in Portugal of shouting to the heavens. A GNR mega-operation that discovered several farms on the outskirts of the Tagus River where 13 speedboats, 11 galleys, a truck, 30 sophisticated engines, 16 top-of-the-range cars, 750 thousand euros in cash and many firearms and bladed weapons were manufactured and stored. 32 suspects were arrested in connection with international drug trafficking, an operation that included the cooperation of the Spanish Guardia Civil. Thus, a criminal network operating in Portugal was dismantled and dedicated to the construction and movement of speedboats to transport drugs from large ships from Colombia and Brazil. This operation had been ongoing for 32 months. During the investigation, several suspects of Spanish nationality were identified. The three-year investigation also led to the arrest in Spain of dozens of drug traffickers and tons of narcotics.
Also last week, the country was shocked by the death of a GNR soldier and three others who were injured after a collision between a GNR vessel and another allegedly belonging to drug traffickers on the Guadiana River, near Alcoutim, Faro. According to an observer of the accident, the traffickers purposely threw their boat at the GNR boat, ramming it and killing one of the soldiers on board, and then setting fire to their boat on one of the banks of the river so that there would be no evidence of drug possession. The same observer said that it was “an authentic homicidal act”. The President of the Republic described the situation as “painful” and “regrettable”. Meanwhile, the Judiciary Police and the GNR have already arrested two suspects of having been involved in the collision of the GNR vessel that caused the soldier's death. Apparently, the two suspects were already known for drug trafficking in Spain. The suspects were arrested when they tried to cross a bridge, in a Spanish-registered car, on their way to the neighboring country. They would have large amounts of money in their possession.
When we contacted a GNR spokesperson, he stated that "Normally, when it comes to cocaine, the origin is South America and traffickers transfer it in the Atlantic. If it is hashish trafficking, the origin is North Africa, passing the narcotic product from a larger vessel, in the Mediterranean, to these speedboats that then try to enter Europe, using Portugal and Spain."
Before fleeing, the suspects ended up stranded on the riverbank, then setting fire to the boat, which was possibly full of drugs. The same spokesperson added that “normally in these cases, the vessels come from the high seas, land (the drugs) in both the Guadiana and the Pedras River, in Spain, burn the boat and then escape.”
All this criminal activity is facilitated because the military does not have the necessary means to fight efficiently. The Government simply laments when a tragedy happens and the President of the Republic and the Minister of Internal Administration rush to the funeral of the soldier killed by drug traffickers, giving an air of great regret. A scene that the family members ignored because the important thing is the disregard that the authorities have given to the calls from security force associations for increased funding to combat drug trafficking. And our position is so significant that it was only hours after the fatal event in Alcoutim that President Marcelo promulgated a diploma regulating the use of speedboats. Possibly if the diploma had been promulgated months ago, the GNR soldier would not have died. As people say, after the robbery, you lock the door...</description><pubDate>2025-11-04 01:52:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Success of “book exchange” leads IC to organize more sessions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/sucesso-de-troca-de-livros-leva-ic-a-organizar-mais-sessoes/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) decided to extend the deadline for carrying out the “Book Exchange” initiative, which covers various activities in the territory's public libraries and community neighborhoods, in order to encourage reading.
According to a statement, the extension of the program is due to the fact that “the activity has been widely acclaimed”, so there will be more sessions on weekends during this month and also in December, in order to “further expand the circulation and sharing of books”.
Therefore, this weekend, Saturday and Sunday, new book exchange sessions will take place at Praça de Luís de Camões, and then at Largo do Lilau on the 27th and 28th of December. These two sessions join those previously scheduled for the Lateral Space of Jardim Cidade das Flores, on the 22nd and 23rd of November. The timing of all sessions is from 12pm to 6pm.
For these sessions, IC describes, “participants only need to take the books that comply with the exchange rules to the staff on site, selecting their favorites and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books”.
Standards to comply with
The rules determine that magazines, leaflets, guides for entering a school, school books, event catalogs, children's books, yearbooks published non-locally, legal books, exam preparation books, books with pornographic and/or violent content, religious books, books without a publishing license or with copyright infringements, books with incomplete or damaged pages, volumes of books belonging to an incomplete collection, books with loose binding, with pages that are easy to separate or with missing pages cannot be exchanged. pages, books with written or scribbled pages and books with more than five copies.
In order to maintain the timeliness and usefulness of the books, science and engineering books published more than five years ago, computer books published more than three years ago, tourist guides published more than two years ago are not accepted. Each person can exchange a maximum of 20 books during the event.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 02:08:29</pubDate></item><item><title>CCM | Opera performance season runs until March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/ccm-temporada-de-espectaculos-de-opera-decorre-ate-marco/</link><description>It is on the 27th of this month that the first cultural initiative integrated into the “1st Season of Chinese Culture Shows” begins. These are “A Gathering of Heroes, Invoking the East Wind and The Huarong Passage”, Chinese opera pieces written by the Chinese National Peking Opera Company. But there are more shows to see until March next year
This week, Tuesday, the program for the “1st Season of Chinese Culture Shows” was presented, an “artistic banquet” promising “excellent shows with diverse experiences”.
The initiative was created from the previous “Season of Performances of National Art Companies in Macau”, with the first performance taking place on November 27th, with the Beijing opera “A Meeting of Heroes. Invoking the East Wind. The Passage of Huarong”, presented in a three and a half hour show by the Chinese National Peking Opera Company, at the Macau Cultural Center (CCM).
According to the official description of the show, main artists Yu Kuizhi and Li Shengsu take to the stage, leading the cast that presents “the Chinese lyrical tradition in all its expressiveness”.
“Three great plays” and “epics taken from the classic Romance of the Three Kingdoms” are presented, with a “mix of singing and theatrical staging, which highlights a perfect balance between civil and military characters, embodied by a series of historical figures”.  On the 28th of this month, it is time to perform, also at CCM, “The Legend of the White Snake”, written by the famous playwright Tian Han and originally directed by the prestigious director Li Zigui.
"This recognized masterpiece has been meticulously refined on stage for more than 60 years. Considered a fundamental work of the operatic repertoire, the piece has been performed by countless generations of 'dan' (female roles) performers", reads the show's description.
On stage, the artists are Li Shengsu, a distinguished representative and defender of the Mei Lanfang school, who is also a mentor to the talented Zhu Fengyi, an artist with whom she shares the main role of Bai Suzhen (Madam White Snake). “In this re-enactment, the performers magnificently portray the unshakable forbidden love that the legendary character has for a mortal, transporting the audience to a mesmerizing dreamlike scenario”, it also reads.
New interpretations
The program for this initiative also includes theatrical performances such as “Goodbye, My Concubine”, performed by the Beijing People's Theatre. It is an adaptation based on the original creation of Nobel Prize winner for Literature Mo Yan, and which has as its backdrop the historical confrontation Chu–Han.
“The play breaks with the traditional narrative structure of historical drama and explores eternal themes such as power, survival and responsibility through multiple encounters and dialogues that cross time and space between consort Yu and Empress Lü”, it can be read.
The performance of the dance theater piece “Mulan”, by the Ningbo Arts and Entertainment Group, is also scheduled. This “main line is filial piety, loyalty, courage and love, combining dance, martial arts, drama and technological elements”.
Groups such as the Chinese Coal Mine Artistic Troupe and the Chinese National Opera will also be invited to carry out exchange performances in various locations in Macau, namely in schools and community neighborhoods. Also noteworthy is the fact that the National Opera of China will return to performances in Macau in January next year to present “Golden Lotus Flowers – Concert of Vocal Works of the National Opera of China” in several schools.
“The concert brings together masterpieces of Chinese and foreign vocal music, with rich musical pieces and exceptional artists, taking students on a musical journey that crosses East and West”, it is said. In total, this first season includes eight exchange presentations and 50 community activities.
“Using Chinese culture as a connecting link, the event aims to create a cultural event that involves the entire population, promote emotional resonance and cultural transmission, working together to build a happy, beautiful and harmonious circle of life,” it is described.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:59:22</pubDate></item><item><title>“Message” by Fernando Pessoa translated into Timorese Tetum</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/mensagem-de-fernando-pessoa-traduzido-para-tetum-timorense/</link><description>The first translation of Fernando Pessoa's “Message” into Tetum, the official language of East Timor alongside Portuguese, is presented tomorrow, in an effort to bring “the greatest work” of the writer “to readers all over the world”.
"We wanted to be the first to launch some editions. Last year we launched it in Hindi, which is the fifth most spoken language in the world, and which had no translation", highlighted the communications director of Valor do Tempo, the group that acquired the Lisbon café and which moved forward with translations of Fernando Pessoa's work in 2020.
According to Sónia Santiago, the group wanted to “have the ‘Message’ again in more editions”, so they chose Tetum, after discovering, in a conversation with Fernando Pessoa specialist Ricardo Belo de Moraes, that there was no work translated into this official language of Timor-Leste. The edition also has an introduction about Fernando Pessoa's relationship with A Brasileira do Chiado.
With the temporary closure of the café due to the Covid-19 pandemic, the group had more “time to think” about how they could “present A Brasileira to the world”, having decided to “start translating the ‘Message'”, as they “receive customers from so many places”, who purposely go “to take photographs with the statue [of Fernando Pessoa] that is on the terrace”, he added.
In 2021, the group launched an edition of the work in Portuguese and bilingual editions in English, French, Spanish, Mandarin, and later, in German and Italian. The group began preparing translations of the book into other languages ​​in 2024, focusing on new editions, particularly in Hindi, launched in October of that year.
Birthday season
The launch of the work in Tetum “acquires particular significance as it takes place in the month in which A Brasileira do Chiado celebrates 120 years of existence, on the 19th of November, and in which Timor-Leste marks, on the 28th of the same month, the 50th anniversary of the first declaration of independence”, according to a statement.
The translation of the work “Mensagem”, an edition of A Brasileira do Chiado, was written by Paulo Henriques, trainer, translator and guest professor of the Master's Degree in Teaching Portuguese in the Context of Timor-Leste at the National University of Timor-Leste.
The group will announce on Friday the launch of editions of the Message in Romanian, Arabic, Polish, Russian, and Ukrainian, which is also a new translation. The launch of the work will take place on Friday, at 11am, at Instituto Camões, in Lisbon, in a session open to the public.
The event is attended by the ambassador of Timor-Leste in Lisbon, Isabel Amaral Guterres, the president of Instituto Camões, Florbela Paraíba, the president of Fundação Oriente, Carlos Monjardino, with the translator, Paulo Henriques, participating via video call from the Timorese capital, Díli.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:29:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix | The years from 1967 to 1978 by Victor H. de Lemos</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/grande-premio-os-anos-de-1967-a-1978-pela-mao-de-victor-h-de-lemos/</link><description>The Grand Prix is ​​Macau's motor sport par excellence, and there are residents who have always dedicated themselves to this passion. Victor H. de Lemos was one of them, and the second part of his estate will be released today in a book at the headquarters of APOMAC – Association of Retirees, Retirees and Pensioners of Macau. HM spoke with his son about the launch of the second volume of Macau Grand Prix – Personal Collection of Victor H. de Lemos (1967-1978)
“My father was very proud of his work.” This is how Carlos Lemos, son of Victor H. Lemos, the great collector of images and materials related to the Macau Grand Prix (GPM) competition, tells HM the parade of memories that are now also paraded on the pages of a book. This is the second volume of the “Macau Grand Prize – Personal Collection of Victor H. de Lemos”, this time dedicated to the years 1967 to 1978. In 2023, the first volume was released, focusing on the years 1954 to 1966. The two editorial projects are supported by the Association of Retirees, Retirees and Pensioners of Macau (APOMAC).
The launch event for the second volume takes place today from 3pm, at APOMAC headquarters. This work contains, as described by Carlos Lemos, “newspapers, photos and GPM events from 1967 to 1978”, and there is no shortage of records of notable episodes of the competition on the Guia Circuit.
Included are “articles related to the first fatal accident on the circuit of popular Filipino racer Arsenio Dodgie Laurel, who was a two-time GPM winner, or articles about the failed creation of the Far East Motor Racing Association (FEMRAC) Circuit”. There are also, in these pages, records “of the first Guia Race and motorcycle races, and of the first female driver to win the ‘Current Production Cars’ race”.
The reader will also be able to find “the race of giants, with the participation of famous racers in the world such as Dan Gurney, Jacky Ickx, who was six times winner of the 24 hours Le Mans, Sir Stirling Moss; Jack Brabham, the only driver to win the Formula 1 championship in a car that bears his name (Brabham); Roy Salvadori”.
“In the last section of the book I made a small introduction with around 100 photos from another collection of my father, entitled ‘World of Motorsport’, which contains almost two thousand photos autographed by drivers, car owners, designers and renowned personalities in the world related to motorsport such as ‘Il Commendatore’ Enzo Ferrari, Juan Manuel Fangio or Sir Jackie Stewart.”
Life of dedication
Victor H. Lemos created this collection on a more permanent basis while he lived in Macau, and from 1975 onwards the Macanese, emigrating to Canada, began to have difficulties in having his collection updated. "He depended on friends to send photos, newspapers and programs for his collection, and decided to finish the project in 1978, on the 50th anniversary [of the competition]. Volume 2 completes a significant part of the collection", he told HM.
Carlos Lemos admits that he had to leave material out of this edition and that the selection process “was difficult”. “I decided to include the most important parts that are of greatest interest to GPM fans, otherwise it would be a bulkier book,” he said. In the years visually described in this work, there was “the transition from ‘Sport’ and ‘GT’ type cars to ‘Formula’ type cars with more powerful and faster engines”.
"The participation of racers from other parts of the world such as Australia, England, Germany and with cars partitioned by factories such as BMW and Renault-Alpina also began, ceasing to be an amateur event. It was also a period of improvement and modernization of the circuit", described Carlos Lemos.
Victor H. Lemos “dedicated a lot to this collection”. “After work, he would wait in the corridors and hotel lobbies to collect the signatures” of the pilots. “People made fun of him, but this collection is, today, probably the most complete in the GPM and contains information that is highly sought after.”
Regarding the possibility of this personal estate being part of the GPM Museum collection, Carlos Lemos assures that there is nothing new. “We touched on this subject twice, a few years ago, and this suggestion was also made when the first volume was released, but nothing came to fruition.”</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:28:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Rua dos Mercadores | Traffic prohibited until Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/rua-dos-mercadores-transito-proibido-ate-segunda-feira/</link><description>The traffic ban on Rua dos Mercadores, created due to work being carried out at the site, and which should come to an end today, will have to be extended until Monday. At issue is the “need to cure the paving concrete”, with the closure of Rua dos Mercadores to traffic and the reverse measures on Rua das Estalagens and Rua de Camilo Pessanha remaining until 10pm on Monday.
Regarding the bus service, bus route no. 18 (direction to Rua dos Currais) will temporarily continue without making stops at “Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro/Tai Fung”, “Rua dos Mercadores”, “Rua das Estalagens” and “Rua de Cinco de Outubro”. During this period, the “Ponte 16” or “Rua do Tarrafeiro” stops can be used for entrances and exits.
The work is expected to end on November 27th, as defined since the beginning of the project, related to the underground cable network, “greater than initially planned and required better reorganization”. The third, and final, phase of the works takes place between Tuesday and the 27th of this month, “with the intervention area concentrated predominantly on internal roads in the area, not affecting the original direction of traffic”, describes the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT).</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:54:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Colégio S. José 5th | Teacher accused of humiliating student</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/colegio-s-jose-5a-professora-acusada-de-humilhar-aluno/</link><description>In response to the complaint, the school admits an internal investigation into the case, but warned the complainant to prepare for the consequences, because “the Internet is not a lawless space”. The Government reportedly received a complaint about the case on October 14th, but until now it has remained silent
A teacher at Colégio Diocesano de São José 5ª is being accused of humiliating a student with autism, allegedly using insulting words, after leaving the student waiting more than 80 minutes for a meeting. The complaint was published on social media, on Monday, by an anonymous user, who justifies the use of this medium with the fact that complaints to the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) and the school were ignored.
According to the report presented online, the episode took place on October 10th in the school's teachers' room. The student with autism, who attends secondary school, had an appointment with the teacher. However, the teacher arrived 80 minutes late and reprimanded the student: "But you can never do anything well, except be here waiting? Why didn't you ask another teacher to call me?", the teacher asked. "I taught you so many times, but you never listen! You always act as if I never taught you anything", he added.
The words disturbed the student who raised his voice against the teacher. However, she again admonished the student: "You are not authorized to speak in that tone of voice! Never speak to a teacher in that way", warned the teacher.
After the reprimand, the teacher will have justified, in front of the other teachers present, the arguments used with the fact that the student suffers from autism.
List of complaints
In view of the case, the author of the online comment admits to having filed a complaint about the teacher's conduct with the DSEDJ, the school's management, the Institute of Social Action, and several deputies, including José Pereira Coutinho, for having received the most votes in the last elections, and Ho Ion Sang, elected indirectly by the education sector.
In the complaints presented, an independent investigation into the case was requested, that the teacher be punished due to her conduct and that a review be carried out of the mechanisms for students to defend themselves against teachers when they are targets of abuse.
Although the complaint was made on October 14th, by November 3rd the complainant had not received any response, so he decided to make the complaint public, through social media.
School investigates
With the case going viral, Colégio Diocesano de São José 5ª issued a statement on Tuesday promising an internal investigation, but warning that it will act against defamation attempts.
"Recently, our institution became aware of anonymous online complaints about members of our faculty. These allegations concern issues of professional conduct [...] The school takes these matters very seriously and immediately initiated a rigorous internal investigation," the institution said.
Furthermore, the college revealed that DSEDJ has started to investigate the case: “The school always defends the rights and legitimate interests of staff and students and will actively cooperate with the supervision and investigation work that has already been initiated by the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services”, it was revealed.
Despite this, the school was prepared to target the complainant: “In accordance with the principle of management based on ‘the truth of the facts’, the school […] reserves the right to demand legal responsibility against any fabrications of facts, malicious threats or damage to the reputation of the school and employees — ‘the internet is not a lawless space’!”, it was highlighted.
DSEDJ and Coutinho in silence
In light of the accusations and inaction, HM contacted DSEDJ to confirm the existence of a complaint dated 14 October and to obtain a reaction to the fact that the complaint remained without any response until the beginning of November. However, at the closing time of the HM edition, no response had been received.
As the online publication specifically targeted deputy José Pereira Coutinho, HM tried to get a reaction from the legislator. “I don’t know where this invention came from,” replied the deputy. “I don’t make any comments”, he pointed out. “I am very busy serving dozens of citizens every day in our Citizens Assistance Office”, he added.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:48:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | Revenues grow 14% in the third quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/galaxy-receitas-crescem-14-no-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>In the one-year period, Galaxy's net revenues grew 14 percent. Francis Lui, president of the group, pointed out that the third quarter numbers were achieved, despite the casinos being closed for 33 hours
The Galaxy dealership announced an annual increase in net revenues of 14 percent in the third quarter of this year. The data was released yesterday by the concessionaire through a statement.
Between July and September, the company that manages the casino with the same name recorded net revenues of 12.2 billion Hong Kong dollars, which represented growth compared to the value of 10.7 billion Hong Kong dollars allocated in the third quarter of 2024.
When the comparison is made between the second and third quarters of this year, the growth was less significant, just 1 percent, given that between April and June total net revenue was 12.0 billion Hong Kong dollars.
Still in relation to the third quarter, the bulk of the company's revenue founded by Lui Che Woo was due to gaming, which contributed to net revenue with 9.7 billion Hong Kong dollars, while the non-gaming sector brought the company revenues of 1.7 billion dollars. At the same time, Galaxy's building materials segment generated revenues of $727 million, the only segment showing a negative trend.
Over the three months between July and September, adjusted EBITDA (Earnings Before Interest, Taxes, Depreciation and Amortization) reached 3.3 billion Hong Kong dollars. This amount meant an annual increase of 14 percent, but a reduction of 6 percent, compared to the second quarter of this year.
Limited numbers
Reacting to the numbers, in a statement, the president of Galaxy, Francis Lui, stated that revenues were affected by the fact that September is a month traditionally with low revenues and due to the passage of typhoon Ragasa. "The first factor involved seasonality, given that September is normally a calmer month, with many visitors postponing their trips until October, to coincide with Golden Week. The second event was Typhoon Ragasa", he indicated. "The typhoon led the Government to decree the official closure of all casinos for 33 hours. And 33 hours may not seem like a very long period of time, but it causes potential visitors to cancel their planned visits", he added.
At the same time, Lui also addressed the closure of the Waldo casino, which took place on October 31st: "In accordance with Government policies, the Galaxy Group is committed to safeguarding local employment. In addition to being able to maintain the same positions, employees also had the opportunity to explore a variety of career paths, if they so desired, and received support to transition to a new work environment", he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:42:50</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Government promises to fight the black market</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/gp-macau-governo-promete-lutar-contra-o-mercado-negro/</link><description>The Grand Prix Organizing Committee admitted having created a task team against the sale of tickets on the black market. The revelation was made by Lei Si Leng, president of the Sports Institute and coordinator of the Grand Prix Organizing Committee.
According to the official's statements, new measures were also adopted in the production of tickets, to prevent counterfeiting, and wristbands will be distributed to prevent tickets from being resold after they have been used. “Reselling even just a penny above the purchase price is illegal,” he said.
Lei Si Leng also clarified that people who buy tickets and are unable to attend the races can sell them, as long as they do so at or below the purchase price.
The statements were made on the sidelines of the Pai San Grand Prix ceremony and Lei Si Leng revealed that at this time around 90 percent of tickets have been sold and that tickets for Saturday and Sunday are sold out. In addition, some tickets will be reserved to be sold on the day of the races.
The person in charge also explained that at this stage the circuit is practically assembled and the organization is now ready to start receiving the cars and motorcycles that will participate in the event.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 01:35:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Association expects greater exchange between companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/comercio-associacao-espera-maior-intercambio-entre-empresas/</link><description>The president of the Macau Commercial Association, Ma Chi Ngai, wants to promote greater cooperation between different companies, as a result of the World Convention of Chinese Entrepreneurs. This event was organized by the Macau Commercial Association and took place between the 2nd and 4th of November.
Speaking to the Ou Mun newspaper, the businessman stated that the event should lead to greater long-term commercial exchange between participating companies. Ma considered that it results from the increasingly close cooperation between the association and the Institute for Trade and Investment Promotion (IPIM) and that the two entities actively participated in identifying potential participants.
Ma Chi Ngai pointed out that there was the participation of around 600 Chinese businesspeople from all over the world, and that more than 300 individual meetings were held, which in his opinion exceeded the organization's expectations. During the event, around ten contracts or cooperation intentions were signed, covering companies from countries participating in the One Belt and One Road initiative and Southeast Asia.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:25:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | Alert for active virus and more people in the emergency room</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/gripe-alerta-para-virus-activo-e-mais-pessoas-nas-urgencias/</link><description>The Health Services issued a note stating that “in recent days” more people have been using the emergency units at Kiang Wu and Conde de São Januário hospitals, taking into account that, in the last 15 days, the positivity rate for the influenza virus has been increasing. In turn, the success of the flu vaccine stands out, with annual increases in doses
The influenza virus, responsible for the flu, has been more active in the territory. The authorities, more specifically the Macau Health Services (SS), reported this in a note issued yesterday. “In the last two weeks in Macau (between 12 and 25 October), the positivity rate for detecting the influenza virus was 28.9 and 26.5 percent, respectively, exceeding 13.1 percent”, this being the alert level in the region.
These data show that, “in general, the influenza virus is active”, in addition to that “in recent days, the number of people who used the Emergency Service at Centro Hospitalar Conde de São Januário and Kiang Wu Hospital on a daily basis has been increasing”. Taking these data into account, the SS warn of the importance of vaccinating the most vulnerable groups against influenza, highlighting the success of the program.
“As of November 3, around 94 thousand people were vaccinated against seasonal flu, representing an increase of around 8 percent compared to the same period last year, in which 87 thousand people were vaccinated.” In this way, the SS consider “the progress of vaccination of high-risk groups to be satisfactory”.
New cases
Since October, the SS “has been sending, on its own initiative, health professionals to homes, daycare centers and preschools, among other relevant establishments in Macau, in order to carry out collective vaccination, providing residents with different forms and convenient vaccination services”.
However, this Tuesday four cases of flu were detected in schools. One of them occurred in a third-year secondary class at the Choi Nong Chi Tai School, located on the Ferreira do Amaral Isthmus, with nine students infected. Another case was detected in a class at the School of Application Attached to the University of Macau, with five students infected.
The remaining two cases occurred at Escola Secundária Pui Va and Escola Internacional de Macau, infecting fifteen students in total. Symptoms began to appear on October 30th, with the patients' clinical status being considered “mild”, with no “cases or other serious complications” occurring. Of the four collective cases, 26 students tested positive for Flu A.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:23:09</pubDate></item><item><title>TSI | Kong Chi accused of 79 crimes in new trial</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/tsi-kong-chi-acusado-de-79-crimes-em-novo-julgamento/</link><description>Kong Chi's second trial began with lawyer Ho Kam Meng's defender, one of the defendants in the case, raising doubts about the legality of Deputy Prosecutor Kuok Un Man's participation in this case.
Yesterday, at the Court of Second Instance (TSI), the second trial of former Deputy Prosecutor Kong Chi, who faces charges of committing 79 crimes, began. Among these crimes, the Public Prosecutor's Office (MP) believes that 67 were committed in co-authorship with lawyer Ho Kam Meng.
The first hours of yesterday's session were used by judge Choi Mou Pan to read the pronouncement order, a procedure that lasted more than three hours. However, even before the reading, Lau Io Keong, Ho Kam Meng's lawyer, raised doubts about the legality of Deputy Public Prosecutor Kuok Un Man's participation in the trial.
The lawyer argued that Kuok should be prevented from doing so, due to the fact that she was the representative of the MP in the pre-trial phase of the case. The lawyer drew a parallel with the situation of the investigating judge, who after participating in this phase of the process is prevented from conducting the trial.
In his response, Choi Mou Pan considered that the impediment should only be invoked in the case of a conflict of interest or when there are family connections, which he indicated was not the case in this case. The judge also considered that the MP has the power to choose the representatives he sees fit. Even so, Choi told Lau Io Keong that if he wished he could present the matter in writing, which would then be analyzed by the panel of five judges.
In relation to the indictment order, Kong Chi is accused of having committed a total of 23 crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act: 10 co-authored with Ho Kam Meng, two co-authored with Ho Kam Meng and businesswoman Choi Sai Ieng, three co-authored with businesswoman Choi Sai Ieng and lawyer Kuan Hoi Lon and eight co-authored with Choi Sai Ieng. Each of these crimes is punishable by a prison sentence of up to eight years in prison.
The indictment also adds to the 23 crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act allegedly committed by Kong Chi, another 56 crimes of malfeasance, all co-authored with Ho Kam Meng. These crimes are punishable by up to five years in prison.
Criminal association
Ho Kam Meng is the second defendant in the case and the only one accused of creating/being part of a secret association, whose punishment can be up to 12 years. This association involves Kong Chi and Choi Sai Ieng, who were convicted of this crime in the first trial.
The lawyer is also accused of another 68 crimes, including 12 crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act (10 co-authored with Kong Chi and 2 co-authored with Kong Chi and Choi Sai Ieng) and 56 crimes of malfeasance co-authored with Kong Chi.
Businesswoman Choi Sai Ieng is accused of 13 crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act, eight co-authored with Kong Chi, two co-authored with Kong Chi and Ho Kam Meng, three co-authored with Kong Chi and Kuan Hoi Lon. Finally, Kuan Hoi Lon, the only one of the defendants who was not in court, being partly uncertain, is accused of three crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act, co-authored with Kong Chi Meng and Choi Sai Ieng.
Customers, lunches and payments
Reading the indictment order revealed that the defendants are accused of having used Kong Chi's functions to “sell” acquittals and other favorable decisions during the Public Prosecutor's Office investigations. According to the MP, in most of the crimes, Ho Kam Meng received payments from clients, with the highest value being MOP500,000, and then paid a commission to Kong Chi, often around 10 percent of the amount received.
In return, the investigated defendants were able to obtain favorable decisions, orchestrated by Kong Chi, ranging from acquittal, by archiving the cases, to the lifting of coercive measures or access to seized assets. This type of modus operandi was also used by Choi Sai Ieng and Kuan Hoi Lon.
The cases in which Kong Chi intervened had very different natures, involving investigations into fraud, illegal work, drug use, theft or usury for gambling. Payments from Ho to Kong were normally made during lunches, dinners or trips to the interior.
Repeated stories
Kong Chi is being tried for the second time for allowing himself to be corrupted, as part of his duties as former Deputy Public Prosecutor. In the first case, which came to an end in February this year, Kong was sentenced to 21 years in prison resulting from 1 crime of management or leadership of an association or secret society, 10 crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act, 2 crimes of violating court secrecy, 3 crimes of malfeasance, 1 crime of abuse of power, and 2 crimes of inaccuracy of elements.
In the first case, Choi Sao Ieng was sentenced to 16 years in prison resulting from conviction for 1 crime of participation in an association or secret society, 9 crimes of passive corruption for an illicit act, 2 crimes of violating court secrecy, 3 crimes of malfeasance, 1 crime of abuse of power.
The first trial also ended with the acquittal of lawyer Kuan Hoi Lon, while lawyer Ho Kam Meng is tried for the first time.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:21:44</pubDate></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
At a lunch with several guests, I heard a friend, who declared herself a spiritualist, explaining the particularities of her belief, in a calm and balanced way, I would even say, without a hint of “irrationalism”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«If transparency is demanded from politicians, we kill them; if anyone demands fidelity to what the other was or what he says, kill him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, representation is killed. These must therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to bend the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). I believe we will be needed to decipher this frantically complex world that has fallen to us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Let men refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish, because of it the tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the pride of the countries will be destroyed.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were restricted, or if it merely lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, in a different way, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse like a shadow
[misshapen
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piela than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestine | Pope defends two-state solution when receiving Abbas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/palestina-papa-defende-solucao-de-dois-estados-ao-receber-abbas/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday reiterated his defense of a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, when he received the President of the Palestinian Authority, Mahmud Abbas, for the first time in an audience at the Vatican.
This first meeting between Abbas and Leo XIV since the pope's election in May also served to mark the tenth anniversary of the signing of the Global Agreement between the Vatican and the State of Palestine, in 2015, the year in which the Catholic Church recognized the Palestinian State. “During the cordial talks, the urgent need to provide assistance to the civilian population in Gaza and to put an end to the conflict, seeking a two-state solution, was recognized,” the Vatican said in a statement.
On Wednesday, shortly after arriving in Rome, Abbas went to the Basilica of Santa Maria Maggiore for a moment of recollection before the tomb of Pope Francis, who died in April. “I came here because I cannot forget everything he did for the Palestinian people,” he told the press.
The President of the Palestinian Authority, in power in the West Bank, visited the Vatican on several occasions during Francis' pontificate, having, in 2014, planted an olive tree in the Vatican gardens alongside former Israeli head of state Shimon Peres and Pope Francis, as a symbol of peace.
In the last months of his pontificate, the Argentine pope toughened his statements against the Israeli offensive, causing diplomatic tensions with the Israeli embassy.
Pope Leo XIV has also expressed solidarity with the “martyred land” of Gaza on several occasions and denounced the forced displacement of Palestinians, but highlighted that the Vatican cannot comment on the alleged genocide in the enclave. On Friday, Abbas will be received in the early afternoon by the Italian Prime Minister, Giorgia Meloni, at the Chigi Palace, the seat of the Government, in Rome.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:29:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Death toll rises to 142 after typhoon hits</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/filipinas-sobe-para-142-numero-de-mortos-apos-passagem-de-tufao/</link><description>The number of deaths and missing people caused by Typhoon Kalmaegi continues to rise in the Philippines. Wind gusts reached 180 km/h
At least 142 people died and 127 are missing following Typhoon Kalmaegi's passage through the central Philippines, according to official data compiled today by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
The Philippines' National Department of Civil Defense confirmed 114 deaths, in addition to 28 fatalities recorded by authorities in the province of Cebu, in the center of the country, AFP reported. The previous balance of civil protection in the Philippines showed 85 dead and 75 missing.
In Cebu, dozens of people were trapped on the roofs of homes and called for help as water rose rapidly. The provincial government declared a state of calamity to allow for the urgent mobilization of emergency funds. The province of Cebu, with 2.4 million inhabitants, was still recovering from a 6.9 magnitude earthquake that occurred in September, which caused 79 deaths.
Most of the victims died by drowning or being hit by debris, following flash floods and landslides caused by the Kalmaegi, which also destroyed houses and swept away vehicles, said on Wednesday the deputy head of the Civil Defense Office, Bernardo Rafaelito Alejandro.
Deadly winds
As it passed through the central Philippines, Kalmaegi brought winds of 130 kilometers per hour (km/h) and gusts of up to 180 km/h. The army indicated that six soldiers died when an Air Force helicopter crashed in the province of Agusan del Sur, during a humanitarian aid mission.
More than 387,000 people were evacuated from risk areas and around 3,500 passengers were stranded in almost a hundred ports due to the navigation ban. Local authorities said years of mining and poor drainage work had worsened the impact of the floods.
After crossing the South China Sea, the storm is expected to hit the coast of Vietnam and cause intense rain in northern Thailand, the region's meteorological services said. Every year, around 20 storms or typhoons hit or come close to the Philippines, with the poorest regions of the country generally being the most affected.
State of emergency
The President of the Philippines, Ferdinand Marcos Jr., yesterday declared a state of emergency in the country, after Typhoon Kalmaegi left at least 142 dead and 127 missing, in the worst disaster to hit the country this year. The declaration of a “state of national calamity” was made by Marcos, during a meeting with disaster response authorities, to assess the consequences of the typhoon. The decision allows the Philippine Government to release emergency funds more quickly and avoid food hoarding and price speculation.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Shein | France temporarily suspends platform</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/shein-franca-suspende-temporariamente-plataforma/</link><description>The French Government began a process on Wednesday to temporarily suspend Shien in the country, until the Chinese platform proves that its content complies with the law.
“On instructions from the Prime Minister, [Sébastien Lecornu], the Government is temporarily suspending Shein so that the platform can demonstrate to the authorities that all its content complies with current laws and regulations,” the French Ministry of Economy announced in a statement.
The Government committed to analyzing the situation “within 48 hours”. The executive's decision comes on the same day that Shein opened its first physical store in Paris, in a space measuring 1,200 square meters (m2).
In response, Shein said it intends to dialogue with the authorities as quickly as possible. “Customer safety and the integrity of our marketplace are our absolute priorities,” he said in a statement. Shein also announced on Wednesday the suspension of sales in France of products from external sellers, after concerns were raised about the sale of child-like sex dolls.
According to the French press, a man was detained near Marseille after receiving a child-like sex doll purchased from Shein. On Monday, the Ministry of Economy had already guaranteed that it will not hesitate to ban the platform's activities in France, if illegal activities are proven to have occurred.
At the beginning of the week, the Public Ministry opened an investigation against the Chinese company Shein for “dissemination of pornographic images or representations of minors”. In the same accusation, AliExpress is targeted for disseminating violent, pornographic or degrading images, accessible to minors. The Chinese Temu and the American Wish are also being accused.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 03:59:51</pubDate></item><item><title>China-Brazil | Ding Xuexiang calls for deepening relations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/china-brasil-ding-xuexiang-pede-aprofundamento-das-relacoes/</link><description>Chinese Vice Premier Ding Xuexiang, visiting Brazil, said on Wednesday that China has always viewed and developed its relations with Brazil from a strategic and long-term perspective and is ready to work with the country to solidly advance the construction of a China-Brazil community with a shared future. Ding made these statements during conversations with the Chief Minister of the Civil House of the Presidency of the Federative Republic of Brazil, Rui Costa, according to Xinhua.
Ding said that under the strategic guidance of the two heads of state, the construction of a Sino-Brazilian community with a shared future and the alignment of the two countries' development strategies have progressed without obstacles, and that cooperation in various fields has achieved fruitful results and bilateral relations have entered the best period in history. The deputy prime minister called on the two sides to become reliable partners on their respective paths to modernization, strengthen the alignment of development strategies, promote cooperation in key areas efficiently and pragmatically, and better support the common development and revitalization of both countries.
For his part, Costa said that the people of the two countries enjoy close ties, and the Brazilian people increasingly believe that cooperation with China has promoted Brazil's economic development and improved people's lives, in addition to improving the well-being of the Brazilian people.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 03:57:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | 80 people arrested in case of cryptocurrency fraud</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/hong-kong-detidas-80-pessoas-em-caso-de-fraude-com-criptomoedas/</link><description>Some of the main suspected perpetrators of the mega-fraud, which amounts to 1.6 billion Hong Kong dollars, are abroad
Hong Kong police announced the arrest of 80 suspects linked to one of the biggest cases of financial fraud, related to the JPEX cryptocurrency exchange platform. Police have been investigating JPEX since September 2023, which the Chinese region's securities regulator accused of suspicious activities and promoting unlicensed products.
Since then, 80 people have been arrested, 16 of whom have already been charged with crimes such as “conspiracy to commit fraud”, the police said on Wednesday, adding that the others remain the subject of investigation.
This is the largest fraud case in Hong Kong in terms of number of victims and amount of losses suffered in recent years, police authorities noted at a press conference.
The police referred to the first use of the rules introduced by Hong Kong in 2023 to prosecute crimes related to the fraudulent encouragement of investment in virtual assets. More than 2,700 complaints related to the case were received by the police, involving a total value of 1.6 billion Hong Kong dollars.
Runaway brains
Police classified the case as “very complex” and identified at least 14 key people. One of these people and two brains were abroad, the police said, adding that arrest warrants had been issued by Interpol.
The police froze assets worth more than 200 million Hong Kong dollars (belonging to the suspects. Questioned by the France-Presse news agency, the chief superintendent of the fight against crime, Ernest Wong, stated that the police authorities “will continue the investigation” and “cannot exclude the possibility of charging or detaining more people in the future”.
JPEX used advertising campaigns promoting high returns and low risks, in addition to promoting online influencers to encourage investors to deposit funds, according to police. The group transferred assets and laundered them through cryptocurrency wallets. Among those detained are social media influencers who helped with the promotion and holders of fictitious bank accounts.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 03:55:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Starbucks | 60% of the operation in China passes to Boyu Capital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/starbucks-60-da-operacao-na-china-passa-para-a-boyu-capital/</link><description>The North American multinational coffee shop Starbucks will form a joint company with the Chinese Boyu Capital to operate its stores in China, in an operation valued at around 4 billion dollars. The new entity will be 60 percent controlled by Boyu, while the North American multinational will maintain 40 percent and will continue to license the Starbucks brand and intellectual property.
The US company expects to complete the operation in the second quarter of fiscal 2026, after obtaining the necessary regulatory approvals, and highlights that the partnership reinforces its commitment to long-term growth in China, one of its largest and most dynamic markets.
According to Starbucks, the total value of the business in the Asian country will exceed US$13 billion, when including the proceeds from the sale of the majority stake, the value of the remaining stake and the current value of future payments for licenses over the next decade or more.
The new company's headquarters will remain in Shanghai, which will remain the hub of operations for the 8,000 Starbucks stores currently operating in China. The two companies plan to reach 20,000 units in the Chinese market.
“Boyu’s deep knowledge and experience in the local market will help us accelerate growth in China, especially as we expand into smaller cities and new regions,” said Brian Niccol, president and CEO of Starbucks. “We seek to combine Starbucks’ global leadership in the coffee sector with Boyu’s expertise to accelerate growth,” said Alex Wong, partner at Boyu Capital.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:36:52</pubDate></item><item><title>US admits using troops in South Korea in case of conflict with China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/eua-admitem-usar-tropas-na-coreia-do-sul-em-caso-de-conflito-com-china/</link><description>United States Secretary of War Pete Hegseth yesterday admitted the use of US troops stationed in South Korea (USFK) in the event of armed conflicts with China.
“[USFK’s] flexibility to respond to regional contingencies is something we should definitely consider,” Hegseth said. His words come at a time when the Administration of US President Donald Trump is seeking to strengthen cooperation with its allies in the Indo-Pacific region to contain China's influence and advance.
As tension in the area increases, the eventual use of these forces could be triggered by reasons related to the issue of Taiwan, which China does not exclude from invading, or due to disputes in the South China Sea. The US secretary stressed, however, that the USFK's main objective continues to be to confront any threat from North Korea.
The US Secretary of War made these statements at a press conference in Seoul, given together with the South Korean Minister of Defense, Ahn Gyu-back, after the 57th Security Consultative Meeting (SCM), the main annual defense forum between the two countries.
Pete Hegseth also praised the South Korean Government's decision to increase defense spending and invest in the development of military capabilities, such as missiles, also anticipating an improvement in the country's military technologies. “As we know, we face a dangerous security climate, even though our alliance is stronger than ever,” said the US secretary.
Nuclear Promotions
Donald Trump had said on social media last Thursday that the United States would share highly restricted technology to allow South Korea to build a nuclear-powered submarine, after meeting with South Korean President Lee Jae-myung.
Hegseth spoke on the matter yesterday, also expressing his support for this initiative to build naval equipment that would use nuclear energy to move. The Ministry of Defense indicated today, at a meeting of the Council of Ministers, that Seoul could launch the submarine in the second half of the 2030s, with its own technology, according to local news agency Yonhap.
South Korean Defense Minister Ahn Gyu-back, in turn, reaffirmed that Seoul will maintain its commitment to the denuclearization of the peninsula and rejected any plan to develop its own nuclear weapons, in accordance with the Non-Proliferation Treaty, an international agreement created to prevent the spread of nuclear weapons, promote disarmament and encourage the peaceful use of nuclear energy.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:34:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Imports | Beijing suspends 24% additional tariff on the US</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/06/importacoes-pequim-suspende-tarifa-adicional-de-24-aos-eua/</link><description>The suspension of more aggressive trade measures for a year follows the meeting between Trump and Xi last week in Busan. Additional taxes on soy are also no longer part of the tariff package
China yesterday announced the suspension for a year of a 24 percent “additional tariff” on US products, a measure that Beijing frames as part of the bilateral trade truce reached last week.
According to a statement from the Tariff Commission of the State Council, the Chinese executive, the decision, which will come into force on November 10 at 1:01 pm, aims to “implement the results and consensus reached in economic and trade consultations between China and the United States”.
“The 24 percent customs duties on US products remain suspended, and the 10 percent customs duties on US goods remain in force”, indicates a statement published on the Chinese Ministry of Finance’s electronic portal, which does not specify which goods are in question.
China will also “stop applying additional customs duties” to imports of soybeans and other North American agricultural products, starting November 10, according to another statement published by the ministry. Some of these customs duties were as high as 15 percent. The suspension extends for 12 months the moratorium on so-called “reciprocal tariffs” that Beijing had announced in March, in response to customs duties imposed by Washington.
Truce in force
The announcement confirms the implementation of the commitments made after the meeting between the Chinese President, Xi Jinping, and his North American counterpart, Donald Trump, held in Busan (South Korea) last Thursday.
At that meeting, the two leaders agreed to a one-year trade truce, which provides for the reduction of tariffs, the resumption of agricultural trade, the suspension of Beijing's controls on the export of rare earths and the temporary freezing of reciprocally imposed port fees, among other measures.
The measure coincides with the United States' decision to reduce average tariffs on Chinese products from 57 percent to 47 percent. The world's two largest economies have been in a trade conflict for several years, which has included mutual restrictions in strategic sectors such as microchips, rare earths and maritime services.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 03:31:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Typhoon Kalmaegi causes two deaths and floods</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/05/filipinas-tufao-kalmaegi-causa-dois-mortos-e-inundacoes/</link><description>With winds that reached more than 200 kilometers per hour, Kalmaegi continues to spread chaos in the Asian archipelago
Almost 400,000 people were evacuated from their homes to escape flooding caused by heavy rains and intense winds from Typhoon Kalmaegi, which swept across the archipelago yesterday and killed at least two people.
The deputy director of the Department of Civil Protection, Rafaelito Alejandro, told local radio that 387,000 people were evacuated from the path of the typhoon and that one man died after being hit by a tree that fell in the province of Bohol (center). An elderly man also drowned in the province of Leyte, in the south of the Philippines, said Danilo Atienza, head of the victim assistance team.
“The elderly man was trapped on the top floor and was unable to receive help”, reported Atienza, on DZMM radio. The typhoon made landfall from the east of the archipelago on Monday night, hitting the Dinagat Islands, in the Eastern Visayas archipelago, with wind gusts that reached 205 kilometers per hour, according to the meteorological service.
Rhon Ramos, information officer on the island of Cebu (center), told news agency France-Presse (AFP), by telephone, that some evacuation centers were also flooded. Cars floated in the flooded streets of the city of Cebu, with around one million inhabitants, according to images obtained by AFP.
Hundreds of people living in tents in camps set up after the 6.9 magnitude earthquake that struck the island in late September were also “forcibly evacuated for their own safety,” Ramos said. Philippine Red Cross Secretary General Gwendolyn Pang said many residents were trapped on rooftops by floodwaters in the coastal town of Liloan in Cebu province.
“We receive a lot of calls from people asking for rescue from roofs and houses, but it is impossible,” Pang told the Associated Press news agency. “There is a lot of debris, we see cars floating, so we have to wait for the flood to subside,” he explained.
Damn combinations
The Philippine Institute of Volcanology and Seismology warned that heavy rains could trigger volcanic mudflows on Mount Kanlaon, one of the country's 24 most active volcanoes, which has been emitting plumes of ash and steam in recent months, on the island of Negros (center).
Philippine authorities had on Monday ordered the evacuation of thousands of people and the closure of schools and public offices in the face of the approach of Kalmaegi, known locally as Tino, the 20th typhoon to hit the country in 2025. Meteorologist Charmaine Varilla predicts that “three to five” more tropical storms will hit the Philippines by the end of the year.
The La Niña climate phenomenon, which cools surface temperatures in the Pacific Ocean, is generally accompanied by a greater number of typhoons, Varilla told AFP. The Philippines is hit by around 20 typhoons and tropical storms per year, mainly during the rainy season, which generally lasts from June to November or December.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:33:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuca Roseta, fado singer: “Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/06/cuca-roseta-fadista-o-fado-e-um-samba-poesia-cantado-vindo-do-coracao/</link><description>During the pandemic, she sang for the Macau public through a video concert, but now, the fado singer gives her heart and soul to a concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra, part of the lineup for the Macau International Music Festival, next Saturday, 11th. In an interview with HM, Cuca Roseta talks about the show's lineup, her 15-year career and the truth found in her compositions.
Performs in Macau on October 11th with the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM). Tell me a little about what we can expect from this show.
Yes, we are finally going to Macau. It will be the first time because we previously did a video concert for Macau during the pandemic, and we were unable to be there physically. We now work with OCM, which is very good, and I am happy with this partnership, for being able to unite, in some way, two cultures. We are a little anxious about that fact.
The concert will have songs such as “Meu”, “Preto e Branco”, “Canção do Mar”, “Não Sei de Onde” and “Finalmente”. What does this alignment bring us?
We already had arrangements made for orchestra by Marinho de Freitas, which are extraordinary arrangements, and which will be adapted to the traditional OCM instruments. These songs are practically all written by me, lyrics and music, and tell different stories, some that I have lived myself or stories that, in some way, I have experienced someone living very closely. They are original fados. “Canção do Mar” is very old and became known in the voices of Dulce Pontes and Amália Rodrigues, and has a new arrangement. We thought it would look beautiful with OCM. Of course, there are songs that we always sing and that never leave the repertoire, linked to traditional phases of my career. There are some songs that people like and request, but we bring a completely different repertoire to what we presented at the time [in Macau, with the video concert], which was very well received. It was a concert that went very well, even though it was via video, and we received wonderful messages.
This year he released the album “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu”, which has an exclusively Brazilian repertoire, with several names in Brazilian music, such as Seu Jorge or Zeca Pagodinho. Why explore this universe, mixing it with the language of Fado?
Yes, but this year I will also release a French album with Amália Rodrigues' agent, who invited me. But “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu” came from an invitation from a great Brazilian producer to record old sambas, which have a lot to do with Fado. Even though it's a Brazilian album, all sambas, it's my saddest album of all, the most melancholic. That's why we went looking for this root of samba to find great poets and great composers that Brazil has, and who have this weight that Fado also has.
As?
Fado has a lot to do with words and composition, in fact, Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart, because there has to be this truth in the interpretation, the idea of ​​truth coming from life's experiences, in transforming the story it tells. This melancholy is in the veins of Portuguese blood and is mixed with art and music. This invitation wanted to put a fado singer to sing seriously and with the weight that Fado brings, and be able to interpret the great poets and sambas. The album [Até a Fé Se Esqueceu] has very old sambas, one of them from 1937. It is, therefore, a very strong and even very beautiful album, with great poems and composers, such as Tom Jobim, Vinicius de Morais, and wonderful partnerships with Seu Jorge and Zeca Pagodinho, who came to Fado. It's an album that made me really proud.

Therefore, it is possible to marry Fado with the joy of samba, which also has a melancholic side, right? Like the melancholy of our Fado.
In fact, when we hear the word samba we think of joy, but in fact the basis of samba is not joy. There is that phrase by Vinicius de Morais, “To make a samba beautifully you need a bit of sadness, otherwise you won’t make a samba”. So that's where the beauty of this work lies, which goes to the roots of samba and shows that there aren't that many differences between the melancholy at the root of samba and the melancholy of Fado. It's a nostalgic and melancholic album, it doesn't bring that joy. It can bring hope, and we can say that some themes bring with them this hope, which we find in Brazilian culture and drums. Because they literally put their sadness on the skirt wheel and on the drums, right? They transform sadness into dance and music, but in this work we don't see that type of samba.
Cuca also has a previous album, “Cabo Verde Nha Cretcheu”, so it can be said that she has explored, in her career, the different Portuguese-speaking sounds, going beyond Fado, mixing sounds?
This album didn't come from my will, and I think [it's a sign] that life takes me, deep down. This album was born from a tour I took across the nine islands of Cape Verde with a live recording of the mornas I sang on each island, as I sang the traditional mornas of each island. Between one island and another there are very different moraines. What I did was, after my Fado concerts, I sang two mornas and then we compiled all the songs in Creole in celebration of the fact that I was the first international artist to do the nine islands in a row. But I was also in Goa and did my concert in Concanim. I find it easy and enjoy learning the traditional songs of the countries where I am going to sing. I already sang in Moscow and learned a Russian song; I learned the songs of Goa, and in Georgia, in Tblisi, I also learned a song. It's a treat I make when I travel around the world taking Fado. But morna is wonderful and there really are similarities between this musical genre, and I wanted to bring this encounter between Fado and morna to Cape Verdeans, and this album came about, which is beautiful.
Once it goes to Macau, can we expect a song in Cantonese, or Mandarin?
Yes. By chance, I had already spoken to my manager to contact someone in this regard, so that we could discover a traditional song that I could learn.
Last year, he celebrated 15 years of career. How do you review your career, which began with the albums “Cuca Roseta” and “Raiz”?
In fact, it was great to celebrate 15 years at MEO Arena [the concert hall in Lisbon], and be able to revisit all the albums since the first. “Raiz” opened something that is rarer, which is the fado singer composing and writing her lyrics. This was a record that went wonderfully well and, from then on, it was good, because in this search for the truth that Fado has, being able to compose and write your own lyrics always means giving a little more of yourself. Each person composes and writes in their own way, and when they can do it, it is always a bit like the lines on the palm of their hand, that is, it is something unique. In this search that people make to follow standards to achieve success, I believe that success exists when we are not afraid to follow our voice and our instinct, what comes from our heart, tell our stories and sing our melodies without fear. In this way we end up becoming unique. Although it is not usual in Fado for a fado singer to compose and write, it was nice to see that my songs became important to many fans. Sometimes I have great composers and poets [to collaborate with me], but I think [writing and composing] brings out this side of the person being more truthful. My poems can never be compared to those of the great poets I have sung, but I think people feel that I am more in my own skin. In a way, this touches and moves them. Celebrating 15 years of career was the closing of a cycle and the beginning of another, and it was great to return to the “roots”, and realize that that was where the “gunpowder” lay, in the sense of not being afraid of ourselves.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 05:24:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Hui So-ying, protagonist of the film “Ah Ying”: “Representing is being human”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/30/hui-so-ying-protagonista-do-filme-ah-ying-representar-e-ser-se-humano/</link><description>In 1983, Hong Kong cinema, through the lens of Allen Fong, revealed “Ah Ying”, a film that portrays the hard life of a girl who sells fish in the market and dreams of becoming an actress. That girl was Hui So-ying and “Ah Ying” was inspired by her life. HM spoke to the actress on the sidelines of “Making Waves – 2nd Hong Kong Cinema Exhibition”, which took place this weekend in Lisbon
 
How did you get involved in this film project?
The main reason I got involved in this film was because my theater teacher passed away. So I felt like I needed to do something to honor him, because he was the one who taught me how to act. So I tried to be an actress. Later, when [director] Allen Fong met me, he found my life story interesting, and he also ended up meeting some of my family members. Then he asked if they were also interested in participating in the film, which led to many of them also ending up joining the project. The film also shows the environment in which my teacher lived, it is a portrait of experiences and stories lived by me and my teacher.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in those times. How did you prepare for the character?
The beauty of this film is closely related to the collaborations that were made, particularly in photography and costumes. It took many collaborations to create the beauty that exists in the film. It was hard work taking on the character [of Ah Ying], because the story was designed to describe some of my past experiences, and that's what the director wanted to do. But that was difficult for me, because there were some things I didn't want to face, but I had to. Of course, I later realized that, deep down, it was nothing, and I even felt relieved after finishing filming. Thinking about whether the story was a form of art or reality, when I was performing, I had to enter the situation of the moment because, in fact, the [real] episode had already passed, but I had to have certain feelings again during the performance. As an actress, it was a big test.
“Ah Ying” is considered one of the great films of the so-called “New Wave” of Hong Kong cinema. During the screening, did you expect the film to be successful?
I didn't think about it, but throughout the project I thought that Allen Fong was a very daring director, because a film of this kind had never been made in the entire history of Hong Kong cinema. It's a kind of “docudrama”, and he had the strength and courage to innovate the way he filmed it, which, at the time, was unprecedented.
What was the biggest challenge you faced in this film?
It was having to return to my old self. There were things I didn't want to face and I had to face them again, with the same feeling I had at that time.
Many years have passed between 1983 and the present. Looking back, what meaning did this film have for you, as a person and actress?
In fact, after seeing the film, I saw it as just a story. For me, acting is being human, every day is a performance.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in the 1980s and has received a restored version. What do you think this project can bring to a younger audience watching the film today?
This year the film was shown several times, and I always ask the same question, whether people don't understand the film or whether they think it can't be immersive enough. In fact, given my experience, most younger viewers responded that this is not the case, that the film is quite real. I don't think this film is outdated or out of fashion just because times have progressed or society has changed. I don't think so.
“Ah Ying” closed, in Lisbon, the second edition of “Making Waves – Hong Kong Film Festival”. How do you feel about seeing this film shown in Portugal?
I found it interesting. I never thought that the film could be shown at this exhibition, I don't know if it was because there was a restored copy. Before this new version it was more difficult to display it. The public can see a film that shows family relationships experienced in the 80s, and I think that the film can be immersive [in the theme], when it addresses family conflicts, because everyone has a family. Watching the film, you may wonder what your relationship with your family is like. Of course, I also hope you learned more about Hong Kong. But, despite this film taking place in the 80s, it focuses a lot on family and interpersonal relationships.
Is there an episode from filming that left an impression on you?
There were several moments throughout the film, but the one that left the biggest impression on me was the last scene, in the interview, in which I was talking to a chair, but it was as if I were talking to my teacher. When I see this scene again I am always moved, because my teacher has already passed away, but all of this still makes a huge impression on me.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:42:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra: “The heroic relationships” of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/03/jorge-figueira-arquitecto-e-academico-da-universidade-de-coimbra-as-relacoes-heroicas-de-macau/</link><description>He has been writing and thinking about architecture for a long time, and Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra, has been doing so in Macau since then. After a session this week in which he highlighted the former Fai Chi Kei public housing complex, by Manuel Vicente, Jorge Figueira addresses the legacy of Nuno Portas today at the Rui Cunha Foundation
 
Participate today in the conference “Nuno Portas: from Architecture to Urbanism, from Man to City”. What legacy did this Portuguese architect leave?
Nuno Portas is someone who, at the end of the 50s, had a critical activity that was completely innovative and pioneering in the Portuguese context. Then, in the 60s, he had a more international activity, having been the first to publicize the work of Siza Vieira. It was there that he had his first contacts with Spanish and Italian architects, mainly. During those years he also wrote two books that were also unusual, such as “Architecture for Today”, in 1964, and “City as Architecture”, in 1969. They were also an extraordinary way of trying to understand what was happening in terms of international currents in architecture. But later he also had an [important] activity as an architect alongside Nuno Teotónio Pereira, namely in the work on the Church of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, in Lisbon, and in a house in Vila Viçosa. Then, on April 25, 1974, he was appointed Secretary of State for Housing and Urbanism and launched SAAL – Outpatient Services for Local Support, a completely revolutionary social housing program, in keeping with the spirit of the time. Afterwards, Nuno Portas dedicated himself more to urban planning issues and not so much to architecture. He was linked to the beginning of Expo 98. He ended up being someone who, in the last 20 years of his work, began to have more scientific and sociological concerns, and less artistic ones. It's something he had from the beginning, but later it became the center of his activity.
Did Nuno Portas have any relationship with Macau?
I think that the relationships would not be as intense compared to other architects and contexts, but we know that Nuno Portas was in Macau at the invitation of the Government for a conference, between 2001 and 2002. It is interesting because from this passage we have echoes of what happened, such as his surprise when discovering Manuel Vicente's Ellen Liang orphanage, which he did not know about. It was Manuel Vicente's first work in Macau, in the 60s, and we know that Nuno Portas was moved when visiting this work, especially the small chapel that exists in the orphanage. It's interesting because there was no direct relationship between Manuel Vicente and Nuno Portas, they are figures at very different poles, and even opposites. There is also an interesting and positive reference to the Siza plan [Vieira, Plano de Expansão da Cidade de Macau (Areia Preta e Porto Exterior, 1982), which is being built when Nuno Portas visits Macau. It is interesting that he commented on this plan because in the 60s and 70s the relationship between Nuno Portas and Siza Vieira was no longer the same, and the fact that he made complimentary references to Siza is very interesting.
He was a student of Nuno Portas. What other aspects of your career or personality can you highlight?
I also worked with him. He was a cultured man, very intelligent and with an overwhelming memory. He was someone who liked to provoke, but in a good way, to argue, to contradict. I was lucky enough to maintain a decades-long dialogue with him, and it is this personal knowledge that I will pass on. I also notice that he was a man very close to the power in Lisbon, to the parties, but always very independent. He was a personal friend of Jorge Sampaio, he was Secretary of State, but he never had a major political role. On the one hand, this is due to his independence, but on the other he was such a controversial and intelligently restless figure, that I think power was also scared of him.
This week he also spoke at the conference “Lisbon, Porto, Macau, Maputo: Heroic Collective Housing from the 60s &amp; 70s”. How do you describe Macau’s public housing projects in those years?
There are many architects I could talk about, but I focused on the work of Manuel Vicente in Macau, namely the public housing complex in Fai Chi Kei, which was demolished and later gave rise to the project by Rui Leão and Carlota Bruni. I didn't specifically talk about Portuguese or Macanese architects, we also have names like, for example, José Maneiras. Especially because Portuguese architects have always been few in Portugal, and from the 1950s there were around 150, later increasing greatly in number. But I paid [at the conference] a tribute to the Portuguese architects who built during that period, because in a complex territory and with its vicissitudes, different from those that existed in Portugal, they knew how to carry out extraordinary architectural experiments in the field of public housing. I tried to demonstrate what was happening in Lisbon, Porto, Macau and Lourenço Marques, now Maputo, in different ways. In Macau, relationships were established, which I call heroic, in the sense that they were relationships of experimental architecture, in which people had to adapt, have their own spirit. These are architectures that already have a bit of history, as 50 or 60 years have passed, but the examples we find in these cities continue to be remarkable.
What projects do you highlight from these years?
I spoke about the “Pantera Cor-de-Rosa” housing development, by Gonçalo Byrne, in Chelas, Lisbon. I showed “Cinco Fingers”, by Vítor Figueiredo, also from Lisbon, and “Bairro da Bouça”, by Siza Vieira, in Porto. I showed the Fai Chi Kei complex, by Manuel Vicente, and a project by Pancho Guedes in Mozambique. Despite being distant in time, these are architectures that remain fundamental references from a cultural and architectural point of view. There is a kind of narrative luck in being able to talk about such different places, and with such different architects, and show how they had this heroic, experimental, moving, even radical side that the architecture of that period in particular had.
Has Macau had a positive evolution with regard to the supply of public housing?
I arrived in August and have been visiting the territory in recent years, so I have been following this process a little. Macau is, obviously, an extraordinary territory and due to the coexistence of very different cultures when it comes to housing, which here has a scale and expression completely different from that of Portugal. In Portugal there is an aversion to public housing towers, it has always been something unusual and the results that are known have not been successful for various reasons. But in Macau this is exactly what we see, public housing in towers and with a very strong expression. This has to do with the characteristics of the territory and also with a certain culture in China and Hong Kong. This does not mean that everything being built in Macau is good, there are towers and buildings with less interesting solutions or that result from a certain repetition. But there is no city that only has good architecture or good public housing. The challenge is to solve the housing problem on a large scale, something that must be studied and thought about. It is beautiful and overwhelming to see that Macau is a territory that grows day after day and it is exciting to observe this from an architectural point of view as well. That's what I'm doing, working on future projects.
Analysis projects, or academic ones?
Yes, I'm a professor and researcher at the University of Coimbra and a columnist for the Público newspaper, so my job is to analyze and investigate. I've already published a lot about Macau and I want to go back to some points that I left unresolved, so to speak. I am very encouraged by everything I have seen and the people I have spoken to, and perhaps I will increase my work on the territory from an academic and research point of view.
At a time when Portugal has a chronic housing problem, with a lack of public housing, could Macau be an example?
Not directly, because of the typological issue of the housing tower. It might not be a welcome model in the Portuguese context. But without a doubt, Portugal needs to learn from other experiences and other territories and needs to find solutions. Certainly, what is happening in Hong Kong and Macau are experiences that are very interesting to know, not to replicate, but to understand that this is a global problem [the lack of housing].
Remember Nuno Portas
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will host today, starting at 6:30 pm, the conference “Nuno Portas: from architecture to urbanism, from man to city”, with Jorge Figueira. It will be time to talk about a journey that the recently deceased architect began in 1959, with a text about the new generation of the Modern Movement in Portugal. Texts followed in the 60s and 70s with “scientific approaches”, with Nuno Portas wandering between architecture and urbanism, always in a reflective way. Nuno Portas was a “multifaceted figure, best known for launching the SAAL social housing program, which is still the subject of research and an example today”, describes Jorge Figueira in a note. The speaker is linked to the Center for Social Studies and the Department of Architecture of the University of Coimbra.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 23:33:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Anabela Santiago, academic: “China is reformist and moderate”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/anabela-santiago-academica-a-china-e-reformista-e-moderada/</link><description>Anabela Santiago has just defended her doctoral thesis at the University of Aveiro that analyzes how China has positioned itself, in recent decades, as an important actor in “Global Health Governance”. Today, Beijing is looking for “alternative mechanisms” of cooperation in the “Global South” and is trying to build an alternative model to the World Health Organization
 
 
Let’s start with the concept of global health governance (GGS). Is it a more contemporary concept or one related to the post-World War II period and the founding of the World Health Organization (WHO)? Who have been the main actors in this governance until China's growth?
GGS is a concept whose prominence and relevance has grown significantly in the 21st century, largely driven by economic globalization and global interconnection. Although global health has always transcended national borders, requiring multidisciplinary approaches and international cooperation, it has only been since the 1990s that greater awareness has been made of it. Historically, GGS has been predominantly influenced by Western powers and neoliberal values. The main actors in this governance, until the rise of China, were historically marked by interventions from entities such as the WHO and non-governmental organizations, predominantly North American and European.
One of the conclusions of his doctoral thesis is that China has gradually positioned itself in this leadership. When and why did this positioning begin?
Yes, China has progressively positioned itself as a key player in the evolution of the GGS system. Although it is not possible to pinpoint an exact start date, China has evolved from a relatively isolated country to a major player in the global political, economic and technological arenas. Its growing economic and political influence also represents a change in the historical dynamics of the GGS, as in the 1960s China tried to play a role in humanitarian health assistance in neighboring countries and in Africa. The thesis highlights that China's experience can be seen as an example of what is achievable when a State chooses its own path instead of a pre-established model, aligning with the prediction of the 21st century as the “Asian Century”.
Did the years of the pandemic influence this position? In what way?
The Covid-19 pandemic has highlighted the need for global health cooperation, as well as the potential consequences of failing to prioritize global health. The thesis explores the evolution of the Health Silk Road before and after the pandemic, indicating that the years of the pandemic allowed for greater awareness of the need for instruments such as the Health Silk Road as platforms for more effective cooperation between Nations. Although not detailed in this specific section, it is implicit that the pandemic has intensified China's role in health diplomacy and health development assistance.
Looking at the internal reforms that China has carried out in the health sector, which ones do you highlight as the most important?
In the thesis, I address the reforms of China's healthcare system and highlight that the Chinese governance model is a unique combination of market-oriented economic reforms and state-led development, incorporating elements of neoliberalism and authoritarianism in political issues in general, with the healthcare sector being no different from the rest. One of China's contributions mentioned, recognized by the WHO, is its primary health care model based on the recognized good practice of “barefoot doctors”. Furthermore, the thesis analyzes the main reform policies and their progress and challenges in the period 2009-2018, which include primary healthcare reforms, hospital and pharmaceutical reform. The “Healthy China 2030” program is also an important and ambitious benchmark for China's domestic health reforms, also covering social determinants.
Is Beijing's intention to create an alternative entity to the WHO, or simply to create an alternative movement that can coexist with the WHO, in the context of its relationship with the Global South? How could this work?
The thesis suggests that China adopts a “dual approach”: while integrating into existing global structures, it simultaneously forges alternative paths, particularly through regional alliances such as the BRICS and partnerships with the Global South. This indicates an intention to create an alternative movement that can coexist with and complement the role of the WHO, rather than a direct alternative entity. China demonstrates a clear commitment to aligning the objectives of the “Belt and Road” initiative with the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals, showing its willingness to present these initiatives as complements to the cooperation mechanisms already existing in the international liberal order. President Xi Jinping's vision of a “Community of Shared Future for Humanity”, which includes the notion of “Global Health Community for All”, also points to a new perspective in the scope of international cooperation.
Masks, vaccines and Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM): what products or instruments are used by China to position itself as an increasingly global actor in GGS?
The thesis highlights that China is an indispensable provider of global public health goods, essential for the supply chain of products, such as masks and vaccines. TCM is also mentioned as one of China's great contributions to global health governance, with its treatments derived from Chinese herbs, some of which were already recognized by the WHO in 2017. Furthermore, Chinese medical assistance and medical teams sent to other regions of the globe are important instruments of Chinese health diplomacy.
In creating an alternative movement or reality to the WHO, could China be taking advantage of the lack of full representation in that same WHO, or gaps in its functioning?
The thesis does not directly address whether China is taking advantage of a lack of full representation in the WHO or gaps in its functioning. However, she emphasizes that the work aims to fill a gap in scientific knowledge regarding the health governance paradigm from a non-Western and liberal perspective, emphasizing China as an actor in the Global South. This suggests that China seeks to strengthen alternative models that can offer more personalized solutions to health challenges, different from those advocated by Western countries, positioning itself as a moderate reformist actor.
How has the European Union's (EU) foreign policy towards China affected or influenced the country's position in global health governance?
In the thesis, the fourth publication, entitled “Challenges on the European Union-China cooperation in higher education from ‘people-to-people dialogue’ perspective: The case of health-related joint projects”, explores cooperation in higher education, in particular that which includes projects related to health. It appears, therefore, that, despite strategic and economic dialogue, the deterioration of EU-China bilateral relations has intensified, with the Commission assuming a decline in enthusiasm due to “China's countermeasures to EU sanctions on human rights, economic coercion and trade measures against the single market, and China's position in the war in Ukraine”. Although challenges and tensions are recognized, cooperation in higher education, including health projects, is seen as part of a broader framework of building a strategic partnership between the EU and China. However, it is clear that there is no long tradition of health cooperation between the EU and China in higher education, and that there are few joint projects compared to the general picture. It is suggested that both the EU and China should make more efforts to align medical study curricula and promote more joint research in areas related to health, infectious diseases, among others.
In the Trump 2.0 era, and without a pandemic, what could China's role be in global health governance?
Although the thesis will be published this year, it focuses on the period leading up to and including the pandemic, where I do not directly speculate on a future scenario of “Trump 2.0” without a pandemic. However, the thesis argues that China is not just a participant but a moderate reformist force in shaping global health norms. Regardless of future political scenarios, its growing economic and political influence, strategic health diplomacy, domestic reforms and initiatives such as the Health Silk Road will continue to shape its role in global health governance. The vision of a “Global Health Community for All” also remains a guiding principle for China's efforts.
Does this power of China in the GGS occur more with bilateral or multilateral agreements?
The thesis suggests that China's power in global health governance is manifested through both bilateral and multilateral agreements, but with an increasing emphasis on certain forms of cooperation that strengthen its role in the Global South and through alternative mechanisms. Although the thesis does not explicitly quantify the predominance between bilateral and multilateral, the focus on regional alliances (BRICS) and partnerships with the Global South (which often involve bilateral agreements and group cooperation initiatives) and the Health Silk Road indicate a hybrid approach.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 23:46:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied the right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on staying, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (even in 2011 the Faro City Council wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
The gentlemen we are talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a member of the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing | Diogo Craveiro with bronze at the figure skating world championships</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/24/pequim-diogo-craveiro-com-bronze-nos-mundiais-de-patinagem-artistica/</link><description>Portuguese skater Diogo Craveiro won this Thursday the bronze medal in the free variant of the World Figure Skating Championship, taking place in Beijing.
Diogo Craveiro, European runner-up, closed the podium with a score of 223.39 in the total of the short and long program events, behind the Spaniards Hector Diez Severino (243.44) and Arnau Pérez Montero (231.55), gold and silver respectively.
Diogo Craveiro's medal is the fourth for the Portuguese team in Beijing, after the world titles of Madalena Costa, first ever in the senior women's category, and Rita Azinheira (junior) and the bronze of João Pedro Cruz (junior).</description><pubDate>2025-10-24 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Mercedes remains aware of the value of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/23/gp-mercedes-continua-consciente-do-valor-de-macau/</link><description>The absence of Mercedes-AMG from the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup entry list is probably the biggest disappointment of the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix. The German manufacturer, who won for the first time in Macau in 1956, cited the new torque sensors as the reason for his absence, but there is evidence that other factors also played a part in the decision.
For the first time since the creation of the FIA ​​GT World Cup in 2015, Mercedes-AMG will not be represented in the race. The reason, officially, is the change in the technical regulations, with the imposition of torque sensors, a requirement that Mercedes-AMG and its customer teams claim they have not been able to prepare adequately to compete competitively. At least, the Hong Kong teams, GruppeM Racing and Craft-Bamboo Racing, had intentions of returning to the Macao SAR race this year.
“This decision was taken together with our teams”, explained Stefan Wendl, responsible for Mercedes-AMG Customer Racing, in a statement shared with the press. "The additional technical and budgetary costs associated with the recently introduced torque sensors are, unfortunately, unaffordable for us. Together with the teams that normally compete in Macau, we carefully evaluated all available options. In the end, we came to the conclusion that, given the current conditions, it would not be possible to guarantee a sufficient level of preparation to ensure a competitive overall package."
Neither of the two Hong Kong-based teams has any experience with torque sensors, Mercedes-AMG knew since March that it would have to solve this problem if it wanted to return to the Guia Circuit. However, he did nothing in this regard. On the other hand, the Mercedes-AMG team competing in the FIA ​​World Endurance Championship (WEC) this year, Iron Lynx, faced difficulties when the MagCanica sensors did not integrate correctly with Magneti Marelli's ECU software. But this is not the whole story,
Other “obstacles”
Mercedes-AMG is in a transition phase, moving away from its former long-time partner, HWA, to establish its own internal competition division, called Affalterbach Racing GmbH. However, in this transition phase, the brand continues to use HWA engineers, despite many of this company's staff having already moved to the brand's new official structure, and to support the sale of material to its customers, which is seen by many as an uncomfortable situation.
On the other hand, the Mercedes-AMG GT3 is reaching the end of its life, with the Stuttgart brand developing another car for the category, the details of which remain secret, based on the Concept AMG GT Track Sport, and whose arrival on the market is expected in 2027. Although Mercedes-AMG continues to invest energy, money and resources in its projects in the GT3 category in this transition phase, the reality is that the brand's focus is on the future and not on the present. The high cost of introducing these torque sensors, without guarantees of reliability, would have forced Mercedes-AMG Customer Racing to make major commitments at a time when it has internal obstacles to overcome.
Guaranteed return
This absence of the German brand marks the end of a series of victories for the Mercedes-AMG GT3. On the streets of Macau, the car, which is now in its second evolution, after its launch in 2015, achieved five World Cup victories, out of a possible seven, the most recent being in 2024 with the German Maro Engel. In the pandemic years, from 2020 to 2022, in which the FIA ​​did not hold the World Cup, the three-pointed star brand won all three editions of the Macau GT Cup.
Therefore, it is no surprise that “the FIA ​​GT World Cup continues to be an attractive event for Mercedes-AMG, both from a sporting and strategic point of view, and we look back and see a long and successful history in Macau”, explained Stefan Wendl, taking the opportunity to wish “all participants in Macau an exciting and successful racing weekend”.
Despite the absence of Mercedes-AMG, the entry list for the FIA ​​GT World Cup, which will take place from 13 to 16 November, will feature sixteen cars from six giants of the automotive industry: Audi, BMW, Ferrari, Lamborghini, McLaren and Porsche.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 23:51:47</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Race week approaches</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/gp-macau-semana-de-corridas-aproxima-se/</link><description>It already smells like a Grand Prix in the city. On Friday, the containers with the sixteen cars from the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be unloaded in the paddock and, after the official stickers have been placed, they will be transported to Praça do Tap Seac, where they will be on display, along with the bikes from the 57th Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, until Sunday.
This year's edition features no less than thirty-two national flags, which will be raised by competitors from the three FIA ​​World Cups and the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour during the packed program of the 72nd Macau Grand Prix. There could have been thirty-three if Serbian Dušan Borković, winner of the 2024 Guia Race, had not been replaced this week by Spaniard Pepe Oriola in one of GOAT Racing's three Hondas.
The FIA ​​Formula Regional (FR) World Cup, which is being held for the second time after the debut edition in 2024, has fifteen countries or special administrative regions represented, including Macau. In its first edition, the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup features thirteen nationalities on the entry list, while the eighth FIA GT World Cup will be contested by drivers from ten countries or special administrative regions.
Therefore, the flags of South Africa, Germany, Argentina, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, China, South Korea, Denmark, United Arab Emirates, Spain, United States of America, Philippines, France, Hong Kong, Hungary, India, Indonesia, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Macau, Mexico, Poland, United Kingdom, Sweden, Switzerland, Thailand, Chinese Taipei, Turkey, Uruguay and Vietnam will be seen.
Highlight is the absence of the Portuguese flag among the pilots. You have to go back to the beginning of the 1970s to find such a low presence of Portuguese-born pilots at the event. In addition to young Tiago Rodrigues, veterans of the territory Rui Valente and Jerónimo Badaraco will be present, both in the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. The universe of Lusophony is completed with the Brazilian Ethan Nobels, who will make his debut at the Guia Circuit in the F4 race.
Couceiro and Lamy present
After being the Race Director of the first edition of the FIA ​​FR World Cup, Rui Marques is one hundred percent focused on the Formula 1 World Championship, where he has carried out these functions since last year's Macau Grand Prix. In his place will be Simon Gnana-Pragasam, who performs this role in the FIA ​​Formula 2 and Formula 3 Championships. The Briton will also drive the first Formula 4 World Cup in history. Dino Lodola will be the Race Director of the Guia Race, while the Czech Miroslav Bartos will have this role in the GT race and the only motorcycle race, while the experienced Chinese Zhang Tao will be at the helm of the GT Cup – Great Bay Race (GT4) and the Macau Roadsport Challenge.
Two well-known faces from national motorsport will also be present in Macau again, now retired from the tracks, but with other roles on the international scene: Pedro Lamy and Pedro Couceiro. The runner-up in the 1992 Formula 3 Macau Grand Prix, and the first driver to score points in the Formula 1 world championship, Lamy will once again be present as Stewards' Driver Advisor in the FR and Guia Races, a role he has already played in the Guia Circuit and in Formula 1, sharing this role with former F1 driver Vitantonio Liuzzi, who will perform this role in the GT and F4 races.
Pedro Couceiro, who, like Pedro Lamy, competed on the streets of Macau in Formula 3 in the 1990s, will be the driver of the Safety Car in the three FIA ​​World Cups and the Guia Race, which this year will be sponsored by BMW Concessionaires (Macau). The former Portuguese driver takes on this position in the FIA ​​World Endurance Championship (WEC) and was previously in the Macao SAR in these roles.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:22:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Football | Shao Jiayi is the new coach</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/07/futebol-shao-jiayi-e-o-novo-seleccionador/</link><description>Shao Jiayi is China's new football coach, replacing Serbian Dejan Djurdjevic, who held the position on an interim basis since June, the federation said yesterday in a statement published on its website. The organization states that when choosing Shao Jiayi, aged 45, in a process that included “several Chinese and foreign candidates”, “the experience and lessons learned from the appointment of other national team coaches” were taken into account.
In June, the Chinese Football Federation (CFA) fired Croatian Branko Ivankovic, who had been hired in February 2024 after having led Iran to the 2006 World Cup and also for his experience in winning titles in China with Shandong Luneng.
Branko Ivankovic's dismissal came following China's elimination from the 2026 World Cup, taking place in the United States, Mexico and Canada, and extended to 48 teams, after the 1-0 defeat to Indonesia. The elimination was a setback for Chinese football, which has not returned to a World Cup since its only participation in 2002, in South Korea and Japan, and, at the time, the then midfielder Shao Jiayi was one of the highlights of that team.
His performance at the World Cup caught the attention of Western clubs, and Shao ended up signing for Bundesliga side 1860 Munich that same season, where he remained until 2006. Shao then continued his career in Germany, playing for Energie Cottbus (2006-2011) and Duisburg (2011), before returning to his childhood club, Beijing Guoan, and retiring in 2015 as a legend.
He later worked with China's youth teams, rising to the position of assistant coach before taking charge of Qingdao West Coast, his first experience as a head coach. It leaves the team in ninth place in the Chinese Super League, after recording nine wins, ten draws and ten defeats this season.</description><pubDate>2025-11-07 04:06:56</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Entry lists presented did not disappoint</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/16/gp-macau-listas-de-inscritos-apresentadas-nao-desapontaram/</link><description>Last Monday, the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix presented the 72nd edition of the biggest sporting event in the territory. In total, there will be seven grids of GT, touring cars, single-seaters and motorcycles that will provide, between qualifying races and races, a total of eleven unpredictable battles for victory in the always charismatic and world-respected Guia Circuit
The Macao SAR will have 19 riders in total, spread across four races in the program, as it will not have riders in either the GT race, the Motorcycle Grand Prix or the Guia Race. The territory will be represented by Charles Leong Hon Chio at the Macau Grand Prix – FIA FR World Cup. The champion of this season's PRO class of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia moves on to Formula Regional, a category that has not been raced since 2020, when it was still called F3 (!) in Asia.
Tiago Rodrigues, in his third participation in the event, and Marcus Cheong, in his second, will defend the colors of the Macao SAR in the first edition of the F4 World Cup, a race that will feature seven former F4 champions or equivalent. The rest of the territory's delegation will compete in the GT Cup – Great Bay Race, with seven drivers, and in the Macau Roadsport Challenge, with nine.
We have to go back to the beginning of the 1970s to find such a low presence of Portuguese drivers in a Grand Prix. In addition to young Tiago Rodrigues, veterans of the territory Rui Valente and Jerónimo Badaraco will be present, both in the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. The universe of Lusophony is completed with the Brazilian Ethan Nobels, who will make his debut at the Guia Circuit in the F4 race.
Portugal's last representation in the race dates back to the 2022 Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, when André Pires and Sheridan Morais overcame mandatory confinement, with Morais achieving a podium, a unique feat for Portuguese motorcycling. In cars, the last participation was in 2019, when Tiago Monteiro drove a Honda Civic Type-R TCR in the Guia Race.
Interestingly, at a time when there is an increase in female participation in motorsport events worldwide, there is not a single lady among the more than one hundred and sixty drivers registered in the Grand Prix.
Mercedes smudges the paint
After two years with pelotons with two dozen GT3 cars, the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup is once again below that benchmark number. Fortunately, the sixteen cars from six different manufacturers, including the returning McLaren, will be driven by drivers with world-class credentials. Well-known names from Macau, such as Edoardo Mortara or Raffaele Marciello, joined by the new hero of Chinese motorsport, the winner of the 24 Hours of Le Mans, Ye Yifei, alleviate any disappointments. If Audi Sport Asia, at a time when the Ingolstadt brand is disinvesting in GT races, had backed down, we would have fewer cars than in the 2018 edition, where only fifteen machines lined up.
The introduction of torque sensors in this year's race – a costly decision made entirely by the FIA ​​– was at the heart of Mercedes-AMG's decision not to participate in the event. The German brand's business model involves registering cars in partnership with teams from the region at the event. In Southeast Asia, cars are constantly on the move via containerized transport, leaving little opportunity for conversion work and sensor testing, which is imperative for Mercedes-AMG. Everyone is certain that the Stuttgart brand will return to the Guia Circuit in the near future, but this year Maro Engel will not be able to defend the crown won last year.
Classics maintain their aura
With Michael Rutter's absence confirmed, there was a lot of apprehension about the entry list for the Motorcycle Grand Prix, but the presence of Davey Todd, last year's winner, and Peter Hickman will keep the race on the international radar. Twelve countries, all European, will be represented on a grid that this year will feature four newcomers, while of the four brands present, BMW and Honda make up more than 70% of the twenty entries.
Notably, no rider competes on a Kawasaki, marking the first time this decade that the company, which next year celebrates 130 years since its founding, has not had a presence in Asia's premier motorcycle road race.
At a time when Tourist racing is experiencing a less vigorous moment worldwide, the Guia Race already has twenty-four cars registered, three of which will still have to be filled by drivers to be nominated. The presence of the stars of the FIA ​​TCR World Tour, which is once again decided on the local circuit, is always synonymous with a good show on the track.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 02:48:16</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau: First names and first questions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/gp-macau-primeiros-nomes-e-primeiras-duvidas/</link><description>October is usually the month of preparations for the Macau Grand Prix. With the championships coming to an end all over the world, attention turns to the Macao SAR's big event, which this year will take place from the 13th to the 16th of November
 
After Marcos Cheong and Vernice Lau raced in the Chinese Formula 4 Championship race, this weekend it is Tiago Rodrigues' turn to pick up the helmet again to compete in the closing race of the Chinese competition season, on the circuit in the neighboring city of Zhuhai. The former Chinese champion of the discipline has been away from single-seater racing since participating in the Middle East Formula 4 Championship at the beginning of the year, but his experience could prove to be an asset in defending the territory's colors at the Guia Circuit.
Twenty of the Mygale M21-F4 single-seaters from the Chinese championship will be overhauled after this race at the Zhuhai International Circuit and handed over to technicians appointed by the French Motor Sport Federation (FFSA), who will put them on the track in the first edition of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup, in Macau. This is the same model used in the French Formula 4 Championship.
Some names of the bikes
Michael Rutter's absence from the entry list for this year's Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix is ​​now a certainty. However, through the specialized press, the first names that will shape the only road race on the Asian continent are beginning to become known.
Practically confirmed are the presence of Davey Todd, winner of last year's edition, and Peter Hickman, the motorcyclist who chases Rutter's record of victories and who should be practically recovered from the injuries suffered in the accident on the Isle of Man. Both will drive the official competitive BMW M1000RR from 8TEN Racing. Rob Hodson, SMT Racing driver, has also guaranteed his presence in the Macao SAR, usually being one of the strong candidates for the Top 5 in the race.
But not only renowned names are tested. Among the debutants already confirmed is ramp driver Maurizio Bottalico. The San Marino driver, who reached the podium at the Manx Grand Prix, follows in the footsteps of other great Italian names in 21st century road racing — such as Stefano Bonetti, Luca Gottardi or Alex Polita — by taking on the most famous and feared race in the East.
According to the Road Racing News portal, there will be more newcomers to the Guia Circuit this year, such as Mitch Rees, a driver with several titles in New Zealand, Ryan Whitehall, a driver from the Isle of Wight, and the new holder of the Frohburger Dreieck lap record in the Supersport category, Paul Jordan.
Questions in the GT
Stéphane Ratel, founder and CEO of SRO Motorsports Group — the company that co-organizes the FIA ​​GT World Cup Macau Grand Prix — has been one of the most critical voices regarding the introduction of torque sensors in GT3 racing. However, the FIA ​​decided in favor of its use in the Guia Circuit World Cup, and the French businessman spoke about the matter for the first time.
"The teams competing in Macau are mostly from Asia, where torque sensors have never been used. The lack of experience could affect the sporting balance, and that's why I opposed their use", said Stéphane Ratel to the German magazine Motorsport Aktuell, adding that he does not believe this is the way forward.
Although the SRO Motorsports Group is co-organizer of the event and has a Balance of Performance (BoP) recognized worldwide, in the last two years the Macau BoP has been determined by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA's BoP was subject to a series of criticisms, with teams and drivers – particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main losers – publicly expressing their displeasure at the differences in pace. For this reason, the FIA ​​decided to introduce these expensive sensors, installed on the cars' transmission shafts, which represent the most accurate tool for measuring the power transmitted to the wheels.
“Some manufacturers supported the idea, but others, like Mercedes, were against it,” said Stéphane Ratel. "As a result, we lost some cars from the entry list. To be clear: I look at this issue pragmatically, not dogmatically. Last year in Macau, three or four manufacturers could have won without these torque sensors. In 2025 we will see if this technology is really useful", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:11:25</pubDate></item></channel></rss>