<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>India threatens “very strong response” against any new Pakistan attack</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/india-ameaca-resposta-muito-forte-contra-qualquer-novo-ataque-do-paquistao/</link><description>Indian Foreign Minister warned yesterday that a new attack on Pakistan will provoke a “very strong response” from India, a day after the most violent military confrontation of the last two decades between the two countries.
"It is not our intention to provoke a new climb" of the conflict, said Subrahmanyam Jaishankar, at the opening of a meeting with the Iranian counterpart, Abbas Araghchi. "But if we are attacked, there is no doubt that we will respond very firmly," he said.
The threat is done a day after Pakistan has guaranteed that it will take revenge on the dead caused by Indian air strikes that, according to Nova Delhi, were an response to an attack on Caxemira. "We are committed to avenge every drop of blood from these martyrs," said Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, in a nation speech on Wednesday night.
Growing
Over the past two weeks, the tension between India and Pakistan has grown, following an attack on April 22 in Pahalgam, a tourist town in the Indian part of the disputed region of Caxemira, in which 26 people died.
India accused Pakistan of supporting the extremist group that liable for the attack, an accusation that Islamabade vehemently denied.
After several diplomatic measures and a series of incidents along the border that separates the two countries in Caxemira, Nova Deli launched attacks on three Pakistan areas, which, according to the Indian government, constituted “terrorist places” in Punjab province.
A few hours later, the Pakistani government announced that it has slaughtered several Indian military aircraft and, on Wednesday morning, a sequence of Islamabade bombing and Nova Delhi caused at least 38 dead in the biggest confrontation in the last 20 years.
Yesterday, India announced that 13 civilians died and 59 were injured in Caxemira in retaliation for the Pakistani attack released on Wednesday over its territory and Pakistan said it slaughtered an Indian drone in Lahore.
Iran offered to mediate the conflict between the two nuclear powers, and the minister responsible for the diplomacy of Tehran reunited with those responsible of the Pakistani government on Monday. Upon arrival in India, Abbas Araghchi admitted that he expects "the parties to have moderation to avoid climbing tensions in the region." Iran maintains good relations with India and Pakistan, with which it borders.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Alvis Lo Vinca bets on professional competitiveness</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/saude-alvis-lo-vinca-aposta-na-competitividade-profissional/</link><description>The Director of Health Services, Alvis Lo, considers that the government's plan to increase the value of health valleys and launch a chronic disease screening program will improve the system and access to health in the territory. The position was taken during the latest board meeting for medical affairs.
To increase the competitiveness of health professionals, Alvis Lo has indicated that the executive will “provide a series of training programs, including the creation of a Family Medicine Training Base” as well as “systematic training to doctors of public and private institutions”.
For doctors who want to focus on a specialty, the SS promised to permanently open the competitions to fill complementary boarding school vacancies, as well as optimize procedures and “shorten the time” necessary for the contests.
In addition, Alvis Lo noted that the Macao Medical Center of the Peking Union Medical College Hospital aims to become a “high-level formation in Macau”, so in the next few times they should start to be sent to Beijing doctors, nurses and other clinical technicians to receive training. At this stage, there is also the possibility that the formations are not limited to the Chinese capital.
Following the tendency to lead the population to leave Macau, Alvis Lo has indicated that the government will support integration in national development, which should start with professionals to large bay and the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, as they are considered “more easy and mature starting points”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:19:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Critical resident due to bacterial infection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/saude-residente-em-estado-critico-devido-a-infeccao-bacteriana/</link><description>A 65 -year -old resident is in critical condition and needs fan to assist in breathing following a vibri vascus infection.
On the afternoon of April 29, the man was accidentally chopped on his little finger his right hand as he handled Cameroon at home. In the next night, it appeared at the "swelling and pain, which then spread to the right hand and right forearm," health services indicated yesterday.
The resident, which has a history of chronic diseases, went to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, where he was "diagnosed with necrotic fascitis of the right upper limb with septic shock."
Health services report that vibri vulinificus is a bacteria that naturally live in hot water and infections can happen when someone has open wounds exposed to seawater with Vibri Vulnifus or when it eats contaminated seafood. People with necrotizing fascitis may have to proceed to the amputation to save their lives, and in about 20 to 30 percent of cases, the infection is fatal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:28:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation hosts “polyphony” until next week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/fundacao-rui-cunha-acolhe-polifonia-ate-a-proxima-semana/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts until Saturday next week, the 17th, the collective exhibition “Polyfonia”, with works by artist Gu Yue and six doctoral students from the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must), co-organizer of the event.
The project makes known 20 works that represent the forms and styles of renowned artist and professor Gu Yue and his disciples Luo Su, Zhu Zhaohui, Wang Kongbin, Ding Song, Guo Weiwei, and Wei Dongsheng.
According to a FRC note, this exhibition presents “a visual banquet that transcends tradition and contemporaneity, the material and digital, the place and the global, through the collision of various media and the resonance of ideas”.
The works include various art forms, “such as installations, oil paintings, lacquer paintings, sand paintings and details to detail brush, displaying Macau's unique artistic ecosystem as a cultural convergence point”, is referred to.
The name of the exhibition originates “in musical terminology, referring to the opposition and symbiosis of multiple voices”. The presentation of the show states that "the mission of art is to create cognitive disorientation", and "through the confrontation between traditional crafts and the new media, and the rapport of local cultural genes and global issues, it breaks the linear narrative and invites the audience to calibrate their cognition in the" glow between brightness and residual shadow. "
Joint work
Professor Gu Yue aligns his work and the investigation with the main theme of the exhibition. The creations of the six doctoral students "start from individual experiences and respond to propositions such as identity, time and memory in the age of digital capital, also forming a multi-wing resonance of thought."
Exhibition is not only a concentrated exhibition of academic achievements, but also a speculative experience on the essence of art. “In this culturally stratified place of Macao, polyphony tries to use art as a prism to reflect the symbiotic possibilities of multiple realities,” describes the team, cited by the same note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:45:47</pubDate></item><item><title>One | Investigation company profits fall 48.6%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/um-lucros-de-empresa-de-investigacao-caem-486/</link><description>The profits of the company linked to the University of Macao fell 9.88 million patacas. The fall was mainly due to the increase in payments made to the institution of higher education by administrative and place services to perform tests
 
Last year, the company's profits of the company Umacert investigation and engineering rehearsals showed a reduction of 48.6 percent, which translated into 9.88 million patacas. Data from the company controlled by the University of Macau were released yesterday and show a profit of 10.45 million patacas.
Umacert Research and Engineering Tests has as an area of ​​activity research and conducting tests facing the construction materials, road traffic and underground facilities. It is detained at 99 percent by the University of Macao, with the remaining 1 percent in the control of the Education Fund.
The profit of 10.45 million patacas contrasts with the positive result of 20.33 million patacas in the previous year. This difference is explained not only with revenue reduction, which fell slightly from 35.00 million to 34.95 million patacas, but mainly with “other operational expenses”. These had a rise of nearly 10 million patacas from 11.24 million in 2024 to 21.18 million patacas last year.
Increased “other operational expenses” essentially include payments for testing one, as well as the supply of administrative services, with costs growing 9.30 million patacas, to 18.79 million patacas, when in 2023 they were 9.49 million patacas. In terms of staff costs, Umacert's spending within one year more than doubled from 1.07 million patacas by 2023 to 2.86 million patacas.
A handful of companies
Umacert Research and Engineering Tests is one of three companies controlled by the University of Macao.
In addition to this, there is a Tec, which is also dedicated to investigation, but in other areas, and which last year presented a profit of 781,500 patacas, which represented a reduction of almost 80 percent compared to 2023, when profits had been 3.8 million patacas.
The third company controlled by UM is Guangdong Hengqin a Higher Education Development, which will be responsible for developing the new UMA campus in an investment that could reach 4 billion Renminbis. Until yesterday, the company that is headquartered in the countryside had not yet presented the annual results.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:27:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | Revenues with annual growth of 6.2%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/galaxy-receitas-com-crescimento-anual-de-62/</link><description>Galaxy Entertainment had net revenues of Hong Kong's $ 11.2 billion in the first quarter of this year, a 6.2 percent rise in annual, but 1 percent from the last trimester of 2024. Francis Lui stressed the resilience of the Macao market, despite the “geopolitical turmoil and continuing economic slowdown” ”.
 
Galaxy Entertainment yesterday presented the financial results of the first quarter of 2025, a period during which net revenues of $ 11.2 billion of Hong Kong (HKD) were determined, representing an annual increase of 6.2 percent, but a break of 1 percent compared to the previous quarter.
Regarding gross game revenues, the group closed the first three months of 2025 with 10.94 billion HKD, a result that reflects an annual increase of 13.6 percent, but a decrease of 0.8 percent compared to the last quarter of last year.
As is normal, the mass segment generated the highest volume of gross revenues, with 8.23 ​​billion HKD, more 6.5 percent over the same period, while the VIP segmentary raised 1.98 billion HKD in gross revenues, plus 52.3 percent in annual terms.
During the period under analysis, the group registered profits before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of nearly 3.3 billion HKD, a result that represented an annual rise of 16.3 percent and 1.8 percent compared to the last quarter of 2024.
As the “tradition” dictates, the group's egg chicken was Galaxy Macau, generating 9.15 billion HKD in net revenues, plus 10 percent in terms annually, and EBITDA profits of 3.02 billion HKD (+15.4 percent compared to the first trimester of 2024).
At the sleeve
"During the quarter under analysis, we continued to boost all segments of the business, in particular Mass Premium, through our unique products and services, continuous property improvements, various shows and entertainment events, as well as the complete implementation of intelligent tables," said Group President Francis Lui, in the statement that presented the results.
The president of Galaxy Entertainment highlighted the performance of the group's casinos during the Chinese New Year and the resilience capacity of the Macao market, “despite the geopolitical turmoil and the continuing economic slowdown,” with gross revenues to recover to 76 percent of 2019.
Francis Lui also mentioned the presentation of the first lines of government action of the Executive of Sam Hou Fai, particularly in the role of leadership to diversify the economy and guide concessionaires for investments in non-game projects.
However, the president of Galaxy referred the comments of the chief executive regarding the difficulties for the game market to reach the estimated gross revenues for this year. "In the short term, we continue to adjust operations as needed, but we are confident of long -term prospects for Macao. Macau's proactive approach in economic diversification, combined with China's firm support, positions the city well for future sustainable growth," said Francis Lui.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:24:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment | Leong Sun Iok warns of collecting candidate information</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/emprego-leong-sun-iok-alerta-para-recolha-de-informacao-de-candidatos/</link><description>Leong Sun IOK warns of the increase of companies that research the past of job candidates and argues that the information obtained by former employers is often skewed and unfair. The deputy calls for regulation to the government
 
Deputy Leong Sun IOK intends that the government regulates the collection of information carried out by companies about job candidates. The request is contained in a written interpellation, in which the legislator linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) warns of the occurrence of various illegalities, without any consequences.
According to the scenario outlined by Leong Sun Iok, when applying for a job, especially through online platforms, interested parties are led to sign forms and to consent that entities research their past.
However, the deputy warns that the practice is illegitimate, uncommon, allowing the creation of informal black lists and the exchange of information between companies. This situation can result in the blocking of job opportunities for former employees who have had different employer entities. "It is a practice that blocks access to employment in an industry, which seriously undermines the right to employment," says the legislator.
Leong Sun Iok also reveals that “over the years he has received a high number of requests and assistance” from people faced from one of the six game dealers and that they have later seen themselves. "Some people who asked me for help told me that they were convinced by supervisors to say goodbye. And if they did not say goodbye to their initiative, they were threatened that they would never find employment in the industry again. All these cases reflect the damage caused by collecting information without any regulation," added the deputy.
However, the practice is not limited to this sector: "In addition to the game dealers, there are a high number of companies in Macao that also requires employment candidates to allow their past to be investigated," he said.
Against the law
Leong Sun IOK also points out that the Labor Relations Law and Decree-Law 101/84/M define that former expirers when issuing a proof of work to a former worker cannot make any unfavorable reference to its past. However, the deputy indicates that the current, even informal practice, contradicts the spirit of the law, ending up being more harmful, because the former employee has no control over information that may not even be true.
"As the verification process lacks transparency and is not controlled by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, it is unfair to employment candidates and can violate the principle of good faith in labor relations," he warns. "How will management regulate information about professional background? It is possible to issue guidelines and change the law to explicitly stipulate that former employers should in no way transmit, make statements or adopt unfavorable behaviors to workers?"</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:22:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | PS again denounces alleged ATFPM practices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/eleicoes-ps-volta-a-denunciar-alegadas-praticas-da-atfpm/</link><description>The Macao Public Service Association is again accused by the Socialist Party to commit illegalities in the context of the vote of local voters for the next legislative elections in Portugal. Rita Santos and José Pereira Coutinho, from ATFPM, deny everything
 
The prosecution is not new: the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM) was the subject of a complaint made by the Socialist Party (PS) to the National Elections Commission (CNE) in Portugal, for making “actions that compromise the freedom and confidentiality of vote” of local voters for May 18, in Portugal, which will serve a new parliament and first minister.
According to the PS complaint sent to the CNE, which includes photos of the alleged illegalities, "the presence of individuals who identify themselves as" volunteers "at the door of a Macao Post station, addressing voters to indicate where they should vote."
Thus, “this is the same practice that occurred in the last legislative elections that took place in 2024 and it was found to be conducted by Rita Santos, a prominent figure of ATFPM and advisor to the Portuguese communities”. Rita Santos, however, stopped being a counselor.
The images attached to the complaint show "one of the volunteers at the Macao postal door, addressing voters", and "in some cases requests the delivery of voting bulletins," a practice that suggests "directing the vote and calling into question the fundamental principles of a democratic electoral process."
Scenario of “impunity”
HM confronted Rita Santos and José Pereira Coutinho, president of ATFPM, with this complaint, both denied the accusations. "We are unaware of the situation of volunteers referring because ATFPM is not involved or interferes with the elections of the Assembly of the Republic of Portugal. This year are the elections of the Legislative Assembly (AL) of Macao and we are committed to the presentation of the candidacy of the Nova Esperança list," said Rita Santos.
Pereira Coutinho, also deputy to Al, said “unaware of” the accusation. "ATFPM has no one to do this, they are inventions to which we are alien," he said.
It is recalled that the last complaint submitted by the PS to the CNE was then sent to the prosecutor in Portugal. The investigation still takes place and is in secret of justice, as already reported, and no accusation has not yet been deducted. Already in 2019, the PS had submitted a similar complaint.
The PS understands that "the constant action of the association in the electoral context raises concerns about the possible misuse of resources to influence the voting process", in the case of "recurring practices in potundous legislative elections".
"The persistence of such behaviors, coupled with apparent impunity, aggravates the severity of the facts and requires, once and for all, a firm response from the competent authorities," the PS.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:14:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Startups | Portugal interested in the SINO-LUSOPHONE TECHNOLOGY FUND</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/startups-portugal-interessado-no-fundo-sino-lusofono-de-tecnologia/</link><description>A delegation from Macao, with government representatives and local startups, is in Portugal to meet with leaders of Portuguese companies and participate in the SIM conference, which ends today in Porto. During the visit, a protocol was signed that signs the Portuguese interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund, managed by Heng Qin Group's state-owned company Zhuhai
 
Several macao startups are represented on a trip to Portugal this week, and whose delegation also includes representatives of the Directorate of Economics and Tourism Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries Association (AEIMCP). The objective is to strengthen ties with the entrepreneurship ecosystems of Lisbon and Porto and reinforce Portugal's interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund designed to support startups, which will be managed by Heng Qin Group's Zhuhai state company.
In this sense, a protocol between AEIMCP and the nascent Value, “Portuguese company with extensive investor capture” and also “accelerating small business growth (SME) and startups in Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, focused on innovation and cutting-edge technology”, is signed on Monday, in Lisbon, in Lisbon, in Lisbon.
The protocol signed on Monday signs the highest Portuguese access to the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund. The document was signed as part of a visit from the Macau Group to Lispolis - Lisbon Technological Pole.
The nascent Value thus becomes a “exclusive agent for investor capture services in Portugal, focusing on the involvement of investors in the background” SINO-LUSOPHONE, whose official name is “from Heng Qin Sino-Maluso Technology and Innovation Investment LPF”. This “promotes investments in high quality science and technology innovation companies in Portuguese -speaking countries”, explains the same note.
Thus, this protocol will allow AEIMCP, as a connecting entity between Portugal and the Fund via Macau, and the nascent Value, “reinforce its commitment to support startups, promote transfronhoring investment and create new opportunities for collaboration between Macau, Portugal and other Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Quoted by the same note, AEIMCP's Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said this new agreement shows how the entity, which also organizes the “929 Challenge” contest, is committed to “creating bridges for the global startup growth, facilitating the entry of Portuguese startups into the Chinese market through Macao, as well as the expansion of Chinese startups to Portugal and Europe”.
In turn, Rui Ferreira said that “the signing of this protocol is an important milestone for connecting innovation ecosystems and promoting synergies between macao startups and Portuguese investors”. "We are confident that this partnership will bring significant results for both sides," he added.
At HM, Rui Ferreira explained that the signature of the protocol represents the culmination of a work of about a year.
“We want to promote a model of welcoming startups and companies from Macao that want to enter Europe through Portugal, as well as in Portuguese-expression countries, and vice versa, that is, to place, through Macau, companies of these territories, but always through Portugal, in the East, in order to obtain easier connections with the Chinese market.”
Thousand Visits
Macao's group visited several essential points of the Portuguese entrepreneurship sector. In addition to the visit to Lispolis, considered the “key moment to foster dialogues between Deep Tech startups and potential investors, consolidating Macau's vision as an innovation and entrepreneurship hub with global range”, the entourage passed through the unicorns factory in Lisbon, and the PWC consultant.
Marco Duarte Rizzolio explained to HM the benefits to Macao from the journey through Portugal. “In addition to the interest in the Sino-Lusophone Fund and its preparation, as it will be released soon, our focus has also been the startups. On the visit to Lispolis macao startups made a pitch [attempted investment tarning], presented their products and had a networking session with other startups. Immersion in the Entrepreneurship Ecosystem in Portugal. ”
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, Macao's entourage only took to Portugal to startups with a more advanced business phase, namely Zence Object, founded by Calvin Sio and obtained a $ 2.5 million financing from the Alibaba Group entrepreneurs to the Great Bay area. Zence Object uses patented technology to transform organic waste, namely tea leaves, into alternative plastic and paper products. The idea is that these recycled and transformed products can be used on a daily basis, such as home or decorating utensils.
"There are startups in Macau who are very advanced in terms of business and we have brought to Portugal. We want to explore new opportunities for internationalization, so that they explore other markets, as these startups already have some development. We want to create partnerships, so that these representatives realize what the market is like and explore possible customers," said the representative of AEIMCP.
By unbeaten paths
Macao's entourage is today in Porto to participate in “SIM Conference” [Startups &amp; Investment Matching], where “it will have its own stand to present projects and connect with investors and possible customers”. This event was organized by the Entity Startup Portugal, which invited to be present.
Also today will be signed another protocol, this time between the association that organizes the contest “929 Challenge” and Startup Portugal. The idea is, according to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, “stimulate the connection of the Portugal ecosystem with Macau and help in the process of internationalization of the startups on both sides, both the Portuguese who are intended for the great bay, through Macau, both the macao startups that go to Portugal”.
The official has no doubt that what is lacking in knowledge is left in interest. “There is a great interest in China, but at the same time there is a great ignorance. The startup ecosystem in Portugal is much more linked to Europe. When we talk to the unicorns factory for months, we were told that there was a great interest in the Macao and China market, but that these visits to Portugal were lacking. It is growing a lot in technology and artificial intelligence, with the launch of DeepSeek, for example. ”
According to Rui Ferreira, the presence of the delegation of Macao in “Yes Conference” will allow access to “privileged and wider contacts”, as it is a national event. "With this visit we have been able to do two things: starting the relationship with AEIMCP more formally and helping Macao companies know of partners and investors. We also want to bet on the work for the future Sino-Musso fund, to prepare companies with investment potential," he said.
For Rui Ferreira, the Macao market has the potential “to be used as a business exchange platform, thanks to linguistic connection, and there is conditions in the territory to establish all the part of reception, support and exchange with China entities and create an ecosystem”. In addition, “it will be interesting Macao to make a specialized innovation hub in strategic areas”, which in this case is technology.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:10:31</pubDate></item><item><title>India threatens “very strong response” against any new Pakistan attack</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/india-ameaca-resposta-muito-forte-contra-qualquer-novo-ataque-do-paquistao/</link><description>Indian Foreign Minister warned yesterday that a new attack on Pakistan will provoke a “very strong response” from India, a day after the most violent military confrontation of the last two decades between the two countries.
"It is not our intention to provoke a new climb" of the conflict, said Subrahmanyam Jaishankar, at the opening of a meeting with the Iranian counterpart, Abbas Araghchi. "But if we are attacked, there is no doubt that we will respond very firmly," he said.
The threat is done a day after Pakistan has guaranteed that it will take revenge on the dead caused by Indian air strikes that, according to Nova Delhi, were an response to an attack on Caxemira. "We are committed to avenge every drop of blood from these martyrs," said Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, in a nation speech on Wednesday night.
Growing
Over the past two weeks, the tension between India and Pakistan has grown, following an attack on April 22 in Pahalgam, a tourist town in the Indian part of the disputed region of Caxemira, in which 26 people died.
India accused Pakistan of supporting the extremist group that liable for the attack, an accusation that Islamabade vehemently denied.
After several diplomatic measures and a series of incidents along the border that separates the two countries in Caxemira, Nova Deli launched attacks on three Pakistan areas, which, according to the Indian government, constituted “terrorist places” in Punjab province.
A few hours later, the Pakistani government announced that it has slaughtered several Indian military aircraft and, on Wednesday morning, a sequence of Islamabade bombing and Nova Delhi caused at least 38 dead in the biggest confrontation in the last 20 years.
Yesterday, India announced that 13 civilians died and 59 were injured in Caxemira in retaliation for the Pakistani attack released on Wednesday over its territory and Pakistan said it slaughtered an Indian drone in Lahore.
Iran offered to mediate the conflict between the two nuclear powers, and the minister responsible for the diplomacy of Tehran reunited with those responsible of the Pakistani government on Monday. Upon arrival in India, Abbas Araghchi admitted that he expects "the parties to have moderation to avoid climbing tensions in the region." Iran maintains good relations with India and Pakistan, with which it borders.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Alvis Lo Vinca bets on professional competitiveness</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/saude-alvis-lo-vinca-aposta-na-competitividade-profissional/</link><description>The Director of Health Services, Alvis Lo, considers that the government's plan to increase the value of health valleys and launch a chronic disease screening program will improve the system and access to health in the territory. The position was taken during the latest board meeting for medical affairs.
To increase the competitiveness of health professionals, Alvis Lo has indicated that the executive will “provide a series of training programs, including the creation of a Family Medicine Training Base” as well as “systematic training to doctors of public and private institutions”.
For doctors who want to focus on a specialty, the SS promised to permanently open the competitions to fill complementary boarding school vacancies, as well as optimize procedures and “shorten the time” necessary for the contests.
In addition, Alvis Lo noted that the Macao Medical Center of the Peking Union Medical College Hospital aims to become a “high-level formation in Macau”, so in the next few times they should start to be sent to Beijing doctors, nurses and other clinical technicians to receive training. At this stage, there is also the possibility that the formations are not limited to the Chinese capital.
Following the tendency to lead the population to leave Macau, Alvis Lo has indicated that the government will support integration in national development, which should start with professionals to large bay and the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, as they are considered “more easy and mature starting points”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:19:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Critical resident due to bacterial infection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/saude-residente-em-estado-critico-devido-a-infeccao-bacteriana/</link><description>A 65 -year -old resident is in critical condition and needs fan to assist in breathing following a vibri vascus infection.
On the afternoon of April 29, the man was accidentally chopped on his little finger his right hand as he handled Cameroon at home. In the next night, it appeared at the "swelling and pain, which then spread to the right hand and right forearm," health services indicated yesterday.
The resident, which has a history of chronic diseases, went to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, where he was "diagnosed with necrotic fascitis of the right upper limb with septic shock."
Health services report that vibri vulinificus is a bacteria that naturally live in hot water and infections can happen when someone has open wounds exposed to seawater with Vibri Vulnifus or when it eats contaminated seafood. People with necrotizing fascitis may have to proceed to the amputation to save their lives, and in about 20 to 30 percent of cases, the infection is fatal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:28:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation hosts “polyphony” until next week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/fundacao-rui-cunha-acolhe-polifonia-ate-a-proxima-semana/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts until Saturday next week, the 17th, the collective exhibition “Polyfonia”, with works by artist Gu Yue and six doctoral students from the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must), co-organizer of the event.
The project makes known 20 works that represent the forms and styles of renowned artist and professor Gu Yue and his disciples Luo Su, Zhu Zhaohui, Wang Kongbin, Ding Song, Guo Weiwei, and Wei Dongsheng.
According to a FRC note, this exhibition presents “a visual banquet that transcends tradition and contemporaneity, the material and digital, the place and the global, through the collision of various media and the resonance of ideas”.
The works include various art forms, “such as installations, oil paintings, lacquer paintings, sand paintings and details to detail brush, displaying Macau's unique artistic ecosystem as a cultural convergence point”, is referred to.
The name of the exhibition originates “in musical terminology, referring to the opposition and symbiosis of multiple voices”. The presentation of the show states that "the mission of art is to create cognitive disorientation", and "through the confrontation between traditional crafts and the new media, and the rapport of local cultural genes and global issues, it breaks the linear narrative and invites the audience to calibrate their cognition in the" glow between brightness and residual shadow. "
Joint work
Professor Gu Yue aligns his work and the investigation with the main theme of the exhibition. The creations of the six doctoral students "start from individual experiences and respond to propositions such as identity, time and memory in the age of digital capital, also forming a multi-wing resonance of thought."
Exhibition is not only a concentrated exhibition of academic achievements, but also a speculative experience on the essence of art. “In this culturally stratified place of Macao, polyphony tries to use art as a prism to reflect the symbiotic possibilities of multiple realities,” describes the team, cited by the same note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:45:47</pubDate></item><item><title>AFA | “Déjà Vu” presents works in the area of ​​Video-Arte</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/afa-deja-vu-apresenta-trabalhos-na-area-da-video-arte/</link><description>Integrated in the poster of this year's edition of the French May festival, here is the new exhibition of the local AFA - Art for All Society Association. This is “Déjà VU-an exhibition of Sino-Francês artistic exchange”, where the themes of video art and artificial intelligence resonate from the signing works of Robert Cahen, Alice Kok and Catherine Cheong. To see in The Parisian between May 15 and June 28
 
Video art, mixed with the real and the fictional, artificial and created with human hands. It is around these ideas and concepts that revolves the new exhibition of AFA-Art for All Society, entitled “Dejá Vu-an exhibition of sino-francês artistic exchange”, and which gains the subtitle “Mirroring ・ Loging ・ Generatting”: from video art to artificial intelligence-exhibition series ”.
The project, patent between May 15 and June 28 in one of the galleries of The Parisian venture in Cotai, presents to the public works of three artists: Alice Kok, co-founder of AFA, artist and curator; Robert Cahen and Catherine Cheong. The project is integrated in this year's edition poster of the French May festival, which brings Hong Kong a series of cultural initiatives.
According to a statement from AFA, “Déjà vu” aims to establish “a bridge between the Sino-Franceses cultural dialogues through art”, also promoting the investigation into “the philosophical intersections of time, memory and perception”.
In addition to the presence in Macao, this show will be evident in France, between 21 and 30 August, at the Espace Temps Gallery in Paris. Thus, the “cultural exchange” is promoted between China and France, highlights AFA, and the public is invited to “witness the evolution of interaction between memory and technology”.
“Déjà vu”, theory developed by the French philosopher Henri Bergson, gives the motto to this show, revealing “the simultaneous division between perception and memory”, that is, “the coexistence between the present 'current' and its 'virtual' image in the mirror”. The works of the three artists thus exploit this abstract philosophical concept, transforming it into “tangible sensory experiences through video art, images generated by artificial intelligence and multimedia facilities”.
The show, which has the keywords “Mirroring”, “looping” and “Generation”, referring to the ideas of mirror, repetition or content generation, reflects “not only the artists techniques, but also metaphorizes the way memory and technology weave the invisible tissue of contemporary reality”.
Initial Workshop
In addition to the show itself, artists will also join to teach others about the world of digital and video art. Robert Cahen, considered one of the pioneers in Video Art in France, collaborates with Alice Kok for the “Video Postcards” workshop, held on May 18 The Parisian Macau. The idea is to lead participants to “dive into Coloane's natural and historical landscapes, inspired by the poetics of fleeting images', characteristic of Cahen's work”. Thus, “through techniques such as slow chamber, overlap and sound design, participants will transform ephemeral sensory experiences into unique '' postcards,” describes AFA, and experience includes filming, post-production context and final projection.
Who is who
Robert Cahen has been developing artistic projects since 1972. According to the official program of the French May festival, in Cahen's work “both fiction and documentation are presented as metaphorical trips of the imaginary, exquisite daydreams that describe passages of time, place, memory and perception”. Having started with the video cassettes, his works were exposed worldwide, in places and events such as the Paris Biennial, France; The Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), New York, USA; or the American Film Institute National Video Festival, Los Angeles, USA.
In 1992 the artist won the Villa Medicis Hors Les Murs award and, in 1995, created a permanent video installation for Euralille (Lille) public space in France.
In the case of Catherine Cheong, she is a local artist who lives between Macau and Paris, having graduated in the area of ​​video installation at the Visual Arts Degree at École Supérieure D'Art et de Design Toulon. In addition, the artist graduated in personal creation and contemporary engraving theory with a master's degree in visual arts at the University of Paris VIII.
“As an individual artist, his inspiration comes from personal experience. Through cultural differences, contradictions and interactions between human beings, the social environment and nature, explores the realization of life and the feelings of the soul. It goes back, juxtaposes and doubles symbolic images to recreate new meanings, seeking coincidence between images with different artistic languages ​​and means to express feelings, thoughts and personal desires”, can be read in the “FRench program”. May ”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:43:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Shanghai | Legoland will open in July largest theme park in the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/xangai-legoland-vai-abrir-em-julho-maior-parque-tematico-do-mundo/</link><description>The Danish brand Lego, which specializes in building blocks, will open on July 5 its largest theme park in the world in Shanghai, east of China, the local press advanced yesterday.
The complex, about 52 kilometers southwest of the city center, will feature more than 75 attractions and shows distributed by eight distinct zones, including thousands of figures built with about 85 million lego pieces.
Visitors will also be able to watch Lego movies in a 4D movie theater as well as lodge in a 250-room themed hotel, decorated according to five different environments inspired by this universe of recognized toy on the global scale.
Currently, the park is in the final phase of construction: the main entrance is completed and the main 24 attractions are practically ready. About a thousand employees will integrate the team since the opening.
The highlight of the park will be the “Miniland” zone, a recreation, built fully with Lego blocks - with a total weight of 45 tons - some of Shanghai's most emblematic areas, as well as other China's cultural and tourist icons.
Among the expected shows, stands out the world's first show dedicated to Lego's “Monkie Kid” series, inspired by King Macaco, from the classic Chinese work Journey to the West. Legoland Shanghai has already started selling season passes and tickets for exclusive visits, including stays at the themed hotel.
"We know this market well and we are enthusiastic about its potential. This complex will be a reference and meeting point for all Lego fans in China," said Fiona Eastwood, executive director of Merlin Entertainments, the British group responsible for managing Legoland parks. According to the company, more than 55 million people live two hours - or less - by car the location of the new park.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MGM Resorts International warns bets in Japan and Thailand</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/mgm-resorts-international-alerta-para-apostas-no-japao-e-tailandia/</link><description>A Casinos operator in Macau said yesterday that the opening of casinos in Japan and the potential legalization of the game in Thailand will increase competition with regard to Asian gamblers.
The director for the global development of the US company MGM Resorts International, which operates two casinos in Macao, said the new game concessions accelerated the transition from a model based on major gamblers to “a more diverse tourism and entertainment economy”.
The six Macao game operators signed 10-year concession agreements in December 2022, committing to invest 108.7 billion in tourism and the diversification of the economy.
“The reinforcement of cultural attractions, from entertainment to families (…) helped attract more vast demographics than traditional gamblers,” said Ed Bowers. But the executive warned that "competition is intensifying in Asian markets, particularly with Japan and potentially Thailand."
MGM started on April 24 with the construction of the first integrated venture with a Japan casino in Osaka, scheduled for 2030. The Thailand government presented a proposal to legalize the game.
"This is excellent news for staff of the development of casinos like me," said Bowers, who recalled that Thailand "already benefits from a strong tourist infrastructure." But the discussion of the proposal in Parliament was postponed in early April, "probably due to the increase in political opposition" to the idea, admitted the executive.
Other bets
Bowers spoke during the Global Gaming Expo Asia, the largest event in the game industry held in Macau, which will take place until Friday.
In another session of the same event, experts argued that, given the greater regional competition, the bet on game -related attractions, such as concerts, themed parks and gastronomy can bring more people to the casinos.
“We built all this to support our casino, the casino is our financial engine,” said Wade Howk, director of operations at Inspire Entertainment Resort, an integrated resort in South Korea, with an exclusive casino for foreigners.
The session focused on the diversification of the economy of Macao, where taxes on casinos represented 88.4 percent of the region's current current revenues in the first three months of the year. But the authorities intend that the sector not related to the game represent 60 percent of Macao Gross Domestic Product by 2028.
As an example, Wade Howk stressed that Inspire Entertainment built a 15,000 -seat entertainment space, the only multipurpose cultural arena in South Korea to increase the number of visitors.
"We are seeing huge results with this now, and then we built a covered water park ... just to make sure we could boost traffic to support the entire property, ... and that it could be used to support the casino," Howk explained. Jeffrey Kiang, an investment group analyst CSSA, stressed that game -related components should “create synergies and complement the business” of casinos.
Kiang has observed an increase in the number of concerts held in Macao in the last two years and said that the casino operators carefully select events or artists who attract gamblers.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:31:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Indian Foreign Minister warned yesterday that a new attack on Pakistan will provoke a “very strong response” from India, a day after the most violent military confrontation of the last two decades between the two countries.
"It is not our intention to provoke a new climb" of the conflict, said Subrahmanyam Jaishankar, at the opening of a meeting with the Iranian counterpart, Abbas Araghchi. "But if we are attacked, there is no doubt that we will respond very firmly," he said.
The threat is done a day after Pakistan has guaranteed that it will take revenge on the dead caused by Indian air strikes that, according to Nova Delhi, were an response to an attack on Caxemira. "We are committed to avenge every drop of blood from these martyrs," said Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, in a nation speech on Wednesday night.
Growing
Over the past two weeks, the tension between India and Pakistan has grown, following an attack on April 22 in Pahalgam, a tourist town in the Indian part of the disputed region of Caxemira, in which 26 people died.
India accused Pakistan of supporting the extremist group that liable for the attack, an accusation that Islamabade vehemently denied.
After several diplomatic measures and a series of incidents along the border that separates the two countries in Caxemira, Nova Deli launched attacks on three Pakistan areas, which, according to the Indian government, constituted “terrorist places” in Punjab province.
A few hours later, the Pakistani government announced that it has slaughtered several Indian military aircraft and, on Wednesday morning, a sequence of Islamabade bombing and Nova Delhi caused at least 38 dead in the biggest confrontation in the last 20 years.
Yesterday, India announced that 13 civilians died and 59 were injured in Caxemira in retaliation for the Pakistani attack released on Wednesday over its territory and Pakistan said it slaughtered an Indian drone in Lahore.
Iran offered to mediate the conflict between the two nuclear powers, and the minister responsible for the diplomacy of Tehran reunited with those responsible of the Pakistani government on Monday. Upon arrival in India, Abbas Araghchi admitted that he expects "the parties to have moderation to avoid climbing tensions in the region." Iran maintains good relations with India and Pakistan, with which it borders.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Indian Foreign Minister warned yesterday that a new attack on Pakistan will provoke a “very strong response” from India, a day after the most violent military confrontation of the last two decades between the two countries.
"It is not our intention to provoke a new climb" of the conflict, said Subrahmanyam Jaishankar, at the opening of a meeting with the Iranian counterpart, Abbas Araghchi. "But if we are attacked, there is no doubt that we will respond very firmly," he said.
The threat is done a day after Pakistan has guaranteed that it will take revenge on the dead caused by Indian air strikes that, according to Nova Delhi, were an response to an attack on Caxemira. "We are committed to avenge every drop of blood from these martyrs," said Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, in a nation speech on Wednesday night.
Growing
Over the past two weeks, the tension between India and Pakistan has grown, following an attack on April 22 in Pahalgam, a tourist town in the Indian part of the disputed region of Caxemira, in which 26 people died.
India accused Pakistan of supporting the extremist group that liable for the attack, an accusation that Islamabade vehemently denied.
After several diplomatic measures and a series of incidents along the border that separates the two countries in Caxemira, Nova Deli launched attacks on three Pakistan areas, which, according to the Indian government, constituted “terrorist places” in Punjab province.
A few hours later, the Pakistani government announced that it has slaughtered several Indian military aircraft and, on Wednesday morning, a sequence of Islamabade bombing and Nova Delhi caused at least 38 dead in the biggest confrontation in the last 20 years.
Yesterday, India announced that 13 civilians died and 59 were injured in Caxemira in retaliation for the Pakistani attack released on Wednesday over its territory and Pakistan said it slaughtered an Indian drone in Lahore.
Iran offered to mediate the conflict between the two nuclear powers, and the minister responsible for the diplomacy of Tehran reunited with those responsible of the Pakistani government on Monday. Upon arrival in India, Abbas Araghchi admitted that he expects "the parties to have moderation to avoid climbing tensions in the region." Iran maintains good relations with India and Pakistan, with which it borders.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 2025
In Chinese proverbial lessons I discovered great affinities between spontaneous Chinese popular philosophy, which runs from mouth to mouth, and the Christian proverbial wisdom, also made so that believers, in every corner of the globe, could memorize, repeat and disseminate.
Nothing like the other's knowledge to bring and dispel prejudice, being one of the most usual that Chinese are extremely pragmatic and cold. But when we come across proverbs such as “love others as yourself,” in a direct translation and faithful to the original “爱人如己” (ài Rú Rú Jǐ), such leads us to think twice, it seems not to be here just a matter of respect, uncharged and formal, but rather a strong feeling for the other, not any, only a deep affection, of those we understand well that we are good, we will be well, we will be well, we will be well, we will be better. Then he runs a love of the Christian way for China without Christ ever been. Such finding can lead us to the assumption of the existence of universal structures, not only logical, including as regards affections, therefore sentimental. After all, selfishness may not be a dominant tendency, there is everything: selfish, aggressive and competitive people, as others will be naturally altruistic, compassionate and cooperatives, ready to recognize the universality of the feeling of love, which crosses borders rather than erecting them, bringing people closer to the most diverse social classes, ethnic groups, geographies, as in "love has no borders", in a direct translation "" (Àiqíng wú jiējí zhī fēn), here is particularly emphasized social borders.
The content of the message gains full sense when one realizes that love to oneself takes place in a culture that many consider wrong and prejudiced only to focus on the whole, in the community.  Attention to the person, the particular and the style and feeling of each, lives, in philosophies such as Taoist for centuries with the valorization of the collectivity, this ultimate tendency manifestly inculcated and worked by Confucianism.  Love to itself, care for the individual body and mind, is emphasized in the so -called Proverbial “well -understood love and virtue must begin with us”, which has the following correspondence in Chinese “爱德从己起” (to Cong Jǐ qǐ).
Anyone who imagines that in proverbial wisdom there is only place to praise and sing relational love, since the Chinese have no religious philosophy that chant spiritual love above all, in the Christian way of St. Augustine, will be surprised to find the following proverb "where there is no other gentleman", that in a direct translation of the Chinese is "the love above all" 爱情至上 爱情至上 爱情至上ZHì Shàng).
If in doubt, there is another saying of complementary meaning and in which the idea of ​​the integrity and unity of this powerful affection, which moves mountains in the Christian sense, when it reads 爱情专一 （（（（iqíng zhuān yī）, in a possible translation "love cannot be broken", "one person cannot have a heart in two parts at the same time."
From a psychological point of view, the acceptance of the other in loving terms will have to be complete, so their tastes, affections, relationships, and objects cannot be rejected, as it follows from the lesson “Who loves Beltrão, loves his dog”, in a relative correspondence for “爱屋及乌” (ài wū jí wū), which in a literal translation would be “love the house and the crows”.
As is well known, proverbs are susceptible to various interpretations, so they say polysemic, but if they are perspective as a whole, and only then as pieces of a puzzle, there seems to be many doubts with regard to the proverb philosophy and psychology of Chinese love, which is echoed in the country's scholarly philosophies.
In Chapter 67 of the Book of the road and virtue (《道德经》), also known by the name of the Patriarch of Taoism, Lazi (老子), is the first of the three guiding virtues of the Wise Way, love, as you can read in the translation of Claudia Ribeiro (2004, 139):
I have three treasures
What entesouro and retains:
The first is love (CI),
The second frugality,
The third is not daring to be the vanguard of the world.
(…)
For love,
In combat, it triumphs,
And in defense it is firm.
The sky will come to aid
And, with love, will protect
(我有三寶/寶而持之/一曰慈/二曰儉/三曰不敢為天下先 (……) 夫慈以戰則勝//以守則固/以慈衛之 1)
It is noted that while in proverbial philosophy the synogram used for love is 爱/愛 2 (AI), in the scholarly philosophy of the Patriarch of Taoism the term employment is 慈 (CI), that is, love with a strong relational and spiritual burden; Although they are different words, both refer to love, the first concerns the most physical and concrete feeling, centered on the heart of the person and the clutches that hold it;  The second to that most relational and general indicates that love comes from inside the heart (内心 nèixīn), where it has the roots, emerging like any plant. However, the truth is that both terms focus on people, or rather in their hearts, affectionate connection with others, such a strong connection that draws the attention of heaven (天 tiān), maximum impersonal power, it ensures victory on all battle fronts, whether in the forefront or rear, when fighting and defended itself for love.
Already the patriarch of Confucianism, Confucius (孔子), in the Chapter Twelve, later entitled the deep face, of the Analects (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 22) defines the main virtue of the school, benevolence or humanity, (仁 Rén) as an act of love to others, maintaining the term of the traditional vernacular 爱 (AI): “Fan Chi asked what was the benevolence was what answered, "love people". " (樊遲問仁 ， 子曰 「愛人 3。 ”) It is in this context of love of neighbor, that one of the main maxims of Confucian philosophy must be understood, which arises in the same chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 2)“ Do not make the others what they do not want for you ”(己所不欲勿施於人 jǐ suǒ bù yù shunk yú rén).
The essentials in Confucian philosophy will then guarantee love of others in terms of respect or humanity towards others, in order to ensure the normal functioning of society, without extreme sacrifices or exaggerated explorations, given to the proverb containment of confusion in relation to feelings, they are important and useful but should not extravate the boundaries of rationality, that is, even the best of them, will have to be measured, controlled and ritualized in the name of harmony collective. Therefore, the love that moves friendships, especially intellectuals, is the most praised, as we remembered at the end of this chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 24):
Zeng Zi stated: “A gentleman resorts to knowing to make friends and friends to cultivate benevolence4” (曾子曰：君以文會友 ， 以友輔仁。)
Finally, also the Buddhist philosophy, especially from the Chan (禅 Chán) or Zen meditation line, praises the love of humanity, but indirectly, drawing attention to the heart and the identification of Buddha with the heart, the way of the Daoxin Patriarch (道信) and its maximum proverbially known “the heart is Buddha and Buddha is the heart” (非心不问佛 ， 问佛不非心 fēi xīn bùwèn fu, wèn fi bù fēi xīn). Here you come to love indirectly, only an enlightened heart can love the Buddha, as it is not surprising in the picture of this philosophy, after all what is Buddha but the very love that expresses itself not in a selfish, sick, self -centered heart, but in a heart capable of establishing relationships, healthy, altruistic and without empty, but not indifferent to the other?  This confirms it the social and humanitarian actions of Via Mahayana Buddhism, which was accepted in China and unfolds in collective works such as the construction of educational institutions, hospitals, centers of social solidarity, in a proselytist action at all similar to the history of the Christian Church and its missionaries around the world.
Bibliographic references
Lansheng, Jiang (Comp.) 1997. 100 Excerpts from Zen Buddhist Texts. Hong Hong Kong: Commercial Press.
NGAN, António André. 1998. SINE-SHORE CONGRELLANCE OF PROVERBS AND IDIOMATIC PHRASES. 中葡對照成語集. Macau: Macao Adult Association.
RIBEIRO, Claudia (Trad). 2004. 《道德經》 The Book of Road and Power. Bilingual edition. Mem-Martins: European American Publications.
Xin Guanjie (辛冠洁) (org. And trad.) 1994. 《論語》 .Tradument for contemporary Chinese falls xiqin (蔡希勤) and English translation of Lai Bo (赖波) and Xia Yuhe (夏玉和). Beijing: Sinolingue.
References:
Text in classic Chinese.
Love in simplified and traditional Chinese.
Text in classic Chinese.
A gentleman in ancient Chinese times was a gentleman and a potential ruler.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Bai Juyi (772-846), the poet of the Tang Dynasty attentive to the slightest changes in everyday life, in the poem in which he celebrates the renewal of the house he had just bought in spring, ends with the verses:
«If there is something that suits my spirit,
There are ten thousand complications seem forgotten.
Assuming that beyond the gate of my residence,
Something happens - I will know nothing about it. »
And this gate of a house or monastery, often cluttering a garden, a mentally ordered space, more than a physical limit marked a spiritual border.
Over the centuries of the imperial regime this ideal of feeling far away, it would endure in the lives of literati who would like to live free as hermit, but could not withdraw from cities due to their obligations with the imperial government.
This was also the case of his contemporary Pei du (765-839), who wrote in a poem:
«On the way to my gate
A clear river is seen,
Old trees grow uniforms
around the stalk roof eaves.
The red dust flies
But it doesn't come so far,
And every once in a while you listen to
the chilre of a bird. »
Eminent painter and theorist Dong Qichang (1555-1636) cited many years later PEI DU verses in the vertical landscape roll (ink on paper, 130.5 x 39.2 cm in Smithonian) made for a friend who visited him in Shanghai, shortly after the new year of 1617.
In it, there is neither a gate nor any person but on the banks of the river that dominates the representation, in the foreground, a willow-chronicle marks the presence of an absence. This same willow who will be found later in various paintings of one of the Qianlong court painters.
As in the 1770 landscape (ink on paper, 26.3 x 33.3 cm, at the Cernuschi museum) in which the use of low ink brush and an empty housing evokes the apparent simplicity of Dong Qichang painting, but with a calculated geometric disposition of the various planes.
Zhejiang's Fang Cong (c.1749-1790) had arrived at the Court in 1736 with other painters that would stand out as Zhang Zhongchang or Ding Guanpeng and deserve the approval of Qianlong, noted in poems that the emperor wrote about his paintings.
About a snow landscape, made on a sheet of album (ink and color on paper, 26 x 32.8 cm, at the Cernuschi museum) is perceived the advantage of being sheltered behind the gate but the beauty of the white scenario causes a disturbing indecision.
Just like the designated willow-songer Liu, which was used in farewells, given the homophony with a word meaning "stays", although the person will leave. Even protected inside houses, sometimes enclosed a courtyard by all sides (Siheyuan), behind the gate the spirit flies that there is something out there that is important and should not be lost.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Duarte Drumond Braga</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/duarte-drumond-braga/</link><description>Arrested to a long and distant oriental princess myth, it seemed to enjoy an impalpable resentment. Half Lispector, Half Pearl Buck, had yet to be the boat of the Empire. It was even further. He then returned to tea with sadness in Benfica. Braga was his first China, Macao the second, no China.
But the Portuguese do not forgive who is different. It had no face of either Quinta do Lago, nor Moimenta da Beira. He was wearing a booth in his green buttons. It remembered a uniform of the cultural revolution. So how did you want to identify class and provenance immediately? In Braga, wouldn't there be any other China to wear?
Nobody:                   ; Portuguese literature from 50 to 80: uninteresting fictions without reference after uninteresting fictions with references. Ah, very telluric, with towers, houses and other totems. Bad weather in the tower, the house of.
However, all the women's struggles, the other's knowledge, Palpar do Si - everything is already in it, before us, waiting to be found. We arrived almost to contemporary identities et alii.
So far from the pastry Agustina with his Pataratice of Entre Douro and Minho (this yard from the northernmost palace) and so close to authors that they seem provincial but they are nothing, like Pascoaes.
However, Ondina's books get dust in the library. The keys to know China or to know the world (almost the same thing) are in the keychain. And how much pedagogy of China (a belt, a road, a rounding around the world we could also form) could not give us, how much another world?
And why don't you read Wenceslau de Moraes too? Here there is no excuse of being a woman. Is it talking about Japan? Would it be better to talk about Telheiras? But isn't it Japan, or perhaps Tibet, the true meaning of Portuguese culture? To die the world? Could it be. For when a Tibetan Ondina, a Malay Wenceslau?
People like it is to talk about their mental palace terreiros: Lisbon, or Times Square. The true, these days, will never want to know, but from now on years - and then it will be too late. It is always too far, already said the Xana of Radio Macau. Et pour cause.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Literature | The interest of linguist Hugo Schuchardt in Patuá de Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/literatura-o-interesse-do-linguista-hugo-schuchardt-no-patua-de-macau/</link><description>Hugo Schuchardt had a genuine interest in Luso-Asian Creole languages, with particular emphasis on Patuá, spoken by the Macanese community. The linguist, who was born in 1842, was the subject of a lecture conducted by researcher Hugo Cardoso, linked to the University of Lisbon
 
Porto, 1883. José Leite de Vasconcelos writes a letter to the German linguist Hugo Schuchardt who had been developing studies, albeit at a distance, about the languages ​​spoken in Asia originated in Portuguese, the so -called Creoles. The letter, written according to the spell agreement of the time, however digitized and today to keep the Archive of the University of Graz, Austria, comes in the context of Schuchardt's own requests to Vasconcelos Milk on the Creole that was then spoken in Macao, known as Patuá.
“My respectable friend: Only today I can respond to V. Ex. Here in Porto there are no books that say, but I wrote to Lisbon to my friend Vianna and he replied that the Balsmanha does not appear, and that in Macao's story there comes nothing about the dialect port. Usual.
I have already asked for information about the Creoles, but I have not yet got anything; This study also interests me about regarding Portuguese. I look forward to the 2 new booklets that promises me. (…) Without anymore I am a friend, J. Vasconcelos Leite, Porto, S. Victor, 25 ”.
Hugo Schuchardt's interest in Luso-Asian Creole has been studied by Hugo Cardoso, a researcher and professor at the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon (FLUL), a Creole specialist who developed investigation at the University of Macao.
The academic recently conducted a lecture at the National Library in Lisbon over the linguist born in Gotha, Germany, in 1842 and died in Graz, Austria, in 1927, being considered one of the most important linguists of the late nineteenth and early twentieth century. The session was called “Hugo Schuchardt and the search for the Luso-Asian Creole”.
Despite Schuchardt's interest on Macao's Creole, he did not publish any academic work on the subject, as he told HM Hugo Cardoso. "Schuchardt did not publish any work on Macau. However, when he covered his correspondence, it is clear that Macau was also on his radar, since he discusses the Macao Creole with several of his correspondents, including Vasconcelos milk and Gonçalves Viana," he said.
After the German linguist, Hugo Cardoso highlights, “there were actually several people who leaned over Macau Creole, including Danilo Barreiros, José dos Santos Ferreira (Adé), Graciete Batalha, Ana Maria Amaro and, more recently, Prof. Raúl Gaião and Prof. Mário Pinharanda Nunes”. Also noteworthy is the study of Marie Arana-ward "about the Creole spoken by the descendants of Macanese in Hong Kong."
This is another change of correspondence with Vasconcelos milk, dated December 28, 1889, in which books and dictionaries about Portuguese and Chinese are mentioned. “Exmo. Friend: I hurried to respond to your ticket, since you are in a hurry. What I know from China-Portuguese is as follows: J. A. Gonçalves,-Portuguese Dictionary and China-Portuguese. Macau 1831;-China art, Alphabeto and Grammatica. (…) I estimate you have good fastests. Friend thanks, José Leite de Vasconcellos ”.
The role of rabbit
Hugo Cardoso, whose doctoral thesis is called “The Indo-Portuguese Language of Diu”, former territory of the so-called Portuguese India along with Goa and Damão, spoke at the National Library of Hugo Schuchardt's Studies around this Creole and also the language of Batávia/Tugu in Indonesia.
For the professor at FLUL, pioneering in the study of the Creoles is an expression that rhymes with Schuchardt. The German linguist was "absolutely pioneering in this domain, not only in the study of the Luso-Sasitive Creole or even the Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles globally, but in the study of Creole languages ​​in general" and, for this reason, is "a larger figure in the history of linguistics."
Hugo Cardoso also points out that "as regards the Portuguese lexical base creoles, before him, there had been some activity, especially by Adolfo Coelho, who, in 1881, had published" Romanesque or Neo-Latin dialects in Africa, Asia and America, "in which he was a caught in various Portuguese-based Creole." However, in this work, Adolfo Coelho refers only to three Luso-Asiatic Creole: “Ceylon's (at Sri Lanka), Malaca and Macau's-giving some examples that he could get from previous publications (such as Macau's Ta-Ss-Yang-Kuo magazine)”.
The academic has no doubt that “Hugo Schuchardt was surely inspired by Rabbit's work, but his efforts to obtain primary data from many other Asian places greatly expanded cartography of the Luso-sinical Creole and resulted in the first published news and the first grammatical descriptions of many of them (such as Diu, Cananor, Mahé, Mangar, Mangar, Mangar etc.) ”.
Future inspirations
According to Hugo Cardoso, the German linguist left works that inspired future academics and many materials from the personal archive. "One effect of his work was to inspire other agents to develop similar work: there stands out the figure of Sebastião Rodolfo Dalgado, who led his own research and made his own publications about the Indo-Portuguese Creoles that Schuchardt had not approached, about Damão, Bombaim, Ceylon and Negapath."
In the case of José de Leite Vasconcelos, who wrote the letter cited at the beginning of this text, "it also corresponded with Schuchardt and reveals, in his linguistic studies, the impact of Schuchardt's work."
Asked by HM about the possible interconnections between the Creole of IUD, Batávia and Macao, Hugo Cardoso states that there are "continuities between the various Luso-Asian Creole, but also many differences." "The Batávia/Tugu Creole is the one that most resembles Creole de Macao, for example, at the Lexicon level. But this is understandable because it has already shown that Macao Creole has an important historical connection with the Creole that developed in Southeast Asia, in particular Malaca."
According to an academic article by Hugo Cardoso himself written in partnership with Tjerk Hagemeijer and Nélia Alexandre, entitled “Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles”, these “were, in most cases, oral languages ​​to the nineteenth century, when the first collections of oral traditions, texts and translations began to emerge, being linked“ to maritime expansion in Africa and Asia, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact between the contact. Portuguese and different African and Asian languages ​​”.
Also according to the same article, "some of these Crioulos, namely in Asia, were extinguished, having only recorded from the transition from the nineteenth century to the twentieth century. With the exception of the Creole of Alta Guinea, the vitality of the living Portuguese Creole is generally decreasing."
In the case of Creoles of Portuguese origin in the southern Asia area, they emerged from the arrival of Vasco da Gama to Calecute, India, in 1498, especially from the phase in which the entire base of the Portuguese empire the East focuses on Goa. According to the same academic article, several Creole were developed, the so-called “Indo-Portuguese” in coastal areas of India, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Burma. "Currently, its presence is much reduced: they survive those of IUD, Damão, Korlai, Cananor and Sri Lanka (Ceylon) - which, despite having, has once been used all over the island, is currently restricted to the cities of Batticaloa and Trinchomalee," is highlighted in the article. The author draws attention to the extinction in 2010 of the Vaipim Creole, in Cochim, due to the "death of what seems to have been the last fluent speaker in this region." There are then the Southeast Asia and East Asia Creole, which includes Macao. Patuá is currently “spoken with native fluency only by some people in Macau and the Macanese diaspora”, is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:19:43</pubDate></item><item><title>PME | Events promoted by Melco generated $ 1 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/pme-eventos-promovidos-pela-melco-geraram-1-milhao-de-dolares/</link><description>Melco Resorts claims to have generated about $ 1 million for small and medium -sized local businesses through events promoted last year. In the 2024 sustainability report, the game operator also highlights the results in terms of waste management and energy spending
 
The Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment Sustainability Report has just been published last year, which highlights the gains obtained by small and medium -sized (SMEs) with the events promoted by the operator. With regard to the “community engagement and investment” part, it is read that “more than $ 1.02 million for local companies and [NGO] non-governmental organizations in Macao through 21 SME events, with 603 SME and NGO participants” were generated. In addition, in the volunteering area, Melco points out that "about 3,600 participants offered their time and effort in more than 359 volunteering initiatives," "more than $ 17.42 million that were donated to decent causes in our communities."
Quoted by the report, Lawrence Ho, Melco's president and executive director, says that "21 Heart of House initiatives and community events have generated more than $ 1 million for local companies in Macao, providing 603 SMEs and NGO opportunities to connect, expand and grow." According to the official, last year were "in -depth partnerships with PME and NGO".
Regarding the relationship with local SMEs, Melco also highlights the connection with the supply chain, because “86 percent of acquisitions arose from local companies in Macao”, and of this total, “59 percent were local SME acquisitions”. Similar scenario occurred in the other operators that Melco holds in Cyprus and Manila, with local acquisitions around 40 and 76 percent, respectively.
Regarding the company's training actions, Melco says it has invested on average "582 US dollars per full -time worker in learning and development activities, which is equivalent to an average of 38 hours of training." In this context, “100 percent of colleagues participated in training actions”, can be read. In addition, "over 758,000 participants have attended more than 1,400 courses offered by" Melco Learning Academy ", which is equivalent to over 870,000 hours of learning." Also noteworthy is that, in all Melco projects, "women represent 23 percent of the boards of business and 32 percent of the higher paintings."
The report also tells that “63 percent of positions at the vice-presidency level, or above this post, were filled from local communities, increasing to 70 percent in Macao”, can read.
All for the environment
Another of the areas highlighted in Melco's sustainability report concerns environmental policies. One of the areas that is “in progress” is the energy consumption, in order to obtain more reasonableness of consumption. "In 2024, despite an increase of 39 percent in terms of the number of visitors and the rise of 19 percent in the occupation rate of the hotel rooms, along with the addition of a property and a new resort integrated into our portfolio, the energy intensity increased by 10 percent from 2023, but was 19 percent lower than our year of reference 2019."
One of the “achieved” objectives is the energy efficiency measures, which “since 2018 has resulted in an annualized savings of more than 62.5 million kWh, an increase of 9 percent compared to 2023”. Another "achieved" goal concerns the installation of "over 25,000 photovoltaic panels on all properties in Macau, Manila and Cyprus, generating about 10,000 kWh annually." Thus, in the properties of Melco "the electricity consumption from renewable sources increased by 72 percent compared to 2023".
Regarding the group's means of transportation, “buses, electric and hybrid vehicles represent 55 percent of our combined fleet, with loading stations, an increase of 25 percent compared to 2023”.
In terms of materials and waste management, Melco says it has avoided plastic spending in the order of 13.2 million bottles, thanks to the installation of “the Nordaq water filtering system that serves almost every hotel rooms in Melco Integrated Resorts”.
In addition, the example of the City of Dreams venture in Manila is presented where “a circular economy system was established in which food waste is decomposed on site, and the excess donated to a local fifth to cultivate some of the vegetables served to guests”.
In terms of water consumption, the report indicates that “despite the increase in the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate”, “total water consumption and water intensity increased only 6 and 2 percent compared to 2023, respectively, and were 6 and 30 percent lower, respectively, to the 2019 reference year”. However, this is a goal that, according to the company, is still "in progress".
Another objective highlighted in the report was the “annual economy of over 510,820 cubic meters of water through water efficiency measures, an increase of 10 percent compared to 2023 ″.
"As we invest in people and communities, we continue to derive environmental efforts with the same determination. (…) The intensity of energy and water consumption, as well as greenhouse gas emissions, remained significantly below our 2019 base line, even adding a new property and an integrated resort," says Lawrence Ho.
The entrepreneur also referred to the increase "of the amount of valuable materials diverted through recycling and composting in global operations - 58 percent over last year." “In our restoration spaces we also fight food waste, with the 'clean dish challenge' to contribute to a 9 percent reduction in waste in the Macao and Manila restoration areas.”
“Mentality change”
For Lawrence Ho, greater sustainability in Melco requires "a change of mindset" verified in "small actions that, on scale, can have a significant impact."
Regarding the supply chain of the group's integrated hotels and resorts, good results are also highlighted. "Although the numbers do not always show exponential heels, our focus on responsible supply remains unshakable, 18 percent of all seafood bought by weight to be sustainable sources, and 100 percent of our points of sale of food and beverage in Macau and Manila to serve eggs of outdoor chickens," he reads.
There is thus "an effort that reflects a deeper ambition to incorporate sustainability into acquisitions," said Lawrence Ho, who added that "more than one service, hospitality has to do with the experience it creates, the people it supports and the impact it leaves."
“Every year, Melco challenges himself to go further, believing that luxury and responsibility are not opposite forces, but partners in progress, which is reflected in the way we defend strong governance, we manage our environmental impact, we support our people and communities and lead the responsible game. This commitment to progress shaped our approach in 2024, as a year of recalibration in which we continue to strengthen operations, operations, rekindle the impetus and ensure that our integrated resorts remain at the forefront of excellence, ”he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:08:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Seismos | Macau will have a monitoring station in national partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/sismos-macau-vai-ter-estacao-de-monitorizacao-em-parceria-nacional/</link><description>The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, presented on Wednesday the report of the 2025 government lines for his tutelage, and said to the deputies that a seismo monitoring station will be created in partnership with interior authorities from China will be created.
 
The Macao government announced on Wednesday the creation, together with the interior authorities of China, of a seismic monitoring station, as part of the authorities' plans to reinforce disaster prevention. “The meteorological and seismic monitoring network will be optimized, and is foreseen, in collaboration with the competent services of the interior of China, the construction of a seismic monitoring station,” said the secretary for public works and transport, by presenting, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), the lines of government action (LAG) for the guardianship, for 2025.
Raymond Tam will justified the new station with the intention of "increasing the capacity for analysis and evaluation in the scope of natural disasters." The space has realized in the direction of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), will be located in Hengqin.
"Macao's earthly area is small and population density is very high, so it is difficult to find space for the creation of monitoring stations and now with the favorable policies with Guangdong province, we have been able to build a joint monitoring station in the cooperation zone [deepened between Guangdong and Macau]," SMG director Leong Weng Kun said. The official noted that the space should contribute to "increasing prevention capacity and public knowledge about weather information."
Agree
Macao and Zhuhai signed the “comprehensive and deepening cooperation project in the context of meteorology, to reinforce the cooperation and sharing of meteorological detection equipment, computer programs and data sharing, according to a statement released by SMG at that time.
Cooperation is also expected to reinforce the “joint prevention of weather catastrophs alert systems, promote scientific and technological research and the development of artificial intelligence applied to weather activity”.
Macao is often affected between May and November by the passage of Tuffons, being July to September the period in which the highest incidence of tropical storms is recorded. This year, the territory is expected to be affected by between five to eight tropical storms, SMG announced in March.
Light Metro | Secretary admits operating gaps
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam said on Wednesday that the light meter is still short of the expectations of the population. "I have to confess that the services of the Light Metro, namely the electronic payment services, are still short of the expectations of the population of Macao," he said, promising measures for the means of transport to improve "gradually".
Environment | Policies planning will be studied this year
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam announced on Wednesday that this year will be "Study for the Next Planning of Environmental Protection", to support new "environmental policies based on a scientific and prospective view." Still in the area of ​​the environment, the ruler promised measures to achieve the national objective of the “double carbon goal”. As such, concrete emission reduction shares will be driven, including legislative elaboration for the control of emissions from non -road mobile sources, the slaughter of highly polluting vehicles, the improvement of the electric vehicle charging network, the exploitation of the potential application of photovoltaic energy in public spaces and the optimization of the energy structure ”, concluded the report.
Housing | Government admits to review the whole policy
With the reduction of demand for economic housing, the government admits to review all housing policy. "We are reviewing our policy at this time, taking into account the changes recorded. We will evaluate if there is a need to review the five housing class policy, but it is a subject that is still being studied," said Raymond Tam, secretary for transport and public works in the debate on governance lines for this year. The ruler said that "public housing policies will be reviewed and perfected, promoting the construction of social and economic housing and ensuring rational availability, in order to satisfy the housing needs of residents with different levels of income." Lots of zone A of new landfills should be completed between 2026 and 2028.</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:08:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Startups | Portugal interested in the SINO-LUSOPHONE TECHNOLOGY FUND</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/startups-portugal-interessado-no-fundo-sino-lusofono-de-tecnologia/</link><description>A delegation from Macao, with government representatives and local startups, is in Portugal to meet with leaders of Portuguese companies and participate in the SIM conference, which ends today in Porto. During the visit, a protocol was signed that signs the Portuguese interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund, managed by Heng Qin Group's state-owned company Zhuhai
 
Several macao startups are represented on a trip to Portugal this week, and whose delegation also includes representatives of the Directorate of Economics and Tourism Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries Association (AEIMCP). The objective is to strengthen ties with the entrepreneurship ecosystems of Lisbon and Porto and reinforce Portugal's interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund designed to support startups, which will be managed by Heng Qin Group's Zhuhai state company.
In this sense, a protocol between AEIMCP and the nascent Value, “Portuguese company with extensive investor capture” and also “accelerating small business growth (SME) and startups in Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, focused on innovation and cutting-edge technology”, is signed on Monday, in Lisbon, in Lisbon, in Lisbon.
The protocol signed on Monday signs the highest Portuguese access to the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund. The document was signed as part of a visit from the Macau Group to Lispolis - Lisbon Technological Pole.
The nascent Value thus becomes a “exclusive agent for investor capture services in Portugal, focusing on the involvement of investors in the background” SINO-LUSOPHONE, whose official name is “from Heng Qin Sino-Maluso Technology and Innovation Investment LPF”. This “promotes investments in high quality science and technology innovation companies in Portuguese -speaking countries”, explains the same note.
Thus, this protocol will allow AEIMCP, as a connecting entity between Portugal and the Fund via Macau, and the nascent Value, “reinforce its commitment to support startups, promote transfronhoring investment and create new opportunities for collaboration between Macau, Portugal and other Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Quoted by the same note, AEIMCP's Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said this new agreement shows how the entity, which also organizes the “929 Challenge” contest, is committed to “creating bridges for the global startup growth, facilitating the entry of Portuguese startups into the Chinese market through Macao, as well as the expansion of Chinese startups to Portugal and Europe”.
In turn, Rui Ferreira said that “the signing of this protocol is an important milestone for connecting innovation ecosystems and promoting synergies between macao startups and Portuguese investors”. "We are confident that this partnership will bring significant results for both sides," he added.
At HM, Rui Ferreira explained that the signature of the protocol represents the culmination of a work of about a year.
“We want to promote a model of welcoming startups and companies from Macao that want to enter Europe through Portugal, as well as in Portuguese-expression countries, and vice versa, that is, to place, through Macau, companies of these territories, but always through Portugal, in the East, in order to obtain easier connections with the Chinese market.”
Thousand Visits
Macao's group visited several essential points of the Portuguese entrepreneurship sector. In addition to the visit to Lispolis, considered the “key moment to foster dialogues between Deep Tech startups and potential investors, consolidating Macau's vision as an innovation and entrepreneurship hub with global range”, the entourage passed through the unicorns factory in Lisbon, and the PWC consultant.
Marco Duarte Rizzolio explained to HM the benefits to Macao from the journey through Portugal. “In addition to the interest in the Sino-Lusophone Fund and its preparation, as it will be released soon, our focus has also been the startups. On the visit to Lispolis macao startups made a pitch [attempted investment tarning], presented their products and had a networking session with other startups. Immersion in the Entrepreneurship Ecosystem in Portugal. ”
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, Macao's entourage only took to Portugal to startups with a more advanced business phase, namely Zence Object, founded by Calvin Sio and obtained a $ 2.5 million financing from the Alibaba Group entrepreneurs to the Great Bay area. Zence Object uses patented technology to transform organic waste, namely tea leaves, into alternative plastic and paper products. The idea is that these recycled and transformed products can be used on a daily basis, such as home or decorating utensils.
"There are startups in Macau who are very advanced in terms of business and we have brought to Portugal. We want to explore new opportunities for internationalization, so that they explore other markets, as these startups already have some development. We want to create partnerships, so that these representatives realize what the market is like and explore possible customers," said the representative of AEIMCP.
By unbeaten paths
Macao's entourage is today in Porto to participate in “SIM Conference” [Startups &amp; Investment Matching], where “it will have its own stand to present projects and connect with investors and possible customers”. This event was organized by the Entity Startup Portugal, which invited to be present.
Also today will be signed another protocol, this time between the association that organizes the contest “929 Challenge” and Startup Portugal. The idea is, according to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, “stimulate the connection of the Portugal ecosystem with Macau and help in the process of internationalization of the startups on both sides, both the Portuguese who are intended for the great bay, through Macau, both the macao startups that go to Portugal”.
The official has no doubt that what is lacking in knowledge is left in interest. “There is a great interest in China, but at the same time there is a great ignorance. The startup ecosystem in Portugal is much more linked to Europe. When we talk to the unicorns factory for months, we were told that there was a great interest in the Macao and China market, but that these visits to Portugal were lacking. It is growing a lot in technology and artificial intelligence, with the launch of DeepSeek, for example. ”
According to Rui Ferreira, the presence of the delegation of Macao in “Yes Conference” will allow access to “privileged and wider contacts”, as it is a national event. "With this visit we have been able to do two things: starting the relationship with AEIMCP more formally and helping Macao companies know of partners and investors. We also want to bet on the work for the future Sino-Musso fund, to prepare companies with investment potential," he said.
For Rui Ferreira, the Macao market has the potential “to be used as a business exchange platform, thanks to linguistic connection, and there is conditions in the territory to establish all the part of reception, support and exchange with China entities and create an ecosystem”. In addition, “it will be interesting Macao to make a specialized innovation hub in strategic areas”, which in this case is technology.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:10:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Blackout | Normality resumed yesterday, it still causes because it</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/apagao-normalidade-retomada-ontem-causa-ainda-por-apurar/</link><description>The week has started atypically on the Iberian Peninsula. It was a few minutes from 11:30 am on Monday, when a widespread electricity failure paralyzed Portugal and Spain. Only near 23h the light returned to the Portuguese house, but the dropper
 
It was an apparent normal Monday, but this normality was dissipated late in the morning with the electricity failure that gradually led to communication failures and impossibility of using mobile data. Portugal and Spain were without electricity for too many hours on Monday, an unprecedented episode in terms of energy failures.
In the case of Lisbon, the light began to fail a few minutes after 11:30 am, followed by the impossibility of communication via mobile data. Traffic in the center of the Portuguese capital became chaotic, without traffic lights in operation, generating some road accidents. Supermarkets, cafes and restaurants, with no possibility of maintaining normal operation and food properly refrigerated, closed doors. Many people, frightened by the possibility of staying several days without light, ran to supermarkets, sagging canned foods, water carboys, candles and batteries.
In addition to the unusual constraints in people's daily lives, with the suddenly closed meter and congested transport, there were suspended flights and closed airports. The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the Center of Portugal.
The circulation in the Lisbon Metropolitan (ML) was resumed at all at 08:38, Lisbon time, first in the blue and red lines at 08h, in yellow at 08:15 and green at 08:38.
"The Lisbon Metropolitano had a vast team working yesterday evening [Monday] and today's dawn [Tuesday] to ensure the replacement of operating systems affected by the widespread energy failure yesterday," the ML said in a statement.
Government words
In a note issued by the Portuguese government in the early hours of yesterday morning, it was said that there were already “virtually all services, including the supply of energy, restored,” Presidential Minister António Leitão Amaro told Lusa.
According to the minister, all 6.4 million customers had access to electricity in the early hours of Tuesday morning, except 800 who had faults not related to the blackout.
Leitão Amaro also said that water supply is working throughout the country, with only a few pressure difficulties in "two or three municipalities" that will be "resolved quickly".
Regarding transportation, the minister said that the "trains are working", and it is still necessary to stabilize some points of the operation, but due to the effects of 24 hours strike that took place on Monday.
About airports, “are operational,” said Leitão Amaro, recognizing that in the case of Lisbon airport, which was the most affected by energy failure and should take two days [to this day] to have stabilized flows, although the systems are all operational.
Normalized Schools and Health
The Portuguese ruler also said that, in relation to schools, the orientation issued at dawn to all directors was to open and function normally, except for cases where there may be some specific security ratio.
"The supply of fuels is normalized and did not record, at night, relevant occurrences of security or civil protection" in the country, advanced Leitão Amaro, stressing that the situation is also stabilized in health services.
"Hospitals and health centers are in terms of supply and supply to function normally," he said. "Right now, what we can say is that [energy] systems are stabilized, both in transportation and consumers supply," said the presidency minister.
In Spain there were also several embarrassment, especially at the level of transport. Pedro Sánchez, Spanish Prime Minister, said on Monday, quoted by Lusa, that this episode was unprecedented in the country. The ruler spoke to the country after the second meeting of Spain National Security Council. "All potential causes are analyzed without discarding any hypothesis," he added.
Gigawatts loss
The Spanish government leader revealed that, according to the technicians and experts of the Spanish power grid, 15 generation gigawatts "suddenly lost the system in just five seconds, something that had never happened."
According to explained, to give a dimension of the event, 15 kilowatts of generation correspond to approximately looking for total electricity in the country at the time of blackout (12:33 in Spain, 11h33 in Lisbon). "What has caused this sudden disappearance of supply" is something that experts cannot yet explain, he added.
In the early hours after the blackout, information began to circulate on a possible cyberathel who never confirmed. A few hours after the blackout, Ursula Von der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on Linkedin's social network that he had spoken with the prime ministers Pedro Sánchez and Luís Montenegro about the monitoring of the case.
“I reaffirmed that the European Commission has supported and monitored the situation with national and European authorities and together with our electricity coordination group. We will gather efforts and share information to help restore the electricity supply system, agreeing to maintain narrow contact,” reads one of the publications.
Eduardo Prieto, head of operations at Spanish Red Electric, told the Associated Press that the situation was not preceded by something “exceptional and extraordinary”. One of the possible causes pointed to the blackout is a rare atmospheric phenomenon, referred to as “induced atmospheric vibration”, which may have originated “anomalous oscillations” in the high voltage lines of the Spanish energy network. "These oscillations have caused synchronization failures between electrical systems, leading to successive disturbances in interconnected European networks," the Portuguese Energy company Ren to BBC told Monday afternoon. But later Ren denied this information.
Many issues
Another causes may have been technical problems in the electric network itself. Onyema NDUKA, a full -sustainability professor of energy sustainability at the University of London, said electric networks are usually interconnected because the production centers that feed them are located far from cities. This means that a power cut in a part of the grid can "lead to a waterfall effect in other areas."
"Ideally, redundancies are incorporated into the system, such as having several supply points, reserve generators located in different locations, wires and interconnected cables, etc.," he said. The solution is through energy companies to restore electricity to affected customers as soon as possible, but the procedure for doing so “has not yet been revealed,” added NDUKA.
The Portuguese authorities, cited by the AP and the local media, have so far attributed the failure of energy to unspecified technical problems, originating outside the country, but mentioned that the investigation is still underway.
The possibility of a cyberatoque is, for now, away. “Spain has mechanisms to deal with this kind of situations. Once again, I appeal to citizens to collaborate with all authorities and act responsibly and civilly, as we have always done,” wrote Pedro Sánchez on social networks. The Portuguese National Cyberrseness Center also stated in a statement that there is no evidence that the failure was caused by a computer attack.
Speaking to Euronews, Taco Engelaar, Neara Director-General, a specialist in energy infrastructure, said the interconnectivity of national networks and their systems would mean that a failure or attack would have the same net result.
"Such a widespread failure of the network is extremely unusual and can be caused by a number of factors: a physical failure on the network that provokes the power cut, a coordinated cybercar or a dramatic imbalance between demand and the supply that has made the network system exceeds the boundaries," he said.
"If it is a system failure, then the interconnectivity between the different regional and national networks can lead to the large amount of power cuts we are watching today [Monday]," he added. "The same applies to a cybership - many of these systems are linked and sharing assets - to overthrow one can overthrow many," he said. With agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:32:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity cut affects Portugal, Spain and parts of southern France</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/corte-de-electricidade-afecta-portugal-espanha-e-partes-do-sul-de-franca/</link><description>A flaw of electricity affected, at 11:33 (18h33 in Macao), Portugal, Spain and some areas of southern France.
In the first moments, information and speculation about the cause of the blackout were disseminated, namely in relation to a possible large-scale cyberataque, a hypothesis that was not excluded in the first instance by the General Secretariat of Internal Administration.
Until the closing of this issue, the cause was not yet clear, nor was there an estimate for the return of electricity, but Prime Minister Luís Montenegro said he had hope that the light supply would be resumed yesterday, according to Lisbon time (7 less for Macau). However, there were news in Portuguese media that pointed to the return of electricity in various parts of the country, as well as in Spain.
The Expresso newspaper cited data collected by the operators of the electricity network in the Iberian peninsula that pointed to tension imbalances as an explanation for the "blackout" rather than a cyberatheck designed to affect energy infrastructures. Until the closing of this edition, the Portuguese government did not rule out any explanation for the incident.
The e-nodes warned that the forecast of electricity replacement remained indefinite and could be prolonged, without advance an estimate. "Given the problems of the network that persist the forecast of energy replacement remains undefined and may be prolonged," said the operator of the electricity distribution network in mainland Portugal, in a statement.
E-Redes reiterated that the supply of electricity in Portugal was being affected by upstream constraints of the distribution network, in the very high voltage network in Spain.
According to REN - national power grid, yesterday's blackout may have been caused by abnormal temperature fluctuations in Spain. The news was advanced by the BBC, which mentions an atmospheric phenomenon.
Pandemonium scenario
The incident caused chaos in the country. At airports, check-ins became manuals and began to be announced on flights at first, but were eventually canceled. TAP has issued a statement to appeal to passengers so as not to go to airports, as operation is temporarily conditioned due to blackout.
Rail traffic was also totally interrupted throughout the Iberian Peninsula. In the hospitals, emergency generators and emergency services and surgeries have been prioritized to respond to urgent cases.
In addition to the Emergency Meeting of the Council of Ministers, the National Operational Coordination Center, which is part of the entities in the context of protection and relief operations, gathered to follow the situation and adopt the necessary procedures due to the lack of energy in mainland Portugal.
The telephone and computer systems of the National Institute of Emergency Medical was operating until the closing of this edition using generators and the fuel supply posts interrupted the services.
On the other hand, the Águas de Portugal (ADP) group appealed to water consumption only for essential uses, “very moderate”, and said there were only “punctual failures”. Heard by Lusa regarding the widespread cutting of electricity and a possible water failure, the company's official source warned that there may be consumer constraints, although without advanced more concrete data.
ADP, which brings together more than a dozen water suppliers on the continent, "appeals to the use of water for the essentials only." "ADP is following the situation in all companies," the source said. The company, he added, intends to ensure that essential services have water and recalled that reservoirs have water but it takes energy to transport it, and that even the buildings themselves need energy to get water to consumers taps.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Facilitated automatic passage from foreign visitors</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/28/lag-2025-facilitada-passagem-automatica-de-visitantes-estrangeiros/</link><description>In the presentation of this year's security lines for security, Wong Sio Chak referred to the idea of ​​facilitating the entry into Macau to foreign visitors, with the creation of more automatic passage points
 
The Secretary for Security announced on Friday, plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors through the use of automatic electronic channels.
During the presentation of the Governing Action Lines Report (LAG) to 2025 in the area of ​​Security, Wong Sio Chak stated that the territory will extend the use of automatic passage points to foreign citizens without resident or work authorization.
To facilitate “exterior exchanges”, authorities will expand autoservice equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, the leader explained.
To the deputies at the Legislative Assembly, the secretary added that the government will continue to optimize iris recognition technology in border controls and to study its extension to non-residents this year.
"We are also studying ways to widen the number of users eligible for automatic passage channels, allowing more foreign tourists to benefit from faster immigration processes and more fluid circulation in the large bay," Wong said.
Speech and company
In his speech, the secretary stated that "regarding the creation of a higher level of opening abroad, the input and output services will continue to be optimized and the facilitation measures of the border passage, to ensure a safe, effective, efficient and comfortable passage."
Thus, "with a view to promoting the exchange with the outside, the automatic passage channels will also have foreigners, so that they deal with the input and exit inspection formalities through these channels."
According to official data, Macau received, in 2024, 34.9 million visitors, 23.8 percent than the previous year, but only 2.42 million were international tourists. In October last year, the Chinese Foreign Ministry extended the Portuguese visa exemption policy, thus inserting Portugal into a list that already covered another 16 European countries.
The measure, which allows the Portuguese to stay in China for tourism, business or traffic for a maximum of 15 days, in force at least until December 31, 2025.
In the same month, Continental China had announced the expansion, from 90 to 180 days, from the permanence period for foreign residents of Macao on multiple entries in the country.
The measure includes permanent and non-permanent foreign residents of Macao that move “to the interior of China for short-term tourism, trade, visit to family members, visits and other activities”.
From July, the Chinese National Immigration Administration (NIA) had already allowed foreign permanent residents from Macao and Hong Kong to request authorization to enter the interior of China, valid for a maximum of five years. The measure covers members of the Portuguese community who are permanent residents in Macao and, until then, were required to ask for a visa to travel to the other side of the border.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:26:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment | Leong Sun Iok warns of collecting candidate information</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/emprego-leong-sun-iok-alerta-para-recolha-de-informacao-de-candidatos/</link><description>Leong Sun IOK warns of the increase of companies that research the past of job candidates and argues that the information obtained by former employers is often skewed and unfair. The deputy calls for regulation to the government
 
Deputy Leong Sun IOK intends that the government regulates the collection of information carried out by companies about job candidates. The request is contained in a written interpellation, in which the legislator linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) warns of the occurrence of various illegalities, without any consequences.
According to the scenario outlined by Leong Sun Iok, when applying for a job, especially through online platforms, interested parties are led to sign forms and to consent that entities research their past.
However, the deputy warns that the practice is illegitimate, uncommon, allowing the creation of informal black lists and the exchange of information between companies. This situation can result in the blocking of job opportunities for former employees who have had different employer entities. "It is a practice that blocks access to employment in an industry, which seriously undermines the right to employment," says the legislator.
Leong Sun Iok also reveals that “over the years he has received a high number of requests and assistance” from people faced from one of the six game dealers and that they have later seen themselves. "Some people who asked me for help told me that they were convinced by supervisors to say goodbye. And if they did not say goodbye to their initiative, they were threatened that they would never find employment in the industry again. All these cases reflect the damage caused by collecting information without any regulation," added the deputy.
However, the practice is not limited to this sector: "In addition to the game dealers, there are a high number of companies in Macao that also requires employment candidates to allow their past to be investigated," he said.
Against the law
Leong Sun IOK also points out that the Labor Relations Law and Decree-Law 101/84/M define that former expirers when issuing a proof of work to a former worker cannot make any unfavorable reference to its past. However, the deputy indicates that the current, even informal practice, contradicts the spirit of the law, ending up being more harmful, because the former employee has no control over information that may not even be true.
"As the verification process lacks transparency and is not controlled by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, it is unfair to employment candidates and can violate the principle of good faith in labor relations," he warns. "How will management regulate information about professional background? It is possible to issue guidelines and change the law to explicitly stipulate that former employers should in no way transmit, make statements or adopt unfavorable behaviors to workers?"</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:22:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Alvis Lo Vinca bets on professional competitiveness</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/saude-alvis-lo-vinca-aposta-na-competitividade-profissional/</link><description>The Director of Health Services, Alvis Lo, considers that the government's plan to increase the value of health valleys and launch a chronic disease screening program will improve the system and access to health in the territory. The position was taken during the latest board meeting for medical affairs.
To increase the competitiveness of health professionals, Alvis Lo has indicated that the executive will “provide a series of training programs, including the creation of a Family Medicine Training Base” as well as “systematic training to doctors of public and private institutions”.
For doctors who want to focus on a specialty, the SS promised to permanently open the competitions to fill complementary boarding school vacancies, as well as optimize procedures and “shorten the time” necessary for the contests.
In addition, Alvis Lo noted that the Macao Medical Center of the Peking Union Medical College Hospital aims to become a “high-level formation in Macau”, so in the next few times they should start to be sent to Beijing doctors, nurses and other clinical technicians to receive training. At this stage, there is also the possibility that the formations are not limited to the Chinese capital.
Following the tendency to lead the population to leave Macau, Alvis Lo has indicated that the government will support integration in national development, which should start with professionals to large bay and the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, as they are considered “more easy and mature starting points”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:19:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Patane | Food Center received 300 thousand customers in 11 months</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/patane-centro-de-comidas-recebeu-300-mil-clientes-em-11-meses/</link><description>Between April 2024 and March this year, the Patane Food Center attracted 300,000 residents and tourists. The data were released by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), in response to an interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai, the residents.
However, AMI states that it will continue to promote the space, which is located in the Patane market, with the placement of a giant announcement in the area: “Currently, the roads around the Patane market already have indicative signs and bright tabs were also placed on access to the market floor”, was indicated by Chao Wai Ieng, president the body. "In parallel, AMI plans to place a large claim on the façade of the Patane Market Complex, with a view to attracting more residents and tourists to eat in that food center," he was added.
The AMI also promised to continue to “raise the competitiveness and attractiveness” of the restoration space by installing “decorations” during holidays and festivities, as well as “the release of awards with points obtained and the invitation to the media for filming and promotion”.
AMI also says it encourages “newsstands to reinforce the promotion” of spaces through “innovation” and “online marketing and offline activities” with discount coupons.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:17:57</pubDate></item><item><title>WONG KIT CHENG calls for more birth incentive measures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/wong-kit-cheng-pede-mais-medidas-de-incentivo-a-natalidade/</link><description>Deputy Wong Kit Cheng considers that the government should create complementary birth incentive measures beyond the childhood assistance allowance in the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for this year, and aims to grant 1,500 monthly patacas for children up to a maximum limit of three years of age.
According to the citizen newspaper, Wong Kit Cheng believes that incentives for birth not only depend on financial support, but also on measures that take into account all the needs faced by local families.
The deputy said that more efforts are needed in areas such as health, housing, education and social facilities to support couples with children. Given that, in their view, public departments do not have sufficient coordination with each other, their own department should be created to promote birth incentive policies permanently.
Regarding the health area, the deputy, vice president of the Directorate of the General Union of Macao, advocates a greater specialization in pregnant care, namely at the level of a greater scope of examination of genetic diseases. Wong Kit Cheng calls for further advances in the level of pediatric health care and new measures regarding painless births. With regard to the free vaccination program, the deputy asks for more vaccines to be covered.
Houses for all
Another point highlighted by the deputy is the housing policy, which according to Wong Kit Cheng should respond to the needs of families in different phases, that is, from childhood to the growth of children. This said that the social and economic housing model has a punctuation system that gives families priority, but that the hypothesis of exchange of houses should be studied, so that families can change their housing depending on the number of children they have.
For the legislator, there is also a need to review the planning of the leisure facilities for the youngest. The deputy stressed that the number of public facilities must be linked to the population density of each zone and the number of children resident.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:15:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | PS again denounces alleged ATFPM practices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/eleicoes-ps-volta-a-denunciar-alegadas-praticas-da-atfpm/</link><description>The Macao Public Service Association is again accused by the Socialist Party to commit illegalities in the context of the vote of local voters for the next legislative elections in Portugal. Rita Santos and José Pereira Coutinho, from ATFPM, deny everything
 
The prosecution is not new: the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM) was the subject of a complaint made by the Socialist Party (PS) to the National Elections Commission (CNE) in Portugal, for making “actions that compromise the freedom and confidentiality of vote” of local voters for May 18, in Portugal, which will serve a new parliament and first minister.
According to the PS complaint sent to the CNE, which includes photos of the alleged illegalities, "the presence of individuals who identify themselves as" volunteers "at the door of a Macao Post station, addressing voters to indicate where they should vote."
Thus, “this is the same practice that occurred in the last legislative elections that took place in 2024 and it was found to be conducted by Rita Santos, a prominent figure of ATFPM and advisor to the Portuguese communities”. Rita Santos, however, stopped being a counselor.
The images attached to the complaint show "one of the volunteers at the Macao postal door, addressing voters", and "in some cases requests the delivery of voting bulletins," a practice that suggests "directing the vote and calling into question the fundamental principles of a democratic electoral process."
Scenario of “impunity”
HM confronted Rita Santos and José Pereira Coutinho, president of ATFPM, with this complaint, both denied the accusations. "We are unaware of the situation of volunteers referring because ATFPM is not involved or interferes with the elections of the Assembly of the Republic of Portugal. This year are the elections of the Legislative Assembly (AL) of Macao and we are committed to the presentation of the candidacy of the Nova Esperança list," said Rita Santos.
Pereira Coutinho, also deputy to Al, said “unaware of” the accusation. "ATFPM has no one to do this, they are inventions to which we are alien," he said.
It is recalled that the last complaint submitted by the PS to the CNE was then sent to the prosecutor in Portugal. The investigation still takes place and is in secret of justice, as already reported, and no accusation has not yet been deducted. Already in 2019, the PS had submitted a similar complaint.
The PS understands that "the constant action of the association in the electoral context raises concerns about the possible misuse of resources to influence the voting process", in the case of "recurring practices in potundous legislative elections".
"The persistence of such behaviors, coupled with apparent impunity, aggravates the severity of the facts and requires, once and for all, a firm response from the competent authorities," the PS.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:14:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Administration | Ng wai han leaves from SAFP to drive dicj</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/administracao-ng-wai-han-sai-dos-safp-para-dirigir-dicj/</link><description>With the passage of Adriano Marques Ho to customs services, the direction of inspection and coordination of games began to be led interim by its sub-director Lio Chi Chong. The secretary for the economy and finances yesterday appointed NG Wai Han, the first woman at the head of the regulating entity of the Macao game
 
The Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ) has a new director. An order signed by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, published yesterday in the official bulletin, names NG Wai Han as director of DICJ for a one year period. The NG Wai Han Service Commission began just yesterday with the publication of the order.
It is recalled that the position had been vacant since Adriano Marques Ho was taken to the post of Customs Director General in December, during the reformulation of the holders of high public positions with the inauguration of the new Sam Hou Fai government. To the place of Adriano Marques Ho, who has directed Dicj since June 2020, the new executive appointed sub-director Lio Chi Chong.
Ng Wai Han became the first woman in the leadership of the DICJ, after the exercise of Manuel das Neves, Paulo Martins Chan and Adriano Marques Ho.
The rise of the former director of administration and civil service services to the top of the DICJ hierarchy marks a difference in the profile of leaders, which have so far come from the area of ​​security forces.
WORK AND ADMINISTRATION
The Secretary for Economics and Finance states that “NG Wai Han has professional competence and aptitude to exercise the position of director of the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination, which is demonstrated by Curriculum Vitae”.
The new leader of the game regulatory entity in the territory is a law degree from the University of Sun Yat-Sen, where he also made a master's degree in Criminal Law.
In 1999, he entered the civil service, to the position of Higher Technique (legal area) of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), where it remained until 2013. Between 2013 and 2016, headed the Divisions of Study of the Department of Studies and Informatics and Labor Rights Control of the Department of Labor Inspection. In May 2016, he began to lead the Labor Inspection Department and a year later was appointed subdirect, substitute of DSAL, and subdirecting until 2020, when it moved to the administration and civil service services after two decades in DSal.
Between June 2020 and August 2023, Ng Wai Han was the subdirect of SAFP and a month later went to the SAFP, a position he held until yesterday.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 23:56:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Tour Guides | Government reduces fines due to the crisis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/guias-turisticos-governo-reduz-valores-das-multas-devido-a-crise/</link><description>Tour guides who work without proper identification must be paid lower fines. This is the will of the government taking into account the new scenario to reduce the number of excursions.
The matter was discussed in another meeting of the Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly (AL) that analyzes, in the specialty, the proposal of the activity of travel agencies and profession of tourist guide. At the meeting, which took place on Tuesday, Deputy Chan Chak Mo, who chairs the commission, explained that the government determined a significant reduction in the amount of the fine in case of offense after hearing the sector's opinions. At question is the fact that the content of the bill was prepared before the pandemic, but the Covid-19 years have changed the tourism landscape, with fewer excursions in Macao, which led to a crisis scenario. Thus, if the initial fine proposal focused between 10 and 20 thousand patacas, the new proposal goes down the penalty for values ​​between 2 and 10 thousand patacas.
In addition, at Tuesday's meeting, it was also referred to by government representatives that a warning mechanism will be created for guides who make the first offense, namely when they do not show the licensing card of the activity.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 23:54:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Manifestation contained</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/manifestacao-contida/</link><description>During the “golden week” on May 1st (Labor Day), the city center of Macao was flooded by a crowd, however, the environment was contradictory and the Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) continue to fight for survival. In the first quarter of 2025 the global unemployment rate (1.9 percent) and the unemployment rate of the residents (2.5 percent) increased 0.2 percentage points, compared to the indicators of the fourth quarter of 2024.
These numbers indicate that Macau's labor market is impacting economic recession and the influx of foreign workers. The numerous stores that closed in residential areas clearly reflect economic desolation. Although the “large award for consumption in community zones 2025” seems to function as a temporary accelerator, it does not attack the root of the problem.
There is social discontent in relation to the administration of the Government of MSAR, however, on May 1st, except for the situation of a citizen who was taken by the police to be investigated in the prosecutor for protesting without warning the direction of services to Labor Affairs (DSAL), no demonstrations or protests were registered. As the public complaints accumulate, the social atmosphere has become visibly silent. And is that good or bad?
The media revealed that the “Power of the People” group had notified the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) of its intention to organize a protest manifestation on May 1, according to the provisions of the “Law of Meeting and Manifestation” Law. Police officers “express their concern repeatedly, promoting several meetings with group members to analyze the situation and take the necessary measures” as well as “warning them of the various possibilities in the face of“ uncontrollable situations ”that would lead them to take on“ joint and and several liability ”or, otherwise, risk the“ law relating to the defense of the state's security ”. They felt the weight of the invisible pressure and reluctantly chose to present a letter where they exposed their views to DSal.
An article from another newspaper praised CPSP for the way he dealt with this case. He claimed that CPSP had significantly perfected its ability to disable “the Protest planned for May 1st”, and believed that CPSP, which supervises protests and manifestations according to the law, had adopted a “pros and cons” approach to neutralizing a mildly inflamed protest, eliminating possible social disturbances that came. On the one hand, the CPSP totally respected the rights of residents to protest and to express themselves and did not explicitly reject the notification presented by the group “Power of the People”. On the other hand, CPSP used persuasion to convince the group to cancel the “May 1 protest”.
Some people become condescending and think that the city gets more peaceful without protests or manifestations, and this thought is the one that worries me the most.
Someone with a minimum of common sense will understand that the accumulation of social discontent is not a motivating force, but a destructive force. The promulgation of the “Right of Meeting and Manifestation Law” has been intended to safeguard residents' freedom to manifest and protest, as guaranteed by the Macao Basic Law, not to ban them.
In the past, the Government of MSAR effectively communicated with the protest and demonstrations organizers and coordinated these events very well. Unfortunately, in recent years, authorities have been very nervous or guided by their own priorities; and often excite the subjects and rush to us to the level of national security. If a slight cough is condemned to cause a highly contagious and fatal virus, a lot of labor is wasted and many resources, and the vitality of society is suffocated!
A forest without any sound is terrifying and a silent river is full of murderous omens. A society cannot survive without any noise.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:47:38</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great America (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/a-grande-america-ii-2/</link><description>(Continuation)
"What is Great About America? Slavery, Hiroshima, Nagasaki, Indian Removal, Segregation, Vietnam War, Watergate." - Anthony Galli
What counts for the US Empire is Western Europe, “the mother of America,” that is, France, Germany, Italy, the United Kingdom, Spain, Portugal and Scandinavia as an opening for the arctic and anti-cruses barrier (anti-chinese). Not forgetting that the least interested in protecting Europe from the east are Euro-width. Question of asking the Danes, Germans and Dutch if they agree to give poles and Lithuanians a decision -making weight equal to their own. Why would a Spaniard fight against Moscow if a stonce decided to organize a colorful revolution in Russia? According to Maitra, the Mediterranean remains central to Americans, but not the Black Sea. Our middle ocean is the weak point of Europe. The danger does not come from the east, but from the south. No Russian tanks in Belgium. But there is a growing number of crises in the Mediterranean, caused by the decomposition of states, such as Libya, because of the French and the British. This is why France is one of the fundamental western countries for common security. However, I never realized why in certain issues, such as the total defense of Ukraine, France and Poland may have Falcon positions. Is it wanting to be more Catholic than the Pope? Over the centuries, France has been the bastion of realism. What happened? This question arises the number three answer that could be called revelation, responsibility and opportunity that is the triangle of our security.
Revelation in the apocalyptic sense referred to above. Trump drops the veil of hypocrisy agreed between Americans and Europeans. The former pretended to ensure unlimited protection and we pretended to believe in them. In such a way that many of us believe. In fact, it worked very well. Grateful, we rejoice. But it is now clear that superpower does not advocate all allies to the limit, some of them change nothing, and certainly none for free. Where the price, more than monetary, is human and military. It is a matter of reversing Norstad's postulate. That is, to have decent men and weapons and weapons so that, in the event of war, we do not fall into a dispensable battlefield, bombarded by friends and nuclear enemies. As it would have happened if the Cold War had warmed, which was narrowly. Responsibility. If we think we can enclose ourselves in a corner of the planet, enjoying our privileges, the story from which we emerge will knock us at the door. It will loot our apartments. Caosland advances. It is approaching Mediterranean Europe through the south and east, with its torrents of cholera and frustration, with the availability for the violence of young and suffering peoples, educated to see in today's Europeans the grandchildren of their former masters.
The decisive parameter of our geopolitical condition is the sum of demographic and biological factors. Southern Europe is the region with the highest average number of elderly people in the world, which is currently understanding 21 percent of the population, over 65 years old. It is expected to reach 30 percent by 2050 and Europe decreases its population between 2022 and 2050 by -7 percent or in a rampant decline up to 2080 compared to at least two billion people spread between Boreal Africa and Levante. Our Middle Ages should be over 50 years, against the 25 years of those who will knock on us at the door. It is not with tanks that this crisis is avoided. Militaryly, we will need naval, air, cyber and spatial control and interdiction instruments, along with a credible (young) terrestrial component. Above all, we will have to develop a courageous policy of coexistence and cooperation with the peoples and regimes of the Middle East, from North Africa to the Arabian peninsula. Regions where we still enjoy a good reputation. However, we are dissipating it as a lifetime pension when it should be regained and extended every day.
The Mattei investment plan in Africa of 5.5 billion euros is a drop in the ocean. It is urgent to resolve the old differences with the northern bank of the Mediterranean, starting with France. The habit of stumbling over each other in the pre -carré of which France is obliged to evacuate prepares the ground for mutual failure. As for Americans, they ask no more than support them as long as they put their boots on the floor if necessary. Opportunity. NATO is not Atan, with an "a" of alliance. A motto in itself indigestible for Washington, because it would allude to an impossible equality between leader and followers. We are in debt to the apocalytic Donald Rumsfeld for revealing, on the eve of aggression to Iraq, the figure of NATO and any other military organization led by the United States or any other leader.
The mission makes the coalition and not the other way around. And it is the leader who defines the mission. Dogma lived threatened by our decision makers in abandonment syndrome. We are so used to consider ourselves passive, to trust the "number one" as in "Our Lady", which we ignore the stimulus the warning contains. In the transactional scheme of tactical alignments that draw current chaos, we could transform the need to trust ourselves first. Do not reduce the pathetic lone knights. Still, some acts of soft piracy would help, considering how dear it is for Anglo-Saxons the sport of keeping someone honest and how little they consider us able to protect our interests. At the very least, we would surprise them. No relationship remains if each one considers the dogmatic fidelity of his partner as an acquired data. A degree of infidelity, that is, of initiative, would help cement the bilateral relationship with the United States. The worst possible agreement, no doubt.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:29:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence on Sex in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/a-inteligencia-artificial-sobre-o-sexo-em-macau/</link><description>I had the experience of asking the most popular artificial intelligence platform that themes about sex, sexuality and gender would make sense to discuss in Macau. The answer brought three proposals that, although not very surprising, I found it interesting. Of course the platform used some creative and intellectual freedom - which I didn't ask for - to invent sources, quotes and points of view. Basically, he went to seek what is already known about Taiwan and Hong Kong, about the growing opening to LGBTQI+themes, and tried to make parallels with Macao. He mentioned the rainbow of Macau/澳門彩虹/Rainbow of Macau as the most active association in defending LGBTQI+ rights in the territory, and even invented interviews with its founder, with fictional quotes.
The first proposal that artificial intelligence suggested is about Macao young people and their opening to non-binary and plural gender identities as a way of navigating western and oriental cultural identities, and monitoring generational changes. Worldwide we have seen an emancipation movement in this area, with many young people to discuss these issues openly. If in some countries institutions and policies follow these changes (and in others until retreat), in Macao the pit may be higher, taking into account its geographical situation. I went looking for studies that deepened the subject and found one who asked young people from Macau between 18 and 25 years old. The authors have analyzed how adherence to polyculturalism, the idea that crops are interconnected and influence each other, associated with lower levels of sexual prejudice, including negative attitudes towards LGBTQ+people. The study suggests that the cultural diversity of Macao, and the belief that cultures mingle, can create a predisposition to also accept sexual diversity. But I would say that it is still necessary to explore more about these issues, listening to real testimonies about the experiences of young people living in Macao.
The second proposal - which I have mentioned here without account - has to do with the lack of accessible, inclusive and focused sex education, promoting more knowledge and pleasure in Macao and worldwide. If a few months ago I gave the example of Hong Kong, where it was suggested to play Badminton as a way to manage sexual abstinence, I would say that Macau is not much more open to talking about sex than that. This lack of discussion creates a series of complications that, due to the absence of data in the region, do not even know the true dimension of the problem. The absence of comprehensive and inclusive sex education increases the risk of sexual violence, discrimination and propagation of sexually transmitted infections.
The third proposal surprised me, because it is a theme in which I rarely think: the growth of LGBTQia+ tourism in Asia and the opportunity that Macau has to bet on this niche. Since the hotel industry is the pillar of the economy of Macao, it would make sense to embrace this opportunity, as they have already made Thailand and Taiwan, creating LGBTQIA+spaces, or with specific events, such as Pride Month celebrations. According to some data produced online, this type of tourism is profitable and growing.
Artificial intelligence even has interesting ideas, although something generic. But I confess that I was pleased to realize that the algorithm is in tune to defend the rights of sexual minorities and has an inclusive discourse. It becomes dangerous, however, when it begins to invent data and information just so that the argument sounds good. Still, in general, it can be a useful tool for discussing these issues without judgment. As the platform itself says, it has the potential to “combat myths, spread ethical concepts and include perspectives of marginalized groups, democratizing access to more complete and positive sex education.” In this suggestion of content creation, it seemed aligned with these values.
If you will ever replace the work of people like me, who write on these topics, or the work of sexual educators… maybe it's too early to draw conclusions. Sensitive and thinking people still have a lot to contribute.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:14:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Saint Valentine's Day in the Czech Republic</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/dia-de-sao-valentim-na-republica-checa/</link><description>In Macao, many people know that May 1st is Labor Day and is an official holiday. The same takes place in mainland China, marking May 1st the beginning of a long holiday. However, few know that in the Republic checked May 1st is the "Day of St. Valentine".
On Valentine's Day, Czech lovers follow tradition and kiss under the cherry trees, singing songs to love. And the kiss why?
According to Czech folklore, if a girl is not kissed under a cherry tree on St. Valentine's day, she will "wither" next year, losing "youth and charm." Therefore, a kiss means "protection and blessings."
And what is “protection in love”? In mid -2015, Sean Lau, the winner of the Hong Kong's best actor's best actor award for his work in the movie “Overheard 3”, presented the “Space Nave Theory”. He used a simple phrase to show how his wife Amy Kwok protected him:
“When I enter a spaceship and travel anywhere in the universe, you always find a way to bring me back to Earth safely.”
The meaning of this phrase is simple and clear. If you are where you are, face what to face, you always bring me back safely. You are always by my side, making me be loved, hot, happy and in peace.
Apart from the “spacecraft theory”, there is another sean Lau phrase that is part of the “passionate quotes for my wife”:
"One day you no longer want to love love, you just want someone who doesn't leave you."
Does true love require two people to stay together? In March 2025, news was released in Taiwan, China, saying that a woman had published an online article, where she said she had a boyfriend six years ago, but eventually found out that he was getting married to another. And this happened because her boyfriend loved her so much and didn't want her to go through the suffering caused by her relationship with her mother-in-law, so she decided to marry a woman from whom her parents liked, but he didn't like and assured his girlfriend that his "relationship" would not be affected. After marrying another woman, she would date forever with her beloved.
Love implies "protection and blessings." Is it in favor of the “spacecraft theory” or “Nora/mother -in -law theory”?
What are "blessings"? In Taiwan, China, the host of the television program “Yu Meiren”, (Yu Yunjie) had no contact with her in -laws for a long time. Once went to court due to a disagreement between mother and husband. Finally, the judge stated that his 16 -year marriage had come to an end. Later, Yu Meiren has lost a lot of weight, but now it is more beautiful than before and at his disposal has changed. She stated:
"The French believe that in love we should accept those who come and we should not retain those who want to leave. 'When love happens, we must be ourselves, follow our hearts and act without schemes. When love is over, we must respect the other and not try to arrest or force it, which means that" letting out is the best of blessings. "
Do you agree with the phrase “letting go is the best of blessings, the blessing is the best relief”? Hong Kong Cine Cine Cine Cenilia Cheung once expressed some disappointment after the divorce:
"In love there is only one thing that can hurt us, it is the unwillingness. When we cannot live with ourselves, we inflicted pain."
Perhaps that “protection and blessings” have different meanings for each person, but for me,
"I have to say this only once. After all these years, I still love you."
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:37:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation hosts “polyphony” until next week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/fundacao-rui-cunha-acolhe-polifonia-ate-a-proxima-semana/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts until Saturday next week, the 17th, the collective exhibition “Polyfonia”, with works by artist Gu Yue and six doctoral students from the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must), co-organizer of the event.
The project makes known 20 works that represent the forms and styles of renowned artist and professor Gu Yue and his disciples Luo Su, Zhu Zhaohui, Wang Kongbin, Ding Song, Guo Weiwei, and Wei Dongsheng.
According to a FRC note, this exhibition presents “a visual banquet that transcends tradition and contemporaneity, the material and digital, the place and the global, through the collision of various media and the resonance of ideas”.
The works include various art forms, “such as installations, oil paintings, lacquer paintings, sand paintings and details to detail brush, displaying Macau's unique artistic ecosystem as a cultural convergence point”, is referred to.
The name of the exhibition originates “in musical terminology, referring to the opposition and symbiosis of multiple voices”. The presentation of the show states that "the mission of art is to create cognitive disorientation", and "through the confrontation between traditional crafts and the new media, and the rapport of local cultural genes and global issues, it breaks the linear narrative and invites the audience to calibrate their cognition in the" glow between brightness and residual shadow. "
Joint work
Professor Gu Yue aligns his work and the investigation with the main theme of the exhibition. The creations of the six doctoral students "start from individual experiences and respond to propositions such as identity, time and memory in the age of digital capital, also forming a multi-wing resonance of thought."
Exhibition is not only a concentrated exhibition of academic achievements, but also a speculative experience on the essence of art. “In this culturally stratified place of Macao, polyphony tries to use art as a prism to reflect the symbiotic possibilities of multiple realities,” describes the team, cited by the same note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:45:47</pubDate></item><item><title>AFA | “Déjà Vu” presents works in the area of ​​Video-Arte</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/afa-deja-vu-apresenta-trabalhos-na-area-da-video-arte/</link><description>Integrated in the poster of this year's edition of the French May festival, here is the new exhibition of the local AFA - Art for All Society Association. This is “Déjà VU-an exhibition of Sino-Francês artistic exchange”, where the themes of video art and artificial intelligence resonate from the signing works of Robert Cahen, Alice Kok and Catherine Cheong. To see in The Parisian between May 15 and June 28
 
Video art, mixed with the real and the fictional, artificial and created with human hands. It is around these ideas and concepts that revolves the new exhibition of AFA-Art for All Society, entitled “Dejá Vu-an exhibition of sino-francês artistic exchange”, and which gains the subtitle “Mirroring ・ Loging ・ Generatting”: from video art to artificial intelligence-exhibition series ”.
The project, patent between May 15 and June 28 in one of the galleries of The Parisian venture in Cotai, presents to the public works of three artists: Alice Kok, co-founder of AFA, artist and curator; Robert Cahen and Catherine Cheong. The project is integrated in this year's edition poster of the French May festival, which brings Hong Kong a series of cultural initiatives.
According to a statement from AFA, “Déjà vu” aims to establish “a bridge between the Sino-Franceses cultural dialogues through art”, also promoting the investigation into “the philosophical intersections of time, memory and perception”.
In addition to the presence in Macao, this show will be evident in France, between 21 and 30 August, at the Espace Temps Gallery in Paris. Thus, the “cultural exchange” is promoted between China and France, highlights AFA, and the public is invited to “witness the evolution of interaction between memory and technology”.
“Déjà vu”, theory developed by the French philosopher Henri Bergson, gives the motto to this show, revealing “the simultaneous division between perception and memory”, that is, “the coexistence between the present 'current' and its 'virtual' image in the mirror”. The works of the three artists thus exploit this abstract philosophical concept, transforming it into “tangible sensory experiences through video art, images generated by artificial intelligence and multimedia facilities”.
The show, which has the keywords “Mirroring”, “looping” and “Generation”, referring to the ideas of mirror, repetition or content generation, reflects “not only the artists techniques, but also metaphorizes the way memory and technology weave the invisible tissue of contemporary reality”.
Initial Workshop
In addition to the show itself, artists will also join to teach others about the world of digital and video art. Robert Cahen, considered one of the pioneers in Video Art in France, collaborates with Alice Kok for the “Video Postcards” workshop, held on May 18 The Parisian Macau. The idea is to lead participants to “dive into Coloane's natural and historical landscapes, inspired by the poetics of fleeting images', characteristic of Cahen's work”. Thus, “through techniques such as slow chamber, overlap and sound design, participants will transform ephemeral sensory experiences into unique '' postcards,” describes AFA, and experience includes filming, post-production context and final projection.
Who is who
Robert Cahen has been developing artistic projects since 1972. According to the official program of the French May festival, in Cahen's work “both fiction and documentation are presented as metaphorical trips of the imaginary, exquisite daydreams that describe passages of time, place, memory and perception”. Having started with the video cassettes, his works were exposed worldwide, in places and events such as the Paris Biennial, France; The Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), New York, USA; or the American Film Institute National Video Festival, Los Angeles, USA.
In 1992 the artist won the Villa Medicis Hors Les Murs award and, in 1995, created a permanent video installation for Euralille (Lille) public space in France.
In the case of Catherine Cheong, she is a local artist who lives between Macau and Paris, having graduated in the area of ​​video installation at the Visual Arts Degree at École Supérieure D'Art et de Design Toulon. In addition, the artist graduated in personal creation and contemporary engraving theory with a master's degree in visual arts at the University of Paris VIII.
“As an individual artist, his inspiration comes from personal experience. Through cultural differences, contradictions and interactions between human beings, the social environment and nature, explores the realization of life and the feelings of the soul. It goes back, juxtaposes and doubles symbolic images to recreate new meanings, seeking coincidence between images with different artistic languages ​​and means to express feelings, thoughts and personal desires”, can be read in the “FRench program”. May ”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:43:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Ka Hó | “Hold on to Hope” gallery welcomes “our time zone”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/ka-ho-galeria-hold-on-to-hope-acolhe-our-time-zone/</link><description>The “Hold on To Hope” gallery, managed by the Macao Toxicode Rehabilitation Association (ArtM) at the settlement of Ka-Hó, in Coloane, has a new show, entitled “Our Time Zone-Collective Art Exhibition and Curative Calligraphy” with works by artists Kinki Wong and Belinda Chim. The exhibition is organized by the Macau Hope Painting Association and, according to words by Kinki Wong, who collaborates not only as an artist, but also as a curator, "was born of the idea that everyone experiences moments of ups and downs, uncertainty and confusion."
Thus, for the artist, “Our Time Zone”, focused on artwork and handwriting, intends to “use sensory interaction to express art theories of art therapy, fostering a different interaction between art, culture and exposure”. Keeping in mind that “art reflects the body”, “Our Time Zone” promotes “the awareness of the local community for mental health” in order to “understand one's own body through art therapy”.
Kinki Wong is a native of Macau and has been working as an expressive art therapist, having a master's degree in this area and specialization in Psychology from European Graduate School in Switzerland.
Already Belinda Chim has done western handwriting since he went to Australia to study design. Having over ten years of experience in this art, Belinda stands out in the creation of works with animal themes, using expressive lines within Western handwriting.
The artist has already held exhibitions and face -to -face courses in Hong Kong, Japan and Malaysia, having taught more than four thousand people in the area of ​​handwriting. The show can be visited until May 25th.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:09:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Saint Lazarus | NG I Weng exhibition to see by the end of the month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/sao-lazaro-exposicao-de-ng-i-weng-para-ver-ate-final-do-mes/</link><description>It is evident, by the end of the month, in Gallery 10 Fantasia, in the neighborhood of São Lazaro, the exhibition of artist NG I Weng. It is an initiative of several entities, namely the Macao Youth Art Association, Society of Artists of Macao, Association of Promotion of Creative Industries of the District of São Lázaro, and Gallery 10 Fantasia-Incubator of Creative Industries.
The artist was born in Macao in 1993, having formed in 2015 at the Department of Fine Arts and Cultural Creative Design at Huafan University in Taiwan. According to an official note about the show, the artist has been, since “tender age”, a “curious person about life, having a rich emotional depth”. Thus, his artistic work "explores themes of humanity, emotional links and nature through various ways, revealing a particular proficiency in oil and acrylic painting."
NG I Weng participated in several shows, such as the Huafan Dalun Mountain University Art Exhibition in 2013; The HUASHAN Undergraduate Exhibition in 2015; and also the exhibition of works of art of the members of the Society of Artists of Macau. The artist, who also does curator work, belongs to various artistic entities, such as the Macau Artists Society, Macao Visual Art Education Association or Macao Reading Promotion Association, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:08:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Critical resident due to bacterial infection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/saude-residente-em-estado-critico-devido-a-infeccao-bacteriana/</link><description>A 65 -year -old resident is in critical condition and needs fan to assist in breathing following a vibri vascus infection.
On the afternoon of April 29, the man was accidentally chopped on his little finger his right hand as he handled Cameroon at home. In the next night, it appeared at the "swelling and pain, which then spread to the right hand and right forearm," health services indicated yesterday.
The resident, which has a history of chronic diseases, went to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, where he was "diagnosed with necrotic fascitis of the right upper limb with septic shock."
Health services report that vibri vulinificus is a bacteria that naturally live in hot water and infections can happen when someone has open wounds exposed to seawater with Vibri Vulnifus or when it eats contaminated seafood. People with necrotizing fascitis may have to proceed to the amputation to save their lives, and in about 20 to 30 percent of cases, the infection is fatal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:28:49</pubDate></item><item><title>One | Investigation company profits fall 48.6%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/um-lucros-de-empresa-de-investigacao-caem-486/</link><description>The profits of the company linked to the University of Macao fell 9.88 million patacas. The fall was mainly due to the increase in payments made to the institution of higher education by administrative and place services to perform tests
 
Last year, the company's profits of the company Umacert investigation and engineering rehearsals showed a reduction of 48.6 percent, which translated into 9.88 million patacas. Data from the company controlled by the University of Macau were released yesterday and show a profit of 10.45 million patacas.
Umacert Research and Engineering Tests has as an area of ​​activity research and conducting tests facing the construction materials, road traffic and underground facilities. It is detained at 99 percent by the University of Macao, with the remaining 1 percent in the control of the Education Fund.
The profit of 10.45 million patacas contrasts with the positive result of 20.33 million patacas in the previous year. This difference is explained not only with revenue reduction, which fell slightly from 35.00 million to 34.95 million patacas, but mainly with “other operational expenses”. These had a rise of nearly 10 million patacas from 11.24 million in 2024 to 21.18 million patacas last year.
Increased “other operational expenses” essentially include payments for testing one, as well as the supply of administrative services, with costs growing 9.30 million patacas, to 18.79 million patacas, when in 2023 they were 9.49 million patacas. In terms of staff costs, Umacert's spending within one year more than doubled from 1.07 million patacas by 2023 to 2.86 million patacas.
A handful of companies
Umacert Research and Engineering Tests is one of three companies controlled by the University of Macao.
In addition to this, there is a Tec, which is also dedicated to investigation, but in other areas, and which last year presented a profit of 781,500 patacas, which represented a reduction of almost 80 percent compared to 2023, when profits had been 3.8 million patacas.
The third company controlled by UM is Guangdong Hengqin a Higher Education Development, which will be responsible for developing the new UMA campus in an investment that could reach 4 billion Renminbis. Until yesterday, the company that is headquartered in the countryside had not yet presented the annual results.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:27:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | Revenues with annual growth of 6.2%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/galaxy-receitas-com-crescimento-anual-de-62/</link><description>Galaxy Entertainment had net revenues of Hong Kong's $ 11.2 billion in the first quarter of this year, a 6.2 percent rise in annual, but 1 percent from the last trimester of 2024. Francis Lui stressed the resilience of the Macao market, despite the “geopolitical turmoil and continuing economic slowdown” ”.
 
Galaxy Entertainment yesterday presented the financial results of the first quarter of 2025, a period during which net revenues of $ 11.2 billion of Hong Kong (HKD) were determined, representing an annual increase of 6.2 percent, but a break of 1 percent compared to the previous quarter.
Regarding gross game revenues, the group closed the first three months of 2025 with 10.94 billion HKD, a result that reflects an annual increase of 13.6 percent, but a decrease of 0.8 percent compared to the last quarter of last year.
As is normal, the mass segment generated the highest volume of gross revenues, with 8.23 ​​billion HKD, more 6.5 percent over the same period, while the VIP segmentary raised 1.98 billion HKD in gross revenues, plus 52.3 percent in annual terms.
During the period under analysis, the group registered profits before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of nearly 3.3 billion HKD, a result that represented an annual rise of 16.3 percent and 1.8 percent compared to the last quarter of 2024.
As the “tradition” dictates, the group's egg chicken was Galaxy Macau, generating 9.15 billion HKD in net revenues, plus 10 percent in terms annually, and EBITDA profits of 3.02 billion HKD (+15.4 percent compared to the first trimester of 2024).
At the sleeve
"During the quarter under analysis, we continued to boost all segments of the business, in particular Mass Premium, through our unique products and services, continuous property improvements, various shows and entertainment events, as well as the complete implementation of intelligent tables," said Group President Francis Lui, in the statement that presented the results.
The president of Galaxy Entertainment highlighted the performance of the group's casinos during the Chinese New Year and the resilience capacity of the Macao market, “despite the geopolitical turmoil and the continuing economic slowdown,” with gross revenues to recover to 76 percent of 2019.
Francis Lui also mentioned the presentation of the first lines of government action of the Executive of Sam Hou Fai, particularly in the role of leadership to diversify the economy and guide concessionaires for investments in non-game projects.
However, the president of Galaxy referred the comments of the chief executive regarding the difficulties for the game market to reach the estimated gross revenues for this year. "In the short term, we continue to adjust operations as needed, but we are confident of long -term prospects for Macao. Macau's proactive approach in economic diversification, combined with China's firm support, positions the city well for future sustainable growth," said Francis Lui.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:24:27</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM Resorts International warns bets in Japan and Thailand</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/mgm-resorts-international-alerta-para-apostas-no-japao-e-tailandia/</link><description>A Casinos operator in Macau said yesterday that the opening of casinos in Japan and the potential legalization of the game in Thailand will increase competition with regard to Asian gamblers.
The director for the global development of the US company MGM Resorts International, which operates two casinos in Macao, said the new game concessions accelerated the transition from a model based on major gamblers to “a more diverse tourism and entertainment economy”.
The six Macao game operators signed 10-year concession agreements in December 2022, committing to invest 108.7 billion in tourism and the diversification of the economy.
“The reinforcement of cultural attractions, from entertainment to families (…) helped attract more vast demographics than traditional gamblers,” said Ed Bowers. But the executive warned that "competition is intensifying in Asian markets, particularly with Japan and potentially Thailand."
MGM started on April 24 with the construction of the first integrated venture with a Japan casino in Osaka, scheduled for 2030. The Thailand government presented a proposal to legalize the game.
"This is excellent news for staff of the development of casinos like me," said Bowers, who recalled that Thailand "already benefits from a strong tourist infrastructure." But the discussion of the proposal in Parliament was postponed in early April, "probably due to the increase in political opposition" to the idea, admitted the executive.
Other bets
Bowers spoke during the Global Gaming Expo Asia, the largest event in the game industry held in Macau, which will take place until Friday.
In another session of the same event, experts argued that, given the greater regional competition, the bet on game -related attractions, such as concerts, themed parks and gastronomy can bring more people to the casinos.
“We built all this to support our casino, the casino is our financial engine,” said Wade Howk, director of operations at Inspire Entertainment Resort, an integrated resort in South Korea, with an exclusive casino for foreigners.
The session focused on the diversification of the economy of Macao, where taxes on casinos represented 88.4 percent of the region's current current revenues in the first three months of the year. But the authorities intend that the sector not related to the game represent 60 percent of Macao Gross Domestic Product by 2028.
As an example, Wade Howk stressed that Inspire Entertainment built a 15,000 -seat entertainment space, the only multipurpose cultural arena in South Korea to increase the number of visitors.
"We are seeing huge results with this now, and then we built a covered water park ... just to make sure we could boost traffic to support the entire property, ... and that it could be used to support the casino," Howk explained. Jeffrey Kiang, an investment group analyst CSSA, stressed that game -related components should “create synergies and complement the business” of casinos.
Kiang has observed an increase in the number of concerts held in Macao in the last two years and said that the casino operators carefully select events or artists who attract gamblers.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:31:22</pubDate></item><item><title>AMCM | Mobile transactions go up in the 1st quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/amcm-sobem-transaccoes-moveis-no-1-o-trimestre/</link><description>Data from the Macao Monetary and Currency Authority (AMCM) show that in the first three months of the year increased the number of mobile payment transactions in Macau as well as its value. Thus, the number of transactions of this type was 90.4 million, an increase of 11.6 percent compared to the first trimester of 2024.
In addition, the value of these mobile payments was 7.9 billion patacas, plus 8.7 percent over the same period last year. Until late March this year, a total of 108,749 devices and units, including “QR code” supports, accepted mobile payments. AMCM data also show that in the use of credit cards there was also an increase in the number of transactions, totaling 11.8 million, an increase of 9.7 percent compared to the first quarter of 2024.
In addition, the number of transactions made with debit cards was 1.2 million, with a total value of transactions of 464.9 million patacas. It should be noted that these values ​​for the use of debit cards do not include cash surveys in atm boxes.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:05:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Land | Government makes evictions at Av. De Sidónio Pais</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/terrenos-governo-faz-despejos-na-av-de-sidonio-pais/</link><description>The government yesterday carried out an action of eviction and cleaning of a land located on Avenida de Sidónio Pais. The space, with an area of ​​about 121 square meters, thus moved to the government's power, since it was being occupied illegally.
According to a note from the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU), “the recovered terrain was paved and, on site, unauthorized works were noticeable, namely a clandestine construction composed of a metallic gate, brick walls and concrete cover, as well as stairs, flower beds and sealing wall”.
DSCCU explains that it had already carried out all the usual procedures for the eviction of the land, "ordering the illegal occupant to vacate the same and reveal it to the government of MSAR within the stipulated time." However, and as this request was never fulfilled, the authorities proceeded to eviction on Wednesday.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:04:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Services warn of “more active” chickenpox viruses</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/saude-servicos-alertam-para-virus-da-varicela-mais-activo/</link><description>The government yesterday launched an alert to the increase of costumes of chickenpox in Macao. Since the beginning of the year, authorities have reported 195 cases of infection, almost double the same period of 2024. About three quarters of infections are contracted by children
 
Macao's varicella virus is becoming more active, health services have indicated yesterday, appealing to parents, educational institutions, and day care centers to be aware of symptoms and adopt a preventive stance.
According to data on communicable declaration diseases, authorities found that last week there was a “trend to increase the number of varicella cases, with the weekly average of 12 cases from April 6 to rise to 23 last week”.
The body led by Alvis Lo points out that "this number is higher than that of last year's same -year period (10 cases)."
Authorities also account for a case of collective chickenpox infection that was recently detected at Pui Ching Secondary School, affecting a total of 21 students.
From May 1, students "had symptoms of rash and small bubbles on the head, face, limbs, back and chest, having undergone medical treatment." Authorities add that there were no serious complications and that "most patients were vaccinated with a dose of chickenpox."
From the beginning
Between January 1 and May 6 this year, 195 cases of chickenpox were recorded in Macao, a number that almost doubled infections during last year's same year, when 105 cases were registered.
About three quarters of cases concern children, most ages between 8 and 17 years old, representing 65.1 percent of the total, while people aged 7 or under or less represent only 6.1 percent of the total. Health services highlight that since the beginning of the year there has been no record of serious or deadly cases.
Authorities add that part of the inoculated population against the chickenpox is still likely to be affected by what health professionals call disruptive infection. However, "symptoms are usually slight and atypical, with fewer bubbles and the duration of the disease is relatively short." According to the government, the cases of chickenpox at Pui Ching secondary school are disruptive infections.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:02:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails about sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise the reading of a beautiful interview book with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my rank of hatter at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over the referected zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>India threatens “very strong response” against any new Pakistan attack</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/india-ameaca-resposta-muito-forte-contra-qualquer-novo-ataque-do-paquistao/</link><description>Indian Foreign Minister warned yesterday that a new attack on Pakistan will provoke a “very strong response” from India, a day after the most violent military confrontation of the last two decades between the two countries.
"It is not our intention to provoke a new climb" of the conflict, said Subrahmanyam Jaishankar, at the opening of a meeting with the Iranian counterpart, Abbas Araghchi. "But if we are attacked, there is no doubt that we will respond very firmly," he said.
The threat is done a day after Pakistan has guaranteed that it will take revenge on the dead caused by Indian air strikes that, according to Nova Delhi, were an response to an attack on Caxemira. "We are committed to avenge every drop of blood from these martyrs," said Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif, in a nation speech on Wednesday night.
Growing
Over the past two weeks, the tension between India and Pakistan has grown, following an attack on April 22 in Pahalgam, a tourist town in the Indian part of the disputed region of Caxemira, in which 26 people died.
India accused Pakistan of supporting the extremist group that liable for the attack, an accusation that Islamabade vehemently denied.
After several diplomatic measures and a series of incidents along the border that separates the two countries in Caxemira, Nova Deli launched attacks on three Pakistan areas, which, according to the Indian government, constituted “terrorist places” in Punjab province.
A few hours later, the Pakistani government announced that it has slaughtered several Indian military aircraft and, on Wednesday morning, a sequence of Islamabade bombing and Nova Delhi caused at least 38 dead in the biggest confrontation in the last 20 years.
Yesterday, India announced that 13 civilians died and 59 were injured in Caxemira in retaliation for the Pakistani attack released on Wednesday over its territory and Pakistan said it slaughtered an Indian drone in Lahore.
Iran offered to mediate the conflict between the two nuclear powers, and the minister responsible for the diplomacy of Tehran reunited with those responsible of the Pakistani government on Monday. Upon arrival in India, Abbas Araghchi admitted that he expects "the parties to have moderation to avoid climbing tensions in the region." Iran maintains good relations with India and Pakistan, with which it borders.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Shanghai | Legoland will open in July largest theme park in the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/xangai-legoland-vai-abrir-em-julho-maior-parque-tematico-do-mundo/</link><description>The Danish brand Lego, which specializes in building blocks, will open on July 5 its largest theme park in the world in Shanghai, east of China, the local press advanced yesterday.
The complex, about 52 kilometers southwest of the city center, will feature more than 75 attractions and shows distributed by eight distinct zones, including thousands of figures built with about 85 million lego pieces.
Visitors will also be able to watch Lego movies in a 4D movie theater as well as lodge in a 250-room themed hotel, decorated according to five different environments inspired by this universe of recognized toy on the global scale.
Currently, the park is in the final phase of construction: the main entrance is completed and the main 24 attractions are practically ready. About a thousand employees will integrate the team since the opening.
The highlight of the park will be the “Miniland” zone, a recreation, built fully with Lego blocks - with a total weight of 45 tons - some of Shanghai's most emblematic areas, as well as other China's cultural and tourist icons.
Among the expected shows, stands out the world's first show dedicated to Lego's “Monkie Kid” series, inspired by King Macaco, from the classic Chinese work Journey to the West. Legoland Shanghai has already started selling season passes and tickets for exclusive visits, including stays at the themed hotel.
"We know this market well and we are enthusiastic about its potential. This complex will be a reference and meeting point for all Lego fans in China," said Fiona Eastwood, executive director of Merlin Entertainments, the British group responsible for managing Legoland parks. According to the company, more than 55 million people live two hours - or less - by car the location of the new park.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ukraine | China controls “strictly” export of double use goods</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/ucrania-china-controla-rigorosamente-exportacao-de-bens-de-dupla-utilizacao/</link><description>China said yesterday that it “strictly controls” the export of double -use goods, in view of suspicions that Russia is using technological civil use devices for military purposes in Ukraine.
"China applies strict controls on the export of double-use goods," said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian when asked reports that exported video games to Russia are being used to operate drones.
Lin Jian also denounced that any "normal technological cooperation" of China "becomes a problem" when there are attempts to "defame the country with unfounded accusations and political manipulation of bad faith." The spokesman has not clarified whether China is considering additional restrictions on technology exports, referring to the competent authorities.
The statements arose after Ukraine expressed concern about the involvement of Chinese companies and citizens in Russian military production, a formal complaint he filed to the Chinese ambassador in Kiev in April, claiming to have evidence.
This week, the European Commission said China "remains a key facilitator" of the Russian war effort and that without this "Moscow support could not continue war with the same strength." Beijing argued that his position on conflict has been “consistent and clear” and is committed to “promoting ceasefire, disagreement and negotiations”, and guaranteed to have never provided lethal weapons “to neither party” involved in the war.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:37:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Moscow | XI greet deepening of trust between China and Russia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/moscovo-xi-sauda-aprofundamento-da-confianca-entre-china-e-russia/</link><description>XI is in Moscow to participate in the anniversary celebrations of the day of victory over Germany Nazi in World War II
 
Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday greeted the deepening of confidence between China and Russia at the beginning of the Kremlin meeting with Russian homologist Vladimir Putin in Moscow.
"Mutual political trust between China and Russia is deepening and pragmatic cooperation ties are becoming stronger," said Chinese President, who is in Moscow for celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the Nazi Germany in World War II.
XI stressed that "in the face of the international tendency of unilateralism and hegemonic intimidation behavior, China will work with Russia to assume the special responsibilities of the main world powers." “I am very happy with this new meeting,” said Vladimir Putin at the beginning of the meeting with Xi, broadcast live on Russian television.
The Russian leader expressed gratitude that Xi decided to attend, in Moscow, to the celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the victory over Germany Nazi, as had happened on the 70th birthday.
The Russian head of state recalled that the former Soviet Union (USSR) lost about 27 million people in the war, while in China the number of dead was 37 million, including soldiers and civilians.
Beneficial ties
Putin said a Chinese guard of honor will march in Red Square on Friday, integrated in the Military Parade, and promised to attend China's victory celebrations about Japan on September 3.
For Putin, the ties between Russia and China are “mutually beneficial” and do not oppose any third country.
The Russian head of state also said that the two countries intend to defend together the "historical truth" about World War II, with Putin to accuse the West of trying to distort.
"Along with our Chinese friends, we firmly defend the historical truth, protect the memory of the events of war years and fight against the modern manifestations of neo -Nazism and militarism," Putin said.
According to the Russian presidency, the leaders will hold meetings in small and large formats and adopt two joint statements.
Novos acordos
Russian President Vladimir Putin announced yesterday the signing of a new investment promotion and protection agreement, under negotiations with Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping. At the opening of a Kremlin meeting, Putin estimated the amount of investment projects treated by the intergovernmental commission estimated by more than $ 200 billion.
It also expressed the conviction that this agreement will contribute positively to the creation of a “more favorable” atmosphere and constitute “an important impetus” to the development of economic cooperation, the Russian leader said. Putin stressed that the current trade, which rose to almost $ 245 billion last year, "is far away" from the top limit to both countries.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:36:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Nintendo with a new record of scholarship capitalization</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/japao-nintendo-com-novo-recorde-de-capitalizacao-bolsista/</link><description>Nintendo, a Japanese video game manufacturer and distributor, recorded a new scholarship capitalization record of approximately 15.36 billion yen (94,831 million euros), exceeding Fast Retailing for the first time.
In early May, only Toyota Automobile company, Sony Multinational, Banco Mitsubishi UFJ and Hitachi Electronics company had a higher scholarship capitalization than Nintendo, according to Japan Exchange Japanese Scholarship operator data.
The Kyoto -based company has sold over 150 million Switch console units worldwide and about 1.36 billion copies of games to the platform.
Nintendo's shares rose 1.77 percent on Friday's negotiations for a record price 12,360 yen (76.09 euros), in anticipation of the release on June 5 of the console successor, Switch 2, which has already sold out in Japan.
The Japanese scholarship market was closed on Monday and Tuesday holidays, and had a volatile opening on Wednesday with investors to assimilate the new tariff threats of US President Donald Trump to film and pharmaceutical industries.
After the first 20 minutes of negotiation, Nintendo continued to record record levels, with a rise of almost 0.3 percent the company closed the negotiation with a slight downward of 0.08 percent, after the volatility that characterized the negotiations.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:27:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese specialist considers urgent domain of Portuguese for national cohesion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/especialista-timorense-considera-urgente-dominio-do-portugues-para-coesao-nacional/</link><description>Timorese linguist Benjamin Real Corte considered yesterday that the Portuguese language is a factor of cohesion in Timor-Leste and is a “national urgency” that all citizens will dominate.
Benjamin Real Corte spoke at the seminar on “Linguistic Policies and Development of the Portuguese Language in Timor-Leste: Challenges and Perspectives”, organized by the National University of Timor-Leste, under his 25th anniversary and the celebrations of World Portuguese Language Day, which was signaled on May 5.
In his speech, the teacher recalled that before the arrival of the Portuguese, the Timorese were scattered by tribal groups, who spoke their own language, and that the communities were isolated from each other, also because of the mountainous relief of the region.
"The arrival of the Portuguese comes to bring a novelty that is the introduction of an element that will precisely dilute our previous situation of isolation of communities. Since the Portuguese language entered Timor, it has served this purpose of uniting the Timorese communicatively," said Benjamin Corte Real.
And, according to the linguist, although it was not introduced in the same way as Indonesian language, whose learning was a matter of survival, the Timorenses, especially the leaders, realized that to unify the country and consolidate national independence to “Portuguese language was essential”.
National urgency
Another reason pointed out by Benjamin Real Cut for the importance of Portuguese for “national cohesion” is that maternal or local languages ​​do not “have enough resourcefulness to absorb administrative practice, for legislative production for territory planning”.
Today, he stressed, although national cohesion has not been achieved in terms of widespread mastery of the Portuguese language, it has already begun to realize that the state must walk in this direction and make a "more proposed" effort so that Portuguese is dominated by all.
“This is a national urgency. Therefore, we are here to appeal to all the instances of education throughout the territory that assume their responsibility and comply with the laws and enforce the laws around the implementation of Portuguese language teaching and teaching through Portuguese,” said Benjamim Corte Real.
"We cannot speak of a harmonized, unified society, without investing in the language that is common to all of us. We must do it by obligation, national vocation, and, above all, also by constitutional mandate," he insisted.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:25:27</pubDate></item><item><title>India / Pakistan | International Community calls for containment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/india-paquistao-comunidade-internacional-pede-contencao/</link><description>Tuesday night's India attack against three Pakistan zones dangerously climbed the conflict between the two nuclear powers
 
The international community yesterday asked India and Pakistan to have military containment after the confrontation between the two nuclear powers, which has already caused dozens of civilians in both countries.
China, Russia, France, and Germany asked for restraint and were concerned about climbing tensions, highlighting the need to avoid confrontation situations and protect civilians. Turkey also expressed concern and warned of the “risk of total war” between India and Pakistan.
"The attack of India last night represents the risk of total war. We condemned this provocative attitude and attacks on civilians and civil infrastructure," the Ministry of Turkish Foreign Affairs said. Similarly, Iran expressed “deep concern” with the confrontation between India and Pakistan, a country with whom it borders.
Earlier, the United States regretted the situation, with the president, Donald Trump, considered that the restart of clashes "was a pity" and advanced to expect "to stop very quickly." US diplomacy leader Marc Rubio also exhorted the leaders of both states to open a dialogue channel to avoid a greater escalation of the conflict.
“The world cannot afford to luxury a military confrontation” between India and Pakistan, the UN Secretary General, António Guterres, said, referring to the attacks at the past few hours, the most serious of the last two decades between these states.
In a more assertive reaction, the United Kingdom also asked for calm countries, but assumed it was ready to intervene if necessary. India and Pakistan have "interest in regional stability," said British Commerce Secretary Jonathan Reynolds, adding that the British government will do "everything it can in terms of dialogue to reduce tension."
Killed and injured
The two armies exchanged artillery shots along the border disputed in Caxemira after Indian attacks on Pakistani soil in retaliation by an attack on 22 April in India -controlled Caxemira, which killed 26 people.
The tension between India and Pakistan rekindled on April 22, when gunmen attacked the tourist region of Pahalgam, in Caxemira Indiana, killing 26 civilians. The attack was attributed to the Lashkar-e-Taiba organization and the relations have deteriorated even more among these neighboring countries, rivals since they became independent of the United Kingdom in 1947.
The two governments ordered the departure of their territories of citizens of the neighboring state and, over the days, incidents were registered at the borders, with shots fired in the so-called Caxemira control line. On Tuesday night, Nova Deli launched attacks against three areas of Pakistan, which, according to the Indian government, constituted “terrorist places” in Punjab province.
A few hours later, the Pakistani government announced that it has slaughtered several Indian military aircraft, and yesterday morning, a sequence of bombing carried out by Islamabade and Nova Deli caused at least 38 dead in the biggest confrontation in the last 20 years.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:22:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Victory Day | Beijing justifies participation in the Moscow Parade as an act of respect for history</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/dia-da-vitoria-pequim-justifica-participacao-na-parada-de-moscovo-como-acto-de-respeito-pela-historia/</link><description>Beijing defended yesterday the presence of Chinese troops at the Military Parade of May 9 in Moscow as a demonstration of “respect for history” and not as a gesture of Russia support in the war in Ukraine.
"China's participation in the 80th anniversary of the Soviet victory in the Great Patriotic War reflects respect for history and the firm determination to defend the achievements of World War II," Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian said at a press conference.
The spokesman recalled that the victory in war was "the result of the joint struggle of all countries and peoples lovers of peace and justice" and both the Chinese people and the people of the former Soviet Union "have made huge national sacrifices and indelible historical contributions."
The comments came a day after Ukraine criticized the presence of foreign troops in the Parade of the Red Square as a “manifestation of support for the aggressor state”. Beijing avoided responding directly to Kiev's rebuke, but insisted that the position on the war "has been clear and consistent."
"Avoiding a new climb of tensions is now the urgent priority. All parties involved must reach consensus and create conditions to achieve this goal," he added. Regarding bilateral cooperation between China and Russia, the spokesman reiterated that "it has always been based on the principles of mutual respect, shared benefit and common success."
The parade in Moscow will also have military units from 12 more countries. Chinese President Xi Jinping will be present on the first visit to Russia since March 2023. A bilateral meeting with Russian President Vladimir Putin is also planned on May 8.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:21:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Chinese scholarships rise with Beijing stimulus measures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/08/economia-bolsas-chinesas-sobem-com-medidas-de-estimulo-de-pequim/</link><description>China's top scholarships yesterday opened with gains, following the announcement of a new package of measures by Beijing to boost economic recovery, pressured by the tariffs imposed by the United States.
During yesterday's morning, the Shanghai index advanced 0.59 percent and that of Shenzhen rose 0.22 percent. In Hong Kong, the Hang Seng reference index rose 0.79 percent. Also Beijing Bolsa, inaugurated in 2021 and with less expression because it was centered on small and medium enterprises, operated on positive land, with an appreciation of 0.48 percent.
Half an hour before the opening of the markets, the governor of the Chinese Central Bank, Pan Gongsheng, announced new interest rates, mandatory reserve rate and seven -day repurchase operations rates, one of the main central bank liquidity injection tools.
Banco Popular da China also announced reductions in mortgage interest rates, credit stimulation measures to buy services and care for the elderly, temporary support for financing for car acquisition and increased credit to technological innovation.</description><pubDate>2025-05-08 00:18:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and I see soon that AI was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return of digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, directed to teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>João Romão, academic: “Macau is in a highly privileged position”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/02/joao-romao-academico-macau-esta-numa-posicao-altamente-privilegiada/</link><description>Professor at Yasuda Women’s University in Japan, João Romão prepares to launch in June a book entitled “Economic Geography of Tourism”. Speaking to HM, the academic enhances the interconnection between tourism, economy and geography, and lists its possibilities, limitations and effects, including Macao
 
 
In this book it speaks of the concept of “spatial economy”, in connection with tourism and geography. How is this connection?
Economic geography combines the geographical context with economic processes, being studied the spatial distribution of economic activities. The economy of tourism is particularly sensitive to these geographical constraints, as they are the characteristics of each place that enhances the development of certain products or services. These characteristics widely exceed the physical aspects of the territory and also include culture, history, ways of life or even institutions and legal frameworks. The case of casino, something particularly important in Macao, is a good example of the importance of legal aspects to develop certain types of tourism. Economic geography has a wider scope than the spatial economy, more focused on strictly economic aspects. Being evident in tourism this relationship between economics and geography, this book establishes a double approach that systematizes the interdependence of these three aspects it refers. First explores how the concepts and theories of economic geography can apply to tourism. In the second half it makes the opposite route, discussing how the analysis of relevant problems of contemporary tourism justifies the use of economic geography. Examples are the degradation of local resources, environmental impacts, contribution to climate change, acceleration of gentrification processes or disturbance of community modes of life.
Can having an excessively -dependent economy of tourism constitute a problem or salvation?
The two things, and are both cases that economic geography can help to understand. The industrialization of economies is linked to the agglomeration processes of activities that reinforce each other when they reach a certain scale. This allows the massification of production and consumption, with reasonable costs. Contemporary industries, more associated with the integration of digital technologies and creative processes, are less clustered in specialized industrial development zones, but tend to focus on large cities and metropolitan areas. It also follows that rural areas, islands, or sites that have not followed industrialization processes, have more difficulty mobilizing investments, technologies or qualified people to innovate and develop new industries. In such cases, tourism often appears as the possible solution as it can be developed with incorporation of technology and relatively low knowledge. On the other hand, tourism consumption, not being essential to human life, is very sensitive to income fluctuations.
Can you give examples?
This was visible, for example, with the 2007/2009 international crisis. Tourism is also very vulnerable to safety problems or international epidemics, such as COVID-19 has demonstrated to the extreme. Economies too specialized in tourism are very vulnerable to external shocks and less resilient to crises. It is also visible that, being the tourist development often supported by intensive and weak labor services, the specialization in tourism can cause, in the long run, embarrassment in terms of population qualifications, the ability to innovate and integrate technology or to add value to the regional economy.
The book also speaks of “intelligent tourism” and “co-creation of experiences”, using the megados and IA. Is tourism definitely becoming more digital?
Social networks are fundamental instruments for new generations. However, they began to generalize the tools for planning or promotion of travel supported by artificial intelligence. The so-called “intelligent tourism” more generally designates the use of digital technologies to intensify information flows, consolidate the formation of networks and promote more informed and shared decision making, eventually contributing to the so-called “co-creation of experiences”. Tourism digitization has its origins in service distribution systems originally developed by airlines since the 1960s, but it would be the internet to accelerate and globalize digitization.
And social networks.
The emergence of social networks promoted the creation of a more interactive universe, potentially in real time and involving wide numbers of users and various types of supports. The generalization of the use of mobile phones permanently connected to the Internet, even on foreign travel, has further increased this potential for intensive and interactive use of data and information. This "co-creation", however, hides obvious imbalances of power.
Such as?
With regard to tourists, or consumer in general, it is usually the role of providing information, for example through social networks. This information is obtained, accumulated and marketed, sometimes without consent or even without knowledge, to eventually translate into the creation, adaptation or promotion of products and services. This process is particularly important in the case of tourism, because there is usually a long period between the decision to travel and the trip itself. This period of travel exploration and planning is used by tourist marketing companies to try to influence choices. This type of interaction also introduces a difference in the “spatiality” of the provision of tourist services, which are usually produced and consumed at the same time and in the same place, in a direct relationship between producer and consumer. The digitization of tourism anticipates most of these interactions and information flows and transfers them to large technological companies or marketing and distribution.
In a world where more and more travel, the routes are shorter and access to information is immense, how can countries and regions be competitive in the tourist offer?
Contemporary tourism lives in a highly competitive international environment. But just as there is a wide variety of destinations and offerings, there is also a wide range of preferences and consumption, what is called “hyper-personalization”, the result of such abundance of information and opportunity for interaction. The challenge that is placed on destinations is to identify the resources, products and services that can be adjusted to a particular group of consumers, to communicate effectively. This competitiveness greatly goes beyond the strict scope of tourist services because it also requires mobility and transportation services, varied infrastructure, safety, medical support, or easy communication. Anywhere you want to develop your tourist industry have to intervene about all these factors.
The book also addresses how “social processes” shape the development of tourism. In the case of China, for example, do you believe we are watching a change, which will have consequences for Macau?
It seems to me that Macau is in a highly privileged position to develop other forms of tourism. China is the largest issuing market in the world, the widespread rise of income in recent decades allows many million people to explore the opportunity to travel. Macao is a very close and distinct destination, with its historical and cultural particularities. For the Chinese population it was not easy to visit Macau and there is certainly a great interest.
How does the Great Bay project come in this?
The strategy that is being followed by integrating the Great Bay allows you to develop a cosmopolitan and diverse offer that can certainly attract Chinese tourists and other parts of the world. Moreover, these three areas have excellent hotel and tourism schools, which guarantee qualified personnel for tourism management and planning. The element of differentiation that Portuguese culture introduces in this context can certainly contribute to the success of the transition from a casinos focused on other forms that value culture and heritage more.
Is it possible to have sustainable tourism?
The problems and difficulties of tourism sustainability are more visible than in other sectors. This “spatiality” of tourism (where the consumer is obliged to move to the place of consumption) implies that the consequences of this consumption become more evident. These effects are less obvious when it comes to the unsustainability of industrial units or intensive forms of agriculture in relatively isolated areas. As mass reduction and investment reduction strategies also apply to tourism, the consequences of the environment or the quality of life of residents in destinations can be devastating. Sustainability implies a long -term perspective based on the idea that today's decisions do not imply future negative consequences. Sustainable practices depend on the control of the impacts that accumulate over time by individual and independent economic agents.
How can this control be done?
When a hotel or airline defines what ability to install on their services they may eventually estimate the impact that consumers will have on the local environment or economy. They will have more difficulties in anticipating that impacts will be generated in the next 10, 15 or 20 years to investment. And surely it will be impossible to measure how this impact accumulates the impacts caused by other service providers, now or in the future. In other words, although the idea of ​​sustainability is widespread accepted, economic agents do not have mechanisms or instruments in practice. Regulating the use of resources and territories by public entities with a more comprehensive and future perspective can contribute to the sustainability more effectively than the regulation associated with market dynamics, which in many cases has been revealed highly predatory. The Chinese economy is one of these examples and may eventually benefit from it.
And in the concrete case of Macau?
Macao has historically known problems: ultra-urbanized and polluted areas, with large energy consumption and waste production; Great concentration of tourists in a relatively small area of ​​great historical and cultural interest; Great dependence on the game, with the resulting imbalances in the appropriation of tourism benefits. The ongoing transition to new forms of tourism should better solve these problems and state regulation will certainly have better results than based on market dynamics.</description><pubDate>2025-04-02 23:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>José Paulo Esperança, Associate Rector of the City of Macau University: “Languages ​​cannot be controlled”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/jose-paulo-esperanca-reitor-associado-da-universidade-cidade-de-macau-as-linguas-nao-podem-ser-controladas/</link><description>Co-author of the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with Luís Reto and Fernando Luís Machado, José Paulo Esperança reveals to HM that the work edited in 2016 and 2018 is being updated, especially due to the growing global value of the language. The Associate Rector and Professor of the City of Macao University suggests partnerships with Macau under the Editorial Project
 
Launched the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, in co-authorship, about the global value of the language. Plan a new edition or update?
Undoubtedly. We are working in this regard, there was a recent conference in Macao and Professor Luís Reto, former Rector of ISCTE, presented some more current elements that were developed. He has worked on a very important issue, which is the role of Portuguese as a frank language, which was for a few centuries in Asia. The exchange between Dutch and the kingdom of Zion was made in Portuguese, because it was the common language used at that time, before English became the contemporary frank language. Therefore, there is a whole interesting story of Portuguese and the role it had in the first pinyins that existed, with the Chinese and the use of the [Roman] alphabet in Vietname. There are a number of elements that are not, therefore, very publicized, and the work of Atlas is the same, to disclose some economic dimensions of the language.
What are these dimensions?
One is the exchange of foreign trade and investment, which is very facilitated by the language. We also talk about migrations, tourism, students' exchange that is greatly influenced by linguistic proximity. Therefore, today we have a set of elements that are very interesting, and we hope to develop some more important partnerships with Macau.
As?
More at work, Professor Luís Reto is doing, which maintains an investigation team about the value of Portuguese. He has collaborated with the Portuguese Language Museum of São Paulo, for example. It is a museum space that was renewed after the fire that destroyed it. In addition, there is a project with Cascais City Council to develop such a structure, and we hope to do some works with Macau, in order to create three poles for the projection of the Portuguese language. As for Atlas' materials, we would like to have a continued update model, as this data is out of date very quickly. The work was edited in many languages, including Mandarin. This is the moment when we would like to give the book a more historical and deep dimension, with more knowledge about the teaching of Portuguese in the world.
What balance does this teaching do today?
Portuguese is developing a great deal of mother tongue and is effectively one of the most expanding languages ​​due to demographic growth in Africa, with countries such as Angola and Mozambique, which around 2050 will have populations of over 100 million inhabitants, each. The Portuguese thus consolidates itself as a language of the southern hemisphere, but much more from Africa, supplanting Brazil itself as the place of largest number of speakers of the language. All of this generates enormous potential, and this also occurs due to the great exchange of universities and internationalization of teaching. Today there is the possibility of Portuguese being a language of science, there is more publications in this language. This is a great challenge because English is the contemporary language of scientists. We want to contribute to all these dimensions, and Macau can also play an important role there. Macao is indeed a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and can play a significant role.
Is Macao an ideal place to train Portuguese teachers who do not have Portuguese as a mother tongue? Do you fear that the territory loses relevance in this matter before the offer of courses in the interior of China?
I see this question more as complementarity than competition. We have identified about 60 higher education institutions in China that have Portuguese courses, but I think Macau has very interesting conditions to start teaching from primary to secondary education so that children have been able to have learning from an early age. It does not mean that there are no young Chinese who began to learn their tongue in adolescence that they speak fantastically, which surprises me, but it is easier to start earlier and earlier. This will be easier in Macau. What is important is to create conditions for greater economic collaboration to many levels, such as joint research. In this respect, Macau has a very interesting opportunity. At the City of Macau University we are very interested in increasingly collaborating with researchers who visit us and work with our teams.
Can you give me examples?
Brazil is today one of China's great business partners. There is a lot of exchange in both directions, but one of the themes that is little studied, and in which I work hard, is the internationalization of Chinese companies. To what extent do these companies follow a model of internationalization similar to that of other countries that started this process earlier? I speak of the United States of America, the European countries, but also of Japan and others. China has, in fact, different models of presence in countries that are not yet well known, and this is important to see, so that we know how to facilitate this process of exchange in a world that lives periods of some setback. It is very sad. I always remember a great economist of Portuguese origin, David Ricardo, who clearly explained how world trade is beneficial to everyone and how countries can take advantage of this situation. Therefore, applying tariffs, making such commercial barriers harms countries that are major exporters, such as China or Germany, and countries that today have a cultural export capacity, for example, and are not just importers.
In relation to the new Orthographic Agreement. It continues without a standardization in Macau. Does it worry it?
Languages ​​are dynamic and cannot be controlled. We think today in English, and we realize that there are almost incomprehensible ways to each other, such as the English one in Nigeria or Australia. Americans have difficulty realizing the Australians. In the nineteenth century, Portuguese from Portugal and Brazil were closer, then some disagreement emerged. There was an effort in Brazil to propose an orthographic agreement, and the Portuguese joined, resulting in a series of negotiations. There have always been resistances. I remember that Fernando Pessoa suggested the famous phrase “My homeland is the Portuguese language”. It was curiously a manifestation of some conservatism, because he thought Pharmacy had to continue writing with pH [Pharmacia]. In fact it did not make much sense. Portugal ended up seeking to impose a certain standardization based on the most genetic changes in the spelling agreement. It is not a process that has been running a hundred percent well, and has been universally adopted. African countries have become more defenders of Portuguese from Portugal. There is sometimes some confusion, but I understand that intercomprehension still remains, achieving a homogeneous language, more perhaps than English.
 
Between words and numbers
José Paulo Esperança is a doctorate in Economics from the European University Institute and was president of the ISCTE Department of Finance and Accounting - University Institute of Lisbon. The “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with editions in 2016 and 2018, contains “a large set of indicators that reinforce the idea of ​​the growth of teaching, speakers and the written use of Portuguese in the world”, having been the target of a series of recent initiatives in Macao.
One of them took place on March 17, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, with a session of the “Roda de Ideas” cycle, entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, which was attended by the former ISCTE Rector, Luís Reto, and José Paulo Hope himself. In addition to the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, José Paulo Esperança is the author of other works in the financial area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:08:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
What are you speaking, is economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). Estão fora da escola, da educação e da Academia. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
To finish, did you like you talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the Guide Circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of copies produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos also underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitano Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major goal will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name in Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSAR VICTORY AND TOP-10 to Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite the safety car entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet beginning, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Council of Motorsport approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and a MSAR test enthusiast, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The growth and development potential in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into details, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula Cup last year, says that “this big step will benefit undoubtedly local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macau-China General Automobile Association, he stated: “We are happy to see the FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from the international events of Karting to F4 and FR monoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, the third of the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Touring cars finding begins with greater presence Macaense</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/16/gp-apuramento-dos-carros-de-turismo-comeca-com-maior-presenca-macaense/</link><description>The Macao-Macao Road Sport Challenge Touring Car Championship will start this weekend at the Guangdong International Circuit in the city of Zhaoqing, 200 kilometers northwest of the ride. For this race, which will serve as qualification for the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, will be on the starting grid a dozen Macau pilots, including five Portuguese names
 
Among the sixty subscribers, all equipped with two types of vehicles - Toyota GR86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) - are well -known guys from Macau's motor racing. With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit in November last year. Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the focus on pre-season has been in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
Also back is Célio Alves Dias, after a difficult year in 2024, far short of his expectations. For this, the pilot Macaense bet on changing the chassis of his Toyota Gr86. This year, its objective is to account for the twenty -fifth participation in the largest sports event of an annual character of MSAR, so all the details are important.
Back is also Jerónimo Badaraco (Toyota Gr86), a pilot who, in the Macao Grand Prix last year, reached second place at Macao Road Sport Challenge. After having been modest in the finding events, “Noni” was very strong in the city streets, where he was the best Macaense pilot, in a race won by law Kit Meng.
In debut this year will be Maximian Mannão. Bringing with him a nickname with a huge tradition in Macao's motorsport, the young Maximiano, who competed for several years in the local Karting events and, in 2022, participated in a Formula 4 Chinese Championship race, will make his debut at Macau Road Sport Challenge with a Toyota GR86.
The Macanese presence will be reinforced by Dionísio Albino Pereira, a pilot regularly seen in the coloane Karting events, which will conduct a Toyota GR86 from LW World Racing Team. In 2013, he competed in the Macao - Macau Touring Car Series Tourism Championship, then driving a Honda Integra DC5 from the Pas Macau Racing Team team.
The representation of the territory in these findings will also feature Chi Wang, Carson Tang, IP Tok Meng, Chan Chi Ha, Lo Kai Tin and Lou Check In.
It will be to hurt
In 2024, the Macao-China General Automotive Association (AAMC) was able to place all the drivers of the Macau Tourism Championship in the end of the Grand Prix. This year, it seems that the scenario of organizing two races for local pilots will be impossible. As such, these qualifying races will have a much higher impact, and only half of those now registered will have entry ticket for the largest annual sports event of MSAR.
Another novelty for this year is that all cars will be equipped with tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, as had already happened in the Grand Prix. However, this year there will be a new compound, the same for everyone, which may shuffle the favorite accounts. Centralins will continue to be drawn, as in the past.
Since the number of participants is high, AAMC will divide the pilots into groups A and B, not two but four races in total. Each race will have 15 laps, two of which will be played on Saturday and two on Sunday.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>