<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>McDonald's | Planned opening in China from another thousand restaurants this year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/mcdonalds-planeada-abertura-na-china-de-mais-mil-restaurantes-este-ano/</link><description>The world's largest rapid food chain, McDonald's, plans to open about 1,000 new restaurants in China in 2025, almost half of the 2,200 that will open worldwide.
At a conference with analysts after the last quarter results, US Frederick Borden's financial director, revealed these numbers, which in the case of China followed the number of openings announced in the last two exercises.
"We are watching the encouraging signs of stabilization in China," said the official about the company's performance in the Asian country for 2024, when global profits fell 3 percent over the previous year.
By 2024, McDonald's executive president Chris Kempczinski had already highlighted the “strong growth” in China, despite the pressure on consumer confidence in the face of economic recovery problems, and said: “We will do what it takes to maintain the maintaining our competitiveness in this market ”.
The hamburgers chain has about six thousand points of sale in China and aims to exceed ten thousand by 2028. Currently, there are over 40,000 McDonald's restaurants worldwide.
At the end of 2023, McDonald's announced an agreement to buy 28 percent participation that Carlyle investment company had in its business in China for an estimated $ 1.8 billion, increasing its participation of 20 percent to 48 percent, with the Chinese investment bank Citic to control the remaining 52 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:06:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Circulation | Deputy alerts to HK vehicle abuse</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/circulacao-deputado-alerta-para-abusos-de-veiculos-de-hk/</link><description>Hong Kong Deputy Adriano Ho warned that the Hong Kong vehicle wate system in Macau is being abused. The complaint was filed through a Facebook post, where the deputy speaks of forgery of information.
“I recently received many complaints that the system is being abused. After people have detected the gaps that exist in the system began to emerge agencies that charge money to falsify the information, to simulate that customers have calls with Macau, ”wrote the deputy. According to Hong Kong regulations, the quotas are attributed to those who show you have connections with the masters.
“Some people have created ghost companies to which quotas were attributed, and then sold these companies to profit from Quota. This causes people with business in Hong Kong and Macau, or work in Macau, have difficulty accessing the quotas, which distorts the initial objective of the program, ”he added.
For this reason, also Edmund Ho's nephew has asked Hong Kong's transportation and logistics authorities to review and reform the quota system and eliminate gaps, as well as asking for data on the effective use of the quotas.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:20:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Carbon Monoxide | Hospitalized elderly due to intoxication</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/monoxido-de-carbono-idoso-hospitalizado-devido-a-intoxicacao/</link><description>Health services revealed yesterday that a 79 -year -old man had to receive medical treatment at the Conde de São Januário hospital emergency service after passing out due to carbon monoxide poisoning.
The case happened on Sunday afternoon in the Vai Long building (block I), in the Alameda da Tranquility, when the resident was taking a shower in a bathroom where a gas water heater is installed. The resident “began to feel sudden dizziness and eventually fell inanimate on the floor of the bathroom”, where he was found by family members, who immediately called an ambulance. At Conde de São Januário Hospital did laboratory tests, which revealed concentrations of carbon monoxide hemoglobin. The elderly was “undergoing hyperbaric oxygen therapy treatment” and is currently considered stable.
Authorities add that the gas water heater has been installed in the bathroom for over a decade, and that despite the installation of a ventilation, the bathroom has no windows. At the time of the occurrence, the exhaust was not connected and the authorities suspect that the incident was caused by the lack of maintenance of the device and the accumulation of residual gas in an environment with poor ventilation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:43:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy Arena | Jason Zhang brings Macao tour in March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/galaxy-arena-jason-zhang-traz-digressao-a-macau-em-marco/</link><description>Chinese singer Jason Zhang (Zhang Jie) will be in Macao in March for three shows at the Galaxy Arena, integrated into the “Future Live - Leave for 1982” tour. This is the opportunity to listen to a singer who has built a career around pop music since 2014 and recently recorded “Adrenaline” alongside James Blunt
 
“Future Live - Leave for 1982” is the name of the tour that Chinese singer Jason Zhang (Zhang Jie) has led to several stages and which in March brings to Macau three concerts, between the 7th and 9th. At Galaxy Arena from 19:30, and tickets have been on sale since Tuesday.
The shows promise to offer the audience and fans the best pop songs of the singer who started in the musical lines in 2004. They will, according to Galaxy, a kind of “journey through time, a train on the way from 1982, a moment when The past meets the future. ”
1982 is, by the way, the date of birth of the artist, born in Chengdu, and which by the end of 2023 already had a total of 15 recorded albums and 87 concerts. The beginning of a happy career happened in 2004, when he won the “My Show” contest. This participation earned him a contract with Universal Music producer in China and, from there, Zhang Jie no longer stopped making music and winning his audience.
In this early phase of his career, Zhang Jie released in 2005 the first album, entitled “The First Album”, having won the “Global Chinese Music Chart Most Male Newcomer” award, as the name implies, to new artists. The second album arrived the following year, with the name "Love Me Again", consecrating themselves as a pop artist with a repertoire of romantic ballads.
His career has also been based on some partnerships with musicians and Western Boys Band, highlighting the concert he gave at the Boao Forum in 2010 in which he sang two songs by star Michael Jackson, “Billie Jean” and “Beat It ”. Moreover, in 2012, Jason Zhang was invited to sing the song “My Love” in a Westlife concert.
"Adrenaline" with James Blunt
Jason Zhang's latest collaboration with a foreign artist is “Adrenaline”, a single of 2021 recorded with James Blunt, who became known for the successes “You're Beautiful” and “Goodbye My Lover”. At the time of the release of "Adrenaline", Jason Zhang stated on social networks that "it was an honor to record the new song" Adrenaline "with James Blunt," a good song I hope to be heard by more fans. "
Last year Jason Zhang started with the tour in China, "Future Live: To 1982", with 17 shows in five cities, including some concerts in international stops. Now follows a new tour with passing through Macau.
Jason Zhang is one of the best known singers in the country, having, in 2020, entered the 86 position of the Forbes China Celebrity 100, ie the ranking of the 100 largest Chinese celebrities. The artist's latest album was released in 2023 and calls himself “Wainan Street 1982”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:00:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | JP Morgan indicates improvements in search</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/jogo-jp-morgan-indica-melhorias-na-procura/</link><description>Despite the most positive trend, JP Morgan admits that compared to February last year there may even be a reduction in gross reciters
 
After the Lunar New Year, the search for the game in the Macau casinos is "better than the feared." The conclusions are part of the latest report by the investment bank JP Morgan Securities (Asia Pacific) over the territory, which does not fail to moderate growth expectations about the main industry in the territory.
"The game's gross recipes stabilized after the Lunar New Year," wrote DS Kim, Mufan Shi and Selina Li analysts in a report quoted by the GGR Asia portal.
However, not everything is good news for the local economy, and analysts now indicate that gross game recipes “may only grow at one digit level, between one percent and four percent throughout this year, compared to the period homologist ”.
Compared to February, analysts expect gross revenues to be between 18.3 billion patacas and the 19.4 billion patacas. These values ​​mean that compared to last year, in the worst scenario, revenues may have a break from one percent, and that in the best scenario can grow up to five percent.
“The gross revenues of the new Lunar post-year game have become better than expected, reaching 725 million patacas a day, thanks to a solid demand at the end of the year, which is in a way offsetting weakness [of the revenues] of the Lunar New Year ”, was justified.
On the other hand, JP Morgan indicates that the weakness of revenues is more related to previous expectations of industry, than actually to the amount generated by the territory tables, which between February 1 and 5 were 900 million patacas per day . The report indicates that in the first nine months of the year the revenues were 7.4 billion patacas.
Low review
The scenario outlined by JP Morgan Post-Anno New Lunar, contrasts with the one that was lived during the festivities and which led another investment bank, Citigroup, to reduce predictions about the expansion of the Macao game this year.
In a report published on Monday, Citigroup analysts, George Choi and Timothy Chau, presented a scenario in which the game's gross recipes record a 3 percent growth, which contrasts with the previous optimism, when it was expected that the sector expansion reached 7 percent. And in the first half of the year, the investment bank admits that gross revenues even record a reduction of about one percent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:39:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | Another 11 thousand vaccines. Markings open today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/gripe-mais-11-mil-vacinas-marcacoes-abrem-hoje/</link><description>The significant increase in citizens who want to get the flu vaccine has led health services to buy an additional 11 thousand doses. The markings to take the vaccines have been widened and open today. The government bought 45,000 doses than last year's flu
 
Following the race for influenza vaccination over the past weekend, taking more than 5,400 residents of health centers and hospitals, the government announced on Monday night that it would buy another 11,000 doses urgently to correspond to demand .
Thus, after the arrival last night of the lots, the markings to take the vaccine opened today on the Internet of Health Services website, with the authorities to reach that people over 65 and children between 6 months and 9 years old are exempt from marking.
Health services acquired for this time flu (2024/2025) 225 thousand doses of the flu vaccine, an increase of 45 thousand doses in relation (or 25 percent). Until Monday, the authorities accounted for 204,000 doses administered, totaling a 22.2 percent increase over the same period last year, when 167,000 vaccines had been administered. It is recalled that the race for vaccination in the past weekend occurred after two residents died following complications after flu infections A.
Macao and the World
The government points out that flu vaccination rates this year between risk groups are “ideal” and increased from last year.
Among the users of elderly homes, more than 90 percent took the vaccine, while in the infantry the rate exceeds 65 percent, in the kindergartens of primary schools more than 80 percent of children were vaccinated, while in secondary education the rate of inoculation is 70 percent. In the general calculation, among residents over 65 years of age, the vaccination rate is almost 60 percent.
The type of vaccines that Macau buys is intended for the northern hemisphere and, as such, their validity expires between May and June of each year. Therefore, the government stresses that "the annual flu vaccination program will end when existing vaccines run out or expire."</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:27:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Post Office | Announced Retoma of Service for the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/correios-anunciada-retoma-de-servico-para-os-eua/</link><description>Macao Post Office resumed sending small packages and orders to the United States, but warned that new suspensions cannot be excluded due to US postal service policies
 
The Post Office of Macao and Hong Kong announced yesterday the resumption of sending small packages and orders to the United States after five days of suspension. In a statement, the Post Office of Macao (CTT) announced that they will accept again, from February 11, “all mail objects (…) for the United States”.
In the same message from the Macao Post and Telecommunications Directorate Directorate, the CTT recalled that the suspension "may have originated a correspondence, which will possibly result in delays in the delivery of shipments to the US."
"Additionally, the possibility of any changes in the policies of US postal services [USPS) cannot be excluded at any time," the company warned.
The Macao Post Office message was preceded by one of Hong Kong's counterpart, in which they said they had been “formally notified” by the US Postal Service that US authorities “currently do not impose additional fees on postal articles. with commodity ”.
On January 5, the company said it had been notified by USPS that it could only send packages or orders that customers had registered with customs and the protection of US borders (CBP).
The registration would require “the necessary import documents and the payment of fees made through a customs dispatcher,” added the Hong Kong Post Office. After the suspension of shipping, the company “continued to negotiate” with USPS and “can temporarily resume” the postal service for the United States.
Temporary suspensions
On February 4, USPS announced that it would temporarily stop accepting orders from China and Hong Kong (without any reference to Macao) “up to new order”.
But hours later, USPS reversed the decision without justifying, just stating that it was going to work with the CBP to implement a collection process for the new rates imposed on Chinese goods in order to avoid interruptions in delivery.
The new US President Donald Trump increased customs rates on China's imports at 10 percent after retreating in the plans to charge Canada and Mexico.
The vast majority of goods sent from China arrive outside the mail system, but Trump's order specifically eliminated a tariff exemption for low -value products, purchased directly by consumers and sent through the postal service.
This exemption covered articles of less than US $ 800. The USPS measurement could block or delay orders made through Chinese e -commerce platforms Shein and Temu.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Teaching | LAM expects universities to be “battlefields”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/ensino-o-lam-espera-que-universidades-sejam-campos-de-batalha/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture wants educational institutions to advance with the integration of education, science and technology, while developing a set of qualified frameworks internationally recognition
 
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture has asked local higher education institutions to take over as “battlefields”, following President Xi Jinping's guidelines in attracting internationally known qualified frames. The request was left at a meeting between the ruler and the representatives of local universities.
According to the government, the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, approached with universities the development of Macao "as a place of aggregation of international qualified pictures." LAM indicated to the present that Macau has to follow Xi Jinping's “important discourse” and that it should “promote the integrated development of education, science and technology, as well as qualified pictures”, as well as “vigorously introduce and cultivate several Types of qualified frames and create a place of aggregation of international qualified frames.
The secretary also stated that the discourse is as "a clear direction for Macao's work on education, science and technology, as well as for qualified paintings, defining objectives, channels and the main areas of action."
LAM also mentioned higher education institutions play a crucial role in the “aggregation of international qualified staff” and which should be constituted as “the most important platforms and the main battlefields”.
Nation
During the meeting with representatives of local universities, LAM said it hoped that the government and educational institutions work “together to firmly implement the spirit of President XI's Directive and do a good job in higher education, the construction of platforms scientific research and internationalization of teaching staff ”.
The official also asked universities to continue to "fully enjoy Macau's unique advantage of" one country, two systems "and their role as a exchange platform." In this way the leader believes that Macau can become "in a place of aggregation of international qualified staff, contributing to the strengths of Macao to the construction of a strong nation."
The University of Macao was represented by Rector Song Yonghua, the Macao Management Institute by President Samuel Tong Kai Chung, Macao Polytechnic University, Rector Marcus Imba Kei, the University of Tourism of Macao by Dean Fanny Vong Chuk Kwan, the Macao Security Forces School by Director Wong Chi Fai, Macao University of Science and Technology by Rector Joseph Hun-Wei Lee, the University of Macao City by Rector Liu Jun, the University of St. Joseph by Vice Rector Zhang Shuguang, and the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute of Macao, by President Van Iat Kio.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:07:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Reluctant government in legislating vital will</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/estudo-governo-relutante-em-legislar-testamento-vital/</link><description>A study by Man Teng Iong, professor at the Faculty of Law of the University of Macao, and Vera Lúcia Raposo draws attention to the absence of the “anticipated directive of will”, or vital will, of the legal system of masters. The document allows a person to decide previously whether or not to receive medical treatments in the terminal phase of life
 
For several years in Portugal any citizen can sign an Early Directive of Will (DAV), also known as the Vital Testament, which allows the conscious decision on the type of medical treatments to receive in a given health context. Being far from constituting a legal form of euthanasia, the document allows to know the patient's will when he, for health reasons, cannot do so.
In Macao, the DAV is not legislated and the authorities have revealed signs of reluctance to advance in the process. This is what the study concludes “Advance Directives in Macao: Not Legally Recognissed, but. . . ” [DAV in Macao: No legal recognition, but… ”, signed by Man Teng Iong, professor at the University of Macao Law School (one), and Vera Lúcia Raposo, former director of the same faculty and currently a teacher at the Faculty of Law from the New University of Lisbon. The study was recently published by Cambridge University Press, although it was the theme of Man Teng Iong's master's thesis defended a few years ago.
The authors analyze the legal framework of the issue in Macao, concluding that “to date, the Macao Executive assumed a precautionary attitude towards DAV, accepting (or tolerating) these instruments, but not investigating this subject with the necessary force” .
"It has been reported that, due to the aging of the population of Macao, and in the light of the adoption of DAV legislation in the last twenty years in countries such as the United States, Australia, Canada and Singapore, the executive recognized the need to legislate DAV." , it is added.
The authors indicate that local authorities even recognize the positive factors of accessing this type of legal document. “Such legal instruments will not only increase quality of life and protect patients' dignity at the end of their lives, but also reduce unnecessary medical expenses. On December 3, 2019, Health Services (SS), and the sub -entity of the Life Science Ethics Committee, introduced the 'guidelines and future policy of the DAV' in Macao, agreeing to legitimize [a matter]. However, despite the agreement around the implementation of DAV, the executive insists on maintaining a preliminary discussions around DAV. ”
Thus, the authors consider that "hesitation may reflect the fear of the [SS] in facing difficulties and controversies around the plans for its implementation."
Consensus as an argument
The authors point out that the “barriers to the implementation” of the DAV legal framework in Macao arise “from a low conscience from the public in the face of DAV legislation and the possibility of patients can change the way of facing the end of life, well as the arrangement of the patient's family members to fulfill the patient's wishes ”.
The study stresses that the SS have always argued that “an extensive and profound action of sensitization and education with the public has been done in academic, social and legal areas whenever necessary, and that the law that regulates DAV can only be implemented later obtained the consensus of all sectors ”.
However, the study states that “it is possible to argue that the position of the executive lacks proper justification”, because “this type of consensus invoked to postpone the regulation of DAV is not possible to achieve, due to the multiplicity of legal, ethical visions and even religious about matter ”. In addition, the authors point out that "even if such a consensus could be achieved, the executive did not take the necessary steps to encourage or facilitate discussion, or awareness, with the population."
Data on a study made about the notions of the population of Macao on the subject are referred to, concluding that "the lack of information about the DAV was the main determining factor in the decision of people to make the DAV."
"The study also found that 73.6 percent of the sample (724 people) were willing to complete a DAV if the document had legal recognition."
Social and political “resistance”
Thus, the study's authors warn of the existence of “a great resistance - from certain groups of residents of Macao and the Executive - for the implementation of adequate DAV regulation”. "A possible reason for this hesitation is to the fear that formally legislating DAV can lead to euthanasia, a forbidden practice in Macau, even if the two situations are clearly different," the authors say, who understand to be "imperative that the executive regulates the DAV ”.
At this particular point, a new law should “clarify some legal aspects, such as the requirements for the [DAV] and to be legally operational”, ensuring the patient's decision autonomy and ensuring “a more appropriate solution from the point of view human rights ”.
The authors draw attention to the influence of Portuguese law of 2012 on the DAV legislation in Macao, drawing attention to the fact that DAV have a greater compatibility with what is currently in the local Civil Code.
However, legislating the DAV also causes a cultural discussion, is pointed out. “It is unclear whether DAV regulation would be in agreement with the widespread values ​​of the predominant Chinese community, which still has a great connection to the family. More studies are needed to clarify this and other subjects, since, for example, there are no data on numbers estimates and implementation of DAV in the jurisdiction of Macao ”, and there is“ an urgent need for further investigations that exploit perspectives of the doctors around the DAV ”.
The case of the Kiang Wu Hospital, which at the “The Hospice &amp; Palliative Care Center” palliative care center provides treatment for cancer terminal patients. However, before the admission of these patients, the signing of the document “Consent for the Hospice &amp; Palliative Care Center” is required, a kind of consent that is mostly signed by family members and not by the patient himself. In addition, "it is not an authorization document by patients, or not, of medical procedures, but an acceptance of hospital terms and conditions."
What current law allows
In general terms, DAV in Macau have some legal framework, namely in the Civil Code, although they are not legislated with their own law. The authors conclude, however, that "there is some uncertainty about to what extent DAV would be effective, in particular given that doctors tend to reject any document that rejects a support and life maintenance treatment."
“In Macau the discussion around the DAV is almost nonexistent. Without a clear and transparent debate that includes specialists and studies with legal arguments, there will be no legal developments related to the nature, content and use of DAV in the near future, ”he describes.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 23:58:36</pubDate></item><item><title>McDonald's | Planned opening in China from another thousand restaurants this year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/mcdonalds-planeada-abertura-na-china-de-mais-mil-restaurantes-este-ano/</link><description>The world's largest rapid food chain, McDonald's, plans to open about 1,000 new restaurants in China in 2025, almost half of the 2,200 that will open worldwide.
At a conference with analysts after the last quarter results, US Frederick Borden's financial director, revealed these numbers, which in the case of China followed the number of openings announced in the last two exercises.
"We are watching the encouraging signs of stabilization in China," said the official about the company's performance in the Asian country for 2024, when global profits fell 3 percent over the previous year.
By 2024, McDonald's executive president Chris Kempczinski had already highlighted the “strong growth” in China, despite the pressure on consumer confidence in the face of economic recovery problems, and said: “We will do what it takes to maintain the maintaining our competitiveness in this market ”.
The hamburgers chain has about six thousand points of sale in China and aims to exceed ten thousand by 2028. Currently, there are over 40,000 McDonald's restaurants worldwide.
At the end of 2023, McDonald's announced an agreement to buy 28 percent participation that Carlyle investment company had in its business in China for an estimated $ 1.8 billion, increasing its participation of 20 percent to 48 percent, with the Chinese investment bank Citic to control the remaining 52 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:06:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Circulation | Deputy alerts to HK vehicle abuse</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/circulacao-deputado-alerta-para-abusos-de-veiculos-de-hk/</link><description>Hong Kong Deputy Adriano Ho warned that the Hong Kong vehicle wate system in Macau is being abused. The complaint was filed through a Facebook post, where the deputy speaks of forgery of information.
“I recently received many complaints that the system is being abused. After people have detected the gaps that exist in the system began to emerge agencies that charge money to falsify the information, to simulate that customers have calls with Macau, ”wrote the deputy. According to Hong Kong regulations, the quotas are attributed to those who show you have connections with the masters.
“Some people have created ghost companies to which quotas were attributed, and then sold these companies to profit from Quota. This causes people with business in Hong Kong and Macau, or work in Macau, have difficulty accessing the quotas, which distorts the initial objective of the program, ”he added.
For this reason, also Edmund Ho's nephew has asked Hong Kong's transportation and logistics authorities to review and reform the quota system and eliminate gaps, as well as asking for data on the effective use of the quotas.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:20:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Carbon Monoxide | Hospitalized elderly due to intoxication</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/monoxido-de-carbono-idoso-hospitalizado-devido-a-intoxicacao/</link><description>Health services revealed yesterday that a 79 -year -old man had to receive medical treatment at the Conde de São Januário hospital emergency service after passing out due to carbon monoxide poisoning.
The case happened on Sunday afternoon in the Vai Long building (block I), in the Alameda da Tranquility, when the resident was taking a shower in a bathroom where a gas water heater is installed. The resident “began to feel sudden dizziness and eventually fell inanimate on the floor of the bathroom”, where he was found by family members, who immediately called an ambulance. At Conde de São Januário Hospital did laboratory tests, which revealed concentrations of carbon monoxide hemoglobin. The elderly was “undergoing hyperbaric oxygen therapy treatment” and is currently considered stable.
Authorities add that the gas water heater has been installed in the bathroom for over a decade, and that despite the installation of a ventilation, the bathroom has no windows. At the time of the occurrence, the exhaust was not connected and the authorities suspect that the incident was caused by the lack of maintenance of the device and the accumulation of residual gas in an environment with poor ventilation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:43:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy Arena | Jason Zhang brings Macao tour in March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/galaxy-arena-jason-zhang-traz-digressao-a-macau-em-marco/</link><description>Chinese singer Jason Zhang (Zhang Jie) will be in Macao in March for three shows at the Galaxy Arena, integrated into the “Future Live - Leave for 1982” tour. This is the opportunity to listen to a singer who has built a career around pop music since 2014 and recently recorded “Adrenaline” alongside James Blunt
 
“Future Live - Leave for 1982” is the name of the tour that Chinese singer Jason Zhang (Zhang Jie) has led to several stages and which in March brings to Macau three concerts, between the 7th and 9th. At Galaxy Arena from 19:30, and tickets have been on sale since Tuesday.
The shows promise to offer the audience and fans the best pop songs of the singer who started in the musical lines in 2004. They will, according to Galaxy, a kind of “journey through time, a train on the way from 1982, a moment when The past meets the future. ”
1982 is, by the way, the date of birth of the artist, born in Chengdu, and which by the end of 2023 already had a total of 15 recorded albums and 87 concerts. The beginning of a happy career happened in 2004, when he won the “My Show” contest. This participation earned him a contract with Universal Music producer in China and, from there, Zhang Jie no longer stopped making music and winning his audience.
In this early phase of his career, Zhang Jie released in 2005 the first album, entitled “The First Album”, having won the “Global Chinese Music Chart Most Male Newcomer” award, as the name implies, to new artists. The second album arrived the following year, with the name "Love Me Again", consecrating themselves as a pop artist with a repertoire of romantic ballads.
His career has also been based on some partnerships with musicians and Western Boys Band, highlighting the concert he gave at the Boao Forum in 2010 in which he sang two songs by star Michael Jackson, “Billie Jean” and “Beat It ”. Moreover, in 2012, Jason Zhang was invited to sing the song “My Love” in a Westlife concert.
"Adrenaline" with James Blunt
Jason Zhang's latest collaboration with a foreign artist is “Adrenaline”, a single of 2021 recorded with James Blunt, who became known for the successes “You're Beautiful” and “Goodbye My Lover”. At the time of the release of "Adrenaline", Jason Zhang stated on social networks that "it was an honor to record the new song" Adrenaline "with James Blunt," a good song I hope to be heard by more fans. "
Last year Jason Zhang started with the tour in China, "Future Live: To 1982", with 17 shows in five cities, including some concerts in international stops. Now follows a new tour with passing through Macau.
Jason Zhang is one of the best known singers in the country, having, in 2020, entered the 86 position of the Forbes China Celebrity 100, ie the ranking of the 100 largest Chinese celebrities. The artist's latest album was released in 2023 and calls himself “Wainan Street 1982”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:00:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Book dedicated to Carlos Paredes includes unpublished recording of show</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/livro-dedicado-a-carlos-paredes-inclui-gravacao-inedita-de-espectaculo/</link><description>The life and work of guitar master Carlos Paredes, who “created a genuinely Portuguese song out of nowhere”, is told in a book to be presented this week in Portugal and which includes the recordings of two concerts, one of which is unprecedented.
In “Carlos Paredes - the guitar of a people”, the researcher Octávio Fonseca begins to tell the guitarist's route before he was born, reminiscent of his family background.
Carlos Paredes, who would complete a hundred years of life on February 16, descend from a family of guitarists and composers: great-grandfather António Rodrigues Paredes, grandfather Gonçalo Rodrigues Paredes, grand-uncle Manuel Rodrigues Paredes and father, Artur Paredes.
According to Octávio Fonseca, Artur Paredes, “in terms of technique, completely revolutionized the guitar of Coimbra”, and Carlos Paredes “took advantage of this work and simplified it”. To tell the story and stories of Carlos Paredes, Octávio Fonseca resorted to the research work he had done to another book dedicated to the guitarist edited in 2000, which included reading articles on music that 'master' wrote in newspapers and interviews that gave to various media.
But to write this book, she had "the extraordinary collaboration" of guitarist and songwriter Luísa Amaro, companion of Paredes. "Most of the stories that are told in the book were she who conveyed to me," he said.
What makes Carlos Paredes a unique artist is, for Octavio Fonseca, the fact that he created “genuinely Portuguese music of nowhere”.
“In the late 1960s, early 1970s, we were very discussing to go to traditional roots, to create a Portuguese popular music, as José Afonso did. But Carlos Paredes did not do that, and created a Portuguese song out of nowhere. He did not start from our traditional song, nor from any experience of Portuguese music, ”said the researcher.
The parallelism between José Afonso and Carlos Paredes was pointed out by the guitarist himself. “He says in two interviews that there is a parallel between him and José Afonso at the beginning of his career. Carlos Paredes's first album is from 1962 and José Afonso's first ballad album as well (he had albums before, but it was from Fado de Coimbra). They both make a new song from Coimbra, ”he said.
The following year, the two musicians “break free from Coimbra, from the song of Coimbra”, but with a difference, “while with José Afonso there is a complete cut, with Carlos Paredes there is a cut, but there are always a 'penguinhos' in the compositions in which Coimbra appears ”.
MUSICAL NEWS
“Carlos Paredes - the guitar of a people” is accompanied by two records. One is “Master of the Portuguese Guitar”, an album recorded in 1977, at the 7th Political Song Festival in Berlin, edited this year by her friend, editor of the former German Democratic Republic (RDA), which is unprecedented in Portugal.
In the other album is recorded “The First Show Carlos Paredes made in his own name in Portugal”, an unprecedented recording registered on March 31, 1984, at the Carlos Alberto Theater, in Porto. The book also includes a photo portfolio by Carlos Paredes, by Augusto Cabrita, Luís Paulo Moura and Inácio Ludgero.
The musician lived mainly in Lisbon and the city inspired many of his compositions. “Green Years”, one of the best known of his work, was composed for the homonymous film of Paulo Rocha, milestone of the new Portuguese cinema of the 1960s.
Anti-fascist combatant, opposed the dictatorship and was arrested by PIDE in the late 1950s. Until the 1990s, it reconciled the guitar with its administrative activity at the São José Hospital in Lisbon. In December 1993, he was diagnosed with myelopathy, a disease that attacked him the bone structure and that prevented him from playing guitar.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 18:27:26</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Pyongyang denounces “hostile military act”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/eua-pyongyang-denuncia-acto-militar-hostil/</link><description>North Korea accused the United States on Monday of committing a "hostile military act," after a US Navy submarine has moved in South Korea for refueling.
"We are very concerned about the dangerous hostile military act of the United States, which can lead the acute military confrontation in the region of the Korean Peninsula to a total armed conflict," said a spokesman for the Ministry of Defense, quoted in a statement released by the agency of State News KCNA.
Pyongyang has asked the United States to "stop the provocations that feed instability," accusing them of ignoring North Korean security concerns. South Korea Yonhap news agency said USS Alexandria, a US nuclear submarine, arrived on Monday on Busan, South Korea on Monday. A similar visit had occurred in November.
"Our Armed Forces are closely monitoring the frequent appearance of US strategic assets on the Korean Peninsula and are ready to use all means to defend state security and interests, as well as regional peace," said the port -Voice of the Ministry of Defense of North Korea.
North Korea emphasized the importance of developing its self -defense capabilities and referred to the promise of leader Kim Jong Un in January to continue his country's nuclear program "indefinitely."
Good old friends
United States President Donald Trump expressed on Friday the intention to build bridges with Kim Jong-un's North Korean regime. “I think it's a great advantage for everyone that I get along with him. I like him, I mean, I get along with him, he gets along with me. And that's a good thing, it's not a bad thing, ”said the Republican.
But North Korea replied that the nuclear weapons it possesses are not a bargaining chip to negotiate, but a force to stop threats, and justified the reinforcement of weapons with the geopolitical aspirations of the West.
The statement suggests that Pyongyang has no interest in returning to the negotiating table with Washington. In the first term as president of the United States, Donald Trump proposed to North Korea to end nuclear weapons in exchange for support in economic development.
The North Korean message also mentioned the recent statements of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the European Union, which reaffirmed that they will not recognize North Korea as nuclear power. Pyongyang accuses the West of being a destabilizing force of peace.
Pyongyang, in addition, denounced the growing participation of NATO and European countries in military maneuvers around the Korean Peninsula, accusing them of seeking the confrontation and disarmament of the Asian country, not for safety reasons, but to “reach the ones their political and impure military objectives ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:06:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP | Reinforced prevention in combating human trafficking</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/cpsp-reforcada-prevencao-no-combate-ao-trafico-humano/</link><description>The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) ensures that it has reinforced prevention in combating human trafficking after in late December revealed that five residents of Macao were victims of human trafficking and forced to “work” on online fraud centers in Taiwan and Cambodia.
In response to questions posed by Macau News Agency, police authorities indicate having published on social networks messages warning of cases of people who are seduced with work proposals in Southeast Asia, but eventually fall into meshes of criminal groups that are dedicated to online fraud. The victims, in their wide Chinese majority, are forced to defraud people in telecommunications centers.
Although they do not reveal whether there have been additional cases of Macao residents beyond the five announced in December, CPSP indicates that the objective of the prevention campaign has alerted the population to be cautious when they are offered a job through online platforms or people Unknown, especially when these jobs imply trips abroad. Another sign of danger covers the form of work that promises high wages, without the need for academic background, technical capacity or work experience in the area.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:35:23</pubDate></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, coordinator of the CCCM Educational Service
February 2025
The Chinese tradition says that the classic works of culture were not just four books: The Analects (《論語/1 论语》 lunyǔ), the book of Mâncio (《孟子》 mèngzǐ), the great study (《大學/大学》 dàxué) and the doctrine of the middle (《中庸》 zhōngyōng), and five classics: The Classic of Mutations (《易經易经》 Yì Jīng), The Book of Odes (《詩經诗经》 Shījīng), The History (《史記/太史公記 // 史记/太史公记》 Shǐjì/tàishǐ gōngjì), the rites (《禮記礼记》 lǐjì), the annals of spring and autumn (《春秋》 chūnqiū)), but four books and six classics, because There was one more relative to music (樂經/乐经) Yuè Jīng, which in the meantime was lost.
However, “music” (樂/乐 yuè) is so important to the Chinese that their synogram is confused in the written form with that of “joy” (樂/乐 lè).  From an etymological point of view, it is the pictogram of a musical instrument, whose base represents the wood part and the top the strings of it.  This, for the satisfaction that raises when it is touched, will serve by extension of meaning to figure the synogram of joy.
Music before belonging to humanity, depends on the deities of the Chinese popular animist religion and natural forces such as wind or biological beings such as birds, or mythological like fenices.  It is known that the yellow emperor (黄帝 Huángdì) ruled in a mythical antiquity that dates back to organized Chinese civilization. But this, according to one of the great Taoist philosophers of Chinese antiquity, Lie Yukou (列御寇 Liè Yùkòu ”) in the homonymous work Liezi (列子“ Lièzǐ ·) puts the emperor to make spiritual trips in which he finds feminine deities of matriarchal times, as Huaxu (華胥/华胥 Huáxū), mother of the first Chinese Emperor Fuxi (伏羲 Fuxī) and, therefore, ancestral matriarch of all Chinese or even the mother and/or mysterious woman of the ninth sky (九天聖 (圣) 母/九天玄女 jiǔtān shèngmǔ/jiiǔtān xuannǚ), which will have taught him a lot, even in the case of the latter to appreciate music, poetry, and was also started by her, who had a human face and body of phoenix, in the arts of love.
As for Phoenix is ​​the bird that symbolizes eternal life and peace; When the gray itself is reborn, it transports the hope of whole, renewed and peaceful beings, as it only arises in the world in times of tranquility and harmony. But it is also in close relationship with the music, because it is a mythological bird that sings, such as the wind, whose sound is composed for the Chinese by the melodious beating of the wings of the birds, when it comes to breeze, or the beating of the same in storm.
Linglun (伶倫/伶伦 Ling Lun) created the twelve shades following a request from the yellow emperor, which after being properly polite and trained his musical ear for the mysterious woman of ninth sky, was bored in the trips of inspection by Earth with The monotony of melodies. This great musician rushed to fulfill orders and surrendered with soul and heart to listen to all the sounds of nature to obtain the required inspiration to the mission. But it was in the Kunlun Sacred Mountain (崑崙山/昆仑山 Kūnlún Shān) that he obtained the lighting necessary for the creation of twelve tones by resorting to twelve bamboo tubes. How did he verify the right tones? “Loading the twelve bamboo tubes, Linglun reached the foot of the Kunlun mountain to hear the song of the Phoenix. When the birds sang, the male gave six shouts and the female answered them with six others. Linglun compared the twelve screams with his sounds and found that there was a perfect match between them. ” (Wang and Alves, 2009, 48)
He had reached his goal. The shades followed the model of the Phoenices, when he presented his creation to the Yellow Emperor, having been precisely rewarded with the title of God of Music [音樂 (乐) 之神 Yīnyuè Zhī Shén] and the world has since filled with More beautiful melodies.
Going now to philosophy, the cosmos faced as a mysterious musical instrument is one of the favorite metaphors of one of the great Taoist philosophers, the prince of Huainan, Liu an [劉 (刘) 安 Liú'ān, 179? -122 BC] It leaves us a work of the early days of the Han Dynasty, entitled Huainanzi (《淮南子》 Huáinánzǐ). The work is known in the Chinese tradition also with the title of (《淮南子鴻烈》 Huáinánzǐ Hóngliè), whose meaning is “the radiant light of Master Huainan”, having been the sixth chapter translated by Canadian synologist Charles Le Blanc, under the Title Huainanzi 淮南子 Philosophical Synthesis in Early Han Thought, containing the suggestive subtitle The Idea of ​​Resonance (Kan-Ying 感應) with a Translation and Analysis of Chapter Six.
Suppose that the whole universe is linked, in the manner of the ropes of an instrument, spreading the sound, echoing and resonating when it touches on a ropes, will have its western counterpart in the mysticism of the Pythagorean pre-Socratic philosopher and its assumption of the “music of the spheres”, that is, the melody produced by the stars in their heavenly trajectories.
Returning to the Master of Huainan, he is informed in section II of the IX of the sixth chapter, that “the mutual response of things belonging to the same category is deeply mysterious and extremely subtle” (BLANC, 1985, 116), to which the text corresponds to the text Original is in Appendix 1 (Blanc, 1985, 221-215): “夫物類之相應玄妙深微知不能論” (6/ 3a.5) 2. These lines can be explained by resorting to another postulate, “the mutual influence of spiritual qì 3 (天神氣 shén qì)” “” (6/4a. 1), whose visible action manifests itself in the similarity of the outer forms of things, But also in the complementary game of the female and masculine forces that make them creative and transforming, and the superior action, as the Taoists believe, is based on the invisible and silent mutual response (相應 xiāngyìng), that is, non -discursive, which It does not prevent it is intuitive and melodious.
The mutual resonance is sustained by a complementary game of the energies yin (陰/阴 yīn) and yang (陽/阳 yáng) at the most varied levels, guided by the principle of causality, which acts between similar and different beings, because it arises O Qì enabling and uniting what is distinct, in a perfect resonance, so as to figure the cosmos as Taiji or “Supreme last” (太极/太極 tàijí). Thus, section IV of Chapter VI is achieved, where musical resonance (6/6b.9-11) is exposed, which works metaphorically to introduce universal resonance, implying a “great immersion” in the “supreme harmony”, impossible to explain (Blanc, 1985, 138). We are told that an tuner of Sè (瑟), an instrument of Chinese strings with 25 strings (vaguely recalling an Arabil), when touching a rope, will obtain the mutual harmony of the same rope in another instrument. However, “if someone changes the tuning of a rope so that it does not respond to any of the five notes, but when touching it gets a resonance with the 25 strings, then there is a difference with regard to the sound, succeeding that it was evoked that to govern all others. ” (Ibidem) “改調一弦其於無音無所比鼓之而二十五弦皆應此未始” (6/6a.11).
The sage, holy, or supreme musician will be one who can put himself in a direct intuitive connection with Tao (道 道), without herself being able to provide the reasons for it. Dip in the numenal world, play and mix essences, becomes what you want and lives in mutual resonance, absolute and total musical, with all that exists, not just relative to your "similar."
There is a music story for Guqin (古琴 Gǔqín), another instrument of seven -string Chinese strings, told by Taoist philosopher Liezi in the chapter of the previously mentioned homonymous work, yellow emperor, 11th section, (《列子 黄帝》第十一 黄帝》第十一部分 Lièzǐ · huángdì ”dì Shíyī Bùfèn), which illustrates this universal resonance, easier to obtain a spontaneous mind, as it happens to children, and as the founder recalls Laozi (老子 lǎozǐ), the founder) Perfect heart-heart is that of a newborn. In the story that I present my translation below, the protagonist is a boy with whom birds play naturally, but when his father asks him to capture one of them in order to entertain himself, the birds distance themselves, That's why the score for Guqin calls on “the distance from water owls” 《鷗鷺忘機/ō ōuu lù wàng jī 4 https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kgte7wzut1y
原文 Original text (classic Chinese)
海上之人有好漚鳥者 ， 每旦之海上 ， 從漚鳥遊 ， 漚鳥之至者百住而不止。其父曰：「吾聞漚鳥皆從汝遊 ， 汝取來 ， 吾玩之。」明日之海上 ， 漚鳥舞而不下也。故曰：至言去言 ， 至為無為。齊智之所知 ， 則淺矣。5
Contemporary Chinese
海边有个喜欢鸥鸟的人 ， 每天早上到海上去 ， ， ， 跟鸥鸟玩耍 “我听说鸥鸟都爱跟你游玩 ， 你抓一只来 ， 我玩玩。 ”第二天他来到海上 ， 鸥鸟都在空中飞翔而不下来。所以说：“ 最好的语言是没有语言 ， 最高的作为是没有作为。同别人比试智慧的想法 ， 那是很浅陋的。
There was a boy near the sea that liked a lot of water owls. Every day, he used to stroll by the sea where he played with the birds, more than one hundred.  Once, the father commented: “I heard that the water owls often play with you, grabs one for me so that I can also entertain me with them. “The next morning, by the sea, the birds danced over his head, but they didn't approach. For this reason it is said: “The best speech is speechless, the best action is not acting. If wisdom can be compared, then it is superficial! ”
Bibliographic references
ALVES, Ana Cristina. 2022. “Mysterious mother of the ninth sky 九天玄母 jiiǔtān xuan mǔ” visits. Fafe: Labyrinth.
Baidu. 2025. 《列子 · 黄帝》 (Yellow Emperor, In Liezi) Available at: https://baike.baidu.com/item/%E5%88%97%E5%AD%90%C2%B7%E9%BB% 84%E5%B8%9D/8828591#1-1, accessed on January 31, 2025.
BESADA, Dennis. 2014. Music Magazine 14 (1): 85. Available at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/312106396_a_genese_da_harmonia_das_esferas_no_antigo_pitagorismo, accessed 5 February 2025.
BLANC, Charles Le (Org. And Trad). 1985. Huainanzi 淮南子 Philosophical Synthesis in Early Han Thought. The Idea of ​​Resonance (Kan-Ying 感應) with a Translation and Analysis of Chapter Six. Hong Kong: Hong Kong University Press.
《鸥鹭忘机》 (the distancing of water owls). Youtube.  https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kgte7wzut1y, accessed 5 February 2025.
WANG SOYING, Ana Cristina Alves. 2009. “Linglun creates the twelve tones 伶伦作十二乐律 Ling Lun Lun Zuò Shí'èr Yuèlǜ” Myths and Legends of the Land of the Dragon. Lisbon; Path.
The relative titles classic works and/or old synograms are presented in traditional and contemporary Chinese so that the evolution of language can be analyzed in its course towards simplification.
The numbering is different in the text translated by Charles Le Blanc and the original, which is why two numbers arise in this article, being that of the translator identified with the quote that follows the system of bibliographic references author and the original text with the numbering of the Chinese manuscript of the Liu Wen-Tien edition.
The standardization of Chinese phonetics was made by the Pinyin system (拼音 pīnyīn), adopted in the Popular Republic of China.
“The distancing of water owls” is a song for Guqin, composed by the song of the Song Liu Zhifang dynasty (宋代刘志芳). The score, which had the privilege of listening to CCCM by teacher and music Du Wanzhen (杜婉贞) in late 2024, was for the first time published by Zhu Quan of the Ming Dynasty (明代朱权), in the edition of the “SECRET MAGIC SHOCS ”(《神奇秘谱》). This old piece, which has come to us, demonstrates human schemes and calculations not to work with birds, but only free spontaneous joke.
The classic text was converted to traditional Chinese.
This space has the collaboration of the Scientific and Cultural Center of Macau, in Lisbon, and the opinions expressed in the article are the entire responsibility of the authors. https://www.ccccm.gov.pt/</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Ba Juyi (772-846), the preclarious poet of the Tang who has known the separation of his family since he was ten years old, sent north to escape a war, and then in his unstable life as an employee ziguly in the empire occupying government posts In distant cities, he celebrated in many of his most singular poems, meetings he had.
As the innovidable impression that caused him the young woman on the bank of the Changjiang River, tangling the strings of the musical instrument that has a pear -shaped wooden base called Pipa, “Strong String Ringing Rooms,/ Soft Cords murmuring as whispered words »
About the affinity that you realized in it, wrote:
"We the two fallen in disgrace, wandering in the ends of the world, we do not ask to be old known to meet by chance."
Often only silent witness to these meetings at random or other equally dilects, only the intriguing moon glow that lasts as a faithful consolation, restoring the memory of so many happy times or the presence of lost loved ones. Memories that, in the words "flooded by the moonlight" of the Tang poet, would revive in the spirit of their readers.
As it succeeded many years later, already in the Qing Dynasty, when a Qiantang -born painter and poet, current Hangzhou, where Ba Juyi was governor, and in his west lake he had a dike that performed to this day, he was inspired by three characteristic circumstances of the poems of the vate.
On a sheet of album (ink and color on paper, 23.5 x 32 cm, Metmuseum) in a painting of GUO (1763-1837) it is written that it results from a request, celebrating the mourning by a dear person, remembering words by Xiangshan Jushi, the "Holly Hill Hill", a name Bai Juyi chose for himself when in his last years he lived in a part of Longmen Buddhist monastery in the fragrant hill. These words referred three situations: "The cold moon, the empty room, a person left."
Gu Luo figured in this painting, admiring the moon in an empty room, a literate sitting with his son next door, in a porch, between high Bambus and Salgueiros in an enhanced atmosphere.
In three other inspiring situations of the poet and novelist Cao Xueqin (1710-1765), the origin of vertical roll painting burying fallen flowers (paint and color on paper, 86.7 x 30.5 cm, in a private collection, can be read sale at Christies). Words that the poet attributes to his character Lin Dayu from the novel Honglou Meng, "Red Apartments Dream": "Flowers withered, flowers flutter, flowers fill the sky."
For Gou Luo these verses seemed to resonate like the haunt of Shimo, the "demon of poetry", with whom it fought Ba Juyi. Their way of resisting the distressing and unsettling kingdom of Emperor Daoguang (r. 1820-50) making absences present.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The world's largest rapid food chain, McDonald's, plans to open about 1,000 new restaurants in China in 2025, almost half of the 2,200 that will open worldwide.
At a conference with analysts after the last quarter results, US Frederick Borden's financial director, revealed these numbers, which in the case of China followed the number of openings announced in the last two exercises.
"We are watching the encouraging signs of stabilization in China," said the official about the company's performance in the Asian country for 2024, when global profits fell 3 percent over the previous year.
By 2024, McDonald's executive president Chris Kempczinski had already highlighted the “strong growth” in China, despite the pressure on consumer confidence in the face of economic recovery problems, and said: “We will do what it takes to maintain the maintaining our competitiveness in this market ”.
The hamburgers chain has about six thousand points of sale in China and aims to exceed ten thousand by 2028. Currently, there are over 40,000 McDonald's restaurants worldwide.
At the end of 2023, McDonald's announced an agreement to buy 28 percent participation that Carlyle investment company had in its business in China for an estimated $ 1.8 billion, increasing its participation of 20 percent to 48 percent, with the Chinese investment bank Citic to control the remaining 52 percent.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>António Graça de Abreu</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/antonio-graca-abreu/</link><description>"Jorge Mazcarenhas Foy to have the city called Chincheo, where it seems to him that he was richer people than in Canton."
Fernão Lopes de Castanheda, History of the Conquest of India, Book IV, Chapter XLI.
“We arrived at the port of Chinchéu, we found three ships from Portuguese that had been a month ago that were arrived (from Liampó) of which we were very well received and wrapped with a lot of party and contentment and then gave us new land, and the merchant , and the peace and quiet of the port. ”
Fernão Mendes Pinto, pilgrimage, chap.57
"When the Portuguese, in the 16th Century, Recovered China to European Knowledge, Zayton Was in the longing the great haven of forreign trade."
Henry Yule, The Book of Marco Polo The Venetian, London, John Murray, 1874, Chapter LXXXII, II Vol., Pag 221, Note 2.
Among the reports of our 16th century chroniclers and adventurers there is some confusion as to the exact location of the place we called Chincheo. The toponym appears associated with two different but close spaces, the cities of Quangzhou 泉州 and Zhangzhou 漳州 or, by extension, the Chincheos will be the inhabitants of the current province of Fujian, and Chincheo may still be the name of the province itself. Now to Quangzhou, the two characters - who sound like "chuanchou" in Mandarin - have the approximate reading of "Chinchew" in the local pronunciation, in the Hokkien or Fulaohua 福佬话 福佬话, (the old language of Fujian), a subgroup of the great min of the South South spoken in the province of Fujian. From "Chinchew" to the chincheo of the Portuguese in China goes a very short step. Moreover, it is curious that, in addition to the Mandarin, the most spoken dialect in Taiwan, Formosa, is exactly the Hokkien since part of the island's population is originally from the Quangzhou region, emigrated to Taiwan in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
Not wanting to enter any other discussion, I believe the city of Quangzhou, such as Liampó or Ningbo 宁波, in the neighboring province of Zhejiang, [1] will be the major ports of commerce and shelter of the Portuguese of the first half of the 16th century, still still Prior to the foundation and fixation in Macau, which will only happen from 1553/55, after our sailors, merchants and adventurers were expelled from these two cities by the Chinese because they are foreigners and have assumed behaviors of true haitao 海偷, the "pirates of the sea" as the Chinese called us. Just read the saga of António de Faria in the pilgrimage of Fernão Mendes Pinto to understand how to trade but also loot, steal, live extremely part of the Portuguese hundredists of the Portuguese by lands of China. Just as they entered the daily lives of other peoples, including Chinese.
Quangzhou or Chincheo, or if we want to Zaiton of Marco Polo that in his book he considers her “a of the two best and Mayors that sound in the world” was one of the first places on China's back to navigation, point of scale and often at the beginning of what is conventionally called the “sea silk route”. From here he left Marco Polo on his long return trip to Italy. It is believed that Zaiton, the Arab name in Quangzhou,-also associated with “olive”-gave rise to the words “satin” in English and “satin” in Portuguese, all related to the many tons of silk that exported by Porto from Quangzhou. [1]
In the dynasties Song and Yuan (from 960 to 1368), the city has reached the zénite of its development as the great warehouse of the seas of Asia. They were Muslim merchants, especially Persians - who since the ninth century they gave body to the expansion of Islam to the vast Southeast Asia - which settled in Quangzhou where they calculate they had reached 150 thousand souls. It was so strong its economic power in the city that between 1345 and 1365 were the subject of a brutal persecution by the Chinese powers, and there were thousands and thousands of dead. In the fourteenth century, Zaiton was also inhabited by Jews, Hindu and Catholics, and the Italian Franciscan Andrea of ​​Perugia was the first bishop in the city in 1332. Then dozens of mosques and three churches, all devastated in the persecution in those years.
In the summer of 2013, I am in search of the city of Zaiton, Quangzhou, Chinchew or Chincheo.
Seventy kilometers of bus since Xiamen and I arrive in the city that seems to me harmonious, well distributed by the valley and the hills that surround it. Where is the river, where is the port? I ask and are saying that Quangzhou has no sea port, only at the mouth of the river, in front of the islands, there is a small port for fishing boats. Path miles along the Jinhera River towards the sea. The river is hardly navigable, everything is blown away, the sand and mud have once deposited in the bed of deep water, the current city lives almost its back facing the Jinhera River and the ocean. The great port of Zaiton, the most likely Chincheo of the Portuguese in China, was swallowed by the mud, the sands deposited in the river, and, before its mouth, the waters almost disappeared with the centuries.
I get a taxi and tell the driver's wife, an affable and friendly lady, I want to go, always on the bank of the river, to the mouth. It's four or five more kilometers, but the driver asserts me that there is no large port, just a village of fishermen and fishing boats. We advanced on the road. I guess a hundred trainers, all blue, made in China, moved down there. There is even a port at the mouth of the river, also with benches and restingas, with a lot of sand and mud, but a port against the sea.
I leave the taxi and advance to the pier, for fishing boats aligned next to the jetty, I enter the confusion of those who arrive with fish to discharge and to sell. Women carry heavy buckets of fish suspended at the end of bamboo sticks, others sitting in stools clean crabs and oysters, others, still, with an entredious hair that turns on the head in a safe pulling by a kind of chopsticks, packing fish Loose and seafood that sell in small lots. There are men playing Weiqi, Chinese chess, and players loudly hitting the top of makeshift tables. Some fishermen, certainly tired of the sea, are quietly watching the bullied mixed with the calm of these seaside people.
Attraven the street, the way to the village next to the side that seems to keep the past centuries. Low wooden houses, some of one townhouse, decrepit and poor. Narrow streets, quite filth, small shops, one or another house of food, almost only fish and seafood, old planted in the threshold of houses, boys jumping happy by alleys and alleys. I'm in Quangzhou, in the chincheo of five hundred. Porto and the city should be so in the sixteenth century and, when returning, I prove, that I am not in a village but in the extension of the old Quangzhou urban fabric itself. Almost guessed Fernão Mendes paint with the conversation with António de Faria, perhaps his alter ego, in a reed, anchored at the mouth of the Jinhera River, here, Chincheo, the year 1545.
The next day, visit the Quangzhou Maritime Museum, meeting the history and the many navigations for these seas of Fujian, southern China.
In the fundamental Chinese sources there is almost no reference to Portugal and the Portuguese. If we were the first to terrify these stops, in the sea connection between Europe and the Empire of the middle realized in 1513 with the arrival of Jorge Álvares to Toumen, at the current Hong Kong, Guangdong province, we were not the pioneers in the navigations along of the back and in the stay in China. In the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, Marco Polo, the Franciscan Muslims and missionaries, all journeying for the old Zaiton, deserve the honors of museum exposure, with the exposure of stones and headds recently discovered with extensive texts in Arabic and tumular stones with Christian crosses.
It is interesting to show the different types of boats that in the past have ventured into these seas, from the high-sea junctions of Admiral Zheng He (1377-1433) that with these ships navigated to Mombasa in 1433, to the stems and ships, these yes linked to a Portuguese presence. Also noteworthy is the patriotic figure of Zheng Chenggong (1624-1662) or Koxinga, who from pirate spent the national hero after expelled in 1661 the Dutch seated 38 years ago at Forte Zeelhand, Taiwan, where they controlled Formosa Island.
Even next to the Maritime Museum is another three-story building, which also works as a kind of museum, the Islamic Cultural Center where the Muslim community once resident in Zaiton/Quangzhou is honored. At the entrance we came across a statue of IBN Battuta (1304-1377), Tânger's great natural Arab traveler, just below our Algarve, who in the fourteenth century undertook a very long journey to China and left us a fabulous account of their travels, something similar to the “book of Marco Polo”. Battuta lived for a year in Zaiton, exactly 1346. In the Garden of the Cultural Center we found a cemetery for the deceased illustrious Muslims in the city and it is also worth visiting the great Qingjing mosque, originally built in 1009 by the first proselytes of Islam and that remain restored ruins, and a portico. Taking advantage of the space adjacent to Qingjing, a new mosque has just been built with money from Saudi Arabia, not too large, but witnessing a long -term and relationship, not always affectionate and peaceful, between Islam and China.
Returning to our five hundred sailors will be to remember that the Portuguese of then were not much given to visit mosques, pagodas, Buddhist temples or Taoists. But in Quangzhou/Chincheo, since the year 686, a magnificent set of pavilions and pagodas dedicated to Buddha veneration, the Kaiyuan temple. Around the year 1100, in the Song Dynasty (960-1279) was inhabited by more than a thousand monks. Today, in the temple of Kaiyuan, stand out the two beautiful stone pagodas, equal, not too high, just five floors with the walls covered by low-relevous original, all dated from the thirteenth century when Zaiton or Quangzhou was one of the big cities From China.
Few people visit Kaiyuan. The unfolding of the gaze, a little reverence for the Buddhas, remember Portugal and the Portuguese of Anthony, and dilute me in the serenity of the day.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Ba Juyi (772-846), the preclarious poet of the Tang who has known the separation of his family since he was ten years old, sent north to escape a war, and then in his unstable life as an employee ziguly in the empire occupying government posts In distant cities, he celebrated in many of his most singular poems, meetings he had.
As the innovidable impression that caused him the young woman on the bank of the Changjiang River, tangling the strings of the musical instrument that has a pear -shaped wooden base called Pipa, “Strong String Ringing Rooms,/ Soft Cords murmuring as whispered words »
About the affinity that you realized in it, wrote:
"We the two fallen in disgrace, wandering in the ends of the world, we do not ask to be old known to meet by chance."
Often only silent witness to these meetings at random or other equally dilects, only the intriguing moon glow that lasts as a faithful consolation, restoring the memory of so many happy times or the presence of lost loved ones. Memories that, in the words "flooded by the moonlight" of the Tang poet, would revive in the spirit of their readers.
As it succeeded many years later, already in the Qing Dynasty, when a Qiantang -born painter and poet, current Hangzhou, where Ba Juyi was governor, and in his west lake he had a dike that performed today, he was inspired by three characteristic circumstances of the poems of the vate.
On a sheet of album (ink and color on paper, 23.5 x 32 cm, Metmuseum) in a painting of GUO (1763-1837) it is written that it results from a request, celebrating the mourning by a dear person, remembering words by Xiangshan Jushi, the "Holly Hill Hill", a name Bai Juyi chose for himself when in his last years he lived in a part of Longmen Buddhist monastery in the fragrant hill. These words referred three situations: "The cold moon, the empty room, a person left."
Gu Luo figured in this painting, admiring the moon in an empty room, a literate sitting with his son next door, in a porch, between high Bambus and Salgueiros in an enhanced atmosphere.
In three other inspiring situations of the poet and novelist Cao Xueqin (1710-1765), the origin of vertical roll painting burying fallen flowers (paint and color on paper, 86.7 x 30.5 cm, in a private collection, can be read sale at Christies). Words that the poet attributes to his character Lin Dayu from the novel Honglou Meng, "Red Apartments Dream": "Flowers withered, flowers flutter, flowers fill the sky."
For Gou Luo these verses seemed to resonate like the haunt of Shimo, the "demon of poetry", with whom it fought Ba Juyi. Their way of resisting the distressing and unsettling kingdom of Emperor Daoguang (r. 1820-50) making absences present.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence | Study highlights China's leadership goal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/inteligencia-artificial-estudo-destaca-meta-de-lideranca-da-china/</link><description>China aims to lead the global market of artificial intelligence, “both in terms of theory and application”, seeking self-sufficiency in this domain. This is one of the conclusions of Muhammed Can's PhD Thesis, “Artificial Intelligence as a resource: an evaluation of China's mobilization and extraction strategies”, defended at the University of Minho
 
A few months before the launch of the “DeepSeek” platform in China, which revolutionized the Artificial Intelligence (AI) market in competition with the chatgPT, was defended at the University of Minho (one) a doctoral thesis that precisely concludes, the ones Steps Beijing is taking to look for global leadership in this area. The work, by Muhammed Can, calls “Artificial Intelligence as Resource: An Appraisal of China's Mobilization and Extraction Strategies” [Artificial Intelligence as a resource: an evaluation of China's mobilization and extraction strategies], and analyzes the connection of the He went to international relations, as well as the strategy that the country has adopted in this domain in recent years. The thesis, in the area of ​​political science and international relations, was defended at the school of Economics and Management of UM.
Thus, it is concluded that the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) “aims to become the world leader in both theory and AI-applications”, and some main objectives were outlined for “the process of resource mobilization and development AI ”. According to the author, they go through the “search for self-sufficiency, a view of 2015 strategy, 'Made in China 2025 ′”, as well as “economic transformation, with a view to perfectly integrating AI and automation in the national economy perfectly ”.
Moreover, the author considers that Beijing seeks to become a competitor and leader in the AI ​​area to combat advances in other markets, namely in the United States, using initiatives such as the “Digital Silk Route of China and definition efforts of patterns as the way for external validation ”.
Thus, "China's external resource extraction strategies are facilitated by the various economic mechanisms, aiming at the transfer of knowledge and talent acquisition, with the aim of filling out the resource gap with the United States."
The “techno-nationalism”
The thesis also speaks of the notion of “techno-nationalism”, linked to the area of ​​international relations, such as “the most important variable in China's AI policy”, and can also “be seen as a continuation and manifestation of the strategy of ' Two markets, two features' of the CCP ”.
With this approach, China intends to "protect the domestic market and, simultaneously, expand abroad, promote the sale of products manufactured in China and extract resources such as data, talent, know-how and many others."
In addition, “the implications of techno-nationalism also extend to foreign technological companies that operate in China”, since, “in the context of ordinary companies, China uses several barriers and takes advantage of its national legal framework as an instrument for an instrument for the strategic transfer of technology and specialized knowledge ”.
Academic work takes into account the policies and laws implemented between 2012 and 2023, concluding that after the launch of the “New Generation Artificial Intelligence Development Plan” [NAIDP, in the English acronym], in 2017, the Chinese strategy for AI Won a new direction. "The thesis shows that the pace to which the resources were mobilized increased sharply after the announcement of NAIDP in 2017", having been revealed a set of "initiatives and plans related to AI, intended for systematic mobilization of essential resources for the development of I was ”.
In the years referring to the study, “the CCP has enacted a series of data related policies and laws, including laws related to the privacy of individual data”, introducing “legal frameworks specifically related to national security, which have direct implications for governance and data regulation ”.
The author also describes the way Beijing has adopted to mobilize all resources available around AI policy, with the Council of State “promulgating comprehensive strategic plans pertinent to AI or AI -related matters - such as the action plan Triennial Internet + Artificial Intelligence ”. It is these documents that will “articulate short and long term goals and standards, serving as a course for a coordinated development in this field”. Essential resources in developing AI projects and policies are “data, algorithms and computing capacity”.
It should be noted that there is a “CCP resource mobilization strategy” that has the “approach of 'whole society' and 'whole government'”. Such "implies that all segments of society, including government institutions, private companies and individuals, may be involved in AI development effort if it is considered necessary." It is, according to the thesis, "an integrated approach that allows a more cohesive and comprehensive strategy for the mobilization of resources in the context of AI development."
After “the introduction of global strategies”, the CCP “begins the process of mobilization of resources through designated government institutions”, namely ministries, the AI ​​promotion office and the China Cyberspace administration ”.
“To improve its resource mobilization strategy, the CCP actively incorporates private actors in the AI ​​development ecosystem. By designating certain large technological companies such as AI national champions, the government not only mobilizes these companies, but also encourages them to mobilize more resources according to the state's strategic objectives ”, it reads.
Importance of local governments
Like in other fields, China realized early on that AI was an important area to invest and would have to be part of economic and political strategies. Thus, Muhammed Can's thesis "demonstrates that CCP changes in technological policy are closely aligned with the strategic environment," as the party "has realized opportunities and threats in significant global developments."
Still regarding the mobilization of resources for the development of AI, the author speaks of a process “complex and distributed instead of a singular approach, from top to bottom, led only by the CCP or the State Council”.
“Although the CCP establishes the general rules and guidelines, it actively involves a wide range of stakeholders - including companies, universities and ministerial bodies - in the mobilization process. This distributed strategy can be understood in the context of China's size, both in terms of population and geographical extension, which requires a more dispersed approach. ”
The author highlights the “preponderant role that local governments play in the development of AI” because “they function as extensions of the central authority, and their active involvement implies direct mobilization of resources”, namely at the level of algorithms and computing capacity.
"The thesis concludes that local governments have also instituted various strategies to improve policies associated with data, algorithms and computing capacity," can be read. “Some local governments took the initiative to formulate their own AI strategies before the central authorities issued official guidelines. Subsequently, these local strategies were reviewed to conform to the central directives. ” To analyze local AI policies, the author analyzed the cases of Shanghai and Shenzhen.
Moreover, the idea of ​​mobilization around the AI ​​area is attached with historical issues, as Beijing has always sought the avant-garde in the technology area, namely since the Cold War times. As read in the thesis, “China began to rely heavily on exported technology from the Soviet Union after the creation of the Popular Republic of China”, but “the restrictive strategic environment began to evolve with the historic visit of US President Richard Nixon , in 1972 ”, having represented" an invaluable opportunity for China and the US counterbalances the Soviet threat. "
Thanks to archive research, the author concludes that "China's strategic environment has moved to a partially permissive state around 1978, coinciding with the beginning of the reform and opening policies of leader Deng Xiaoping." From this year onwards, “a dramatic expansion of opportunities for the CCP in the field of technological development”. In general terms, "the concept of mobilization is intrinsically linked to the longtime vanguard role of the CCP, a role that facilitated the rapid mobilization of resources during key moments of its history."
Not on purpose, China has participated since yesterday at the Summit about AI that takes place in Paris, the AI ​​action summit, having sent Deputy Prime Minister Zhang Quoqing. In this summit, which ends today, “heads of state, researchers and technology companies that will discuss how governments should respond to rapid advances in this domain are present,” according to Lusa.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 02:52:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Analysis says that Macau is increasingly a leisure destination</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/10/turismo-analise-diz-que-macau-e-cada-vez-mais-um-destino-de-lazer/</link><description>The academics Pedro Steenhagen and Sofia Xiaoying have analyzed the Macao Tourism Industry, concluding that, increasingly, the territory is viewed as a leisure destination and not as much as a gaming land. The authors warn of the “long way to go regarding the promotion of sustainable tourism”
 
The Macao Tourism sector has changed in recent years and the visions of the tourists themselves as well, facing the territory as a place where one can walk and enjoy leisure zones, not as much as a game land. This is one of the conclusions of the “Tourism as A Driver of China's Cultural Soft Power: The Role of Macau and the Convergences Between The New Silk Road and the Greater Bay Area” [Tourism as the engine of China's Soft Power: The Role From Macao and the convergences between the new silk route and the Great Bay area], by Pedro Steenhagen, Fudan University, and Sofia Xiaoying Hou, linked to the Xi'an University of International Studies. Analysis of the tourism industry at MSAR is one of the chapters of the book “The Palgrave Handbook on China-Europe-Africa Relations”, recently edited.
Thus, it is concluded that “the perception of the image of Macau by tourists has been changing in the last 10 years, being the more and more seen as a place of leisure and vacation in general, and not specifically or purely as a game center. ” It is also added that “the image of masters as a tourist destination is in transition, and people visiting Macao have greatly valued their unique cultural attractions, including their architecture and gastronomy, the result of the mixture of Chinese and Portuguese cultures and inheritances” .
However, the authors consider that "Macau still has a long way to go regarding the promotion of effective sustainable tourism." It is understood that sustainable tourism “must fully take into account its economic, social and environmental impacts, addressing the needs of visitors, sector, environment and related communities”.
In this field, the authors highlight, quoting another author, that "Macau has made efforts to achieve good grades in these and other subjects, because the rider tourism industry has been undergoing a" silent revolution "since the beginning of the pandemic."
It is also noteworthy that, worldwide, the International Tourism Organization has created some guidelines on sustainability, creating “an important framework of sustainable tourism”. For this, “five fundamental pillars were proposed to evaluate the sustainability of the tourism sector of a state”, such as “tourism policy and governance; trade, investment, data and competitiveness; Employment, decent work and training; Reduction of poverty and social inclusion; and sustainability of natural and cultural environments ”.
The Silk Route
The academics also analyze the role of the Macao tourist sector in the strategy of “a track, a route”, noting that the territory “has been gaining a prominent role in local, regional and external policies, being an actor capable of improving the Tourism Silk Route and streamline tourism in the Great Bay region ”.
Macau is understood to make new contributions to the way China presents its culture, because “due to existing heritage and tourist products, it presents the Chinese culture to foreign visitors through a new, more diverse lens that goes beyond traditional” . Thus, tourists are allowed, “especially in the Lusophone world, [create] a better connection and understanding of the country through common historical and cultural bonds”.
With regard to the Great Bay project, it is also considered that both this region and the territory of Macao have “actively integrated the tourism development strategies in the BRI frame”, ie “Belt and Road Initiative”, English designation for “a track, a route”.
Macao has “a diverse and distinct range of tourist resources, such as the arts, history, constructions and religious traditions, gastronomy, sport, museums, among others”, and local authorities have sought, according to the authors, “Mark its tourist industry, promoting 'Tourism+' with transfronic cooperation in the scope of bri”. The idea is to “create an image of Macau as a city with diverse cultures, integrating the sectors of tourism, entertainment, culture, sports, business, conventions and exhibitions, health care, recreation, technology and big events”.
IMPROVEMENTS ON COURSE
Pedro Steenhagen and Sofia Xiaoying Hou understand that the Macao government “has been trying to improve cultural soft power and increase tourist attractiveness through product development, facilities and advertising improvement”, and “projects to improve Facilities such as hotels, restaurants, transport and digital tours. ”
The example of two digital pathways created by the Cultural Institute, namely, in 2021, “The House of the Family of Zheng Guanying” and also “Fortaleza da Guia”. Moreover, authorities have created several interactive platforms using increased virtual reality.
Despite all the efforts pointed out to the local authorities, it is understood that "masters still have an unexplored potential to reinforce cultural ties between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, and this decade may present great opportunities in this regard."
The tourist bet
In this chapter, the authors also look at the positioning of tourism in the initiative “a track, a route” by Beijing, given that “China has been increasingly paying attention to the need to expand its cultural soft power , both regional and global. ” Thus, the country "has formulated several cultural development plans associated with" a track, a route "and the area of ​​the great bay, and tourism has constantly appeared as an essential element of its global strategy.”
In the country "tourism has gained relevance, either as a means of improving international image and as a source of revenue." Only in 2018 “about 159 million visitors traveled to the country, which invested $ 155 billion in tourist infrastructure-a value behind the United States, but should become the first by 2028- since you saw the sector represents 11 percent of your total gross domestic product. ”
The authors argue that “by connecting and increasing the dynamics between BRI [Belt and Road Initiative] and the Great Bay area, with an interesting effort on the diversification of Macao's economy and strengthening its tourist sector, as well as among the objectives. National and regional, China seems to be finding a way to boost tourism and reap the fruits in terms of cultural soft power. ”
Thus, and in the long run, it is considered that the country “may not only grow the power of its narratives and culture, but also improve normative power and institutional positioning in the world scene, especially with regard to issues of governance ”.
It should be noted that the book “The Palgrave Handbook on China-Europe-Africa Relations” is edited by Yichao Li, Jorge Tavares da Silva, Carlos Rodrigues and Francisco José Leandro, from the University of Macau. The edition is in charge of Palgrave Macmillan.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:56:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese | Study points to Brazil's lack of focus in Macau and China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/07/portugues-estudo-aponta-falta-de-foco-do-brasil-em-macau-e-na-china/</link><description>“Brazilian Foreign Policy and the Quest to Promote Portuguese: Building Bridges Through Macau”, a study by João Simões, from the City of Macau, and Daniel Veras, draws attention to the need for Brazil to bet more on the advantages of Macau in the promotion of Portuguese, as well as in China
 
A study recently published in Janus magazine, from the Autonomous University of Lisbon, draws attention to the fact that Brazil is not properly enjoying the advantages that Macau can offer in the promotion of the Portuguese language, integrated into the country's foreign policy. “Brazilian Foreign Policy and the Quest to Promote Portuguese: Building Bridges Through Macau” [Brazilian foreign policy and the issue of Portuguese promotion: building bridges through Macau] is authored by João Simões, assistant professor at the City of Macau (UCM ) and Daniel Veras, professor at the Pontifical Catholic University of Minas Gerais, in Brazil.
“It is time for Brazil to have a more significant presence in Macao, not only through diplomatic channels, but also encouraging the involvement of several non -state actors, such as commerce and investment chambers, professional associations, Brazilian cultural centers, media organs , artistic and cultural foundations, among others ”, read in the article.
Thus, the authors consider that this set of partners could help Brazil “leverage the role of Macau as a generator of opportunities, something Brazil has not yet fully enjoyed”, since this “reinforced presence in Macau would allow the consolidation of Existing partnerships between Brazilian universities and mainland China ”.
In addition, at the level of students, a more robust presence in Brazil in the MSAR could “bring Chinese students closer to Portuguese from Brazilian companies, reinforcing the connection between education and the business ecosystem of the great bay”, as well as to enhance the production of "Locally adapted didactic materials to the Chinese context and, ultimately, bringing Brazil and China closer to the unique environment that Macau offers."
Based on official documents and other studies on this theme, the authors consider that, in general terms, there is “the need for Brazil effectively to take advantage of Macau's strategic position to capitalize on these opportunities”. Noteworthy among the main points of this position is the fact that, in Macao, the policy of “a country, two systems”, being “an International Porto, an autonomous customs zone” and having “a simple and reduced tax regime”, is noted among Macao. , without forgetting the role of commercial platform.
Academics also refer to the “Development Plan for Proper Economic Diversification of MSAR (2024-2028)” which “also offers opportunities, especially the promotion of key industries such as traditional Chinese medicine, the modern financial industry, state -of -the -art technology and MICE (meetings, incentives, conferences and exhibitions) and culture and sports.
A weak bet
Regarding China, Brazil is also not exploring every opportunity, João Simões and Daniel Veras highlight. "Brazil's foreign policy has actively promoted the Portuguese language in certain geographies, but has not given priority to China, despite the importance of the bilateral relationship between the two countries."
It is stated that “the Portuguese language is expanding in China, but Brazil's participation is not up to its magnitude as the largest Portuguese-speaking country in the world”. It is argued that this “discrepancy is even more surprising if we consider that China has been Brazil's largest commercial partner since 2009”.
The study highlights Victoria Almeida's position on the origin of Portuguese teachers in China, which “historically the teaching of Portuguese in China was referenced teachers from Portugal”. Thus, “only recently teachers in Brazil became more predominant”, and one of the explanations pointed out to this is the creation of the reader program, which sends teachers to teach Portuguese worldwide.
The situation of this program is mentioned in 2010, when "13 readers were selected, two of which placed in China: one in Bisu and one at Guangdong University of Foreign Studies."
Still, "Brazil's didactic materials are scarce, and although there are Chinese students who want to go to Brazil, these opportunities are limited and the costs are high."
It is understood that Brazil “could take advantage of what is happening with the teaching of Portuguese in mainland China”, because “after years of rapid growth in the number of Portuguese apprentices, we are now in an investment phase in the so-called area studies. or regional ”. Thus, “Brazilian higher education and research institutions can contribute to the reinforcement of China's area studies on Lusophone and Latin America countries, through the investigation and analysis of social, economic, political and cultural dynamics of the target regions ”, Especially given the initiative“ a track, a route ”, is stressed by the authors.
Portugal does better
The study denotes that, despite the various exchanges between Brazilian and Chinese higher education, the truth is that “many more Chinese students return from exchanges in Portugal, whose best universities offer exchanges with Chinese students”, considering that “it will take a long time until that Brazil builds a teaching culture in China ”.
Thus, “compared to Brazil, Portugal has a greater framing in the teaching of Portuguese abroad”, providing “Teaching Programs and Scholarships for Chinese Students”, Master's and PhD level, without forgetting “Partnership with the Camões Institute ”. “Portugal also facilitates the acquisition of titles, as well as promoting the translation of Portuguese novels in China. On the other hand, Brazil does not make such a structured effort. As a result, currently, most Chinese Portuguese-speaking students tend to use European Portuguese as a base or at least as a reference, ”he says.
Thus, João Simões and Daniel Veras consider that “Brazil can capitalize on the current context, which encompasses several favorable factors, to adopt a more collaborative approach to the promotion of Portuguese language in China”.
The study states that, currently, Portuguese is spoken by more than 264 million people on five continents, and this number is expected to rise to nearly 400 million people in 2050, with “the African continent responsible for the largest increase”, reinforcing The preponderance of Portuguese as one of the most spoken languages ​​in the southern hemisphere. In addition, Portuguese is an official or work language in 32 international organizations.
With the arrival of Lula da Silva to the presidency of Brazil for the second time, the authors consider that he “has tried an approach to China”, namely in the commitment to join the initiative “a track, a route” and the appointment “of a representative permanent at the Macao Forum ”. The academics cite another author's idea regarding the existence of “distrust and reserve that Brazil has shown over the years in relation to the Macao Forum”.
Greater involvement “can help to guarantee China access to vital resources and markets in Brazil and Africa, potentially contributing to China's food and internal energy security” as well as enhancing Macau as a “cultural channel between China and the World Lusophone ”.
However, “although there is political will and a favorable environment in Macao, more concerted efforts will be needed by Brazil to materialize these opportunities,” is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 01:48:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Reluctant government in legislating vital will</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/estudo-governo-relutante-em-legislar-testamento-vital/</link><description>A study by Man Teng Iong, professor at the Faculty of Law of the University of Macao, and Vera Lúcia Raposo draws attention to the absence of the “anticipated directive of will”, or vital will, of the legal system of masters. The document allows a person to decide previously whether or not to receive medical treatments in the terminal phase of life
 
For several years in Portugal any citizen can sign an Early Directive of Will (DAV), also known as the Vital Testament, which allows the conscious decision on the type of medical treatments to receive in a given health context. Being far from constituting a legal form of euthanasia, the document allows to know the patient's will when he, for health reasons, cannot do so.
In Macao, the DAV is not legislated and the authorities have revealed signs of reluctance to advance in the process. This is what the study concludes “Advance Directives in Macao: Not Legally Recognissed, but. . . ” [DAV in Macao: No legal recognition, but… ”, signed by Man Teng Iong, professor at the University of Macao Law School (one), and Vera Lúcia Raposo, former director of the same faculty and currently a teacher at the Faculty of Law from the New University of Lisbon. The study was recently published by Cambridge University Press, although it was the theme of Man Teng Iong's master's thesis defended a few years ago.
The authors analyze the legal framework of the issue in Macao, concluding that “to date, the Macao Executive assumed a precautionary attitude towards the DAV, accepting (or tolerating) these instruments, but not investigating this subject with the necessary force” .
"It has been reported that, due to the aging of the population of Macao, and in the light of the adoption of DAV legislation in the last twenty years in countries such as the United States, Australia, Canada and Singapore, the executive recognized the need to legislate DAV." , it is added.
The authors indicate that local authorities even recognize the positive factors of accessing this type of legal document. “Such legal instruments will not only increase quality of life and protect patients' dignity at the end of their lives, but also reduce unnecessary medical expenses. On December 3, 2019, Health Services (SS), and the sub -entity of the Life Science Ethics Committee, introduced the 'guidelines and future policy of the DAV' in Macao, agreeing to legitimize [a matter]. However, despite the agreement around the implementation of DAV, the executive insists on maintaining a preliminary discussions around DAV. ”
Thus, the authors consider that "hesitation may reflect the fear of the [SS] in facing difficulties and controversies around the plans for its implementation."
Consensus as an argument
The authors point out that the “barriers to the implementation” of the DAV legal framework in Macao arise “from a low conscience from the public in the face of DAV legislation and the possibility of patients can change the way of facing the end of life, well as the arrangement of the patient's family members to fulfill the patient's wishes ”.
The study points out that the SS have always argued that “an extensive and profound action of sensitization and education has been done with the public, in academic, social and legal areas whenever necessary, and that the law that regulates DAV can only be implemented later obtained the consensus of all sectors ”.
However, the study states that “it is possible to argue that the position of the executive lacks proper justification”, because “this type of consensus invoked to postpone the regulation of DAV is not possible to achieve, due to the multiplicity of legal, ethical visions and even religious about matter ”. In addition, the authors point out that "even if such a consensus could be achieved, the executive did not take the necessary steps to encourage or facilitate discussion, or awareness, with the population."
Data on a study made about the notions of the population of Macao on the subject are referred to, concluding that "the lack of information about the DAV was the main determining factor in the decision of people to make the DAV."
"The study also found that 73.6 percent of the sample (724 people) were willing to complete a DAV if the document had legal recognition."
Social and political “resistance”
Thus, the study's authors warn of the existence of “a great resistance - from certain groups of residents of Macao and the Executive - for the implementation of adequate DAV regulation”. "A possible reason for this hesitation is to the fear that formally legislating DAV can lead to euthanasia, a forbidden practice in Macau, even if the two situations are clearly different," the authors say, who understand to be "imperative that the executive regulates the DAV ”.
At this specific point, a new law should “clarify some legal aspects, such as the requirements for the [DAV] and to be legally operational”, ensuring the patient's decision autonomy and ensuring “a more appropriate solution from the point of view of the point of view human rights ”.
The authors draw attention to the influence of Portuguese law of 2012 on the DAV legislation in Macao, drawing attention to the fact that DAV have a greater compatibility with what is currently in the local Civil Code.
However, legislating the DAV also causes a cultural discussion, is pointed out. “It is unclear whether DAV regulation would be in agreement with the widespread values ​​of the predominant Chinese community, which still has a great connection to the family. More studies are needed to clarify this and other subjects, since, for example, there are no data on numbers estimates and implementation of DAV in the jurisdiction of Macao ”, and there is“ an urgent need for further investigations that exploit perspectives of the doctors around the DAV ”.
The case of the Kiang Wu Hospital, which at the “The Hospice &amp; Palliative Care Center” palliative care center provides treatment for cancer terminal patients. However, before the admission of these patients, the signing of the document “Consent for the Hospice &amp; Palliative Care Center” is required, a kind of consent that is mostly signed by family members and not by the patient himself. In addition, "it is not an authorization document by patients, or not, of medical procedures, but an acceptance of hospital terms and conditions."
What current law allows
In general terms, DAV in Macau have some legal framework, namely in the Civil Code, although they are not legislated with their own law. The authors conclude, however, that "there is some uncertainty about to what extent DAV would be effective, in particular given that doctors tend to reject any document that rejects a support and life maintenance treatment."
“In Macau the discussion around the DAV is almost nonexistent. Without a clear and transparent debate that includes specialists and studies with legal arguments, there will be no legal developments related to the nature, content and use of DAV in the near future, ”he describes.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 23:58:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese New Year | Tourism and trips boosted consumption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/ano-novo-chines-turismo-e-viagens-impulsionaram-consumo/</link><description>Arrived to the end of Chinese New Year's holidays, official numbers do not lie: China has crossed an intense consumption period, especially related to travel and tourism. Between January 28 and this Tuesday, some destinations in the country broke records of visitors
 
It is at the beginning of each year that the economy expects the one of the high moments for tourism and consumption in China. The Chinese New Year represents not only a moment of family life, but also the opportunity for many Chinese to travel. This year, to celebrate the year of the serpent, millions of people traveled internally and also out of the country between January 28 and Tuesday, and according to Xinhua the numbers are impressive with regard to purchases or number of visitors in some Destinations.
The Altay City Hall, in the Xinjiang Autonomous Region, is referred to as one of the great ski destinations in the country, having received between January 28 and 31 191,900 visitors, a tourist flow that generated 225 million yuan in revenues.
The agency points out that "skiing has definitely became the most popular activity in Altay during the holidays," leading to "a record number of practitioners, more than 10,000, to visit Jiangjunshan's ski resort on February 2". This represented "an increase of 23 percent over the previous year."
The Altay zone is famous for registering between 170 and 180 days of snow per year, and in the mountainous areas the average snow depth reaches between one and two meters.
Another region of China that reached considerable numbers on the Chinese New Year holidays was Yangshuo County in the Autonomous Guangxi Zhuang region, thanks "to unique natural landscapes and rich cultural activities." Between January 28 and 30, this area received about 410,600 tourists, generating tourist revenues of 589 million Yuan.
In turn, Lhasa (in Tibet) also registered an increase in the number of visitors. Between January 28 and Monday, the city received 1.95 million tourists, representing an increase of 20.6 percent over the previous year, and found in tourist revenues almost 1.76 billion Yuan. This is an increase of 14.75 percent compared to the previous year, according to the Lhasa Municipal Culture and Tourism Office.
Positive data from agencies
Also according to Xinhua, the Chinese New Year's numbers also revealed themselves on travel reserve platforms. In the case of Fliggy, one of the main online agencies, "an increase in reserves, especially for cities such as Shanghai, Beijing and Guangzhou" was recorded. On the other hand, "international travel orders have increased significantly, with international cruise reserves increasing more than six times compared to the previous year."
Regarding air traffic, Shanghai Airport Group reported that passenger traffic on Sunday has reached a new historic record of 404,000 people, with Pudong Airport in Shanghai, to record 259,000 passengers and Hongqiao Airport 145,000 passengers.
There was also a “reinforced coordination of the services of metro, buses and taxis to ensure transport without problems” with the arrival of the end of the holidays, said the group.
On Monday, China State Railway Group Co., Ltd. recorded “a historic milestone” as they were transported on all railways a total of 16.45 million people. This is the “largest passenger traffic in a single day in the history of the Spring Festival Race”.
Only this Tuesday, the last day of the holidays, will have traveled 16.9 million passengers, a number that highlights “even more the peak of travel, since hundreds of millions of people returned to their destinations after family meetings” .
Comes and Babies
As far as tourism is concerned, it was found “a growing number of people who sought to know the heritage of China, motivated by the registration of the Spring Festival in the representative list of UNESCO's Immaterial Cultural Heritage, in December 2024”, indicates the state agency.
Data from the Ministry of Commerce show that sales in major retail and restoration companies throughout China, during the first four days of holidays, increased 5.4 percent compared to the same period last year.
There was an increase in consumption of imported food and drinks, such as lobsters, beer and wine. "Due to increased demand during the Spring Festival, our company's imports increased almost 50 percent last month," said Yang Xinyu, who represents a company in the Guangzhou -based international supply chain.
Since January that the customs authorities of Guangzhou Baiyun International Airport have enlarged the importation of food and crab products, 31.8 percent compared to 2024, translated the total of 14.3 million Yuan.
Many online shopping
And if the Chinese New Year is synonymous with family reunion, the holidays were once again a time for online shopping. Meituan, one of the country's leading electronic service platforms, has recorded an “impressive increase” of 300 percent over the previous year in online reserves for Lunar New Year's Eve.
It should be noted that “group orders for packages with the theme 'intangible cultural heritage' have increased more than 12 times since January, year after year, reflecting the growing interest of consumers in cultural experiences.”
Sun Jiashan, an associate researcher at the Central Academy of Culture and Tourism Administration, said, according to Xinhua, a change in consumer behavior, especially by young people and families. "Young families are increasingly becoming the driving force of consumption, with a tendency for diverse, high quality and culturally rich experiences," he said.
Meituan Travel data corroborates the analyst's observation that young people increasingly choose to celebrate the Spring Festival in smaller cities, plunging into intangible cultural heritage and historical landmarks.
The increase in tourism and cultural consumption, from equity experiences to successful films, indicate a growing demand for traditional and contemporary cultural activities. "This trend has also led to increased demand for cultural and tourist products and services, giving rise to the introduction of new models and business formats that adapt better to contemporary cultural consumption standards," Sun said, highlighting the potential of the Chinese consumer market and the internal driving forces of the economy.
But not only shopping was made this Chinese New Year, as "the country's film industry proved to be one of the biggest winners during the spring festival's consumer wave." Between January 29 and February 3, the ticket daily revenues exceeded billion yuan for six consecutive days, raising the ticket offices of this year's Spring Festival to 8.02 billion yuans,
According to China's movie administration data, China's total box office on this year's holidays, including real-time pre-sale, exceeded ten billion Yuan.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Denmark | PM Refusal Sell Grolândia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/04/dinamarca-pm-recusa-vender-gronelandia/</link><description>Denmark Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen was yesterday available to dialogue with the United States over Granelândia, stressing that the autonomous territory “is not for sale”.
"We have been very clear: we all have to respect the sovereignty of all states in the world - and Granelândia is today a part of the Denmark Kingdom - it is not on sale," he said. The Danish leader spoke at the entrance of the first EU leaders' retreat, an initiative created by European Council President António Costa for more informal debates.
I totally agree with Americans that the region of the far north, the Arctic region, is increasingly important when we talk about defense and security and dissuasion, and it is possible to find a way to ensure a stronger [United States] footprint in Granelândia, where they are already, ”said Mette Frederiksen.
The head of the Copenhagen government also recalled that Danish troops fought alongside the US for many decades. US President Donald Trump has claimed greater access to the Arctic and expressed the interest of acquiring Granelândia, an autonomous territory managed by Denmark.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 01:22:03</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Trump will impose rates on “very soon” European products</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/04/eua-trump-vai-impor-taxas-sobre-produtos-europeus-muito-em-breve/</link><description>United States President Donald Trump said European products will be subject to “very soon” customs rates following the imposition of tariffs on the importation of products from Canada, Mexico and China.
“They are really enjoying us, we have a $ 300 billion deficit. They do not take our cars or our agricultural products, practically nothing, and we all bought millions of cars, huge levels of agricultural products, ”he said on Sunday to the press.
The European Union lamented on the same day the increase in customs rates by the United States of America about products from Canada, Mexico and China, and said it will retaliate strongly if it is targeted by unfair tariffs.
"The EU firmly believes that low customs rights promote economic growth and stability," the European Commission in a statement said through which he considered the imposition of more US tariffs as "harmful to all parties."
If the European bloc is also the target of these measures, the community executive will “retaliate strongly”. Donald Trump signed on Saturday the executive order to apply customs rates to products from Canada, Mexico and China.
The signature, which officializes the decision that had already been announced, determines the imposition of 10 percent rates to China, 25 percent to Mexico and 25 percent to Canada, except in Canadian oil, which will have a tariff of 10 by one hundred.
Trump had threatened the imposition of tariffs to ensure greater cooperation from countries to prevent illegal immigration and the smuggling of chemicals such as Fentanil, an opioid that is causing important additions in the United States. The three countries promise to take action.
Sacrifice (dis) necessary
In the case of the European Union, a decision has not yet been made, but the concern is general and France defended on Sunday a "scathing response" of Europe in the face of threats of new customs tariffs by the US President.
Trump admitted that the new rates can cause suffering to the American people, but has ensured that "everything will be worth it" because it will "make America big again."
“Will there be suffering? Yes, maybe (and maybe not). But let's make America big again, and everything will be worth it, ”wrote Donald Trump, in capital letters, in the profile of the social network he founded, the Social Truth, quoted by the France-Presse news agency.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 01:18:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Circulation | Deputy alerts to HK vehicle abuse</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/circulacao-deputado-alerta-para-abusos-de-veiculos-de-hk/</link><description>Hong Kong Deputy Adriano Ho warned that the Hong Kong vehicle wate system in Macau is being abused. The complaint was filed through a Facebook post, where the deputy speaks of forgery of information.
“I recently received many complaints that the system is being abused. After people have detected the gaps that exist in the system began to emerge agencies that charge money to falsify the information, to simulate that customers have calls with Macau, ”wrote the deputy. According to Hong Kong regulations, the quotas are attributed to those who show you have connections with the masters.
“Some people have created ghost companies to which quotas were attributed, and then sold these companies to profit from Quota. This causes people with business in Hong Kong and Macau, or work in Macau, have difficulty accessing the quotas, which distorts the initial objective of the program, ”he added.
For this reason, also Edmund Ho's nephew has asked Hong Kong's transportation and logistics authorities to review and reform the quota system and eliminate gaps, as well as asking data on the effective use of the quotas.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:20:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Post Office | Announced Retoma of Service for the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/correios-anunciada-retoma-de-servico-para-os-eua/</link><description>Macao Post Office resumed sending small packages and orders to the United States, but warned that new suspensions cannot be excluded due to US postal service policies
 
The Post Office of Macao and Hong Kong announced yesterday the resumption of sending small packages and orders to the United States after five days of suspension. In a statement, the Post Office of Macao (CTT) announced that they will accept again, from February 11, “all mail objects (…) for the United States”.
In the same message as the Macao Post and Telecommunications Directorate Directorate, CTT recalled that the suspension "may have originated a correspondence, which will possibly result in delays in the delivery of shipments to the US."
"Additionally, the possibility of any changes in the policies of US postal services [USPS) cannot be excluded at any time," the company warned.
The Macao Post Office message was preceded by one of Hong Kong's counterpart, in which they said they had been “formally notified” by the US Postal Service that US authorities “currently do not impose additional fees on postal articles. with commodity ”.
On January 5, the company said it had been notified by USPS that it could only send packages or orders that customers had registered with customs and the protection of US borders (CBP).
The registration would require “the necessary import documents and the payment of fees made through a customs dispatcher,” added the Hong Kong Post Office. After the suspension of shipping, the company “continued to negotiate” with USPS and “can temporarily resume” the postal service for the United States.
Temporary suspensions
On February 4, USPS announced that it would temporarily stop accepting orders from China and Hong Kong (without any reference to Macao) “up to new order”.
But hours later, USPS reversed the decision without justifying, just stating that it was going to work with the CBP to implement a collection process for the new rates imposed on Chinese goods in order to avoid interruptions in delivery.
The new US President Donald Trump increased customs rates on China's imports at 10 percent after retreating in the plans to charge Canada and Mexico.
The vast majority of goods sent from China arrive outside the mail system, but Trump's order specifically eliminated a tariff exemption for low -value products, purchased directly by consumers and sent through postal service.
This exemption covered articles of less than US $ 800. The USPS measurement could block or delay orders made through Chinese e -commerce platforms Shein and Temu.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>IAS | In four years subsidies were assigned to 80 caregivers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/ias-em-quatro-anos-foram-atribuidos-subsidios-a-80-cuidadores/</link><description>From the implementation of the Subsidy for Caregivers, in December 2020, until the end of 2024, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) received 111 requests for cases of people with an unconnected, severe or deep degree intellectual disabilities.
From this universe, 80 requests met the assignment requirements, IAS President Hon Wai said in response to a written interpellation of Mrs Song Pek Kei. In the current way, the caregiver allowance is intended for low-performance families.
Since the start of the pilot project, IAS has widened the range of recipients of support, starting with permanent bedrooms who cannot rise or sit without help and with intellectual disabilities, without grade attributed, severe or deep. Later, it was extended to autistic people and people with motor disabilities. Three years after the pilot project began, the caregiver allowance was permanent.
In Macao there are 13 social equipment that welcomes disabled people, with about 1,060 vacancies, volume that Hon Wai considers “to satisfy the needs of the services concerned”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:11:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Minimum Wage | Au Kam San criticized reduced value</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/salario-minimo-au-kam-san-criticou-valor-reduzido/</link><description>Former Deputy Au Kam San considers that the minimum wage value is too low and that nothing justifies that it is below the values ​​practiced in Taiwan (46.53 patacas) or Hong Kong (41.25 patacas). This is how the Democrat reacted to Forbes magazine's recent ranking on the richest countries and regions in the world. The MSAR arises secondly on the list with the Gross Domestic Product Per capita of 134,140 US dollars.
“Macao is a rich city, but the minimum wage per hour is only 34 patacas, while the minimum wage per month is 7,072 patacas. We look at Luxembourg, who took first place in the ranking, and not only his wealth is the highest in the world, but the minimum wage is also the highest in the world, with 2,500 euros monthly [20,705 patacas], ” If in a public publication on Facebook.
The former deputy recalled that during his career in the Legislative Assembly, he participated in the preparation of the minimum wage law and the process was difficult. “It has dragged on for many years, before the legislation was approved, and the starting salary was only 30 patacas per hour. Since 2016 until now, it has only been increased to 34 patacas per hour, in a period of nine years, and this is shameful, ”he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:09:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching | LAM expects universities to be “battlefields”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/ensino-o-lam-espera-que-universidades-sejam-campos-de-batalha/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture wants educational institutions to advance with the integration of education, science and technology, while developing a set of qualified frameworks internationally recognition
 
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture has asked local higher education institutions to take over as “battlefields”, following President Xi Jinping's guidelines in attracting internationally known qualified frames. The request was left at a meeting between the ruler and the representatives of local universities.
According to the government, the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, approached with universities the development of Macao "as a place of aggregation of international qualified pictures." LAM indicated to the present that Macau has to follow Xi Jinping's “important discourse” and that it should “promote the integrated development of education, science and technology, as well as qualified pictures”, as well as “vigorously introduce and cultivate several Types of qualified frames and create a place of aggregation of international qualified frames.
The secretary also stated that the discourse is as "a clear direction for Macao's work on education, science and technology, as well as for qualified paintings, defining objectives, channels and the main areas of action."
LAM also mentioned higher education institutions play a crucial role in the “aggregation of international qualified staff” and which should be constituted as “the most important platforms and the main battlefields”.
Nation
During the meeting with the representatives of local universities, LAM said it hoped the government and educational institutions work “together to firmly implement the spirit of President XI's Directive and do a good job in higher education, the construction of platforms scientific research and internationalization of teaching staff ”.
The official also asked universities to continue to "fully enjoy Macau's unique advantage of" one country, two systems "and their role as a exchange platform." In this way the leader believes that Macau can become "in a place of aggregation of international qualified staff, contributing to the strengths of Macao to the construction of a strong nation."
The University of Macao was represented by Rector Song Yonghua, the Macao Management Institute by President Samuel Tong Kai Chung, Macao Polytechnic University, Rector Marcus Imba Kei, the University of Tourism of Macao by Dean Fanny Vong Chuk Kwan, the Macao Security Forces School by Director Wong Chi Fai, Macao University of Science and Technology by Rector Joseph Hun-Wei Lee, the University of Macao City by Rector Liu Jun, the University of St. Joseph by Vice Rector Zhang Shuguang, and the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute of Macao, by President Van Iat Kio.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:07:35</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | Chan iek lap admits to leave hemiciclo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/al-chan-iek-lap-admite-deixar-hemiciclo/</link><description>Elected by the indirect way, Deputy Chan Iek Lap admitted yesterday to journalists who is fulfilling the one who will be his last term in the hemiciclo. The doctor first entered the Hemiciclo in 2013, remaining until this year.
To journalists, the 68 -year -old explained that with the end of his term, he will devote more time to his activities. In 2021, the last time he was elected by the Indirect Road, Chan Iek Lap in third place joined the list “Union of Professional Interests of Macao”, which also had deputies and entrepreneurs Chui Sai Cheong and Vong Hin Fai.
Elections | Wong Kit Cheng wants more women in al
Wong Kit Cheng expects the composition of the next legislature to bring more deputies to the Legislative Assembly to defend women's rights and work for the development of MSAR, calling for more young and women political discussion.
The deputy who represents the General Association of Macao Women, in conjunction with Deputy Ma Io Fong, again referred to the low birth rate as a problem to solve, namely through the increase of maternity leave and birth allowance. However, to change the maternity leave it will be necessary to move the Labor Relations Law, which the deputy regrets does not know advances, not even in the level of public consultations.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Press | Kou Hoi in did not make statements at l lunch</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/imprensa-kou-hoi-in-nao-prestou-declaracoes-no-almoco-da-al/</link><description>As president of the Legislative Assembly, Kou Hoi in broke with the tradition of lunch with the media to answer the journalists' questions. Yesterday, the entrepreneur again maintained his posture adopted, and although he made the traditional speech was not available to be questioned.
This is a stance that contrasts much contrasts with the one adopted by Ho Iat SENG, as president of the Legislative Assembly, which reserved almost half an hour to answer the questions raised by the media.
All About Macau | Barrado newspaper at the entrance
In the image of the posture adopted by the Public Administration and the Executive Bodies, the Chinese language newspaper All About Macau was again prevented from participating in the events for the media, this time by the Legislative Assembly. According to the report made by the publication, contrary to what happened in previous years, the publication was not invited to the event, despite having made at least two contacts with the organizers. Yesterday, during the event, the journalists asked for access to the room, but were told that there were no places available.
However, inland there were at least 30 places for occupying. As happened at other official events, authorities prevent the access of All About Macau journalists claiming that they are a monthly media body, while allowing the access of other media, in languages ​​other than officers, with the same periodicity. Kou Hoi In was approached on the subject to leave the event, but was silent, while accelerating the step to leave the place.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 03:03:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Year of the Serpent and Ophiússa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/ano-da-serpente-e-ofiussa/</link><description>Lunar, the Chinese calendar leaves no room for doubt that by conquering the world printed on our lives dormant archetypes and striking characteristics where we all gain in this vast mat of cultures and civilizations. For some time we have also celebrated this extremely beautiful and initiatory cycle as if we were incorporated a rite into those known and became accomplices and therefore more fraternal.
It starts at the first free moon of the Gregorian calendar approved by China in 1912, and as a lunar calendar is about his bestiary, he will reign for a year to the East, while we, we are still demarcating the Astral Code in our month where the pointer runs in solar cycle. However, there is a new year a call for our roots ancestors in a fascinating and strange symbology, which as for the tangible part, must know how to differentiate a snake from a snake.
Ophiússa or the land of the snakes! - Well, this was called by the Greeks in very remote time the current Portuguese territory, the land of the 'ofis', a mountainous people who lived north going to Galicia and probably also located at the mouth of the rivers (mouth of OFIR).
For the Greeks this place was in the unknown sea, but Ulysses, the brave hero, was not frightened by the maritime vastness, and it is believed that it landed on these backs, and both he and his men were terrified by the beauty of these lands, where he believes he believes , a queen of Indomitual will -looking, fascinating, seductive, and extremely affable for those who discovered her kingdom from distant extremities, still seems like a kind of Urizen when from the hills where she is Lisbon, said: she said: "It's me queen for all eternity." But, often, the fascinating ones also fall in love, who, seeing Ulysses, had fallen into the trap of his magnetic load itself. Ulysses, who now at a distance seems to have been a difficult man, refused her, but not first of all for the love of the most beautiful place in the world, having named it Ulisseia, in the serpent territory, the magnificent.
Much later when Manueline impeached, we would recover this legendary caps on winged -up -rushes, wires that descend, circles and sinuosities, in fact finding one of the most eloquent artistic manifestations that pervaded our gaze and would never subjugate us to a straight line.
The perfusion of all this cast to stand with the weights that a certain horizontality transports, perhaps it was, and it is, the derivation of the serpent that in us had not exhausted (which in the background we were always very little gothic). In the psychic modality, it was diabolical, and we can still feel inertia, the lack of criterion that devours everything that goes out of its way, and this hideous peace of those who believe hypnotic, characteristics of demons to “grab the sewing” with pupil Sagaz for a strange crane that is not subservience but an incredible and tenacious producer of "poisons".
Also the octagonal architecture that was so dear to us brings us to the Mercury stick and its two intertwined snakes that when forming countless eights almost flow into our very illustrious imperfect chapels. The reason for being named like this, perhaps this strange world without vickers, ceilings and tiles, which brings us to an anti-Foguet movement and an impression that is inscribed in the mandala of infinity always in a circle, That after all, everything in the vast universe seems serpentant. As for us, as we are dubious it does not yet mean being evil, we fit the duality and mutability of our perceptions, but what was once proposed to us was a triangulation that overcome the reducing definition of a certain binary concept.
"Ophis" in Greek, but also the rod of Moses indicates that a watertight object and law can be converted into something else when it turns into flexibility and overcoming. Serpents like milk, and there are beautiful passages of what they respond to the calling of full terrinas, like those that Ernst Junger in the "marble cliffs" described us, saying that they had a burning solar symbol.
Who has never seen her before you? Caleidoscopic… fascinating… improper but never banal. After all, it was not even the one who killed Jesus, it is only made him a company. Who killed him were the men.
A great year for the world.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Australia interdicts social networks to children under 16 (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/australia-interdita-redes-sociais-a-menores-de-16-anos-ii/</link><description>Last week, we mentioned that the Australian Parliament approved the amendment to the “Internet Security Law (minimum age for access to social networks) on November 28, 2024, interdicting access from under 16 to most networks. The content of the law is simple, but from the point of view of its operation, there are several issues that deserve to be debated.
First of all, Australia is not the first country to legislate this matter. In Europe, many countries have already restricted children's access to social networks. The established minimum age varies from country to country, but usually between 13 and 17 years old.
Secondly, in Florida, the United States, the restriction of access from children under 13 to social networks triggered a process by limiting freedom of expression. The same may happen in Australia after the implementation of the new law and this will be a risk that the Australian government will have to run.
Third, when one identifies a minor that transgresses the law, only the company that manages the social network is punished. The minor and parents are not considered responsible. In this sense, the law fails as a disciplinary. This approach can lead to conflicts around the assignment of liability when it comes into force. Some question whether this means to blame for social networks, ignoring the pedagogical responsibilities of families.
There may be two reasons why the new law does not criminally responsible for infrastructors. First, as social networks are very popular, people generally use them, and those under 16 are easily influenced. Second, laws may predict different minimum ages for infrastructors to assume criminal liability. In Australia, the age of criminal liability is between 10 and 14 years, which means that certain transgressors aged between 10 and 14 may assume a certain degree of criminal responsibility. The new law increases the age of criminality in two years, apparently to allow users under 16 to avoid being held responsible and to prevent more children from breaking the law due to their tender age. But, on the other hand, if we only punish social networking companies that provide the tools for children to violate the law, the responsibility will only fall into these companies? Isn't this a way to put the car ahead of the oxen?
In Australia, there is a new law in force to which social networking companies have to obey. However, in countries where there is no restrictions on the use of social networks by children, personal technology companies may consider establishing some restrictions to deny minors access to these networks. For example, Tiktok, Facebook and Snapchat have stipulated the minimum age of 13 years for their users. The restrictions imposed by these companies can benefit their image and reduce criticism from children's access permission to networks. Industry self-regulation is an effective way to reduce the impact of social networks on children.
Fourthly, the new law requires social networking companies to take measures to verify the age of users. There are currently three viable methods of age verification: biometric analysis, online activities verification and identity document verification. Biometric analysis implies that users send a photo to the platform for the software to determine their age. It is not known if the photo will be eliminated after the age determination process is completed. Online activity verification requires users to provide their email account and, from there, an analysis will be based on the accounts related to the account. Verification of identity documents is another possibility of determining the age of users.
It is unlikely to be accurately evaluated whether a user is over 16 years old based on photos or based on his online activity. However, the new law clearly stipulates that users cannot carry identity documents on social network companies' platforms, which will make the process of determining their age difficult. If the three age determination methods have problems, it is questionable that the new law can be implemented without startles.
No wonder the goal, the mother company of Alphabet's Google, Facebook and Instagram, has declared in a presentation in the Australian parliament that expects the new law to be postponed until the age test will be completed. A goal spokesman said Facebook respects Australian law, but is concerned about the process in which they have rushed to pass legislation to ensure an age of access to social networks, but ignoring the opinions of others.
Next week we continue our analysis.

Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the School of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Blog: http://blog.xuite.net/legalpublications/hkblog
Email: LegalpublicationSreaders@yahoo.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 03:58:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The (in) justice we have</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/10/a-in-justica-que-temos/</link><description>For many decades we met a judge, we had studied together, who was homosexual. A magistrate of excellence, from professional virtuosity to all the introvert evidence, has never taken any less dignified attitude towards his subordinates and even severely condemned an admittedly homosexual individual who had sexually abused a minor. At that time it was a scandal if it came to know that the judge was homosexual and would certainly be expelled from the judiciary. One day he confessed to me that he had a single and secret companion almost his age. I pretended that I did not give importance to the outburst and always had the ease of obtaining important information about legal proceedings that the judge was kind to provide me as a journalist. My comrades were surprised how I had such credible court sources and even asked the origin. Obviously they never got any response on my part.
This comes by justice that in Portugal we have judges and judges of very high degree of competence, seriousness and independence. Absolutely incorruptible. And we have others who simply fulfill their mission with the aim of obtaining the greatest possible peculio. They are corrupt, they are maneuvered by the Lobis of Powerful Lawyers' offices and, unfortunately, if they are homosexuals take positions of a deplorable degree. They reach the point of warning the defendant suspected of domestic violence or sexual abuse of minors in order to know how much possible amounts can pay if they are acquitted at the time of trial. These facts have happened over decades. Before and after the military coup of April 25, 1974. Recently, we all were aware of the shameful attitude of Judge Rangel who was to the point of handing over to a trainee lawyer to write the judgments that were distributed to him. These judgments, which rangel or neither read or only provided the intern the indications that he was in. As it would have to happen, Rangel was expelled from the judiciary.
Justice in Portugal has always been led by absurd corporatism, where no sovereignty organ had the power to intervene in structural change. Justice in Portugal these days,-not to mention the past where a trainee judge was left to obtain his promotion was seen by a clerk to have oral sex to a senior judge in his office-it is manifestly a justice for very rich citizens. No poor man has any chance of paying a lawyer so that his defense is worthy and fair. Of course we know the existence of unofficial defenders, who most often are little interested in the processes concerned, but justice that there are exceptions. We, from our own experience, had an exceptional unofficial defender, of a peculiar competence that dedicated themselves to the process as if they were receiving a lot of money.
Last week, the country was aware of a scandal related to a judge accused of paying poor minors for sex. A jubilant magistrate from the Azores paid 25 euros to minors each time he had sex. There is no memory that a magistrate was accused and investigated by the court of a crime allegedly of such seriousness. A man reported that the judge attracted minors for sex with ice cream and pizza and that the judge resorted to the prostitution of minors paying to have oral sex after approaching the minors on the street and who lived in precarious conditions. The judge will be tried for resorting to minor prostitutes. The conclusions of a case of this gravity can lead the Portuguese to think what would have been this judge's career. Would there have been maneuvered sentences in exchange for homosexual sex? Had the magistrate received amounts of money when they appeared in the bar of the defendants accused of violation of minors? Will the magistrate misrepresented judgments that accused sexual violators of minors? Everything can be considered in the face of ignoble behavior that came to public by a jubilated judge.
We are waiting for the best Portuguese magazine that addresses all social and judicial problems, “Justice with A”, directed by a great prestigious judge, will address this theme in a next edition. It turns out that the theme that involves incompetent, corrupt and now pedophiles cannot be unpunished and should be the target of the biggest debate on the part of society. Jubilated Judge Manuel Mota Botelho is now being tried for 16 crimes of resorting to the prostitution of minors. The crimes will have occurred between 2019 and 2023 in São Miguel, in the Azores. The Jubilee Judge is renovated but ended his career as Judge Counselor of the Court of Auditors, and this institution decided to call the Permanent Commission to analyze the situation of the Azorean Councilor accused of abusing six minors over four years. The Permanent Commission has the responsibility to establish disciplinary proceedings and apply sanctions.
It has long been asking for a structural reform of justice in the political sphere and nothing has been done. Corporatism remains a reality and the country is fed up with processing processes that take more than a decade to be completed, especially when it comes to "important" citizens. The important thing in court is that the day the laws are developed by honest people, the court will be done.</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 01:21:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao in 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/07/macau-em-2025/</link><description>After taking office as a sixth chief executive of Macao, Sam Hou Fai announced that in the next five years he would strive to realize the four great visions: "Macau founded in the rule of law, dynamic, cultural and happy." Will these four views be really realized in 2025, the first year of the new Government of MSAR?
To achieve these four objectives, RAE's sixth government has to actively engage with patriotic organizations for communication and exchange purposes, and take government officials to Beijing to listen to Xia Baolong's instructions, the Director of the Work Office Hong Kong and Macao from the Communist Party Central Committee of China and the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office with the Council of State. All of this will be necessary to prepare the first report of the Governing Lines of Action to be presented by the Sixth Government of MSAR.
Based on reports from all over, and changes from members of the Management Committee and the Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, it seems that the “integration of Macao and Hengqin” will probably be a priority topic of the future policies of RAE. This is because this is a national policy defined by the central government for the sectoral diversification of the Macao industry and for the efficient integration of Macau in the Great Guangdong-Hong Bay Kong-Macau.
Although the path has already been opened, to prevent Macao from becoming confused with any other city in the interior of China, the proposal of the four visions is undoubtedly necessary. The question that remains is how to reach them.
Firstly, about the view of “Macao founded in the rule of law”, some scholars believe that “the law should not just be a tool for the government to control society. If we want to speak of a rule of law, the people must also be able to exercise control over government action through the law; This bilateral supervision is what constitutes the rule of law. Otherwise, the “rule of law” would mean controlling the people through legal provisions.  Therefore, the concept of Sam Hou Fai of “Macao based on the rule of law” must be persecuted in the direction of the rule of law, and not through the formulation or alteration of legal documents to control the people and society.
As for the creation of the “dynamic Macao”, the key is to break the limitations of the region. Otherwise, the coming of more tourists will only make the whole city chaotic, moving away from the goal of becoming the world center of tourism and leisure. To increase the vitality of Macao, it is necessary to expand its territory.
Hengqin is no longer a new zone directly under jurisdiction in the city of Zhuhai to become a deepened cooperation zone built and run jointly by Guangdong and Macau province. The next step is undoubtedly moving towards the integration of Macau and Hengqin. Anyone with a basic understanding of public administration knows that having two power centers and two leadership teams often affects administrative efficiency and reduces its effectiveness due to the lack of unified authority. Therefore, when the central government fully transfer the administration of Hengqin to Macau, it should also be the time to materialize the "dynamic Macau".
Macau has only a few hundred years of history compared to the thousands of years of China's cultural heritage. But what makes Macau stand out among many Chinese cities? The sino-Portuguese cultural and religious fusion. The files of the Diocese of Macao, Synical Sheets, and “Files and Manuscripts of the Kong Tac Lam Macau Temple (1645-1980)” were included in the registration of the memory of the UNESCO world to ASIA and PACIFIC, which fully demonstrates to Singularity of Macao's culture. If this advantage can be used, transforming Macau into “Macao Cultural” should not be difficult
As for the “Macao Happy” view, it should be the main priority of the Government of MSAR. After pandemic, affected by several internal and external factors, Macau's small and medium -sized companies faced difficulties, and social progress lacks driving force, with the increase of suicide incidents. The Government of MSAR has the responsibility of preventing Macau, “governed by patriots”, becomes a tragic city. For Macao residents to feel happy, it is essential to concentrate not only in the material aspects, but also in their mental well-being.
With the strong support of the central government and Sam Hou Fai's efforts and his team, 2025 is expected to be the best year of the next decade.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 02:28:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy Arena | Jason Zhang brings Macao tour in March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/galaxy-arena-jason-zhang-traz-digressao-a-macau-em-marco/</link><description>Chinese singer Jason Zhang (Zhang Jie) will be in Macao in March for three shows at the Galaxy Arena, integrated into the “Future Live - Leave for 1982” tour. This is the opportunity to listen to a singer who has built a career around pop music since 2014 and recently recorded “Adrenaline” alongside James Blunt
 
“Future Live - Leave for 1982” is the name of the tour that Chinese singer Jason Zhang (Zhang Jie) has led to several stages and which in March brings to Macau three concerts, between the 7th and 9th. At Galaxy Arena from 19:30, and tickets have been on sale since Tuesday.
The shows promise to offer the audience and fans the best pop songs of the singer who started in the musical lines in 2004. They will, according to Galaxy, a kind of “journey through time, a train on the way from 1982, a moment when The past meets the future. ”
1982 is, by the way, the date of birth of the artist, born in Chengdu, and which by the end of 2023 already had a total of 15 recorded albums and 87 concerts. The beginning of a happy career happened in 2004, when he won the “My Show” contest. This participation earned him a contract with Universal Music producer in China and, from there, Zhang Jie no longer stopped making music and winning his audience.
In this early phase of his career, Zhang Jie released in 2005 the first album, entitled “The First Album”, having won the “Global Chinese Music Chart Most Male Newcomer” award, as the name implies, to new artists. The second album arrived the following year, with the name "Love Me Again", consecrating themselves as a pop artist with a repertoire of romantic ballads.
His career has also been based on some partnerships with musicians and Western Boys Band, highlighting the concert he gave at the Boao Forum in 2010 in which he sang two songs by star Michael Jackson, “Billie Jean” and “Beat It ”. Moreover, in 2012, Jason Zhang was invited to sing the song “My Love” in a Westlife concert.
"Adrenaline" with James Blunt
Jason Zhang's latest collaboration with a foreign artist is “Adrenaline”, a single of 2021 recorded with James Blunt, who became known for the successes “You're Beautiful” and “Goodbye My Lover”. At the time of the release of "Adrenaline", Jason Zhang stated on social networks that "it was an honor to record the new song" Adrenaline "with James Blunt," a good song I hope to be heard by more fans. "
Last year Jason Zhang started with the tour in China, "Future Live: To 1982", with 17 shows in five cities, including some concerts in international stops. Now follows a new tour with passing through Macau.
Jason Zhang is one of the best known singers in the country, having, in 2020, entered the 86 position of the Forbes China Celebrity 100, ie the ranking of the 100 largest Chinese celebrities. The artist's latest album was released in 2023 and calls himself “Wainan Street 1982”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:00:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Book dedicated to Carlos Paredes includes unpublished recording of show</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/livro-dedicado-a-carlos-paredes-inclui-gravacao-inedita-de-espectaculo/</link><description>The life and work of guitar master Carlos Paredes, who “created a genuinely Portuguese song out of nowhere”, is told in a book to be presented this week in Portugal and which includes the recordings of two concerts, one of which is unprecedented.
In “Carlos Paredes - the guitar of a people”, the researcher Octávio Fonseca begins to tell the guitarist's route before he was born, reminiscent of his family background.
Carlos Paredes, who would complete a hundred years of life on February 16, descend from a family of guitarists and composers: great-grandfather António Rodrigues Paredes, grandfather Gonçalo Rodrigues Paredes, grand-uncle Manuel Rodrigues Paredes and father, Artur Paredes.
According to Octávio Fonseca, Artur Paredes, “in terms of technique, completely revolutionized the guitar of Coimbra”, and Carlos Paredes “took advantage of this work and simplified it”. To tell the story and stories of Carlos Paredes, Octávio Fonseca resorted to the research work he had done to another book dedicated to the guitarist edited in 2000, which included reading articles on music that 'master' wrote in newspapers and interviews that gave to various media.
But to write this book, she featured “the extraordinary collaboration” of guitarist and songwriter Luísa Amaro, companion of walls. "Most of the stories that are told in the book were she who conveyed to me," he said.
What makes Carlos Paredes a unique artist is, for Octavio Fonseca, the fact that he created “genuinely Portuguese music of nowhere”.
“In the late 1960s, early 1970s, we were very discussing to go to traditional roots, to create a Portuguese popular music, as José Afonso did. But Carlos Paredes did not do that, and created a Portuguese song out of nowhere. He did not start from our traditional song, nor from any experience of Portuguese music, ”said the researcher.
The parallelism between José Afonso and Carlos Paredes was pointed out by the guitarist himself. “He says in two interviews that there is a parallel between him and José Afonso at the beginning of his career. Carlos Paredes's first album is from 1962 and José Afonso's first ballad album as well (he had albums before, but it was from Fado de Coimbra). They both make a new song from Coimbra, ”he said.
The following year, the two musicians “break free from Coimbra, from the song of Coimbra”, but with a difference, “while with José Afonso there is a complete cut, with Carlos Paredes there is a cut, but there are always a 'penguinhos' in the compositions in which Coimbra appears ”.
MUSICAL NEWS
“Carlos Paredes - the guitar of a people” is accompanied by two records. One is “Master of the Portuguese Guitar”, an album recorded in 1977, at the 7th Political Song Festival in Berlin, published this year by her friend, editor of the former German Democratic Republic (RDA), which is unprecedented in Portugal.
In the other album is recorded “The First Show Carlos Paredes made in his own name in Portugal”, an unprecedented recording registered on March 31, 1984, at the Carlos Alberto Theater, in Porto. The book also includes a photo portfolio by Carlos Paredes, by Augusto Cabrita, Luís Paulo Moura and Inácio Ludgero.
The musician lived mainly in Lisbon and the city inspired many of his compositions. “Green Years”, one of the best known of his work, was composed for the homonymous film of Paulo Rocha, milestone of the new Portuguese cinema of the 1960s.
Anti-fascist combatant, opposed the dictatorship and was arrested by PIDE in the late 1950s. Until the 1990s, it reconciled the guitar with its administrative activity at the São José Hospital in Lisbon. In December 1993, he was diagnosed with myelopathy, a disease that attacked him the bone structure and that prevented him from playing guitar.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 18:27:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | ‘Nezha 2’ becomes the most viewed movie in China's history</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/cinema-nezha-2-torna-se-no-filme-mais-visto-da-historia-da-china/</link><description>The ‘Nezha 2’ animation became the most viewed movie in China's history, days after hitting the revenue record, reaching 5.8 billion Yuan. On Sunday, ‘Nezha 2’ exceeded the film of Wolf Warrior (2015), also Chinese, reaching 159 million tickets sold, according to data from the Specialized Portal Maoyan.
Both ‘Nezha 2’ and the prequel, ‘Nezha’ (2019), are based on a 16th -century Chinese classic novel called "Investiture of the Gods." The film, which premiered during Lunar New Year's holidays, captivated viewers for the narrative, cultural impact and visual quality, according to Chinese official news agency Xinhua.
Maoyan predicts that production can become the first movie to raise more than 10 billion Yuan in the Chinese market. The success of ‘Nezha 2’ is a breath of fresh air for an industry in trouble: in 2024, the Chinese box office raised 42.502 billion yuan, less 22.5 percent than in 2023.
Chinese productions dominated the domestic market in 2024, generating 78.7 percent of total revenues. Chinese authorities limit the number of foreign films, with a quota system that allows the display of about 35 productions per year.
The drop in revenues in 2024 was a setback for a sector that had already been affected during the rigorous Zero Covid politics, which led to the closing of thousands of movie theaters and the functioning of others with boundaries in the number of spectators.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 03:55:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Super Bowl | Artist detained after unfurling Sudanese-Palestinian flag</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/super-bowl-artista-detido-apos-desfraldar-bandeira-sudanesa-palestiniana/</link><description>An artist who acted during the break of Super Bowl, the final of the Football Championship (NFL), was arrested on the field after unfurling a Sudanese-Palestinian flag with the words "Sudan" and "Gaza" written.
The NFL confirmed that the detainee was part of a list of about 400 artists who participated in the show during the interval of Sunday's game, where the star was rapper Kendrick Lamar. The New Orleães Police Department said in a statement that "police are working to determine the accusations applicable in this incident."
"The individual will be banned forever from all NFL stadiums and events," said NFL spokesman Brian McCarthy in a statement. The artist climbed to a used car during Lamar's action and raised the flag.
The NFL said that "the individual hid the item with him and revealed it at the end of the program" and that "no one involved in production was aware of the intention of the individual." Roc Nation, an entertainment company that produced the show, said the act "was not planned or part of the production and was never rehearsed."
The concert continued without interruption, and so far there was no confirmation that the flag was seen during the transmission of Lamar's performance. The Philadelphia Eagles were sacred NFL champions for the second time as they prevented an unprecedented Kansas City Chiefs 'tri', who beat 40-22 on the 59th Super Bowl in New Orleães, Luisiana.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Carbon Monoxide | Hospitalized elderly due to intoxication</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/monoxido-de-carbono-idoso-hospitalizado-devido-a-intoxicacao/</link><description>Health services revealed yesterday that a 79 -year -old man had to receive medical treatment at the Conde de São Januário hospital emergency service after passing out due to carbon monoxide poisoning.
The case happened on Sunday afternoon in the Vai Long building (block I), in the Alameda da Tranquility, when the resident was taking a shower in a bathroom where a gas water heater is installed. The resident “began to feel sudden dizziness and eventually fell inanimate on the floor of the bathroom”, where he was found by family members, who immediately called an ambulance. At Conde de São Januário Hospital did laboratory tests, which revealed concentrations of carbon monoxide hemoglobin. The elderly was “undergoing hyperbaric oxygen therapy treatment” and is currently considered stable.
Authorities add that the gas water heater has been installed in the bathroom for over a decade, and that despite the installation of a ventilation, the bathroom has no windows. At the time of the occurrence, the exhaust was not connected and the authorities suspect that the incident was caused by the lack of maintenance of the device and the accumulation of residual gas in an environment with poor ventilation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:43:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | JP Morgan indicates improvements in search</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/jogo-jp-morgan-indica-melhorias-na-procura/</link><description>Despite the most positive trend, JP Morgan admits that compared to February last year there may even be a reduction in gross reciters
 
After the Lunar New Year, the search for the game in the Macau casinos is "better than the feared." The conclusions are part of the latest report by the investment bank JP Morgan Securities (Asia Pacific) over the territory, which does not fail to moderate growth expectations about the main industry in the territory.
"The game's gross recipes stabilized after the Lunar New Year," wrote DS Kim, Mufan Shi and Selina Li analysts in a report quoted by the GGR Asia portal.
However, not everything is good news for the local economy, and analysts now indicate that gross game recipes “may only grow at one digit level, between one percent and four percent throughout this year, compared to the period homologist ”.
Compared to February, analysts expect gross revenues to be between 18.3 billion patacas and the 19.4 billion patacas. These values ​​mean that compared to last year, in the worst scenario, revenues may have a break from one percent, and that in the best scenario can grow up to five percent.
“The gross revenues of the new Lunar post-year game have become better than expected, reaching 725 million patacas a day, thanks to a solid demand at the end of the year, which is in a way offsetting weakness [of the revenues] of the Lunar New Year ”, was justified.
On the other hand, JP Morgan indicates that the weakness of revenues is more related to previous industry expectations, than actually to the amount generated by the territory tables, which between February 1 and 5 were 900 million PATACAS per day . The report indicates that in the first nine months of the year the revenues were 7.4 billion patacas.
Low review
The scenario outlined by JP Morgan Post-Anno New Lunar, contrasts with the one that was lived during the festivities and which led another investment bank, Citigroup, to reduce predictions about the expansion of the Macao game this year.
In a report published on Monday, Citigroup analysts, George Choi and Timothy Chau, presented a scenario in which the game's gross recipes record a 3 percent growth, which contrasts with the previous optimism, when it was expected that the sector expansion reached 7 percent. And in the first half of the year, the investment bank admits that gross revenues even record a reduction of about one percent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:39:50</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP | Reinforced prevention in combating human trafficking</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/cpsp-reforcada-prevencao-no-combate-ao-trafico-humano/</link><description>The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) ensures that it has reinforced prevention in combating human trafficking after in late December revealed that five residents of Macao were victims of human trafficking and forced to “work” on online fraud centers in Taiwan and Cambodia.
In response to questions posed by Macau News Agency, police authorities indicate having published on social networks messages warning of cases of people who are seduced with work proposals in Southeast Asia, but eventually fall into meshes of criminal groups that are dedicated to online fraud. The victims, in their wide Chinese majority, are forced to defraud people in telecommunications centers.
Although they do not reveal whether there have been additional cases of Macao residents beyond the five announced in December, CPSP indicates that the objective of the prevention campaign has alerted the population to be cautious when they are offered a job through online platforms or people Unknown, especially when these jobs imply trips abroad. Another sign of danger covers the form of work that promises high wages, without the need for academic background, technical capacity or work experience in the area.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:35:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Fai chi kei | Fine of 600 Patacas for shooting Cutelo through the window</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/fai-chi-kei-multa-de-600-patacas-por-atirar-cutelo-pela-janela/</link><description>At the end of last year, an individual was arrested for shooting the street window street where a cleaver lives. According to the secretary's office for security, the man was fined 600 patacas for violating rules established in the General Regulation of Public Spaces.
The question was raised in a written interpellation signed by Nick Lei and, in response, the substitute chief of the Secretary's Office, Cheong Chang, stressed that as the incident did not cause wounded or property damage to shoot a cleaver to the public road did not constitute a crime. However, if the intention was proved to cause injuries, death or property damage, the man could be accused of crimes of severe offense to physical integrity, murder or damage.
On the other hand, the direction of services to legal affairs stressed that Macao laws and regulations have established mechanisms to hold offenders responsible. As for the question of whether the act of throwing objects from high places should be classified as a separate crime, the government indicates that it is necessary to study the need and viability of criminalization.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:34:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | Another 11 thousand vaccines. Markings open today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/gripe-mais-11-mil-vacinas-marcacoes-abrem-hoje/</link><description>The significant increase in citizens who want to get the flu vaccine has led health services to buy an additional 11 thousand doses. The markings to take the vaccines have been widened and open today. The government bought 45,000 doses than last year's flu
 
Following the race for influenza vaccination over the past weekend, taking more than 5,400 residents of health centers and hospitals, the government announced on Monday night that it would buy another 11,000 doses urgently to correspond to demand .
Thus, after the arrival last night of the lots, the markings to take the vaccine opened today on the Internet of Health Services website, with the authorities to reach that people over 65 and children between 6 months and 9 years old are exempt from marking.
Health services acquired for this time flu (2024/2025) 225 thousand doses of the flu vaccine, an increase of 45 thousand doses in relation (or 25 percent). Until Monday, the authorities accounted for 204,000 doses administered, totaling a 22.2 percent increase over the same period last year, when 167,000 vaccines had been administered. It is recalled that the race for vaccination in the past weekend occurred after two residents died following complications after flu infections A.
Macao and the World
The government points out that flu vaccination rates this year between risk groups are “ideal” and increased from last year.
Among the users of elderly homes, more than 90 percent took the vaccine, while in the infantry the rate exceeds 65 percent, in the kindergartens of primary schools more than 80 percent of children were vaccinated, while in secondary education the rate of inoculation is 70 percent. In the general calculation, among residents over 65 years of age, the vaccination rate is almost 60 percent.
The type of vaccines that Macau buys is intended for the northern hemisphere and, as such, their validity expires between May and June of each year. Therefore, the government stresses that "the annual flu vaccination program will end when existing vaccines run out or expire."</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:27:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Mortgage loans fell 17.9% in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/habitacao-emprestimos-hipotecarios-cairam-179-em-dezembro/</link><description>The Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) yesterday revealed that the new mortgage loans for housing approved by Macao banks in December fell 17.9 percent compared to November, to a total of 1.01 billion patacas. Of these loans, 96.6 percent were contracted by local residents, in a total amount of 975.39 million patacas, 17.7 percent than in November. Also the non-resident component decreased 22.6 percent.
AMCM indicates that, “until the end of 2024, in compliance with the reimbursement of several high loans, the gross balance of mortgage loans for housing reached 218.14 billion, corresponding to one 0.5 percent decrease in relation to the previous month and 4.9 percent in annual terms.
The new commercial loans for real estate activities still fell more in December in front of November, with a decrease 22.7 percent to 685.51 million patacas.
AMCM also indicates that at the end of last year, the poorly mortgage loan credit for housing reached 3.5 percent, which corresponds to an increase of 0.1 percent compared to November and a 2.7 rise by one hundred in annual terms.
Malporated trade for commercial loans is even higher, corresponding to 5.3 percent of the total value of these loans, an increase of 0.5 percent compared to November and more percent in annual terms.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:22:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Concert | Burlada on 8,900 yuan when buying tickets</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/concerto-burlado-em-8-900-yuan-na-compra-de-bilhetes/</link><description>A man was circumvented in 8,900 yuan while trying to buy, over the internet, tickets for a concert in the interior. The case was released yesterday by the Judicial Police (PJ), who received the complaint.
According to the contours presented by PJ, the victim was added to the Wechat platform in May last year for a contact he did not know.
However, it found that this contact sold tickets to different concerts in the black market. So in June last year, the man decided to buy two tickets for a concert, making a payment of 8,900 yuan. The concert was scheduled for July, but was postponed to January this year.
In the face of scheduling, the man contacted the alleged seller, who assured him that he would send him the new tickets in time from the new show. However, this never happened, and the victim eventually filed a complaint to the Macao authorities.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 03:27:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us around the house, pies us his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on violations in Ukraine in this “special operation”), an act that he forced us to watch, and then we tell him: High There we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You haven't said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - Madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is managed to seek a reason for Things abroad to us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed with scholastic rigor stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicidou -If and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ that had not entered the story. »
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when you announced the Nobel Prize in this year's literature, I couldn't help but remember this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, compared to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large newspaper Daily National Wrote wrote Five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize of Literature was awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete unknown. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners - I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example - but that only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone is He knows and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from him.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I also preferred that in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have been awarded. Les années ”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday an article came out in Maputo's morning “News”, to realize that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho Award Coast.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification as to their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained the guts to the dogmas of the "modern". For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but to be highlighted simply that we "we do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funeral trips for countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - which starts still awaits us, that secret spells we will still have to overcome, what horrors will be erected before our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to nature itself, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the mountain of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most undevailed ambitions, if they are fortunately fortunate to glimpse a fuxi, it is true that the fields will be triggered soon and the fields will be triggered by it Cultivated, it will be beheaded the meek animals, by it will be sacrificed the best young men of two generations and destroyed the pride of countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the midst of Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneousness and frankness were coarcet in relationships in relations Human, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a "essence", therefore declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, "one and absolute". Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as António Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter My Dear Friend: You are a pure, excellent and very noble poet, but one Also victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I malice.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people, who always seems the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters At eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Evidently, they are the two 'Bigger Than Life', but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my rank of hatter at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and Treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over the referected zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>McDonald's | Planned opening in China from another thousand restaurants this year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/mcdonalds-planeada-abertura-na-china-de-mais-mil-restaurantes-este-ano/</link><description>The world's largest rapid food chain, McDonald's, plans to open about 1,000 new restaurants in China in 2025, almost half of the 2,200 that will open worldwide.
At a conference with analysts after the last quarter results, US Frederick Borden's financial director, revealed these numbers, which in the case of China followed the number of openings announced in the last two exercises.
"We are watching encouraging signs of stabilization in China," said the official about the company's performance in the Asian country for 2024, when global profits fell 3 percent over the previous year.
By 2024, McDonald's executive president Chris Kempczinski had already highlighted the “strong growth” in China, despite the pressure on consumer confidence in the face of economic recovery problems, and said: “We will do what it takes to maintain the maintaining our competitiveness in this market ”.
The hamburgers chain has about six thousand points of sale in China and aims to exceed ten thousand by 2028. Currently, there are over 40,000 McDonald's restaurants worldwide.
At the end of 2023, McDonald's announced an agreement to buy 28 percent participation that Carlyle investment company had in its business in China for an estimated $ 1.8 billion, increasing its participation of 20 percent to 48 percent, with the Chinese investment bank Citic to control the remaining 52 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:06:58</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Pyongyang denounces “hostile military act”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/eua-pyongyang-denuncia-acto-militar-hostil/</link><description>North Korea accused the United States on Monday of committing a "hostile military act," after a US Navy submarine has moved in South Korea for refueling.
"We are very concerned about the dangerous hostile military act of the United States, which can lead the acute military confrontation in the region of the Korean Peninsula to a total armed conflict," said a spokesman for the Ministry of Defense, quoted in a statement released by the agency of State News KCNA.
Pyongyang has asked the United States to "stop the provocations that feed instability," accusing them of ignoring North Korean security concerns. South Korea Yonhap news agency said USS Alexandria, a US nuclear submarine, arrived on Monday on Busan, South Korea on Monday. A similar visit had occurred in November.
"Our Armed Forces are closely monitoring the frequent appearance of US strategic assets on the Korean Peninsula and are ready to use all means to defend state security and interests, as well as regional peace," said the port -Voice of the Ministry of Defense of North Korea.
North Korea emphasized the importance of developing its self -defense capabilities and referred to the promise of leader Kim Jong Un in January to continue his country's nuclear program "indefinitely."
Good old friends
United States President Donald Trump expressed on Friday the intention to build bridges with Kim Jong-un's North Korean regime. “I think it's a great advantage for everyone that I get along with him. I like him, I mean, I get along with him, he gets along with me. And that's a good thing, it's not a bad thing, ”said the Republican.
But North Korea replied that the nuclear weapons it possesses are not a bargaining chip to negotiate, but a force to stop threats, and justified the reinforcement of weapons with the geopolitical aspirations of the West.
The statement suggests that Pyongyang has no interest in returning to the negotiating table with Washington. In the first term as president of the United States, Donald Trump proposed to North Korea to end nuclear weapons in exchange for support in economic development.
The North Korean message also mentioned the recent statements of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and the European Union, which reaffirmed that they will not recognize North Korea as nuclear power. Pyongyang accuses the West of being a destabilizing force of peace.
Pyongyang, in addition, denounced the growing participation of NATO and European countries in military maneuvers around the Korean Peninsula, accusing them of seeking the confrontation and disarmament of the Asian country, not for safety reasons, but to “reach the ones their political and impure military objectives ”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 01:06:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China | Reinforced rules for publication of military information on the Internet</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/china-reforcadas-regras-para-publicacao-de-informacoes-militares-na-internet/</link><description>China will impose new rules that limit information that can be shared about the Popular Liberation Army (ELP) on the Internet, which may make it difficult to monitor its development and evolution.
According to a circular issued by the country's armed forces, “military information suppliers on the Internet” will be prohibited from March 1 from “producing, copying, publishing or disclosing” previously unclogged information, including details on systems weaponry and military facilities.
The new rules prohibit the publication of information involving “military secrets and national defense technology”, such as “research and development, production, testing, transportation, equipment and maintenance of weapons and equipment, [as well as] tactical performance and weapons and equipment technician ”.
It also prohibits the dissemination of information about the organizational structure of the Armed Forces, their chain of command, previous commanders and details on military units that have not been officially disclosed.
The rules, which also aim at “false military information and the escape of military secrets on the Internet”, were adopted by the Central Military Commission and the China Cyberspace Administration on Saturday.
According to experts cited by the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper, many internet users who follow the ELP served as a valuable information source about their development, publishing photographs of new equipment such as fighters and aircraft carrier. However, authorities now consider that this information "endangers national security" and can make data sensitive "vulnerable to foreign spy exploration."
Wipe
The new directive prohibits the publication of information that "deny or attack China's national defense and military strategy and military strategy," including the "construction, development and use of strategic nuclear forces."
The circular also establishes that users of social networks wishing to be identified as “military accounts” must meet a series of requirements, including the provision of personal data and registration with military authorities and cyberspace.
In recent years, China has called for mobilization of “whole society” to “prevent and combat espionage” and announced a series of measures to “reinforce national defense” against “foreign secret services activities”.
Since 2024, the ELP has been carried out a broad anti -corruption campaign that resulted in the dismissal of at least nine generals and several defense industry executives.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:58:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Space | Created planetary defense team against possible asteroid clash</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/espaco-criada-equipa-de-defesa-planetaria-face-a-possivel-embate-de-asteroide/</link><description>China began gathering a planetary defense team following the discovery of a large asteroid that could reach Earth within seven years, local press advanced yesterday.
According to the South China Morning Post newspaper, the state administration of science, technology and industry for China's national defense is looking for professionals with experience in monitoring asteroids and early alert systems. The initiative is in line with the widest planetary defense strategy in the Asian country, which includes an asteroid deviation mission planned for 2027.
China has been working on the development of technologies to follow, analyze and potentially change the trajectory of objects near Earth. NASA and the European Space Agency (ESA) had similar programs in the past. On Friday, ESA updated to 2.2 percent the likelihood that Asteroid 2024 YR4 reached Earth in 2032, placing it at the top of the agency's risk list.
The asteroid, with an estimated width between 40 and 90 meters, was discovered by the University of Hawaii Institute of Astronomy at the end of December. The discovery has awarded global asteroid response mechanisms after the probabilities of impact on Earth have surpassed an international monitoring threshold.
Defense to three
The announcement of the State Administration of Science, Technology and Industry for China's National Defense aims at recruiting three professionals for a “Planetary Defense Post”.
The Center, which is responsible for the investigation and implementation of aerospace engineering and the observation of the land, is recruiting graduates to study asteroid monitoring and create early warning methods, according to the announcement, published in China Space magazine account Science and Technology.
There are several methods that can be used to try to prevent an asteroid from reaching the earth. In the world's first successful planetary defense test in 2022, NASA's US space agency changed the trajectory of an asteroid by provoking a clash against a ship.
Scientists will be able to follow the 2024 YR4 until April 2025, with the next observation opportunity to arrive in 2028. In early February 2025, NASA placed the asteroid at level 3 of the Torino Impact Danger scale, a classification that Indicates a situation that deserves attention, but not immediate concern.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:56:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Shanghai | New Tesla Battery Factory starts to work</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/xangai-nova-fabrica-de-baterias-da-tesla-comeca-a-funcionar/</link><description>The American Tesla electric vehicle manufacturer began production yesterday in a new storage battery factory at the Xangai metropolis in east China, official Chinese news agency Xinhua said.
The complex began to be built at the end of May 2024 and should have started to work before the end of the year, with the aim of becoming a “very important production and export base,” according to one official of the company.
The official press stressed, however, that the time elapsed between the launch of the first stone and the opening of the facilities was just eight months, and praised what it described as “Tesla Speed”: in 2019, the North Company's 'gigable' -American in Shanghai was built in just one year.
In this new complex, Tesla will manufacture its megapacks, energy storage batteries used to stabilize electric networks and avoid power cuts.
According to the company, each megapack can store more than three energy megawatts (MWh) of energy, "enough to feed an average of 3,600 homes for one hour." Initial production capacity is estimated at about 10,000 units of the device per year, which is equivalent to the annual electricity consumption of 50,000 homes.
According to local authorities, Tesla invested about 1.45 billion Yuan at the factory, located on a plot of 200,000 square meters. Tesla already has one of these 'megafábricas' in Lathrop, California, southwest US, where she manufactures about 10,000 batteries a year, which add up to a storage of about 40 gigawatts-hours (GWh).
Powerful ties
In 2019, Tesla opened its first 'gigable' outside the United States in Shanghai. The factory produced about 947,000 vehicles in 2023, which, according to Xinhua, represented just over half of the company's global sales.
Since 2019, Tesla has intensified its investment in the Lingang free trade zone, the Shanghai area where it has operations, expanding production in its 'gigable' and building additional facilities, such as a production factory for its 'superloaders' of Electric vehicles.
Tesla's executive president, Elon Musk, who is the richest man in the world and an ally close to the new US President Donald Trump, maintains good relations with China's authorities, a country he has visited several times and where he has one of the its main markets.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:54:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Ia | Provincial governments in China start using DeepSeek</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/ia-governos-provinciais-na-china-comecam-a-utilizar-deepseek/</link><description>Several local governments in China have begun to incorporate DeepSeek's artificial intelligence (AI) model to help with administrative tasks and improve assistance to public needs, local media told yesterday.
Large cities like Shenzhen, Canton or Suzhou have already joined the new great model of Chinese language, according to the Official Global Times.
Longgang district in Shenzhen installed the Deepseek-R1 model on its external network with access to all departments, while Suzhou, in Jiangsu province, along with Shanghai, incorporated this model and also DeepSeek-V3 on its platform public service information technologies.
"The goal is to make AI an efficient assistant to government tasks and transform the way its operations are conducted, making it smarter, collaborative and data-oriented," said the director of the data management office and Governmental Services of Shenzhen, XI Wei, quoted by the Shenzhen News portal.
In the case of Suzhou, the model will be applied for research and generation of images, among other purposes. DeepSeek caused a great stir in the global AI sector after the launch a few weeks ago from its V3 model, which will have only taken two months to develop and cost less than six million dollars.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:47:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomacy | China does not confirm conversation that Trump says he had with Xi Jinping</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/12/diplomacia-china-nao-confirma-conversa-que-trump-diz-ter-tido-com-xi-jinping/</link><description>China did not confirm yesterday that Chinese President Xi Jinping spoke to the US counterpart after his inauguration on January 20, as Donald Trump revealed on Monday.
A meeting between the leaders of the two worldwide powers could facilitate bilateral relations, still threatened by a potential trade war initiated by Donald Trump. In an interview broadcast by US television channel Fox News on Monday, a journalist asked Donald Trump if he had spoken with Xi Jinping since the beginning of his second term.
"Yes, I talked to him and also talked to the people of his team," said the US President, although neither Washington nor Beijing had ever reported that call. Asked yesterday, whether the conversation actually happened, a Beo Puts of Beijing merely remembered the conversation that took place three days before Trump's inauguration.
“President Xi Jinping had a telephone conversation with US President Donald Trump on January 17. China has issued a statement on the subject, ”said Guo Jiakun, spokesman for the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, at a press conference. Since taking office, Trump has announced the imposition of punitive fees on his main trading partners, including China, Mexico and Canada.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:46:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Government will study Trump's tariffs on steel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/japao-governo-vai-estudar-as-tarifas-de-trump-sobre-o-aco/</link><description>The Japanese government said yesterday that it will study the plans of the president of the United States regarding the imposition of tariffs in the order of 25 percent on steel and aluminum imports.
"We are aware of what President Trump said about steel and aluminum, from Japan, we will carefully study the content of the measure he takes and his influence and later we will take the right measures," said the spokesman From the Japanese government, Yoshimasa Hayashi, at a press conference.
Hayashi made these comments when asked about President Trump's announcement to impose reciprocal tariffs on other business partners and a 25 percent rate on steel and aluminum imports.
"I don't know if the announcement includes Japan, but the agreement between Nippon Steel and U.S. Steel is a great way to resolve the issue and, although not knowing how it will be realized, I think this is how they intend to overcome the problem," he said Masakazu Tokura, president of the largest Japanese employer organization, Keidanren, to NHK public station.
Tokura referred to the latest developments in the process of acquiring U.S. Steel by the Japanese Nippon Steel.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 04:19:15</pubDate></item><item><title>HK | Electronic cigarettes will be prohibited in public places</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/11/hk-cigarros-electronicos-vao-ser-proibidos-em-locais-publicos/</link><description>Hong Kong will prohibit the possession and use of electronic cigarettes in public spaces by mid -2026 due to the health implications of young residents, authorities of the Chinese Semiautonoma region said.
"To protect our young people, we believe it is time to ban the use of electronic cigarettes cartridges," the secretary for health, Lo Chung-Mau, said on Sunday.
"We will start by legislating against possession and use [of electronic cigarettes] outdoors," he added. "When everyone gets used to [the prohibition], we will implement it everywhere," he added. The announcement was made almost three years after the territory of southern China prohibited the importation, manufacture and sale of electronic cigarettes and heated tobacco products.
According to the Hong Kong law, anyone who imports electronic cigarettes can face up to seven years in prison and a two million dollars of Hong Kong. Manufacturers and sellers risk catching up to six months in prison.
Also the neighboring region of Macao banned, in 2022, the manufacture, distribution, importation, export and transportation at the entrance and exit of the territory of electronic cigarettes. The government justified the changes to the law with “the strong evidence that this type of tobacco product is not only harmful to health, but also the use can endanger the safety of people”, noting that the consumption of electronic cigarettes increased, increased, increased, increased, increased, increased cigarettes, especially among young people.
Fashion
Since 2015, the consumption of electronic cigarettes among young people aged 13 to 15 has increased by “2.6 percent to 4 percent”, according to data revealed in May 2022 by the Director of Health Services of Macao.
That is, he stressed Alvis Lo Iek Long, there are already young people to use electronic cigarettes than traditional (2.1 percent). The law provides for penalties to four thousand patacas, and in the case of entities, a fine between 20 thousand patacas and 200 thousand patacas can be applied.
Although the proposal was unanimously approved, during the debate in the Legislative Assembly, several deputies maintained that Macau should go further and advance also with the total ban on the use of electronic cigarettes.
The then Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, Elsie to Ieong U, confirmed that the government consisted later forbid the use of electronic cigarettes after giving "some time" to smokers who could "have some in stock." Thirty -five countries banned the sale of electronic cigarettes, the World Health Organization said in 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 03:59:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Ricardo Clara Couto, author of the documentary about Francisco de Pina | The weight of the guilt that persists</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/ricardo-clara-couto-autor-do-documentario-sobre-francisco-de-pina-o-peso-da-culpa-que-persiste/</link><description>“Francisco de Pina - The Portuguese who wrote the future of Vietname” tells the story of Father Jesuit, born in Guarda in 1586, who made the romanization of the Vietnamese alphabet. The documentary, by Ricardo Clara Couto was funded by RTP2 and aired at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
How did you come across this character in Portuguese history in the East?
My brother, named Filipe Pires, traveled for Vietnam for a while and when he arrived from the trip he told me that he had to know the incredible history of the Jesuit Francis of Pina who had made the romanization of the Vietnamese alphabet, providing freedom and cultural independence tremendous. I was a little skeptical at first, because I found it strange no one to know this in Portugal, but I started my research on the subject and discovered a university study of a Franco-Vietnamese teacher who teaches in Madeira. I then confirmed that the idea that my brother had brought from Vietname was correct. From there, I tried to discover the origin of this priest, the work he had done, and realize why there was so little knowledge about Francisco de Pina in Portugal.
In addition to being a Jesuit missionary, can you highlight some biographical points that help you understand your legacy?
In the documentary I did not have the time to be able to take a more exhaustive biographical approach. I focused on the part where he arrives at Vietname. We talk about a man with an incredible culture and a desire to acculturate and be acculturated. A man who was a musician and was easier, thus learning the Vietnamese, which is a six -tone language. Deep down, despite being a Jesuit priest, he had the first of course culture and not so much religion. This, for me, is a reason for huge admiration. For him the essential objective of evangelization was secondary, because, for him, if we could not understand the culture of Vietname, we could not teach the Vietnamese people. It was more important to deepen local culture and language, making it possible to be able to explore the most religious part. It was also a man who had a hard time when he arrived at Vietname.
Why?
There were some internal wars before some local gentlemen of the regions who did not agree with the mission of the priests. This is not explored in the documentary, but in fact Francisco de Pina even made some steps [for the Jesuit mission], as the priests were not totally accepted everywhere. He eventually took refuge in a Japanese neighborhood and, from there, built his base.
Francisco de Pina, like what happened to many Jesuits at the time, was training in Macau, at the College of S. Paulo. How was it influenced by this period spent in the territory?
There is not much information about this time. It is known that it was indeed formed in this college, as was the case with many Jesuit priests at the time, but then went to Japan. Only then go to Vietname. So far, there was nothing of great relief in the life of Francisco de Pina, who followed the normal way. Japan was already expelling the Jesuit priests and it is in this context that goes to Vietname. The only most prominent thing about this period is that the 14 ships that left Portugal to arrive in Macau this year remained only three, and the ship where I was Pina Francisco was one of those who survived the storm.
Do you consider that your great legacy was the romanization of Vietnamese? What are the great contributions of this process in linguistic terms?
It is a giant contribution. If we think that even in the romanization of the language, Vietname was very dependent on the Chinese alphabet, and could not have cultural, linguistic and economic independence as well. After the romanization of the alphabet it was possible for Vietname to grow in these domains and have her own identity. The country has grown a lot to this day, because without writing a tongue passes only to the new generations of mouth in mouth, and the legacy of Francisco de Pina also remains today. The Vietnamese people are very grateful to this, and the proof is that two years ago a delegation of the Vietnammemesse Language Foundation Foundation came to Portugal and offered a monument to Guarda City Council (see Caixa) in honor of Francisco de Pina. However, I was surprised by the fact that the Vietnamese, and we talked about full -sided academics, know the story, the figure of Francisco de Pina, existing in the country several references. But in Portugal it is a little known figure.
How do you explain this?
I think this will have to do with the need Portugal has to make its catharsis about this period of history. Portugal was a completely different country from Africa to the East, and completely different from Africa to the Americas. But, however, there is this weight of guilt. Portugal cannot talk about this period of time, despite having a rich history between Africa and the East, but this time is not very approached because the country has not taken over what happened and, therefore, cannot talk about this period. Therefore, so much of the rich history of Portugal is unknown to the Portuguese.
How was the research process for the documentary?
I quickly arrived at the study of Professor Minh Ha Nguyen Lo Cicero of the University of Madeira, and with her we went to the roots of the Vietnamese language. When I discovered it was amazing, because it is part of the Vietnamese alphabet romanization triangle, as it is Franco-Vietnamese. Until recently, the official version that existed was that Alexandre de Rhodes, French Jesuit, had romanized the alphabet, later registering it in the Vatican and saying that it was a work in honor of his master, Francisco de Pina. However, the name of Francisco de Pina disappeared. From here we passed to the nationalist French official narrative that the romanization of the alphabet had been made by French because Vietname was a French colony. Then I also arrived at Professor António Morgado. The remaining contacts were made at Vietname, linguists, university professors and language specialists, especially in writing, who later joined the documentary.
How would you describe the Vietname of the time of Francisco de Pina?
It was very fragmented. They have a very their own culture that existed through a writing with Chinese hieroglyphics, but deals with Vietnamese, which led only 1 to 3 percent of the population to read and write. With the romanization this percentage increased exponentially, and with this the culture developed with the populations, united them more around common writing. I think this has made Vietname more modern and prepared to integrate into the rest of the world by having a more affordable language.
Do you feel it will help unravel this part of the history of Portugal, as well as the history of the Jesuit mission itself?
I hope so. Portugal seems to have a certain fear and shame to talk about this time, and proof of this is that this Vietnamese people came to Guard to offer a monument and practically did not come out of the subject. In addition, the representatives of the Vietname delegation were a little admired for not being received at an official level, except for the mayor of Guarda. I, who was invited by them to be present, felt a little shame of others, because Vietname came to Portugal to offer a monument and this is viewed as a secondary event, which is not. It would be important to make known this priest and this made to the country and the world, because Portugal and Vietnam have a very close and rich cultural history, as with Japan and China. But this is a little known aspect of the Portuguese people and [this documentary] can be a good opportunity for the country to make their catharsis.
Vietnamese artist sculpture resembles Francisco de Pina at Guarda
In November 2023, the Vietnamese Language Foundation offered the city of Guarda the sculpture “Nova Estela” by Vietnamese artist Nguyen Huy Anh. The work can be seen in the Garden of the Eduardo Lourenço Municipal Library. According to news from the agency Ecclesia, the event took place under the celebrations of the 824th anniversary of the attribution of Foral by King D. Sancho I to the city. “This is a posthumous tribute to Father Francisco de Pina, a Guarda-born Jesuit priest in 1586, whose religious path underwent a mission in Vietname, where he lived nine years of intense missionary activity, linguistics and of interculturality, ”said the Diocese of the Guard, in a statement.
According to the same note, the missionary Francisco de Pina was responsible for the introduction of the Latin alphabet and diacritical signs in the transcription of the sounds and tones of the Vietnamese language, which used, in writing, Chinese characters.
The priest embarked for over 400 years at the Nau de Nossa Senhora do Mount of Carmo, having completed the training at the São Paulo College in Macau and received the priestly ordination in Malaca. It was then called to the newly created Mission of the Jesuit Cchinchina, a zone that corresponds to the central part of the current Vietname. “He never came to the city where he was born and now returned in a bronze -carved boat by Vietnamese artists brought by the distant Vietname sea. From now on, Father Francisco de Pina will be in the historical memory of the guard and its inhabitants, materialized in this boat that brought him back to his city, leaving the name of the guard far, also written in Bronze letters ” , concluded the diocese.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 00:46:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Francisco Leandro, author and professor at the University of Macao: “Support from the country reinforces the role of Macao platform”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2024/12/16/francisco-leandro-autor-e-professor-na-universidade-de-macau-apoio-do-pais-reforca-o-papel-de-plataforma-de-macau/</link><description>Gang Wen interview with China Daily newspaper
Francisco Leandro, an associate professor at the Faculty of Social Sciences at the University of Macao, states that the nation's support has allowed the MSA to serve as the Center for Commerce, Investment and Cultural Interactions between China and Portuguese Language Communities.
 
 
How do you see Macau's development since your return to the homeland? Among the city's achievements, which ones impressed him most? What about its sector, has there been an important progress in the last 25 years?
The 25th anniversary of Macau's return to the homeland and the creation of the Special Administrative Region of Macao is a significant milestone in the history of the region, reflecting a successful diplomatic process and demonstrating its current political and economic stability. Currently, RAE de Macao enjoys political stability and is deeply integrated into national development plans. The governance of the city under the beginning of “a country, two systems” allowed him to maintain a high degree of autonomy, while aligning himself with national policies. This integration facilitated Macao's economic growth, making it a vital part of the country's broader economic strategy.
Macao's socioeconomic development strategy is consecrated in the policy “a center, a platform, a base”. This picture aims to position MSA as a world center of tourism and leisure, reinforcing its attraction as a global tourist destination. In addition, MSAR acts as a platform for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, promoting international trade and cultural exchange. Rae de Macao is also becoming a base of exchange and cultural cooperation, promoting cultural interactions and the conservation of heritage. This multifaceted approach supports Macao's integration into national development plans and reinforces its global presence. The unique position of MSA as a bridge between China, in particular the large Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay, and Portuguese-speaking countries underline their strategic importance.
The concept of “a platform, three centers” enhances Macao's role in promoting economic and cultural exchange. This platform allowed the city to serve as a platform for trade, investment and cultural interactions, reinforcing the ties between China and the Lusophone world.
Macau's development as a tourism and leisure center, along with the promotion of four main industries - conventions and exhibitions, cultural and creative industries, traditional Chinese medicine and modern financial services - diversified its economy. These initiatives not only boosted economic activity, but also reinforced the global attraction of Macau as a tourist destination.
The central government adopted a series of policies for Macao. Is there any specific measure that has benefited your sector? As?
The interior of China and the Macao Economic Economic Partnership Agreement (Cepa) play a crucial role in the great bay and in the promotion of ties with Portuguese -speaking countries. By promoting commercial and economic cooperation, the strain reinforces the position of MSA as a bridge between China and Lusophone countries. This agreement facilitates access to the market, investment and cultural exchange, promoting Macao as an international business center. In addition, the strain supports the integration of Macau in the Great Bay area, contributing to regional development and economic diversification. This strategic role underlines the importance of Macau in the broader economic and diplomatic initiatives in the country.
The promotion of higher education in RAE de Macao also played a crucial role in its development. In investing in education and research, Macau contributed to the objectives of national development and was positioned as a center of academic excellence. This bet on education has allowed to create a skilled labor, essential to sustain economic growth and innovation. The University of Macao is highly considered in global academic rankings. It was classified in 180th place at the World University Rankings 2025 by Times Higher Education, and 245th at QS World University Rankings 2025. In addition, the University of Macao is ranked 262nd in the best global universities by US News &amp; World Report. These classifications reflect the university's commitment to excellence in teaching and research, particularly in areas such as Artificial Intelligence, Engineering and Social Sciences. The university's strong international collaboration and innovative investigation contribute significantly to their estimated global position.
This year is the third anniversary of the creation of the Guangdong-Macau in-depth cooperation zone in Hengqin. In your opinion, how should Macau continue to take advantage of the advantages of the zone to develop himself and the education sector?
Hengqin's cooperation zone is one of the main objectives of Macao's modernization efforts. This zone has been fundamental to boosting innovation and economic diversification, providing a space for new industries and promoting a narrower integration with the continent. The area exemplifies Macau's commitment to modernization and its strategic role in regional development.
Macao is a unique mix of Chinese and Portuguese cultures. In your opinion, how can this merger help the nation to reinforce communication with the international community and tell the good stories of China?
Macao is a fascinating mix of cultures, where the East meets the West in a unique and harmonious way. His linguistic landscape is a testimony of his multicultural heritage. The Chinese is the official language and the Portuguese language can be used for official purposes, reflecting the historical ties of Macao with Portugal and its Chinese roots. English is also widely spoken, especially in business and tourism, which makes Macau a truly multilingual society.
The legal system of MSAR is another domain in which this cultural mixture is evident. Based on the Portuguese Civil Law System, it was adapted to the local context under the “one country, two systems” principle. This double legal system allows a unique mix of Chinese and Western legal traditions, ensuring that Macau's legal environment is familiar to its residents and accessible to international companies.
Macao's approach to the extrajudicial resolution of commercial conflicts further enhances its multicultural policy. The city offers various arbitration and mediation services that serve both local and international parts, promoting the efficient and friendly resolution of disputes. Macao's open city policy and multicultural attitude are the key to its success as a global center. The city welcomes people from around the world, promoting a diverse and inclusive community. This opening is reflected in its festivals, its gastronomy and their daily lives, where different cultures coexist and enrich each other. Essentially, the mix of language, legal systems and multicultural attitudes of Macau makes it a unique and dynamic place that establishes bridges between cultures and promotes global bonds.
What achievements would you like to see by Macau in the next 25 years?
In short, Macao's future is brilliant, with greater integration with mainland China, its central role in international trade, diversified economic growth and a strong global presence. These elements will ensure Macao's continuous success and development at the world scene. The 25th anniversary of Macao's return to the Fatherland celebrates not only a successful diplomatic achievement, but also the continuous contributions of the region to national and world development. Macao's strategic initiatives and their integration in national plans underline their importance as a dynamic region and facing the future.</description><pubDate>2024-12-16 02:20:12</pubDate></item><item><title>António Antunes, cartoonist: “Sometimes I consider myself an artist”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2024/12/12/antonio-antunes-cartoonista-as-vezes-considero-me-um-artista/</link><description>It's called Antonio Antunes, but signs her cartoons simply as Antonio. For 50 years it has characterized today using drawing and humor, most of them in the Express. In an interview, the cartoonist, who designed the days of the April 25, regrets that today young cartoonists do not have so many opportunities to sing in their career
This 50 -year adventure is already long dedicated to Cartoon. Have you ever thought you were going to do this for so many years?
No. Things were happening, and the result is this. There were not even perspectives to have a plan. Portugal has not been a country that greatly favors this type of activities.
He did training at António Arroio school during the Estado Novo period. What was it like to learn arts at a time when the country [Portugal] was so gray, with limits to creativity?
We mainly learned techniques, work or composition. Now creativity is something else. Not only was she very limited, but it's not something to sell either. There are no courses to take artists, there are courses that give us notions about painting composition or techniques, or colors. But that alone is not enough. Then there needs to be anything beyond what is academic. In the arts there is always anything that escapes even if you learn everything. Creativity is a strange thing because there is no rule.
Is Antonio considered an artist?
(Hesitates) Sometimes I consider.
He has had many controversial cartoons, namely Pope John Paul II with the condom in his nose. What were the cartoons that forced you to make the biggest waist play or deal with more pressures?
Maybe it's my happiness, but my problems are never a priori, but to posteriori. So far I have not been very limited in what I can do in the newspaper [Expresso]. Now, when things go out, sometimes have consequences. In Portugal it was the issue of condom in the Pope, internationally other things. This cartoon continues to move.
What was it like to deal with all this controversy?
This cartoon [Pope John Paul II] was controversial because they wanted to be so. That went very well and did not generate any ranks. Then there was a conservative movement within the church that wanted to make it a controversy, three weeks began to excite that, to make a petition. The man who led the Catholic forces said he expected a million signatures, but fortunately he got only 29,000, and the difference made the mountain not a mouse Parisse. It was even discussed at the Assembly [of the Republic]. It is a controversy a lot of little, even more, 30 years later, when the church itself is changing its point of view on this matter, namely with this Pope [Francis], fortunately. In the face of what led me to do this cartoon, I did it again. The Pope's statements at the time were public, they were not even hidden, inside walls, and spoke to the whole world, so also to me. I felt injured, that it made no sense. I think the Pope's attitude at that moment was criminal at the Pico da Aida and in Africa. It was of huge insensitivity and foolishness.
Is Cartoon a throwing weapon, a form of expression?
Throw of throwing is a hard expression of too much, but the cartoon is, in fact, the way I express myself. There are my colleagues who make articles, but I make drawings.
What other cartoons highlights, for what they brought you?
The first one that sensitized me was the one who made me win the world's largest salon in the world [major prize of the XX Salon International of Cartoon, Montreal, 1983], from this corner that is Portugal. A hall that had over a thousand participants, and gaining it was very good. I was safer, confident, because from then on they could continue to do things. This first cartoon also gave controversy, the “Warsaw Ghetto in Shatila”, in which I use the known photograph of the ghetto, a Jewish kid raised, harassed by Nazi soldiers, and in the cartoon the kid is Palestinian and Israeli soldiers. [The controversy was] with all the voices of the Jews, who are experts in this, making a lot of noise, with a certain tone of victimization, even if they are attacking. A hall director said he tried to change the vote, such is the weight of Jewish lobby, but failed.
This cartoon could be drawn today again.
I already published it again. Unfortunately it is not out of date.
But do you feel that much of what you designed about today is repeated, in a sign that the story is cyclical?
There is a resistance to change. One of the merits of the cartoonist is to be able to see ahead of time, or over time if you want. I have the invasion of Crimea made in 2014, and I assume that vision. It was above, and others did it later. There are other examples.
It begins to do cartoon after April 25, 1974, there a little there in the aftermath of the revolution. Do you feel that, in a way, has inaugurated the discipline of the Political Cartoon in Portugal?
Perhaps. But I'm not very clear about it, because before me there was a great designer, João Abel Manta, a fantastic chart, which had a huge difference from us, because we were kids and he already had a culture that allowed him that. But there is a less good side, because he did political propaganda. He was a man of the Portuguese Communist Party (PCP), and made this advertisement to where the revolution allowed it. Then when things stabilized, he went out and went to do other things. This does not remove the quality, but it is not my notion of Cartoon. I respond to the various stimuli of events otherwise. Cartoon allows me to express opinions, but be able to do so in different meanings of life, perspectives, without being a prisoner, as he became a prisoner of the PCP, was something that helped me a lot.
Did you ever feel any pressure from the newspapers where you collaborated?
(Hesitates). Some things, but they are not important. One thing I got, without much effort, was to make people think I have a bad shape, and it was better not to get me. It helped because they thought twice before talking to me. Once in Expresso, a type of sport commissioned me a cover, and began to give tips on how I should make the design. Until I asked you if I ever told you how to write news. This must have been in memory for many years, and must have reverberated this conversation in other people. I did not go to the Express, I was always in my corner and did not wear out with everyday life, with friendships and enmities.
Do you usually draw here at the studio?
Here. But this [the image of bad shape] really helped me. And there is also the story of me having another profession. I often say that I really had two professions, because I was a cartoonist and graphic designer, and then I had my clients who were also of the Express, namely the Tabaqueira. He was a friend of the commercial director, a comfortable type, who was staring to negotiate contracts with the newspaper in the name of A Tabaqueira. Therefore, I conveyed an effective image of power that actually did not have. If you add a type that has bad shape to a type that apparently has power, it is a boring (laughs).
When I ask you about the pressures, I think in the period right after April 25, 1974-1975, when everything was politicized. Were there bigger?
I managed to deal with it. During this period of the Prec (ongoing revolutionary process) it even had a cartoon over the need that lasted two years. It was a kind of escape forward. There was a great confusion, and I think it was interested in my newspaper [express], although that was never said. It gave an idea of ​​freshness of the newspaper about a complex period, but they never told me that. I have the idea of ​​this use of Cartoon, it was the way of consolidating the newspaper's independence regarding events, even when sometimes there was no such independence.
Are we today in a politically correct era, where everything seems to offend?
I don't feel, because I don't want to feel. I came to a phase of my life where if they didn't want to put up with me, they don't work. It's easy. Everything that was a struggle to impose a name and a point of view, a career, has already been made. It can be improved and consolidated, but if not, it is not. If I become very inconvenient for the newspaper where I work, and I want to believe this does not happen…
But in general terms, to the news, comments on social networks, do you feel that there is the politically correct?
Of course there is. My situation is of exception. The younger ones in the world of Cartoon have no opportunities at all. They have less than when I started. For various chances of life I have a position that has solidified, but this is not exemplary to what goes on. The new cartonists are full of trouble, there is no room for them, there is no means of payment. They are pushed to get out of the newspapers, not to enter.
Doesn't Cartoon have no place on social networks?
(Hesitates) It may appear, but it doesn't seem to me… Journalism is said to die and we cartoonists are going first. I think this is the trend. Journalism has been losing power in the face of social networks, with an anonymous opinion, which cannot be scrutinated, is very bad and mediocre. And that will grow.
What about Artificial Intelligence (AI)? Can replace the cartoonist.
This one I don't even speak because I do not know the limits, but I am intended to be terrible. It can indeed replace the cartoonist, but there is a subverting creativity.
Is there any public figure who particularly likes to portray in Cartoon?
The other day he said that, in relation to Trump, he had two antagonistic feelings: as a citizen, I find man detestable; But as a cartoonist is my raw material. Putin is also good. All men with many narratives and much power are likely to give good things from the point of view of analyzing a cartoonist. They are politicians with a very clear speech about what they want and what they want, and this can be good for Cartoon.
How do you feel to go to Macau again?
The exhibition [at the Military Club] will be different from the others, with 160 works. It's still a lot. It is a trip for these years, for Portuguese and international politics as well. I'm full of curiosity, promoting the show, seeing what they ask me, but this is part of the game.
The press of Macao does not have a great presence of Cartoon, except for Rodrigo [Rodrigo de Matos].
I know him, I get along with him. But I must say that the phenomenon is similar to Portugal. What do we have here? I, in the Express; Cristina Sampaio in the public; André Carrilho left the Diário de Notícias; António Maia in Correio da Manhã and little more. This is a general trend. Sometimes, and I think this happened to me, there are times when a cartoonist can represent a more value for the newspaper, but it's just a few moments when it can happen. In my most complicated period in Expresso, in the late 1970s, a reference newspaper that was in a country in convulsion, with some “irresponsibility” I could go ahead, and I have the perception that I helped the newspaper to detangle of these limitations. But this happens in very specific periods. In this phase [after April 25], I even made drawings at night that were already out of date.
Do you really have a bad shape or is it just to disguise?
I am shy, but I've been treating myself. (laughs) It was never something that had blocked me, I speak well in public. I'm a type I don't like to take stupid risks. I have been in this building for several years and I know only the gate because it has to be, and I do not want to have the risk of having an antipatic person to whom I confident. I do this with the greatest naturalness.
Military Club Exhibition
After the lecture at the Rui Cunha Foundation, this Wednesday, António will be today at the University of São José to talk to students at the “Cartoon Drawing: Ideas” workshop. This Friday follows the inauguration of the exhibition at the Military Club, which will be evident until January 2.</description><pubDate>2024-12-12 00:58:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Ben Lee, a game analyst, about the new concessions: “We need something grand”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2024/12/03/ben-lee-analista-de-jogo-sobre-as-novas-concessoes-precisamos-de-algo-grandioso/</link><description>The game analyst and consultant Ben Lee believes that it is necessary to do much more to diversify the economy of Macau beyond the game, especially given the type of events organized under the new concessions. The analyst thinks that Macau could look at two resorts in Vietnam as examples to follow international tourists
 
What balance do you do the two years of new game concessions?
There is still a lot of work to do. From what we could see so far, dealers have focused on lighter projects, such as local art galleries, cultural events, concerts and small rehabilitation of cultural neighborhoods. Large projects, such as the high -tech amusement park, the conservatory or new hotels have not yet been seen. Since two of the ten years have passed [concession], and given that the construction of some of these projects should take several years, it seems that it will be necessary to add them. The non-game segment revenues, in a percentage of gross revenue obtained by the dealers, seem to be higher than 2019, but have diminished in the last two years. It is possible to return to the next two years to be between the 10.5 and 11 percent verified in 2019.
Recently, Ho Iat Seng thanked the concessionaires for compliance with contracts and collaboration in the development of the non-game segment, reiterating that they were able to make some profits during the pandemic. Do you think it was fair in your words?
Casinos are making efforts to develop the non-game segment, but once again most of these efforts are focused on lower, lower-level events. We don't see great ideas like the $ 2.3 billion investment sphere we see in Las Vegas, for example. If that happened, it would easily fit the $ 15 billion commitments promised by the concessionaires [when signing the new contracts]. We could also talk about the idea of ​​making a Formula 1 competition on the street, as seen in Singapore and recently in Las Vegas.
How do you analyze the recovery of operators in terms of game revenue in recent months?
The recovery of the game in Macao has been extremely good, and the sector is expected to recover to about 78 or 79 percent of the levels recorded in 2019.
The Macao Game Society (SJM), for example, was one of the game operators with the greatest difficulty in terms of cash flow during the pandemic. Do you consider that your recovery, compared to the other five, was positive?
The SJM had difficulties at first, but it seems to be finally making some progress. But there will still be some challenges to reposition your hardware [facilities and other enterprises] in the future.
What can we expect from the new government of Sam Hou Fai for the game area?
The chief executive elected seems to be trying to ensure that operators honor their commitments. Your two terms will probably cover the next eight years of the new concessions. I think that, ultimately, everything will be known to know if he can motivate the various government appliances to perform his vision and mission.
In the context of new contracts, how do you see the global evolution of the game sector?
In 2019, the percentage of non-game segment revenues compared to the game's recipes reached 10.5 percent. This percentage rose to 22 percent during COVID-19, and has since gradually fallen to 13.5 percent, according to the third quarter of this year. This percentage will continue to decrease as game recipes continue to grow. In recent times we have seen residents of Macau and Hong Kong go to the north [China] to save money. The question that arises is why the inhabitants of the continent would go down and do the reverse? The solution, as provided by the authorities, is that Macau needs to diversify the market [of tourists and players] that comes from the continent. This makes perfect sense in terms of logic, but the reality is that our efforts seem to be regressing. Visitors from outside the Greater China represented 7.8 percent of the total visitors from Macao, but decreased to 6.5 percent by the end of September this year. This refers to the lightweight events that have been organized that, by far and largely, are really oriented to the Chinese who, after all, constitute most of our source of recipes.
How can you get around this scenario?
Returning to the beginning, I think we really need something large, iconic, similar to the sphere in Las Vegas or even something like the “Golden Bridge” project in Da Nang, worthy of appearing on Instagram, or “Bridge From the kiss ”, in Phu Quoc, both in Vietname. The fact that these projects were built by a local group linked to the hotel sector, without any connection to profits from the game, demonstrates long -term creativity and perspective in terms of planning.
Class struggle
Ben Lee warns of the mass market danger of “running away” from Macau
The conversation with Ben Lee comes in the context of a lecture that recently starred in the two years of new game concessions. Promoted by the France-Macau Chamber of Commerce, the session was named “Macau New Gaming Landscape: Two Years Into Concessions, What Now?”, Having Igamix Management &amp; Consulting, according to Asian Gaming Brief, according to the portal Gaming Brief (AgBrief), that the VIP game did not end completely, thus being the target of a new classification.
According to Agbrief, quoting words by Ben Lee, "the mass game incorporated the same [players] level that was so openly criticized by the government," but that operators "are changing their focus to accommodating it."
The analyst highlighted the "recent focus on the transformation of older and older hotel rooms into luxury options, with all operators understanding the need to get quality rather than quantity."
However, he argued that “the focus on the luxury segment continues to create an impasse” because “Macau has long focused on increasing the number of visitors to increase revenues”, but the business model “goes against the need to increase expenses per person ”.
Ben Lee also warned that many tourists could, in fact, start choosing other more affordable destinations. The analyst argued that mass players "cannot be ignored" as they remain "the main engine" of the sector. "Exorbitant prices from hotel rooms can be a" dam "for the increase of visitors," as, as suggested, "gamblers can go to other vacation places, such as Thailand, if the price is not good." This Asian country “is growing and is expected to exceed Singapore in terms of gross revenues” at a time when Thai work in the new legislation on the game.
“They hope to pass your game law in May next year. Starting from the principle this happens three to five years to build an integrated resort or enterprise. They may be working considerably before the opening of Japan, ”said Ben Lee.
Still in relation to the game market in Asia, the analyst pointed out that Asian gamblers will focus on the future game markets of Thailand and Japan "while enjoying the current offers in Macau, Singapore and Philippines," wrote Agbrief.</description><pubDate>2024-12-03 00:08:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion expropriated from any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnicidal violence and persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies inquired live below the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death , systematically carried out to this day (still in 2011 the Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the county).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and masquerade/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MOTOR EMBALISM | Rui Valente is not due</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/21/automobilismo-rui-valente-nao-se-da-por-vencido/</link><description>Rui Valente will return this year for another season in motorsport in the region. The Macao driver has been in the active for the same time and will play the Macau Roadsport Challenge, the tourist car competition organized by the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), as well as the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix , in November
 
With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive, in the 2025 season, a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit last November in the Macao Roadsport Challenge race. In the event held at the event of the territory, the Portuguese pilot finished sixth place, after losing some positions in the start, where he descended to tenth. The result was not even better because the rain -played race ended prematurely due to an opponent's accident.
In the competition for local pilots, which currently combines starting grids with more than half a hundred cars, all of them Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8), Rui Valente admitted to HM that “not being overcome”, revealing still who is “missing the podium, both in China and Macau…”.
Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the bet for this year will be in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
"At this time, I just wanted to increase the diameter of the front wheels and widen the gauge to improve the car's behavior," he confided to HM, also reporting that he intends to "optimize weight transmission during the curve and its. exit". These improvements, along with lock system updates, should increase the competitiveness of the Japanese machine in a fierce grid, consisting of Macau, Hong Kong pilots and China interior, with constantly evolving cars.
Undefined calendar
The AAMC -organized car competition calendar has not yet been revealed. In 2024, Macao Roadsport Challenge debuted at the Zhuzhou International Circuit in East of Hunan Province, but Rui Valente would rather the competition returned to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC) in Zhaoqing.
“I was very fond of returning to Gic, because I have everything there,” says the Portuguese pilot, defender of the track located in the neighboring province. “When you go to a qualification test, for those who make four races and then Macau, if you are on a track you already know, such as GIC, where you are seven or more years, each time you get on the track and try to do better than which last means you are improving and improving your driving. So you know you soon that you are stronger that year to Macau. ”
On the other hand, for the experienced pilot of the territory, “if you go to a new track, like the Zhuzhou circuit, besides floors there to learn the new layout and improve your time, you will never know if you are really stronger For Macao, as you know when you run in the gic. ”
Like what happened in past seasons, the Macau Roadsport Challenge calendar is expected to be composed of two weekends, with two races each, which also serve as an investigation for the Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-01-21 23:47:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Tennis | Nuno Borges will play in front of Alcaraz in the Australia Open</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/16/tenis-nuno-borges-vai-jogar-frente-a-alcaraz-no-open-da-australia/</link><description>Nuno Borges surpassed the nervousness to defeat Australian Jordan Thompson in three sets in the second round of Australia Open, and will now face 'Carlitos' Alcaraz without pressure, admitted the Portuguese tennis player to Lusa agency.
“I feel it was a good game on my part. Undoubtedly it was better than the first round, the sensations were there, ”he began by analyzing national number, in statements to Lusa, after moving to the third round of the first Grand Slam of the season.
The 27-year-old Maiato contradicted Wednesday the favoritism of the 'local' Jordan Thompson, 27th standard head, imposed on 6-3, 6-2 and 6-4 partials, in one hour and 47 minutes, in a John Cain Arena - the third most important court by Melbourne Park - crowded.
"It was very nervous, it was a big stadium, not every day [that happens], so I think within that I could make a very good game and I really am very happy for the result," he said.
Follow to Alcaraz
Semifinalist in Auckland at the start of the year, Borges has now extended his good moment, setting a meeting in the third round with Spanish Carlos Alcaraz, the third world player.
“Now, against 'Carlitos', there is not much to say. Everyone knows what he is capable of and everything he has done, [is] quite famous around the world, there is not much to highlight, ”he said about his opponent who, in Australia, seeks to become the younger Tennis player (is 21 years old) to complete the career Grand Slam.
In front of Spanish, the 33rd ATP ranking will try to do its best and "make it the most uncomfortable possible." "I will play without pressure, try not to put high expectations in my head to see if I can bring my best tennis," he concluded.
Last year, Nuno Borges, who will still start his walk in the pairs alongside Francisco Cabral, became the first Portuguese tennis player to reach the round of 16 at the Australia Open.</description><pubDate>2025-01-16 22:38:03</pubDate></item><item><title>FHO RACING | Peter Hickman denies closing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/07/fho-racing-peter-hickman-nega-encerramento/</link><description>Peter Hickman, four times winner of the Macao Motorcycle Grand Prix, denied the rumors that claimed that the team Racing, from Macau Faye Ho businesswoman, would have closed the doors and would be absent on the British Superbike Championship grid (BSB Championship ) and the Macao Grand Prix in 2025
 
Peter Hickman goes to the fifth season in the British Championship with Fho Racing, however, before the season's start, some rumors came to circulate in Paddock about the team's future. In recent years, FHO Racing has become one of the top teams in the British Superbike Championship and road events, such as the MAN's island TT or the Macao Grand Prix.
Last November, the team announced that they featured Peter Hickman and Davey Todd, winner of the troubled last edition of the Macao Grand Motor Prize in the British Superbike Championship. Faye Ho said at the time that “for 2025 and also for this year's Macao Grand Prix, we have a very strong team, with Davey joining Pete and Michael aboard the BMW. We have two super talented drivers on the roads for next season, and with Davey jumping to the Superbike class, after winning the Superstock Championship for the second time, I think we'll have a strong season. I can't expect my team to return to Macau, I love to share my hometown with the team and show all points of interest, it's such a special place for me. ”
Although Hickman and Todd have been present at the BMW Motorrad Motorsport season in Berlin in mid -January, since November that Fho Racing has no news, which has generated some discomfort and doubts among fans. Hickman was testing his BMW M1000RR of his phr Performance in Spain, when he responded with a blunt "no" to a fan of a fan on Instagram social network about the rumor of the ceiling of activity of FHO Racing, a "no" that " It had wide repercussions in the specialized British press.
It's not the first time
After a difficult season of his team in 2024 in the British Superbike Championship, Faye Ho, Stanley Ho's granddaughter, had to face similar rumors last September. In Oulton Park, before the opening race of the 2024 showdown, Faye Ho confirmed to journalists that FHO Racing would continue to participate in the British Superbike Championship of 2025, “which is good news, but anything will be announced to your time. But I'm happy to be back here and to stay here, it's a big championship and I love to be in this racing environment. ”
To increase speculation between fans, Hickman suggested on social networks a change of direction this year, leaving an announcement about his plans for the North West 200 and TT of the island of Man. In Spain, the British will have tested with the Your motorcycle without any reference and FHO Racing stickers, while Todd changed his profile photo on social networks, for a photo with a motorcycle from Milwaukee BMW by Tas Racing.
Sources of the world of motorcycling tell us that the future of the Racing should be known in the coming days, but one right thing is that Hickman, regardless of the team, has in his sports program to travel to MSAR in November, to try win the fifth victory in the guide circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-02-07 02:20:15</pubDate></item><item><title>GT Cup | Great Bay Race gains impulse from the interior</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/27/taca-gt-corrida-da-grande-baia-ganha-impulso-do-interior/</link><description>The GT Cup-Great Bay Race will be part of this year, the newly created Sro GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macau Grand Prix
 
On the eve of last Christmas, Sro Motorsport Group, the entity responsible for organizing numerous races and championships, including the GT World Challenge Asia and, as the official partner of the FIA, the co-coordination of the FIA ​​GT World Cup in Macau , announced the creation of a competition for GT4 vehicles, consisting of four events in China. At the time of the announcement, only the inaugural event in Shanghai and the end in Beijing had been confirmed as part of the calendar.
Almost 30 cars, representing an impressive total of ten automotive builders, participated in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race of 2024, a race that has become an important milestone over the weekend of the Macao Grand Prix in recent years. Indeed, no other GT4 event in Asia brings together such quantity and diversity of cars. The Balance of Performance (BOP), responsible for balancing the performance of the various participating cars, was, at the time, managed by SRO.
In a statement, Benjamin Frannasovici, managing director of Sro Motorsports Asia, said:
“We are enchanted, proud and privileged for adding the GT Cup - Great Bay Race to the inaugural calendar of Sro GT Cup, which begins and ends with the two largest motorized sports events in China. We already have a strong working relationship with the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, which has become the most significant race for GT4 cars in Asia. Its inclusion in the 2025 calendar of the SRO underlines the size of our ambition for this new national series. ”
High interest
The SRO GT Cup debut season starts in March at China's Formula 1 Grand Prix in Shanghai, before moving to the Zhuhai International Circuit - a place previously visited by SRO in BPR times and the FIA ​​GT Championship - where two 30 minutes races are planned. This is followed by the new Citadine Circuit of Beijing, which will host the GT World Challenge Asia on the same weekend, before the big end of the Sro GT Cup season, scheduled for a month later at the Guide Circuit in Macao.
The enthusiasm surrounding this competition is evident. As Benjamin Franassovici said, “This is reflected in the number of consultations and registration for the full season we have received since the release of the championship, just before Christmas. The demand has exceeded our expectations. ”
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the season end event on the streets of Macau, with places to be assigned based on the classification after the second round of the championship, which is scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit. All pilots with “bronze” or “silver” classifications attributed by the FIA ​​are eligible to compete in this competition, as long as they use approved cars from the GT4 class.
To attract brands, the results of SRO GT Cup races will tell the SRO GT4 builders ranking, a title attributed to the brand with better performance in the GT4 category at the end of each season. SRO GT CUP joins its Asian equivalent, Japan Cup, in a list that also includes continental and national competitions in Europe, America and Australia.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 11:13:41</pubDate></item><item><title>After “very positive meeting”, Borges “looking forward to playing at a stadium” with Thompson</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/14/apos-encontro-muito-positivo-borges-ansioso-por-jogar-num-estadio-com-thompson/</link><description>Portuguese tennis player Nuno Borges premiered yesterday, the 13th, at the 113rd edition of the Australia Open, first major of the time, with a “very positive meeting” against Frenchman Alexandre Muller in Melbourne Park, where he will now face Australian Jordan Thompson.
“I am very happy. It was a very positive meeting. I think, in general, I served very well, at least I managed to put the ball on the places where I wanted and have a good percentage (69%). I felt that I kept quite constant except in the tie-break of the first set, which I didn't play very well. I always kept looking for and very consistent during a meeting and this turned out to be the key to the result, ”he said in statements to Lusa.
The world's national and 33rd number one needed two hours and 55 minutes to get the best of the Gaul opponent, recently champion of the Hong Kong ATP 250, in four sets, by the 6-7 (2-7) partials (2-7) , 6-3, 6-2 and 7-5, but believes it has deserved the triumph, in the return to Melbourne, where a year ago became in the first Portuguese tennis player to reach the round of 16.
“I feel like I deserved to win in four sets, I was slightly higher from the first set and I'm very happy. The first rounds are never easy in terms of sensations. Tennis does not flow the same way, is trying to gain pace, but fortunately meetings at the best of five sets give more time to find this pace. I feel that I ended up the meeting quite well, although exhausting too, ”he explained.
After the inaugural round victory, Nuno Borges will “take the opportunity to rest and recover tomorrow to play possibly Wednesday” with a home player, Jordan Thompson (27th ATP), who today surpassed at Margaret Court Arena O 'Qualifier' German Dominik Koepfer also in four partials, 7-6 (7-3), 6-4, 4-6 and 6-3.
“I hope it's a good opportunity to play at a stadium possibly, I'm looking forward to it. We have played a long time ago [Estoril Open of 2021]. In 2024, he made a great season, very impressive and I know that he, here in Australia, competes very well, always available to play five sets. I know I'll have to play my best tennis and I'm waiting for another big challenge, maybe even more challenging than today, ”said Borges, winner of the only duel with Thompson.</description><pubDate>2025-01-14 16:15:44</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Luca Engstler still recovers from the accident</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/12/gp-macau-luca-engstler-ainda-recupera-do-acidente/</link><description>Although every year the Macau Grand Prix Organizing Committee puts a lot of resources and a lot of energy in the driver's safety, the Guide Circuit Continates, and will continue to be one of the most dangerous and risky in the world. This year, the young German Luca Engstler, who first participated in a GT3 car, felt the old maxim of this circuit in the skin: “The mistakes pay dearly”
 
After eight weeks after the most severe accident of his career, the 24 -year -old is still recovering from the apparent misfortune at the Cup of GT World Cup of the 71st Macao Grand Prix. On Friday afternoon, with the chronometer counting and when trying to improve his brand, Luca Engstler lost control of his Lamborghini Huracán GT3 Evo in the dreaded Mandarin curve, beating over 230 km/h in protective barriers. The car inscribed by the Liqui Moly Team Engstler, but prepared and ran by Grasser Racing Team, was completely destroyed and the German pilot even became unconscious after the impact.
“This is a unique event, Lamborghini's progress was not very good and to be ahead we had to risk more than the others. Basically, I was completely thoroughly and was unsuccessful, ”said Luca Engstler, at the time, the accident she suffered. Two months after what was “the most horrible day of my life to this day,” former German Touring Champion (TCR) is still in the recovery process.
“It was really a big impact,” Luca Engstler recalled, in conversation with the specialized portal motorsport-total.com, who needed a wheelchair after the accident. “The big problem was that my right ankle suffered a lot. I tore the lateral ligaments and had a lot of hemorrhages in tibia and fibula, which caused some concern, ”he recalled.
Returning to walk normally was also a big challenge for the young Lamborghini pilot, who in the 2024 season impressively won two DTM races and first participated in a GT3 car in Macao. "It took me a long time to be able to walk," he recalled. “In the first two or three days, I was really a wheelchair, because I just couldn't do anything and all the bones hurt me,” Engstler described to the publication of his country, saying that “he had bruises everywhere and everything was difficult ”.
Recover
Still, Lucas Engstler, at the end of the day of the accident, already at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, made a publication on social networks to say that everything was fine. The pilot, who was in Macao accompanied by his father, Franz Engstler - also a pilot and a well -known figure of Asian motorsport - wanted to reassure the closest. Two days after the accident, appeared on the GT da Fia World Cup starting grid on Sunday, without crutches, only slightly supported by an umbrella.
"What was important to me was not wanting to make a big sink about this," he explained to the Germanic portal. "In the end, the accident seemed very serious, but that only shows how safe the cars are," he said.
The pilot continues to recover from the sequelae of the strong impact. He took advantage of the winter break to take a trip from Autocaravana to Sweden with his best friend. "Everything is going well," he said, clarifying that he can run. "I would say I'm 95 percent and I have no permanent damage."
After the accident, the German worked on their recovery in the Allgäu region, in their homeland, “with some acquaintances, who are physiotherapists and doctors. I received excellent assistance. ”
Return
Luca Engstler admits that she has become impatient during the recovery process. "I was told that I could only do sports again in early February, but of course this could not accept," recognizing that he started training earlier than recommended.
Fortunately to Luca Engstler, DTM only starts on the last weekend of April. In the coming times, the pilot plans to sit back behind the wheel, possibly in a rental kart to start. The aim is to be in shape for the beginning of the preseason and the preparation tests of the popular German championship, scheduled for mid-February and early March.
As for the Macao Grand Prix, two days after the accident, Luca Engstler was quite clear: “I told everyone that my goal is to return and try to fight for victory in this great race.”</description><pubDate>2025-01-12 23:43:24</pubDate></item></channel></rss>