<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Tokyo | Chinese mne accused of misrepresenting meeting statements</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/toquio-mne-chines-acusado-de-deturpar-declaracoes-sobre-reuniao/</link><description>The Japanese government announced yesterday that it presented a formal protest to China for “misrepresented” observations made by Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba during a meeting with Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi.
Wang and Ishiba met last Friday in Tokyo, at a reception of courtesy organized by the Japanese leader, on the eve of a trilateral meeting between the Japan, South Korea and China foreign ministers, with the aim of promoting future cooperation between the three neighboring countries.
After the meeting, the Chinese Foreign Ministry issued a statement stating that Ishiba "fully recognizes the important meaning" of the four documents signed between the two nations, when the deciplind of diplomatic relations in 1972, and that the Japanese leader "respects the positions defined by the Chinese party."
Japan urged Beijing to “immediately withdraw” the statement, which “does not resist” the facts, yesterday said Japanese government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi at a press conference. Hayashi considered "unfortunate" that the Chinese government issued a statement that "does not correspond to the truth."
The Japanese Foreign Ministry also condemned the Chinese statement in a note, stating that during the meeting with Wang, Ishiba “stressed the need to reduce concerns” in bilateral relations, including “the situation in the east of China”, “ensuring the safety of Japanese citizens in China” and raising Chinese restrictions on Japanese seafood importation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:29:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Social Security | Coutinho defends the regime update</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/seguranca-social-coutinho-defende-actualizacao-do-regime/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho requires the government to review the Social Security System to cease to exist discrimination with the elderly with disabilities.
In the written interplies handed over to the Executive, the deputy and president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) spoke of one of the allegedly discriminatory situations, noting that “a citizen who, since youth, receives a subsidy for disability and reaches the elderly, should have the right to accumulate it with the elderly pension”.
In addition, Coutinho states that he has been confronted, through the Citizens Care Office, with "a growing number of support requests from disabled residents, especially those who, reaching the elderly, are faced with a significant reduction in income."
"This situation proves to be particularly alarming to those who are not entitled to the pensions of the elderly," he said.
According to the deputy, “disabled citizens who reach legal age to be considered elderly are, by definition, individuals who have long -term impediments, physical, mental, intellectual or sensory, limiting their full participation in society, on equal conditions for other elderly”.
Review the law
In this sense, the deputy says it is “imperative” that “the current norms governing the granting of pensions to disabled citizens who affect the elderly”, since “it is essential to ensure that all citizens, regardless of their condition, have access to rights that promote dignity and quality of life”.
"Considering that the relevant legislation is fundamental, in order to ensure that disabled citizens have the right to review the pension to the elderly, I question whether the government will update and modernize the current social security regime that is manifestly disabled taking into account the decade and a half of validity of Law 4/2010 [Social Security Regime]," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:27:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Legionella | Tourist in serious condition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/legionella-turista-em-estado-grave/</link><description>A 58 -year -old tourist is in serious condition due to a Legionella infection, known as Legionaries' disease. The infection was diagnosed on Saturday at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, and the patient has a history of chronic diseases.
According to the report presented by the health authorities, the man traveled inland with his family on 10 March. On the other side of the border went to the doctor, after having had fever but did not show improvements. He returned to Macao on March 19, having a shortage of breath, which made it entry into the Conde São Januário Hospital Center.
On March 20, the patient resorted to hospital medical assistance, having been diagnosed with pneumonia in both lungs, which led to the need to connect to the mechanical fan. The next day, the analyzes to the expectoration presented a positive result for Legionella, with complications for respiratory failure.
According to the SS, "currently, the patient is considered severe, and still needs respiratory support by mechanical fan." Authorities also indicated that family members did not have any symptom of malaise.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:13:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Letters Route | Cinema by Luís Filipe Rocha this week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/rota-das-letras-cinema-de-luis-filipe-rocha-esta-semana/</link><description>The Rota das Letras Literary Festival presents this week a series of films by Portuguese director Luís Filipe Rocha, including “Love and Fores de Fé”, adaptation of Henrique de Senna Fernandes's novel, filmed in Macao.
After the exhibition, yesterday, of "Gray and Black", in Capitol Cinema, today will be displayed, also in the same place, "Cerromior", from 18h, and "Love and Fores de Fé", from 21h. This Thursday will also be displayed “Signs of Fire” in the auditorium of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, from 20:30.
Also noteworthy is the exhibition, tomorrow, of a short film based on a tale of Valério Romão, one of the festival guests, followed by the projection of a documentary about Natália Correia, by Rosa Coutinho Cabral. The session is attended by one of the acts that make up the cast of this documentary, Alexandra Sargento.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:24:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Pass | Thousands of elderly people carried a card for discounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/macau-pass-milhares-de-idosos-carregaram-cartao-para-descontos/</link><description>Early in the early hours of the morning, seniors formed lines at the door of the services to change or carry Macau Pass cards and access the discounts of the great consumption award. Until 1pm, more than 22,200 elderly people had already enjoyed the benefits of the consumption incentive program
 
Even before opening the doors, a line with about half hundred people was at the entrance of the Macau Pass Service Center in the Preta Areia, announcing the beginning of another round of the consumption award, which began yesterday.
Before starting the initiative to distribute consumer coupons to residents, to boost local businesses in neighborhoods away from tourist circuits, more than 10,000 residents asked to change Macau Pass to the elderly, 6,000 of which already had the card ready to use. The rest, in addition to residents who wanted to charge the card to access the 300 -Patacas automatic discount and start benefiting from the 50 percent discount on purchases, have been hosted on Macau Pass stores, as well as the various service stations to carry the cards.
The Director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, revealed that until 1 pm yesterday, more than 22,200 elderly people had already taken advantage of discounts under the initiative, according to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau. The official said the process was running without problems.
However, some elderly people waiting in the center of the center of Macau Pass in the black sand indicated that the earlier opening of the store would have made life easier for residents. An elderly woman said to the public broadcaster that she took off to the store to receive the new card, but that the place was full of residents who wanted to carry the card, see her balance, order second cards of cards, which resulted in a situation chaotic. In the immediate vicinity of the Macau Pass Service Center in the Preta Areia, the resident line clogged buildings of buildings, shops and parking parks.
Attention to fraud
The DSEDT director also stated that the government will be aware of fraudulent activities during the consumer incentive campaign and that a supervision mechanism was created together with financial institutions with payment applications to prevent consumers from buying something online to access the draw and then cancel the transaction. If activities of this genre are detected, residents will be prevented from participating in the coupon draw for the fraudulent transaction.
The president of the Macao Commercial Association, Frederico MA Chi Ngai, was optimistic about the impact of the major consumption award on small and medium enterprises. The leader of the association that organizes the initiative with the government advanced to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau that about a hundred traders plans to add a discount campaign to the consumer incentive program, and that more traders are expected to follow the example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:12:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Maternity | APPLIED ATTRIBUTION OF FAMILY ASSEMBLY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/maternidade-pedida-atribuicao-de-abonos-de-familia/</link><description>Given the fall of birth, the associations ask the government of Sam Hou Fai to increase the number of support to families. In addition to the birth allowance, currently 5,418 Patacas, the creation of a family allowance and the extent of maternity and paternity licenses are asked
 
The General Association of Macao Women and the People's Youth Association have defended the assignment of families' allowances to help local families face increasing financial charges.
Through a statement, Loi I Weng, vice president of the Association of Women, indicated that there are currently about 23 provinces in the interior to distribute subsidies. For example, the city Hefei, in Anhui province, distributes a single allowance to couples with two or three children, with a value from 2,000 Renminbis to 5,000 Renminbis. In turn, the authorities of the city Jinan, in the province of Shandong, distribute monthly support to families who have two or three children of 600 Renminbis per child, until they have three years.
In Macao, Loi I Weng acknowledged that there is a birth allowance, currently in the amount of 5,418 patacas. However, LOI argues that the amount must be increased and the distribution of a family allowance must be considered, having as reference the value of the allowance for caregivers or the family of civil servants, which have the value of 2,175 patacas and 940 patacas, respectively.
For its part, the vice president of the Tam Sio Pang Youth Association also defended the idea of ​​childhood assistance.
Heard by the newspaper or Mun, the head of the Macao's Subordinate Alliance Association suggested that the government should follow the practice of the Hohhot city, the capital of the Autonomous Region of Mongolia Interior, which offers a unique subsidy worth 10,000 Renminbis to couples who have a child. When couples have two children receive about 50,000 Renminbis over 5 years, and if they have three children receive 100,000 Renminbis over 10 years.
Other requests
In addition to the subsidy, associations officials argued that it is also important for the government to launch other measures to create a “more favorable environment” to increased birth rate.
Loi I Weng suggested to the government to subsidize companies to implement work measures to support workers' families. In addition, the official considers that the government extend the license of maternity and paternity so that residents have less concerns about birth.
Tam Sio Pang also wants the extent of maternity and paternity license and argues that maternity leave should be increased to 90 days compared to 70 days. Tam Sio Pang also suggested that the government increase vacancies in subsidized day care centers, as well as a gradual integration of child care services into the free education system.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:09:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Leong Sun Iok wants protection for “false collaborators”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/trabalho-leong-sun-iok-quer-proteccao-para-falsos-colaboradores/</link><description>The Fan deputy warns of the abuse of the independent work regime, which can be used by employer entities to avoid obligations, such as the acquisition of insurance
 
Deputy Leong Sun IOK intends that the government present new measures to protect “false employees”, that is, workers who are hired for independent services on paper, but in practice they are under the authority of the employer. The subject was approached through a written interpellation, released yesterday by the office of the legislator linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom).
According to the scenario reported by Leong Sun Iok, it is becoming increasingly normal in Macau employers to resort to false employees, as "the market is limited and many people can only work this way." Without options, workers end up accepting the proposals.
Under normal conditions, employees provide a service, and can choose when and how they work, being the most relevant to present the result for which they were hired. However, under the conditions reported by the deputy, in practice, workers are required to follow working hours established by the boss and his instructions, typical characteristics of the dependent worker regime. For the bosses, although this performance is illegal, the regime has the advantage of allowing expenses arising from the guarantee of labor rights.
As such, Leong Sun Iok asks the executive to "verify that employers are resorting to this possibility as a means to run away from the responsibilities and duties of the employment relationship."
One more study
The deputy of the parliamentary bench of Faom asks to follow the example of the interior of China, to increase the protection of these workers. To this end, it argues that it is necessary to “study how to ensure workers' professional guarantees on their own and liberal professionals”, and “encourage employers to acquire work insurance for their workers with service contracts”.
The member of the Legislative Assembly also asks the government to be aware of the emergence of “new employment modalities”.
At the interpetement, it is also requested to perform “an inquiry into the number and types of workers on their own and existing liberal professionals” in the territory to “safeguard the professional rights and interests of workers”.
On the other hand, Leong indicates that in Macau there is always an employment contract, regardless of the designation of the contract, when it is required to the “collaborator” who is “available” to perform the duties at the employer's request. Therefore, it asks the government if it will issue clear instructions and strengthen disclosure actions on the Macao labor regime to “avoid breach of law by employers and safeguard workers' rights and interests”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:07:17</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE | Sam Hou Fai gathers with Deputy Minister Hua Chunying</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/mne-sam-hou-fai-reune-se-com-a-vice-ministra-hua-chunying/</link><description>The chief executive received at the government headquarters the deputy minister of foreign business, Hua Chunying, to whom he requested support in the expansion of relations with the abroad. Sam Hou Fai pointed to the Portuguese -speaking, Spanish and Southeast Asia markets
 
The chief executive received on Sunday at the headquarters of the Government of Masters a delegation of representatives of the central government led by the Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs, Hua Chunying, according to a statement released on Sunday night by the office of social communication.
During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai and Hua Chunying exchanged impressions about the implementation of the proper diversification of Macau's economy, namely through strengthening and “even greater expansion of relations with the outside”.
The Chief Executive highlighted Macao's “great historical and cultural wealth”, trinks that allow the territory to serve as “a platform for communication and cooperation between the country and the abroad”. Regarding government goals, Sam Hou Fai said it will “strengthen and expand their relations with the outside, especially Portuguese -speaking, Southeast Asia markets”, in order to promote “further the proper diversification of the Macao economy”. To achieve such objectives, the Leader of the Government of MSAR said it hoped "that the Ministry of Foreign Affairs could support during the process."
Natural habitat
In addition to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, also the commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China in the Special Administrative Region of Macau, Liu Xianfa, attended the meeting, to whom Sam Hou Fai thanked “support on all issues related to abroad”.
The chief executive also stressed that Macau is "a prosperous, stable, peaceful and harmonious society," and "a successful example of the implementation of" one country, two systems. "
Hua Chunying's international notoriety rose considerably during the period when he was a spokesman for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. At the end of May last year, the Council of State announced its appointment as Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:59:05</pubDate></item><item><title>History | Lara Reis, Professor of Macao High School, remembered in Lisbon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/historia-lara-reis-professor-do-liceu-de-macau-recordado-em-lisboa/</link><description>The former teacher of the Macao High School Fernando Lara Reis was remembered in the “Spring Conferences”, from the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center, by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira. A native of Leiria, Lara Reis fought in the 1st World War and lived on Avenida da República, in the villa that today houses the Macau Red Cross house
 
Fernando Lara Reis was born in 1892 and died in 1950. Throughout a life filled with historical events and testimonies, the natural man of Leiria was a military man and a teacher at Macao High School, eventually making the territory his home.
Lara Reis's life was recently remembered at the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira, herself to her former teacher in the territory.
At the session, the historian, who won the 2024 Macao International Institute Identity Award (IIM), recalled the “teacher, meritorious, driving of the arts”, and owner of “unusual knowledge”.
“He was a native of Leiria and lived in Macao until his death. He attended Leiria High School, the Military College, then joined the Army School. In World War I was in Elvas, and then left to Angola in 1915 when he faced the German threat over Portuguese colonies in Africa. Observer-Aviator. ”
Lara Reis was never a pilot as she wanted, having dedicated much of her life to teaching and Macao. “In 1919, Lara Reis went to Macao High School. He took a long circum-gap trip, leaving Portugal from Lisbon, going to the United States of America, crossed the entire territory and then went to Japan, down to Hong Kong and even Macau. He was a teacher in Macao, drawing, handicrafts and gymnastics until the end of his life,” said Celina Veiga de Oliveira.
The historian took to the session some written testimonies left by other Macao figures who wrote about Lara Reis, namely Monsignor Manuel Teixeira in the book “Macao Lyceu”. He said he never found "no teacher who had served the High School with greater dedication."
“He was a rigorous methodical teacher, whose military formation was certainly not oblivious to these characteristics. What was truly standing out was his artistic vein, because Lara Reis was always concerned with ascertaining the aesthetic meaning of the students and opening their mental horizons. This at the time when Macau was a small town. that he organized and also exhibitions by Portuguese and foreign artists he sponsored, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira also highlighted the words left by the writer Henrique de Senna Fernandes in an interview on "one of the greatest qualities of Lara Reis", which "besides rigor and discipline, was the consideration by the students, not distinguishing rich from the poor."
Professor Lara Reis was "a party prosecutor who served to obtain tuition fees for needy students," and "he is due to the initiative of the creation of the High School Association, of which he was the first president." This association organized in the former canhydrome “sports parties of the end of the year when students performed the most difficult exercises”.
Work done in Macau
The historian also highlighted “another aspect of dedication to territory” by Lara Reis. The Leiriense "participated in the First World War and this led him to interest all those who were incorporated into this conflict, having founded the League of the Great War fighters and had built in the cemetery of St. Miguel Archangel the monument where the bodies of combatants rest."
Moreover, "another facet of his personality was a taste for travel, because he had no family and thus left for the world." "I visited museums, art schools and photographed everything I saw, having created a estate with 32 volumes that is now a heritage of Leiria."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira did not forget the old “Sol Pente” villa, located in the middle-leaf zone, namely the Avenida da República, which was the house of Lara Reis, later donated to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao to “an anti-cancer clinic that was the first institution of the genre in the Portuguese colonial space”. Today this villa serves as a house to the Red Cross of Macao, and on its walls you can find a stone with the following message: “In this building legacy by the Rotary Fernando Reis to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao, it was installed at the initiative of the Rotary Club of Macao the first anti-cancer fighting center on April 15, 1951.”
“Change of Ares”
When Fernando Lara Reis goes to Macao, political times are troubled, with the political agitation to be lived in China after the fall of the Empire and the Republican Revolution of 1911.
"In the 1920s the nationalist shock waves lived in the Canton, which sometimes haunted the Portuguese enclave quiet, but never moved with everyday life. The Portuguese administration guaranteed a standard appearance, and the parties at Christmas, Chinese New Year, the religious festivities of the Catholic community and the Chinese population were habitual."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recalled that in the late 1920s, Lara Reis decided to transfer to Goa, a trip that would only accentuate her belonging to Macau.
“In the late 1920s, he felt he was time to change his air and asked to be transferred to the Afonso de Albuquerque High School in Pangim, and was there between 1941 and 1945, taking the opportunity to know India, and met the whole country. Instead, with a graceful and already sick license, choosing Macau to be his last address, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recordou também as palavras de Orlando Cardoso, que no artigo “Macau e o Oriente na vida de Lara Reis” falou do homem que se deslumbrou com Macau “a partir do momento em que, às 8 horas da noite de 23 de Outubro de 1919, avistou pela primeira vez o Farol da Guia, um pouco antes de se instalar no ‘New Macao Hotel’ e sorver de sentidos atentos os sons, os cheiros e as luzes desta porta of an immeasurable and fantastic Asia that he would describe to exhaustion. ”
These Lara Reis testimonies are “in a remarkable set of travel books that lay virtually unexplored in all their research potentialities on the shelves of the Leiria District Archive”, and were investigated by Orlando Cardoso himself.
In the same article, this one refers to a text from the newspaper “News of Macau” of January 17, 1950, about Lara Kings: “The Auster and Worsen Teacher; the tenacious and thorough tourist; the military who fought and consecrated the memory of those who fell in the field of struggle; the honest and firm friend; the lovely and humorous companion; social celibate that, despite this, did not disdain any opportunity to undo its gallants, always kind and inconsequential to any palm with a face that in the goto ”.
Given the few studies that exist about Lara Reis and the estate he left, Celina Veiga de Oliveira left a suggestion: "May the CCCM get the detailed index of the Leiria Archive, so that the research is possible for any interested researchers."</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:57:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Tokyo | Chinese mne accused of misrepresenting meeting statements</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/toquio-mne-chines-acusado-de-deturpar-declaracoes-sobre-reuniao/</link><description>The Japanese government announced yesterday that it presented a formal protest to China for “misrepresented” observations made by Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba during a meeting with Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi.
Wang and Ishiba met last Friday in Tokyo, at a reception of courtesy organized by the Japanese leader, on the eve of a trilateral meeting between the Japan, South Korea and China foreign ministers, with the aim of promoting future cooperation between the three neighboring countries.
After the meeting, the Chinese Foreign Ministry issued a statement stating that Ishiba "fully recognizes the important meaning" of the four documents signed between the two nations, when the deciplind of diplomatic relations in 1972, and that the Japanese leader "respects the positions defined by the Chinese party."
Japan urged Beijing to “immediately withdraw” the statement, which “does not resist” the facts, yesterday said Japanese government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi at a press conference. Hayashi considered "unfortunate" that the Chinese government issued a statement that "does not correspond to the truth."
The Japanese Foreign Ministry also condemned the Chinese statement in a note, stating that during the meeting with Wang, Ishiba “stressed the need to reduce concerns” in bilateral relations, including “the situation in the east of China”, “ensuring the safety of Japanese citizens in China” and raising Chinese restrictions on Japanese seafood importation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:29:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Social Security | Coutinho defends the regime update</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/seguranca-social-coutinho-defende-actualizacao-do-regime/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho requires the government to review the Social Security System to cease to exist discrimination with the elderly with disabilities.
In the written interplies handed over to the Executive, the deputy and president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) spoke of one of the allegedly discriminatory situations, noting that “a citizen who, since youth, receives a subsidy for disability and reaches the elderly, should have the right to accumulate it with the elderly pension”.
In addition, Coutinho states that he has been confronted, through the Citizens Care Office, with "a growing number of support requests from disabled residents, especially those who, reaching the elderly, are faced with a significant reduction in income."
"This situation proves to be particularly alarming to those who are not entitled to the pensions of the elderly," he said.
According to the deputy, “disabled citizens who reach legal age to be considered elderly are, by definition, individuals who have long -term impediments, physical, mental, intellectual or sensory, limiting their full participation in society, on equal conditions for other elderly”.
Review the law
In this sense, the deputy says it is “imperative” that “the current norms governing the granting of pensions to disabled citizens who affect the elderly”, since “it is essential to ensure that all citizens, regardless of their condition, have access to rights that promote dignity and quality of life”.
"Considering that the relevant legislation is fundamental, in order to ensure that disabled citizens have the right to review the pension to the elderly, I question whether the government will update and modernize the current social security regime that is manifestly disabled taking into account the decade and a half of validity of Law 4/2010 [Social Security Regime]," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:27:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Legionella | Tourist in serious condition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/legionella-turista-em-estado-grave/</link><description>A 58 -year -old tourist is in serious condition due to a Legionella infection, known as Legionaries' disease. The infection was diagnosed on Saturday at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, and the patient has a history of chronic diseases.
According to the report presented by the health authorities, the man traveled inland with his family on 10 March. On the other side of the border went to the doctor, after having had fever but did not show improvements. He returned to Macao on March 19, having a shortage of breath, which made it entry into the Conde São Januário Hospital Center.
On March 20, the patient resorted to hospital medical assistance, having been diagnosed with pneumonia in both lungs, which led to the need to connect to the mechanical fan. The next day, the analyzes to the expectoration presented a positive result for Legionella, with complications for respiratory failure.
According to the SS, "currently, the patient is considered severe, and still needs respiratory support by mechanical fan." Authorities also indicated that family members did not have any symptom of malaise.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:13:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Letters Route | Cinema by Luís Filipe Rocha this week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/rota-das-letras-cinema-de-luis-filipe-rocha-esta-semana/</link><description>The Rota das Letras Literary Festival presents this week a series of films by Portuguese director Luís Filipe Rocha, including “Love and Fores de Fé”, adaptation of Henrique de Senna Fernandes's novel, filmed in Macao.
After the exhibition, yesterday, of "Gray and Black", in Capitol Cinema, today will be displayed, also in the same place, "Cerromior", from 18h, and "Love and Fores de Fé", from 21h. This Thursday will also be displayed “Signs of Fire” in the auditorium of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, from 20:30.
Also noteworthy is the exhibition, tomorrow, of a short film based on a tale of Valério Romão, one of the festival guests, followed by the projection of a documentary about Natália Correia, by Rosa Coutinho Cabral. The session is attended by one of the acts that make up the cast of this documentary, Alexandra Sargento.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:24:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | G-Dragon starred in two concerts in June</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/galaxy-g-dragon-protagoniza-dois-concertos-em-em-junho/</link><description>The Galaxy Arena, one of the main show rooms in the territory, is preparing to receive two concerts from the South Korean rapper and composer G-Dragon, integrated into the “Ubermensch” tour, which also goes through other Asian cities. This is the opportunity for the local audience to see and listen to one of the sleepless names of South Korean music
 
G-Dragon, Kwon Ji-Yong's stage name, is a 36-year-old South Korean rapper and songwriter who, in June, named after 7 and 8, comes Macao for two shows at the Cotai Galaxy Arena, who promise to delight fans or lovers of South Korea music.
The two shows are part of the “übermensch” tour, which means superhuman, and which goes through several Asian cities, namely Tokyo, on May 10 and 11; Bulacan, in the Philippines, on May 17; Osaka, on May 25 and 26 and then Taipei, Kuala Lumpur and Jakarta, in July.
Highlighted by Forbes magazine in 2016, as the most influential person in Asia's entertainment industry under 30, G-Dragon is linked to the world of the show and the arts since childhood, as his first television appearance took place on the children's “BBO BBO BBO” children's program. At the age of six he joined the children's group “Litlle Roo'ra”. Over the years he bet on rap, also becoming a composer, entrepreneur and fashion designer.
His connection to hip hop was gradual, having integrated in 2006 the boys-band "Big Bang", releasing the solo album "Heartbreaker" in 2009, which included a song of the same name. Success felt right there, as it was recognized as the “album of the year” at Mnet Asian Music Awards. The following year, 2010, was already part of another musical group, the “T.O.P.”, which released an album of the same name, also another of success.
The first G-Dragon worldwide diffress took place in 2013, calling itself “One of a Kind World Tour”, and that same year it released its second studio album, “Coup d'Atat”, which was also worth recognizing criticism.
With regard to the musical style, G-Dragon says he is inspired by the Wu-Tang Clan group and the American Pharrell Williams, which is his "musical hero." Other hip-hop names, such as Kanye West, count on your reference list.
A kind of revolution
According to Tatler Asia magazine, Kwon Ji-Yong managed to innovate and “transcend the traditional borders of Asian pop star”, turning everything into “creative gold” into musical terms.
It is classified by this publication as a chameleon in the music world, and in almost 20 years of career it was “a virtuous musician, provocative of fashion and an innovative entrepreneur” who caught the attention of fans. It presents “avant-garde clothing” that wear “an artistic genius whose professional trajectory permanently altered the DNA of Korean entertainment”, writes Tatler on G-Dragon.
About the fashion designer aspect, it is described that G-Dragon does much more than wearing such “avant-garde clothing”, turning them into “cultural statements”, having been Chanel's first Asian global ambassador.
In the fashion week in Paris, the South Korean rapper dared to wear women's tweed coats, transposing the limits of the gender. G-Dragon recently adopted an aesthetics called the "Grandma-Core", which includes the use of head scarves and a red-haired hair. It may or may not shock, but the style remains.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:22:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Increased defense expenses on the gutter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/taiwan-aumento-de-despesas-com-defesa-na-calha/</link><description>Taiwan announced yesterday that he will try to use accumulated surpluses in previous years to cover the increase in the defense budget announced by Taiwanese leader William Lai, who promised to increase military expenses to more than 3 percent of GDP.
In a parliamentary comparison, the head of the Taiwan government's Directorate of Budget, Accounting and Statistics, Chen Shu-Tzu, ensured that the executive will seek to finance this increase with an excess of 200 billion Taiwanese, without excluding the contraction of loans as a last appeal.
"In general, we hope not to get into debt. But if we have to stray, we have to do so, because the defense expenses are very important," he said, quoted by the state news agency CNA.
Taiwan's defense budget is currently around the Taiwanese $ 600 billion, after the oppositionist parliament, approving a number of budget cuts and freezes regarding the government's initial proposal.
Lai, considered a “independentist” and a “hunting” by the Chinese government, reiterated her intention to increase Taiwan's military expenses last Thursday to more than 3 percent of GDP this year, amid added tensions between Taipei and Beijing.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:28:26</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM | Open registrations for 30 jobs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/sjm-abertas-inscricoes-para-30-empregos/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) has announced that today open the registrations for the “Professional Development Plan in Guided Visit Service in SJM activities”, on a “First Hiring, After Training” regime, which will provide job opportunities with 30 job openings for the “Guided View Agent in activities” category.
Admitted candidates will receive vocational training for 18 months, divided between the Hotel Operations Department and the Activities Planning Department. The training includes initiation to arts and culture, practical English of Cambridge Linguaskills (Oral) - English conversation training course for the service provision sector, Forbes Travel Guide - Basic Excellence Training in the Guided Tour Service and Course.
Those who have good use in the evaluations and pass the training phase can continue their professional career in one of the departments mentioned. Interested parties can register on the DSAL page until April 1st.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:10:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Japanese government announced yesterday that it presented a formal protest to China for “misrepresented” observations made by Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba during a meeting with Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi.
Wang and Ishiba met last Friday in Tokyo, at a reception of courtesy organized by the Japanese leader, on the eve of a trilateral meeting between the Japan, South Korea and China foreign ministers, with the aim of promoting future cooperation between the three neighboring countries.
After the meeting, the Chinese Foreign Ministry issued a statement stating that Ishiba "fully recognizes the important meaning" of the four documents signed between the two nations, when the deciplind of diplomatic relations in 1972, and that the Japanese leader "respects the positions defined by the Chinese party."
Japan urged Beijing to “immediately withdraw” the statement, which “does not resist” the facts, yesterday said Japanese government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi at a press conference. Hayashi considered "unfortunate" that the Chinese government issued a statement that "does not correspond to the truth."
The Japanese Foreign Ministry also condemned the Chinese statement in a note, stating that during the meeting with Wang, Ishiba “stressed the need to reduce concerns” in bilateral relations, including “the situation in the east of China”, “ensuring the safety of Japanese citizens in China” and raising Chinese restrictions on Japanese seafood importation.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Houcong (1507-67), Emperor Jiajing devoting much of his time to his own person, discovered the state's affairs, delegating them in the corrupt Yan Song (1480-1567) who, among other infamies, would have a recognized righteous man who denounced him in a memorial sent to the monarch where his resignation proposed.
This is called this poet literate and painter Yang Jisheng (1516-1555). The animadversion he felt in the face of injustice, risking his life to tell the truth, did not allow him to falter. Late on the night of December 2, 1553, feeling grateful for so many things that life had given him, in a conversation with his wife, Mrs. Zhang, who installed him to avoid the conflict given the impossibility of counteracting Yan Song's power, he replied that this was the way he had to pay all the assets he had received, as he recalled in a chronological biography (Nianpu).
And yet, like many celebrated literati, he had also suffered exile on the distant margins of the Empire. It was in the course of one of these days in 1551 that, moved by the beauty of a landscape, made the painting traveling along the roller coaster (vertical roll, paint on paper, 147.5 x 39.5 cm, sold on Sotheby's) where he reveals his scholarship in the art of painting the literati in which the painted figure tends to the abstraction and the accompanying poem.
In front of the mountain, whose name can be translated as "the heavenly beauty," he writes:
«The Tianhua Mountain is not too far west of the provincial city walls,/ which chases admire these climbing blue-peeled blue clutches and rocks of a red-red!/ Towers and pavilions settle to the mutant shapes of the descent and climbed the mountain,/ shadows of flags and shamelies up and down the trees. shining against the vision of the clean sky,/ clouds entering; One could catch one with the sleeve.
Yang Jisheng made in this painting a literate traveling in a river on a vessel that is suddenly alerted by the boatman who with a staff points to houses nested on the mountain. As on an album page that signed Jiaoshan, "Pepper Mountain" (PAPER, 27 x 35 cm ink, sold in the auctioneer Nagel) represented a home hung on top of a mountain, would say the figuration of its search for a place in the world, which would after all to refuse it.
In the night that preceded his execution he wrote a famous pair of verses, in a practice known as Juemingshi, "poem of a cut life", which seeks to make a brief reflection on the meaning of his own life: "Iron Shoulders, to carry the length and the way,/ the pungent hand to writing ingeniously."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Houcong (1507-67), Emperor Jiajing devoting much of his time to his own person, discovered the state's affairs, delegating them in the corrupt Yan Song (1480-1567) who, among other infamies, would have a recognized righteous man who denounced him in a memorial sent to the monarch where his resignation proposed.
This is called this poet literate and painter Yang Jisheng (1516-1555). The animadversion he felt in the face of injustice, risking his life to tell the truth, did not allow him to falter. Late on the night of December 2, 1553, feeling grateful for so many things that life had given him, in a conversation with his wife, Mrs. Zhang, who installed him to avoid the conflict given the impossibility of counteracting Yan Song's power, he replied that this was the way he had to pay all the assets he had received, as he recalled in a chronological biography (Nianpu).
And yet, like many celebrated literati, he had also suffered exile on the distant margins of the Empire. It was in the course of one of these days in 1551 that, moved by the beauty of a landscape, made the painting traveling along the roller coaster (vertical roll, paint on paper, 147.5 x 39.5 cm, sold on Sotheby's) where he reveals his scholarship in the art of painting the literati in which the painted figure tends to the abstraction and the accompanying poem.
In front of the mountain, whose name can be translated as "the heavenly beauty," he writes:
«The Tianhua Mountain is not too far west of the provincial city walls,/ which chases admire these climbing blue-peeled blue clutches and rocks of a red-red!/ Towers and pavilions settle to the mutant shapes of the descent and climbed the mountain,/ shadows of flags and shamelies up and down the trees. shining against the vision of the clean sky,/ clouds entering; One could catch one with the sleeve.
Yang Jisheng made in this painting a literate traveling in a river on a vessel that is suddenly alerted by the boatman who with a staff points to houses nested on the mountain. As on an album page that signed Jiaoshan, "Pepper Mountain" (PAPER, 27 x 35 cm ink, sold in the auctioneer Nagel) represented a home hung on top of a mountain, would say the figuration of its search for a place in the world, which would after all to refuse it.
In the night that preceded his execution he wrote a famous pair of verses, in a practice known as Juemingshi, "poem of a cut life", which seeks to make a brief reflection on the meaning of his own life: "Iron Shoulders, to carry the length and the way,/ the pungent hand to writing ingeniously."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Houcong (1507-67), Emperor Jiajing devoting a lot of his time to his own person, discovered the state's affairs, delegating them in the corrupt Yan Song (1480-1567) who, among other infamies, would have a recognized righteous man who denounced him in a memorial sent to the monarch where his resignation proposed.
This is called this poet literate and painter Yang Jisheng (1516-1555). The animadversion he felt in the face of injustice, risking his life to tell the truth, did not allow him to falter. Late on the night of December 2, 1553, feeling grateful for so many things that life had given him, in a conversation with his wife, Mrs. Zhang, who installed him to avoid the conflict given the impossibility of counteracting Yan Song's power, he replied that this was the way he had to pay all the assets he had received, as he recalled in a chronological biography (Nianpu).
And yet, like many celebrated literati, he had also suffered exile on the distant margins of the Empire. It was in the course of one of these days in 1551 that, moved by the beauty of a landscape, made the painting traveling along the roller coaster (vertical roll, paint on paper, 147.5 x 39.5 cm, sold on Sotheby's) where he reveals his scholarship in the art of painting the literati in which the painted figure tends to the abstraction and the accompanying poem.
In front of the mountain, whose name can be translated as "the heavenly beauty," he writes:
«The Tianhua Mountain is not too far west of the provincial city walls,/ which chases admire these climbing blue-peeled blue clutches and rocks of a red-red!/ Towers and pavilions settle to the mutant shapes of the descent and climbed the mountain,/ shadows of flags and shamelies up and down the trees. shining against the vision of the clean sky,/ clouds entering; One could catch one with the sleeve.
Yang Jisheng made in this painting a literate traveling in a river on a vessel that is suddenly alerted by the boatman who with a staff points to houses nested on the mountain. As on an album page that signed Jiaoshan, "Pepper Mountain" (PAPER, 27 x 35 cm ink, sold in the auctioneer Nagel) represented a home hung on top of a mountain, would say the figuration of its search for a place in the world, which would after all to refuse it.
In the night that preceded his execution he wrote a famous pair of verses, in a practice known as Juemingshi, "poem of a cut life", which seeks to make a brief reflection on the meaning of his own life: "Iron Shoulders, to carry the length and the way,/ the pungent hand to writing ingeniously."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Japanese government announced yesterday that it presented a formal protest to China for “misrepresented” observations made by Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba during a meeting with Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi.
Wang and Ishiba met last Friday in Tokyo, at a reception of courtesy organized by the Japanese leader, on the eve of a trilateral meeting between the Japan, South Korea and China foreign ministers, with the aim of promoting future cooperation between the three neighboring countries.
After the meeting, the Chinese Foreign Ministry issued a statement stating that Ishiba "fully recognizes the important meaning" of the four documents signed between the two nations, when the deciplind of diplomatic relations in 1972, and that the Japanese leader "respects the positions defined by the Chinese party."
Japan urged Beijing to “immediately withdraw” the statement, which “does not resist” the facts, yesterday said Japanese government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi at a press conference. Hayashi considered "unfortunate" that the Chinese government issued a statement that "does not correspond to the truth."
The Japanese Foreign Ministry also condemned the Chinese statement in a note, stating that during the meeting with Wang, Ishiba “stressed the need to reduce concerns” in bilateral relations, including “the situation in the east of China”, “ensuring the safety of Japanese citizens in China” and raising Chinese restrictions on Japanese seafood importation.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Public Hiring | New regime “is on the good way,” says lawyer</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/contratacao-publica-novo-regime-esta-no-bom-caminho-diz-advogado/</link><description>Marco Caldeira, a lawyer and auxiliary teacher at the University of Lisbon Faculty of Law, argues that the proposed public hiring law, under analysis in the specialty in Hemiciclo, is “on the good way” regarding the attempt to “promote transparency and competition and bet on digitization”. The theme was discussed last week at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
 
The proposal of public hiring, currently under analysis in the specialty in the First Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly (AL), was one of the topics addressed in the “Spring Conferences”, at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) last week. The author of the lecture, the lawyer and teacher Marco Caldeira, made praise for the diploma for his attempt to reform and innovation in many respects.
"Although not perfect, the bill under discussion is justified by the need to update legislation that was approved four decades ago. It is a proposal that seems to point in the good way, with an effort to codify the regime, promote transparency and competition and bet on digitization," said the professor at the University of Lisbon Law School (FDUL) to HM.
In addition, Marco Caldeira understands that the diploma, and the content proposed by the government, aims to "follow what are good practices adopted in Europe and the West in general."
"It is also very commendable that the proposal was prepared following a serious and participated procedure of public consultation, which gave the opportunity to economic operators and contracting entities to identify deficiencies in current legislation and make suggestions," added Marco Caldeira.
At the CCCM session, the FDUL professor also pointed out that the concern [demonstrated, in the diploma] with the competition and transparency of the procedures ”, as well as“ the focus on training in the use of databases, as well as the focus on centralization ”.
The teacher also understood that, in this bill, the Portuguese regime "can help, because the practice followed in Portugal, and legislative evolutions, have useful teachings that, with proper adaptations, can be transposed to Macao."
Positive points
In the presentation at CCCM, Marco Caldeira highlighted several positive aspects of the current law proposal, namely “the express determination of inapplicability to certain contracts”, or the fact that “fundamental principles of public hiring” are established.
It is also required with the new law “qualifications to candidates and competitors” of public tenders, and there is also “the clarification and standardization of the types of public hiring procedures”.
Thus, a “centralized hiring regime” is created, as well as regulating “award criteria” in competitions, and the creation of an exclusive website for the public hiring area is also foreseen.
Marco Caldeira also drew attention to the real need of this diploma, as public hiring was legislated with various diplomas, including two decrees of 1984 and 1985, which established, respectively, the expenditure regime with works and service acquisitions, and the process of acquisition of goods and services. Such diplomas were “undone of reality” of Macao, even though the 1984 decree was reviewed in 2021, the teacher considered.
Marco Caldeira also considered that the process of reviewing this diploma has been “lengthy”, as the public consultation took place between November 6, 2018 and January 4, 2019, and a later report was prepared, but the truth is that the proposal has been under analysis since December 2023, having been voted generally on January 11 last year.
What has to change
In the same session, the causal and university professor also highlighted the points already addressed by the first Standing Commission of AL regarding the necessary changes to legislate in the area of ​​public hiring. It was imposed “expressly consecrating fundamental legal principles, such as economy, efficiency and effectiveness, as well as publicity and transparency”, and there is also “a lack of regulation of public hiring policies”.
There was also the “need to promote transparency in public hiring procedures” and ensure “greater protection of loyal competition”. There was also “lack of rigorous and explicit regulation on the composition and operation of the proposals evaluation committees” submitted to a public tender, and there is “lack of explicit demands on the qualifications and capabilities of candidates and competitors in hiring procedures”.
Other gaps point to “insufficient regulation and transparency in the evaluation and adjudication procedures”, or “lack of explicit regulation on proposals presentation with an abnormally low price”. It was still necessary to “improve the sanctioning and inspection regime”, as well as bet on “regulation that promotes the development of electronic hiring”.
Says the executive
Looking at the justification of the law proposal, submitted by the Executive to AL, it is read that one of the great reasons for his presentation was even the legislative dispersion that was verified and the misfit over the current reality.
"The nuclear part of these diplomas was prepared in the mid-1980s, and has been in force for over 30 years. A significant part of the provisions of other legal diplomas already has an obvious divergence regarding the needs of Macao's current socioeconomic development, the efficiency of public administration management and the reinforcement of transparency and supervision," he reads.
According to the executive, "given that public hiring involves the use of the public purse, it is essential to review these regimes in order to meet the needs of the society of our day." Thus, in this law proposal, “the process and regime of expenses and acquisitions of goods and services” are regulated, with some provisions of a 1999 law, as “the provisions related to the public works contract regime have a high degree of specialization and are still effective”.
It is intended, with the new law of public hiring, to “guarantee justice, impartiality in the evaluation of proposals”, defining “expressly aid criteria and rigorously determining the rules of conduct of workers and members of the opening and evaluation of proposals” subjected to contest, so that “excerpt their functions impartially and entirely”.
Thus, it is foreseen that “contracting entities must adequately publicize the informative elements related to public hiring procedures”. They are “those related to the public tender, the clarifications provided, the rectification of documents, the extension of the deadline for the presentation of proposals, the causes for non -adjudication, the decision to annul the procedure and the award decision”.
In order to guarantee loyal competition, the government wants to ensure that all entities interested in participating in a competition have “the broader access” to all procedures, prohibiting “all acts, agreements or practices that can prevent, false or restrict competition”. Moreover, there is the “principle of impartiality”, which determines that “the program of procedures, book of charges or other documents, made by the contracting party, cannot contain any clause designed to favor or harm a particular interested party”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:18:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Aviation | Maria José de Freitas regrets removal of panels from the airport</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/20/aviacao-maria-jose-de-freitas-lamenta-retirada-de-paineis-do-aeroporto/</link><description>The first attempts to establish in Macao airlines in the early twentieth century were approached by historian Célia Reis in the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center. The architect Maria José de Freitas regretted the removal of panels from Macao International Airport that told this same story
 
Between the departure of the plane and the entrance to Macao International Airport (AIM) was a corridor that told the history of civil and military aviation from the territory of the early twentieth century. The project of this area of ​​the airport is by the studio of architect Maria José de Freitas, which regrets the removal of the panels and historical information that were installed in 2013.
The architect left this idea in an intervention after the presentation of historian Célia Reis about the history of civil and military aviation in Macao on Monday, on the occasion of the “Spring Conferences” that take place at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon.
“We decided to tell the story of Aviation in Macao in this corridor, with a great extent, although at the time there was little documentation about it. I discovered some information in a work by Luís Andrade de Sá. We collected texts and images and put it all on the walls of this corridor, and that was there for a while.”
"With a new direction [at AIM], I was asked how I could prove that all these events had happened. I had documentation in Portuguese, but I had nothing in Chinese and English, and at a time when I moved to Portugal on vacation, I saw, when I returned to Macau, who had removed all the information and images from this corridor. This story is unfortunate," he added.
The architect added that she would like the history of the early days of Aviation in Macao to be told in these same walls. "It would be important to realize where there is more information, so that they realize the history of aviation in Macao, which was a pioneer. There was, for example, an aviation hangar near the mud houses, and there are a series of references linked to the history of this land that should be made visible at the airport, in the rooms, for example. This story should be told and things should be placed in the right place," he said.
Ricou plans
Célia Reis, historian and teacher, is developing an investigation project around the early days of aviation in Macao and this was the theme that led to the “spring conferences” on Monday, with the session “Aviation and Air Navigation in Macao in the 1920s-a process of colonial innovation”.
Célia Reis spoke of a time when aviation began to be important to China for security reasons, and also begins to be thought to Macau. In this process, there is a personality whose name is important, a Hong Kong -born Frenchman: Charles William Ricou, a engineering and aviation pilot. From November 1919 the possibility of “establishing an air career between Macao, Hong Kong, Shanghai, Philippines, Java, India” began to equate, from November 1919, the possibility of Macaoi, Shanghai, Java, India, "contacting local government entities to obtain facilities and agreements.
Célia Reis explained that Ricou intended to form two airlines, the “Far East Aviation Company”, with “a much wider connection, reaching Manila”, and another to connect Macau, Hong Kong and Cantão, named “Macau Aerial Transport Company”.
This company "was constituted in Hong Kong, with a capital of $ 50,000, and had as founding partners personalities from Macau, such as Humberto de Avelar, Rodrigues dos Santos, Francisco Nolasco and Francisco da Silva". The historian also said in the presentation that the idea "was to complete the rest of the capital necessary with low value actions so that they could be bought by all [the inhabitants] in Macao."
"There is even the appeal of the company's board of directors for the Macanese to subscribe to capital, showing that the company was extremely important for the inhabitants of Macao, highlighting its patriotic value, of solidarity with progress," he added.
"Several voices demonstrated at that time that the company's commercial success, at first, could be little or none, although it was thought that the company could have some profits, having the ability to transport the air mail. However, this transportation capacity would be extremely limited, as the number of mail objects to transport from Macau was 24 letters a day," said Célia Reis.
At the time it was thought that Macau would be a pioneer, because "it would be the first territory to the East to have an aviation company", something that would "bring more visitors and increase trade." The Government of Macao, then led by Governor Correia da Silva, "gives in to the company's appeals, granting various facilities, such as the permission to build a provisional hangar on public ground that was vacant or from sea access infrastructure." In addition, “exemption from payment of the fuel storage tax” was allowed.
Thus, Macao even had hydroavião and 21 American airmen hired by the company. "It was considered that it was the largest load of air material exported by the United States of America (USA), all brought to Macao." Then the company tries to organize itself, "even asking for space on Taipa Island, designed to have definitive hangars, although provisional concessions have existed." In this context, he recalled the historian, "there were subsidies, a contract for the transportation of postal bags", to "allow a development of air navigation."
Impasses to the end
In May 1920, a new worldwide aviation convention emerged, to which Portugal adheres, which causes the “Macau Aerial Transport Company” to be nationalized. The project comes to advance, but quickly retreats.
“The airline therefore accesses the condition of obtaining a subsidy, and having four aircraft available for military service in Macau, if necessary. The issue of defense was always present. There was then some disagreement between the conditions required by the company and those that the governor understood were necessary. In addition, the government of Macao needed the Lisbon authorization for the operation of the airline. Advance, and this one begins to negotiate with the company. But voices begin to emerge in Lisbon that will make things change. ”
This is the idea that the US would be showing hidden interests through the establishment of the company. "[In Lisbon] it is fear that this is the found form of an American aviation company to settle in Macao, Portuguese territory, by different ways."
First, Lisbon forbids, retreating in the negotiations, and the next governor, Rodrigo Rodrigues, "is not in accordance with the company, understanding that it will not be viable," which leads to the entire project and dialogue to be suspended.
Célia Reis also pointed out that "the government of Correia da Silva has undergone several difficulties in these years, in terms of security", having occurred "very serious incidents in the relationship between Portugal and China".
“For this reason, the governor considered that having airplanes was extremely important because, at this moment, China was also resorting to aviation. The authorities of Portugal, however, considered that the planes of Macao would be of no importance, comparing with the set of aircraft that would have China or even Japan. When permission for the constitution of the airline in Macao, Lisbon understands that the territory could have in a worrying situation and planes could have functions with planes Military, even if there were few, ”explained the historian. The project would fall, however, by land.</description><pubDate>2025-03-20 01:43:40</pubDate></item><item><title>The garden of Almerindo in Timor-Leste can be watered from Portugal or England</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/a-horta-de-almerindo-em-timor-leste-pode-ser-regada-de-portugal-ou-inglaterra/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
"It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It's the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden," he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth formation center,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:19:38</pubDate></item><item><title>History | Lara Reis, Professor of Macao High School, remembered in Lisbon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/historia-lara-reis-professor-do-liceu-de-macau-recordado-em-lisboa/</link><description>The former teacher of the Macao High School Fernando Lara Reis was remembered in the “Spring Conferences”, from the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center, by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira. A native of Leiria, Lara Reis fought in the 1st World War and lived on Avenida da República, in the villa that today houses the Macau Red Cross house
 
Fernando Lara Reis was born in 1892 and died in 1950. Throughout a life filled with historical events and testimonies, the natural man of Leiria was a military man and a teacher at Macao High School, eventually making the territory his home.
Lara Reis's life was recently remembered at the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira, herself to her former teacher in the territory.
At the session, the historian, who won the 2024 Macao International Institute Identity Award (IIM), recalled the “teacher, meritorious, driving of the arts”, and owner of “unusual knowledge”.
“He was a native of Leiria and lived in Macao until his death. He attended Leiria High School, the Military College, then joined the Army School. In World War I was in Elvas, and then left to Angola in 1915 when he faced the German threat over Portuguese colonies in Africa. Observer-Aviator. ”
Lara Reis was never a pilot as she wanted, having dedicated much of her life to teaching and Macao. “In 1919, Lara Reis went to Macao High School. He took a long circum-gap trip, leaving Portugal from Lisbon, going to the United States of America, crossed the entire territory and then went to Japan, down to Hong Kong and even Macau. He was a teacher in Macao, drawing, handicrafts and gymnastics until the end of his life,” said Celina Veiga de Oliveira.
The historian took to the session some written testimonies left by other Macao figures who wrote about Lara Reis, namely Monsignor Manuel Teixeira in the book “Macao Lyceu”. He said he never found "no teacher who had served the High School with greater dedication."
“He was a rigorous methodical teacher, whose military formation was certainly not oblivious to these characteristics. What was truly standing out was his artistic vein, because Lara Reis was always concerned with ascertaining the aesthetic meaning of the students and opening their mental horizons. This at the time when Macau was a small town. that he organized and also exhibitions by Portuguese and foreign artists he sponsored, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira also highlighted the words left by the writer Henrique de Senna Fernandes in an interview on "one of the greatest qualities of Lara Reis", which "besides rigor and discipline, was the consideration by the students, not distinguishing rich from the poor."
Professor Lara Reis was "a party prosecutor who served to obtain tuition fees for needy students," and "he is due to the initiative of the creation of the High School Association, of which he was the first president." This association organized in the former canhydrome “sports parties of the end of the year when students performed the most difficult exercises”.
Work done in Macau
The historian also highlighted “another aspect of dedication to territory” by Lara Reis. The Leiriense "participated in the First World War and this led him to interest all those who were incorporated into this conflict, having founded the League of the Great War fighters and had built in the cemetery of St. Miguel Archangel the monument where the bodies of combatants rest."
Moreover, "another facet of his personality was a taste for travel, because he had no family and thus left for the world." "I visited museums, art schools and photographed everything I saw, having created a estate with 32 volumes that is now a heritage of Leiria."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira did not forget the old “Sol Pente” villa, located in the middle-leaf zone, namely the Avenida da República, which was the house of Lara Reis, later donated to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao to “an anti-cancer clinic that was the first institution of the genre in the Portuguese colonial space”. Today this villa serves as a house to the Red Cross of Macao, and on its walls you can find a stone with the following message: “In this building legacy by the Rotary Fernando Reis to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao, it was installed at the initiative of the Rotary Club of Macao the first anti-cancer fighting center on April 15, 1951.”
“Change of Ares”
When Fernando Lara Reis goes to Macao, political times are troubled, with the political agitation to be lived in China after the fall of the Empire and the Republican Revolution of 1911.
"In the 1920s the nationalist shock waves lived in the Canton, which sometimes haunted the Portuguese enclave quiet, but never moved with everyday life. The Portuguese administration guaranteed a standard appearance, and the parties at Christmas, Chinese New Year, the religious festivities of the Catholic community and the Chinese population were habitual."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recalled that in the late 1920s, Lara Reis decided to transfer to Goa, a trip that would only accentuate her belonging to Macau.
“In the late 1920s, he felt he was time to change his air and asked to be transferred to the Afonso de Albuquerque High School in Pangim, and was there between 1941 and 1945, taking the opportunity to know India, and met the whole country. Instead, with a graceful and already sick license, choosing Macau to be his last address, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recordou também as palavras de Orlando Cardoso, que no artigo “Macau e o Oriente na vida de Lara Reis” falou do homem que se deslumbrou com Macau “a partir do momento em que, às 8 horas da noite de 23 de Outubro de 1919, avistou pela primeira vez o Farol da Guia, um pouco antes de se instalar no ‘New Macao Hotel’ e sorver de sentidos atentos os sons, os cheiros e as luzes desta porta of an immeasurable and fantastic Asia that he would describe to exhaustion. ”
These Lara Reis testimonies are “in a remarkable set of travel books that lay virtually unexplored in all their research potentialities on the shelves of the Leiria District Archive”, and were investigated by Orlando Cardoso himself.
In the same article, this one refers to a text from the newspaper “News of Macau” of January 17, 1950, about Lara Kings: “The Auster and Worsen Teacher; the tenacious and thorough tourist; the military who fought and consecrated the memory of those who fell in the field of struggle; the honest and firm friend; the lovely and humorous companion; social celibate that, despite this, did not disdain any opportunity to undo its gallants, always kind and inconsequential to any palm with a face that in the goto ”.
Given the few studies that exist about Lara Reis and the estate he left, Celina Veiga de Oliveira left a suggestion: "May the CCCM get the detailed index of the Leiria Archive, so that the research is possible for any interested researchers."</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:57:07</pubDate></item><item><title>IC | Launched book on the historical roots of Rua das Estlagês</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/ic-lancado-livro-sobre-as-raizes-historicas-da-rua-das-estalagens/</link><description>“In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Street of Estalagins” is the name of the work Bilingual, launched in digital format, which tells the story of this historic street of Macao, revealing the business that survived the passage of time. Production was in charge of the Macao Artists Society, with the support of the Cultural Institute and Sands China
 
The history serpes through the stalage street since the end of the nineteenth century. The narrow artery has always been the scene of an intense social and commercial rebolement and it was where Sun Yat-Sen, considered the father of modern China and the Republican Revolution, opened pharmacies and drugstores, especially from 1893. Over the years, Rua das Estalagem, in Porto, was a living example of commerce, and the Portuguese governors were progressively expanding the street, composed of the street Chinese -style buildings and temples, such as the Temple of the Bazaar and Goddess Temple NOVA WO.
All these pieces of history are now counting on the digital publication “In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Rua das Estlagês”, a work produced by the Society of Macao Artists and authored by Siguo Chen in Shirley Lule's texts and illustrations. Those responsible for the edition are the Cultural Institute (IC) and the game operator Sands China.
According to a press release of Sands China, the book, in Chinese and English, intends to “highlight the fascinating past of the historic Macau Street and the beauty of its legacy”, containing interviews with street -related figures, whether merchants or residents. Thus, it is intended to bring “residents and visitors to rediscover the preciousness of the centenary stores and the cultural heritage of the street through legendary stories” so that they can “widen their understanding of the transformation of the neighborhood and its inhabitants”.
The content of the book results from “close conversations with representatives of associations, business entities and residents of the neighborhood,” having dozens of oral stories that can easily be lost if not recorded. This work is not closed in the digital world, having been printed to appear in the public libraries of Macao and schools, in order to “promote the meaning of cultural heritage and enhance mutual ties among the people of Macao”, intending to be “a valuable community resource to deepen the understanding and appreciation of Macao and the street”.
200 years of history
One of the highlights given in the book is to the textile sector that has always predominated on Rua das Estlagenas. In the chapter entitled "Two Centuries of Prosperity: Spinning A Legacy in the Textiles Trade" [two centuries of prosperity: the construction of a legacy in the textile trade], it is read that "Street of Estlagins has always been a center for the textile industry." In the years when the textile sector had a larger presence in the territory, between the 70's and 90's, "Rua housed more than 20 stores with factory products, including three spaces from the Veng On Farm Store." “Around 30 businesses related to these stores, such as tailors, clothing stores, western products and funeral ornament stores, which brought a reputation to the street,” he reads. In Rua das Estlagenas “Tissue trade is over 200 years old,” says the same text.
Other chapters of the book speak of the presence of the republican revolutionary in Macao in “The Starting Point of Sun Yat-Sen’s Story” [The Starting Point of the story of Sun Yat-Sen] or stories of street-linked personalities and their commerce.
In the conclusion of the work, it refers that after the transition, the street "faced new challenges: the global financial crisis, the SARS epidemic, the COVID-19, and the uncertainty of the economy, leaving the need for renewal again."
"In the past, the business has flourished, by themselves, thanks to hard work and resilience. But nowadays the community joins with a shared vision, actively planning [the development of the street] with the support of the Macao government and the integrated resort companies. With these efforts, there is a sense of hope that the street of the stalage will briefly recover its old vitality, being ready for a new era."
Visão institucional
IC President Deland Leong Wai Man pointed out that the book results from the “weighted effort to widen the discussion around preservation and revitalization [of the street],” according to the same press release. "Street renewal is expected to inspire more people to learn about the historic neighborhoods of Macao and participate in their preservation, combining ideas and resources to ensure that the city's culture and history continue to prosper during generations," he said.
In turn, Wilfred Wong, CEO of Sands China, argued that "Street of Estalagues is a microcosm of Macao itself, a place where a rich story meets a modern future."
"The walls of their alleys witnessed the transformation of Macao, and their stories and people deserve to be remembered, as they are precious sources of Macao's cultural heritage. Our effort to publish the book was possible thanks to the collaboration of our local team to conduct interviews with owners of historical stores, create illustrations and take pictures, among other works," he said.
New facades
It is recalled that this publication arises after the Government was announced by the Sands performance at the Rua das Estalagens Revitalization Plan, namely with the “Entrepreneurs Recruitment Program for Rua das Estlagês”, launched in April last year.
The game operator explains that the seven businesses selected for the initiative “have been opening through phases, bringing energy to the zone along with other new businesses, providing a platform for young ambitious entrepreneurs to realize their dreams”.
In addition, the game operator intends to revitalize stores' façades “with drawings that enhance their characteristics, resonating the history of the street and the city”. For this initiative, Sands has also collaborated with the Macao Artist Society, and the drawings will be created by two young local artists, Chek On Law and Sit Kat Kit.
"The aim is that, with a collective effort like this, the community can rediscover the history of the street and learn about its past stories and stores through the visual interpretations of these local artists from Macao and their perceptions of the territory," he reads.
Siguo Chen, the book's author, is a veteran journalist with a career of over 60 years who has been deeply linked to the media area in Macau and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 01:50:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Sun Yat-Sen | Marked centenary of the death of the “father of modern China”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/13/sun-yat-sen-assinalado-centenario-da-morte-do-pai-da-china-moderna/</link><description>Sun Yat-Sen died on March 12, 1925. Unavoidable figure in the political history of modern China and the father of the movement that led to the fall of the imperial regime, Sun Yat-Sen was celebrated yesterday in Guangzhou, where he was born, Beijing and Taiwan
 
The first president of China post-imperial and considered the father of the country's modern era, Sun Yat-Sen, was remembered yesterday in mainland China and Taiwan, the 100th anniversary of his death.
In Beijing, there was a “brief and solemn ceremony” of honor to Sun in Beijing Park that has its name. Authorities and “people from all the sectors of society” were present, kept silence and made three venias in front of their statue, the Xinhua official news agency said.
The Chinese Academy of History praised the political figure in his Weibo account, describing him as "a great national hero, a great patriot and a major precursor of the Democratic Revolution of China."
The city of Guangzhou, the capital of Guangdong Province, where Sun Yat-Sen was born, inaugurated on Tuesday an exhibition of old objects related to the man who was one of the promoters of the revolution that overthrew the Qing Dynasty (1644-1911). The Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Building in the city welcomed the first performance of a musical based on the revolutionary's youth.
In Guangzhou, where there is also a university named Sun Yat-Sen, this exhibition is exhibited, which includes objects such as the Sun Yat-Sen Graduation Exam report at the College of Medicine for Chinese, in Hong Kong, from 1892. The certificate of marriage between Sun Yat-Sen and Soong Ching-Ling is also highlighted in 1915, a woman later, woman later, Vice-President of China during the government of Mao Tse-Tung, embracing communism. In the same exhibition you can also see the bronze bust of Sun Yat-Sem itself, made by order of the Japanese friend Umeya Shokichi in 1929.
The "father" of modern China was also remembered in Taiwan, with a ceremony by the Sun Yat-sen memorial in Taipei, where flowers were deposited and express respect.
Double memories
Despite founding, in 1919, the Kuomitang, which would become the main rival of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Sun is remembered in both mainland China and Taiwan. The Board of State's Taiwan Cabinet stated that Sun Yat-Sen “sought China's national unity and revitalization throughout his life,” appealing at the same time to the “compatriots of Taiwan to join us in the inheritance of his legacy” and to “oppose secession” of the island.
Born in 1866, Sun studied medicine in Hong Kong - then a British colony - and, after leading several revolts, gained notoriety as a revolutionary leader and as a driving force of an attempt to modernize the country.
In 1911, the Xinhai Revolution led to the fall of the Qing and Sun Yat-Sen dynasty was appointed provisional president of the New Republic of China in January 1912, but quickly gave power to the country's main military leader, Yuan Shikai, who, far from consolidating republican ideals, dissolved the parliament in 1914 and proclaimed herself in 1915, annulling Grande, annul Part of the democratic progress by which Sun had fought.
From then on, he continued to promote his ideal of a unified and republican China, reorganizing the KMT and seeking international support for his cause. In 1923, he established an alliance with the newly founded CCP and received the support of the Soviet Union to reinforce the political movement. However, he failed to consolidate a stable government before his death in 1925.
A LIFE OF FIGHT
In the work “Sisters Soong-the oldest, younger and redest,” by Jung Chang, some details of Sun Yat-Sen's life are described before embracing the revolutionary cause and the way he left his parents' house in Guangzhou, looking for a better life.
The place of destination was Hawaii, which on July 4, 1894 declared itself as a Republic, an event that, according to the book, "helped shape today's China." “A 27-year-old radical Chinese, Sun Yat-sen, landed in the archipelago and entered a world where the word 'republic' was in every mouth,” he is described.
In China, the agitation against the power of the empire became strong. The Republic "was a new concept," for "the monarchy was the only political system that China knew." "At the time, the country was governed by the Manchu dynasty," the Manchus "were not natural from China, but they had conquered the territory in the mid -seventeenth century." "Since they did not get more than one percent of the population, they were considered a minority of foreign rulers and had never been lacking opposition from the native rebels Han. Sun was one of them," he describes in the same work.
Sun Yat-Sen was "a low, dark man with well-proposed and pleasant traits." Its home village, Cuiheng, had soils inappropriate for agriculture, which provided “a life of extreme misery” to those who lived there. As such, the revolutionary's family did not escape adverse conditions.
In his first escape from the context of poverty, Sun went to Hong Kong, finding shelter to the diocesan school and boys orphanage, then accepted a marriage arranged by the family as a gimmick to return to the village. Sun Yat-Sen married Mu-Zhen, had children, but was an absent figure and something carefree in the face of family responsibilities, traveling the world to seek support for the revolution he wanted for China.
Jung Chang's work describes how Sun's course linked to the "three sisters," Ei-Ling, May-Ling and Ching-Ling. Charlie Soong funded and supported Sun Yat-Sen in her revolutionary causes, one of her daughters, Ei-Ling, became the republican secretary. This, although married, had made attempts to approach loving and EI-Ling, but eventually had a relationship with Ching-Ling, who was nationalist, but later embraced communism, being known as the "red sister." Ching-ling was also known as the Madame Sun Yat-Sen, but at the time of Sun Yat-Sen's death, the relationship between them had cooled.
After the establishment of the Popular Republic of China, Ching-Ling was vice president of the country, between 1949 and 1954, and then between 1959 and 1975, and was vice president of the Permanent Commission of the National Assembly.
Passage through macau
Moreover, Sun Yat-Sen's life crossed Macao several times, where he lived a short time, unlike his woman, Mu-Zhen, and the children who remained in the territory longer. To remember the short period in which the Republican lived in the territory, at the time under Portuguese administration, the memorial house of dr. Sun Yat-Sen, where he "witnesses the short but significant stay in Macao in the early twentieth century when, running away from the power of imperial mandarins, tried to move his supporters forces in order to implement a new regime in China." “In Macau received support from some friends who were illustrious and influential figures of social and political life at the time,” reads the description of the museum.
Another interesting detail of the 1911 Republican Revolution is the proximity of dates against the establishment of the Republic in Portugal, which took place on October 5, 1910. Macau, in the midst of events in China and Portugal, was only aware that the constitutional monarchy had fallen into Lisbon thanks to the sending of a telegram published in an official bulletin on October 10, 1910, changing the governor in this context. Lame</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 01:04:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Clinical Psychology | The benefits and risks of the introduction of AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/12/psicologia-clinica-os-beneficios-e-riscos-da-introducao-da-ia/</link><description>Artificial intelligence is there to stay and its use in the field of psychology begins to be spoken. Recently, Deputy Lam Lon Wai defended its use and, in Portugal, the Order of Psychologists created the “PSIA” platform, which allows it to detect symptoms. Nuno Gomes and Goreti Lima, two resident therapists, talk about the benefits, risks and potential uses of technology
 
Understanding whether emotions can result in psychological forum diseases is something that is already possible to do using Artificial Intelligence (AI). The issue begins to discuss in Macao still shyly, namely through Deputy Lam Lon Wai, who in February interpelled the government about the need to apply AI tools in clinical cases with young people.
HM spoke to two clinical psychologists who work with residents of Macao, in person or distance, about the benefits and risks of betting on AI. Nuno Gomes, a psychologist in a local clinic, says that “is, for now, a help, and it will always be”.
"AI is an irreversible process and it is inevitable that it covers all fields of our lives, and in them is psychology and helps people. But I come from a field of psychology that is the humanist school, which is based on the relationship with the patient, so I see no great benefits, for the use of AI, because in human relationships AI does not enter," he defended.
Nuno Gomes believes that AI can help in the diagnostic phase, although he thinks "the psychologist will always be the central character." "AI can be an advantage in Macao for people who have difficulty asking for help. The use of the well -defined AI, even in ethical terms, can be very useful for the beginning of a therapy. However, at this time we are not able to use AI at the level of a more complete and background therapy," he said.
Nuno Gomes also recalls that for those who want to talk to someone, AI "can give the feeling that we are not alone and that is someone on the other side." It is a feeling that is still "strange", but "in the future will no longer be, because AI will be part of our days."
The psychologist believes that AI "may work as long as it is ethically well regulated and can help in brief therapies, but always as a complement to a larger process."
Goreti Lima, who has lived in Macao, continues to do clinical psychology at a distance with residents living in the territory. It is more skeptical in relation to the use of AI, arguing that human relationship is always fundamental for quality monitoring.
“Therapy is made in the relationship and these applications do not contemplate it. I think very well that we can use AI to diagnose, see symptoms, but this we can also do with a book or article. ChatgPT already tells us some things in the area of ​​psychology, possible analysis of symptoms. AI helps in this process, but then the rest works in the therapeutic relationship. Data are stored like?
Recommendations in Portugal
In a written interpeação directed to the Government of MSAR, Deputy Lam Lon Wai questioned whether there will be “cooperation” between government departments, technological companies and local academic institutions in the use of AI in the area of ​​mental health. However, Goreti Lam regrets that deputy "do not speak in the figure of the psychologist."
“Academics have a different experience from psychologists and therapists, who have acquired this experience in practical terms. This develops over time. All these questions have to be thought when applying AI. AI can identify what the person has and even use, but then we have to take into account deontological conditions. Undersisted, ”he added.
Portugal is one of the countries where the application of AI in Psychology begins to gain some form, to the point of the Order of Portuguese Psychologists (OPP) has created the online “Psia” tool, which allows you to state a series of symptoms and reach a diagnosis. Personal data appear to be protected with the introduction, on the website, the citizen card number, with the digital mobile key.
In addition, OPP has created a manual of good practices, entitled “The Human Factor in Artificial Intelligence - Strategic Recommendations for Sustainability”, which states that there are “virtual therapists who can identify, in communication with people, emotional difficulties that facilitate deliberate psychological education”, as well as enhancing “the learning of techniques and skills that aim, for example, to reduce anxiety”.
In addition, the OPP document concludes that "some studies suggest that these chatbots, developed based on validated therapeutic models, may be effective in reducing depressive symptoms and even that some people establish a bond similar to that of a human relationship." However, “these evidence is not consolidated and security-related (people and data), eventual dependence on technologies and the responsiveness of support given to different psychological difficulties are not clarified”, it reads.
Regarding PSIA, it is referred to the OPP website that "on very specific or complex issues should not be used in tasks that require specialized judgment and evaluation, deep technical analysis or professional counseling." It is also clarified that the answers provided are based on “available documents and information” until July 31 last year, and PSIA “does not replace the role of a psychologist or any supervision activities”.
In the case of Hong Kong, some solutions are also beginning to emerge, which motivated, by the way, the interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai. This is the case of Hollo, a mobile phone application developed in connection with the University of Hong Kong (UHK) that aims to “make mental health care more accessible to patients, service platforms and organizations”.
Hollo uses AI power and technologies to bring clinical practices standardized to another level of productivity, intelligence and digital connectivity. According to Cameron Van Breda, Hollo's CEO and co-founder, the company aims to be "an easily accessible tool in stress times, offering analysis and friendship suggestions for better mental health exercises." In practical terms, “focuses on young people from 12 to 24 years old, works in English and Chinese and introduce them to therapy and counseling practices through mindfulness activities and daily games,” reads UHK's website.
Almost the same
Asked about Macao's mental health landscape, Nuno Gomes understands that he persists "some conservatism and ignorance not only in what is AI and areas where one can apply, but also what psychology can do."
"Psychology is here to help people and in the context of Macao there is no such understanding yet. This stigma prevents many people from seeking help and AI can give this support. However, the older population is still very unaware of the operation of AI, but the younger people will increasingly resort to this type of platforms," ​​he said.
In general terms, "the overview of mental health has changed little from the pandemic," because "in general, people do not feel the need to express emotions and since they are encouraged to keep emotions, that when they are bad and stored a long time, they start to do harm. People do not know how to express them out of shame or guilt." Goreti Lima also understands that in the area of ​​mental health there is still some ignorance in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:36:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Social Security | Coutinho defends the regime update</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/seguranca-social-coutinho-defende-actualizacao-do-regime/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho requires the government to review the Social Security System to cease to exist discrimination with the elderly with disabilities.
In the written interplies handed over to the Executive, the deputy and president of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) spoke of one of the allegedly discriminatory situations, noting that “a citizen who, since youth, receives a subsidy for disability and reaches the elderly, should have the right to accumulate it with the elderly pension”.
In addition, Coutinho states that he has been confronted, through the Citizens Care Office, with "a growing number of support requests from disabled residents, especially those who, reaching the elderly, are faced with a significant reduction in income."
"This situation proves to be particularly alarming to those who are not entitled to the pensions of the elderly," he said.
According to the deputy, “disabled citizens who reach legal age to be considered elderly are, by definition, individuals who have long -term impediments, physical, mental, intellectual or sensory, limiting their full participation in society, on equal conditions for other elderly”.
Review the law
In this sense, the deputy says it is “imperative” that “the current norms governing the granting of pensions to disabled citizens who affect the elderly”, since “it is essential to ensure that all citizens, regardless of their condition, have access to rights that promote dignity and quality of life”.
"Considering that the relevant legislation is fundamental, in order to ensure that disabled citizens have the right to review the pension to the elderly, I question whether the government will update and modernize the current social security regime that is manifestly disabled taking into account the decade and a half of validity of Law 4/2010 [Social Security Regime]," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:27:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Leong Sun Iok wants protection for “false collaborators”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/trabalho-leong-sun-iok-quer-proteccao-para-falsos-colaboradores/</link><description>The Fan deputy warns of the abuse of the independent work regime, which can be used by employer entities to avoid obligations, such as the acquisition of insurance
 
Deputy Leong Sun IOK intends that the government present new measures to protect “false employees”, that is, workers who are hired for independent services on paper, but in practice they are under the authority of the employer. The subject was approached through a written interpellation, released yesterday by the office of the legislator linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom).
According to the scenario reported by Leong Sun Iok, it is becoming increasingly normal in Macau employers to resort to false employees, as "the market is limited and many people can only work this way." Without options, workers end up accepting the proposals.
Under normal conditions, employees provide a service, and can choose when and how they work, being the most relevant to present the result for which they were hired. However, under the conditions reported by the deputy, in practice, workers are required to follow working hours established by the boss and his instructions, typical characteristics of the dependent worker regime. For the bosses, although this performance is illegal, the regime has the advantage of allowing expenses arising from the guarantee of labor rights.
As such, Leong Sun Iok asks the executive to "verify that employers are resorting to this possibility as a means to run away from the responsibilities and duties of the employment relationship."
One more study
The deputy of the parliamentary bench of Faom asks to follow the example of the interior of China, to increase the protection of these workers. To this end, it argues that it is necessary to “study how to ensure workers' professional guarantees on their own and liberal professionals”, and “encourage employers to acquire work insurance for their workers with service contracts”.
The member of the Legislative Assembly also asks the government to be aware of the emergence of “new employment modalities”.
At the interpetement, it is also requested to perform “an inquiry into the number and types of workers on their own and existing liberal professionals” in the territory to “safeguard the professional rights and interests of workers”.
On the other hand, Leong indicates that in Macau there is always an employment contract, regardless of the designation of the contract, when it is required to the “collaborator” who is “available” to perform the duties at the employer's request. Therefore, it asks the government if it will issue clear instructions and strengthen disclosure actions on the Macao labor regime to “avoid breach of law by employers and safeguard workers' rights and interests”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:07:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Cotai | Government declined concerts to the air-free</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/cotai-governo-recusou-concertos-ao-ar-livre/</link><description>The president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Deland Leong Wai Man, acknowledged that the concert zone to the air-free air in Cotai will not receive shows during this month. Leong's statements to the social communication body were cited by the newspaper or Mun.
According to Deland Leong Wai Man, the IC has planned to organize concerts in this area of ​​major shows in March and May. And about 30 proposals were received for the use of the space.
However, the authorities considered that the proposals submitted to March did not meet the criteria required for the use of the enclosure. Leong explained that this was mainly due to the fact that the proposals do not have a highly highly high audience to justify the use of the concert zone to the free air, which has a capacity of 50,000 people.
However, authorities do not yet want to receive a show with 50,000 people. According to the official, at this stage is preferable a show with an audience of 20,000 people, given that the government intends that producing entities test the enclosure and gain experience in coordinating the entrances and exits of the public and the organization of traffic.
The proposed times were another of the obstacles to the use of the enclosure. However, Leong is confident that concerts can return to the concert zone to the free air in May.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:04:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Water | Law chan u asks for balanced saving measures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/agua-lei-chan-u-pede-balanco-medidas-de-poupanca/</link><description>Deputy Lei Chan U asks the government to present a first balance of the water savings program in Macao, which after 15 years in force ends later this year. The request arises through a written interpellation, released yesterday by the deputy of the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom).
“The government will proceed to an assessment and a balance on the effectiveness of implementing the Macao Water Savings Program in the last 15 years? This program proposes to achieve a series of objectives by 2025. Have these objectives have been achieved?” Asks the deputy.
In the document, Chan U Lei indicates that “Macao Water Resources are extremely scarce and raw water supply depends mainly from the interior of China”, therefore, he stresses that “the good execution of water savings work and the increase of social consciousness are very important”.
Despite this position, Law recognizes that the executive may have no interest in launching a new edition of this program. In this case, the deputy intends to know how to promote the savings of water resources. “If the government is not intended to define a new water savings program, which plans have to continuously reinforce water resources and promote the construction of a water saving city?” He asks.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:01:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Gongbei | Former director of customs administration accused of corruption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/gongbei-ex-director-da-administracao-alfandegaria-acusado-de-corrupcao/</link><description>Former director of the customs administration of Gongbei, Zhao Min, was expelled from the Chinese Communist Party and faces accusations of various types of bribe and abuse of power.
As is natural, due to the connection between Gongbei and the doors of the siege, the main border between Macau and the interior of China, Zhao Min participated in various initiatives and joint policies, such as the process of opening and bureaucracy to facilitate the circulation of vehicles from Macao in Zhuhai and Hengqin.
According to the Central Disciplinary Inspection Commission, "Zhao Min has lost its ideals and convictions, betrayed its original mission," and "accepted gifts, money offers, feasts and travels to violation of regulations, made others pay expenses that should have been paid by him and borrowed vehicles from others without any charge."
The disciplinary body also indicates on its official page that Zhao Min "used the convenience created by the power or statute of its family members and, through the official actions of other state officials, sought to obtain undue benefits to others and illegally accepted goods."
In addition to the expulsion of the Chinese Communist Party, the benefits that the assets acquired improperly acquired and confiscated on suspicion of the crime of accepting bribes using their influence were canceled and confiscated. The Central Disciplinary Inspection Committee adds that the nature of Zhao Min's offenses is severe, so it must be treated seriously and subject to criminal action.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:00:48</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE | Sam Hou Fai gathers with Deputy Minister Hua Chunying</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/mne-sam-hou-fai-reune-se-com-a-vice-ministra-hua-chunying/</link><description>The chief executive received at the government headquarters the deputy minister of foreign business, Hua Chunying, to whom he requested support in the expansion of relations with the abroad. Sam Hou Fai pointed to the Portuguese -speaking, Spanish and Southeast Asia markets
 
The chief executive received on Sunday at the headquarters of the Government of Masters a delegation of representatives of the central government led by the Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs, Hua Chunying, according to a statement released on Sunday night by the office of social communication.
During the meeting, Sam Hou Fai and Hua Chunying exchanged impressions about the implementation of the proper diversification of Macau's economy, namely through strengthening and “even greater expansion of relations with the outside”.
The Chief Executive highlighted Macao's “great historical and cultural wealth”, trinks that allow the territory to serve as “a platform for communication and cooperation between the country and the abroad”. Regarding government goals, Sam Hou Fai said it will “strengthen and expand their relations with the outside, especially Portuguese -speaking, Southeast Asia markets”, in order to promote “further the proper diversification of the Macao economy”. To achieve such objectives, the Leader of the Government of MSAR said it hoped "that the Ministry of Foreign Affairs could support during the process."
Natural habitat
In addition to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, also the commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China in the Special Administrative Region of Macau, Liu Xianfa, attended the meeting, to whom Sam Hou Fai thanked “support on all issues related to abroad”.
The chief executive also stressed that Macau is "a prosperous, stable, peaceful and harmonious society," and "a successful example of the implementation of" one country, two systems. "
Hua Chunying's international notoriety rose considerably during the period when he was a spokesman for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs. At the end of May last year, the Council of State announced its appointment as Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:59:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | Council of Communities defends electronic vote</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/eleicoes-conselho-das-comunidades-defende-voto-electronico/</link><description>The president of the Regional Council of Portuguese Communities of Asia and Oceania, Rui Marcelo, defended the electronic vote to facilitate the participation of emigrants in the elections.
"The electronic vote has been a flag of the Portuguese Communities Council there are already several mandates, because it has not been a consensual theme, I would say, with the Portuguese government authorities and with parliamentary groups," said Rui Marcelo, when asked by Lusa.
"We have been discussing this possibility with the Portuguese authorities and, for our part, the process would have been accelerated," he said. Rui Marcelo spoke to journalists at the end of the meeting of the Regional Council of the Portuguese Communities of Asia and Oceania (which includes China, Thailand, South Korea, Japan, Singapore, Australia and Timor-Leste), which took place at Dili last week.
Although correspondence vote was the normal procedure, the official said that there are “always problems regarding the dates on which these votes eventually arrive at the National Election Commission”, noting that the next legislatures, scheduled for May 18, will “create very important challenges in the participation process”.
In February, Parliament approved a resolution presented by the PSD to carry out an experience to test the electronic vote in emigration.
During the two days of the meeting, the counselors also discussed forms of cooperation between the circles in the education and associativism sector, in the area of ​​economics and consular issues and on artistic and cultural potentialities.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:32:52</pubDate></item><item><title>LIMITS OF WORK</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/limites-do-trabalho/</link><description>On March 17, the Hong Kong Census and Statistics Department released data showing that approximately 12,900 people worked on digital food delivery platforms and other goods over the past year.
52.5 percent of these workers are between 15 and 39 years old, more than half are less than 40 and 24.2 percent over 50 years. 64.7 percent of respondents stated that this work is their main source of income, 61 percent receives less than $ 5,000 from Hong Kong (HKD) per month and 37.1 percent earns more than 15,000 hkd a month.
53.9 percent work less than 44 hours a week, 24.9 percent over 44 hours per week and 21.2 percent of these workers claim not to have a fixed time. 68.6 percent work only for a delivery platform every day.
91.3 percent of respondents say they have started working in this business because it is easy to enter, having a flexible working method and having great control over methods and procedures. 98.2 percent claim to have more maneuver field to balance work with personal life. 45 percent are attracted to this work due to salary.
Other data previously issued by the Hong Kong government show that the average salary of these workers was 22,000 USD between October and December 2024. By comparison, only 37.1 percent earn more than 15,000 USD, showing that they usually receive wages below average.
Office employees in Hong Kong usually work from 9am to 6pm during the week and another four hours on Saturdays, which means a total of 49 hours of weekly work. Excluding the break from an hour for lunch from Monday to Friday, exactly 44 hours. Since 53.9 percent of distributors work less than 44 hours per week, it is reasonable that their salaries will be lower than the market average.
98.2 percent of people who make deliveries say they do this service by giving them more room to balance their work with family life. This demonstrates that the new generation pay more attention to the balance between work and personal life, a different phenomenon from the “tele-work” that emerged during the epidemic. The “tele-work” means working from home because it is difficult to evaluate the limit between work and family life.  As people working on delivery platforms can control their working hours, the problem of defining the border between work and leisure is very small.
The three main limits that define the exercise of labor functions are psychological, temporal and physical. Psychological boundaries are rules created by individuals who determine specific thoughts, behaviors and emotions, which means that one should have a rational attitude when working and an emotional attitude when one is in family. Time limits mean defining working hours, turning off duties outside this time, and dedicating this extra labor time to home and family. The physical limit is defined by the workplace. When you go to the office you will work, when you leave the work ended. The statistical data of delivery platforms show that people choose to collaborate with them mainly because they have more room to control their hours and work model. This phenomenon indicates that the new generation values ​​the existence of boundaries to work time and, in terms of psychological limits, seeks to have more control over their work.
In the post-epicide era, it is given greater importance to the balance between professional and family career. Limits theory helps companies understand and better manage work and family boundaries, thus achieving better balance and allowing workers' quality of life to improve.
In Hong Kong, delivery platform distributors earn less. Although it has a better notion of the limits of work and a happier family life, material goods that can give to the family are limited. These workers need to achieve balance between family life and material goods. From a business point of view, giving workers more space and flexibility, as well as broader borders, will help recruit a new generation of employees.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:26:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mata Minor, in the prison “committed suicide”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/mata-menor-na-prisao-suicidou-se/</link><description>Family or passionate crime is increasing every year. Authorities have no hands to measure to investigate the causes of crimes, and in most cases investigators are perceived. There are people who kill or have their mates kill, allegedly, for love.
It is a transverse reality to all age groups and all social strata, which happens throughout the year. The passion crime happens by jealousy, revenge, a sense of possession brought to the extreme, or simply because the relationship has ended and cannot be lived without the presence of the other person - most of these passionate crimes are imputable being rare cases of unconsciousness due to pathological causes.
Quem decide castigar desta forma os seus companheiros ou ex-companheiros, encontra sempre uma razão que legitima a morte do outro. Acontece muitas vezes o homicida, suicidar-se de seguida. Os dados mais recentes apontam para um aumento no homicídio conjugal em Portugal, nos últimos dez anos. O pior de tudo é quando o crime passional insere a morte dos filhos pequenos. Há psicólogos que ainda não arranjaram explicação cabal que justifique como é que um pai consegue matar um filho menor.
Our arrests are full of criminals, but in prisons there is a very special "statute" for the prisoners who have killed their mate or a child, as they will know later. This internal status is a justice for those who, even having committed another kind of crime, does not accept or admit to killing a child. The arrests of our country have been dozens of times in the various media. Or because they have more prisoners, without hygiene conditions, without food with the minimum of quality, with little recess, with the postponement of medical support, finally, a gap panoply that places Portugal on the tail of countries that do not fulfill human rights rules. The Portuguese prisons are a world apart, where it happens a little and even escapes so scandalous that they are international news. We recently had that Jewish Valley Escape, where five of the biggest detained criminals managed to escape while a vigilante ate a cream pastel…
By the way, with us a prison guard resides with us and one day I invited him to have a coffee. By chance, I drank the coffee but he drank six beers. All good. The conversation demonstrates well what is happening in the underworld of prisons.
So you now had an increase. Wasn't it bad?
Ah!… O senhor pensa que o aumento no salário foi alguma coisa que resolva a vida difícil que temos? Nem pensar. 
And the risk allowance?
Look, I haven't received anything yet and from what I heard there in the prison of Monsanto, the risk allowance is a bullshit…
Tell me one thing: How was it possible that those dangerous criminals had managed to escape from the Jewish valley? And why weren't they in Monsanto?
Well, first I never realized how the worst of them was in my Monsanto prison and was transferred to Jewish Valley, where I had friends… Surely there was a lot of money…
To whom?
Well, that now I can't tell you, but the Lord certainly imagines that those who are in prison are not saints ... and that escape was very well prepared with the mobster support from abroad.
But, you prison guards are the reputation for being corrupt. To take the drug, to introduce mobile phones and other lethal objects…
Not quite. We cannot take a dry branch through the tree. Of course, I have colleagues who make good money from what they just said, but not all. And about the mobile phones and drugs, I can tell you that we have already caught women of prisoners who were visiting and had all this inside the vagina…
A mobile phone?
Exactly! Nothing special for some…
Another thing, do you run or not danger to life, or have a "agreement" with prisoners' heads?
We risk life if we make black life to prisoners. There are many who do not play in service, there are many who control the drug business through coded abroad messages, there are even mobsters who control life within arrests in all aspects and even control abroad activity. I give you an example: in prisons there is a certain “statute” among prisoners. These heads of the prisoners admit nothing to those who go to prison for killing the woman or a small son… Then we couldn't do anything, even if we put the children who killed their children… They arrange the way when the bath time treats them.
Do they take a beating?
Batcher? A lot and not only. They sticking them with a stick by the tail inside, oblige them to oral sex and whenever they can kill them…
And the news is not given to the family and the public?
Of course, the information is given. But always the same way.
As?
That the prisoner committed suicide ...
- And you, prison guards, silents…
Obviously. Do you have no family either? Are you realizing me?
Absolutely. I would like to ask him something else: there is a lot of homosexuality in prisons. Do you allow?
It is not a matter of allowing. This happens during the bath, in the cells with more than one inmate, in the work in the countryside and even in the libraries, especially oral sex.
Do you see any solution so that life in prisons can have more quality and more human rights?
I don't see. From now on it will always be worse because new arrests are not built, such as in the Nordic countries.
I thank this meeting and I can inform you that our conversation will be read in Macau, but be rested that your name does not exist. Thanks. I was pleased to know him better.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:21:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Let us be practical</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/sejamos-praticos/</link><description>The annual plenary session of the National Popular Congress and the National Committee of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference, held in Beijing, has recently ended. One of the main concerns of Macau representatives was the “Integration of Macao and Hengqin”. I transcribe an excerpt from a conversation I heard as I had breakfast, "Are you going to buy an apartment in Hengqin?" "No, if I wanted a house, I bought it in Zhuhai, because it gets closer to Macau."
Living in Hengqin certainly has its advantages. Many students from China who study at Macao universities live in Hengqin and catch the bus to the mud every day. There are also many residents and newly arrived people living in Hengqin for reasons related to work or children's school.
But even if they come to live in Hengqin, which has an area of ​​106.46 square kilometers, 100,000 people, or even more than 200,000, is still not much. At the time when the housing fractions of the “new neighborhood of Macau” were for sale, there were many restrictions, which were being raised over time on the grounds of “development policy changes with development”. But deep down, they are "policies that give in to reality." In fact, whether it is politics or economics, the practical sense is imposed.
I am not opposed to the improvement of the legal framework aimed at the “integration of Macao and Hengqin,” as it is necessary to clarify the difference between “in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin” and “New Zone of Hengqin”. If we think about the efforts that are being developed for the “integration of Macao and Hengqin,” we will see that Macau has played a more active role than Guangdong Province. In the case of Macao, I suggest that hengqin circulation of all types of vehicles from the city is allowed. However, how can Hengqin attract residents of Macao to live there and contribute to their development if there is not even a public parking park for Macao vehicles at the Hengqin border post?
If there are those who ask that the “Macao vehicle circulation policy in Guangdong province” has already made it difficult to survive companies in the North Zone of Macao, then if these vehicles are allowed to circulate in Hengqin, will this not even have negative consequences for Macao's economy? In my opinion, the introduction of reforms in the commercial sector is just a way to get out of your current situation. It is a priority to end the monopoly of the commercial sector, to open the economy to different markets, to develop and use the unoccupied land as much as possible, while reducing the negative impact of “road works” on companies and store owners.
For example, the Jockey Club of Macao has been closed since last year and the clues have been covered with grass. However, the Macao government has not announced any development plan for the site, thus being wasted valuable resources. Perhaps the Macao government can be inspired by the operational management of Hong Kong's “Kai Tak Sports Park”.
As for this subject, the Macao Executive can grant one of six resort and leisure companies integrated the Jockey Club's land development and management rights for a given period of time, which can somehow help create a new commercial zone that attracts the consumption of more tourists.
It would also be important to create political incentives and/or flexibility of restrictions on companies to attract traders to settle in the old neighborhoods and community neighborhoods throughout the city. If we look at the “reordering of the amendment street and four other streets of the parish of Santo António” that took place a few years ago, and compare the agitated environment that existed before and after reordering, it becomes evident that the “ideas” that come out of those who “are sitting in their offices” have to be put to the test to be effective. We impose on reality only usually results in disaster.
The “Integration of Hengqin and Macau” is an ambitious venture that the homeland has entrusted to Macao. Before Hengqin is officially under the jurisdiction of Macao, the most important thing is to preserve and develop Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 17:17:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence in Macao Culinary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/20/inteligencia-artificial-na-culinaria-de-macau/</link><description>"Macau's Opulent Fine Dining Scene is Using Ai to Tackle Sustainability: How Restaurants in Galaxy Macau, Sands China and Grand Lisbon Are Leading The Green March Forward."
Amanda Sheppard
Macao's cuisine scene, a region known for its vibrant mixture of Portuguese and Chinese influences, is taking its first steps in a technological revolution with the integration of Artificial Intelligence (IA). AI entered the world of cooking as a tool of efficiency and innovation. In Macao, a territory with a diverse culinary heritage, AI application may reshape traditional approaches to food.
The fusion of advanced technology with rich culinary traditions creates a unique landscape, offering both opportunities and challenges. The historical background of the kitchen in Macau enhance the unique identity of the region. Macau was a Portuguese colony for over four centuries, creating an intricate mix of Asian and European culinary practices.
This mixture formed a rich culinary tapestry, with dishes such as cod and minchi macanese to gain local and international fame. As we examine this story, we appreciate the unique features of Macao's kitchen, which AI technologies are now prepared to improve. In recent years, the growing adoption of AI technologies in the global gastronomic scene has marked a significant change. Restaurants began to use AI for various purposes, such as improving customer experience and rationalizing food preparation processes.
AI -powered chatbots, for example, entered the world of food services, providing customers immediate assistance to navigate the menus, order, and make reservations. This technology eliminates linguistic barriers, allowing tourists and local inhabitants to get involved with culinary offers smoothly. In addition, the food preparation sector is watching the influence of robotics and intelligent equipment. AI algorithms can optimize cooking processes by analyzing data on ingredients, cooking times and consumer preferences.
This data -based approach allows bosses to focus on creativity by minimizing the risks of human error. For example, Michelin restaurants such as Chief Tam Seasons, SJM's Robochon Au Dôme, Galaxy's Walk Kitchen and The Londoner's Churchill’s Table are all stimulating change and received praise for using AI to improve operational efficiency and maintain high food quality standards. Heads António Coelho, Sally Jimenez and Cristiano Tavares do Lisboeta study the introduction of AI into their culinary practices. Mizumi's chief André Chiang is making progress in the world of culinary with technology. Known for his innovative gastronomy approach, chief Chiang has taken advantage of AI in his culinary developments. Its Japanese restaurant at Wynn Macau uses smart technologies to improve traditional kitchen techniques.
When using AI tools to analyze customer reactions and service standards, it can continually improve dining experience. The prospects for the role of AI in Macao cuisine range from the professionals of the sector. Some bosses adopt the integration of technology, facing it as a way of overcoming the boundaries of cooking. The supporters argue that AI can help maintain the cultural essence of Macaense food, while innovating with new flavors and presentation styles. By analyzing large amounts of culinary data, AI may suggest unique combinations of ingredients that could not occur to human heads.
On the other hand, there are those who express concern about the potential loss of authenticity. Critics argue that trusting technology can harm traditional kitchen methods and the human touch that is an integral part of the culinary arts. Its point of view underlines the importance of preserving heritage and emotional links associated with handmade food.
Despite these different perspectives, the thesis remains that AI's role in Macao's culinary industry can represent a fascinating evolution and not a substitution of human ability.
(continues)</description><pubDate>2025-03-20 02:16:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Letters Route | Cinema by Luís Filipe Rocha this week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/rota-das-letras-cinema-de-luis-filipe-rocha-esta-semana/</link><description>The Rota das Letras Literary Festival presents this week a series of films by Portuguese director Luís Filipe Rocha, including “Love and Fores de Fé”, adaptation of Henrique de Senna Fernandes's novel, filmed in Macao.
After the exhibition, yesterday, of "Gray and Black", in Capitol Cinema, today will be displayed, also in the same place, "Cerromior", from 18h, and "Love and Fores de Fé", from 21h. This Thursday will also be displayed “Signs of Fire” in the auditorium of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, from 20:30.
Also noteworthy is the exhibition, tomorrow, of a short film based on a tale of Valério Romão, one of the festival guests, followed by the projection of a documentary about Natália Correia, by Rosa Coutinho Cabral. The session is attended by one of the acts that make up the cast of this documentary, Alexandra Sargento.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:24:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | G-Dragon starred in two concerts in June</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/galaxy-g-dragon-protagoniza-dois-concertos-em-em-junho/</link><description>The Galaxy Arena, one of the main show rooms in the territory, is preparing to receive two concerts from the South Korean rapper and composer G-Dragon, integrated into the “Ubermensch” tour, which also goes through other Asian cities. This is the opportunity for the local audience to see and listen to one of the sleepless names of South Korean music
 
G-Dragon, Kwon Ji-Yong's stage name, is a 36-year-old South Korean rapper and songwriter who, in June, named after 7 and 8, comes Macao for two shows at the Cotai Galaxy Arena, who promise to delight fans or lovers of South Korea music.
The two shows are part of the “übermensch” tour, which means superhuman, and which goes through several Asian cities, namely Tokyo, on May 10 and 11; Bulacan, in the Philippines, on May 17; Osaka, on May 25 and 26 and then Taipei, Kuala Lumpur and Jakarta, in July.
Highlighted by Forbes magazine in 2016, as the most influential person in Asia's entertainment industry under 30, G-Dragon is linked to the world of the show and the arts since childhood, as his first television appearance took place on the children's “BBO BBO BBO” children's program. At the age of six he joined the children's group “Litlle Roo'ra”. Over the years he bet on rap, also becoming a composer, entrepreneur and fashion designer.
His connection to hip hop was gradual, having integrated in 2006 the boys-band "Big Bang", releasing the solo album "Heartbreaker" in 2009, which included a song of the same name. Success felt right there, as it was recognized as the “album of the year” at Mnet Asian Music Awards. The following year, 2010, was already part of another musical group, the “T.O.P.”, which released an album of the same name, also another of success.
The first G-Dragon worldwide diffress took place in 2013, calling itself “One of a Kind World Tour”, and that same year it released its second studio album, “Coup d'Atat”, which was also worth recognizing criticism.
With regard to the musical style, G-Dragon says he is inspired by the Wu-Tang Clan group and the American Pharrell Williams, which is his "musical hero." Other hip-hop names, such as Kanye West, count on your reference list.
A kind of revolution
According to Tatler Asia magazine, Kwon Ji-Yong managed to innovate and “transcend the traditional borders of Asian pop star”, turning everything into “creative gold” into musical terms.
It is classified by this publication as a chameleon in the music world, and in almost 20 years of career it was “a virtuous musician, provocative of fashion and an innovative entrepreneur” who caught the attention of fans. It presents “avant-garde clothing” that wear “an artistic genius whose professional trajectory permanently altered the DNA of Korean entertainment”, writes Tatler on G-Dragon.
About the fashion designer aspect, it is described that G-Dragon does much more than wearing such “avant-garde clothing”, turning them into “cultural statements”, having been Chanel's first Asian global ambassador.
In the fashion week in Paris, the South Korean rapper dared to wear women's tweed coats, transposing the limits of the gender. G-Dragon recently adopted an aesthetics called the "Grandma-Core", which includes the use of head scarves and a red-haired hair. It may or may not shock, but the style remains.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:22:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Tickets for sale since Saturday to the 35th edition of FAM</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/bilhetes-a-venda-desde-sabado-para-a-35-a-edicao-do-fam/</link><description>Since Saturday, tickets are for sale for the 35th edition of the Macao Arts Festival (FAM), which runs between April 25 and May 31, and this year's central theme is the idea of ​​“growth”. It is presented to the public, with organization of the Cultural Institute (IC), a set of 15 shows that cover theater, Chinese opera, dance, circus, music and visual arts.
This edition of FAM starts with “The Life of Pi”, a theatrical production of West End of London and Broadway, which, with FAM, begins the first tour of East Asia in Macao. The show blends state -of -the -art techniques with impressive puppets techniques to explore the meaning of life and the theme of courage.
Moreover, in order to show the idea of ​​“East-Kidade Meeting, Asia in Harmony”, linked to the “Culture City of East Asia 2025-Macao, China” initiative, two shows are presented. They are “Deling and Cixi”, a collaboration between Beijing and Hong Kong teams that recreates intimate narratives in the court's private rooms during the Qing dynasty; and also the Cantonense opera concert “Discorting Harmonious Voices”.
This musical show is presented by the Chinese orchestra of Macao along with notable figures of the Cantonense opera, such as Zeng Xiaomin and Wen Ruqing, making known to Macau's public the culture of Lingnan.
Another of the highlights of the 35th edition of FAM is the show “A Phoenix Louca”, from the Cantonense opera troupe of Foshan. It is an adaptation of a classic play centered on the life of the talented playwright Kong Yu-Kau, which will provide viewers with a totally new experience, maintaining the dramatic intensity of the piece and ingeniously integrating innovative elements of the Cantonense opera.
Japan Premiere
FAM also features the original Japanese musical “Kiki, the Apprentice of Witch”, which in Macau will have its debut outside Japan. In this show, it presents itself with a new musical repertoire and a production team that will faithfully capture the charm of the homonymous work and animation.
Local audiences can also see the Tago, from South Korea, which feature “the shaman's beat”, a show that will combine traditional percussion techniques with a modern aesthetic.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:13:14</pubDate></item><item><title>World Book Day | IC organizes “Book Exchange” and various activities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/dia-mundial-do-livro-ic-organiza-troca-de-livros-e-varias-actividades/</link><description>April is a month to celebrate the reading. On the 23rd, the “World Book Day” takes place, and in this context, the government, through the Cultural Institute, will organize a series of programs to promote reading, such as the exchange of old books, and other activities
 
The “World Book Day” is celebrated on April 23rd and, therefore, the Cultural Institute (IC) organizes activities such as the “Book Exchange”. In various places of the city there will also be reading points, in an activity designated by “joint reading month throughout the city of Macau 2025”, that is, throughout April.
The “Book Exchange” initiative has begun, notably with regard to the process of collecting books that people can have in their homes and who want to exchange for others through a point system. The delivery of old works can be done until April 13, and residents can deliver their collections of books that meet the conditions required in the 11 public libraries under the IC aegis, including the Macao Central Library, the Sir Robert Ho Tung library, the mud library and the Seac Pai Van library, among others.
This year, for the first time, there will be an electronic system of points, and each book will be classified according to the original price, being attributed a unit for every 10 patacas or to a fraction of not less than five patacas. The maximum score per book or collection is 100 units. In collection of electronic points, residents can use the application “my library”. The exchange of books will take place on April 26 and 27, with the points obtained to be replaced by the new works chosen, to the counters of the Macao Cultural Center and the Auditorium of the Seac Pai Van Activities Center.
The IC describes that, in the book exchange system, no textbooks and textbooks, magazines, pornographic publications, damaged books or non -original books are allowed.
Readings in the city
Another activity of promoting the book, is the “reading points”, a program where you can register the entities or associations of the territory. The aim is to “share reading time in community neighborhoods, increase participation and broaden reading coverage to the public”.
Thus, interested parties can submit their proposals for the organization of “reading points” by April 30, and these “points” can be organized in stores, restaurants, schools, educational centers, associations, companies and offices, with no format limitations.
Participating entities must organize reading activities by their own initiative from April 1st to 30th and present photographs and the number of participants after the activities. Relevant photographs will be published on the thematic electronic page of libraries and on the cultural pages of IC on social networks, “so that more residents can feel the charm of reading,” explains the IC.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:11:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Legionella | Tourist in serious condition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/legionella-turista-em-estado-grave/</link><description>A 58 -year -old tourist is in serious condition due to a Legionella infection, known as Legionaries' disease. The infection was diagnosed on Saturday at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, and the patient has a history of chronic diseases.
According to the report presented by the health authorities, the man traveled inland with his family on 10 March. On the other side of the border went to the doctor, after having had fever but did not show improvements. He returned to Macao on March 19, having a shortage of breath, which made it entry into the Conde São Januário Hospital Center.
On March 20, the patient resorted to hospital medical assistance, having been diagnosed with pneumonia in both lungs, which led to the need to connect to the mechanical fan. The next day, the analyzes to the expectoration presented a positive result for Legionella, with complications for respiratory failure.
According to the SS, "currently, the patient is considered severe, and still needs respiratory support by mechanical fan." Authorities also indicated that family members did not have any symptom of malaise.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:13:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Pass | Thousands of elderly people carried a card for discounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/macau-pass-milhares-de-idosos-carregaram-cartao-para-descontos/</link><description>Early in the early hours of the morning, seniors formed lines at the door of the services to change or carry Macau Pass cards and access the discounts of the great consumption award. Until 1pm, more than 22,200 elderly people had already enjoyed the benefits of the consumption incentive program
 
Even before opening the doors, a line with about half hundred people was at the entrance of the Macau Pass Service Center in the Preta Areia, announcing the beginning of another round of the consumption award, which began yesterday.
Before starting the initiative to distribute consumer coupons to residents, to boost local businesses in neighborhoods away from tourist circuits, more than 10,000 residents asked to change Macau Pass to the elderly, 6,000 of which already had the card ready to use. The rest, in addition to residents who wanted to charge the card to access the 300 -Patacas automatic discount and start benefiting from the 50 percent discount on purchases, have been hosted on Macau Pass stores, as well as the various service stations to carry the cards.
The Director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, revealed that until 1 pm yesterday, more than 22,200 elderly people had already taken advantage of discounts under the initiative, according to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau. The official said the process was running without problems.
However, some elderly people waiting in the center of the center of Macau Pass in the black sand indicated that the earlier opening of the store would have made life easier for residents. An elderly woman said to the public broadcaster that she took off to the store to receive the new card, but that the place was full of residents who wanted to carry the card, see her balance, order second cards of cards, which resulted in a situation chaotic. In the immediate vicinity of the Macau Pass Service Center in the Preta Areia, the resident line clogged buildings of buildings, shops and parking parks.
Attention to fraud
The DSEDT director also stated that the government will be aware of fraudulent activities during the consumer incentive campaign and that a supervision mechanism was created together with financial institutions with payment applications to prevent consumers from buying something online to access the draw and then cancel the transaction. If activities of this genre are detected, residents will be prevented from participating in the coupon draw for the fraudulent transaction.
The president of the Macao Commercial Association, Frederico MA Chi Ngai, was optimistic about the impact of the major consumption award on small and medium enterprises. The leader of the association that organizes the initiative with the government advanced to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau that about a hundred traders plans to add a discount campaign to the consumer incentive program, and that more traders are expected to follow the example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:12:09</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM | Open registrations for 30 jobs</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/sjm-abertas-inscricoes-para-30-empregos/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) has announced that today open the registrations for the “Professional Development Plan in Guided Visit Service in SJM activities”, on a “First Hiring, After Training” regime, which will provide job opportunities with 30 job openings for the “Guided View Agent in activities” category.
Admitted candidates will receive vocational training for 18 months, divided between the Hotel Operations Department and the Activities Planning Department. The training includes initiation to arts and culture, practical English of Cambridge Linguaskills (Oral) - English conversation training course for the service provision sector, Forbes Travel Guide - Basic Excellence Training in the Guided Tour Service and Course.
Those who have good use in the evaluations and pass the training phase can continue their professional career in one of the departments mentioned. Interested parties can register on the DSAL page until April 1st.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:10:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Maternity | APPLIED ATTRIBUTION OF FAMILY ASSEMBLY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/maternidade-pedida-atribuicao-de-abonos-de-familia/</link><description>Given the fall of birth, the associations ask the government of Sam Hou Fai to increase the number of support to families. In addition to the birth allowance, currently 5,418 Patacas, the creation of a family allowance and the extent of maternity and paternity licenses are asked
 
The General Association of Macao Women and the People's Youth Association have defended the assignment of families' allowances to help local families face increasing financial charges.
Through a statement, Loi I Weng, vice president of the Association of Women, indicated that there are currently about 23 provinces in the interior to distribute subsidies. For example, the city Hefei, in Anhui province, distributes a single allowance to couples with two or three children, with a value from 2,000 Renminbis to 5,000 Renminbis. In turn, the authorities of the city Jinan, in the province of Shandong, distribute monthly support to families who have two or three children of 600 Renminbis per child, until they have three years.
In Macao, Loi I Weng acknowledged that there is a birth allowance, currently in the amount of 5,418 patacas. However, LOI argues that the amount must be increased and the distribution of a family allowance must be considered, having as reference the value of the allowance for caregivers or the family of civil servants, which have the value of 2,175 patacas and 940 patacas, respectively.
For its part, the vice president of the Tam Sio Pang Youth Association also defended the idea of ​​childhood assistance.
Heard by the newspaper or Mun, the head of the Macao's Subordinate Alliance Association suggested that the government should follow the practice of the Hohhot city, the capital of the Autonomous Region of Mongolia Interior, which offers a unique subsidy worth 10,000 Renminbis to couples who have a child. When couples have two children receive about 50,000 Renminbis over 5 years, and if they have three children receive 100,000 Renminbis over 10 years.
Other requests
In addition to the subsidy, associations officials argued that it is also important for the government to launch other measures to create a “more favorable environment” to increased birth rate.
Loi I Weng suggested to the government to subsidize companies to implement work measures to support workers' families. In addition, the official considers that the government extend the license of maternity and paternity so that residents have less concerns about birth.
Tam Sio Pang also wants the extent of maternity and paternity license and argues that maternity leave should be increased to 90 days compared to 70 days. Tam Sio Pang also suggested that the government increase vacancies in subsidized day care centers, as well as a gradual integration of child care services into the free education system.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:09:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Man accused of domestic violence hurts two police officers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/homem-acusado-de-violencia-domestica-fere-dois-agentes-da-policia/</link><description>One resident wounded two police with a knife while trying to resist a detention. The case happened on Thursday after the man was the subject of a new ex-wife complaint for two theft crimes. Already last year he had been accused of domestic violence.
According to the newspaper or Mun, the Judiciary Police (PJ) was able to stop the man on Thursday after receiving a complaint for the ex-wife's theft. The alleged criminal was arrested near the vicinity of the former partner's housing.
When he realized that he was going to be arrested, the man tried to escape and used a knife to resist, slightly hurting two of the agents.
According to the contours of the case, after the divorce, the victim went to live alone in the Nam Van area. Man was applied as a measure of coercion the prohibition of contact with women, due to physical aggression, which will have happened in January.
However, on 25 February, the suspect violated the coercion measure, and went to the victim's house to discuss money issues. That day he physically assaulted the woman, besides having pointed to him a knife. The attacker also locked the woman at home for 31 hours. Before leaving, he stole a suitcase of 9,000 patacas that was sold by the suspect in the interior of China for 2,000 Renminbis.
On the 18th of this month, the man returned to his wife's house, took advantage of the fact that the door was not locked and asked him for money again. Once again he kidnapped the woman in the apartment for 15 hours, forcing her to apply for a 5,000-pass loan from a friend.
The case was referred to the MP for the crimes of forbidden weapon, theft, kidnapping, resistance and coercion, qualified offense to physical integrity and domestic violence.
Appeal to protection
After becoming public, the General Association of Macao Women's Women came to ask the government to improve the protection measures provided for in the Domestic Violence Prevention and Combat Law. For long years, this association has taken an abstention position in the face of the possibility of allowing the police to investigate the crimes of domestic violence without a complaint of the victims.
The director of the association's Lai Yuen Solidarity Center, Wong Law Law, came to the authorities to review the victims' protection measures during the proceedings that have not yet been tried, but where there were complaints, to ensure effective protection of the victims.
Wong Law Lei also highlighted the need for the authorities to investigate well the reason that led to the woman had not filed a complaint earlier, tolerating the aggressions.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:27:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Technology | More families with internet access in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/tecnologia-mais-familias-com-acesso-a-internet-em-2024/</link><description>Last year, about 97.7 percent of household aggregates sde macau accessed the internet, equivalent to 200,200 household aggregates, a total of 205,000 families. Data on the use of the Internet in Macau were revealed by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) and represent a growth of 0.4 percentage points in annual terms.
About 99.4 percent of household aggregates who accessed the internet used the mobile network.  The number of Internet users in Macau was 610,300, plus 13,000 people, a growth of 2.2 percent compared to the year 2023.
Approximately 91.4 percent of users accessed the internet daily, with the penetration rate increasing 1.2 percentage points to 94 percent.
The Internet penetration rate increased by 1.2 percentage points to 94 percent of the population for 2023. The rate of individuals aged 65 or over, recorded the most remarkable growth of 3.5 percentage points, causing 81.3 percent of the elderly to use the internet.
As for purposes, most users aimed to use communication applications or social networks, a total of 578,600 users. Use for entertainment (547,300 users) and online banking services or mobile payments (457,400) was followed.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:43:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Demography | Macaense population in San Francisco surpasses Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/demografia-populacao-macaense-em-sao-francisco-supera-a-de-macau/</link><description>A study released by a Chinese researcher concludes that, currently, the population of Macanese and Luso-Asia that resides in the area of ​​San Francisco Bay in the United States is larger than that of Macao
 
"There are about 70,000 macanese and Luso-Asia to reside in San Francisco, which is more than the number in Macao," researcher Leong Wong Un NA was told Lusa, who presented last Thursday at the University of Macao, the book "Macanese and Luso-Assian in the San Francisco Bay Area" from 1940 to 1950, a title that results from his doctoral thesis.
According to the latest censuses held in Macao in 2021, only 13,021 residents in Macau had Portuguese ancestry, representing 1.9 percent of the total population. The data also reveal that 6,668 people, 1 percent of the total population, had Chinese and Portuguese descent, characteristics usually used to define the Macanese community.
The Portuguese Leadership Council of the United States has a total population of 1,454,262 with Portuguese ancestry.
According to Leong, the Macanese, some of which had departed to various regions of Asia in the nineteenth century, Luso-Asian and the Portuguese in Asia, emigrated to the United States from Macao in the twentieth century, due to political and economic reasons, choosing as the main destination of the São Francisco Bay in California.
The Language Question
Leong Wong Un NA, a Chinese who grew up in Macao and says maintaining a close relationship with the Macanese community, has many family members resident in San Francisco, including parents and siblings.
The immigrated macanese and Luso-Asiatic-symatics in San Francisco, concluded Leong, were not soon recognized as Portuguese when they arrived in the United States and were even discriminated against for decades by the Portuguese community itself.
At the same time the Communist Party was taking power in China, “the macanese and the Luso-Asiatics, when they immigrated there [San Francisco], could not participate in the organizations created by the Portuguese of Portugal,” said Leong Wong Un na.
"Some of the descendants of Portuguese who came from Asia did not speak fluent Portuguese, so the Portuguese from Portugal said that if they did not know Portuguese, they were not Portuguese," he explained.
Leong describes in his book not only how the community of Macaenses and Luso-Asia that is currently living in the area of ​​São Francisco Bay, such as the origins and cultural traits of the Portuguese community there and even the architectural characteristics they have imprinted on the urban surroundings.
The researcher concluded that the Macaenses and Luso-Asia of San Francisco "maintain habits still very alive in Macau, such as the Macaense cuisine and the Catholic religion."</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:42:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim committed himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
E sobre a política dizia, desassombradamente:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Tokyo | Chinese mne accused of misrepresenting meeting statements</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/toquio-mne-chines-acusado-de-deturpar-declaracoes-sobre-reuniao/</link><description>The Japanese government announced yesterday that it presented a formal protest to China for “misrepresented” observations made by Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba during a meeting with Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi.
Wang and Ishiba met last Friday in Tokyo, at a reception of courtesy organized by the Japanese leader, on the eve of a trilateral meeting between the Japan, South Korea and China foreign ministers, with the aim of promoting future cooperation between the three neighboring countries.
After the meeting, the Chinese Foreign Ministry issued a statement stating that Ishiba "fully recognizes the important meaning" of the four documents signed between the two nations, when the deciplind of diplomatic relations in 1972, and that the Japanese leader "respects the positions defined by the Chinese party."
Japan urged Beijing to “immediately withdraw” the statement, which “does not resist” the facts, yesterday said Japanese government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi at a press conference. Hayashi considered "unfortunate" that the Chinese government issued a statement that "does not correspond to the truth."
The Japanese Foreign Ministry also condemned the Chinese statement in a note, stating that during the meeting with Wang, Ishiba “stressed the need to reduce concerns” in bilateral relations, including “the situation in the east of China”, “ensuring the safety of Japanese citizens in China” and raising Chinese restrictions on Japanese seafood importation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:29:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Increased defense expenses on the gutter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/taiwan-aumento-de-despesas-com-defesa-na-calha/</link><description>Taiwan announced yesterday that he will try to use accumulated surpluses in previous years to cover the increase in the defense budget announced by Taiwanese leader William Lai, who promised to increase military expenses to more than 3 percent of GDP.
In a parliamentary comparison, the head of the Taiwan government's Directorate of Budget, Accounting and Statistics, Chen Shu-Tzu, ensured that the executive will seek to finance this increase with an excess of 200 billion Taiwanese, without excluding the contraction of loans as a last appeal.
"In general, we hope not to get into debt. But if we have to stray, we have to do so, because the defense expenses are very important," he said, quoted by the state news agency CNA.
Taiwan's defense budget is currently around the Taiwanese $ 600 billion, after the oppositionist parliament, approving a number of budget cuts and freezes regarding the government's initial proposal.
Lai, considered a “independentist” and a “hunting” by the Chinese government, reiterated her intention to increase Taiwan's military expenses last Thursday to more than 3 percent of GDP this year, amid added tensions between Taipei and Beijing.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:28:26</pubDate></item><item><title>South Sea | Announced Naval Exercises with Thailand</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/mar-do-sul-anunciados-exercicios-navais-com-tailandia/</link><description>The naval forces of China and Thailand will perform the joint military exercise “Blue Strike-2025” in late March, in waters near the coastal city of Zhanjiang, in Canton province, southern China, the Chinese Ministry of Defense said yesterday.
The training will focus on anti-terrorist tactics in urban areas, as well as joint maritime and anti-submarine attack operations, with the aim of “strengthening practical cooperation and improving joint operational capabilities at sea,” said the Chinese Ministry of Defense, in a statement in his official Weibo account.
The Popular Liberation Army Navy and Thai Royal Navy will participate in the exercises, which are part of a series of bilateral exercises that the two nations began to perform in 2010.
Blue Strike-2025 will be the sixth edition of these joint training exercises, which aim to consolidate mutual trust, interoperability and coordination in maritime security scenarios in a context marked by increasing regional tensions. In its latest edition, “Blue Strike-2023”, the naval forces of both countries performed urban combat training, jungle survival and joint air operations.
China and Thailand also perform joint air exercises, such as “Falcon Strike”, whose most recent edition took place in August 2024 on a Thai base, to reinforce tactic cooperation between the respective air forces.
The Southern Sea of ​​China, where the exercise will be held, is a fundamental zone of Indo-Pacific, through which about 30 percent of world maritime trade and where several territorial claims overlap.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:18:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Fórum | Prometidos “resultados benéficos” a investidores estrangeiros</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/forum-prometidos-resultados-beneficos-a-investidores-estrangeiros/</link><description>The forum that gathered in Beijing High Government officials and representatives of companies such as Apple, Mercedes-Benz or Samsung served China to announce greater opening to the foreign market with benefits for all
 
Chinese vice-master-master, he Lifeng, told executives of several multinationals present in a Asian country forum that China will “continue to open”, with “advantageous results for all”.
On the sidelines of the China Development Forum, He has met with executive directors from companies such as Apple, Mercedes-Benz or Samsung, stressing that Beijing will take steps to “further improve the business environment,” the Chinese Ministry of Commerce said in a statement.
"China will host more investments from multinational companies, sharing development opportunities," said the minister, on the sidelines of the Forum, that Beijing presents as a dialogue platform between senior Chinese government leaders, multinational and academic executives.
The forum comes at a time when Beijing is trying to recover foreign investment, which has reached a record negative flows in 2024, and promote the development of the private sector, with confidence among investors close to historical minimums. He Lifeng described the Chinese economy as "very resistant" and "full of vitality."
Some of the executives who attended the event, which ended yesterday, should meet this week with Chinese President Xi Jinping, according to Bloomberg news agency.
According to the Chinese government, the meeting is an opportunity to maintain direct contact with the leadership of the Asian country, being usually frequented by academics who sympathize with Beijing.
This year's theme, according to CGTN state television, is to “free all the potential for development”, with symposiums on macropolitics, scientific and technological innovation, environment or demographic challenges.
The forum has as its backdrop the slowdown of China's economy, in a period when facing the impact of the trade war launched by US leader Donald Trump.
Shoulder with shoulder
At the opening ceremony, Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang said Beijing is "prepared" for "unexpected shocks from abroad," referring to the trade war triggered by the US tycoon, and promised that China will open more sectors of its economy to foreign investment.
The Chinese executive chief urged international companies to “resist” to “protection”.
Li also met on Sunday with US Senator Steve Daines of the Republican Party, whom Beijing seeks “dialogue and cooperation with the United States”, and stressed that economic and commercial ties are “fundamental to bilateral relations”, according to an order issued by the official news agency Xinhua.
Li appealed to the United States to join the "principles of mutual respect and peaceful coexistence" and called for a "frank communication" to "deepen trust." Daines also met with vice-prime minister He, whom he transmitted Trump's appeal to "stop the flow of Fentanil precursors," and said he expected "more high level dialogue."
These were the first meetings of an American politician with senior Chinese officials since Trump's return to the Oval Room. The visit comes at a time when tensions between the world's two largest economies increase due to the mutual imposition of customs rates.
Actions trigger
The actions of CK Hutchison, by billionaire Li Ka-Shing, took up after one of their children was invited to a forum with high Chinese employees in Beijing, despite the sale of the company's ports in Panama. Richard Li was invited, as founder of Pacific Century Group, to the China Development Forum of the State Council.
Although Richard Li supervised his own business group and not playing any role in CK Hutchison, investors seem to have played their presence as a positive sign for the LI family.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Beijing and Tokyo together in the first high level dialogue in six years</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/pequim-e-toquio-juntos-em-primeiro-dialogo-de-alto-nivel-em-seis-anos/</link><description>Japanese Foreign Minister Takeshi Iwayaya and his Chinese homologist Wang Yi woke up on Saturday in a mutually beneficial cooperation during their first high -level economic meeting in six years.
In particular, the two ministers discussed issues such as decarbonization and the fight against the low birth rate, which are problems in both countries, and Iwayaa made a request to China to raise the ban on Japanese Impações de Seafood, imposed after the treated water of the Fukushima Electric Center began to leak into the sea.
The two ministers led the first high-level economic dialogue between Japan and China in six years, after a pause due mainly to Covid-19 pandemic, and the two countries later had separated conversations about bilateral relations in general.
At the beginning of economic conversations, Iwaya said, quoted by EFE agency, expecting the meeting to “personify” cooperation between the two countries and has committed to make efforts so that Japanese and Chinese citizens can “feel the benefits” of progress in bilateral relations.
Wang, for its part, seemed to criticize the recent policies of the ally near Japan, the United States, stating that "unilateralism and protectionism are on the agenda."
The meeting between the two countries takes place after the entry into force, in early March, of 20 percent rates on China, to which the Asian giant responded with customs rights of 10 percent and 15 percent over agricultural products from the United States.
China has already responded to a first round of 10 percent rates charging 10 percent to 15 percent over certain American products, as well as introducing new export controls on essential minerals and opening an investigation against the Google American technological giant.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:09:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin | Marathon delayed after attack that killed 35 people</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/hengqin-realizada-maratona-adiada-apos-ataque-que-matou-35-pessoas/</link><description>More than 19,000 people participated yesterday at the Hengqin marathon, which had been postponed after the city in southern China was the scene of an attack with a car that killed 35 people.
Authorities in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin reported that athletes from 12 countries and regions participated in the marathon, half marathon races and in a six -kilometer race.
In a statement, local authorities stressed that more than 900 runners came from Macao and showed hope that sport could also reinforce cooperation with neighboring semi -autonomous region. The marathon was originally scheduled for December 29, but six days earlier, the organization postponed the marathon to March 23, without any reason.
Marathon organizers include in -depth cooperation authorities between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, the Zhuhai Huafa group and Nam Kwong, a group controlled by the Guangdong province authorities but based in Macao.
By the end of November, the organizers had already postponed this year's edition of the Zhuhai Marathon, which was initially scheduled for December 8. The competition had been scheduled for January 12, 2025, but was eventually canceled.
On November 11, Fan Weqiu, a 62 -year -old man, drove a car deliberately against a multitude in a sports center in Zhuhai, causing the death of 35 people and injuries to 43. The striker “was angry” with the divorce process defined, according to a preliminary police investigation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:05:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing simplifies wedding records to encourage birth</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/pequim-simplifica-registos-de-casamento-para-incentivar-a-natalidade/</link><description>China announced on Saturday measures to simplify wedding registration and try to reduce financial pressure on bride and groom, as another measure to foster the increase in the birth rate.
Marriage is almost a prerequisite for having a child in China, as out-of-marriage births are poorly seen and do not offer the same level of recognition and protection.
However, the number of marriages decreased by 20.5 percent last year and, by 2024, China will register the third consecutive year of decreasing the population, which is a challenge for economic growth and pensions financing.
Authorities have already launched various measures, such as subsidies for those who marry and have children, and the construction of more children's reception centers was promised.
The last initiative states that couples can now register weddings anywhere in the country, according to information released on Saturday by state broadcaster CCTV, citing a government document.
So far, couples had to move to the place where the bride or groom were registered. For example, a couple living in Beijing for professional reasons, but whose wife was from Guangzhou and Shanghai's husband had to move to one of these two cities to fulfill the necessary formalities.
Financial obstacle
According to the channel, the Ministry of Civil Affairs also promises to "fight certain harmful habits such as excessive skills and excessively expensive marriage ceremonies." One dowry is the sum of money that the groom's family usually gives the bride and is often seen as a sign of respect for in -laws and a contribution to the beginning of the young couple's life.
But in some cases the amounts became very high, creating financial pressure for the groom's family and feeding social inequalities. Many young Chinese are reluctant to marry and have children.
Among the main reasons for this, there are financial disability to buy an apartment, which is often a previous condition for marriage, and the high cost of education, from child care to private classes, considered almost indispensable for a child's school success.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:54:58</pubDate></item><item><title>China | PM promises to open more sectors to foreign investment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/china-pm-promete-abrir-mais-sectores-ao-investimento-estrangeiro/</link><description>Li Qiang has pledged to reinforce the country's economic opening and protect the interests of “all companies”, regardless of the nationality of owners
 
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang has promised yesterday that China will open more sectors of the economy to foreign investment and "protect legitimate rights and interests from all companies."
The guarantee was given in a speech given at the opening of the China Annual Development Forum in Beijing, which was attended by important business leaders. Li emphasized the commitment of the Chinese regime to “economic opening” and also asked international companies to resist protectionism.
"We hope entrepreneurs will bear more active measures to maintain globalization," said Beijing government number two. Li also stated that he expects business leaders to “work together, cooperate and achieve greater development of (…) companies for mutual benefit”.
"The Chinese government will strive to protect the legitimate rights and interests of all companies," regardless of the nationality of the owners, promised the prime minister. The forum is attended by executives from multinational companies such as Mercedes-Benz and Samsung, including the executive director of the US technology Apple, Tim Cook.
Predict
Beijing has been trying to restore consumer and business confidence for months, which has been weakened by a persistent crisis in the real estate sector and new commercial tensions with the United States.
I read Qiang said Beijing is prepared for “unexpected external impacts,” referring to the trade war triggered by US President Donald Trump. "We are prepared for unexpected shocks, which, of course, come mainly from abroad. The Chinese government will have policies in force to ensure the proper functioning of its economy," Li said.
The leader promised that China will continue in the “right direction of globalization” in the face of the growing fragmentation of the world economy as the trade war with the US intensifies. "As a large responsible country, China will remain firmly on the right side of history (…) [practicing] true multilateralism," Li said at a meeting with leaders of multinational companies in Beijing.
China "will follow the correct direction of economic globalization, will practice true multilateralism and strive to be a force of stability and certainty," Li said, adding that "the fragmentation of the global economy is intensifying," while "instability and uncertainty are increasing."</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:47:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Inflation slows down in January</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/hong-kong-inflacao-desacelera-em-janeiro/</link><description>Inflation in the Hong Kong region slowed down in February, when mainland China fell into deflation for the first time in over a year, it was announced yesterday.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) rose 1.4 percent in February, compared to the same period, Hong Kong's Census and Statistics Department (CSD) reported. In January, inflation settled in 2 percent.
In a statement, the CSD justified the slowdown with the impact of Lunar New Year's variation, "particularly food prices and tour package costs." The Lunar New Year, the largest mass movement in the world, is the main traditional party of Chinese families and takes place in January or February, depending on the lunar calendar.
This year, the so-called 'Gold Week', a period of holidays in mainland China, celebrated between January 28 and February 4, while in 2024, this high time for tourism in Hong Kong took place in February.
“To neutralize the effect of the Chinese New Year,” the CSD stressed that homologous inflation for the first two months of 2025 set out at 1.7 percent, higher than in December (1.4 percent). The CSD also recalled that a 10 percent increase in the income of most residents in public housing in Hong Kong came into force in January.
A local government spokesman argued that inflation was modest in February and added that, overall, "pressures on the prices of various main components have remained widely contained."
In a statement, the spokesman predicted that inflation "should remain moderate in the short term," but admitted that "uncertainties arising from geopolitical tensions and commercial conflicts continue to demand attention."</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 17:08:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Vera Lúcia Raposo, jurist and teacher: “It was propagated today as a virus”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/vera-lucia-raposo-jurista-e-docente-ia-propaga-se-hoje-como-um-virus/</link><description>Vera Lúcia Raposo presented on Wednesday at the University of Macao the new regulatory framework of the European Union for Artificial Intelligence, in a session promoted by the Institute of European Studies of Macao. The former Macao University officer argues that China is gaining the race in an area that has never been so present in our lives
 
 
Spoke on Wednesday of “Ai Act” approved by the European Union (EU). Specifically, what are the main points of this document?
This is the Artificial Intelligence Regulation (IA) published last year in the EU official newspaper. It is a European law, but it is also, so far, the most detailed legal regime about the products surrounding AI.
Is it difficult to legislate on the AI ​​at this preliminary phase?
Maybe we will never stop being at this stage. Notice, AI did not come up with ChatgPT or anything that looks like. Since the middle of the last century, and even before, but especially since Alan Turing's 'Paper' that Ia exists, first in the laboratory, girded with a group of researchers. Then it began to be released into the world and to be part of our lives, but never as now. We are currently in a kind of pandemic, where AI propagates in our existence as a virus, but not a bad virus, because I understand that the AI ​​often propagates with positive effects. Of course, although it is not a completely new thing, it is a very mysterious reality for us jurists. The problem begins that we can't even get a definition mostly accepted by experts of what AI is. First of all, we don't know what it is, because it is a moving entity that constantly changes. What we thought was ten years ago, today it will be an algorithm.
In the areas of private life defense, or personal data, for example, or copyright, what does European legislation tell us in concrete terms?
The AI ​​regulation [of the EU] is part of what we call “Data Package” [Data Package], it is inserted in the group of regulations that concern product security. But this is understood in very comprehensive terms, not only security as we are used to thinking about it, as something that calls into question physical integrity, but covers environmental issues, respect for fundamental values ​​and technology rights and data protection. It is true that the regulation has these practical aspirations and realization in some standards, but the idea is to develop with other existing regulations on data protection and intellectual property, and that does not conflict with them.
We currently have ChatgPT on the American side, and DeepSeek on the Chinese side. Do you think China positions itself as a leader in the AI ​​area?
China is found to be a colossus in the digital world. The way the world has been evolving has differentiated. 100 years ago we had war conflicts, and today we have wars where we continue to kill people, but we also have commercial wars and these technological wars. And I say that more than a war is a race to reach the new invention. The old blocks of countries have different strategies. For example, in the case of the United States of America (USA), this strategy has changed a lot with the presidency of Trump, but was always more liberal and "Laissez-Faire". This has also been the form of US action, but with Trump is more in the line of "Vale Tudo", what matters is to arrive first. There is a great promotion of technological companies, as you see with the great support they gave to Trump's presidential campaign. Then we have China, with a state policy, which is not so much in the hands of the private. There is a great focus on technological advancement, but it is visible that the country is already in a position that will hardly be achieved by others. Europe is not exactly well positioned.

Why?
Europe has made the decision that the best way to develop technological progress and foster innovation is through hyper-regulation. There is no centimeter that is not regulated or not being regulated by the EU. Of course, it may have some advantages, and the aspirations can be in the face of controlled and sustainable development, and respect our fundamental rights and the rule of law. But I have some doubts. First, that this is achieved, because the protection of fundamental rights does not go through this hyper-regulation either. Then it seems to me that we are doing this at the expense of a value that seems to me, which is innovation. This idea comes, by the way, in the report of Mario Draghi, who warned the EU to the ability to mortgage future generations because we are leaving innovation behind. I don't see that any of these three technological models [US, China and EU] be particularly fruitful because they have benefits and disadvantages. We have an interesting model, which is the British.
In what sense?
The United Kingdom maintains the legal framework it inherited from the EU, and has not yet changed it. The United Kingdom will not adopt AI regulation [Europe's Ai Act], because it is no longer part of the EU, it seems that it will not create such a regulatory framework, but have an approach that is having a very generic picture that fixes the main points and limits, but then there will be a sectoral regulation. This regulation, which is still being created, is to establish the 'guidelines' for each area of ​​activity, so that there is autonomy in each sector and always respecting the particularities of each. In theory, it is more interesting, but everything is at first and I have not seen cases applied in practice.
How do you comment on the use of AI in the legal and judicial area?
Using sources that are not desirable to do our work was not something that came with ChatgPT. Speaking of something I know well, such as academic theses or scientific papers, it is not unprecedented that some less scrupulous authors quote sources in which they have never put their eyes, and then quote the wrong way, or quote sources that do not exist. There are situations in which unafable sources are cited, such as blogs, or papers that have not been subject to the peer review system. This is not new. We have the chatgpt beside it helps a lot and the temptation is great. I don't think it's the end of the world. Literacy was fundamental to the academy and any citizen. We all have to understand the benefits of Generative AI and risks as well. Research on Wikipedia pages can also generate errors. It is impossible to tell students not to use chatgPT, because this ban would be hollow. I can't know how people do their job. There may be situations of scientific dishonesty and situations where information is not true, but if someone tells me who wrote something with ChatgPT support, I have no problem with that. I have if the person is considered to be the author's author. ChatgPT works a lot as a Google search, it's not completely new. But I have to realize that the information that ChatgPT gives me has to be very analyzed and again investigated. ChatgPT can only give me clues where I can go, and then it can be useful and make us think. It is a source like any other, but it is not very credible. Chatgpt never deals with things in detail, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 16:42:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby Hui, President of the Macao Autism Association: “Autism differs from person to person”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/ruby-hui-presidente-da-associacao-de-autismo-de-macau-autismo-difere-de-pessoa-para-pessoa/</link><description>Created in 2012, the Macao Autism Association continues to fight for more care for children and young people with this development disturbance. But the association's president, Ruby Hui, warns of the need for more incisive policies for adolescents and their specific needs, especially in access to employment
 
 
What balance does the work done by the association in recent years?
My work is above all to establish a connection with all the entities and resources made available by the government and also the game industry, as the authorities have started to [the context of the new game concession contracts] that develop more social support activities. Therefore, we have gathered all these resources to organize recreational activities for children and youth. In addition, we organize therapy sessions for our members. Usually, we request financial support from private companies and the government, covering 30 to 50 percent of these expenses.
The support of the game sector is therefore quite important.
Yes, but it has not really been a great support. For example, the government covers part of our monthly expenses, about 40,000 patacas. But this amount comes only to hire two full -time employees and one part -time employee. They are the ones who organize all activities, deal with the bureaucratic part, which includes the presentation of many reports to the government, because we ask for subsidies for almost half of our expenses.
Therefore, do you consider that they need more support from the executive to be able to hire more professionals?
Yes, it would be ideal. Associations like ours are getting bigger and the children we support are growing. I would say that 60 percent of our members are 11 or more, and about 20 percent are even larger, over 14 years old. We have to think about their future and the needs of therapy and treatment for adolescents, as it is not only small kids who need therapies such as speech or occupational therapy. They are young people who are still in high school and need to acquire different types of social skills, boys need to know how to deal with girls and vice versa. Then, when they become adults, they need to know how to deal with bosses in jobs. There are many valences to explore, but at this moment I would say that the supports are not enough.
Are schools not yet prepared to receive these students, for example?
Autism may be different from person to person. Students with autism, but who have better learning skills, are in normal schools. But parents tell me that there are not enough teachers with certain skills to deal with and teach these children. There are teachers who still have a very traditional mindset to treat these young people, who often have to deal with alone with bullying, for example. I would say that there are many children and young people with autism with psychological problems because of the school.
When it speaks of the traditional mindset, what does this mean in concrete?
In the case of my son, for example, he is obliged to always be sitting at school, but often likes to move and get up from his chair. From the point of view of parents who have children with this problem, there would be no problem, as long as it did not bother others, but for teachers it cannot be, and complain. They say things of the genre: "He will beat the table, he will move the painting, makes a lot of noise." Every day I receive complaints from parents to connect with the school, and for small situations like this.
What are the main difficulties or challenges that Macao families face when they deal with an autistic child?
In my case, my family is middle class, and we are financially well. But when my son was younger needed to do therapy and it was very expensive. Now these therapies cost even more. At the time my son was in primary education, 600 to 700 patacas was paid for each therapy session, but there are days a father told me that the sessions now cost about 1000 patacas per class, which is very expensive. Families of lower social classes cannot afford. Therefore, this support is one of the great objectives of our association, raising money so that we can provide explanations, therapy sessions or other type of support. All so that our members can attend classes with 50 percent discount, where the association pays half the amount.
When the association was created, what were its main objectives?
Em 2012 o autismo não era um tema muito falado. Por isso, juntámo-nos [alguns pais e famílias] e começámos a pedir apoio ao Governo e a tentar chamar a atenção para o assunto. Conseguimos algumas coisas, porque o Governo agora dá mais apoio a estes jovens, pelo menos para os que têm menos de 12 anos. O problema que sentimos é que esses jovens estão a crescer e para os adolescentes são necessários outros tipos de apoios, que não existem.
What is necessary to change in mindsets and society in relation to autism?
In Macao there are not many companies willing to hire young people with autism. Situation that is not seen in Hong Kong, where there are several hiring programs with social companies. Macau needs to follow this path.
One day in Rio
World Autism Consciousness Day is celebrated on April 2 and, in this context, the Macao Autism Association joined Sands China for a series of activities with children and parents, which took place last March 10th. Through the program “Sands Care”, the game operator provided a visit to the exhibition “Coastal Fantasia”, with the figure of “King Lobster”, a creation of Philip Colbert artist ” A boat trip through the Delta of the Pearl River.
In total, 70 people participated. Quoted by a game operator statement, Ruby Hoi said the tour "allowed children to enjoy the maximum of the trip." "Thank you for all the support provided to people with autism in Macau, and I hope that all sectors of society can continue to support the development of these people and promote their inclusion in society," he said.
For the game operator, this type of events can help “reinforce the cohesion of families dealing with autism, but also promote the awareness of society and support for the community of people with autism fostering a more inclusive and supportive social environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul French, writer: Looking for Wallis Simpson in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/paul-french-escritor-a-procura-de-wallis-simpson-na-china/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival, which starts on Friday, will feature the presence of writer Paul French, who launched last year a new biographical book, "Her Lotus Year", which describes Wallis Simpson's experience in China before being a Duchess of Windsor. The British author will also talk about “Destination Macau”, a nostalgic and almost cinematic account of the city's history
 
How did you come to the history of Wallis Simpson's life experience in China?
I lived in Shanghai for many years and many visitors knew that Wallis Simpson had spent time in the city. Rumors ran on what he had done, and visitors always wanted to know if the rumors were true, such as the idea that she had learned esoteric sexual techniques or had posed naked for photographs. It was also said that he had belonged to a group of opium smuggling, or a group of bets that combined horses races. For me, as an author and expert in foreign experiences in Shanghai in the first half of the twentieth century, none of this made sense. So I thought this was the ideal time to really find out what Wallis had done in China. The fact that she was in the country in 1924 and 1925, two of the most fascinating years in the history of modern China, helped a lot.
How do you describe the life of the duchess in the country during that specific political period?
China was in total chaos when she was there, because Puyi, the last emperor, had been expelled from the forbidden city and occurred the biggest strikes ever in Hong Kong history. In addition, political fractions were recorded in Guangzhou, warlords of war in Shanghai and northern China. These were also the most wet years that there is a record in China, with crop production breaks and the occurrence of tiphoid and cholera fever outbreaks. He fired the number of bandits and pirates. Then, in March 1925, Sun Yat-Sen, leader of the Republican Revolution of 1911, died without leaving an obvious successor. Wallis came across all this, as he was retained on the island of Shamian, Guangzhou, while the city struggled; In Shanghai, he saw corpses to be brought to the city from the battles of the warlords; He saw victims of typhus and anger in Tianjin; and troops of the warlords threatening Beijing. But he was also largely in a foreign protective bubble that protected her from foreign soldiers and her white skin. He could delight in China's culture and aesthetics, while around him the whole country threatened to explode.
How was the personality of Wallis Simpson, a controversial figure in the context of the marriage to the Duke of Windsor?
It is very important not to confuse Wallis of 1924 with the later Wallis, from the long years of exile and controversy as Duchess of Windsor. In 1924 Wallis was only 28 years old, fleeing from a physically abusive husband (her first husband, Win Spencer, an American Navy commander) and was not yet particularly sophisticated or cosmopolitan. These were characteristics that would learn in China, mingling in the “colonies” [concessions] international foreign and bohemiums of Shanghai and Beijing. In fact, it was in Beijing that it first mixed with ambassadors, high -level Chinese politicians, high -ranking military officers and a stretch, and from them learned everything from playing Bridge and enjoying Jade to how to behave in high society. Obviously, this was useful a decade later when he met the Prince of Wales in England. Admittedly, the posterior Wallis, the Duchess, is a more difficult figure to like. Perhaps she and the Duke have made some bad political decisions and made some friendships, perhaps Wallis became a little bitter for not being accepted by the British royal family. But the truth is that in 1924 she was young, free of a bad husband and was in one of the most fascinating countries in the world.
What can readers perceive this figure and about China of that time, with "Her Lotus Year"?
China in 1925 was on the brink of potential explosion, as the whole country could have fallen into total chaos, dividing into the size of Portugal managed by warlords with private armies, or a resurgent Qing Dynasty supported by Japan in the North [China], the South and, of course, the foreign powers-England, America, France and Japan-who had Chinese lands like colonies. Ultimately, this did not happen, but no one knew this in 1925. Wallis herself oscillated between feeling incredibly comfortable and happy in what was her "year of lotus," as he described him, quoting Homer's Sopoifers who never want to return home; and feel terrified of the violence of the warlords or those who were against foreigners.
What are the biggest challenges, as a writer, in the process of researching the history of Wallis?
Wallis probably became the most photographed and spoken woman in history, more than Marilyn Monroe, more than Queen Isabel II. But in 1924 she was not famous at all. So it left a very difficult trail to follow. He wrote his memories, but these were "disinfected." A big problem was also the rumors that the British government and secret services circulated in 1936 in an attempt to destroy the idea of ​​a marriage between King Eduardo VIII and Wallis. The attempt failed because he abdicated the throne and they married, but these sexual rumors and insinuations, many of them racist and misogynists, have remained to this day, and they continue to be regularly recycled in the British and American Tabloid Press. I found the real Wallis a much more friendly character than I expected, and I hope readers will feel that too.
Is invited to another edition of Rota das Letras. How do you feel for being part of the festival?
I love to be part of the Macao Literary Festival. Although he had spoken before in Macao, namely in the Portuguese bookstore and other places, he had never participated in the festival. I look forward to being able to talk about Wallis Simpson and also about my new collection of rehearsals about Macau, entitled "Destination Macau". Some stories of Macao that have pleased me over the years, some of them presented with a more English look, as it were, may be interested and will be new to the local public.
Book | “Destination Macau”, the city between “The Imaginary and the Real”
Paul French has just launched the third volume of the “Destination” collection, which had editions of Shanghai or Beijing, and is now dedicated to telling stories of the ancient macao, a “place as imaginary as real”, as described the synopsis of the work. The work of the British author presents "The Macao by artists George Chinnery and George Smirnoff, from Writers Deolinda da Conceição and Maurice Dekobra, to the fantasies of" Pulp Fiction "and febrile dreams of Josef von Sternberg and Jean Delannoy."
There is still no shortage of Paul French, stories around historical figures such as Pedro José Lobo and Ian Fleming, author and creator of James Bond. Macao of the time of World War II, those who “came to Macao in search of gold, and those who sought war refuge” is described, not forgetting “the combatants looking for a secret passage through the 'neutral' macao”.
Paul French unveil mysteries or tells forgotten stories to many, such as the idea that Japan had tried to buy Macau in 1934 or the person who sailed with the Macau pirates queen, Lai Choi San. There are, in all, 18 stories “true of fascinating people who lived or visited Macau in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Augusto Nogueira, President of Artm: “Macau is ahead of Hong Kong”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/augusto-nogueira-presidente-da-artm-macau-esta-a-frente-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Macao toxicode dependent rehabilitation association is 25 years old this year. Augusto Nogueira makes a positive balance of the fourth century that began with a small therapeutic community and reached international recognition. The Association's president argues that, in prevention, Macau is at the head of Hong Kong and that the use of synthetic drugs is not yet problematic in the territory
 
 
What balance does the work developed by ArtM in these 25 years?
We do the balance very positive, because we started with a small area and a small therapeutic community. Nowadays we have a community with a capacity of 60 people, much more than the 15 we had at the time. We have developed several programs, namely the syringe distribution, which is a success, because it has led to a reduction and almost suppression of HIV contagion by people who inject drugs. For nine years there is the program and we have zero cases of infection. We developed support for social integration and follow -up after treatment, with “After Care”. We do preventive work in schools with the “Be Cool” program. We have the project “Hold on To Hope”, betting on vocational education, through coffee and the art gallery. It is a project that is well achieved and that turns out to be turned to tourism. We have visits from international entities and various non-governmental organizations, and the United Nations themselves. The most positive for us is to know how many people are recovered and who are well today. Unfortunately, we could not recover all people, but in each relapse there is always the possibility of the person coming again to do treatment.
How many people have recovered in 25 years?
We couldn't get this notion. We maintain contact with many people, but others have already left Macau, followed their lives. We have some contacts in the first two years after treatment, but then life goes on. People also want to go on a lifetime with no connection with the artm, sometimes marry and new companions don't know about their previous life and want to keep some confidentiality. But sometimes we meet. The other day they paid me a water without me knowing (laughs). These are small gestures that give us satisfaction to continue and make us believe that recovery is always possible.
What are the big challenges to maintain the ArtM project in terms of space and financing?
In terms of space and places for treatment we are well. The facilities are ten years old, there are maintenance problems, but this is more related to the panorama of construction in Macao. We need a space for the After Care, because what we have currently rented and is deteriorated. We are talking to the Institute of Social Action (IAS) to have a new space. With regard to the back, all our departments have financing, but we obviously seek support for our activities otherwise.
Regarding the authorities' posture regarding consumption and treatment, do you understand that it is still conservative in relation to other countries and regions?
This question is a little ambiguous. In terms of treatment and strategy in combating consumption, I think Macau is very ahead of Hong Kong, for example. In Macao, we have therapeutic community, we work on prevention and treatment, as well as our syringes and methadone distribution program. We have a range of treatments available to those in need. In the area of ​​prevention, the government has given a lot of support. The IAS has been quite open in strategies to combat consumption and prevention. In Hong Kong, for example, there is no syringe distribution program. Macao is from the few regions of Southeast Asia that has a government -supported syringes distribution program. But there could be another different interpretation of the law, with a differentiation between what is trafficking and their own consumption. For example, at this time if the person has a higher amount than that stipulated is soon considered trafficking, without proof. We think that in this case there should be a differentiation. It is then up to the police to investigate whether the quantities found are for consumption or trafficking. There should be an opening to give people more opportunities to be referred for treatment instead of going to prison. But lately, there have not been as many cases as that.
How do you describe the current consumer profile in Macau?
There is a large reduction in heroin consumption, and the few people who did so consume it today, or sleep. At this time the highest consumption is metabetamin, cannabis and some ketamine residues. As for the new synthetic drugs, there have been some records, but so far nothing alarming. But of course we have to be alert, we have to continue to do a good prevention job so that people are aware of the problems related to drug use. Regarding trafficking, we know that before the pandemic there was much cocaine trafficking to Macao, and after Covid-19 this situation almost ceased to happen. A good dissuasive work has been done and has to continue to be done so that there is less traffic to pass through Macau. It does not mean that there are no situations currently, but we are not in such a chaotic situation as that.
Speaking of synthetic drugs and their consumption, which according to the latest United Nations report has reached a worrying situation around the world. What is your comment to the scenario described in the annual report of the International Narcotics Control Board?
It is evident that the use of this type of drugs has been increasing over the years. Synthetic drugs are a real problem in the United States of America, for example, with fentanyl consumption, and Asia in some countries. It is a global problem because consumption and production are easy. Some of these drugs are made with other chemicals and many other products that are not well known to the origin and that can cause many overdoses. The UN suggests combating the production of ingredients that are used to produce these drugs, continue to reinforce the investigation to catch traffickers. But there are points of this report that it is necessary to follow, for many countries, which is the struggle between ideologies.
In what sense?
There is a struggle between those who argue that harm reduction is sufficient to combat all these problems that are arising, and that it is the solution to everything. Then we have those who think that harm reduction is not missing. In the artm we consider that there has to be a balance, because prevention is something important that cannot stop. What happened in Portugal, for example, when they liberalized the drug and failed to prevent and support treatment, [it was not good], and today Portugal is again in a slightly chaotic situation at consumption and trafficking. This means that prevention can never cease to exist. There should be quality treatments, with supervision of entities. The speed of access to treatment has to exist, and it can not be like in some countries where people have been waiting for a vacancy or permission to enter, as non -governmental organizations do not let the person enter until they receive the subsidy for each bed and patient. In these months a lot can happen. Damage reduction should be seen as a continuity for recovery, with rooms for consumption with medical and technical support, or syringe management programs. There is another problem, especially in Europe, which is heroin consumers, when they reach a more advanced age, already have many health problems and need sites to be, of a certain dignity. We have been wasting a lot of time with these ideological wars, and some of them exist for the sake of power, to influence the liberalization of drugs, and this is quite harmful. People's rights end when it is beginning to harm the rights of all other people, there must be a balance. As the report also says, there is a lack of medicines for some countries in Africa.

Art
To commemorate the 25th anniversary, the artm inaugurated on Friday the “Exhibition of the 25th Anniversary of Artm”, which is evident in the Hold on To Hope Gallery until the 23rd of this month. In the cultural space in the village of Nossa Senhora in Ká-Hó, which is part of the Occupational Therapy Program for the Arts users, you can see an art show done by these, with 45 works of ceramic, painting and wooden works. According to a press release of the association, the exhibition “celebrates resilience, creativity and healing”. “Throughout the last quarter of century, the artm has been a symbol of hope for individuals on its journey of recovery of dependence. This exhibition presents the extraordinary works of art created by our residents,” he is also read.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Iame Asia finals of Karting back in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/finais-da-iame-asia-de-karting-voltam-em-dezembro/</link><description>The Macao Karting International Award will receive again, from December 11 to 14, the Iame Asian finals. Like last year, the coloane karting race will give invitations to the very coveted world end of Iame in 2026.
Organized by the Institute of Sport, Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Otk Kart Asia and Iame Asia, the 2024 event brought back the international spirit to one of the largest competitions of the sport on the Asian continent. Coloane's karting received several races and different categories of Iame Series Asia, recovering the international prestige of an event that has been the scene of the Cik-Fia World Championship events.
Pilots from the interior of China, Singapore, Philippines, Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Japan, India, Sri Lanka, Australia, New Zealand, Sweden, Italy, France, Austria, the United States of America, Brazil, Hong Kong, and, of course, Macao, filled the track from the mashes in 2024 for four days of intense Competition, something that has not been seen for several years.
After the success of the previous edition, the formula is repeated this year. Singapore's organization again chooses Coloane's karting for its biggest event of the season, confirming the presence of the usual categories: Cadet, Junior, Senior and Master.
Thank you Macau!
The Iame (Italian American Motor Engineering) is one of the world's leading engine manufacturers for Karting. Founded in 1968 by Bruno Grana, the company is headquartered in Italy and is one of the references in Karting Internacional, having bet strongly in the Asian market in recent years. The presence in Macau is part of this strategy of growth and expansion.
The announcement of the return to the territory was made on social networks: “After an incredible debut in 2024, we are back with the Macao International International Award and the Iame Asia final for another epic confrontation! The city of emotions at high speed and legendary races will be the stage for the best pilots in Asia and the world!
Satisfied with the reception in 2024, Iame Asia organizers took the opportunity to leave a "huge thanks to AAMC and the Macao government for their continuous support and confidence to make it possible!"
In addition to the Macao test, the 2025 calendar of Iame Series Asia includes three events in Malaysia and three events in Thailand. However, for the first time, last weekend of March, the Iame Asia Cup will be held at the International Shanghai Circuit Karting.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 01:04:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to GIC | Local tests return to Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/regresso-ao-gic-provas-locais-voltam-a-zhaoqing/</link><description>The dates for the Macao of Tourism Car Championship (MTCs in the English acronym) were made known on the past Friday by the General Automóvel Association of Macau-China (AAMC) through a newsletter. The competition for local pilots and decides to find out the Macao Grand Prix in November will again return to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC).
After a year when the MTCS headed to the Zhuzhou International Circuit in Hunan province, AAMC listened to most of the territory pilots and chose to make these important races closer to the main interveners' house - the pilots. In recent years, the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing has been the preferred stage for the realization of these races, due to the proximity and the fact that it serves as an operational basis to most teams.
The first of the two events scheduled for the 2025 MTCS is scheduled from 18 to 20 April, while the second round is scheduled from 16 to 18 May. The AAMC newsletter says that "all riders must go through a selection process before they can participate in the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix - Macau Touring Car Challenge."
Registration, for the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), are open until March 29 and after the end of the registration period, "all applications will be subject to AAMC approval, which reserves the final right to accept or reject any registration."
The technical regulation was also published, as was officially confirmed the use of tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, which belongs to the Chinese conglomerate Sinochem, as had already happened on the last edition of the Macao Grand Prix.
Confirmation of the Great Bay
AAMC also confirmed the two findings for the GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4), which will be concomitant with the new Chinese Championship Sro GT Cup. The first race will be played from March 21 to 23, at the International Circuit of Shanghai, in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix. Internacional de Zhuhai. Também aqui a Pirelli será o fornecedor único de pneus.
These two tests will be determined for the big holiday party on the guide circuit, and it is defined that only 28 cars will be accepted on the starting grid in the mashed race. The 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix runs from November 13 to 16.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 04:17:32</pubDate></item><item><title>FIRST RALENT PROOF FOR THE MACAU GP took place in Shanghai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/primeira-prova-de-apuramento-para-o-gp-macau-decorreu-em-xangai/</link><description>The first determination test for the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix took place last weekend at the International Shanghai Circuit. Integrated in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix Program, Chen Weian and Lichao Han won the two races that will serve to select competitors entitled to participate this year in the GT - Great Bay Cup -
 
The GT Cup-Great Bay Race joined the newly created SRO GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macao Grand Prix. Thirty-three cars, six of them driven by Macau pilots, signed up for this debut-a record number of participants in a GT4 category in Asia category.
According to the organizer's statement, Sro Motorsports Group, “the total number of cars and the variety of builders have even exceeded the organizers' expectations for a championship that only began to be discussed in late November 2024. Since then, the Sro Asia team and their partner AAMC (Macau-China General Automobile Association) have worked tirelessly to make the series a reality before their debut.”
The event started in a troubled way. Due to a customs problem that affected several cars, more than a dozen competitors was unable to participate in the free training session on Friday. Fortunately, for this group of pilots, among which were included the drivers of the Kevin Leong Ian Veng, Kim Hou Lao and Un Hou IP, the cars arrived at the circuit in time for Saturday's qualification.
Animated races and decision in Zhuhai
With three dozen cars, from ten different brands, on track, all with very balanced tasks, was attended by two animated races in the imposing Shanghai track. In the first 12 -lap race, the two Lotus Emi GT4 Officials, by Daniel Lu and Luo Kailuo, who departed from the first line of the grill, were overcome on track by the Chen Weian Audi R8 LMS GT4. In the second match of the weekend, Lichao Han, behind the wheel of the same Toyota GR GT4 who beat the GT Cup - Great Bay Race in 2024, triumphed ahead of Chen Weian and Lotus de Liu Kai Shun.
Macao pilots had no easy life on a track where they had little or no experience. The most rewarded of all, Kelvin Leong, abandoned in the second round of the first race, while Miguel Law, in Audi R8 LMS GT4, was the best of the riders of MSAR, ending in 19th place. In Sunday's race, Leong took his BMW M4 GT4 F82 to 11th place.
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, at the end of the season, on the streets of Macau. The places will be attributed based on the classification after the second round of the championship, scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit, in a date yet to be announced.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:20:30</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Fia introduces costly measure to GT world cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/gp-macau-fia-introduz-medida-onerosa-para-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) announced on Tuesday afternoon a technical measure for the GT3 cars participating in the GT World Cup of the Macao Grand Prix, which will certainly have an impact on a race that is the event's headlord
 
To improve the Balance of Performance (BOP) - the method that balances the progress between all cars in the GT3 category - the FIA ​​decided to force the use of torque sensors, like what you already do in their championships, such as resistance worlds (WEC) and Rally Raid or Formula E. Torque sensors offer a very high precision in power measurement, allowing FIA ensures that the power of each car does not exceed the values ​​assigned by BOP and that external factors, such as atmospheric conditions, do not influence performance.
Although Sro Motorsports Group is co-organizer of this race, and having a bop recognized worldwide, in the last two years, the Macao Bop has been provided by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA ​​BOP was worth a series of criticisms, with teams and pilots-particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main impaired-to publicly express their natural discontent with the difference in progress.
These sensors are installed in car transmission veins and represent the most effective tool for measuring wheel power, being individually attributed by the BOP process to each car model that participates in the world's most prestigious “sprint” race for GT3 class machines. According to FIA, the decision to make torque sensors mandatory after consultations with the brands involved in the GT3 technical working group.
Custos vão disparar
For a race that has several private teams, this measure will be expensive, as these sensors exceed half a million patacas per car, and the teams need to have another same spare reserve system. This, given that most teams that participate in the MSar test do not use torque sensors in their cars in any competition, and cannot amortize the brutal investment.
"From the experience I had in Qatar, it is noted that there is a difference between several builders in the way it generates this technology. An extra support team is needed to monitor and maximize performance without exceeding the stipulated limits," he told HM Duarte Alves, the experienced track engineer in the territory who was with the official Ford team in the first WEC season in the Arab country.
"A good example is the difficulty and time needed for a builder who enters as a newcomer. An illustrative case is Mercedes-AMG, which is facing growth pains while developing its own systems," said Duarte Alves. “In more flat circuits, the management of these systems is simpler. In places like Macau, where 'torque peaks' will always be frequent, it will be a real challenge for the engineers of these systems!”
Confident
Immune to all this, the FIA ​​chooses a speech directed to builders, forgetting that most of the starting grid is made up of private competitors.
Lutz Leif Linden, chairman of the FIA ​​GT commission, said the institution that represents “made this decision in consultation with the builders”, adding that, to the international federation, “this means even more justice and improved control of BOP values, which is particularly important in such a prestigious and media event, in such a demanding circuit, where the long -speed straight lines contrast with tight curves and narrow ”.
Fabrice Van Ertvede, FIA speed technical manager, stressed the idea that "our goal, as a regulatory entity, is to ensure total equity for all participants." The implementation of torque sensors “is an extremely effective tool for achieving this goal, allowing us to align very different cars in parameters such as pure power, but also at full speed, a crucial factor in a circuit like the guide circuit.”
Despite the difficulties that Mercedes-AMG encountered with this system last month, Fabrice Van Ertvede praises that “the builders we hope to see in Macau this year are already familiar with this innovation, through their experience in the FIA's LMGT3 LMGT3 class, and the decision to adopt torque sensors resulted from the dialogue we kept with them.”
This is the second news that the FIA ​​introduces in the mashed race, having announced last month that the second qualification segment will have a super pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification laps. The eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will take place from November 13 to 16, as part of the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 17:11:10</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | FIA confirms GT World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/gp-macau-fia-confirma-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The World Council of the FIA ​​last Wednesday confirmed the expected, that the eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be held as part of the Macao's 72nd Grand Program, from November 13 to 16. However, there is a big news for this year's edition
 
The International Federation, which co-organizes this race in partnership with Sro Motorsports Group and the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), took the opportunity to announce a new qualification model for the race. In addition to the 30 -minute qualification session equal to the previous editions (Q1), a second qualification segment (Q2) was added, reserved for the top ten pilots of the first session.
The Q2 session will be held in Super Pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification turns, and each pilot is also allowed to use a new tire set at this session. This novelty will allow qualification to be decided without interference from third parties.
The remaining program of the Queen of GT will remain the same as the previous editions, with the free training session, the traditional 12-lap classification race on Saturday afternoon, followed by the 16-lap main race that will decide the world's Cup winner on Sunday.
Veterans compliments
These measures introduced by the FIA ​​were very well received by the most experienced GT riders. This is because traffic has always been a huge obstacle in obtaining a good qualification return on the guide circuit, something essential for those who aim to win this title.
"It's an excellent idea to introduce the Super Pole session in Macao," said German Maro Engel, the winner of the World Cup last edition by Mercedes-AMG. This will be one of the most spectacular and exciting sessions of the season and should also secure sports justice.
Raffaele Marciello, por duas ocasiões vencedor deste troféu, e um dos pilotos de fábrica da BMW, também reagiu positivamente, acrescentando: “Em Macau, era sempre complicado fazer uma volta limpa. Com este novo formato, não vais ouvir a desculpa do trânsito ou de uma bandeira vermelha. Ter apenas duas voltas será muito desafiante, mas agora o piloto mais rápido provavelmente ficará na pole.”
This is an opinion shared by Laurens Vanthoor, the World Cup winner in 2016, who said there will no longer be “apologies” in the qualification. Porsche's experienced Belgian pilot believes that “there will be an added pressure because you only have these two turns”, because in a difficult circuit like this, “if you make an error, there is nothing more to follow. In a normal qualification, you have more opportunities. Personally, a shootout is always something that I appreciate a lot. For pilots like this, it will be almost the highlight of the weekend.”
And the younger ones too
Chinese pilot Yifei Ye premiered at the Grand Prix last November at the World Cup. Ferrari's official pilot, which competes in the Endurance Fia World Championship (WEC), has left a good impression on the guide circuit, and he also welcomes the now introduced measurements.
“It's good to eliminate these red flag interventions and yellow flags, so that in the end, the one that really is the fastest to get pole position,” said Yifei Ye that she could return to the race this year. "In Macao, everyone is very close in terms of times, so it will be extremely difficult for pilots to try to get to 'Super Pole'. I think it will also be great for viewers."</description><pubDate>2025-02-28 01:03:51</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Célio Alves Dias will continue to run this season</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/gp-celio-alves-dias-vai-continuar-a-correr-esta-temporada/</link><description>Macaense pilot Célio Alves Dias was one of the long -term returns of the 2024 car.
 
The Macao Cup winner of Macau in 2021 was removed from motorsport at the time of 2023 for personal reasons, but last year made his debut in the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8). Despite the vast experience in tests of the specialty, having conducted several generations of tourism cars, Célio Alves Dias had never managed the new bobbinns that the Macao-China General Association (AAMC) introduced in its competition in 2023. Last time turned out to be of learning, with some difficulties in the tuning and behavior of the Japanese car.
Participation in races at the Zhuzhou International Circuit and the Macau Grand Prix made Célio Alves Dias realize that his Toyota GR86 was not at the strongest competition level. Based on the conclusions drawn from these experiences, he decided to start preparing for the new season.
"The car had to be all dismantled. My car was bought in Monday, and the chassis and the security arc, for me, were not well done," explained Fu Lei Racing Team pilot to HM. "This, I made the car too hard and very difficult to bow. I tried a well -mounted China car, and there is a difference. I had a long time in January, in China, with this car. Our cars, made in the same workshop, were very hard, which made it difficult to get around quickly."
If in the Macao Grand Prix, the house riders, excellent guide circuit, managed to equate the progress to their hong Kong opponents and the interior of China, in the initial races on the Zhuzhou track in Hunan province, it wasn't quite like that. "There are many differences between cars, but especially in chassis, because the engines, in terms of power and horses, are almost all at the same level. Our opponents have also experienced many pieces, many engines, even speed boxes, and chassis. Competition cars are always the same.
Silver Jubilee in November
Being a usual Portuguese name in the Macao Grand Prix in recent decades, Célio Alves Dias debuted at the Guide Circuit in 2000 and from then was a frequent presence and no faults in the race until 2023. This year, its objective is to account for its twenty-fifth participation in the biggest sports event of RAEM, but will have to align in the findings.
While awaiting the announcement of the 2025 calendar by AAMC, Célio Alves Dias details details to start his test program, because his Toyota, after being reviewed, "is ready to test" in the interior of China, something that will happen "very soon," says the pilot.
In the last edition of the Grand Prix, Célio Alves Dias qualified in 12th place for the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. However, his participation was short and unhappy: at the wheel of Toyota with dorsal No. 11, was forced to give up after being immobilized on the climb of San Francisco. The Macanese pilot was out of the race on the first lap, in an incident that caused the Safety Car.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:50:53</pubDate></item></channel></rss>