<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Asia | Thailand and Cambodia signal from the ordinary border</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/asia-tailandia-e-camboja-assinam-desminagem-da-fronteira-comum/</link><description>Thailand and Cambodia have agreed to remove the mines along the border that separates the two countries and to proceed to the “clear assignment” of territories whose sovereignty is disputed by Bangkok and Phnom Penh.
The decision results from an extraordinary meeting Friday of the Regional Border Committee (RBC), integrated by both countries, said yesterday the spokesman for the office of the Prime Minister of Thailand, Jirayu Huangsap.
Several incidents with terrestrial mines in the border zones were recently recorded, the latest from which it occurred on August 12, when a Thai military man was injured.
Two other incidents on July 16 and 23 preceded the armed confrontation that broke out on the 24th of this month between Thailand and Cambodia, which lasted for five days and left at least 44 killed, including civilians, at various points in the near 820 kilometers of border.
The agreement for the removal of mines and “clear attribution” of the border zones disputed is added a pact for the “joint disarticulation” of criminal networks dedicated to global cyberphraud, strongly implanted along the border of the two countries.
Precisely, these very powerful cyberphraude sites were pointed out by Thailand's first-rate minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra as one of the possible triggers of the armed confrontation in which Thailand and Cambodia were involved last month.
Paetongtarn stated that the conflict could be related to his government's plans to combat these centers, with a large presence in Cambodia and are determinant for his economy.
On July 28, Bangkok and Phnom Penh signed in Malaysia a ceasefire for armed confrontation, although both parties were later charged with violating the agreement. The border between these neighboring countries was cartographed by France in 1907, when Cambodia was a French colony.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:20:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Economic Association praises government</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/economia-associacao-economica-elogia-governo/</link><description>Following the announcement that the government would launch another round of the Grand Prix of Consumption to boost the business of commerce and restoration, the vice president of the Macao Economic Association, Chang Chak Io, praised the measure as an effective response in the short root to encourage consumption.
But the praise of the official to the executive in economic policies was not due to the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption. Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, Chang Chak Io highlighted long -term measures to improve the business environment, such as the launch of the stores plan with their own characteristics and professional consulting services to support small and medium -sized companies (SME) to transform their business, changing branch and exploring new markets. The leader also highlighted support for digitizing (SMEs), encouraging traders to resort to social networks and online marketing, attracting the consumption of new generations.
Regarding economic performance in the second half of this year, Chang Chak Io is optimistic not only due to the great consumption award from early September to the end of November, but due to the various events that are avilled, such as the International Fire Competition, the anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China and the national games.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:01:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Fai chi kei | New pedestrian passage inaugurated tomorrow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/fai-chi-kei-nova-passagem-pedonal-inaugurada-amanha/</link><description>It will be inaugurated tomorrow, from 10am, the new pedestrian crossing next to Avenida Marginal do Patane, in the vicinity of Doca do Lam Mau and Fai Chi Kei neighborhood. According to a note from the Directorate of Public Works Services and the Directorate of Service for Traffic Affairs, it is a work that ended early. "For the first phase of the work referring to the pedestrian crossing of Patane Marginal Avenue, which began in June last year, the provisional reception was performed in mid-August, verifying that, compared to the date of completion provided for in the contract, the work was completed with the anticipation of about a month."
After operating this upper pedestrian passage, the existing treadmills will be eliminated from the Trust Leisure Garden buildings, Van Sion Son Chun and Asia Industrial Building, and to strengthen the circulation of separate pawns from vehicles ”. The government also states that this pedestrian passage is equivalent with elevators, it is intended that "the pedestrian crossing of the Lam Mal dock becomes a continuous pedestrian system."
In the same note, the two services directions explain that “the construction work of a superior set of passage to pawns is being accelerated between Rua Norte do Patane and Rua do Commander João Belo”, and “the work of Foundations, by stakes, from the access from the superior passage to pedestrians, will start in September and its conclusion is scheduled for the second semester of 2026”.
In addition, it was “extended the sidewalk of the entrance door of the Santa Madalena School”, and a provisional cargo and discharge zone of passengers and goods on the stretch of Commander João Belo Street was created, next to the Wang Hoi building ”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:08:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Orchestra | New season opens with “brightness of the east”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/orquestra-chinesa-nova-temporada-abre-com-brilho-do-oriente/</link><description>The Chinese orchestra of Macau is about to begin a new show of shows and it is in this context that the show “Brightness of the East” takes place this Saturday, the 30th, marking the start of a new season of various sounds and international music. Highlight for the debut of the symphonic suite of traditional Chinese music that has the same name as the concert
 
The first show that gives the motto to a new season starred by the Chinese orchestra of Macau (OCM) and other guests for 2025/2026 is already known. It is “brightness of the East”, name of the symphonic suite of traditional Chinese music that will make its debut in this show that takes place Saturday, the 30th, in the large auditorium of the Cultural Center of Macau (CCM), from 20h.
This “symphonic suite” was composed of a whole by composers from China, Japan and South Korea, in a creation that, according to the Cultural Institute (IC), celebrates “Cultural Integration and Artistic Synergy of the three countries within the Cidade de Cultura East Asia 2025 ′”.
The show features Zhang Lie as a music director and the main conductor, followed, in addition to “brightness of the East”, a “selection of commissioned works and classic pieces of regional inspiration”.
It was up to OCM to invite “the renowned Chinese composer Zhao Lin, the young composer Luo Maishuo, the Japanese Master Kaoru Wada and the Korean composer of traditional Park Bum-Hoon music to collaborate in the creation of the Chinese Traditional Music Symphony Suite” that gives the show's name. The public will be able to see an interpretation by 12 musicians from the three countries, “who will play traditional musical instruments such as Chinese Pipa and Zhongruan, Shakuhachi and Japanese Shamisen, and Haegeum and Gayageum Koreans, revealing vividly the ethnic characteristics and musical essence of the three cultures, promising a unique and engaging action,” describes the IC.
One more order
In addition to the aforementioned sounds, the public can also have an OCM interpretation of the composition “Night of Macau”, a work commissioned to Singapore Cultural Medal, Eric Watson, as well as other prominent regional pieces, with a view to sharing with the public Macau's vibrant cultural identity through music. Tickets are already on sale for this show, varying prices between 120 and 380 patacas.
OBMEP has several musicians who dominate the art of some traditional Chinese musical instruments, such as ERHU, GAOHU or ZHONGHU.
The music director and main conductor, Zhang Lie, plays the same roles in the Chinese nanjing orchestra and the Chinese orchestra of Henan. It is a renowned Chinese conductor, vice president of the Professional Committee of Regency of China and national conductor, having been recognized as a “prominent artist” by the Ministry of Culture of China.
Previously, he was a permanent conductor of the Radio Symphonic Orchestra and the China and the Radio National Orchestra, as well as the Zhejiang National Orchestra, Chinese Orchestra of Guangdong and National Orchestra of Shaanxi Radio and Television.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:10:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | More than 22.6 million tourists until July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/turismo-mais-de-226-milhoes-de-turistas-ate-julho/</link><description>In the first seven months of the year, more than 22.6 million tourists visited Macau, almost 15 percent in annual terms, a brand that can represent a return to times before the pandemic. In July alone, more than 3.4 million tourists entered Macau, the large majority of Chinese tour
 
Between the beginning of this year and the end of July, they entered Macau 22,676,906 tourists, which means a 14.9 percent increase over the same period last year, driven largely by the rise of the tour market from the interior of China.
The bar exceeds half of the forecast of the director of tourism services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, out of a total of 38 and 39 million inputs at the end of 2025, when the traditional period of high time for national holidays of October is still missing. Following this pace of inputs, 2025 may close with numbers similar to the pre-parish period. It is recalled that in 2019, Macau was a destination chosen by about 39.4 million tourists.
According to data revealed on Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), of the approximately 22.7 million visitors, number of tour entries were almost 13.2 million, while individual tourists totaled 9.5 million, representing annual increases of 25.5 and 2.8 percent, respectively
Despite the increase of people visiting Macau, their stay in the territory has decreased by 0.1 days to 1.1 days, compared to the first seven months of 2024. DSEC explains the descent with the “increase in the proportion of tour of visitors”, since the average period of permanence of the tour (0.2 days) and that of tourists (2.3 days) have remained.
Good neighbors
Last month, more than 3.4 million visitors entered Macau. The July monthly record has been the highest since January, when the territory was visited by 3.65 million tourists. But of the 3,458,366 visitors who moved to the territory, more than half (1,980,732) were tour, which represents an increase of 24.1 percent compared to the same month of the previous year, refers to the DSEC note. The number of tourists (1,477,634) also increased 3.7 percent in annual terms.
Most visitors (2,563,212) came from the interior of China -another 17.4 percent -and 625,343 arrived from Hong Kong and 92,037 from Taiwan, a homologous rise of 6.2 and 21.4 percent respectively.
The number of visitors from nine cities of the Greater Bay River Delta was 1,225,642, plus 23 percent, compared to July 2024, thanks to the 56.8 percent increase of visitors from Zhuhai.
With regard to international visitors (177,774), it also states DSEC, the increase recorded was 2.8 percent. In this chapter, highlighting tourists from Thailand that rose 48.9 percent to a total of 12,352 compared to July last year.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:07:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado | SME debts rise to higher value since 2008</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/malparado-dividas-das-pme-sobem-para-valor-mais-alto-desde-2008/</link><description>Macao's badly and medium -sized corporate credit has risen at the first half of the year to 7.6 percent, the highest value since 2008, when the mandate faced the impact of the international financial crisis. However, in the same period more credits were approved, with fewer guarantees required
 
In the first six months of this year, the balance-related balance balance unpaid by small and medium enterprises (SME) reached a level of 5.6 billion patacas, Macao monetary authority (AMCM) revealed on Friday. The authority adds that the 7.6 percent increase in the evil credit in the first half of 2025 was due, "mainly, the fall in the balance of debt loans granted to SMEs."
The proportion of misconduct in the first half of 2025 registered a 1.4 percentage points, compared to the 6.2 percent of the first half of 2024, or an annual increase of 700 million bars of credit for paying.
AMCM advised the bank sector to stress negotiations with the SMEs to create “flexible reimbursement plans, under the principle of prudent risk management and in accordance with their own credit policies, continuing to provide credit support to customers with liquidity difficulties”.
The level of misconduct registered in the first half of this year reached the highest absolute value since 2028, when the MSAR felt the impact of the world financial crisis.
Credit death
Despite the historical levels of the debt ratio for paying, in the first half of 2025 there was a considerable increase in SME -approved credits, compared to the previous semester, plus 47.7 percent to a total of 4.9 billion patacas.
At the same time as approved credits increased, the requirements for approval went in the opposite direction. "The warranty ratio (which indicates the proportion of credit limit with promised bodily assets) was 62.2 percent, corresponding to a decrease of 14.5 percentage points (PP) when compared to the latest data," said AMCM.
Another contradictory trend revealed by AMCM data concerns the balance of SME loans, which, despite the increase in approved credits, descended in the first half of this year 4.7 percent to a total of 743.5 billion patacas, compared to the last semester of 2024.
When the analysis is made according to economic use, it was found that the loans granted to the sector in “Transport, Storage and Communications” increased 14.1 percent, while to sectors in “thick trade and retail” and “construction” registered decreases of 9.9 and 2.8 percent, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:05:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumption | New Round of the Grand Prix in September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/consumo-nova-ronda-do-grande-premio-em-setembro/</link><description>Next week it starts another major consumption award, which by the end of November will draw discounts on local commerce. The budget of this edition rose almost 65 percent and brings two news: the increase in the direct discount to the elderly, which passes to 500 patacas and the social care card
 
The government and the Macao Commercial Association presented on Friday another edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption, which begins on September 1 (Monday next week) and ends on November 30.
The new round of discounts will follow the same molds of the previous edition, but the budget will be higher, totaling 485 million patacas for consumption benefits awarded over the 13 weeks of the initiative, more 64.4 percent, or 190 million patacas, compared to the edition that took place between March and May this year.
However, the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption will have two news. The first is the increase in the value of the “immediate discount for the elderly” to 500 patacas, compared to the 300 patacas from the previous edition, which inaugurated direct support to the elderly to the second news, is the creation of a “social care card” with 500 patacas for immediate discount benefits to the holders of the disability assessment card.
Regarding the Macau Pass card for the elderly, users can use the anterior edition card, just to load 500 patacas at more than 100 service stations scattered by Macao.
If you need a new card, you can request it until November 18 at the Central Zone-South (Patane), North Zone (Tamagnini Barbosa), Northwest (Green Island), Taipa and Coloane (on Harmonia Avenue and Regisher Rua), and at the General Rehabilitation Evaluation Center.
The Social Care Card can be raised in institutions and centers coordinated by the Institute of Social Action. The government points out, however, that "it is not possible to enjoy the two types of benefit simultaneously."
The street spoke
Moreover, the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption will keep the same molds. During the week, mobile QR code mobile applications collaborating with the initiative have three draws to gain discount coupons when they spend more than 50 patacas on a transaction. For each mobile application, the user is entitled to three draws per week. Discount coupons will remain between 10 patacas and 200 patacas that have to be spent on purchases "equal to or greater than triple the nominal value of the coupon." That is, a 10 -headed coupon can only be spent on a purchase of at least 30 patacas.
In addition, every week there is a draw for those who used the mobile applications that will assign three 8,000 patacas awards.
During the presentation of the new edition of the consumption and trade support measure, the director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, said that the previous edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption “obtained remarkable successes” and “produced a positive effect on the stimulus of local consumption”.
The official also mentioned that the Chief Executive when he heard "opinions of society, numerous small and medium enterprises expressed the desire for the government" to continue "support for the community economy during the low season."
It is also important to note that the edition of the initiative is entitled “Strength of National Games - a major award for consumption in community zones”, a name given to “respond to the enthusiastic environment of national games and taking advantage of the event effect to revitalize consumer market confidence,” the government said.
Kaifong | Order Use of Cups during the Week
Deputies Leong Hong leaves and Ngan Iek Hang want the government to extend the period to spend the discount coupons of the great consumption prize on the days of the week.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, the vice-presidents of the Center for the Policy of Collective Wisdom subordinate to the General Union of Macao residents (Kaifong) stated that during the promotional activity there will be holidays, and that these days the government should allow the use of coupons. In addition, the deputies suggested to the Executive of Sam Hou Fai to enjoy the national games to launch a range of promotional products that sell in trade in community neighborhoods.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAG 2026 | CCPPC asks for more economic hotels</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/lag-2026-ccppc-pede-mais-hoteis-economicos/</link><description>On Thursday, Sam Hou Fai met with representatives of Macau to the National Popular Assembly (APN) and Political Advisory Conference of the Chinese people (CCPPC) regarding the elaboration of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for next year.
On the part of CCPPC representatives, the suggestion that the government “should promote the construction of more low-cost hotels to streamline visitors and the economy of the neighborhoods,” he stands out in a note from the chief executive's office.
It was also registered the request for the “increase in the use rate of the Hengqin Border Post” and “Improvement of the Financial System, the reinforcement of business and investment and the use of young people”, without forgetting “the policy of non -resident workers”.
Sam Hou Fai stressed the “Zape with Flavors” fair as an example of promoting the community economy and promises to “advance with innovative reforms” in the economic and cooperation area.
In turn, Macao to APN representatives defended “the creation of a team of experts (Think Tank), in order to provide scientific and strong foundations in political decision making”, and the development of the economy of neighborhoods ”and the“ organization of more activities that benefit consumption ”was also discussed. In this part, Sam Hou Fai pointed out that the return of “Esplanade Licenses has had positive effects”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:00:38</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2026 | Mobility in public function and economy in the agenda</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/lag-2026-mobilidade-na-funcao-publica-e-economia-na-agenda/</link><description>Already the usual round of the collection of opinion of associative leaders for the government lines for 2026. On Friday, the meeting of the chief executive took place with six associations linked to the civil service, and was discussed the improvement of workers' mobility and economic promotion measures
 
Sam Hou Fai, chief executive, is already collecting opinions with associations in order to elaborate the government program for next year, better known as lines of governing action (LAG). On Friday, the meeting took place with six representative associations of civil servants, which includes the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM).
According to an official note from the Chief Executive's Office, “some representatives suggested improving the internal mobility mechanism”, as well as “increasing the relevance between the formation and the functions of civil servants in order to support the modernization of the system and macao governance capacity”.
Policies formulation were also requested to ensure the “protection of the rights and legitimate interests of civil service workers, the continuous improvement of training for public administration personnel, optimization of the subsidy regime and increasing the effectiveness of inter-departmental work”, among other points.
Sam Hou Fai promised to “optimize personnel management and career regime”, thus creating a “internal access regime”, the promotion of “horizontal mobility and the creation of direct training plans” in the civil service. It should be noted that some leaders delivered a letter to Sam Hou Fai with concrete requests to the Public Administration area.
SME and Employment in Mira
Also on Friday, the maximum leader of the MSAR gathered, at the Government headquarters, with representatives of the industrial, commercial and financial sectors regarding the elaboration of LAG to 2026. In all, there were 16 associations represented at the meeting, having defended policies such as the “acceleration of urban renewal, the development of the seafarer tourism” or the incentives for the “transformation and updating of the convention and exhibition sector”.
The “optimization of the business environment of small and medium enterprises (SMEs)” was also requested, as well as “safeguarding the use of the local population” or the need to “introduce high quality qualified frames in the financial sector”.
In this meeting, suggestions were presented for the tourism area, in the sense of “increasing the integral competitiveness of Macau as an international tourism city”. This can go through the “concert industry development”, without forgetting “support for local cultural and creative intellectual property and improving the measures of the public transport network, attracting the flow of tourists to the development of the economy of neighborhoods”.
Sam Hou Fai, in turn, admitted the existence of a “complex and changeable internal and external environment”, having argued that companies must “innovate and strengthen, injecting new dynamics into the general development of the sectors”.
It was the promise of adjustment “of the development of the convention and exhibition sector”, and the adoption of “various measures to increase the flow of people in the neighborhoods and guide the market in its transformation to new consumption models”, thus supporting local SMEs.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 03:59:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Asia | Thailand and Cambodia signal from the ordinary border</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/asia-tailandia-e-camboja-assinam-desminagem-da-fronteira-comum/</link><description>Thailand and Cambodia have agreed to remove the mines along the border that separates the two countries and to proceed to the “clear assignment” of territories whose sovereignty is disputed by Bangkok and Phnom Penh.
The decision results from an extraordinary meeting Friday of the Regional Border Committee (RBC), integrated by both countries, said yesterday the spokesman for the office of the Prime Minister of Thailand, Jirayu Huangsap.
Several incidents with terrestrial mines in the border zones were recently recorded, the latest from which it occurred on August 12, when a Thai military man was injured.
Two other incidents, on July 16 and 23, preceded the armed confrontation that broke out on the 24th of this month between Thailand and Cambodia, which lasted for five days and left at least 44 killed, including civilians, at various points in the almost 820 kilometers of border.
The agreement for the removal of mines and “clear attribution” of the border zones disputed is added a pact for the “joint disarticulation” of criminal networks dedicated to global cyberphraud, strongly implanted along the border of the two countries.
Precisely, these very powerful cyberphraude sites were pointed out by Thailand's first-rate minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra as one of the possible triggers of the armed confrontation in which Thailand and Cambodia were involved last month.
Paetongtarn stated that the conflict could be related to his government's plans to combat these centers, with a large presence in Cambodia and are determinant for his economy.
On July 28, Bangkok and Phnom Penh signed in Malaysia a ceasefire for armed confrontation, although both parties were later charged with violating the agreement. The border between these neighboring countries was cartographed by France in 1907, when Cambodia was a French colony.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:20:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Economic Association praises government</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/economia-associacao-economica-elogia-governo/</link><description>Following the announcement that the government would launch another round of the Grand Prix of Consumption to boost the business of commerce and restoration, the vice president of the Macao Economic Association, Chang Chak Io, praised the measure as an effective response to the short-term to encourage consumption.
But the praise of the official to the executive in economic policies was not due to the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption. Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, Chang Chak Io highlighted long -term measures to improve the business environment, such as the launch of the stores plan with their own characteristics and professional consulting services to support small and medium -sized companies (SME) to transform their business, changing branch and exploring new markets. The leader also highlighted support for digitizing (SMEs), encouraging traders to resort to social networks and online marketing, attracting the consumption of new generations.
Regarding economic performance in the second half of this year, Chang Chak Io is optimistic not only due to the major consumption award from early September to the end of November, but due to the various events that are fired, such as the International Contest of Firewhere, the anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China and the national games.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:01:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Fai chi kei | New pedestrian passage inaugurated tomorrow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/fai-chi-kei-nova-passagem-pedonal-inaugurada-amanha/</link><description>It will be inaugurated tomorrow, from 10am, the new pedestrian crossing next to Avenida Marginal do Patane, in the vicinity of Doca do Lam Mau and Fai Chi Kei neighborhood. According to a note from the Directorate of Public Works Services and the Directorate of Service for Traffic Affairs, it is a work that ended early. "For the first phase of the work referring to the pedestrian crossing of Patane Marginal Avenue, which began in June last year, the provisional reception was performed in mid-August, verifying that, compared to the date of completion provided for in the contract, the work was completed with the anticipation of about a month."
After operating this upper pedestrian passage, the existing treadmills will be eliminated from the Trust Leisure Garden buildings, Van Sion Son Chun and Asia Industrial Building, and to strengthen the circulation of separate pawns from vehicles ”. The government also states that this pedestrian passage is equivalent with elevators, it is intended that "the pedestrian crossing of the Lam Mal dock becomes a continuous pedestrian system."
In the same note, the two services directions explain that “the construction work of a superior set of passage to pawns is being accelerated between Rua Norte do Patane and Rua do Commander João Belo”, and “the work of Foundations, by stakes, from the access from the superior passage to pedestrians, will start in September and its conclusion is scheduled for the second semester of 2026”.
In addition, it was “extended the sidewalk of the entrance door of the Santa Madalena School”, and a provisional cargo and discharge zone of passengers and goods on the stretch of Commander João Belo Street was created, next to the Wang Hoi building ”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:08:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Orchestra | New season opens with “brightness of the east”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/orquestra-chinesa-nova-temporada-abre-com-brilho-do-oriente/</link><description>The Chinese orchestra of Macau is about to begin a new show of shows and it is in this context that the show “Brightness of the East” takes place this Saturday, the 30th, marking the start of a new season of various sounds and international music. Highlight for the debut of the symphonic suite of traditional Chinese music that has the same name as the concert
 
The first show that gives the motto to a new season starred by the Chinese orchestra of Macau (OCM) and other guests for 2025/2026 is already known. It is “brightness of the East”, name of the symphonic suite of traditional Chinese music that will make its debut in this show that takes place Saturday, the 30th, in the large auditorium of the Cultural Center of Macau (CCM), from 20h.
This “symphonic suite” was composed of a whole by composers from China, Japan and South Korea, in a creation that, according to the Cultural Institute (IC), celebrates “Cultural Integration and Artistic Synergy of the three countries within the Cidade de Cultura East Asia 2025 ′”.
The show features Zhang Lie as a music director and the main conductor, followed, in addition to “brightness of the East”, a “selection of commissioned works and classic pieces of regional inspiration”.
It was up to OCM to invite “the renowned Chinese composer Zhao Lin, the young composer Luo Maishuo, the Japanese Master Kaoru Wada and the Korean composer of traditional Park Bum-Hoon music to collaborate in the creation of the Chinese Traditional Music Symphony Suite” that gives the show's name. The public will be able to see an interpretation by 12 musicians from the three countries, “who will play traditional musical instruments such as Chinese Pipa and Zhongruan, Shakuhachi and Japanese Shamisen, and Haegeum and Gayageum Koreans, revealing vividly the ethnic characteristics and musical essence of the three cultures, promising a unique and engaging action,” describes the IC.
One more order
In addition to the aforementioned sounds, the public can also have an OCM interpretation of the composition “Night of Macau”, a work commissioned to Singapore Cultural Medal, Eric Watson, as well as other prominent regional pieces, with a view to sharing with the public Macau's vibrant cultural identity through music. Tickets are already on sale for this show, varying prices between 120 and 380 patacas.
OBMEP has several musicians who dominate the art of some traditional Chinese musical instruments, such as ERHU, GAOHU or ZHONGHU.
The music director and main conductor, Zhang Lie, plays the same roles in the Chinese nanjing orchestra and the Chinese orchestra of Henan. It is a renowned Chinese conductor, vice president of the Professional Committee of Regency of China and national conductor, having been recognized as a “prominent artist” by the Ministry of Culture of China.
Previously, he was a permanent conductor of the Radio Symphonic Orchestra and the China and the Radio National Orchestra, as well as the Zhejiang National Orchestra, Chinese Orchestra of Guangdong and National Orchestra of Shaanxi Radio and Television.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:10:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy again hosts the second edition of the Short Film Festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/galaxy-volta-a-acolher-a-segunda-edicao-do-festival-de-curtas-metragens/</link><description>The second edition of the International Festival of Macao Entertainment Group, in a joint organization between this game operator and the Cultural Institute (IC), In addition to the screening of several films, there are also workshops, a conference on the film industry, masterclasses and awards to the best short films.
According to a note from the IC, the “aims to promote Macao's film production and television production, to foster industrial diversification and reinforce the exchange and cooperation between local and international film and television sectors”.
The festival includes five sections, namely “Macao Shorts”, “New Voices of the Horizon”, “Featured Director”, “East Asian Panorama” and “Special Sessions”, with views in places such as Cinemateca Passion and Galaxy theaters. The festival ends on September 20, with a ceremony at the Galaxy auditorium of the Galaxy International Convention Center.
There will be awards to the directors with the best works. For the “Shorts de Macao” section, the “Macao Unit Prize” and “Special Mention of the Jury” will be delivered; For the “New Voices of the Horizon” section will be awarded the “best short film” prizes, “special jury mention”, “best director” and “innovative narrative award”. The “Asian East Prize of Tomorrow” was also created in order to distinguish prominent works from East Asia.
Ten local works
In the “Shorts de Macao” section, which reveals to the public “the unique cultural landscape and the innovative perspective” of local filmmakers, ten cinematic works are presented, including Chao Koi Wang's “Chuff Chuff”; Ho Cheok Pan's “Cockroach Family”; Fox Box, by Ka Meng; Teng Kun Hou; Granny Pirate 3: Typhoon Again ”by Ho Wai Tong; Jarvis Xin's “hand hand”; Chan Chon Sin's “Nuptial Flight”; Purple, by Ho Kueng Un; Keo Lou's “The Performance” and Chan Si Ieong's “Waves Under The Sea”.
In "New Voices of the Horizon" are "more than 20 innovative productions of emerging directors from around the world, including the interior of China, East Asia, Southeast Asia, Europe and America." Thus, “the perspectives of the new generation of filmmakers” are presented, and provides a reflection on “the diversity and richness of film narratives around the world”.
In the “Featured Director” section, short films and feature films of renowned directors will be displayed, “highlighting the significant contributions to the film arts in their respective fields”.
This year, the featured director will be the Japanese Nobuhiro Yamashita, "known for his discreet style and narrative full of nuances." It is, according to the IC, a director who "captures the wit of youth and everyday life, while deepening in the psychology of the characters," performing "works that exploit Japanese society and culture with a mixture of realism and humor."
In turn, in the “Panorama do East Asia” section, ten “carefully selected and characteristic” films of the Asian continent are presented.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:17:40</pubDate></item><item><title>OCX | Putin and Modi Gifts at Tianjin summit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/ocx-putin-e-modi-presentes-na-cimeira-de-tianjin/</link><description>China said Saturday that the Russian President and the Indian Prime Minister will be present at the Summit of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization, rejecting any confrontation between blocks.
The summit, which will take place between August 31 and September 1, in Tianjin (Northeast), "will be the largest" since the foundation of the organization, told foreign journalists in Beijing, the assistant minister of Chinese foreign affairs, Liu Bin.
Liu said that “the spirit” of the organization is based on trust, mutual benefit and respect for diversity, maintaining all values ​​in the face of “outdated concepts”, such as block confrontation or the Cold War mindset.
"In today's world, the old hegemony mentalities and power policies still prevail. Some countries try to put their own interests above others, which seriously threatens peace and worldly stability," he said.
"The more complex and turbulent the international situation becomes, the more countries need to reinforce solidarity and cooperation to promote common development," he said.
Members of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization include, in addition to the Popular Republic of China, Russia, India, Pakistan, Iran, Belarus, Kazakhstan, Kyrguistan, Tajiquistan and Uzbekistan, representing approximately 40 percent of the world population.
Although member countries claim that the organization is not a military block and seeks to protect threats such as terrorism, some experts said they believed that the main objective is to be "counterpoint to the Atlantic Alliance."
However, there are internal tensions within the group, which includes opposing countries such as India and Pakistan.
In June, the meeting of the Ministers of Defense of Member Countries, held in the Chinese city of Qingdao, ended without a joint statement due to disagreements on security issues, particularly about terrorism. New Delhi, who refused to sign the final text, reported that some countries use terrorism as a political tool, in a veiled reference to Pakistan.
Other presences
In addition to Vladimir Putin and Narendra Modi, the Deputy Minister of Chinese Foreign Affairs confirmed the presence of the presidents of Belarus, Iran and Pakistan, among others. Liu said that leaders from various countries were invited, such as Mongolia, Azerbaijan, Armenia, Cambodia, Maldives, Nepal, Turkey, Iraq, Turquemenistan, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia and Vietnam.
Liu Bin also summoned the UN Secretary-General António Guterres, leaders of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean), the Independent States community and the Asian Bank for Infrastructure Investment.
Chinese President Xi Jinping will lead heads of state heads and the meeting with representatives of observing countries, in which issues linked to "regional security, multilateralism and sustainable development will be addressed."
The meeting will take place before the Military Parade of September 3, in Beijing, in celebration of the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II in the Pacific, to which Putin will watch.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:18:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Sales with annual break 11.4% in the first half</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/comercio-vendas-com-quebra-anual-114-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>In the first half of this year, the average sales volume rate of retail trade establishments registered a homologous drop of 11.4 percent, the Directing of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said on Friday. In this chapter, the jewelery and watchmaker sector recorded a descent of 26.5 percent sales volume, while pharmacies and car trade increased sales 4.9 and 3 percent, respectively.
DSEC also indicates that in the first half of this year the retail trade volume was set at 33.55 billion patacas, 9 percent less than the last semester of 2024.
In quarterly terms, the retail trade volume “has been moved at 15.97 billion patacas, decreasing 1.4 percent, in annual terms, this decrease was significantly tightened compared to the first quarter of this year (-15 percent)”.
DSEC points out that the volume of leather and cosmetic and hygiene products dropped 15.8 and 14.3 percent, but respectively, the pharmacies rose 4.5 percent, and the sale of cars grew by 3.6 percent.
After eliminating the factors that influence prices, the sales volume index of retail trade establishments registered in the reference quarter of a homologous decrease of 2.4 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:06:11</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xu Zhaohua (1662-1722), who used expressive literary pseudonyms such as Lanchi, or Yibi, "crazy about orchids" and "Jade as a woman", was one of the recognized poets who, at the beginning of the Qing Dynasty, reflected on the unstable place of women who, if well confined to Gineceu, already had a literary culture that allowed them in form. of poems, paintings or literary rehearsals of the most subtle shades of their accurate sensitivity.
The way these women in the Ming-Qing dynastic transition, referred later as Guixiiu, "cultured" or cainu, "women of talent", acquired this knowledge when they rarely absent from their homes, varied. But in his case, as from others equally bold, this learning depended on an older literate man with whom he had no family relationship.
Mao Qiling (1623-1716), this preceptor, was one of the most extraordinary figures among men of letters that ensured the continuity of literary culture. An unlikely destination that came from a refusal.
Born in Xiaoshan (Zhejiang) after the fall of the Ming feeling, like other literati and arts cultivators, uncomfortable by the new powers that seemed to ignore the millennial tradition, wandered without destination through the regions of Baixo Changjiang. But after all, what was afraid did not happen and he took advantage of an opening decreed by Emperor Kangxi to perform in 1679, already late in relation to the usual, imperial examination and his vocation used for example in the writing of Mingshi, the "Ming History".
It would participate in other imperial projects, but from1687 it goes to Hangzhou where the ambicked life removed from men of letters, far from the red dust of cities. And in one of the arts he knew, that of painting, this place was a disposition of the Spirit.
Mao Qiling alludes in a lonely fisherman on a vertical roller on a vessel, or Songling Yuyin, 'hidden fisherman' pine pines' (paper ink, 63.5 x 35.6 cm, in the metmuseum) to the modest figure, without worldly ambitions, of the lonely man who on a bon -free fishing vessel in an endless river.
Xihe, Rio do Oeste, was one of his literary names and what appears in the edition of his complete works. And if in the vast empire the rivers flow in the East, in the west are the springs, go there was to return to the origins.
As a philologist, Mao Qiling studied the origin of ancient words and concepts, discussing issues that in their time put themselves as to the interpretation of the classics, or the excess of antagonism that the neo-conficians placed between human desire and the principle of heavenly goodness.
This clairvoyance allowed him to appreciate the poetry of authors such as Xu Zhaohua who praised the longing, the resistance to adversity, and the jade that takes the temperature of those who play it.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Sara F. Costa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/sara-f-costa/</link><description>Nursed to observing European powers to enslave and colonize various spaces around the globe, Qing Dynasty China was not interested in negotiations with Western countries. In addition to wanting to maintain distance in diplomatic and relational terms, I felt no need to import any western manufacturing, that is, it did not depend on any imports.
Several European countries, however, did trade with China as they were interested in Chinese products, especially in tea, porcelain and silk. These products were particularly appreciated by the British.
The Chinese attitude was not well regarded by Britain that was displayed before Europe as a dominant hegemonic power. Since Britain imported large amounts of tea, silk and porcelain China, via its trade balance very unbalanced with the Chinese.
This happened until they realize a highly lucrative product planted in their India colony that could be interested in the Chinese: opium. In addition to being lucrative, this product also had the power to weaken this country-continent country that appeared so interesting as a market for the European powers. With the introduction and rapid propagation of opium into Chinese society, the Beijing government decided to ban the marketing of the narcotic that was being devastating and to constitute one of the most serious public health problems in the country's history. This decision is seen by the British government as an affront to its commercial freedoms. After the introduction, marketing and spread of opium in China in 1839 Britain declares the First Opium War.
Its official narrative falls on the importance of opening China's doors to international trade, for the sake of order, stability and peace. This essay aims to refute the thesis of peace by trade referring to this historical context. When objectively analyzed the international economic situation of the time, Britain's commercial interest in China was more than evident. It was a large market and, if weakened and dominated, another colony with a lot of labor to explore. That is, behind a narrative that wanted only a modern, worldwide order and which, above all, led to peace, there was a marked material interest in the Chinese market that was not harmful as it was for the British to date. Beyond material interest, the sovereign interest was also present, it was not represented in the one that would become the British colony of Hong Kong.
The mandate of the sky and the singing system
Beijing's isolation was an economic model parallel to the western model and did not fit the general belief in Europe of the 19th century. XIX that integration into an international order of law and trade was the only possibility of a sovereign state being recognized as civilized and, consequently, as peaceful - as it would become transparent, predictable and, according to Palmerston, modern (Palmerston, 1840).
However, the Qing Empire did not share this belief. By this time the mandate of heaven [i] (天命, in Pinyin: Tianming) [II] was still the model of governance followed. According to this model, diplomacy and international trade were forms of recognition of Chinese prominence. The mandate did not necessarily imply a war relationship with neighboring peoples. Like the United States, China thought he had a special role in the universal order and they were all free from enjoying the privileges that conveyed contact with its culture. However, in an antithesis to the United States, he never expressed a desire to disseminate their values ​​around the world: it was limited to achieving foreign states to consider the tax states of China.
International trade between the Chinese and foreigners formed the first sino-widening place of the modern era. Although Porto Xiamen in Fujian, it was the main gateway with Southeast Asia and the Chinese coast, after 1759 Guangzhou had become an official door for meetings with Europeans.
The “Canton System” as it became known in the West was organized from typically Chinese lines: the government commissioned one of the Chinese families of merchants to act as controllers of trade with the abroad. These merchants formed an association known as Cohong, who responded to the command of a Guandong trade specialist, usually a Manchu sent from the Imperial Court in Beijing, known by foreigners as HOPPO. Cohong and Hoppo had the task of taxing foreigners and especially tea and silk exports.
Until 1834, when the British Indian Company lost real support to monopolize trade with China, the company had adapted to this particular singing system. During the seasons of exchanges, the Board of Directors of the British Company of India in London lived in the British Factory (Center for Commerce and Residence), in Rio, outside the Great Capital of Guangzhou, from October to March. At the time without exchanges from April to September, they retreated to the only Chinese space concessioned to Europeans, the Portuguese city of Macau.
For the Chinese, the accumulation of European interest on the Southeast coast required an efficient method to deal with “Western Sea barbarians” as they were officially designated.
Nursed to observing European powers to enslave and colonize various spaces around the globe, the totalitarian attitude of Qing was not interested in major negotiations with “barbaric merchants”. It was not authorized to grant a space of foreign representation in the capital - embassies [III] - and were rarely admitted to the Court in Beijing representatives. When this happened, it was expected to be familiar with the prostration ritual before the emperor [IV].
This prostration ritual is an important detail in the British mission led by George Macartney in 1793 to Beijing to meet Emperor Qianglong. Its purpose was to ask the Qing Empire to respect those who were at the time the minimum international rights of which Europe enjoyed almost all the rest of the world: free trade, permanent embassies and equality of sovereignty. Until then, Europeans had no choice but to reduce the role of supplicants in the Chinese tax order-trade with barbarians was considered no more than a tribute to the Great Empire of the environment. The Macartney Mission was a failure at various levels, as appealing and trying to demonstrate the technical and scientific superiority of the West, could not carry out any of the negotiations that had been ordered to it. This Chinese attitude was particularly offensive to Britain, but China's GDP was even about seven times that of Britain and hence the Emperor considered that it was London who needed help and not the other way around (Maddison, 2006).
The rising western powers would not tolerate a diplomatic mechanism for much longer that referred to them as “barbarians” who paid tribute or a tight seasonal trade regulated in a single port. After the Macartney mission the Britain of the Western civilizational top had been particularly offended.
A single world order
- From trade to peace
With the trade balance unbalanced in the face of Chinese disinterest in British manufactures, the insistence on import without opium restrictions to China was the solution found by them to finally conquer the Chinese market. Opium was introduced illicitly and with the clear purpose of addicting the Chinese population in the only product that could make profits to Britain.
When opium began to circulate in the country, Beijing made an attempt to regulate and sell the product. However, the progressive destruction of populations and public health problems that quickly became visible all over the country led the court to ban their marketing. For a Britain that was beginning to ban the globalization of slavery (of which it had been paradoxically path) in order to affirm its moral superiority before the rest of Europe, the commercialization of opium caused Western a certain sense of embarrassment. But it was not only westernly that opium marketing was seen as an embarrassment. The official agent for opium eradication in China, Lin Zu, even asked Queen Vitória to be in charge of suppressing opium trade not only in China but in the Indian territories of Great Britain from where the deep degradation reports caused by the drug use were already heard all over the world (TSE-HSU, 1839). Lin makes an ultimatum to Britain that threatened to end the export of Chinese products if the British did not end the opium marketing. Certainly the great Chinese empire could not suffer from greater retaliation, the Chinese court underestimated foreign military capabilities already much more developed than the Chinese - which never had to wage great battles after the unification of the empire due to more exquisite ways to call war, such as those that can be studied in the classic art of Sun Tzu war. Centuries of supremacy had distorted the meaning of the reality of the heavenly court. The claim of superiority only accentuated the inevitable humiliation (KISSINGER, 2011).
British commissioner Palmerston writes back to the Chinese court and clearly defends his point of view: Chinese legal systems had, according to Western legal principles, labeled a long time ago, so the next step of the British government was to immediately send an armed to block the main Chinese ports, to take 'all the Chinese ships' and take 'convenient part of the territory' Chinese »Until London gets satisfaction. (PALMSSTON, 1840). [V] The results of the interaction between the overwhelming Western force and the typical psychological management of China resulted in two treaties: the Nanjing Treaty and the Bogue Treaty. China had to pay Britain six million dollars of compensation, to give up Hong Kong and open five coastal ports in which Western residence and trade would be allowed (Guangzhou, Ningbo, Shanghai, Xiamen and Fuzhou).
The “Canton System” had come to an end. The British also obtained the right to make direct trade that did not pass by Beijing and the power to exercise jurisdiction over their national residents in the Chinese ports of the treaty. This meant that foreign opium traders would be subject to the laws of their own countries and not China. This principle of "extraterritoriality" eventually represented the decline of imperial power. Following the concessions allowed to Britain, many other Western powers wanted to come to complain about their piece. The mandate of heaven had ended and had been replaced by the western concept of sovereignty.
The Peace Thesis for Trade
The thesis of peace for commerce argues that it reduces the likelihood of armed conflicts between states in a logic of interdependence in which commercial liberalism plays a central role in conducting peace, thus surpassing the conflict logic defended by realistic theorists. The Organization of International Trade (WTO) presents several arguments that underlie the fact that trade between sovereign states leads to peace, namely arguing that traders have less tendency to generate conflicts with their clients (World Trade Organization, 2003: 2); The second argument is that disputes are constructively dealt with in the procedures of institutions and organizations. Liberal peace supporters argue that interdependence reduces conflict because conflict reduces trade. Economic interdependence promotes peace because the conflict is inconsistent with economic ties that promote mutual benefit (Polachek &amp; Xiang, 2008).
The thesis was, however, over time changing the empirical basis. At first time when the essential operating concept is called “comparative advantages”. It is the time of international economic life that has been conceptualized in traditional international trade theories. Each state explores the competitive advantages it has in the international system. Where before we had political units, we now have economic units. From the 80s onwards it becomes a mesh of bilateral relations, thus globalization the loss of this national reference.
The Anglo-Chinese war was presented by the British government as a necessary process in which the ends justified the means. Despite the universally recognized ethical and moral failure of the illegal dissemination of a narcotic view to the forced opening of a state to international trade legislation, the united kingdom's official apology has never been formalized, not even when the recovery of Hong Kong sovereignty by the popular republic of China in 1997. To free trade, invasions and attempts at colonization by the Western powers continued to foster war in China in a logic of expansion of power and sovereignty. 完
Grades
[I] The mandate of heaven has its origins in Confucian thinking developed by Mencius (372 - 289 BC) and has been followed since then as a way to justify the legitimacy of the emperors.
[II] Pinym and Wade-Giles are the two Chinese language romanization systems used in this work.
[III] Exception to Russia, as their advances in the east represented an imminent threat to China. In 1715 the Qing granted the possibility of installing a Russian Orthodox Mission in Beijing.
[IV] Known as a precautionary, the act of prostration before the emperor was a form of greeting or veneration to the emperor who implied touching his forehead three times.
[V] «Lord Palmerston to the Minister of the Emperor of China» (London, February 20, 1840)</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xu Zhaohua (1662-1722), who used expressive literary pseudonyms such as Lanchi, or Yibi, "crazy about orchids" and "Jade as a woman", was one of the recognized poets who, at the beginning of the Qing Dynasty, reflected on the unstable place of women who, if well confined to Gineceu, already had a literary culture that allowed them in form. of poems, paintings or literary rehearsals of the most subtle shades of their accurate sensitivity.
The way these women in the Ming-Qing dynastic transition, referred later as Guixiiu, "cultured" or cainu, "women of talent", acquired this knowledge when they rarely absent from their homes, varied. But in his case, as from others equally bold, this learning depended on an older literate man with whom he had no family relationship.
Mao Qiling (1623-1716), this preceptor, was one of the most extraordinary figures among men of letters that ensured the continuity of literary culture. An unlikely destination that came from a refusal.
Born in Xiaoshan (Zhejiang) after the fall of the Ming feeling, like other literati and arts cultivators, uncomfortable by the new powers that seemed to ignore the millennial tradition, wandered without destination through the regions of Baixo Changjiang. But after all, what was afraid did not happen and he took advantage of an opening decreed by Emperor Kangxi to perform in 1679, already late in relation to the usual, imperial examination and his vocation used for example in the writing of Mingshi, the "Ming History".
It would participate in other imperial projects, but from1687 it goes to Hangzhou where the ambicked life removed from men of letters, far from the red dust of cities. And in one of the arts he knew, that of painting, this place was a disposition of the Spirit.
Mao Qiling alludes in a lonely fisherman on a vertical roller on a vessel, or Songling Yuyin, 'hidden fisherman' pine pines' (paper ink, 63.5 x 35.6 cm, in the metmuseum) to the modest figure, without worldly ambitions, of the lonely man who on a bon -free fishing vessel in an endless river.
Xihe, Rio do Oeste, was one of his literary names and what appears in the edition of his complete works. And if in the vast empire the rivers flow in the East, in the west are the springs, go there was to return to the origins.
As a philologist, Mao Qiling studied the origin of old words and concepts, discussing issues that in their time put themselves as to the interpretation of the classics, or the excess of antagonism that the neo-conficians placed between human desire and the principle of heavenly goodness.
This clairvoyance allowed him to appreciate the poetry of authors such as Xu Zhaohua who praised the longing, the resistance to adversity, and the jade that takes the temperature of those who play it.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Thailand and Cambodia have agreed to remove the mines along the border that separates the two countries and to proceed to the “clear assignment” of territories whose sovereignty is disputed by Bangkok and Phnom Penh.
The decision results from an extraordinary meeting Friday of the Regional Border Committee (RBC), integrated by both countries, said yesterday the spokesman for the office of the Prime Minister of Thailand, Jirayu Huangsap.
Several incidents with terrestrial mines in the border zones were recently recorded, the latest from which it occurred on August 12, when a Thai military man was injured.
Two other incidents, on July 16 and 23, preceded the armed confrontation that broke out on the 24th of this month between Thailand and Cambodia, which lasted for five days and left at least 44 killed, including civilians, at various points in the almost 820 kilometers of border.
The agreement for the removal of mines and “clear attribution” of the border zones disputed is added a pact for the “joint disarticulation” of criminal networks dedicated to global cyberphraud, strongly implanted along the border of the two countries.
Precisely, these very powerful cyberphraude sites were pointed out by Thailand's first-rate minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra as one of the possible triggers of the armed confrontation in which Thailand and Cambodia were involved last month.
Paetongtarn stated that the conflict could be related to his government's plans to combat these centers, with a large presence in Cambodia and are determinant for his economy.
On July 28, Bangkok and Phnom Penh signed in Malaysia a ceasefire for armed confrontation, although both parties were later charged with violating the agreement. The border between these neighboring countries was cartographed by France in 1907, when Cambodia was a French colony.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Thailand and Cambodia have agreed to remove the mines along the border that separates the two countries and to proceed to the “clear assignment” of territories whose sovereignty is disputed by Bangkok and Phnom Penh.
The decision results from an extraordinary meeting Friday of the Regional Border Committee (RBC), integrated by both countries, said yesterday the spokesman for the office of the Prime Minister of Thailand, Jirayu Huangsap.
Several incidents with terrestrial mines in the border zones were recently recorded, the latest from which it occurred on August 12, when a Thai military man was injured.
Two other incidents on July 16 and 23 preceded the armed confrontation that broke out on the 24th of this month between Thailand and Cambodia, which lasted for five days and left at least 44 killed, including civilians, at various points in the near 820 kilometers of border.
The agreement for the removal of mines and “clear attribution” of the border zones disputed is added a pact for the “joint disarticulation” of criminal networks dedicated to global cyberphraud, strongly implanted along the border of the two countries.
Precisely, these very powerful cyberphraude sites were pointed out by Thailand's first-rate minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra as one of the possible triggers of the armed confrontation in which Thailand and Cambodia were involved last month.
Paetongtarn stated that the conflict could be related to his government's plans to combat these centers, with a large presence in Cambodia and are determinant for his economy.
On July 28, Bangkok and Phnom Penh signed in Malaysia a ceasefire for armed confrontation, although both parties were later charged with violating the agreement. The border between these neighboring countries was cartographed by France in 1907, when Cambodia was a French colony.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Rain | HK alerts and more than 80,000 residents of Beijing removed from home</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/chuva-alertas-em-hk-e-mais-de-80-mil-residentes-de-pequim-retirados-de-casa/</link><description>China and Hong Kong have faced periods of heavy rainfall in recent days that have forced extra care and residents' travel. In the Chinese capital 82,000 people had to leave their homes, while in Hong Kong streets and a hospital suffered floods and some subway seasons were closed
 
Strong rains continue not to give respite, not only in Macau (see page 7), but in Hong Kong and in the interior of the country. In the case of China, Beijing authorities moved more than 82,000 people from home due to torrential rain, a week after deadly floods that led those responsible for recognizing failures in the response, the official news agency Xinhua said yesterday.
Thus, tens of thousands of residents were removed from the most affected areas by rain until 9 pm on Monday, local time, according to the Municipal Flood Response Center. The center warned of the high risk of floods in the districts of Miyun (northwest), Fangshan (southwest), lied (west) and Huairou (north).
The Chinese capital kept in force the red alert-the highest-until yesterday morning, before predictions of heavy rain between Monday and the morning of Tuesday.
Last week, these same rural districts north of Beijing were the most affected by the weather that caused 44 dead and nine missing, according to official data. Most of the deadly victims were registered in a home of elderly in Miyun.
New measures in agriculture
A gravidade da catástrofe levou as autoridades municipais a reconhecerem “lacunas” na preparação dos serviços de emergência. Desastres naturais são frequentes na China durante o Verão, com algumas regiões sujeitas a chuvas torrenciais e outras a secas severas.
However, the Chinese authorities have reinforced the device to respond to the adverse effects of intense rainfall and heat waves on agricultural crops in various regions of the country, at a crucial time for autumn harvesting.
Since the beginning of the rainy season, east and northern China areas have recorded episodes of extreme precipitation, while provinces such as Henan (Center) and Anhui (East) face prolonged periods of drought and high temperatures.
This combination of meteorological phenomena represents a challenge for farmers, especially when about two months left to harvest the main autumn cereals, the official news agency Xinhua yesterday pointed out.
In the province of Shaanxi (Center), where precipitation recently exceeded 100 millimeters in less than 24 hours, local authorities adopted preventive measures such as channel cleaning and reinforcement of dikes, which allowed to protect most of the cultivated lands.
However, Henan agricultural cooperatives affected by drought opted for gout watering systems and localized application of fertilizers to conserve moisture and minimize losses.
Authorities have given priority to the rehabilitation of water infrastructure and the dissemination of efficient water management techniques in the absence of precipitation in some areas. The autumn campaign represents a fundamental component of China's annual cereal production.
In a statement issued yesterday, the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs warned that weather conditions in the coming weeks will be determining and appealed to "all efforts to protect the harvest and give strong support to the country's food security."
Chinese President Xi Jinping said in 2023 that, although “1,400 million Chinese eat well” currently, “the food issue should not be careless”, stressing that the supply of food “is not an insignificant issue”.
China has less than nine percent of the planet's aurable land, although it represents about 18 percent of the world's population. In the last summers, weather disasters have caused significant damage in the country: the 2023 scirred months were marked by flooding in Beijing, which caused more than 30 dead, while by 2022 several extreme and dried heat waves hit the center and east of China.
Hong Kong on Alert
With regard to the panorama of heavy rains in neighboring territory, they have not given respite either. According to public broadcaster RTHK, some hong Kong stations were closed yesterday due to the risk of flooding, given that the Hong Kong Observatory kept the black signal of storm [Black Rainestorm Warning Signal] until around 17 hours.
Winds of about 110 kilometers per hour were recorded in some areas of the territory, and thunderstorms were also registered. The rthk channel also reveals that more than 10,800 lightnings were counted in the territory between midnight and 10 am yesterday, half of them occurred on Lantau Island.
Until 11 am yesterday, the authorities responsible for the drainage systems recorded 21 episodes of flooding, and 180 emergency responses were made in 240 different locations.
Highlight for the occurrence of an episode at Queen Mary Hospital this Tuesday, namely “on some roads” hospital access in Pok Fu Lam, and patients were displaced by firefighters to Ruttonjee Hospital in the Wanchai area. In some zones of the hospital the water reached the knees, and sand bags were placed to stop the flow of the rains. At about 11 am yesterday this scenario was resolved, with the normal one returning to the Queen Mary Hospital near noon.
The rains also led to the large increase in water level in the Lower Shing Mun reservoir in the Shaan area, which led to the notification of nearby housing complexes, such as Mei Lam Estate, May Shing Court, Mei Chung Court and Granville Garden.
Despite the heavy rains, some people went to work normally doing alternative routes. This was the case of Mak, a woman who, to the RTHK channel, said she had to make a deviation to get to the office. “I couldn't go straight to there and had to make a longer route. The metro [mtr] made some warnings [about the storm and closures], but I would like them to do them in the carriages as well, because I only realized that access was closed when I got to the exit,” he described.
The sun
Information provided by the Hong Kong Observatory speaks of the passage of an active "southwest monsoon and high altitude disturbances that are bringing heavy rainfall and violent thunderstorms to the southern coast of China and the northern part of the southern China Sea."
Yesterday the highest daily precipitation record was broken to August since 1884, upon registered, until 14h, 355.7 millimeters of precipitation at the Observatory's headquarters.
For today time should stay unstable in Hong Kong, with “heavy rains at the beginning” of the day. However, these "should gradually decrease" tomorrow, expected "a lot of heat with sunny periods in the next two days."
Also the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) leave a heavy rain alert to this day with “frequent, sometimes intense, thunderstorm”. The sun is expected to start appearing at the MSAR from tomorrow, still with some clouds, extending this weather scenario until next Monday. Temperatures should reach 33 degrees.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:29:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Iam | Cats captured due to complaints from the University of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/05/iam-gatos-capturados-devido-a-queixas-da-universidade-de-macau/</link><description>The collection of cats from the land of the University of Macao resulted from “university complaints about the large amount of cats in its campus,” the institute for municipal affairs told HM. The public body removes, for now, the scenario of slaughtering animals, feared by the students
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) clarifies that the collection of 15 cats between July 22 and 25 of the University of Macao campus (one) emerged in response to complaints from the institution of higher education in relation to hygiene problems in the campus generated by the presence of animals.
"AMI has constantly receiving complaints from one about the large amount of cats on its campus and food waste that is not removed in time and affecting environmental hygiene," was referred to in the response sent to HM.
UM UM Campus Cats led to a wave of students' indignation, who say Temer the slaughter of animals after the period of complaint and adoption. AMI will move away, this scenario.
"Regarding cats captured, if they are not claimed by the owner after the period of complaint, AMI will implement the policy of" open capture, sterilization and adoption "(TNA), prioritizing finding appropriate adopters for cats. It should be noted that AMI does not set a deadline for retention of the adopted animals."
In the same answer it is said that during the waiting period for host families, AMI “will continue to provide clinical care and daily care to animals, never existing their slaughtering situation due to the term of retention period”.
In this sense, it is explained that AMI veterinarians “are performing a series of medical care that include body examination, vaccine administration and microchips.” In addition, “cats can only be available for adoption after being sterilized,” Iam said.
“Lack of sensitivity”
The warnings for the adoption of these animals continue on social networks, and in a note sent to HM and signed by “a member of the UMERS - UMM groups”, is questioned the “worrying situation” that occurred during the summer vacation and therefore the absence of most students.

“These cats, considered an integral part of the university community, survived the sign of signal 10, but unfortunately they could not escape these AMI capture operations in recent days. For many students and teachers, these cats were like 'veterans' of campus, following them during significant moments of academic life and providing comfort and joy in the university environment.”
The note explains that "UMERS" members cannot adopt cats "due to various circumstances," such as family allergies, possession of other animals, or "additional restrictions" for students in the interior of China.
The alerts on social networks aim to “sensitize the public for this situation and encourage people with adequate conditions to adopt these cats in the municipal Kennel of Macau.
On the Red Note platform there is even the group “A CatStories”, where the stories of cats captured by AMI are shared, and only one publication generated 460 tastes and 160 comments. A group was also created on Facebook, “Macao Cats II”, and there is also publications on Threads, with a total of 500 tastes and 500 shares, including the ten thousand views.
One of the profiles of the "a catstories" concerns a "slight little cat," described as "a" unnamed "file, just created on the computer: still blank, slowly exploring the world and trying to type loose fragments to write" his own story.
“Hurryned to a corner, I watch the people who pass, evaluating who can become an important character of my plot. So far, few people have been written in my story, and I have also left few brands in someone's life. Before leaving the campus maybe this" unnamed "file is only 5kb, registering some timid explorations and a soft desire for human warmth," reads the adoption.
The HM questioned one on this subject, given that the animals were being cherished by the students, but until the closing of the edition did not receive an answer. "UMERS" members also question how one can one, "an institution that seeks academic excellence and better classifications in the world rankings, demonstrate such a lack of sensitivity, allowing the capture of these animals without any alternative solution."
Aborted association
In the same grade it is said that students considered creating an association to “organize the sterilization of campus cats, but the university did not approve the creation of such a student association”.
UMERS members enhance “contrast with renowned universities in the interior of China, such as the University of Beijing, where there is a student association dedicated to the care of university campus cats, and at the University of Zhejiang, where UM UM Rector Song Yonghua has previously worked an association to protect university campus animals since 2005”.
Regarding animal collection and treatment actions, AMI says that "TNA policies correspond to the guiding principles of the World Animal Health Organization (WOAH), which contribute to reducing the possibility of stray animals being exposed to disease and facing unfavorable environmental factors."
Such policies also contribute to the reduction of the number of animals "and their excessive long -term reproduction." It is also noted that "TNA policies still take into account the state of survival and welfare of animals, in order to find adopting families for animals with conditions, dedicating themselves to helping them to obtain permanent and stable proper care."
The AMI also says it has "constantly optimized the municipal kennels", and in recent years, "complementary facilities and equipment have been perfected." In addition, there is also cooperation “with animal protection associations”, and joint projects in schools and community neighborhoods for animal adoption and care.
Official data available on the AMI website indicates that in the first quarter of this year 264 animals were captured without microchip, which increased to 280 in the second quarter. The numbers are similar to the first two quarters of 2024: the first were caught 266 animals without microchip, followed by 327 animals in the second quarter. In the third and fourth quarters of last year 258 and 203 animals were caught, respectively.
Regarding sterilization actions, in the first quarter of this year 289 were made, followed by 211 actions of this kind in the second quarter. In the first quarter of this year were claimed, or adopted, 102 cats and 29 dogs, and in the following quarter, 93 cats and 49 dogs were adopted.
As for the number of animals slaughtered, in the first quarter of this year alone 32 cats and 69 dogs were killed. If in cats this number reduced in the second quarter to 11, the same did not happen with the dogs: 101 were slaughtered.</description><pubDate>2025-08-05 01:24:52</pubDate></item><item><title>CCCM | Fusion with Foundation for Science and Technology creates new agency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/04/cccm-fusao-com-fundacao-para-a-ciencia-e-tecnologia-cria-nova-agencia/</link><description>Operating since 1999, the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center will merge with the Foundation for Science and Technology and the National Innovation Agency, creating a new institution. The practical consequences for the CCCM that aims to promote studies on Macao, China and Asia in Portugal are unknown. The president of the center says it is early to make comments
 
It is not known whether it will maintain its name, the number of scholarships for studies on China, Macao and Asia, or whether to change staff, but what is certain is that the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) will merge with the Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT) and the National Innovation Agency. Of these three entities will be born the new agency for research and innovation.
The process is linked to the desire to reform the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology by the Portuguese government led by Luís Montenegro, and the changes were announced on Thursday.
However, there is still no great information about the consequences of this merger to the CCCM. At HM, Carmen Amado Mendes, its president, chose to refer to clarification for the future operation of the center, considering that it is "premature" to give answers about something "that is not yet defined."
On Thursday, Minister Fernando Alexandre announced the reform of the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation with the extinction of several entities, including FCT that has been the main financier of PhD and other research projects in Portugal.
The reform of the ministry was approved by the Council of Ministers and, at a press conference at the end of the meeting, Fernando Alexandre justified the restructuring by describing his ministry as an “anacronic structure”, with fragmented organizations, disintegrated information systems and disarticulated governance.
With 18 entities and 27 higher leaders between the services of the non -higher education system and higher education, science and innovation, the ministry will have only seven entities and 27 higher leaders, with the integration of extinguished entities into new entities.
Regarding the extinction of the FCT, the minister assured that the financing of science will be preserved, with funding for four years that guarantees stability, predictability and “the protection of the financing of the most basic fundamental investigation”.
“When we started thinking about this reform, we do it with a vision: to ensure equal opportunities to access quality education,” said Fernando Alexandre, also underlining the reinforcement of the education system.
Marcelo can veto
The extinction of FCT has generated some less good reactions in Portugal because it fears a reduction in investment in science and research. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, president of the Portuguese Republic, said he had “the sensation” that the foundation was replaced “with an agency in which he was integrated, and had other functions beyond those of FCT.”
Marcelo acknowledged that the Foundation was a “very old structure” and that “it had many aspects that deserved to be rethought”, but said: “Just seeing what the new agency will do can I answer if this extinction is a good or bad idea.”
As for the eventual 'green light' from Belém, Marcelo said that if he thinks this extinction is "good", promulgates the diploma "without anguish." "If you have doubts about a point that is this diploma that is very important I ask the government to rethink. It has happened. I may not veto soon. If the government insists, I can come to veto, if it is until the end of my mandate," he also admitted.
A history of the transition
The CCCM was born in 1995 during the administration of Vasco Rocha Vieira, the last Portuguese governor of Macao, intending to be “a place of excellence for the dissemination of Macau, its history, its culture and its economy”, reads in the memories of Rocha Vieira, “to all the ports I arrived”.
This entity, operating in the Alcântara area, in Lisbon, was inaugurated in November 1999 by the then President of the Republic, Jorge Sampaio, and had as first president Alexandra Costa Gomes.
On the CCCM website it is read that the institution is endowed with administrative autonomy and its own heritage, being a public institute integrated in the indirect administration of the state and under the tutelage of the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation.
In the objective booklet, it is read that the CCCM “has as its mission to produce, promote and disseminate knowledge about Macao as a platform between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China, as well as between Europe and Asia”, also presenting itself as “a space dedicated to the study and teaching of Chinese language, culture and history”. The center has also been established as "a center for scientific research and continuous and advanced training on the relations between Portugal and China, as well as between Europe and Asia."
After the long presidency of Luís Filipe Barreto, academic at the University of Lisbon, the CCCM began to be chaired, from February 2020, by Carmen Amado Mendes. The leader recently saw her service committee renewed by 2030.
A few months after taking office as president, Carmen Amado Mendes presented, on September 18, 2020, the new “Strategic Development Plan of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center 2020-2030”.
Since then, the CCCM has awarded dozens of doctoral scholarships for the studies of Macao, China and Asia, and the “Spring Conferences”, which bring together academic performances around the same themes every year. Also noteworthy that the CCCM opened, in December last year, the “Gallery of Governors”, with 41 paintings of the former Portuguese governors of Macao. A new building that houses the file and library was also inaugurated.
This plan sets objectives by 2030, "the reinforcement of scientific and cultural cooperation in the domain of past understanding, present and future trends of relations between Europe and Asia."
With regard to archives, it is intended to “modernize and dynamization within a network of documentation centers and international reference file on euro-seatic themes, with emphasis on the various files in Lisbon, but also in Portugal and Europe”.
Given that the CCCM houses, in its facilities, the Macao Museum, the board points to the “insertion and appreciation in the museum network at the level of Lisbon and National”.
The central idea of ​​the plan was to develop, by 2030, “CCCM facilities as a pole of streamlining scientific, cultural and economic relations between Portugal and China, including the installation of entities such as the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry, the Erasmus+Youth Entrepreneurs Association, as well as research nuclei in eurical studies”. It remains to be seen if, with the merger, all these initiatives will continue their initial course.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 07:39:48</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ | Researchers discover a new species of bacteria in Portugal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/08/usj-investigadores-descobrem-nova-especie-de-bacteria-em-portugal/</link><description>A team of local university researchers identified a new species of bacteria in the Salinas of Rio Maior, Portugal. The type of discovered organism, which lives in extreme environments, widens the limits of biological knowledge and may have implications in areas such as biomedicine, pharmacy or even spatial exploration
 
There is news in the field of microbiology thanks to the latest discovery of a team of researchers linked to the University of São José (USJ), led by André Antunes, interim director of the Institute of Sciences and Environment of the same educational institution.
It is the discovery of a new species of bacteria from 12 samples collected in the Salinas of Rio Maior, in Portugal, which led to the establishment of the new species “Fodinibius alkaliphilus”. The species of bacteria previously known as “Alifodinibius salipaludis” for “Fodinibius salipaludis” was also reclassified.
The conclusions appear in the article “Fodinibius alkaliphilus sp. Nov., Moderately halophilic and alkaliphilic bacterium isolated from an Inland Saltern in central and reclassification of aliifodinibius salipaludi as fodinibius salipalis sp. SYSTEMATIC AND EVOLUTIONARY MICROBIOLOGY. The scientific journal is a publication “reference for new macrobial data”, being the official publication of the International Procaryotes Systematic Committee and the Applied Bacteriology and Microbiology Division of the International Union of Microbiological Societies, describes a USJ note.
In addition to André Antunes, the authors team includes researchers from the University of Science and Technology of Macau, coordinated by Marta Filipa Simões; Researchers at the University of Minho and Seville University.
According to the same USJ note, "the new [bacteria] species grows better in salinities about four times higher than those of seawater and also prefers alkaline conditions, combining the ability to grow in different extreme environmental conditions."
The importance of this type of studies, including analyzes to “such extreme environments”, is “future applications in a wide range of fields, including biomedical and pharmaceutical, but also extends to the discovery of new useful materials and the provision of useful information for future space exploration”.
The same team of investigators is not stopped, as "other samples of these places are currently being investigated and new publications describing other new species are expected in the coming months."
“This publication highlights the strengths of Macao in articulation with partners from Portuguese and Spanish -speaking countries, as well as its growing importance in the fields of biodiversity and biotechnology,” is still described.
The Power of Salinas
The researchers explain that "the species Aliifodinibius Salipaludis has been described, but their name has not yet been validly published." In field work the team isolated these species from “hypersaline environments, including saline, salt mines and saline soils”.
Prior to the fieldwork itself, the team conducted “an investigation to the microbial diversity of hypersaline environments in downtown Portugal”, and samples were collected in the Rio Maior area in July 2019. There were 12 genera bacteria from the Rio Maior salines.
Located in the central area of ​​Portugal, in these Salinas there is the “brine, which is about seven times more salty than seawater”, being “pumping from a well and generated by the crossing of a local underground course with an extensive salt deposit”.
The article also gives a historical context of this location. "Although they were first referred to in twelfth-century documents, these places are believed to have been linked to salt extraction from prehistoric times. They offer a single scenario, as they are the only interior saline in Portugal and the only ones in full functioning throughout Europe."
Thus, the study in question “was part of a bioprospecting campaign centered on this place”, resulting in “the isolation of a bacterial strain (N2T) and the discovery of a new putative species within the genus Fodinibius”.
In this work is determined “the taxonomic position of this new isolated based on the phenotypic, chemotaxonos and molecular properties”, is described.
Importance for Science
At HM, André Antunes explained that this discovery is, first of all, interesting to the scientific community, by bringing “additional information” and constituting a discovery “about the biodiversity that exists on our planet, more concretely at the macrobial level”.
"So far, we have been able [general scientific community] to study less than 1 percent of all microbes species on the planet. In over 99 percent we have no idea what they are, what they do and what their abilities, or what impact on the environment and our lives," he explained.
The researcher also said that "the microbes that come from extreme environments, and above all from environments with a lot of salt, which is the case of this species we now discover, are very interesting for a large range of biotechnology applications."
"We can include things like the medical area, biomedicine, the production of new pharmaceutical compounds or the production of new biomaterials, such as bioplastics," said André Antunes. The academic even talks about applications in “more exotic areas, which are now beginning to have a little more visibility, such as the potential application in construction, the production of more sustainable cements or concrete structures that have the self -repair capacity”.
This discovery also has some impact "for space exploration, more specifically to better understand what the limits of life are and where to seek life outside our planet." It is also included "very important implications for missions that are exploring Mars, namely as to the type of environments where it may be feasible to find past signs of life or present or other parts of the solar system."
A job that continues
The investigation is not for the Salinas of Rio Maior, and the team led by André Antunes last year, an expedition to Antarctica. “There are antarctic samples that we are currently studying and we have samples taken from the red sea bottom, where salt concentration is also quite high.” Therefore, the saga of discovering new bacteria and potential reclassifications in those that already exist.
André Antunes says that the discovery of a new species of microbes "is quite important to science, not only for the perspective of science at the basic level, but because we can have a better perspective of diversity we have on the planet."
“As we study extreme environments we can have additional information about what the limits of life are and how life adapts to extreme conditions.” Thus, André Antunes advocates investment in science so that there is later “an associated practical component, so it is not always easy to convince the financing entities”, as to this point.
The researcher also points out that the article and the investigation fits “very well in the priorities of Macau and the USJ itself, with regard to the focus in the area of ​​environment, biodiversity and biotechnology, anchored in connection with Lusophony”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:04:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia | Great Coral Barrier has been declining since there is a record</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/australia-grande-barreira-de-coral-sofre-maior-declinio-desde-que-ha-registo/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values ​​“the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's world heritage, has a “high to extreme” prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees Celsius above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the most extensive and severe bleaching that there is registration to date”, read in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot recover sufficiently quickly between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:22:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Economic Report Highlights Startup “Historical Record”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/hong-kong-relatorio-economico-destaca-recorde-historico-de-startups/</link><description>"Hong Kong's startups are on the rise." This is how the executive in the neighboring region describes the business environment in the region, where they were created in 2024 about 4,700 startups, plus 10 percent of 2023. In the "Report of Hong Kong's Business Environment 2025" it is read that the territory is far from losing economic competitiveness
 
The Hong Kong government released last July 30 the latest report on the neighboring region's economic scene. And one of the highlights is given to the scenario of growth of entrepreneurship.
In the “Report of Hong Kong’s Business Environment 2025” [Hong Kong 2025 Business Environment Report] it is noteworthy that “Startups in Hong Kong are on the rise”, given that last year there were “about 4,700 startups in the city, a historic record and an increase of 10 percent from the previous year”.
The document explains that "more than a quarter of these startups has founders from outside Hong Kong," it is companies that operate in a "broad spectrum of sectors, including Fintech [High Technology], Electronic Trade and Information, Informatics and Technology", having hired more than 17,000 people. This number of human resources also represents an increase of seven percent compared to 2023. "All this is proof of Hong Kong's strong appeal for startup entrepreneurs," the authorities highlight.
But it's not just startups that record growth, with the report to point out that the current government, led by executive head John Lee, "achieved remarkable results in the attraction of companies, investments and talents."
"For example, in 2024, the number of companies in Hong Kong with headquarters outside the territory increased significantly by about 10 percent, reaching almost 10,000." The “Office for the attraction of strategic companies, created more than two years ago, attracted 84 strategic companies to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, including companies with market capitalization or valuation of over $ 10 billion, involving cutting -edge technology”, it is added.
The report also points out that between January 2023 and the first half of this year, Invest Hong Kong, linked to the Raehk government's direct foreign investment department, "helped over 1300 foreign and continent companies establishing or expanding their business in Hong Kong, bringing investments of over $ 160 billion."
Still with regard to Invest Hong Kong, the entity helped "539 companies from the continent or foreign to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, which represents an annual growth of over 40 percent."
At the end of June this year, Hong Kong had 1.5 million local companies, while the total number of companies not registered in Hong Kong reached 15 509. "Both numbers represent historical records," it reads, and for the government of the neighboring territory the data "demonstrate the great confidence that continent and abroad companies have in the future of Hong Kong."
Given that Hong Kong also has a talent capture program, the Hong Kong Talent Engage, reads in the report that by June this year "were received about 500,000 candidates in the shelter of various talent admission programs, of which about 330,000 were approved." Of these numbers, Hong Kong actually arrived to work 220,000 qualified frames.
Good scholarship scenario
Quoted on an official press release, a government spokesman stated that "in a complex and volatile external environment, Hong Kong is undergoing a phase of economic update and transformation, but there are more opportunities than challenges."
Given that the territory has always positioned itself as a strong financial market worldwide, this scenario seems to have recorded a recovery in recent years.
“This year Hong Kong's financial market performance has been constantly improving. The Hang SENG Index has a 18 percent increase last year and an increase of more than 25 percent this year so far. The average daily business volume in the first half of the year was about $ 240 billion, with an increase of about 120 percent.”
Authorities highlight the maintenance of the economic competitiveness of the territory, pointing out that "over the years Hong Kong has been constantly classified as a global leader in economic freedom and competitiveness."
Attention to the trade war
In conclusion, Raehk's government clarifies that territory seems to maintain economic stability in times of constant commercial conflicts, with Donald Trump threatening and imposing tariffs on a number of countries.
“As volatile and turbulent as the world may be, we remain firmly committed to the rules -based multilateral commercial system, with the WTO [World Trade Organization] as a nucleus, while actively participating and supporting regional economic cooperation.”
The “numerous advantages of Hong Kong” are referred to, with its “highly internationalized business environment, a flexible and solid financial system, a simple and secure tax regime with low tax rates and a robust and independent legal system”.
However, in the document it is also stressed that the “tariff war caused a global reallocation of capital”, and Hong Kong wants to bet on the attraction of “foreign companies and capital” to the region.
The report also tells that "international organizations and foreign trade chambers in Hong Kong are confident in the future perspectives" of the territory, and that for the authorities "there is no reason to worry about some excessively pessimistic feelings."
"In fact, the Raehk government is creating a new momentum and expanding the ability to support Hong Kong's economic growth, thus increasing its overall competitiveness and achieving high quality development," is still added.
The executive spokesman also established a parallelism between good economic situation and political stability. "In recent years, the implementation of the National Security Law has restored a stable social environment in Hong Kong. This not only protected the rights and freedoms of the general public, but also made Hong Kong a safe haven to attract international capital and investment," he concluded. The report was presented by the secretary for Hong Kong finances, Paul Chan.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese knight bets on the formation of competition horses in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/17/cavaleiro-portugues-aposta-na-formacao-de-cavalos-de-competicao-na-china/</link><description>Report by João Pimenta, Agência Lusa
Step, trot and gallop: On a farm outside Beijing, Portuguese João Ruas training six horses daily to the practice of Dressage, an equestrian Olympic discipline that seeks to expose the maximum of the animal's athletic capabilities.
“It's a very very relationship,” he described to Lusa the Knight, a native of Lisbon. "There are days when we are almost like a father to teach the son, others where it is the horse that teaches us to us. But there must always be mutual respect," he said.
Streets, 28, arrived in China a year ago to raise six horses and form Dressage on a farm in Shunyi, the district in northeastern Beijing where the villages and agricultural fields resemble the interior of China than the capital of 22 million.
Ten kilometers from the Huairou reservoir, a 12 -kilometer artificial lake that supplies Beijing and regulates the flow of local rivers, the fifth is surrounded by watercourses, tree -lined slopes, corn fields and natural reserves.
On the horizon, the mountainous chains that rise to the north of the Changing and Huairou districts complete a landscape that contrasts with the tangle of glazed torres and apartments blocks of Beijing's urban network. “When I'm here I don't remember if I'm in China, Portugal or Germany,” explained João Ruas. "I'm in a bubble, let's say, and it's a good bubble."
Without previous experience in the country, the Portuguese was surprised by the sympathy of the Chinese and the reception of the local community. On the day he was interviewed by the Lusa agency, his cargo tricycle advocated on his way to the supermarket. Depressing the neighbors quickly sent to try to fix the vehicle.
“I am the only foreigner here. I communicate for gestures, I am still learning Chinese, but I have always been very well treated. The neighbors help in everything,” he said.
Despite the enthusiasm with life in the countryside, the coach admits difficulties in the exercise of the sport he has been practicing since he was nine years old. "There is a lot of amateurism, little technique, expensive and poorly frequency evidence. And everything that involves horses here is frankly more expensive than in Europe."
The horse “is not dominated by force: it requires patience, knowledge and sensitivity,” he said. "It's like an athlete. There are good days and bad days. And don't speak. We have to know how to read the signs. A small reaction may indicate a serious problem," he noted.
In Portugal, João Ruas studied at the D. Dinis Agricultural Professional School, where he reconciled classes for last weekends with the coach. Since then, it never left the horses. "I started with once a week, then two, then three, until I got to five. I had to insist a lot with my parents to start," he said.
In China, he works with European horses, brought on purpose to compete in Dressage evidence. The goal is to prepare animals since the age of three for competitions that normally start at four. "There is still a tradition of creation with sports focus. Horses have been raised for many years, but not with selective criterion for sport," he said.
Shanghai, the country's economic “capital”, leads the practice of drassage in the country, with more proof and better infrastructure. In Beijing, there is a growing interest, but there is still a long way to go. “It can be good to start like this, almost from scratch. It allows you to do things well. Without addictions,” reflected streets.
With the arrival of another horse soon and the prospect of continuing work in China, João Ruas is said. "I see myself here for many more years. It only costs the distance. But with today's technology, we managed to shorten it," he said. "There are sacrifices that are good for the soul."</description><pubDate>2025-08-17 22:54:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumption | New Round of the Grand Prix in September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/consumo-nova-ronda-do-grande-premio-em-setembro/</link><description>Next week it starts another major consumption award, which by the end of November will draw discounts on local commerce. The budget of this edition rose almost 65 percent and brings two news: the increase in the direct discount to the elderly, which passes to 500 patacas and the social care card
 
The government and the Macao Commercial Association presented on Friday another edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption, which begins on September 1 (Monday next week) and ends on November 30.
The new round of discounts will follow the same molds of the previous edition, but the budget will be higher, totaling 485 million patacas for consumption benefits awarded over the 13 weeks of the initiative, more 64.4 percent, or 190 million patacas, compared to the edition that took place between March and May this year.
However, the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption will have two news. The first is the increase in the value of the “immediate discount for the elderly” to 500 patacas, compared to the 300 patacas from the previous edition, which inaugurated direct support to the elderly to the second news, is the creation of a “social care card” with 500 patacas for immediate discount benefits to the holders of the disability assessment card.
Regarding the Macau Pass card for the elderly, users can use the anterior edition card, just to load 500 patacas at more than 100 service stations scattered by Macao.
If you need a new card, you can request it until November 18 at the Central Zone-South (Patane), North Zone (Tamagnini Barbosa), Northwest (Green Island), Taipa and Coloane (on Harmonia Avenue and Regisher Rua), and at the General Rehabilitation Evaluation Center.
The Social Care Card can be raised in institutions and centers coordinated by the Institute of Social Action. The government points out, however, that "it is not possible to enjoy the two types of benefit simultaneously."
The street spoke
Moreover, the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption will keep the same molds. During the week, mobile QR code mobile applications collaborating with the initiative have three draws to gain discount coupons when they spend more than 50 patacas on a transaction. For each mobile application, the user is entitled to three draws per week. Discount coupons will remain between 10 patacas and 200 patacas that have to be spent on purchases "equal to or greater than triple the nominal value of the coupon." That is, a 10 -headed coupon can only be spent on a purchase of at least 30 patacas.
In addition, every week there is a draw for those who used the mobile applications that will assign three 8,000 patacas awards.
During the presentation of the new edition of the consumption and trade support measure, the director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, said that the previous edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption “obtained remarkable successes” and “produced a positive effect on the stimulus of local consumption”.
The official also mentioned that the Chief Executive when he heard "opinions of society, numerous small and medium enterprises expressed the desire for the government" to continue "support for the community economy during the low season."
It is also important to note that the edition of the initiative is entitled “Strength of National Games - a major award for consumption in community zones”, a name given to “respond to the enthusiastic environment of national games and taking advantage of the event effect to revitalize consumer market confidence,” the government said.
Kaifong | Order Use of Cups during the Week
Deputies Leong Hong leaves and Ngan Iek Hang want the government to extend the period to spend the discount coupons of the great consumption prize on the days of the week.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, the vice-presidents of the Center for the Policy of Collective Wisdom subordinate to the General Union of Macao residents (Kaifong) stated that during the promotional activity there will be holidays, and that these days the government should allow the use of coupons. In addition, the deputies suggested to the Executive of Sam Hou Fai to enjoy the national games to launch a range of promotional products that sell in trade in community neighborhoods.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Economy | Economic Association praises government</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/economia-associacao-economica-elogia-governo/</link><description>Following the announcement that the government would launch another round of the Grand Prix of Consumption to boost the business of commerce and restoration, the vice president of the Macao Economic Association, Chang Chak Io, praised the measure as an effective response to the short-term to encourage consumption.
But the praise of the official to the executive in economic policies was not due to the new edition of the Grand Prix of Consumption. Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, Chang Chak Io highlighted long -term measures to improve the business environment, such as the launch of the stores plan with their own characteristics and professional consulting services to support small and medium -sized companies (SME) to transform their business, changing branch and exploring new markets. The leader also highlighted support for digitizing (SMEs), encouraging traders to resort to social networks and online marketing, attracting the consumption of new generations.
Regarding economic performance in the second half of this year, Chang Chak Io is optimistic not only due to the great consumption award from early September to the end of November, but due to the various events that are avilled, such as the International Fire Competition, the anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China and the national games.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:01:34</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2026 | CCPPC asks for more economic hotels</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/lag-2026-ccppc-pede-mais-hoteis-economicos/</link><description>On Thursday, Sam Hou Fai met with Macao representatives to the National Popular Assembly (APN) and Political Advisory Conference of the Chinese people (CCPPC) regarding the preparation of the Government Action Lines (LAG) for next year.
On the part of CCPPC representatives, the suggestion that the government “should promote the construction of more low-cost hotels to streamline visitors and the economy of the neighborhoods,” he stands out in a note from the chief executive's office.
It was also registered the request for the “increase in the use rate of the Hengqin Border Post” and “Improvement of the Financial System, the reinforcement of business and investment and the use of young people”, without forgetting “the policy of non -resident workers”.
Sam Hou Fai stressed the “Zape with Flavors” fair as an example of promoting the community economy and promises to “advance with innovative reforms” in the economic and cooperation area.
In turn, Macao to APN representatives defended “the creation of a team of experts (Think Tank), in order to provide scientific and strong foundations in political decision making”, and the development of the economy of neighborhoods ”and the“ organization of more activities that benefit consumption ”was also discussed. In this part, Sam Hou Fai pointed out that the return of “Esplanade Licenses has had positive effects”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:00:38</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2026 | Mobility in public function and economy in the agenda</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/lag-2026-mobilidade-na-funcao-publica-e-economia-na-agenda/</link><description>Already the usual round of the collection of opinion of associative leaders for the government lines for 2026. On Friday, the meeting of the Chief Executive took place with six associations linked to the civil service, having discussed the improvement of workers' mobility and economic promotion measures
 
Sam Hou Fai, chief executive, is already collecting opinions with associations in order to elaborate the government program for next year, better known as lines of governing action (LAG). On Friday, the meeting took place with six representative associations of civil servants, which includes the Macao Public Function Workers Association (ATFPM).
According to an official note from the Chief Executive's Office, “some representatives suggested improving the internal mobility mechanism”, as well as “increasing the relevance between the formation and the functions of civil servants in order to support the modernization of the system and macao governance capacity”.
Policies formulation were also requested to ensure the “protection of the rights and legitimate interests of civil service workers, the continuous improvement of training for public administration personnel, optimization of the subsidy regime and increasing the effectiveness of inter-departmental work”, among other points.
Sam Hou Fai promised to “optimize personnel management and career regime”, thus creating a “internal access regime”, the promotion of “horizontal mobility and the creation of direct training plans” in the civil service. It should be noted that some leaders delivered a letter to Sam Hou Fai with concrete requests to the Public Administration area.
SME and Employment in Mira
Also on Friday, the maximum leader of the MSAR gathered, at the Government headquarters, with representatives of the industrial, commercial and financial sectors regarding the elaboration of LAG to 2026. In all, there were 16 associations represented at the meeting, having defended policies such as the “acceleration of urban renewal, the development of the seafarer tourism” or the incentives for the “transformation and updating of the convention and exhibition sector”.
The “optimization of the business environment of small and medium enterprises (SMEs)” was also requested, as well as “safeguarding the use of the local population” or the need to “introduce high quality qualified frames in the financial sector”.
In this meeting, suggestions were presented for the tourism area, in the sense of “increasing the integral competitiveness of Macau as an international tourism city”. This can go through the “concert industry development”, without forgetting “support for local cultural and creative intellectual property and improving the measures of the public transport network, attracting the flow of tourists to the development of the economy of neighborhoods”.
Sam Hou Fai, in turn, admitted the existence of a “complex and changeable internal and external environment”, having argued that companies must “innovate and strengthen, injecting new dynamics into the general development of the sectors”.
It was the promise of adjustment “of the development of the convention and exhibition sector”, and the adoption of “various measures to increase the flow of people in the neighborhoods and guide the market in its transformation to new consumption models”, thus supporting local SMEs.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 03:59:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Seac Pai Van | Education Center with Patriotic Exhibition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/21/seac-pai-van-centro-de-educacao-com-exposicao-patriotica/</link><description>The government is preparing a pavilion for nationalist exhibitions at the Seac Pai Van Education Center, yesterday revealed the director of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), Kong Chi Meng.
Speaking cited by the newspaper or Mun, the DSEDJ director raised the veil a little about the contents that will be exposed, such as materials on Chinese Armed Forces, International Policy and Patriotic Education.
The official revealed that the place is already prepared to organize the inaugural show, which should happen this year, but that the government is still collecting all necessary informative materials, waiting through various methods, including some interactive, captivate the attention of the younger ones.
Kong Chi Meng also mentioned the great importance of the base of patriotic education dedicated to Macau and Hong Kong, inaugurated in Beijing. In its optics, the space will provide the opportunity for joint organization with Hong Kong of initiatives such as writing contests and study visits, as well as youth exchanges and patriotic education activities.</description><pubDate>2025-08-21 23:51:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | Inaugurated base of patriotic education for the RAES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/21/pequim-inaugurada-base-de-educacao-patriotica-para-as-raes/</link><description>The “Patriotism Base for Hong Kong and Macau in Beijing” is already inaugurated, and this patriotic education entity facing the special administrative regions organized together with the interior authorities of China.
Speaking to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the underdirector of Hong Kong and Macau's work office, Xu Qifang, stressed that the compatriots of Hong Kong and Macau have always demonstrated a “glorious tradition” of love to homeland and Macau, which is the important basis for stable and lasting implementation of a country concept, two systems. For its part, the secretary for Macao Social Affairs and Culture, Lam, who presided over the inauguration ceremony, pointed out that the establishment of this patriotic education base shows how patriotism can be innovative based on the concept of a country, two systems.
LAM also said that the government will resort to this entity to organize more visits with residents and young people, so that they can know more about Chinese Communist Party actions against Japanese occupation in World War II, that is, in the resistance war against Japanese aggression.</description><pubDate>2025-08-21 23:50:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Maternity | Women ask for subsidy to become permanent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/21/maternidade-mulheres-pedem-que-subsidio-se-torne-permanente/</link><description>The General Association of Women applauds the extent of the maternity leave support subsidy, but asks to be permanent and extended to companies with more than 100 workers. In addition, the association wants faster legislative process to increase maternity and paternity licenses
 
Macao's General Association of Women's Women, the Executive Council's announcement that the complementary subsidy plan attributed to employers for the remuneration paid in the maternity leave will be extended for another year. The allowance in question began to be distributed after the legal review that extended the maternity leave from 56 to 70 days, which entered into force on May 26, 2020, and would have as a maximum limit 14 days of base renumbering.
The allowance was presented as a measure to apply for a transient period, allowing employers to gradually adapt to economic expenses caused by increasing the number of maternity leave days.
The transition period ended in May 2023, but since then it has been consecutively renewed annually. In a statement issued on Wednesday night, the association represented by Deputy Wong Kit Cheng and Deputy Director Loi I Weng asked the complementary allowance to be permanent.
Loi I Weng argued that the continuity of the temporary character of the measure does not transmit security to potential new mothers or small and medium enterprises. The leader also points out that the complementary allowance should have a wide scope and not just stay by companies with less than 100 employees and that if in the future the maternity leave increases, the government needs to readjust the allowance to alleviate companies.
Quickly and well
Regarding the increase in maternity leave, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) charged a third entity of studying the subject, and a public consultation and the beginning of the legislative process next year.
Wong Kit Cheng is concerned about this calendar, taking into account the severity of low birth and the urgent need to solve it. As such, the deputy defends the acceleration of the process, the extension of paternity leave and that it is also complemented with a subsidy, allowing both parents to benefit from the measure.
It is recalled that the paternity license remains fixed in just five days.</description><pubDate>2025-08-21 23:49:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Scorned journalists</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/jornalistas-desprezados/</link><description>The country continues to burn. The flames do not give respite. A former supply and candidate for president of a 40-year-old parish council was trying to fight the flames and save animals in his village died charred. Five Covilhã firefighters on their way to fighting the flames saw the car fall into a ravine and one of the firefighters died, another, fight for serious life and three are injured in the hospital. A Wide Experience Drag Machine Operator died when he was fighting the flames in the Mirandela area. A firefighter car was swallowed by the flames and while completely burning the peacekeepers managed to escape resulting a serious injured firefighter.
Thousands of villages and villages fight the fires at the door of their homes with buckets and small hoses without any air support or for lack of firefighters who are not enough to serve everywhere. Residents vent to the televisions that hell has never seen guilty of census criminals, some mentally ill, others, and the rulers who have not been delayed in recent years the long planning has been outlined to reduce catastrophe. At the Funeral of the Covilhã firefighter who passed away, the prime minister was stunned and shouted, "Go away! You don't deserve to be here!" Portugal does not even have a Canadair plane for the efficient combat to the flames. Dozens of houses burned and several hectares of agricultural products have disappeared.
The Minister of Internal Affairs, former Provider of Justice, has no idea what it is to combat a fire and, in principle, called journalists to a press conference. After proclaiming some bullshit and merely announced that the state of alert would continue, when journalists were preparing to confront the minister with several pertinent questions, the ruler said, "Let's go!" Absurd, insolent, revolting the minister's attitude in despising journalists. Many of them who have risked life in reporting in the middle of the flames, forced to escape, day and night to eat and sleep without conditions. The attitude of the minister has already deserved the appeal of most Portuguese to the prime minister to fire them. Luís Montenegro listens as a merchant and after swimming in the waves of the Algarve sea and holding the Pontal party while the country burned, social networks were the scene of the biggest insults to the chief executive forcing him to interrupt his holidays and show that he was concerned about the tragedy situation in the country. The government has also been criticized for not having requested European support when the drama was at its peak.
The fires have been devastating. Many permanent housing burned, the elderly are evacuated to sports pavilions or for parish councils. The food support logistics of the Firefighters and the GNR military has been very disabled. The coordination between Civil Protection and Firefighters does not exist and the president of the League of Firefighters has already claimed an autonomous national command for firefighters to fight the fires. We thought the president of the Fire Department is talking to the doll.
On television we have watched the most diverse experts on territory planning, about the future planning solutions of positive solutions, about what is wrong in the Portuguese forest. And why does the government not call these experts and gather with them so that in October they start already tending to resolve much of what is not right and that has put the lives of thousands of Portuguese at risk? It would be urgent to hear these people and then act in accordance.
Insufficient firefighters are exhausted. They fall to the floor and sleep a few minutes, dehydrated and sometimes the water does not exist. In villages neither water nor electricity. The interventions of those responsible for civil protection never record these dramas and, much less, find solutions. It is the burning and faith in God. It cannot remain like this. Something has to change dramatically, otherwise next year we will have the same scene. The people are sad, desolate, without confidence in politicians and, once again, who takes advantage of this is the demagogy and populism of the arrival. Ventura has more and more good press and there is no day that does not appear on television to utter what the desolate like to hear. This is how the number of voters increases. Democrats are going to make a vacation to the beach and do not even realize the evil they are doing to themselves and their parties for a short term future when more elections arrive.
Millions of euros do not avoid these tragedies, but the astronomical expenditure of thousands of euros is still admitted to an airport in Alcochete, when Beja Airport could solve the problem. In such a way, many football teams in their travels to European competitions already depart and arrive using Beja Airport. And this, without there is a small venture that would call Lisbon and vice versa of TGV. We watched rulers concerned about the millions of euros they have to send to Ukraine and there is no money to save the Portuguese.
The revolt of the people hit by the fires is huge and close to Seia-Covilhã we heard an outburst of a resident who says everything: "If you caught a politician here would throw him into the middle of the flames!" The situation is serious, very serious and we have the idea that those responsible are completely powerless to solve the problem.
The letters open to the prime minister have been numerous. We had access to a letter written by the citizen Mário Gonçalves, in which the step step states that: “I write it in the name of revolt, indignation, and the deepest contempt for the show we watched in recent days. While the country burned, while families lost houses, memories and lives, while firefighters were exhausted on the ground fighting the uncontrollable flames, V. “Exhaustion”. Exhausted, Mr. Prime Minister? masked of political staging ”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:17:46</pubDate></item><item><title>The American Pope (III)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/20/o-papa-americano-iii-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the August 14th edition)
Europeanism springs tangiblely at European-widening Catholicism and begins to decline when, also thanks to Polaco's impetus, the "two lungs" of the continent crossed by the iron curtain, joining with the left hand in a morganatic marriage, find it too different. Absolute nationalisms and particularisms petty afflict both the geopolitical continent and the church in Europe, in an emphasis on themselves of the individual episcopal conferences. In search of the smaller and smaller and therefore purer. Antithesis of the Augustinian motto chosen by Leo XIV "in Illo Unum (in the one who is one, we are one)." It is not a finding. It is an act of faith. Pre-Constantine martyrs would diagnose today the moon/church in advanced decline, but confident in the next generator cycle, finally illuminating. Very different from today's dark climate. Catholics of low faith or excessive rationality discover the dead church in Europe. Precisely while in various regions of the 'global south', especially in Africa thanks to demographic impulse and the Americas, Catholics also grow in terms of political-cultural influence.
But it is physical law that observes in spatial dilation the dilution of coherence in any collective or institution, in the Catholic case (Holy Roman Church) and secular (European Union). The diffusion of liturgies inherent to the specific genius loci expresses the cultural heterogeneity that sometimes makes it difficult for a Catholic to recognize himself in another Catholic. If the European Church exhausts its driving force, to the West is the coup of mercy. This is, at least, the thesis of Cardinal Christoph Schönborn, colossus of the Central European Clerical Aristocracy and Dominican theologian, open to tradition during his thirty years as Archbishop of Vienna, which ended last January by (extension) of the age limit. At the conference of February 3, 2010 at Catholic University of America, this intimate of Ratzinger and then cautious Bergoglio resorter reveals his letters already in the title "Christianity, alien presence or foundation of the West?". Answer: "Both things." In fact, "Christianity is one of the roots of Europe." But "for many, it is a strange element in a world determined by reason, the Enlightenment, and the democratic principles." Conclusion: "This Europe, and the whole western world, will not survive without this strangeness brought by Christianity."
In the sense exploited by Diogneto, anticipated by the Pauline commandment in the letter to the Romans "do not be with this world" (Rom. 12: 2). This unclassifiable prince of the Church is inscribed in the current of habsburgs Catholicism, already the bastion of the reaction to the "French news" denounced by Novalis in the classic "Christendom or Europe" ie Europe (1802), but the only European empire not to stain with colonial sin unless the Balcanic and Centropeu Set is considered colonies. belonging to Vienna. In this context, they emerge in the twentieth century personalities of high culture almost morbidly attached to the idea of ​​Europe, as could be soon after the cold war the "saved" of the second lung, forced for half a century in the Soviet cage and, therefore, relegated to the "East". Informal geopolitical-spiritual network verticalized with Karol Wojtyła de Wadowice, near Krakow, immediately sanctified Pope. The name was imposed on him by his father, who served in the Imperial-Real Army, in memory of Charles I, last Kaiser Habsburg, beatified in 2004 by John Paul II.
Another remarkable exponent of this lineage is Cardinal Péter Erdö, Budapest Archbishop and Hungary Primate, in whom the minority wing, led by American cardinal Timothy Dolan, Catholic archbishop, New York Archdiocese and other not only American cardinals, bet as flag candidate in the conclave that will converge to PREVOST. Virtual Deputy Virtual Papa, ahead of Cardinal Pietro Parolin, Secretary of State of the Holy See, in the final vote of the cardinals. For him, "without Europe, the church loses its heart." We do not know if J.D. Vance, Trump's outgoing vice-president, eager to succeed him, has visited the São Francisco de Assis Basilica in Arezzo. If you did not, it is daring to suggest you to do so. Here you can mirror the dream of Constantine, the wonderful fresco of Piero della Francesca. Almost dawn nightly in the Roman field at the end of October 312. Emperor Jaz Dreamer under the tent of his camp near Bridge Milvia, where he is about to defeat rival Maxencio. Surrounded by mystical light on Piero, threshold between the dying shadow and the nascent rays of Christ, an angel extends the cross whose Constantine sign will overcome. Origin of the turn started by the emperor-bishop in the Council of Niceia, of which the seventh centenary is celebrated.
Sealed on February 28, 380 by Edict of Emperor Theodosius I, who decrees faith in Christ as a state religion. Romanization of Christianity and Christianization of the Empire. An angel must also have appeared Vance, who, in analogy with Constantine, dreams of the Americanization of Catholicism and the conversion of America to the religion of the American Pope. The gospel according to J.D. is instrumentum regno. Soul Supplement for Postliberal America, nostalgic of the “Roaring Forties and Furious Fifties”, Augusta of the Empire of Stars and Stripes. Waiting for Elvis's Parusia. In the hypothetical vansian exegesis of the "Mysterium Lunae", America would be assimilated to the "lunar" church, illuminated by the divine sun. About the strategic function of this vision converges the expansion Catholic tribe between the Maga leaders. Exuberant branch of trumpster that postulates the reciprocal fertilization between the state and the church for greater glory of the first.
Among these apostles, many converts, quorum vance. Inspired by the Encyclical "Longinqua Oceani" (1895) of Leo XIII, according to which the American Catholic Church "would be even more abundant if, besides freedom, also enjoyed the favor of laws and public protection." Vance's dream is that Leo, the American, can celebrate the nuptials between the United States and the Church. Maybe by agreement. Network to be extended to consistent countries. For an international nationalists, open to the strategic West, of which the United States is the fulcrum. And sensitive to skin color, preferably white. Super Magi who will unite the nations they want to join, followers of the moon with stars and stripes. Neoconstantinism with steroids aims at the balance of power between states in mutually legitimized competition to protect their own interests. Regular matches in the market where each actor plays and exchanges their own cards with those of others.
Of course they are addicted. It's all a deal. Trump tried in vain to explain him to Zelensky in the White House confrontation last February 28: "There are no cards!" Among the founding partners of the Vansiana coalition stand out personalities of neoconservative ancestry, such as Secretary of State Marco Rubio, the most influential after the nine exponents of the Catholic patrol that animates the federal government.</description><pubDate>2025-08-20 23:51:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Reforms for all tastes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/19/reformas-para-todos-os-gostos/</link><description>A recent news triggered a heated discussion. A 77 -year -old American signed a 15 -year contract with a cruise company, paying approximately $ 3,000 a month to live on board and travel during this period by 147 countries. He invested all his savings on a seas trip, buying the time of his freedom.
However, the “micro-reform” fashion appeared in Hong Kong. A study conducted last May, conducted by T. Rowe Price, a global asset management company and retirement investment management, revealed that 47 percent of retired people prefer to continue working full -time or part -time, but with a lifestyle change. Micro-reform no longer view work as the center of their lives, but as a supplement something that can brighten their days.
The other traditional retirement model is “full -time renovation”. People leave work behind and dedicate themselves to taking care of their grandchildren, shopping, lunch with friends, enjoying a quiet reform within the family and the community.
The American who began to live in a cruise bought their freedom, Hong Kong seniors have a flexible job to control their lives and those who reform completely to family and the community. Although these models differ in shape, they share three pillars:
First, the need for sufficient financial reserves. The American pays for the fourth in Cruzeiro about 360,000 US dollars a year, a value that can push a great pressure on its financial stability. Data from the Hong Kong Institute of Financial Planners related to the fourth quarter of 2023 show that the monthly average spending of a reformed reaches the $ 14,700 dollars of Hong Kong, while the most spent reaching 23,671. While micro-reform can have a salary, they still need to assess whether their savings and passive income can cover expenses when salary disappears. Although full -time retired people do not start travel expenses, they should not underestimate unforeseen costs such as health expenses and inflation.
Secondly, they must be psychologically prepared for life change. The American has reinvented themselves as a "long-term traveler," micro-reproach conserves part of their professional identity that acts as a psychological anchor and full-time retired are the role of "domestic grandparents." The core of this transformation is based on personal appreciation. Like a retired teacher who teaching again is not only waiting to receive a salary, but the respect of the students and the recognition for their knowledge. Often spiritual realization feeds another elderly person than financial rewards.
Third, as we get older, health problems begin to emerge. Continuing to work not only keeps motivation, but also helps to slow down the aging of the mind. Health is missing everyone. Regular exercise, a balanced diet and sleep quality are things that the retired prioritize. Only when we have health can we enjoy the reform in full.
The wisdom of reform planning involves transforming the work from a "necessity" to the "condiment of life" and transforming "forced labor" into a "right of choice." A well -thoughtful retirement plan never has to choose to work or not, but to find the perfect balance between the two options. For this to happen, sufficient financial reserves, acceptance of the change in the role we play and health to achieve “an active reform and a reform without fatigue, successfully performing the second stadium of life.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-08-19 02:04:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Eternal beatas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/17/beatas-eternas/</link><description>No, I will not write about the beatas who frequent the sacristies of the churches and who are insinuated with the priests to provoke sex, because this would give a very controversial chronicle and I won't be there. I come to emphasize what is happening from north to south by all the cities, villages and villages of this country about the cigarettes consumed by smokers.
Cigarette beatas take between 10 to 12 years to deteriorate in nature never to decompose in full. And if the beatas filters are plastic, the beatas take over 100 years to disappear. During this period, the beatas release toxic chemicals in the soil and water, contaminating the environment and impairing wild and urban life. We no longer consider the fact that smokers harm their health, each makes the decision they want. But smokers have to compete in this severe fact that the beasts are thrown to the floor or water.
In any town, village or village we can see Blessed on the floor. Are to the millions. We well know that some coffees do not put ashtrays on the terraces of the terraces, although there are already people who have their reduced dimension grades to put their beatas who later throw the trash. Often citizens are walking the streets, passing their own container to put the beatas and throw them to the ground. They are abroad of a bar in the conversation and shoot the beatas to the floor. They are boating and shoot the beatas to the water. They go to the beach and put the beatas in the sand or throw them into the sea. They are driving a car smoking and in the end shoot the beatas through the window with grant in the car. They are in a picnic in forest zone and throw the beatas anywhere, forgetting the danger of starting a fire. The streets are full of millions of beatas. In conversation with a municipal worker who cleans the streets, he told us that it is virtually impossible to collect all the beatas because some are among the sidewalk stones.
Blessed are a serious damage to the environment and the health of humans. Most smokers have to compensate that they have to change their habit of throwing the beatas to the ground or the waters of a river or sea. It is a gesture of civility and solidarity for the health of others if the smokers do not put the beatas in their own containers. It seems to be a fact of less importance, but it is not. Seriously is millions of beatas through the open -air streets. An environmental matters expert has conveyed to us that one of the worst health of the health of the streets is the existence of thousands of Beatas in their city, village or village. This paradigm is important that it is gradually changed and that smokers stop shooting the beatas where they should not.
According to the Continental Portugal Monitoring Program promoted by the Portuguese Environment Agency, in 2022, the Beatas and the Cigarette Filters occupied third place in the top 10 of the marine waste, corresponding to 13.1% of all caught trash. Read well: It is estimated that 7000 beatas to the ground is estimated. The cigarette beatas are the remaining part after the cigarettes are smoked. They are made up of tobacco remains and a filter. Tobacco remains contain about 4000 chemicals, of which more than 50 are proven carcinogens. They will tell me that they know 80-year-old smokers and smoke one pack a day and have not caught cancer. And we responded that smokers have already died, 40 and 50, and that doctors diagnosed that the contracted cancer was due to tobacco.
It turns out that filters include a central part of cellulose acetate (a synthetic fiber that looks like cotton, but consists essentially of plastic and hence the possibility of being able to get 100 years to undo), involved in two layers of paper or other synthetic fibers. While the cigarette is smoked, the filters accumulate part of the pollutants present in the smoke. When the beasts degrade, filters free these pollutants, such as nicotine and heavy metals such as iron and copper. A cigarette beat can contaminate up to six liters of water. We think it is a serious matter and to take into account, that we cannot continue to shoot with the beasts to the floor or water. It is an appeal that we leave to potential smokers, who think twice before we get rid of the Beata who have their fingers. To the floor, the river or the sea, please, no!
P. S. - Our solidarity for how many in Macao were harmed by the recent and serious floods that were recorded in the MSAR.</description><pubDate>2025-08-17 22:56:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese Orchestra | New season opens with “brightness of the east”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/orquestra-chinesa-nova-temporada-abre-com-brilho-do-oriente/</link><description>The Chinese orchestra of Macau is about to begin a new show of shows and it is in this context that the show “Brightness of the East” takes place this Saturday, the 30th, marking the start of a new season of various sounds and international music. Highlight for the debut of the symphonic suite of traditional Chinese music that has the same name as the concert
 
The first show that gives the motto to a new season starred by the Chinese orchestra of Macau (OCM) and other guests for 2025/2026 is already known. It is “brightness of the East”, name of the symphonic suite of traditional Chinese music that will make its debut in this show that takes place Saturday, the 30th, in the large auditorium of the Cultural Center of Macau (CCM), from 20h.
This “symphonic suite” was composed of a whole by composers from China, Japan and South Korea, in a creation that, according to the Cultural Institute (IC), celebrates “Cultural Integration and Artistic Synergy of the three countries within the Cidade de Cultura East Asia 2025 ′”.
The show features Zhang Lie as a music director and the main conductor, followed, in addition to “brightness of the East”, a “selection of commissioned works and classic pieces of regional inspiration”.
It was up to OCM to invite “the renowned Chinese composer Zhao Lin, the young composer Luo Maishuo, the Japanese Master Kaoru Wada and the Korean composer of traditional Park Bum-Hoon music to collaborate in the creation of the Chinese Traditional Music Symphony Suite” that gives the show's name. The public will be able to see an interpretation by 12 musicians from the three countries, “who will play traditional musical instruments such as Chinese Pipa and Zhongruan, Shakuhachi and Japanese Shamisen, and Haegeum and Gayageum Koreans, revealing vividly the ethnic characteristics and musical essence of the three cultures, promising a unique and engaging action,” describes the IC.
One more order
In addition to the aforementioned sounds, the public can also have an OCM interpretation of the composition “Night of Macau”, a work commissioned to Singapore Cultural Medal, Eric Watson, as well as other prominent regional pieces, with a view to sharing with the public Macau's vibrant cultural identity through music. Tickets are already on sale for this show, varying prices between 120 and 380 patacas.
OBMEP has several musicians who dominate the art of some traditional Chinese musical instruments, such as ERHU, GAOHU or ZHONGHU.
The music director and main conductor, Zhang Lie, plays the same roles in the Chinese nanjing orchestra and the Chinese orchestra of Henan. It is a renowned Chinese conductor, vice president of the Professional Committee of Regency of China and national conductor, having been recognized as a “prominent artist” by the Ministry of Culture of China.
Previously, he was a permanent conductor of the Radio Symphonic Orchestra and the China and the Radio National Orchestra, as well as the Zhejiang National Orchestra, Chinese Orchestra of Guangdong and National Orchestra of Shaanxi Radio and Television.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:10:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy again hosts the second edition of the Short Film Festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/galaxy-volta-a-acolher-a-segunda-edicao-do-festival-de-curtas-metragens/</link><description>The second edition of the International Festival of Macao Entertainment Group, in a joint organization between this game operator and the Cultural Institute (IC), In addition to the screening of several films, there are also workshops, a conference on the film industry, masterclasses and awards to the best short films.
According to a note from the IC, the “aims to promote Macao's film production and television production, to foster industrial diversification and reinforce the exchange and cooperation between local and international film and television sectors”.
The festival includes five sections, namely “Macao Shorts”, “New Voices of the Horizon”, “Featured Director”, “East Asian Panorama” and “Special Sessions”, with views in places such as Cinemateca Passion and Galaxy theaters. The festival ends on September 20, with a ceremony at the Galaxy auditorium of the Galaxy International Convention Center.
There will be awards to the directors with the best works. For the “Shorts de Macao” section, the “Macao Unit Prize” and “Special Mention of the Jury” will be delivered; For the “New Voices of the Horizon” section will be awarded the “best short film” prizes, “special jury mention”, “best director” and “innovative narrative award”. The “Asian East Prize of Tomorrow” was also created in order to distinguish prominent works from East Asia.
Ten local works
In the “Shorts de Macao” section, which reveals to the public “the unique cultural landscape and the innovative perspective” of local directors, ten cinematic works are presented, including Chao Koi Wang's “Chuff Chuff”; Ho Cheok Pan's “Cockroach Family”; Fox Box, by Ka Meng; Teng Kun Hou; Granny Pirate 3: Typhoon Again ”by Ho Wai Tong; Jarvis Xin's “hand hand”; Chan Chon Sin's “Nuptial Flight”; Purple, by Ho Kueng Un; Keo Lou's “The Performance” and Chan Si Ieong's “Waves Under The Sea”.
In "New Voices of the Horizon" are "more than 20 innovative productions of emerging directors from around the world, including the interior of China, East Asia, Southeast Asia, Europe and America." Thus, “the perspectives of the new generation of filmmakers” are presented, and provides a reflection on “the diversity and richness of film narratives around the world”.
In the “Featured Director” section, short films and feature films of renowned directors will be displayed, “highlighting the significant contributions to the film arts in their respective fields”.
This year, the featured director will be the Japanese Nobuhiro Yamashita, "known for his discreet style and narrative full of nuances." It is, according to the IC, a director who "captures the wit of youth and everyday life, while deepening in the psychology of the characters," performing "works that exploit Japanese society and culture with a mixture of realism and humor."
In turn, in the “Panorama do East Asia” section, ten “carefully selected and characteristic” films of the Asian continent are presented.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:17:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Mam | Lok Cheong works on display at Tibet</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/mam-obras-de-lok-cheong-em-exposicao-no-tibete/</link><description>It's called “Tibet's Heart Ties” and is a show presented in Tibet with a total of 100 works by Lok Cheong, provided by the Macao Art Museum. It is an “exhibition that continues the artistic link between Tibet and Macao”
 
The Tibet Art Museum welcomes, until October 12, an exhibition with a hundred works by artist Lok Cheong provided by the Macao Art Museum (MAM). It is an event that takes place in partnership with several official entities, such as the Central Government's connection office at MSAR, the Cultural Institute (IC) or the Federation of Literary and Artistic Circles of the Tibet Autonomous Region, among others.
The show in question is entitled “Ties with the Heart of Tibet: Commemoration of the 60th anniversary of the establishment of the autonomous region of Tibete-Exhibition of Lok Cheong works in Tibet” and opened to the public on the last 13th of this month, being proof of the existence “of the 30 years of artistic friendship between the two regions”.
According to an IC note, the exhibition features about 100 masterpieces created over half a century by Lok Cheong, born in 1923 and died in 2006, complemented by more than 70 sketches, archival materials, photographs and other “invaluable” historical materials.
According to the IC, most of these items belong to the MAM collection, and the rest are part of the artist's family spoils and the Tibet Art Museum.
Portraits in 1994
The exhibition is organized in three themes, such as “Love to the Fatherland”, “capturing the character of Macao” and “portraits”, offering to the public “a systematic view of Lok Cheong's artistic development”.
You can see work within the “Tibetan theme”, as is the case with “the mysterious Potala Palace” and “a hidden path, shigatse”, described by the IC as having “vibrant color explosions, in a tribute to the sacred landscapes of Tibet”.
In turn, the "witnesses of history (trees with branches intertwined in the Kun Iam Tong Temple)" and "Octagonal Pavilion Library" capture "the essence of the Macao scenario over the last fifty years in dynamic brushstrokes."
In addition, works such as “technicians starting to serve the homeland” and “rice offering by the homeland” demonstrate “the artist's tribute meaning to the patriotism of his compatriots”. In this exhibition and for the first time, the manuscripts of Lok Cheong's trip to Tibeto in 1994, are accompanied by rare documents that report their cultural exploitation of the heart of the homeland and the Tibet.
Lok Cheong's paintings with Tibet themes became "an eternal testimony of friendship between the two regions." In 1991, the artist participated in the “Painting Exhibition of Planalto Nevado”, held in Guangzhou, starting the artistic exchange between Macau and Tibet. Subsequently, Lok Cheong continued, with his brush, to build a friendship bridge between Tibet and Macau, having organized several visits by artists from Macau to Tibet and promoted to create the first primary school under the Hope Project in Nagqu. “His pioneering spirit continues to lead cultural integration between the two regions,” he describes.
Given that this year are the 60th anniversary of the establishment of the Tibet Autonomous Region, this show is held with works that carry “deep ethnic feelings in Tibet” and that honor “Lok Cheong pioneering efforts in promoting cultural exchange between Macao and Tibet”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:16:35</pubDate></item><item><title>“Oxfam Towerrun” takes place at Macau Tower in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/20/oxfam-towerrun-acontece-na-torre-de-macau-em-outubro/</link><description>The 12th edition of “Oxfam Towerrun”, a solidary race event takes place on October 19th at the Macao Tower, this time with the theme “Each Mind Real - Each Step turns lives”. Registration for the race has already begun and ending on September 26.
This event aims to support the Non -Governmental Organization (NGO) Oxfam in the fight against poverty worldwide. "Whether participant, sponsor or supporter, it is helping to build a movement where each step turns lives and each mind actually counts. The success of this event is only possible thanks to the joint effort of all. The funds raised this year will support Oxfam's combat and development projects, including support for educational development and well-being of children left in mainland China, bringing real changes to their lives." Tang, Oxfam's interim director-general in Hong Kong.
At the press conference that announced the date of the 12th edition, Oxfam also announced that the winner of the 2024 race, Soh Wai Ching, and rail corridor, also from Macau, Vivi Cheung, will be ambassadors of this year's event.
Games Support
Participants can apply for the various categories, namely the “individual challenge”, which includes the full 61-story race, or the “elite or open categories” for men and women. The program also includes the “individual challenge” in the 31 -story half -tasting format, or “team challenge”, with teams running between 4 to 61 floors. Another category is the “leader race” with only 7 floors. Participants 16 years or older can apply for individual race, paying a minimum amount of 525 patacas. Students pay 350 patacas. These values ​​are charged for the full tower challenge of a tower.
The registration fee for the relay of four people is also 525 patacas, and the “Donativa suggested by team” is five thousand patacas. The top three classifieds of the Individual Complete (elite) (male and female) test will receive a cash prize in the total amount of 1,200 euros (about 11 thousand patacas).
In addition to organizing the race for a cause, Oxfam is also aligned with the national games, which this year are organized for the first time in the province of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau. "The goal is to take this opportunity to attract more corridors of mainland and abroad China, making known and promoting this meaning sports event, as well as fostering local sports culture." The “Oxfam Towerrun” has international certification, namely Towerrunning World Association and Asia-Pacific Vertical Marathon Association.</description><pubDate>2025-08-20 23:33:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Fai chi kei | New pedestrian passage inaugurated tomorrow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/fai-chi-kei-nova-passagem-pedonal-inaugurada-amanha/</link><description>It will be inaugurated tomorrow, from 10am, the new pedestrian crossing next to Avenida Marginal do Patane, in the vicinity of Doca do Lam Mau and Fai Chi Kei neighborhood. According to a note from the Directorate of Public Works Services and the Directorate of Service for Traffic Affairs, it is a work that ended early. "For the first phase of the work referring to the pedestrian crossing of Patane Marginal Avenue, which began in June last year, the provisional reception was performed in mid-August, verifying that, compared to the date of completion provided for in the contract, the work was completed with the anticipation of about a month."
After operating this upper pedestrian passage, the existing treadmills will be eliminated from the Trust Leisure Garden buildings, Van Sion Son Chun and Asia Industrial Building, and to strengthen the circulation of separate pawns from vehicles ”. The government also states that this pedestrian passage is equivalent with elevators, it is intended that "the pedestrian crossing of the Lam Mal dock becomes a continuous pedestrian system."
In the same note, the two services directions explain that “the construction work of a superior set of passage to pawns is being accelerated between Rua Norte do Patane and Rua do Commander João Belo”, and “the work of Foundations, by stakes, from the access from the superior passage to pedestrians, will start in September and its conclusion is scheduled for the second semester of 2026”.
In addition, it was “extended the sidewalk of the entrance door of the Santa Madalena School”, and a provisional cargo and discharge zone of passengers and goods on the stretch of Commander João Belo Street was created, next to the Wang Hoi building ”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:08:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | More than 22.6 million tourists until July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/turismo-mais-de-226-milhoes-de-turistas-ate-julho/</link><description>In the first seven months of the year, more than 22.6 million tourists visited Macau, almost 15 percent in annual terms, a brand that can represent a return to times before the pandemic. In July alone, more than 3.4 million tourists entered Macau, the large majority of Chinese tour
 
Between the beginning of this year and the end of July, they entered Macau 22,676,906 tourists, which means a 14.9 percent increase over the same period last year, driven largely by the rise of the tour market from the interior of China.
The bar exceeds half of the forecast of the director of tourism services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, of a total of 38 and 39 million entries at the end of 2025, when the traditional period of high season for national holidays of October is still missing. Following this pace of inputs, 2025 may close with numbers similar to the pre-parish period. It is recalled that in 2019, Macau was a destination chosen by about 39.4 million tourists.
According to data revealed on Friday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), of the approximately 22.7 million visitors, number of tour entries were almost 13.2 million, while individual tourists totaled 9.5 million, representing annual increases of 25.5 and 2.8 percent, respectively
Despite the increase of people visiting Macau, their stay in the territory has decreased by 0.1 days to 1.1 days, compared to the first seven months of 2024. DSEC explains the descent with the “increase in the proportion of tour of visitors”, since the average period of permanence of the tour (0.2 days) and that of tourists (2.3 days) have remained.
Good neighbors
Last month, more than 3.4 million visitors entered Macau. The July monthly record has been the highest since January, when the territory was visited by 3.65 million tourists. But of the 3,458,366 visitors who moved to the territory, more than half (1,980,732) were tour, which represents an increase of 24.1 percent compared to the same month of the previous year, refers to the DSEC note. The number of tourists (1,477,634) also increased 3.7 percent in annual terms.
Most visitors (2,563,212) came from the interior of China -another 17.4 percent -and 625,343 arrived from Hong Kong and 92,037 from Taiwan, a homologous rise of 6.2 and 21.4 percent, respectively.
The number of visitors from nine cities of the Greater Bay River Delta was 1,225,642, plus 23 percent, compared to July 2024, thanks to the 56.8 percent increase of visitors from Zhuhai.
With regard to international visitors (177,774), it also states DSEC, the increase recorded was 2.8 percent. In this chapter, the highlight of tourists from Thailand that rose 48.9 percent, to a total of 12,352, compared to July last year.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:07:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Sales with annual break 11.4% in the first half</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/comercio-vendas-com-quebra-anual-114-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>In the first half of this year, the average sales volume rate of retail trade establishments registered a homologous drop of 11.4 percent, the Directing of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said on Friday. In this chapter, the jewelery and watchmaker sector recorded a descent of 26.5 percent sales volume, while pharmacies and car trade increased sales 4.9 and 3 percent, respectively.
DSEC also indicates that in the first half of this year the retail trade volume was set at 33.55 billion patacas, 9 percent less than the last semester of 2024.
In quarterly terms, the retail trade volume “has been moved at 15.97 billion patacas, decreasing 1.4 percent, in annual terms, this decrease was significantly tightened compared to the first quarter of this year (-15 percent)”.
DSEC points out that the volume of leather and cosmetic and hygiene products dropped 15.8 and 14.3 percent, but respectively, the pharmacies rose 4.5 percent, and the sale of cars grew by 3.6 percent.
After eliminating the factors that influence prices, the sales volume index of retail trade establishments registered in the reference quarter of a homologous decrease of 2.4 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:06:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado | SME debts rise to higher value since 2008</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/malparado-dividas-das-pme-sobem-para-valor-mais-alto-desde-2008/</link><description>Macao's badly and medium -sized corporate credit has risen at the first half of the year to 7.6 percent, the highest value since 2008, when the mandate faced the impact of the international financial crisis. However, in the same period more credits were approved, with fewer guarantees required
 
In the first six months of this year, the balance-related balance balance unpaid by small and medium enterprises (SME) reached a level of 5.6 billion patacas, Macao monetary authority (AMCM) revealed on Friday. The authority adds that the 7.6 percent increase in the evil credit in the first half of 2025 was due, "mainly, the fall in the balance of debt loans granted to SMEs."
The proportion of misconduct in the first half of 2025 registered a 1.4 percentage points, compared to the 6.2 percent of the first half of 2024, or an annual increase of 700 million bars of credit for paying.
AMCM advised the bank sector to stress negotiations with the SMEs to create “flexible reimbursement plans, under the principle of prudent risk management and in accordance with their own credit policies, continuing to provide credit support to customers with liquidity difficulties”.
The level of misconduct registered in the first half of this year reached the highest absolute value since 2028, when the MSAR felt the impact of the world financial crisis.
Credit death
Despite the historical levels of the debt ratio for paying, in the first half of 2025 there was a considerable increase in SME -approved credits, compared to the previous semester, plus 47.7 percent to a total of 4.9 billion patacas.
At the same time as approved credits increased, the requirements for approval went in the opposite direction. "The warranty ratio (which indicates the proportion of credit limit with promised bodily assets) was 62.2 percent, corresponding to a decrease of 14.5 percentage points (PP) when compared to the latest data," said AMCM.
Another contradictory trend revealed by AMCM data concerns the balance of SME loans, which, despite the increase in approved credits, descended in the first half of this year 4.7 percent to a total of 743.5 billion patacas, compared to the last semester of 2024.
When the analysis is made according to economic use, it was found that the loans granted to the sector in “Transport, Storage and Communications” increased 14.1 percent, while to sectors in “thick trade and retail” and “construction” registered decreases of 9.9 and 2.8 percent, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:05:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Pandas | Iam signs agreement with HK Ocean Park</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/pandas-iam-assina-acordo-com-ocean-park-de-hk/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has signed a memo of cooperation with Ocean Park de Hong Kong “with a view to further reinforcing the cooperation relationship related to giant pandes and wildlife conservation work of both territories,” says an official note.
This agreement was signed as part of a visit made yesterday by Ocean Park officials to AMI.
Thus, it is intended to “raise the quality of care provided to giant pandes, promote wildlife conservation and reinforce public awareness of nature conservation”. There will be “exchange and formation of personnel and sharing medical knowledge and nursing experiences on wild animals, building a technical cooperation platform”, highlights the same note.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:27:33</pubDate></item><item><title>SMG | Thunderstorms and wind from Sunday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/smg-trovoadas-e-vento-a-partir-de-domingo/</link><description>Meteorological and geophysical services yesterday revealed that they are following a low-pressure area east of the Philippines, which over the weekend can be developed in a tropical storm. The authorities pointed out that there was still no certainty about the evolution of the storm and the degree of influence it will have in Macao.
However, weather forecasts point to high temperatures today and tomorrow due to the formation of an anticyclone of high altitude. However, forecasts indicate that from Sunday, the thunderstorms and rain, which should continue to stretch Macao until at least Wednesday.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:13:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Isaf | Intercepted “truck” that sold illegal medicines</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/isaf-interceptado-camiao-que-vendia-medicamentos-ilegais/</link><description>Last Monday, a joint action from the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (Isaf) and customs services (SA) intercepted a truck used to store and sell illegally imported medicines.
The “mobile drug distribution point”, as designated by the authorities, was found in the northern zone of the peninsula. Authorities found inside the vehicle "over 3000 boxes of painkillers, drugs for erectile dysfunction and traditional Chinese drugs for oral and external use." According to a statement issued Wednesday by Isaf, among the products found there were some who were not even registered or approved for import by the Isaf.
The head of the commercial agency owner of the truck is suspected of having imported and provided illegally medicines. The case led Isaf to open an investigation process and the SAs accused the “the offender regarding the violation of the provisions of product imports by the commercial agency”.
Anyone who imports to Macau drugs without permission or license issued by Isaf can be punished with a “maximum fine of 700,000 patacas and, for serious circumstances, incur criminal liability”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:12:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Asia | Thailand and Cambodia signal from the ordinary border</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/asia-tailandia-e-camboja-assinam-desminagem-da-fronteira-comum/</link><description>Thailand and Cambodia have agreed to remove the mines along the border that separates the two countries and to proceed to the “clear assignment” of territories whose sovereignty is disputed by Bangkok and Phnom Penh.
The decision results from an extraordinary meeting Friday of the Regional Border Committee (RBC), integrated by both countries, said yesterday the spokesman for the office of the Prime Minister of Thailand, Jirayu Huangsap.
Several incidents with terrestrial mines in the border zones were recently recorded, the latest from which it occurred on August 12, when a Thai military man was injured.
Two other incidents on July 16 and 23 preceded the armed confrontation that broke out on the 24th of this month between Thailand and Cambodia, which lasted for five days and left at least 44 killed, including civilians, at various points in the near 820 kilometers of border.
The agreement for the removal of mines and “clear attribution” of the border zones disputed is added a pact for the “joint disarticulation” of criminal networks dedicated to global cyberphraud, strongly implanted along the border of the two countries.
Precisely, these very powerful cyberphraude sites were pointed out by Thailand's first-rate minister Paetongtarn Shinawatra as one of the possible triggers of the armed confrontation in which Thailand and Cambodia were involved last month.
Paetongtarn stated that the conflict could be related to his government's plans to combat these centers, with a large presence in Cambodia and are determinant for his economy.
On July 28, Bangkok and Phnom Penh signed in Malaysia a ceasefire for armed confrontation, although both parties were later charged with violating the agreement. The border between these neighboring countries was cartographed by France in 1907, when Cambodia was a French colony.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:20:05</pubDate></item><item><title>OCX | Putin and Modi Gifts at Tianjin summit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/ocx-putin-e-modi-presentes-na-cimeira-de-tianjin/</link><description>China said Saturday that the Russian President and the Indian Prime Minister will be present at the Summit of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization, rejecting any confrontation between blocks.
The summit, which will take place between August 31 and September 1, in Tianjin (Northeast), "will be the largest" since the foundation of the organization, told foreign journalists in Beijing, the assistant minister of Chinese foreign affairs, Liu Bin.
Liu said that “the spirit” of the organization is based on trust, mutual benefit and respect for diversity, maintaining all values ​​in the face of “outdated concepts”, such as block confrontation or the Cold War mindset.
"In today's world, the old hegemony mentalities and power policies still prevail. Some countries try to put their own interests above others, which seriously threatens peace and worldly stability," he said.
"The more complex and turbulent the international situation becomes, the more countries need to reinforce solidarity and cooperation to promote common development," he said.
Members of the Shanghai Cooperation Organization include, in addition to the Popular Republic of China, Russia, India, Pakistan, Iran, Belarus, Kazakhstan, Kyrguistan, Tajiquistan and Uzbekistan, representing approximately 40 percent of the world population.
Although member countries claim that the organization is not a military block and seeks to protect threats such as terrorism, some experts said they believed that the main objective is to be "counterpoint to the Atlantic Alliance."
However, there are internal tensions within the group, which includes opposing countries such as India and Pakistan.
In June, the meeting of the Ministers of Defense of Member Countries, held in the Chinese city of Qingdao, ended without a joint statement due to disagreements on security issues, particularly about terrorism. New Delhi, who refused to sign the final text, reported that some countries use terrorism as a political tool, in a veiled reference to Pakistan.
Other presences
In addition to Vladimir Putin and Narendra Modi, the Deputy Minister of Chinese Foreign Affairs confirmed the presence of the presidents of Belarus, Iran and Pakistan, among others. Liu said that leaders from various countries were invited, such as Mongolia, Azerbaijan, Armenia, Cambodia, Maldives, Nepal, Turkey, Iraq, Turquemenistan, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia and Vietnam.
Liu Bin also summoned the UN Secretary-General António Guterres, leaders of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean), the Independent States community and the Asian Bank for Infrastructure Investment.
Chinese President Xi Jinping will lead heads of state heads and the meeting with representatives of observing countries, in which issues linked to "regional security, multilateralism and sustainable development will be addressed."
The meeting will take place before the Military Parade of September 3, in Beijing, in celebration of the 80th anniversary of the end of World War II in the Pacific, to which Putin will watch.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:18:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan and South Korea want to face commercial and security changes together</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/japao-e-coreia-do-sul-querem-enfrentar-juntos-mudancas-comerciais-e-de-seguranca/</link><description>The leaders of Japan and South Korea yesterday agreed to strengthen cooperation to face rapid changes in business and security matters, which concern the two Asian countries.
The objective was defined in Tokyo during a summit between Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba, and South Korean President Lee Jae-Myung, who makes the first trip abroad since taking office in June.
Ishiba and Lee promised to expand collaboration in several areas, while striving to minimize the friction caused by historical disputes, especially by the Japanese occupation of Korea between 1910 and 1945.
"Given that the international order of trade and security is volatile, I believe that the Republic of Korea [official name of South Korea] and Japan, which share similar positions in terms of values, order and ideology, must strengthen cooperation more than ever," Lee said.
Ishiba said it is necessary to have political consistency, even when "difficult issues" persist between the two countries.
It also advocated the importance of strengthening cooperation with the United States, the common ally in a region where China seeks hegemony. "Peace and stability will not come to less than active efforts, and this is even more important in such a turbulent time," said Ishiba, according to the Spanish news agency Efe.
Both reaffirmed the commitment made by previous administrations to reach the complete denuclearization of North Korea. They also advocated the need to cooperate to face commercial uncertainties, in a veiled reference to Washington's current aggressive tariff policy.
Filled
The conversations between Ishiba and Lee lasted about two hours, and began with a restricted meeting at Kantei, the Japanese government headquarters, followed by a wide meeting and a joint press conference.
Ishiba settled with Ishiba's decision to visit Japan before traveling to the United States, where he will meet with President Donald Trump in Washington on Sunday.
"It is extremely encouraging that its first visit to Japan since taking office has been in such a complex strategic environment," he said.
The two leaders agreed to develop bilateral relations in the light of the principles of the normalization of diplomatic relations between Japan and South Korea in 1965, and create a joint organ to deal with common issues.
Among them, they referred to regional revitalization, the reduction of birth, aging and the decline of the population, agriculture, disaster prevention and the promotion of new alternative energies such as hydrogen and ammonia, and technologies such as artificial intelligence.
They also agreed to extend a visa program that allows you to work during temporary stays to finance the trip, in order to intensify the exchange of people between countries.
Ishiba and Lee plan to publish the results of the summit, the first joint statement of this type between a Japanese prime minister and a 17-year South Korean president. Yesterday's meeting was the second between Ishiba and Lee, who gathered in June in Canada, on the sidelines of the G7 summit, to which South Korea was invited.
Lee will meet with Trump at a time when doubts persist about the new bilateral tariff pact, on which both governments have disclosed contradictory messages, and the course of the strategy in relation to North Korea.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:16:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | China says "separatism" is "condemned to failure"</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/taiwan-china-diz-que-separatismo-esta-condenado-ao-fracasso/</link><description>The failed attempt to dismiss seven deputies of the opposition of Taiwan demonstrates that the "separatism" favorable to the "independence" of the island "goes against the will of the people and is condemned to failure," the Chinese government said yesterday.
Hundreds of thousands of Taiwanese came to the polls on Saturday to vote for the removal of seven Kuomintang deputies (KMT), the main Taiwan opposition party, under the second lap of a revocation referendum held in the territory.
According to data from the Central Electoral Commission, none of the seven proposals for dismissal reached the minimum limit of 25 percent of the favorable votes in the respective district, nor was it able to gather more positive than negative votes.
The vote was part of the second round of a referendum designed to dismiss 39 of the 39 KMT legislators elected by direct vote in January 2024.
In the first lap, held on July 26, none of the 24 dismissal initiatives prospered, which represented a hard setback for the Progressive Democratic Party (PDP) in power, which sought to recover the control of a KMT -dominated parliament and the minority Popular Party of Taiwan (PPT).
"After the first round of the vote, on July 26, the people of Taiwan again say" no "to the malicious political farce of the PDP," Chinese Executive Executive's Taiwan Office of the Taiwan Cabinet said yesterday in statements collected by the Xinhua agency.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:15:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Bloomberg | Forced journalist to leave Hong Kong</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/bloomberg-jornalista-forcada-a-sair-de-hong-kong/</link><description>A journalist who works in Hong Kong for the American news agency Bloomberg News announced Saturday that he will have to leave Chinese territory after authorities refused to renew his visa.
“After six years covering Hong Kong, and eight -month -old pregnant, I am very sad to leave my colleagues, my friends and the place I considered my home,” wrote Rebecca Choong Wilkins, responsible for coverage of Asian policy and economy at the Economics Specialized News Agency.
Contacted by AFP, Hong Kong immigration services have responded that they do not comment on individual cases, adding that "they act in accordance with the laws and policies in force."
Bloomberg, through a spokesman, said he did not want to "comment in detail the situation", however, ensuring "fully supporting" the journalist and being "working through the right ways to try to solve the problem."
The Hong Kong Foreign Press Club has denounced what has considered an unjustified decision of the authorities, which, according to the organization, "reinforces widespread concerns about the erosion of press freedom" in the former British colony.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:13:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Rare Lands | Beijing reinforces production and export control</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/25/terras-raras-pequim-reforca-controlo-da-producao-e-exportacao/</link><description>The government has indicated new rules for the extraction, casting and separation of rare land to ensure the correct use of precious minerals
 
China, the world's leading rare land supplier, has issued a set of “provisional” standards to reinforce control over their extraction, casting and separation in a context of tensions by supplying strategic minerals, the Xinhua agency said.
The regulations, released last Friday, were jointly driven by the Chinese Ministry of Information Industry and Technology, the National Development and Reform Commission and the Ministry of Natural Resources, specified the official agency.
Under the new normative framework, the authorities will set “annual quotas” to the extraction, casting and separation of rare land, which will later be attributed to corresponding companies, taking into account factors such as “economic development”, national reserves of these minerals and “market demand”.
Companies must carry out the activities of extraction, foundry and separation “within the limits of the approved quotas” and “strictly comply with administrative laws and regulations, indicated Xinhua.
The new rules also state that rare land producers should maintain “accurate records” of product flows and load data in a tracking information system of these minerals.
In statements collected by the Global Times newspaper, Zhou Mi, lead researcher at the Chinese Academy of International Trade and Economic Cooperation, pointed out that the tracking system ensures that resources "are not used in areas that may threaten national security."
"In other words, while its use is safe and fulfilling the rules, exportation and trade of rare land products will not be harmed," said the expert.
Rich nature
The rare elements are a set of sixteen chemical elements that are usually united in nature: the scand to the fifteen elements of the lantnic group (Lantânio, Cerius, Praseodim, Neodimio, Promécio, Samarius, Europe, Gadolinium, Terbian, Display, Holmium, Erbium, Tulio, Iérbio and lutecio).
These features, present in products such as artificial intelligence chips, electrical vehicles or guided missiles, are at the center of the trade war between the United States and China, whose government intensified export restrictions in April, alleging national security reasons.
The Asian giant has 49 percent of the rare lands of the planet - about 44 million tons - and controls more than 70 percent of world production, especially through the exploration of important deposits in Myanmar (formerly Burma) and almost 90 percent of their processing.</description><pubDate>2025-08-25 04:13:05</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean President reveals a plan to denuclearize North Korea</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/presidente-sul-coreano-revela-plano-para-desnuclearizar-coreia-do-norte/</link><description>South Korean President Lee Jae-Myung yesterday presented a three-phase plan for North Korea's denuclearization, a few days before the summits with the American and Japanese leaders.
"The political direction is the denuclearization of the Korean peninsula. Phase 1 is the freezing of the nuclear program and missiles of Pyongyang, phase 2 is the reduction [of these weapons] and phase 3 to denuclearization," Lee said in an interview with the Japanese Diary Yomiuri, distributed to the press by the South Korean presidential cabinet.
The leader stated that in order to create the necessary conditions, Seoul will work closely with Washington, promoting the Intercorean dialogue.
The statements were made before Lee's visit to Japan to meet the Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba on Saturday and Sunday and the bilateral meeting with US President Donald Trump on Monday in Washington.
Peace and stability in the Korean peninsula are essential not only for South Korea, but also for Japan, China and Russia, also stressed Lee. The possibility of multinational cooperation for the opening of the Arctic route, which could involve Seoul, Washington, Moscow, Tokyo and Pyongyang, was also mentioned by the new South Korean president.
Northern criticism
Observations arise a day after Kim Yo-Jong, the influential sister of the North Korean leader, directly accused Lee of promoting an “absurd dream” of Intercorean reconciliation, stressing that Pyongyang has no intention of improving bonds with Seoul.
The South Korean government expressed, in response, “deep grief”, considering the observations a misrepresentation of sincere efforts to restore confidence between the two sides. Since taking office in June, the Lee government has been trying to alleviate the tension between the two countries, namely with the dismantling of border altifacts and the suspension of advertising emissions.
Despite North Korean criticism, the fact that Kim directly mentioned Lee and the South Korean ministers in recent statements may reflect the attention with which measures made by the new South Korean government, the EFE news agency at the European Center for North Korean Studies Gabriela Bernal told EFE.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:26:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand | PM suspended presents defense before court</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/tailandia-pm-suspensa-apresenta-defesa-perante-tribunal/</link><description>The recording of a telephone call between the Thai Prime Minister and a powerful Cambodian politician compromised Paetongtarn Shinawatra, accused of lack of severe ethics
The Prime Minister of Thailand, Paetongtarn Shinawatra, who is suspended from duties due to the disclosure of an audio in which he allegedly questioned the army, appeared yesterday before the Constitutional Court to present his defense.
Paetongtarn, who turned 39 yesterday and took office just over a year ago, attended the court in northern Bang of Bangcoque, to present a testimony due to the release of a call from a call on June 18 between her and the influential Cambodian politician Hun Sen, who published audio on the social network Facebook.
During yesterday's hearing, the testimony of the Secretary-General of the National Security Council, Chatchai Bangchuad, was also planned.
In the audio of about 17 minutes, the prime minister referred to Hun Sen as "uncle", in respect of respect, and classified as "opponent" Lieutenant General Boonsin Phadklang, who directs a Thai military command, positioned on the border with Cambodia.
Paetongtarn, who admitted that the voice played on Facebook is his, publicly apologized for the audio, and explained that, with which he said, he tried to reduce the border tension between the two countries, which had increased since late March, after a brief confrontation between the armies, in which a Cambodian soldier died.
Layoffs and suspensions
The content of the dialogue led the second party with the highest representation in the government coalition, the conservative Bhumjaithai, to abandon the executive, and a group of senators to ask the Constitutional Court to analyze whether the ruler had committed a “serious ethical lack” when questioning the military command.
On July 1, the Judges of the Constitutional Court decided to temporarily suspend the Prime Minister for the Exercise of Functions while analyzing the case, which may result in dismissal, a decision that is scheduled for Friday next week.
After weeks of tension between the two countries, on July 24, an armed confrontation between the armies of Thailand and Cambodia, which lasted five days and cost at least 44 people out of the border, lasted.
Paetongtarn's hearing takes place a day before his father, former Prime Minister Thaksin Shinawatra, appears before another Bangkok Court to hear the decision of a case in which he is argued for an alleged crime of mashed masters, punishable with up to 15 years in prison.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:24:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Xi asks for unity in Tibeta after Dalai Lama announces that he will appoint successor</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/22/xi-pede-unidade-no-tibete-apos-dalai-lama-anunciar-que-vai-nomear-sucessor/</link><description>The Chinese president called for a unit in Lhasa, the capital of Tibeta, where the 60th anniversary of the creation of this autonomous region was signaled, six years after the Dalai Lama watched in India following a failed revolt.
Xi Jinping's unusual visit to Tibet is marked by political symbolism, when it occurs after the 14th Dalai Lama reaffirmed that only the Gaden Phodrang Foundation founded by him has the authority to recognize the future reincarnation of the spiritual leader.
Beijing, for his part, insists that Dalai Lama's successor "must be sought inside China and receive the approval of the central government." Xi exhorted on Wednesday the authorities of the region to build a tibet “united, prosperous, civilized, harmonious and beautiful”, according to state news agency Xinhua.
Not to mention Dalai Lama directly, Xi added that “stability must be guaranteed” and “Tibetan Buddhism must be guided in its adaptation to socialist society”, stressing “the importance of maintaining the leadership of the Chinese Communist Party [CCP]” in the region.
However, China's main political counselor, Wang Huning, stressed yesterday in a commemorative ceremony, with the presence of Xi, that Tibeth entered the “best period of development”.
The official stressed the “important national projects and policies that transformed the region”, leading “an improvement of life standards and a vibrant and modern socialist tibet”. "This fully demonstrates the strong leadership of the CCP and the important political advantages of our socialist system," he added.
Visiting
Xi arrived at Tibet on Wednesday, on the second visit as head of state, to attend commemorative events. Images transmitted today by state station CCTV showed dozens of people in Potala Palace Square raising a giant Chinese flag, as well as the insignia of the CCP and XI portraits.
Xi Jinping's first visit to Tibet as President took place in 2021, on the occasion of the 70th anniversary of Beijing's so -called “peaceful liberation”, when, after the entry of the communist troops, the 17 points agreement was signed, sealing the incorporation of the region in the Popular Republic of China.
The anniversary that is now celebrated celebrates the creation of the Tibet Autonomous Region in 1965. The arrival of XI coincides with a visit this week, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi, the New Delhi, where the two parts pledged to improve relationships after the border confrontations of 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-08-22 00:23:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Anabela Santiago, Academic: “China is a reformist and moderate”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/anabela-santiago-academica-a-china-e-reformista-e-moderada/</link><description>Anabela Santiago has just defended at the University of Aveiro the doctoral thesis that analyzes how China has been positioned in recent decades as an important actor in the “global health governance”. Today, Beijing seeks “alternative mechanisms” of cooperation in the “global south” and tries to build an alternative model to the World Health Organization
 
 
Let's start with the concept of Global Health Governance (GGS). Is this a more contemporary concept or relating to the post-war period and the Foundation of the World Health Organization (WHO)? What have been the main actors of this governance until China's growth?
GGS is a concept whose prominence and relevance have grown significantly in the 21st century, largely driven by economic globalization and worldwide interconnection. Although global health has always transcended national borders, demanding multidisciplinary approaches and international cooperation, only from the 1990s it was made greater awareness of it. Historically, GGS has been predominantly influenced by western powers and neoliberal values. The main actors of this governance, until China's growth, were historically marked by interventions of entities such as WHO and non-governmental, predominantly American and European organizations.
One of the findings of its doctoral thesis is that China has been progressively positioning itself in this leadership. This position started specifically when and why?
Yes, China has been progressively positioned as a relief actor in the evolution of the GG system. Although it is not possible to point out an exact date of start, China has evolved from a relatively isolated country to a main actor in global political, economic and technological arenas. Its growing economic and political influence also represents a change in GGS's historical dynamics, and in the 1960s China tried to play a humanitarian health care role in neighboring countries and Africa. The thesis points out that China's experience can be seen as an example of what is achievable when a state chooses its own way rather than a pre-established model, aligning itself with the 21st century prediction as the "century of Asia."
Did the pandemic years influence this position? How?
Covid-19 pandemic highlighted the need for global health cooperation, as well as the potential consequences of the failure to prioritize global health. The thesis explores the evolution of the Health Silk Route before and after the pandemic, indicating that the pandemic years allowed greater awareness of the need for instruments such as the Health Silk Route as the most effective cooperation platforms among nations. Although not detailed in this specific section, it is implicit that the pandemic intensified China's performance in health diplomacy and health development assistance.
Looking at the internal reforms that China has carried out in the health area, which highlights as the most important?
I approach, in the thesis, the reforms of the China Health System and I point out that the Chinese governance model is a unique combination of state -oriented economic reforms and development by the state, incorporating elements of neoliberalism and authoritarianism into political issues in general, and the health sector is nothing different from the rest. One of China's mentioned contributions, recognized by WHO, is its primary health care model based on the recognized good practice of “barefoot doctors” (barefoot doctors). In addition, the thesis analyzes the main reform policies and their progress and challenges in the period 2009-2018, which comprise the reforms of primary health care, hospital and pharmaceutical reform. The “Healthy China 2030” program is also an important and ambitious reference of China's domestic reforms in health, also encompassing social determinants.
Is Beijing's intention to create an alternative entity to WHO, or simply create an alternative movement that can coexist with WHO, in the context of the relationship with the global south? How could this work?
The thesis suggests that China adopts a "dual approach": while integrating in existing global structures, forging simultaneously alternative paths, particularly through regional alliances such as BRICS and partnerships with Global South. This indicates an intention to create an alternative movement that can coexist and complement the role of WHO, rather than a direct alternative entity. China demonstrates a clear commitment to align the objectives of the “Belt and Road” initiative with the united nations sustainable development objectives, showing their willingness to present these initiatives as complements to the existing cooperation mechanisms in the international liberal order. President Xi Jinping's view of a “future community shared for humanity”, which includes the notion of a “global health community for all”, also points to a new perspective in international cooperation.
Traditional Chinese Masks, Vaccines and Medicine (MTC): What are China's products or instruments to position itself as an increasingly global actor in GGS?
The thesis points out that China is an indispensable provider of global public health, essential for the product supply chain, such as masks and vaccines. The MTC is also mentioned as one of China's great contributions to global health governance, with its chinese herbal treatments, some of which already recognized by WHO in 2017. In addition, Chinese medical assistance and medical teams sent to other regions of the globe are important instruments of Chinese health diplomacy.
In creating an alternative movement or reality to WHO, China may be taking advantage of the lack of full representativeness in the same WHO, or gaps in its operation?
The thesis does not address directly whether China is taking advantage of a lack of full representativeness in WHO or gaps in its operation. However, it emphasizes that the work aims to fill a gap in scientific knowledge in relation to the paradigm of health governance from a non-western and liberal perspective, emphasizing China as an actor of the global south. This suggests that China seeks to strengthen alternative models that can offer more personalized health challenges, different from those defended by Western countries, positioning itself as a moderate reformist actor.
How has the European Union (EU) foreign policy in relation to China affecting or influenced this position of the country in global health governance?
In the thesis, the fourth publication, entitled "Challenges on the European Union-China Cooperation in Higher Education from" People-To-People Dialogue ’Perspective: The Case of Health-Related Joint Projects," explores cooperation in higher education, in particular that includes health-related projects. Therefore, despite the strategic and economic dialogue, the deterioration of UE-china bilateral relations intensified, with the commission to assume a decline of enthusiasm due to “China's countermeasures to EU human rights sanctions, economic coercion and commercial measures against the single market, and the positioning of China in the war in Ukraine”. Although challenges and tensions are recognized, cooperation in higher education, including health projects, is seen as part of a broader picture of strategic partnership between EU and China. However, it is evident that there is no long tradition of health cooperation between EU and China in higher education, and that there are few joint projects compared to the general panorama. It is suggested that both EU and China should make more efforts to align medical study curricula and promote more joint research in areas related to health, infectious diseases, among others.
In the Trump 2.0 era, and without pandemic, what could be China's role in global health governance?
Although the thesis is published this year, it focuses on the preceding period and includes the pandemic, where it does not speculate directly on a future scenario of “Trump 2.0” without pandemic. However, the thesis argues that China is not just a participant, but a moderate reformist force in the formation of global health standards. Regardless of future political scenarios, their growing economic and political influence, strategic health diplomacy, internal reforms and initiatives such as the Health Silk Route will continue to shape their role in global health governance. The view of a “global health community for all” also remains a guiding principle for China's efforts.
Does this power of China in GGS verify more with bilateral or multilateral agreements?
The thesis suggests that China's power in global health governance manifests itself through both bilateral and multilateral agreements, but with a growing emphasis on certain forms of cooperation that strengthen their role in the global south and through alternative mechanisms. Although the thesis does not explicitly quantify the predominance between bilateral and multilateral, the focus on regional alliances (BRICS) and partnerships with the Global South (which often involve bilateral agreements and group cooperation initiatives) and the Health Silk Route indicate a hybrid approach.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 23:46:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Forum | Secretary-General says it has never discussed widening to Hispanic countries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/forum-macau-secretario-geral-diz-que-nunca-se-discutiu-alargamento/</link><description>In an interview with Lusa agency, the secretary general of the Macau Forum, Ji Xianzheng, assured that “never discussed” the widening of action to Hispanic countries, but that to realize the will already stated by the government of Sam Hou Fai will have to be the authorities to decide a new direction to the cooperation strategy
 
The Secretary-General of the Macau Forum stated that the institution “never discussed” the creation of an entity to extend to Hispanic countries to promote economic cooperation similar to those who provide the connection between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
“Within the Macao Forum, we have never discussed this topic,” said the Forum Secretary-General for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries Ji Xianzheng.
The official acknowledged that, "in society, there were some conversations to discuss or address the possibility of promoting more contact and cooperation with Spanish -language countries, but at the Forum level we have never addressed this theme."
The Macao executive announced in mid -April the intention of creating a center to promote economic services between China and the Portuguese and Spanish languages ​​in the neighboring special Economic Zone of Hengqin.
The idea is to provide companies in Hispanic countries services in the “linguistic, legal, fiscal, verification of compliance with norms, formation, arbitration and mediation”, according to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong.
Days earlier, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, had also announced the intention of “promoting exchange and cooperation” through Macao, between China and the universe of Spanish -speaking countries.
Although Macau wants to widen focus to Castilian -speaking countries, “the forum will remain the forum for China and Lusophony countries,” said Ji Xianzheng. The secretary general clarified that the institution that directs "can contribute contributions to the greater opening of Macao in international cooperation", as is the intention announced by the new government of MSAR.
Complementary forum
Personally, the secretary general has ensured that he had “pleasing to work with all parties,” but stressed that this is a “decision that is up to central governments to make” and that the forum was never contacted in this regard.
"Yes, I worked in Latin America, Spain, nine years in Madrid and Caracas. But this is not a decision of personal interest, it is up to politicians to make the decision," he said, explaining that the idea will be to promote the relationship between Macao and Brazil and then to other Latin American countries, as well as expanding the relationship with Portugal to Spain.
"There is no limit. The Macao Forum is complementary. It does not restrict any promotion of the cooperation of the other parts," he said.
According to the Macao Government Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai admitted on June 21 that he postponed a trip to Portugal, scheduled for July, and should also pass through Spain and the European Union headquarters in Brussels.
Bad interpretations
In the same interview with Lusa, the secretary general of the Macao Forum imputed to national governments the responsibility for conducting economic development and cooperation policies, stressing that the institution “has no investment projects”.
Ji Xianzheng attributes criticism to the Macao Forum to an wrong interpretation regarding the body's mission. "The forum is a mechanism of cooperation between central governments. Many people think it is to the secretariat that it is up to the execution of policies, but we have a limited number of people," added Ji.
"The secretariat has no investment projects, it is a mechanism for preparing the ministerial conference, connecting with governments, not a promotion agency. It has not been thought of, connects with the promotion agencies. We are four people sent by China and one delegate for each country," he said.
At the last ministerial conference, in April 2024, then Portuguese Economy Minister Pedro Reis argued that the Portuguese Language China-Parais Cooperation and Development Fund should bet more on small and medium enterprises (SMEs).
The Cooperation Fund was created in 2013 by the China Development Bank and the Macao Industrial and Commercial Development Fund, with a thousand million dollars, of which about 60 percent have already been invested, according to the secretary general.
Action plans
Ji Xianzheng has admitted that SMEs are "a difficult theme for any government" and that "international cooperation for the promotion of development and cooperation of small and medium enterprises is even more difficult. It is a theme that is being debated in the world worldwide." But admitted, "here, little."
"But it is stipulated in the action plan [2024-2026]. It is up to central governments and commerce chambers, promotion agents, to work together to do this. The secretariat assumes responsibility as authorized by the central governments, specifically, in the activities program," he said.
Politicians from various countries, including Portugal, Angola and Mozambique, have appealed to a change in the rules of the fund's candidacy. Current rules require, for example, that candidate projects have a minimum investment of five million dollars, and the fund only covers 20 percent of total investment, referring the rest to governments or companies.
Ji Xianzheng said the new fund's new direction "is committed to promoting a broader investment, with better coverage for all forum countries, [relatively] to projects that have a strategic or significant impact on the socioeconomic development of participating countries."
According to the secretary general, "the terms of application [of the rules of access to the background] will be more flexible and the forms of application will also be more diverse." “Instead of being just direct investment, they are also studying ways to apply the fund, in cooperation with other funds or with other financial institutions,” he gave as an example.
"This fund has an operation according to market rules. It is not a humanitarian aid fund. Therefore, it has to guarantee the minimum return of benefit. But, on that, they are very open to study, in this case, the conditions of each project," added Ji Xianzheng, but to give examples of "flexibilization of the rules."
Regarding the approximation of the China universe and countries of the Iberian Peninsula, already cemented in official speeches, economist Maria Fernanda Ilhéu, president of the Seda's New Route Association, told HM, earlier this month, that this intention is “very objective and pragmatic and can be summarized to the Macao economy diversification project, for which companies and investors are not only in Macao, but also from Macao, but also from Macao, but also from countries, but countries Portuguese Language ”.
"But the fact is that companies and institutions from Portuguese-speaking countries are not being effective in responding to this need for Macao. Therefore, widening companies and Spanish-speaking institutions this invitation to cooperation seems logical to me," the economist said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Isabel Rio Novo, author of the biography of Luís de Camões: “Time in Macau was of tranquility”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/26/isabel-rio-novo-autora-da-biografia-de-luis-de-camoes-tempo-em-macau-foi-de-tranquilidade/</link><description>It will be launched tomorrow, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, the biography of Luís de Camões, by Isabel Rio Novo. In an interview with HM, the author unravels some secrets about the poet's life in Macau, a period of relative calm in the middle of a almost always turbulent life
 
Why did you decide to get in the writing of another biography of Camões?
It is true that Luis Vaz de Camões has been biographed many times over 500 years. However, 50 years ago there was no biography about him. From my point of view and the editor, Camões deserved a more current biography that revised all kinds of prejudices, seeking known sources, the uncovered information research and where the rereading of all previous works were rereading. This biography is not only a summary, but also the reinterpretation of what has been known, but which had rarely been related. The book also brings some new data with some documentation that was discovered.
How was your relationship with the writing of Camões born?
I fell in love and went to those young readers who was not tormented with Camões. On the contrary, I liked it soon and let myself be seduced by Camões Lyric. I am from the areas of comparative literature and history, and in this sense I always understood the dimension and importance of the work of Camões.
And what are they?
It is a work and an author of its time and its time, which was extraordinary, with the Renaissance, Humanism and the travels of navigation. But at the same time, it is a work that is the product of an outstanding literary genius, one that we can tell a handful in the history of universal literature.
What camões we find in this biography?
I tried to go to the bottom, remove layers of the meaning that these 500 years were adding to Camões, in the sense that each season read its Camões and produced its interpretation. I wanted to discover the substrate, the man of flesh and bone he lived and wrote 500 years ago.
He was a man suffered, with many financial difficulties.
He was a man with a complex and difficult relationship with reality, not only of his time, but also with reality [itself]. The theme of the time, the disconcerting of the world, how society seems to work instead of what should work, being a literary topic of the Renaissance, it was something Camões felt personal and genuinely.
How?
He lived a series of disagreements, of extreme experiences. Suffice it to say that you have been stuck several times and for various reasons. He made great trips at a time when these were absolutely risky, long, and complicated enterprises. Camões was involved in military expeditions, and almost all his life was soldered. But this set of experiences allowed him to be almost everything that someone could be at the time he lived.
He was one of the most traveled authors of the time, having been in Brazil, Goa…
Yes. Even the connection to Macau, which is contested by some scholars, but not by me… I am persuaded, given the existing documentation and indirect testimonies, which Camões passed through China with the position of Dead and Missing Provider. When this happened, albeit very incipiently, the Portuguese establishment in China, which was already Macao. It is not known whether Camões held this position assigned to him by Viceroy D. Francisco Coutinho, if he was exactly assigned to be a provider during the trip, or a provider at Macao's establishment. But what he knew from China was surely this little warehouse that Portugal had achieved, at a lot of cost, with great difficulty and after many attempts to obtain in China.
What did a deceased provider?
Whenever a Portuguese died in the East, a soldier or merchant, it was necessary to ensure the rights of the heirs, the families who were normally in Portugal. The provider had to identify the deceased, his naturalness, origin and make the heirs known. He also had to keep the deceased's assets before they were stolen, auction them, keep the coins that would result in, and then take it all to Lisbon. It was a process that, if it went well, took many months, because it was necessary to send this money to the authorities of Goa who later sent him in the career from India to Lisbon.
Can we talk about a period of stability in Camões's life in Macau?
Yes. Until this appointment as a deceased provider, everything Camões knew from the East had been as a soldier. As soon as Goa [1553] arrives weeks later in a first military expedition. We know why: Not because I had some war appeal, but because only participating in expeditions earned your welding. Although everyone said that the soldiers lived very poorly, the welding was what Camões had to survive. The time lived in Macao, when he was free from soldier obligations, was a time of tranquility regarding subsistence, which was assured. He had some time and calm to continue the work with "the Lusíadas." More than that, as much as the sources allow to deduce, Camões met in Macau a phase of balance in terms of personal and loving life, as, on the return trip, he brought with him, according to the testimony of Diogo do Couto, a Chinese girl.
Dinamene.
This was the term used by the chronicler. We don't know if it would be a Chinese or Asian girl. This girl with whom Camões lived maritally was someone who liked it very much, according to the testimony of Diogo do Couto. But Dinamene would certainly not be her name, as it was a mythological name that, by the way, Camões used in her lyric, even before she boarded the East. Chinese girls with whom soldiers and merchants in Macao lived amanced were baptized and received a Christian name. Therefore, Dinamene would even have a Christian and Portuguese name. But as we do not know her name, and if we are aware that we use a kind of metaphor, we can call it Dinamene.
She dies later on a trip and makes Camões very shaken.
On Macao's return trip to Goa, probably at the end of his mandate as a provider, Camões suffers the celebrated wreck, in which he loses the personal assets he had ease, including the assets of the deceased that he was guardian, and this will bring him complications. It also suffers the loss of dynamine. The wreck went with some in the seas of China, probably by the mouth of the Mekong River.
Considers unlikely to have lost part of "the Lusíadas."
The first biographers say Camões was saved from this wreck with a board. It is not unreasonable that he managed to save the manuscript of the Lusíadas on this board. But it is also no excluding that Camões knew his poem by heart. The memory of people in the sixteenth century was different. They were very used to keeping things from memory. And we know, because the proof is obtained in the work of Camões, that it had an extraordinary memory. I have a way to prove it, of course, that Camões is one of the rare authors who knew his poem by heart.
Do you think Camões had a lower life to his true talent?
Undoubtedly. According to a too extensive set of concordant testimonies, he dies poor, even in miserable conditions, and according to an eyewitness, without having a blanket with which he covered himself. On the other hand, Camões was known to follow the publication of the Lusíadas, who were commented and read [in the poet's life time]. We have the testimony of Faria de Sousa, one of the first biographers of Camões, which says that when he passed the streets, people stop and pointed. Camões also had a figure that stood out, with a leaked eye and using a pale. By then, I would be quite sick, using crutches. But there is a set of poets, which is very unreliable that they did not know Camões, who never refer to them. There are, on the other hand, other humanists, such as Pedro Magalhães Gândavo, who from the outset praises him as the prince of Portuguese poets.
But the king gives him a tendency for deeds provided and the publication of "The Lusíadas."
This famous tendency, which should not be a big deal, because all ancient biographers say it was derisive, is attributed to him as a kind of military reform, because of the 17 years of service in the East, and not as a reward for the publication of "The Lusíadas." D. Sebastião's mercy letter, which attributes him the title of nobleman knight, had no repercussion in practice, but gave him 15 thousand reais. [The publication of “the Lusíadas”] was an additional argument [for the letter] and not the main argument. This leads us to believe that D. Sebastião will not even have read or heard “the Lusíadas”, will have received indirect information, favorable about the poem.
How did the process of editing “Os Lusíadas” occurred?
It was an event, because both the press and the books that were published a year were a very small amount. In the year in which “the Lusíadas” are published were the only work of non -religious caress [to be edited]. To fund the edition, it is more than likely that Camões had the support of a patron, probably D. Manuel de Portugal, from the Condes do Vimioso family. Getting the work was a press was a mere and complicated process, as it had to go through the prior examination of the civil authorities, the royal authority and the censorship of the Inquisition. The resident of the Holy Office does not only let the book pass, but to make an amount of almost unprecedented compliments in the license that authorizes the publication of the work. If we go to the opinions emitted by the same rear, there is no other work on which he is as compliments as it was with the epic of Camões.
In Indonesia, he befriended a slave on the island of Java.
Camões was, at least once, on the island of Ternate, Indonesia, in the archipelago of molucas, at a time when there were conflicts motivated by an extremely cruel Portuguese captain towards the king or sultan of Ternate, which originated a kind of war between the Portuguese and the places. Camões has a song that describes the island of Ternate. We do not know if it was at this time, or in another passage to the Far East, that Camões turned on to a Jaú, or Javanese, but could not be exactly from the Far East, but a freed slave who had been linked by friendship to Camões. And this is because in one of the first biographies of Camões it reads that Jaú, with the Christian name António, asked for alms at night. This freedom of movements of a slave indicates that he would probably be a freed slave. He asked for alms to Camões, for himself and the mother of Camões, with whom Camões will have lived in recent years of life.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 23:30:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the right place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
What do you talk about is economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | FR World Cup will have a new car in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/gp-taca-do-mundo-de-fr-tera-novo-carro-em-2026/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) has recently revealed some details about the future of the Regional Formula (FR), the discipline that currently gives body to the Macao Grand Prix and which, from 2026, will finally have a new monolugar - faster and safer
 
Initially baptized by FIA as F3 Regional, the now designated regional formula (FR) is above the Formula 4 Formula 4 National Competitions and FIA Championship, which, in turn, supports the FIA ​​Formula 2 Championship and Formula 1. Last year, the FIA ​​decided that this category was the one that best filed the Guide Circuit, thus ending four decades of Formula 3 Macao Award.
Last week, the regulator of world motorsport and the Italian national sports association has jointly presented the future monoligue that will compete in the European regional FIA (FREC in English) regional formula championship and will succeed the current freka. The fact that the acronym has lost the letter “A” is due to the exit of the Alpine brand as a partner and engine supplier to the championship. FRECA premiered in 2019, succeeding the Formula Renault Eurocup. In recent seasons, more than 160 pilots, representing 44 nationalities and 22 teams, participated in the championship. This category has gained importance in the FIA ​​monologene pyramid, having as old pilots former champion Andrea Kimi Antonelli, Isack Hadjar, Gabriel Bortoleto and Franco Colapinto-all of them now militate in Formula 1.
The competition will have the FIA ​​support seal and should be the largest supplier of teams and pilots for the FR World Cup of the Macao Grand Prix from next year. FIA involvement in the competition is intended to generate more revenues for it, something that may have reflexes on the price scale. The FR championships in the Americas and Japan, as well as the FIA ​​-certified trophies in the Middle East and Oceania will continue, and progressively will introduce the new car produced in Italy.
FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulayem believes this project "will create a stronger and more support for young pilots. With the full support of the FIA ​​regions and a clear progression vision, we are taking an important step to ensure the future of junior monoliga pyramid." Former Ralis pilot and today maximum leader of automobile sports, who was recently in the territory for the FIA ​​general assembly, said that “accessibility, international credibility and cost efficiency are at the center of this initiative.”
New car promises more
The new Tatuus T-326, the second-generation FR monolugar, is equipped with a 3-cylinder and 1.6 liter Toyota engine, which debits 270 horsepower and 360 Nm of torque, specially adapted and prepared by ATM-Autotechnic Motori. The T-326 represents a natural evolution of the T-318 model, the Tatuus monolugar that defined most FR championships worldwide and says goodbye to the big stages next November, during the weekend of the Macao Grand Prix. The second edition of FR's FR World Cup will continue to use the Tatuus T-318 Monolugar, motorized by a 1.75-liter Turbo Alpha Romeo block, also prepared by ATM-Autotechnic Motori, but the Italian brand has failed to manufacture.
The future car, which will use a new special tire built by Pirelli, will have a fully redesigned aerodynamic profile, shaped by the new FIA technical regulations for the category and inspired by the latest trends in the top categories of single -molding. The result is a general increase in performance, better aerodynamic efficiency and reduction of turbulence effect, which will facilitate overtaking.
Main improvements include weight reduction, optimized direction rack and magazine suspension, offering greater lightness and ease of driving. Security remains a key pillar in all Italian tatus projects, and this car is no exception. Chassis further increased its impact resistance. Crucial elements such as front and rear impact absorption structures, anti-intrusion panels and roll bar have been updated to meet the latest safety standards. In addition to safety, the cockpit is designed to maximize pilot's comfort and ergonomics, welcoming both men and women in a wider range of heights, ensuring the best conditions to compete on track.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:59:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Nürburgring Nordschleife is a new favorite stage of Chinese brands</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/01/nurburgring-nordschleife-e-novo-palco-predilecto-das-marcas-chinesas/</link><description>In the middle of the Eifel forest - in German, Eifelwald - Two cars with Chinese enrollment are parked in front of a hotel unit. The scenario appears to be intriguing at first glance, but it is not.
Nürburgring Nordschleife, in Rhineland-Palatinado, already close to the Belgium and Luxembourg border, has become the favorite stage of new Chinese auto builders to show the world that they can also measure their European, American and Asian rivals for high-performance vehicles.
Chinese automotive industry bet is strongly concentrated in NEVs - “New Energy Vehicles” - as part of the strategy for reducing pollution, reducing dependence on fossil fuels and boosting innovation in the automotive industry. China represented almost two thirds of global electric vehicle sales in 2024, and their builders, all relatively new, discuss Taco the Taco with the large traditional builders a piece of this appetizing market.
It is undisputed that the growth of sales of this type of vehicles in the world has not been accompanied at the same speed by the evolution of technology applicable to automobile sport, especially with regard to electric vehicles (EVs).
The World Formula World Championship and is the only truly global competition for electric vehicles, after the fiasco and the premature death of the FIA ​​- FIA etcouring world cup. With no alternatives to affirm their everyday products on the tracks, Chinese brands headed in weight to Nürburgring Nordschleife, known to be one of the favorite places of European car manufacturers to test high performance cars.
The “green hell”, a name given by the legendary pilot Jackie Stewart due to its difficulty and the density of the surrounding forest, is a circuit with over 20 kilometers and 170 curves, combining fast lines, technical sections and sharp unenforcement. Many return records are measured here for sports and super -sports car cars, making Nordschleife an unavoidable reference to car performance.
Chapters for History
In 2017, Nio became known to the western world when it established a record with its EP9 electric supercar. The vehicle completed a circuit of 20.8 km in 6 minutes and 45.90 seconds, becoming the fastest production car at the time to go through the famous Germanic layout.
This feat has evidenced the ability of Nio and Chinese industry to compete with brands established in the high performance cars segment. Two years later, Lynk &amp; Co, the first Chinese brand to win a race in the guide circuit, with model 03 Cyan Concept, a high performance version of the Sedan 03, reached a time back in 7 minutes and 20,143 seconds, setting a new record for four -door cars.
Brands such as Zeekr, MG and Lotus passed the old stage of the Formula 1 German Grand Prix, until, in 2024, Xiaomi arrived with a crash. With a production version of the SU7 Ultra, it registered a time of 7 minutes and 4.957 seconds, surpassing rivals such as Porsche Taycan Turbo GT and Rimac Snowra. To keep up with the sales success of your car, the electronic technology brand was even further: Last month, the Su7 Ultra Prototype, built in partnership with Prodrive, reached an impressive 6-minute and 22.091 seconds, becoming the third fastest car of all time on the circuit, behind only the Porsche 919 Hybrid and Volkswagen ID.R.R.
These results from Xiaomi had a significant impact, both in the western and home press, as well as proof of the international affirmation of an industry that wants to be an undisputed leader with regard to Nev vehicles. On the other hand, Xiaomi took the opportunity to “surf the wave” and launched in the market a special limited edition of Su7 -all -how.
More will come
Nürburgring Nordschleife is part of the Chinese auto industry vocabulary and the trend is for an even stronger presence of Chinese brands in the coming years on the German track.
"I believe it was the decision of Xiaomi that brought greater attention to the definition of records back in Nürburgring," explained Chinese journalist Bruno Qi to HM. “With a huge media influence in China and a high profile CEO like Jun Law, Xiaomi attracted a significant focus on this scenario. After Nio's success, this was another strong performance of a Nürburgring high -performance electric vehicle.”
Xiaomi, which already names a bend of the German circuit, may want to improve its time back, while other Chinese brands seek to follow the trend - even to show off on a respected and good memories.
"Brands like Yangwang (BYD's luxury brand) have also sent their models for time attempts around," says Chinese publication journalist Bec Motorsport. “I think Chinese auto builders have now found a relevant opportunity to demonstrate the capabilities of their high performance electrical platforms, and this strategy is already helping to boost sales.” Also, at the end of the day, what weighs is what is sold.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 01:14:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Carlos Barreto takes the experience of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/20/filipinas-carlos-barreto-leva-a-experiencia-de-macau/</link><description>Carlos Barreto, former racing director of the Macao de Motorcycle Grand Prix, is still active in the motorized sports of the Asian continent, more precisely in the Philippines, where he has been putting into practice the experience of more than three decades in the service of Macau Automobile and Motorcycle
 
“I was invited in 2024 to help develop National Track Motorcycle Championships-Underbone, Scooters and Superbikes-organized by Morac and Fetap,” Macau's former Macau-China General Association (AAMC) told HM. “The experience gained over three dozen years helps. I have done several motorcycle and karting championships on temporary circuits, mud and nape, then in the coloane karting, trials with local riders (motorcycles and karts) and international (karts). several motorcycle championships. ”
With a strong connection to the Macao Grand Prix, Carlos Barreto was a test director in the Karting and Motorcycle Championships between 1991 and 1996, and later, between 2004 and 2008. He was also president of the College of Sports Commissioners between 2009 and 2010. This vast experience allows him today to face this new reality in a different country, but always showed great passion for motorized sports, ease of “some aspects. that deserved more attention to the level of the tests. ” Among them, it highlights “sports regulations, the application of the rules, the dissemination of official documentation, some infrastructure equipment, as well as the structure and functional organization of the team that generates these championships, from the secretariat to track commissioners and proof direction”.
This collaboration began in November last year and, by 2024, already extended to three rounds of the championships. The contribution of Portuguese, born in Mozambique, has been significant: “The various suggestions I presented to each of the two circuits I know, the Clark International Speedway and the Racing Circuit Batangas, some have already been implemented and the rest will be resolved by the end of the year.
The competition itself is also growing: “The pandemia, in a way, delayed the development of these championships, but the number of pilots has been increasing, there are teams with financial capacity and good equipment. Clark tests sometimes come together to gather close to 80 pilots, while Batangas have about 60. The prospects are encouraging.”
Contribution to Karting
The Philippines is a country with a long tradition in Karting, dating back to the 1960s and the enthusiasm generated by Arsenio “Dodjie” Laurel, a pilot who lost his life on the Guide Circuit in 1967. The presence of Philippine Teams and Pilots in the Asian continent is common and, internally, the discipline has always followed what has been done worldwide.
“At Karting level, national tests have a local and functional structure - for years it was Akoc,” recalls Carlos Barreto, adding: “My collaboration has been a sports commissioner at two international events. I did one in 2024 and another recently, the Fifth Rok Cup Asia Philippines, organized by Kilton Motors Corporation (KMC) and performed in Clark. ”
Also there, the former director of the Macao International Kart Prize (2004-2016), the 46th SKF World Championship of CIK-Fi (2009) and the 49th CIK-CIA World Championship (2012), had the task of “auscultation of people and answering the questions that put me, and having made suggestions for improvement”.
As for the future, Carlos Barreto believes that “the seed is launched, and now it remains to be expected to grow and that the results will become visible in the medium term.”
Macao a step ahead
For the author of the book “History of Karting in Macao”, written in co -authorship with Pedro Dá Mesquita, the MSar remains a step forward with the sports organization of this nature. “Macau has a clear advantage, but it must be borne in mind that events in Macao have the precious support of government entities, while in the Philippines it is an organization without these supports,” says Carlos Barreto.
Still, the evidence in the Philippines, a country with a vast history in the motorized Southeast Asia sport, are nothing to do with what is done in the territory in terms of competitiveness. "At the event level, scooter races are often very excited and competitive, with six to eight riders fighting every lap in the first place, numerous overtaking and suspense until cutting the goal. In superbike events, they compete for ducatis and enclosures and there is always a spectacle.</description><pubDate>2025-08-20 00:55:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorsport: FIA continues to dream of a Chinese team at F1</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/15/automobilismo-fia-continua-a-sonhar-com-uma-equipa-chinesa-na-f1/</link><description>It's no secret to anyone: the International Automobile Federation (FIA) would like to have a Chinese team in the F1 World Championship. FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulaym is the first to demonstrate this will.
For the first time since 2015, F1 will receive a 11th team on the starting grid next season, with Cadillac's entry, putting an end to a three-year wait since the US team presented its candidacy following the FIA ​​appeal for demonstrations of interest. As there will be a margin for a 12th team, Ben Suulayem is willing to launch a new process of manifestation of interest, making it clear that an application from China would be welcome.
The entry of a Chinese team would be aligned with F1's strategic efforts to expand its presence in key markets. China's Grand Prix has recently renewed its contract by 2030, consolidating the country's role in the long -term view of the sport.
"We have a 11th team [Cadillac]. I believe we should analyze the performance of this 11th team and then if there is a Chinese [candidacy]-and I will now speak on behalf of Fom [Formula One Management]-they will approve it, because it is about sustaining the business," said the FIA ​​president in a joint interview with several journalists from the automobile sector.
Ben Suulayem made it clear that there is no urgent need to have a 12th team. However, given F1's upward trajectory in recent years, the addition of another team to the starting grid, especially one from China, would further increase the call of the sport in the largest business market on the planet. "If there is a team from China, let's say, and the first to approve - and I'm 100% sure that it will approve it - would no longer make money with China's entry? I believe yes," he said.
A huge market for exploring
The Chinese automotive market is incomparable, producing more than 30 million vehicles a year - more than the United States of America, Japan and India together. In addition, China has contributed to the increase in the fan base in sports, with over 150 million fans and more than 1 million new followers on Chinese social networks, increasing the total to 4.3 million. F1 fan segmentation analysis itself has revealed that more than half of fans in the country have started following the sport in the last four years. Interestingly, the audience is younger than the average F1 supporters and more diverse, with a 50% female demography.
For Ben Sulayem, it is more than just increasing the number of teams: it is to unite the main global markets under the F1 flag, because the number of Chinese sponsors and partners in the “Queen Class” of motor sport is currently limited, boiling down to the official Aston Martin Content Creation Partner, and Sauber's Sensetime. The presence of the Chinese brand Yili, which in the meantime came out, and the Sensetime in the Sauber universe was undoubtedly linked to the fact that Zhou Guanyu, the first full -time Chinese driver at F1, running the Swiss team at the time the agreements were signed.

Geely in pole-position
The dream of a Chinese team may still be in an embryonic phase, but with the support of the president of FIA and the growing focus of the sport in China, the view of a Chinese brand on F1's starting grids may be getting closer to reality. A Chinese brand like Geely could naturally fit into F1, taking into account its global presence and the fact that it stops international brands reputed such as Volvo or Lotus, appearances as a shareholder at Aston Martin and Mercedes-Benz Group, and Joint Ventures with Renault.
It is also worth mentioning that, recently, Lotus Cars, owned by Geely, recovered the name Team Lotus, bringing together its competition programs with official support, partner teams, lotus coup championships and drivers development programs. According to the company, the Renaissance of Team Lotus "means our commitment to global competition and the culture of motorized sport." For now, this is limited to GT cars, but one cannot help but imagine where it may evolve in the future.
Lotus Group has been the property of Geely since 2017. Team Lotus team was a constant presence in Formula 1 between 1954 and 1994, and there were some attempts to reactivate the name linked to their historic past in F1, attempts that ended just over nine years ago. In addition to the Lotus Sports Program and others of regional or national work, Geely is also present in Auto Sport with Lynk &amp; Co, at FIA TCR World Tour, and through its partnership with Renault, as a engine supplier, in the Chinese F4 Championship.</description><pubDate>2025-08-15 16:34:43</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA has already defined what the F4 World Cup will be like</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/25/gp-fia-ja-definiu-como-sera-a-taca-do-mundo-de-f4/</link><description>The Macao Grand Prix hosts the first edition of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup, between November 13 and 16 this year. The International Automobile Federation has published the Sports Regulation, which reveals some details about what will be the latest cup in the world integrated into the 72nd Macau Grand Program
 
Registration for the Formula 4 Macao Race - Formula 4 World Cup of the International Automobile Federation (FIA) is open until July 30, and FIA is the selection of the pilots who will participate. FIA responsible will have been pre-selected by the best Formula 4 national championship riders, also encouraging all the pilots interested in directly contacting the FIA ​​and providing details of their sports history to be considered.
The final list of twenty pilots will be confirmed through an official invitation letter, taking into account the current classification of the pilots in the respective championships. The final selection should only be made public in mid -October, as is tradition in the guide circuit test.
At a time when behind the scenes, it is spoken of the possibility of increasing the minimum age of formula 4 to 16 years, the sports regulation stipulates that all pilots must be at least 15 years old, and the birthday is binding. An inscribed pilot may not have participated in more than two races of a championship with any type of monolugar that has been conceived and/or built to achieve a power-to-weight ratio of less than 3.0 kg/hp, which prevents participation in this riders running regional formula seasons or Formula 3.
The sports regulation does not specify technical details, but in previous communications, the FIA ​​had already confirmed that Mintimes - organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship - will be the “unique operator” of the race, together with FFSA (Fédération Française Du Sport Automobile (FFSA), responsible for the world's cup technical support. In practice, all competitors will use Mygale M21-F4 singlesules, recently re-baptized as Ligier JS F422.
These formulas, equipped with 1.3 -liter Turbo Renault engines, will be rented to teams from the interior of China and operated by a single technical team - the same that organizes the French F4 Championship. Pirelli will be the exclusive tire supplier, as is the case with the Macao Grand Prix of Regional Formula and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
Although the official time of the event has not yet been released, it is known that the World Cup will feature a qualification race played over 8 laps, or at most 60 minutes, most likely on Saturday. The main race will be held on Sunday, with 10 laps or, equally, a maximum of 60 minutes. Prior to that, a 40 -minute free training session will take place, followed by a qualification session with the same duration.
PATACA AND POINTS
About 350,000 patacas in monetary awards will be distributed to the competitors present in this first cup of the world, with the winner of the main race to raise eight thousand US dollars. As a curiosity, all participants will receive three hundred dollars of participation-the same value attributed to the pole-position of Saturday's qualification race and the rider who reaches the highest tip speed during the event.
More important than the monetary awards, the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup winner on the streets of Macau will win two points for the super license - points that may be decisive to access the restricted Formula 1 world. The winner will also be forced to attend the FIA ​​awards ceremony, which will take place on December 12 in Tashkentão, USBekistan.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 05:01:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Lamborghini | Charles Leong returns to the Academy of Young Pilots</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/20/lamborghini-charles-leong-regressa-a-academia-de-jovens-pilotos/</link><description>The Lamborghini Squadra Corso, the Automobili Lamborghini competition division, will give Macau pilot a new opportunity for Macao Charles Leong Hon Chio, who was again selected to join the Italian -brand prestigious youth academy, the “Young Driver Program”
 
Charles Leong, who participates for the second year in a row in the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia, by SJM team Theodore Racing, currently leads the Pro category, with four wins in six races already played. This weekend, the territory pilot travels to South Korea to compete in the fourth race of the Sant'Agata Bolognese builder's Asian competition season, a small locality in the Emilia-Romanha region in northern Italy, between Modena and Bologna.
In a statement, the transalpina brand made known that, in all, selodes were pre-selected pilots of the various Super Trofeo championships and five of the various international GT3 championships, including Portuguese Rodrigo Testa, for the annual Lamborghini Squadra Corso program, which focuses on both track and outside performance. The twenty -one pilots will be accompanied and evaluated throughout the season, with specific analysis of their progression, consistency, experience, professionalism and ability to provide technical feedback. In addition, five additional pilots are part of Lamborghini's young professional pilots, receiving direct support from the factory in Sant'Agata Bolognese and Scola Federale ACI Sport, an entity managed by the Italian Federation.
The big news for the 2025 edition of the Young Driver Program is the selection process: it failed to settle only in age criteria, focusing on the most impressive pilots of the first two rounds of the year, based on a classification coefficient covering the three continental championships. The pilots were evaluated by Scoola Federale ACI-Sport chief instructor Niki Cadei, in collaboration with YDP consultants and official Lamborghini drivers Andrea Caldarelli (North America), who has already competed at the Macao Grand Prix, and Marco Mapelli (Europe and Asia), taking into account several performance indicators.
The results of qualification training and racing are thoroughly analyzed, such as track conduct, the pilot's post-end reports and the technical feedback provided to engineers and Squadra corse's technical team. The average score determines the final list of pilots selected for the decisive phase. A group of these young pilots will participate in a dedicated training camp at Lamborghini headquarters in Sant'Agata Bolognese, as well as at the final selection session in Misano. The best of the session will then receive support from Lamborghini Squadra Corso for the 2026 season.
Future is played in Italy
Among Super Trofeo Junior pilots, ten compete in the European series, while the rest come from the American and Asian championships. In addition to Macao's 24 -year -old pilot in Asian representation, Lamborghini also chose Singapore's Ethan Brown and Ireland's Alex Denning, which this year shares the steering wheel with Charles Leong to join this program.
Charles Leong will be evaluated throughout the season, and the final selection - whether or not to integrate Lamborghini's youth professional riders program - will be made in November at the Italian circuit of Misano, after the traditional closing of the Season of the various Super Trofeo, during the Lamborghini world endings. It is recalled that the winner of the Macao Formula 4 Grand Prix in 2020 and 2021 was part of this program last year, but was not selected. At the time, the final assessment took place at the Jerez circuit in Spain - an unknown layout, unlike his opponents.</description><pubDate>2025-07-20 15:23:35</pubDate></item></channel></rss>