<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Nissan | Cuts of another 10,000 jobs around the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/nissan-cortes-de-mais-10-mil-empregos-em-todo-o-mundo/</link><description>Nissan automotive construction will suppress more than 10,000 jobs around the world, in addition to the nine thousand already announced in November, several Japanese social communication agencies yesterday reported. According to NHK television, the approximately 19,000 workers who will be dismissed are about 15 percent of the Japanese company's workforce.
The automobile group was deemed to confirm this information, which was also released by the Diário Económico Nikkei. Nissan, in which the French group Renault holds a 35 percent participation, is expected to publish on Tuesday the results for fiscal year of 2024-2025 finished in March.
Nissan is expected to announce a record annual loss in a context of restructuring the company and after the application of more tariffs by the United States. By the end of April, the automotive group had already foreseen net losses between 700 and 750 billion yen (between 4.32 and 4.62 billion euros) in the fiscal year of 2024-2025, about nine times more than it foresaw in February.
The damage is explained, in particular, “by the costs associated with the ongoing relaunch plan,” said the automotive builder at the end of April.
Given the persistence of the slowdown of sales in their main markets - the American and the Chinese - Nissan announced in early November that it intended to suppress 9,000 jobs worldwide and reduce its production capacity by 20 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:38:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Transport | Song Pek Kei requires improvement of service on holidays</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/transportes-song-pek-kei-exige-melhoria-do-servico-nos-feriados/</link><description>Representative Song Pek Kei brokered the executive about the need to improve the public transport service on holidays, namely with regard to buses and taxis.
The deputy, representative of the community of Fujian, recalled that during the golden work week, May 1st, there were great gatherings of people at bus stops at the various border stations of Macao and the city's sights, even if companies have provided the largest transportation offer, with more careers.
“During the holidays, with the increase in the number of tourists, the government can increase the frequency of buses, so that there is a better response in the peak period and ensures a greater balance between supply and demand from residents and tourists?” Song Pek Kei.
The deputy also asks the authorities to reinforce the combat of tariff abuse by taxi drivers on holidays, as well as disseminating the results of a study elaborated on the future increase in the number of taxis in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:44:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau maintains shipping by air to the United States</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/macau-mantem-envio-de-encomendas-por-via-aerea-para-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Macau Post Office Director told Lusa yesterday that, unlike neighboring Hong Kong, the region kept ordering orders to the United States (USA), but only by air. On May 2, the US government eliminated the exemption of customs rights on small orders from mainland China and Hong Kong, such as those sent by the giants of Electronic Trade Shein and Temu.
"In practice, now Macau is not included and the mail [which] goes to the United States is walking, except maritime. The rest, we keep normal," said Derby Lau Wai Meng. The Director of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT) explained that the shipping of any goods, from sea to the US, implies a passage through Hong Kong, one of the busiest ports in the world.
That is, there is only the hypothesis of sending orders by air, confirmed Derby Lau. "This case is sensitive," admitted the leader. "I think it's better not to talk [this subject], because the best thing is not to remember us," he added.
Trump in Action
The end of the exemption of customs rights on small orders from mainland China and Hong Kong emerged in an executive order, signed by US President Donald Trump on April 2.
The document asked the US Secretary of Commerce, Howard Lutnick, to submit a report, within 90 days, if the end of the exemption should also cover Macao, "to avoid escape to these measures."
On April 16, Hong Kong's post office announced the suspension of sending orders to the United States in response to the imposition, "abusive", tariffs by US authorities.
A presidential decree issued by Donald Trump, still in the first term, in 2020, eliminated the preferential treatment granted to Hong Kong. The ancient British colony is therefore also affected by the 145 percent surcharge imposed on China.
Chinese Communist Party's main official for Hong Kong and Macao affairs and governments of both regions accused the United States of imposing tariffs in mid -April to sabotage China.
Macao Executive leader Sam Hou Fai criticized the United States for the “abusive imposition of customs taxes on all his business partners,” including China, “under various pretexts”. Yesterday, the US representative for the United States, Jamieson Greer, said Washington and Beijing will suspend the majority of customs rights and negotiate for 90 days.
In the negotiations made in Geneva, the United States and China agreed to reduce the reciprocal customs rights imposed on each other, passing Chinese imports to pay a 30 percent customs right, while US products will pay a 10 percent customs right.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:36:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Venice receives “Parallel Worlds”, from Macao, at the Architecture Biennial</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/veneza-recebe-mundos-paralelos-de-macau-na-bienal-de-arquitectura/</link><description>It was inaugurated last Thursday, in Venice, at the 19th Biennial of Architecture, the show “Parallels”, which represents Macao at the Biennial and which is a project carried out by photographer Iwan Baan with architectural students at the University of St. Joseph (USJ). The curatorship is still with Wang Shu, the last Pritzker award, and Lu Wenyu.
This is a show that reveals the coexistence of “parallel worlds” in Macao, combining “Macao urban landscape images captured by the famous humanistic architecture photographer Iwan Baan and facilities created by teachers and students from the Faculty of Architecture of the China Academy of Arts and the Faculty of Architecture and Design at the University of São José de Macao”. Thus, it is represented “the urban fabric of the city where Chinese and Western cultures, old and new styles have coexisting for over 400 years,” says a note from the Cultural Institute (IC).
There are, in this show, four “parallel worlds”, namely “the deep space of the historic city, the hotel architecture that embodies the merger between East and West, the geometric order of the modern city, representing its vibrant development; and the future projection of a digitized and intangible city, which defines an innovative view for Macau”.
Reveal the heritage
According to the IC, "through aerial photography and a unique perspective, Iwan Baan demonstrated the relationship between architecture, urban landscape and the natural environment of Macau, being highly engaging and narrative." "Young people from the colleges of architecture in the interior of China and Macao brought to the exhibition several creative facilities that provide ideas for the future development of Macao's urban architecture."
Leong Wai Man, president of the IC, said in his speech in Venice that "world cultural heritage focused on the historic center of Macau and the modern buildings around the city show the harmony between the past and the present, constituting a vivid representation of the integration of Chinese and Western cultures," this exposure in Venice "reflects exactly the precious cultural content of Macau."
The exhibition “Parallel Worlds” can be seen until November 23 this year at Arsenale, Campo Della Tana, Castello 2126/A, 30122, in Venice.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:00:51</pubDate></item><item><title>History | Launched Chinese edition of the book by Manuel V. Basilio</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/historia-lancada-edicao-chinesa-do-livro-de-manuel-v-basilio/</link><description>It's called “Stories and Memories-Baixo do Monte and surroundings”, it is a book by Manuel V. Basilio and its edition in Chinese will be released on May 19 at the headquarters of the Macao Retired, Retired and Pensioners Association (Apomac). The work, presented in 2023, now wins a new version and has a preface by Lok Po, director of the newspaper or Mun
 
It will be released next Monday, 19, the Chinese edition of another book by Manuel V. Basil, a retired teacher who has been dedicated to various investigations into the history of Macau. This time, this is the book “Stories and Memories-Baixo do Mount and surroundings”, already presented in its Portuguese version in 2023, and now has preface by Lok Po, director of the newspaper or Mun. The launch runs at the headquarters of Apomac - Macao's Retired, Retired and Pensioners Association.
According to a statement from Apomac, since the first launch of the work that “several people encouraged the author to also edit a Chinese language version, given the interest that may be with the Chinese community in the dissemination of one of the most striking periods in the history of Macao - the integration of the Chinese population in the so -called 'Christian city'”, when the effective miscegenation of western and eastern crops created the barrier created by the old wall and doors of the city, all living in harmony as neighbors ”.
We were in the mid -nineteenth century. More specifically, from 1844, the Portuguese administration "authorized all foreigners to buy or build houses and have any terrain in Macao." Thus, "this measure eventually favored years later, the Chinese traders who had some wealth and came to Macao from southern China to escape the Taiping rebellion, also known as the Taiping Civil War, which lasted from 1850 to 1864, having settled here and restarts their activities as entrepreneurs."

According to the same note, the end of the separation between the so -called Christian city and the zone in which the Chinese community lived was thanks “to the end of the coexistence of two jurisdictions in the Macao Peninsula - the Portuguese and the Chinese, respectively, inside and outside the city's wall that, over centuries, separated the two communities”. It was also fundamental for this new phase “the beginning of the so -called colonial period, in which the Portuguese government had territorial autonomy throughout the peninsula to the door door, which later became known as the siege door”.
Election zones
Where did the Chinese were installed when the end of this separation between communities and modes of life? The book describes that "one of the zones preferred by the Chinese traders to reside was precisely the one that was then designated by low of the mount, because it is near the heart of the city."
"Since then some names of public roads have changed by the desire of their residents. Do you know, by chance, the old name of Travessa dos Anjos? And the reasons why it was changed, and what was the old method used to give names to public roads? Did you know that some Chinese were also awarded with honorific titles by the Portuguese court, and that these titles had an expiration date for one or two lives?" in the note. To all these curiosities and historical facts the book of Manuel V. Basilio intends to respond.
In the case of Baixa do Monte, and according to the information available in the “register of public roads and other places of the city of Macau, 1957, it was a designation for“ the southern hill slope and covering an entire area, vaguely defined, ranging from Fortaleza to the nearby streets of Palha, S. Domingos and Pedro Nolasco da Silva, between Rua de S. Paulo and Calçada do Monte ”.
This was an area “where many Portuguese and macanese families lived”, and to prove this fact, Manuel V. Basil “collected data on several families, especially macanese, who resided in that city from the mid -nineteenth century to the second half of the twentieth century, and whose collection includes, in particular, Baptist, Baptist, Valoma, Marques, Xavier families, Crestejo, medicines, Lopes, Morais, Nogueira, Simões, Cameirão, Costa, Silva, Fernandes, Souza, Pires, Gonçalves, Jorge, Eusébio, Placé, Osório, Santos, Rosario and Martins ”.
From 1963, there are families who lived in blocks 3 and 4 of “Kwok Wá Tai Há”, ie “Capitol neighborhood”, next to the sidewalk of truths, and “formed, for decades, an authentic community neighborhood of Macanese”. Currently "just a few macanese reside there."
Biographies and titles
But not only of streets speaks this book. The author also wrote summarized biographies of some individuals and Chinese traders who lived in downtown Mount, namely Chou Iau and Fong Seng, who, in 1880, were awarded the title of Knight by the honorary mercy of King D. Luís I of Portugal, due to the valuable contributions they made to Macau's economic and social life.
The author also makes a brief description of the divinity on the Tcha, the temple dedicated to him, along with the sidewalk of truths, as well as the festivities in his honor that are held annually on the 18th day of the fifth month of the lunar calendar.
It also makes a brief summary of the history of some buildings that existed and others that still exist, located in the boundary zone of Baixa do Monte, including the Capitol Theater building, since its inauguration, on April 18, 1931 until its closing, on August 1, 1987, and its later requalification, which became the “Capitol Theater Shopping Center”.
Thus, “Stories and Memories - Baixa do Mount and surroundings” includes “Memories, Experiences, Uses and Customs, as well as stories based on the history of Macao”, as well as valuable information about the toponymy of some Macao zones and their history.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:25:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Church | Stability in local Christian communities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/igreja-estabilidade-nas-comunidades-cristas-locais/</link><description>Robert Francis Prevost was chosen for days as the new leader of the Catholic Church, having adopted the name of Leo XIV. HM has heard two analysts on any impacts on the functioning of dioceses in Macau and Hong Kong and what is expected is continuity and stability, such as a peaceful relationship with Beijing
 
Only two days lasted the choice of a new Pope after Francis' death. Leo XIV, born Robert Francisc Prevost in Chicago, USA, was the choice of Vatican's conclave cardinals. HM spoke to two analysts to try to understand any impacts or changes in the functioning of the Catholic Church on the dioceses of Macau and Hong Kong, but the course seems to be that of stability.
“I don't think there will be nothing concrete. The situation in Hong Kong and Macau is quite well understood and stable. I know that Catholics and people of good will in both places will be praying and wishing Pope Lion all graces, blessings and successes in their pontificate,” said Stephen Morgan, Rector of the University of St. Joseph (USJ).
Already Peter Stilwell, who preceded Morgan in the rectory of USJ and is currently director of the Department of Ecumenical Relations and Interreligious Dialogue of Patriarchate of Lisbon, argues that "the relationship of Hong Kong and Macao with mainland China [regarding religion] is determined by the 90s agreements."
“What will happen, at the end of the 50 years planned for the transition, will depend on many variables in a world and in a country (China) in very quick transformation. However, the Holy See has established with both dioceses [from Macau and Hong Kong] a relationship that maintains them outside any episcopal conference and in a direct relationship with Rome. To answer 'no'. However, the evolution of the agreement as Beijing, about the appointment of the Catholic bishops to the dioceses of mainland China, will be an important factor to observe, ”noted Peter Stilwell.
He also added that "those interested in this evolution, however, will be closely observed how Pope Leo XIV Restructure, or not, the Vatican Secretariat of State - namely, the team that directly accompanies the Dossier of China."
Ancient relationship
Asked about the Vatican State relationship with Beijing with Leo XIV in power, the former USJ rector also does not foresee major changes. "The relationship will continue, discreet, but persistent, as so far. Contact has a 400 -year story, and we should not reduce it to the recent agreement on bishops."
It is an agreement that "takes place between two entities with millennial memory, which think in terms of decades and centuries." "The fact that the new Pope is US nationality will be irrelevant. As head of state, his nationality is now from the Vatican City; and the daily interpeairs to which he will respond will have the perspective of a religious community that today extends to virtually every country in the world," said Peter Stilwell.
Stephen Morgan believes that Roberto Prevost's choice for Pope has nothing to do with Trump's presence at the White House or political moves in the face of the China-Use relationship.
"His election will have more to do with the fact that he is familiar with the situation of Catholics in the developing world and having had a few years of experience in Roman Courier, where he has established himself as a pair of safe hands he thinks for himself and hears broadly."
Robert Prevost was brought to the Vatican by Pope Francis in 2023 to be responsible for examining the nominations of bishops around the world, one of the most important works of the Catholic Church, thus gaining prominence in the conclave.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:20:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Andy Wu says concerts are not enough to attract visitors</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/turismo-andy-wu-diz-que-concertos-nao-bastam-para-atrair-visitantes/</link><description>The government says it wants to bet on the organization of large -scale shows to streamline the economy in neighborhoods with less tourism, but Andy Wu, a tourism -related associative leader, says that this is not enough, defending the sale of tickets with associated discounts to take more people to consume in the territory
 
It is not music for the ears of tourism. In the view of Andy Wu, president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association, it is not enough to perform major shows in Macau, namely concerts, to increase the number of consumers in the community neighborhoods, that is, who are further away from sights.
According to the newspaper or Mun, Andy Wu argued that complementary measures are needed to perform the concerts, namely the sale of tickets combined with associated discounts in local stores, so that people who go to the concert can also consume before the shows.
Regarding the night economy, in bars and nightclubs, Andy Wu has stated that it still cannot be attractive enough for tourists, so it is important to have complementary measures to concerts.
The government said that it is negotiating with ticket sales platforms a partnership to have ticket packages with discounts in stores, which should be a reality in the second half of the year, following many visitors from the interior of China to watch concerts or sports competitions in Macao.
About the discount model to adopt, Andy Wu argued that one can take into account the format of the consumer award for the currently underway community zones, which would allow visitors to use coupons in local commerce. This would be more suitable than leading tourists to consume only in stores adhering to the discount program, he said.
Be effective
Given the negotiations carried out by the executive, Andy Wu referred to the newspaper to expect these partnerships to be launched in due time, namely in June, when the second large concert was held at Cotai, in the outdoor shows, near the Grand Lisboa Palace venture.
Andy Wu has not yet forgotten public transport factor, essential for tourists to have better access to community neighborhoods before and after the shows. The suggestion of experimental creation of exclusive buses, of the genus Shuttle-Bus, was made, with concrete paths between the shows zone and the community neighborhoods, so that visitors move to less known neighborhoods in Macau during the day and see the show at night.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:14:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Criticized opacity in alternative investments</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/jogo-criticada-opacidade-em-investimentos-alternativos/</link><description>Ron Lam accuses the government of “acting on the closed door” compared to investments of 130 billion patacas that concessionaires will spend over 10 years to revitalize the city. Without public budgets, plans and calendar, the deputy understands that society is removed from projects
 
As established in the new game concession contracts, the operators made a commitment to contribute 130 billion Patacas over the 10 years of concession in non-game investments. The measure expected to print “vitality” to the city and stimulate local economic development has passed along with the population and various social sectors, from the optics of Ron Lam.
At today's plenary session of responses to oral interpeairs, the deputy will ask the government what measures will promote to increase the transparency of these projects, both at the budget level, but also on plans and execution calendar.
According to the interpellation released yesterday by the deputy's office, "society still knows nothing about the calendar of these plans and the form of its realization." Giving as an example the International Parade of Macao, in which the Cultural Institute said it did not assume expenses due to “narrower cooperation with leisure companies this year,” Ron Lam criticizes the lack of transparency of authorities who argued that it was not “convenient to disclose the budget value, as it involved investments from private companies”.
Since investments result from commitments made in public contracts, “the use and situation of the respective budget must be treated equivalent to that of the public purse”, argues Ron Lam.
The deputy accuses the government of being “acting on the closed door”, without prior, interchange and subsequent inspection of society on non-game investments. In fact, Ron Lam indicates that investments, which on average exceed 10 billion patacas per year, "have become a government's private portfolio for their plans and activities."
Given its nature, the legislator understands that they should follow the rules of public services, fully public capital companies and public capital companies with dominant influence, being obliged to fully publish information related to the capital involved.
Returning to the case of the Macao International Parade, Ron Lam asks what law the government was based on “to escape public law to information about non-game investments”.
The larger
In view of the scenario set, Ron Lam asks if the executive will define mechanisms that guarantee the disclosure of data on the investments of the dealers, as well as the situation of the execution of the projects.
The deputy also asks which “the service responsible for the supervision and implementation of the non-game plans of the six concessionaires, by evaluating the performance of the respective investments” and whether there is a sanctioning regime if the results did not meet expectations.
Ron Lam takes the opportunity to underline the employment situation of residents and non-residents hired by the concessionaires, denouncing the dismissal of "veteran workers who have not made mistakes, without offering them any job change option." In addition, it states that participating workers in the “specific employment + training plans” were failed to be just cause, and that residents looking for full -time employment at dealers were eventually in part time, after not being hired after employment interviews. For Ron Lam, this situation reflects the position of residents as “complement of the labor imported from the game dealers”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:10:35</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | Xia says that relationship with executive differs from separation of powers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/al-xia-diz-que-relacao-com-executivo-difere-de-separacao-de-poderes/</link><description>At a meeting with the deputies, the Director of the Office for Hong Kong and Macao affairs to the Council of State stated that the relationship between the Executive and the Legislative Assembly is different from the concept of separation of powers from the “West”. Xia Baolong characterized the relationship as a collaboration with the predominance of the executive branch
 
Hong Kong and Macau's workst a director of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office with the Council of State, Xia Baolong, went to the Legislative Assembly (AL) on Sunday for an ideas exchange with all the plenary deputies.
During the meeting, Xia Baolong will have stated that "the way basic law regulates the relationship between the executive and legislative powers is not the same relationship that exists in the separation of powers used by the" West "," said the president of AL. Since the beginning of his passage through Macao, and like previous visits, Xia Baolong is quoted by guardians of high government positions and, in this case, by Kou Hoi In and some deputies.
In statements cited by the Chinese channel of Rádio Macau, the president of AL indicated that Xia Baolong had binded the government's ancestry in relation to the House of Laws.
“[The Director] said we have to further reinforce and optimize the relationship between the executive and legislative powers. The two parties need respect and mutual support so that we can benefit and develop the particularity of our political system to be characterized by the predominance of the executive power,” said Kou Hoi In.
It should be noted that in no article of the basic law of the MSAR, or even the annex that regulates the methodology for the constitution of the AL, the predominance of the Executive Power is indicated in the face of the Legislative Power. In fact, Article 71 of the Basic Law establishes the possibility of the Legislative Assembly approving a motion of censorship “accusing the chief executive of serious violation of the law or abandonment of his duties”. In addition, despite having powers to dissolve the Legislative Assembly, article 54 of the Basic Law indicates two situations of conflict with the Legislative Power that may result in the resignation of the position of the Chief Executive.
Roll
During the meeting with the deputies, Xia Baolong praised the legislative work, in particular the revisions of laws related to national security, electoral laws and the legislation related to the game sector.
Cooperation with Hengqin was one of the most discussed topics, with deputies and the director to agree on the need to reinforce integration between the two territories.
The director pointed out that it is necessary to be aware of and prepared “for adversities, do the work of accelerating hengqin-macau integration and the proper diversification of the economy of Macau, and take another step in optimizing the relationship between executive branch and legislature, in the sense of respect and mutual support, to enhance the institutional advantages of the executive branch's predominance.
According to a statement released yesterday by AL, the director expressed the desire that Macao, while “Pearl in the palm of the hand” of the homeland, will brush more sickly.
Tariffs | Appeal to the determination of local companies
Hong Kong and Macau's workst a director of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office Director with the Council of State, Xia Baolong, gathered yesterday with more than 20 representatives of the business sector.
In a meeting that lasted more than two hours, the official left words of encouragement and resilience to the adversities caused by the trade war. According to the chairman of the Board of Directors of the Nam Kwong Group, Fu Jianguo, the director presented four specific requirements for the business community of Macao. Firstly, the need to have a spirit of struggle and face the current geopolitical situation at a higher level. Xia Baolong also asked entrepreneurs to have confidence in medium and long term national plans and tell the stories of China, Hong Kong and Macao well.
The president of the Macao Banks Association and president of the Bank of China's Macao branch, Jia Tianbing, said that Xia Baolong will have made hope that Macau will overcome the difficulties of economic development.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nissan | Cuts of another 10,000 jobs around the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/nissan-cortes-de-mais-10-mil-empregos-em-todo-o-mundo/</link><description>Nissan automotive construction will suppress more than 10,000 jobs around the world, in addition to the nine thousand already announced in November, several Japanese social communication agencies yesterday reported. According to NHK television, the approximately 19,000 workers who will be dismissed are about 15 percent of the Japanese company's workforce.
The automobile group was deemed to confirm this information, which was also released by the Diário Económico Nikkei. Nissan, in which the French group Renault holds a 35 percent participation, is expected to publish on Tuesday the results for fiscal year of 2024-2025 finished in March.
Nissan is expected to announce a record annual loss in a context of restructuring the company and after the application of more tariffs by the United States. By the end of April, the automotive group had already foreseen net losses between 700 and 750 billion yen (between 4.32 and 4.62 billion euros) in the fiscal year of 2024-2025, about nine times more than it foresaw in February.
The damage is explained, in particular, “by the costs associated with the ongoing relaunch plan,” said the automotive builder at the end of April.
Given the persistence of the slowdown of sales in their main markets - the American and the Chinese - Nissan announced in early November that it intended to suppress 9,000 jobs worldwide and reduce its production capacity by 20 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:38:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Transport | Song Pek Kei requires improvement of service on holidays</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/transportes-song-pek-kei-exige-melhoria-do-servico-nos-feriados/</link><description>Representative Song Pek Kei brokered the executive about the need to improve the public transport service on holidays, namely with regard to buses and taxis.
The deputy, representative of the community of Fujian, recalled that during the golden work week, May 1st, there were great gatherings of people at bus stops at the various border stations of Macao and the city's sights, even if companies have provided the largest transportation offer, with more careers.
“During the holidays, with the increase in the number of tourists, the government can increase the frequency of buses, so that there is a better response in the peak period and ensures a greater balance between supply and demand from residents and tourists?” Song Pek Kei.
The deputy also asks the authorities to reinforce the combat of tariff abuse by taxi drivers on holidays, as well as disseminating the results of a study elaborated on the future increase in the number of taxis in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:44:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau maintains shipping by air to the United States</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/macau-mantem-envio-de-encomendas-por-via-aerea-para-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Macau Post Office Director told Lusa yesterday that, unlike neighboring Hong Kong, the region kept ordering orders to the United States (USA), but only by air. On May 2, the US government eliminated the exemption of customs rights on small orders from mainland China and Hong Kong, such as those sent by the giants of Electronic Trade Shein and Temu.
"In practice, now Macau is not included and the mail [which] goes to the United States is walking, except maritime. The rest, we keep normal," said Derby Lau Wai Meng. The Director of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT) explained that the shipping of any goods, from sea to the US, implies a passage through Hong Kong, one of the busiest ports in the world.
That is, there is only the hypothesis of sending orders by air, confirmed Derby Lau. "This case is sensitive," admitted the leader. "I think it's better not to talk [this subject], because the best thing is not to remember us," he added.
Trump in Action
The end of the exemption of customs rights on small orders from mainland China and Hong Kong emerged in an executive order, signed by US President Donald Trump on April 2.
The document asked the US Secretary of Commerce, Howard Lutnick, to submit a report, within 90 days, if the end of the exemption should also cover Macao, "to avoid escape to these measures."
On April 16, Hong Kong's post office announced the suspension of sending orders to the United States in response to the imposition, "abusive", tariffs by US authorities.
A presidential decree issued by Donald Trump, still in the first term, in 2020, eliminated the preferential treatment granted to Hong Kong. The ancient British colony is therefore also affected by the 145 percent surcharge imposed on China.
Chinese Communist Party's main official for Hong Kong and Macao affairs and governments of both regions accused the United States of imposing tariffs in mid -April to sabotage China.
Macao Executive leader Sam Hou Fai criticized the United States for the “abusive imposition of customs taxes on all his business partners,” including China, “under various pretexts”. Yesterday, the US representative for the United States, Jamieson Greer, said Washington and Beijing will suspend the majority of customs rights and negotiate for 90 days.
In the negotiations made in Geneva, the United States and China agreed to reduce the reciprocal customs rights imposed on each other, passing Chinese imports to pay a 30 percent customs right, while US products will pay a 10 percent customs right.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:36:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Venice receives “Parallel Worlds”, from Macao, at the Architecture Biennial</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/veneza-recebe-mundos-paralelos-de-macau-na-bienal-de-arquitectura/</link><description>It was inaugurated last Thursday, in Venice, at the 19th Biennial of Architecture, the show “Parallels”, which represents Macao at the Biennial and which is a project carried out by photographer Iwan Baan with architectural students at the University of St. Joseph (USJ). The curatorship is still with Wang Shu, the last Pritzker award, and Lu Wenyu.
This is a show that reveals the coexistence of “parallel worlds” in Macao, combining “Macao urban landscape images captured by the famous humanistic architecture photographer Iwan Baan and facilities created by teachers and students from the Faculty of Architecture of the China Academy of Arts and the Faculty of Architecture and Design at the University of São José de Macao”. Thus, it is represented “the urban fabric of the city where Chinese and Western cultures, old and new styles have coexisting for over 400 years,” says a note from the Cultural Institute (IC).
There are, in this show, four “parallel worlds”, namely “the deep space of the historic city, the hotel architecture that embodies the merger between East and West, the geometric order of the modern city, representing its vibrant development; and the future projection of a digitized and intangible city, which defines an innovative view for Macau”.
Reveal the heritage
According to the IC, "through aerial photography and a unique perspective, Iwan Baan demonstrated the relationship between architecture, urban landscape and the natural environment of Macau, being highly engaging and narrative." "Young people from the colleges of architecture in the interior of China and Macao brought to the exhibition several creative facilities that provide ideas for the future development of Macao's urban architecture."
Leong Wai Man, president of the IC, said in his speech in Venice that "world cultural heritage focused on the historic center of Macau and the modern buildings around the city show the harmony between the past and the present, constituting a vivid representation of the integration of Chinese and Western cultures," this exposure in Venice "reflects exactly the precious cultural content of Macau."
The exhibition “Parallel Worlds” can be seen until November 23 this year at Arsenale, Campo Della Tana, Castello 2126/A, 30122, in Venice.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:00:51</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM Theater | Symphonic concert about Disney's movie “Frozen” at the end of the month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/teatro-mgm-concerto-sinfonico-sobre-o-filme-frozen-da-disney-no-final-do-mes/</link><description>The MGM Theater welcomes, on May 31st and June 1st, the Symphonic Concert entirely dedicated to the Disney animation movie “Frozen”, thinking about World Children's Day, which is celebrated precisely on the first day of June. The song is in charge of the Macau Orchestra
 
The smallest and fans of Disney's movie "Frozen" will have the opportunity to see and hear a concert entirely to the history and characters of this production, being an initiative to celebrate World Children's Day, the ephemeris celebrated on June 1. The concert, welcomed by the MGM Theater on May 31st and June 1, takes place, respectively, at 20h and 15h.
With co-organization of the Cultural Institute (IC), it is, according to a note of this organism, with “a charming and fantastic concert that will combine live symphonic music with scenic technology, bringing adult children and friends from Macao to the magical cold world”.
The sound is in charge of the Macau Orchestra (OM), which will play live “various iconic songs from the animation soundtrack, synchronized with images projects on a giant 900 square meter and 28 million pixels, installed in the theater, with the 19.1-channel 19.1-channel sound system”.
Thus, with the use of technology, the “fusion of sound and image will create an immersive experience that transports viewers to a fascinating ice and snow kingdom”, verifying “the excellence of international level and international level” in the space chosen for both shows, the MGM Theater. According to the IC note, this show room was officially recognized by Disney as a space to perform Disney concerts in Macao.
Voices and Folding
The concert has a “cast of excellence, bringing together musicians and top singers from Macao and abroad”, being directed by OM assistant conductor Tony Cheng-Te Yeh. The songs of the animation will be played by OM and several “international renowned singers”, such as Alyssa Fox, who played Elsa in the American tour of the Broadway musical “Frozen”; Ray Liu, who folds and sings Anna's voice in the Mandarin version of the animation, RJ Woessner, who gives life to the characters Kristoff and Hans and, CJ Tan as Olaf, as well as the Vocal Vocal Vocal Band group.
The movie “Frozen” premiered in 2013 and “won the world”, having won the Oscar for best animation movie. Highlight for the song, taken from the movie's soundtrack, “Let It Go”, which became a success on the global scale. There are also other great musical hits that came out of the movie "Frozen", such as "Do You Want to Build to Snowman?" and "For the First Time in Forever", which had the power to "captivate hearings of all ages."
“Let It Go” received the Oscar for best original song at the 86th edition of the Academy Awards and raised three important awards on the 57th Grammy Awards.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:59:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | Gold falls more than 3 % after agreement between Washington and Beijing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/tarifas-ouro-cai-mais-de-3-apos-acordo-entre-washington-e-pequim/</link><description>Gold, asset of safe haven in times of uncertainty, fell strongly yesterday, more than 3 percent, endangering the level of $ 3,200, after the United States and China announced a trade agreement.
At 11:00 in Lisbon, the price of gold went down 3.23 percent to $ 3,217.58, although after the announcement of that agreement, a few minutes after 8:00 am, it fell even more pronounced to 3,216.29 dollars. And this after the US and China announced a reduction in tariffs. Specifically, Chinese tariffs will go from 125 percent to 10 percent over US products in the next 90 days.
The US will do the same from 145 percent to 30 percent over Chinese products, as part of the terms agreed over the weekend to lock the new trade war this year. The tariff reductions agreed by China and the US will take effect on May 14.
The above agreement between the two main commercial powers drives the dollar, affecting metal prices in general. Gold also descends with the reduction of geopolitical tensions, following the ceasefire agreed between India and Pakistan, while Russia and Ukraine can meet Thursday in Istanbul to start a diplomatic way to resolve the conflict.
With yesterday's fall, gold is moving away from the current historical maximum of $ 3,414.65, checked on April 21.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:37:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco | “Employment + Training” plan offers 30 vacancies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/melco-plano-de-emprego-formacao-oferece-30-vagas/</link><description>Enrollment opens today for another specific “Employment + Training” plan launched by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and, this time, by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, which will make 30 vacancies available to “entertainment ambassador”.
According to a statement released yesterday by DSAL, the plan follows the “first hiring, then training” regime, “providing training in all aspects and professional development opportunities for Macao residents who are interested in exercising game -related entertainment activities”.
Admitted candidates will participate in training actions, organized by Melco, over a year and a half, which include a practical part and real context of work. The training will appeal candidates for “knowledge of activities in theaters and other leisure establishments” and enable them to respond immediately to “safety incidents and crisis control management”.
Registrations end on May 20, in a week. For May 27, a lecture is planned and interviews will be held to candidates.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:22:12</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Liu Yuxi (772-842), Luoyang's poet (Henan), contemplating the heavens noticed in certain birds who liked to dwell with families and indicated a permanence within the constant change of stations. Observing the habits of the swallows and the decay of the high classes in Jinling, he wrote in the last two verses of the poem to Rua das Mansions of Black Village:
Under the eaves of the powerful Wang and Xie
before they were swallows,
Now flying, they seek so many times
our humble dwellings.
This proximity that speaks, for example, the founding legend of the first dynasty that there are written records and that is the origin of the Shang lineage (c. 1500-1050 A. C.) it was long recognized with the first.
Then, according to historian Sima Qian, a woman named Jiandi would have eaten a swallow egg (Yan), previously called simply Xuanniao, "black bird", then giving birth to a man named Xie, who was the ancestor of the founders of the dynasty. Over time, in various arts such as architecture, painting or poetry, repeated references were unfolded to this relationship of perceived friendship with black birds.
In times of uneasiness, such as those who followed the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition in which painters identified with the losers and belonging to the previous reigning family, such as Zhu da (1626-1705) known as Bada Shanren, found new, expressive forms of the fluidity of the caligraphic brush trace along the Tang and Song Dynasties and Song and that in the ming dong and that Qichang would make an ideal.
In the epitome of its speed, this trait was designated Feiba, the "flying white", which left only the traces of the brush passage. A painter from Xinghua (Yangzhou, Jiangsu) admirer of Bada Shanren showed in several paintings the same independent attitude of canons that would lead to one of the Yangzhou Baguai, "the eight eccentrics of Yangzhou."
Li Shan (1686- C.1756) who would use the stage name Futang, which can be translated as a "recovery of family relationships", in the vertical roll swallows (paint and color on paper, 134.9 x 33 cm, metmuseum) painted slowly, carefully two swallows in a branch made with the spontaneity of the speed of the trace used to write with the pinl.
And as in many paintings by Bada Shanren, the words in Him are written in harmony with the figuration, and just like the swallows in the branch depend on each other. In this roll Li Shan wrote: «As soon as the fall does salguels begin to wither cruelly wither,/ how do they compare to the spring brisa and the corner of the swallows?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Nissan automotive construction will suppress more than 10,000 jobs around the world, in addition to the nine thousand already announced in November, several Japanese social communication agencies yesterday reported. According to NHK television, the approximately 19,000 workers who will be dismissed are about 15 percent of the Japanese company's workforce.
The automobile group was deemed to confirm this information, which was also released by the Diário Económico Nikkei. Nissan, in which the French group Renault holds a 35 percent participation, is expected to publish on Tuesday the results for fiscal year of 2024-2025 finished in March.
Nissan is expected to announce a record annual loss in a context of restructuring the company and after the application of more tariffs by the United States. By the end of April, the automotive group had already foreseen net losses between 700 and 750 billion yen (between 4.32 and 4.62 billion euros) in the fiscal year of 2024-2025, about nine times more than it foresaw in February.
The damage is explained, in particular, “by the costs associated with the ongoing relaunch plan,” said the automotive builder at the end of April.
Given the persistence of the slowdown of sales in their main markets - the American and the Chinese - Nissan announced in early November that it intended to suppress 9,000 jobs worldwide and reduce its production capacity by 20 percent.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Nissan automotive construction will suppress more than 10,000 jobs around the world, in addition to the nine thousand already announced in November, several Japanese social communication agencies yesterday reported. According to NHK television, the approximately 19,000 workers who will be dismissed are about 15 percent of the Japanese company's workforce.
The automobile group was deemed to confirm this information, which was also released by the Diário Económico Nikkei. Nissan, in which the French group Renault holds a 35 percent participation, is expected to publish on Tuesday the results for fiscal year of 2024-2025 finished in March.
Nissan is expected to announce a record annual loss in a context of restructuring the company and after the application of more tariffs by the United States. By the end of April, the automotive group had already foreseen net losses between 700 and 750 billion yen (between 4.32 and 4.62 billion euros) in the fiscal year of 2024-2025, about nine times more than it foresaw in February.
The damage is explained, in particular, “by the costs associated with the ongoing relaunch plan,” said the automotive builder at the end of April.
Given the persistence of the slowdown of sales in their main markets - the American and the Chinese - Nissan announced in early November that it intended to suppress 9,000 jobs worldwide and reduce its production capacity by 20 percent.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 2025
In Chinese Proverbial Lessons I went to discover great affinities between spontaneous Chinese popular philosophy, which runs from mouth to mouth, and the Christian proverbial wisdom, also made so that believers, in every corner of the globe, could memorize, repeat and disseminate.
Nothing like the other's knowledge to bring and dispel prejudice, being one of the most usual that Chinese are extremely pragmatic and cold. But when we come across proverbs such as “love others as yourself,” in a direct translation and faithful to the original “爱人如己” (ài Rú Rú Jǐ), such leads us to think twice, it seems not to be here just a matter of respect, uncharged and formal, but rather a strong feeling for the other, not any, only a deep affection, of those we understand well that we are good, we will be well, we will be well, we will be well, we will be better. Then he runs a love of the Christian way for China without Christ ever been. Such finding can lead us to the assumption of the existence of universal structures, not only logical, including as regards affections, therefore sentimental. After all, selfishness may not be a dominant tendency, there is everything: selfish, aggressive and competitive people, as others will be naturally altruistic, compassionate and cooperatives, ready to recognize the universality of the feeling of love, which crosses borders rather than erecting them, bringing people closer to the most diverse social classes, ethnic groups, geographies, as in "love has no borders", in a direct translation "" (Àiqíng wú jiējí zhī fēn), here is particularly emphasized social borders.
The content of the message gains full sense when one realizes that love to oneself takes place in a culture that many consider wrong and prejudiced only to focus on the whole, in the community.  Attention to the person, the particular and the style and feeling of each, lives, in philosophies such as Taoist for centuries with the valorization of the collectivity, this ultimate tendency manifestly inculcated and worked by Confucianism.  Love to itself, care for the individual body and mind, is emphasized in the so -called Proverbial “well -understood love and virtue must begin with us”, which has the following correspondence in Chinese “爱德从己起” (to Cong Jǐ qǐ).
Anyone who imagines that in proverbial wisdom there is only place to praise and sing relational love, since the Chinese do not have any religious philosophy that chants spiritual love above all, in the Christian way of St. Augustine, will be surprised to find the following proverb "where there is no other gentleman", that in a direct translation of the Chinese is "the love above all" 爱情至上 爱情至上 爱情至上ZHì Shàng).
If in doubt, there is another saying of complementary meaning and in which the idea of ​​the integrity and unity of this powerful affection, which moves mountains in the Christian sense, when it reads 爱情专一 （（（（iqíng zhuān yī）, in a possible translation "love cannot be broken", "one person cannot have a heart in two parts at the same time."
From a psychological point of view, the acceptance of the other in loving terms will have to be complete, so their tastes, affections, relationships, and objects cannot be rejected, as is clear from the lesson "Who loves Beltrão, loves their dog", in a relative correspondence for "爱屋及乌" (ài wū jí wū), which in a literal translation would be "love the house and the crums."
As is well known, proverbs are susceptible to various interpretations, so they say polysemic, but if they are perspective as a whole, and only then as pieces of a puzzle, there seems to be many doubts with regard to the proverb philosophy and psychology of Chinese love, which is echoed in the country's scholarly philosophies.
In Chapter 67 of the Book of the road and virtue (《道德经》), also known by the name of the Patriarch of Taoism, Lazi (老子), is the first of the three guiding virtues of the Wise Way, love, as you can read in the translation of Claudia Ribeiro (2004, 139):
I have three treasures
What entesouro and retains:
The first is love (CI),
The second frugality,
The third is not daring to be the vanguard of the world.
(…)
For love,
In combat, it triumphs,
And in defense it is firm.
The sky will come to aid
And, with love, will protect
(我有三寶/寶而持之/一曰慈/二曰儉/三曰不敢為天下先 (……) 夫慈以戰則勝//以守則固/以慈衛之 1)
It is noted that while in proverbial philosophy the synogram used for love is 爱/愛 2 (AI), in the scholarly philosophy of the Patriarch of Taoism the term employment is 慈 (CI), that is, love with a strong relational and spiritual burden; Although they are different words, both refer to love, the first concerns the most physical and concrete feeling, centered on the heart of the person and the clutches that hold it;  The second to that most relational and general indicates that love comes from inside the heart (内心 nèixīn), where it has the roots, emerging like any plant. However, the truth is that both terms focus on people, or rather in their hearts, affectionate connection with others, such a strong connection that draws the attention of heaven (天 tiān), maximum impersonal power, it ensures victory on all battle fronts, whether in the forefront or rear, when fighting and defended itself for love.
Already the patriarch of Confucianism, Confucius (孔子), in the Chapter Twelve, later entitled the deep face, of the Analects (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 22) defines the main virtue of the school, benevolence or humanity, (仁 Rén) as an act of love to others, maintaining the term of the traditional vernacular 爱 (AI): “Fan Chi asked what was the benevolence was what answered, "love people". " (樊遲問仁 ， 子曰 「愛人 3。 ”) It is in this context of love of neighbor, that one of the main maxims of Confucian philosophy must be understood, which arises in the same chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 2)“ Do not make the others what they do not want for you ”(己所不欲勿施於人 jǐ suǒ bù yù shunk yú rén).
The essentials in Confucian philosophy will then guarantee love of others in terms of respect or humanity towards others, in order to ensure the normal functioning of society, without extreme sacrifices or exaggerated explorations, given to the proverb containment of confusion in relation to feelings, they are important and useful but should not extravate the boundaries of rationality, that is, even the best of them, will have to be measured, controlled and ritualized in the name of harmony collective. Therefore, the love that moves friendships, especially intellectuals, is the most praised, as we remembered at the end of this chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 24):
Zeng Zi stated: “A gentleman resorts to knowing to make friends and friends to cultivate benevolence4” (曾子曰：君以文會友 ， 以友輔仁。)
Finally, also the Buddhist philosophy, especially from the Chan (禅 Chán) or Zen meditation line, praises the love of humanity, but indirectly, drawing attention to the heart and the identification of Buddha with the heart, the way of the Daoxin Patriarch (道信) and its maximum proverbially known “the heart is Buddha and Buddha is the heart” (非心不问佛 ， 问佛不非心 fēi xīn bùwèn fu, wèn fi bù fēi xīn). Here you come to love indirectly, only an enlightened heart can love the Buddha, as it is not surprising in the picture of this philosophy, after all what is Buddha but the very love that expresses itself not in a selfish, sick, self -centered heart, but in a heart capable of establishing relationships, healthy, altruistic and without empty, but not indifferent to the other?  This confirms it the social and humanitarian actions of Via Mahayana Buddhism, which was accepted in China and unfolds in collective works such as the construction of educational institutions, hospitals, centers of social solidarity, in a proselytist action at all similar to the history of the Christian Church and its missionaries around the world.
Bibliographic references
Lansheng, Jiang (Comp.) 1997. 100 Excerpts from Zen Buddhist Texts. Hong Hong Kong: Commercial Press.
NGAN, António André. 1998. SINE-SHORE CONGRELLANCE OF PROVERBS AND IDIOMATIC PHRASES. 中葡對照成語集. Macau: Macao Adult Association.
RIBEIRO, Claudia (Trad). 2004. 《道德經》 The Book of Road and Power. Bilingual edition. Mem-Martins: European American Publications.
Xin Guanjie (辛冠洁) (org. And trad.) 1994. 《論語》 .Tradument for contemporary Chinese falls xiqin (蔡希勤) and English translation of Lai Bo (赖波) and Xia Yuhe (夏玉和). Beijing: Sinolingue.
References:
Text in classic Chinese.
Love in simplified and traditional Chinese.
Text in classic Chinese.
A gentleman in ancient Chinese times was a gentleman and a potential ruler.
“This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors” https://www.cccm.gov.pt</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Liu Yuxi (772-842), Luoyang's poet (Henan), contemplating the heavens noticed in certain birds who liked to dwell with families and indicated a permanence within the constant change of stations. Observing the habits of the swallows and the decay of the high classes in Jinling, he wrote in the last two verses of the poem to Rua das Mansions of Black Village:
Under the eaves of the powerful Wang and Xie
before they were swallows,
Now flying, they seek so many times
our humble dwellings.
This proximity that speaks, for example, the founding legend of the first dynasty that there are written records and that is the origin of the Shang lineage (c. 1500-1050 A. C.) it was long recognized with the first.
Then, according to historian Sima Qian, a woman named Jiandi would have eaten a swallow egg (Yan), previously called simply Xuanniao, "black bird", then giving birth to a man named Xie, who was the ancestor of the founders of the dynasty. Over time, in various arts such as architecture, painting or poetry, repeated references were unfolded to this relationship of perceived friendship with black birds.
In times of uneasiness, such as those who followed the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition in which painters identified with the losers and belonging to the previous reigning family, such as Zhu da (1626-1705) known as Bada Shanren, found new, expressive forms of the fluidity of the caligraphic brush trace along the Tang and Song Dynasties and Song and that in the ming dong and that Qichang would make an ideal.
In the epitome of its speed, this trait was designated Feiba, the "flying white", which left only the traces of the brush passage. A painter from Xinghua (Yangzhou, Jiangsu) admirer of Bada Shanren showed in several paintings the same independent attitude of canons that would lead to one of the Yangzhou Baguai, "the eight eccentrics of Yangzhou."
Li Shan (1686- C.1756) who would use the stage name Futang, which can be translated as a "recovery of family relationships", in the vertical roll swallows (paint and color on paper, 134.9 x 33 cm, metmuseum) painted slowly, carefully two swallows in a branch made with the spontaneity of the speed of the trace used to write with the pinl.
And as in many paintings by Bada Shanren, the words in Him are written in harmony with the figuration, and just like the swallows in the branch depend on each other. In this roll Li Shan wrote: «As soon as the fall does salguels begin to wither cruelly wither,/ how do they compare to the spring brisa and the corner of the swallows?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Osaka 2025 | Japanese architect Kengo Kuma considers it to be friendly with architecture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/osaka-2025-arquitecto-japones-kengo-kuma-considera-ia-amiga-da-arquitectura/</link><description>Japanese architect Kengo Kuma states in an interview with Lusa that she wanted to show the uniqueness between Portugal and Japan in the Portuguese Pavilion project at Expo 2025 Osaka and considers AI (artificial intelligence) friendly to architecture.
Asked if Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a friend or enemy of architecture, Kengo Kuma opts for the first option. "Yes, it's a friend", because in fact in the design process "we are working with AI".
Artificial intelligence “is a very strong team between us” and “we like to work” with this technology, he says. “We wanted to show the relationship with the ocean in Portugal,” says Kengo Kuma, when asked what was the project's inspiration. Portugal participates in Expo Osaka with the theme “Ocean, Blue Dialogue” and is located in the “Empowering Lives” zone, in a lot with 1,836.75 square meters, being close to the Japan Pavilion.
The Kuma Kuma project expresses the dynamics of the ocean moment, using 9,972 suspended cables weighing more than 60 tons, and recycled networks to create a perennial effect and exposed to natural elements such as sun and wind, according to the organization.
Sea connections
The life of Portugal and Japan is “very linked to the ocean”, in the sense that “we eat fish, we travel a lot through the oceans and history and life are closely linked to the ocean,” adds the architect. There is this “uniqueness of Portugal and Japan and we want to show” this similarity between the two countries.
The volume of the Portugal Pavilion is characterized by a scenic facility that symbolizes the upper square suspended as a wave.
"This design is very, very new to the history of art. We have long tried to use lines as a resource for navigation. With these lines, we try to show the beauty of natural phenomena," in the sea "we see natural light and breeze," he explains.
“We tried to bring this kind of natural phenomenon to the Expo, perhaps the first attempt in the history of the expo to bring its own nature to the pavilion,” says the architect. About what will happen to the pavilion after finishing the Expo, the architect says he wants to bring the diversity of the project (which includes cables of various diameters and lengths) to different places.
“I want to bring this diversity to different places” and “now we are planning to work with some artists” about it. Kengo Kuma said that the Slaughterhouse Project in Porto is completing and has two more projects in Portugal.
The architect says he loves the side of the big cities in Portugal, but also the mountainous side and the ocean of the country. “We want to enjoy the diversity of Portugal,” he says.
Create Memories
Asked how can the more sustainable architecture become currently become, Kengo Kuma considers that "the most important for sustainability is to leave the memory of architecture forever." That is, "architecture, life, basically, are not so permanent."
However, “we can leave the memory of architecture forever, which is the connection between architecture and humanity” and this “is the most important for sustainability,” he says. Used to comment on the controversy around his choice to project the Portuguese pavilion, the architect points out that he has an international office working in Portugal.
"Maybe that's why we were invited," he concludes. Regarding the challenges that architecture currently faces, Kengo Kuma states that its cost is increasing “dramatically” and that everyone wants to reduce it.
"But at the same time, people want to create a new monument" for this pillar. "And the cost and monumentality must walk together" today. Expo 2025 runs since April 13 and runs until October 13 on the artificial island of Yumeshima, located on the edge of Osaka, Kansai, Japan.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:03:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Startups | Portugal interested in the SINO-LUSOPHONE TECHNOLOGY FUND</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/startups-portugal-interessado-no-fundo-sino-lusofono-de-tecnologia/</link><description>A delegation from Macao, with government representatives and local startups, is in Portugal to meet with leaders of Portuguese companies and participate in the SIM conference, which ends today in Porto. During the visit, a protocol was signed that signs the Portuguese interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund, managed by Heng Qin Group's state-owned company Zhuhai
 
Several macao startups are represented on a trip to Portugal this week, and whose delegation also includes representatives of the Directorate of Economics and Tourism Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries Association (AEIMCP). The objective is to strengthen ties with the entrepreneurship ecosystems of Lisbon and Porto and reinforce Portugal's interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund designed to support startups, which will be managed by Heng Qin Group's Zhuhai state company.
In this sense, a protocol between AEIMCP and the nascent Value, “Portuguese company with extensive investor capture” and also “accelerating small business growth (SME) and startups in Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, focused on innovation and cutting-edge technology”, is signed on Monday, in Lisbon, in Lisbon, in Lisbon.
The protocol signed on Monday signs the highest Portuguese access to the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund. The document was signed as part of a visit from the Macau Group to Lispolis - Lisbon Technological Pole.
The nascent Value thus becomes a “exclusive agent for investor capture services in Portugal, focusing on the involvement of investors in the background” SINO-LUSOPHONE, whose official name is “from Heng Qin Sino-Maluso Technology and Innovation Investment LPF”. This “promotes investments in high quality science and technology innovation companies in Portuguese -speaking countries”, explains the same note.
Thus, this protocol will allow AEIMCP, as a connecting entity between Portugal and the Fund via Macau, and the nascent Value, “reinforce its commitment to support startups, promote transfronhoring investment and create new opportunities for collaboration between Macau, Portugal and other Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Quoted by the same note, AEIMCP's Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said this new agreement shows how the entity, which also organizes the “929 Challenge” contest, is committed to “creating bridges for the global startup growth, facilitating the entry of Portuguese startups into the Chinese market through Macao, as well as the expansion of Chinese startups to Portugal and Europe”.
In turn, Rui Ferreira said that “the signing of this protocol is an important milestone for connecting innovation ecosystems and promoting synergies between macao startups and Portuguese investors”. "We are confident that this partnership will bring significant results for both sides," he added.
At HM, Rui Ferreira explained that the signature of the protocol represents the culmination of a work of about a year.
“We want to promote a model of welcoming startups and companies from Macao that want to enter Europe through Portugal, as well as in Portuguese-expression countries, and vice versa, that is, to place, through Macau, companies of these territories, but always through Portugal, in the East, in order to obtain easier connections with the Chinese market.”
Thousand Visits
Macao's group visited several essential points of the Portuguese entrepreneurship sector. In addition to the visit to Lispolis, considered the “key moment to foster dialogues between Deep Tech startups and potential investors, consolidating Macau's vision as an innovation and entrepreneurship hub with global range”, the entourage passed through the unicorns factory in Lisbon, and the PWC consultant.
Marco Duarte Rizzolio explained to HM the benefits to Macao from the journey through Portugal. “In addition to the interest in the Sino-Lusophone Fund and its preparation, as it will be released soon, our focus has also been the startups. On the visit to Lispolis macao startups made a pitch [attempted investment tarning], presented their products and had a networking session with other startups. Immersion in the Entrepreneurship Ecosystem in Portugal. ”
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, Macao's entourage only took to Portugal to startups with a more advanced business phase, namely Zence Object, founded by Calvin Sio and obtained a $ 2.5 million financing from the Alibaba Group entrepreneurs to the Great Bay area. Zence Object uses patented technology to transform organic waste, namely tea leaves, into alternative plastic and paper products. The idea is that these recycled and transformed products can be used on a daily basis, such as home or decorating utensils.
"There are startups in Macau who are very advanced in terms of business and we have brought to Portugal. We want to explore new opportunities for internationalization, so that they explore other markets, as these startups already have some development. We want to create partnerships, so that these representatives realize what the market is like and explore possible customers," said the representative of AEIMCP.
By unbeaten paths
Macao's entourage is today in Porto to participate in “SIM Conference” [Startups &amp; Investment Matching], where “it will have its own stand to present projects and connect with investors and possible customers”. This event was organized by the Entity Startup Portugal, which invited to be present.
Also today will be signed another protocol, this time between the association that organizes the contest “929 Challenge” and Startup Portugal. The idea is, according to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, “stimulate the connection of the Portugal ecosystem with Macau and help in the process of internationalization of the startups on both sides, both the Portuguese who are intended for the great bay, through Macau, both the macao startups that go to Portugal”.
The official has no doubt that what is lacking in knowledge is left in interest. “There is a great interest in China, but at the same time there is great ignorance. The startup ecosystem in Portugal is much more linked to Europe. When we talk to the unicorns factory, for months, we were told that there was a great interest in the Macao and China market, but that these visits to Portugal were lacking. It is growing a lot in technology and artificial intelligence, with the launch of DeepSeek, for example. ”
According to Rui Ferreira, the presence of the delegation of Macao in “Yes Conference” will allow access to “privileged and wider contacts”, as it is a national event. "With this visit we have been able to do two things: starting the relationship with AEIMCP more formally and helping Macao companies know of partners and investors. We also want to bet on the work for the future Sino-Musso fund, to prepare companies with investment potential," he said.
For Rui Ferreira, the Macao market has the potential “to be used as a business exchange platform, thanks to linguistic connection, and there is conditions in the territory to establish all the part of reception, support and exchange with China entities and create an ecosystem”. In addition, “it will be interesting Macao to make a specialized innovation hub in strategic areas”, which in this case is technology. Highlight for the fact that the visit also had the organization of the Macao Sino-Lusophone Platform Association for sustainable development.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Literature | The interest of linguist Hugo Schuchardt in Patuá de Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/literatura-o-interesse-do-linguista-hugo-schuchardt-no-patua-de-macau/</link><description>Hugo Schuchardt had a genuine interest in Luso-Asian Creole languages, with particular emphasis on Patuá, spoken by the Macanese community. The linguist, who was born in 1842, was the subject of a lecture conducted by researcher Hugo Cardoso, linked to the University of Lisbon
 
Porto, 1883. José Leite de Vasconcelos writes a letter to the German linguist Hugo Schuchardt who had been developing studies, albeit at a distance, about the languages ​​spoken in Asia originated in Portuguese, the so -called Creoles. The letter, written according to the spell agreement of the time, however digitized and today to keep the Archive of the University of Graz, Austria, comes in the context of Schuchardt's own requests to Vasconcelos Milk on the Creole that was then spoken in Macao, known as Patuá.
“My respectable friend: I can only respond to you today. Here in Porto there are no books that say, but I wrote to Lisbon to my friend Vianna and he replied that the Balsmanha does not appear, and that in Macao's story there comes nothing about the dialect port. From Macau. Usual.
I have already asked for information about the Creoles, but I have not yet got anything; This study also interests me about regarding Portuguese. I look forward to the 2 new booklets that promises me. (…) Without anymore I am a friend, J. Vasconcelos Leite, Porto, S. Victor, 25 ”.
Hugo Schuchardt's interest in Luso-Asian Creole has been studied by Hugo Cardoso, a researcher and professor at the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon (FLUL), a Creole specialist who developed investigation at the University of Macao.
The academic recently conducted a lecture at the National Library in Lisbon over the linguist born in Gotha, Germany, in 1842 and died in Graz, Austria, in 1927, being considered one of the most important linguists of the late nineteenth and early twentieth century. The session was called “Hugo Schuchardt and the search for the Luso-Asian Creole”.
Despite Schuchardt's interest on Macao's Creole, he did not publish any academic work on the subject, as he told HM Hugo Cardoso. "Schuchardt did not publish any work on Macau. However, when he covered his correspondence, it is clear that Macau was also on his radar, since he discusses the Macao Creole with several of his correspondents, including Vasconcelos milk and Gonçalves Viana," he said.
After the German linguist, Hugo Cardoso highlights, “there were actually several people who leaned over Macau Creole, including Danilo Barreiros, José dos Santos Ferreira (Adé), Graciete Batalha, Ana Maria Amaro and, more recently, Prof. Raúl Gaião and Prof. Mário Pinharanda Nunes”. Also noteworthy is the study of Marie Arana-ward "about the Creole spoken by the descendants of Macanese in Hong Kong."
Eis outra troca de correspondência com Leite de Vasconcelos, datada de 28 de Dezembro de 1889, em que são mencionados livros e dicionários sobre português e chinês. “Exmo. Friend: I hurried to respond to your ticket, since you are in a hurry. What I know from China-Portuguese is as follows: J. A. Gonçalves,-Portuguese Dictionary and China-Portuguese. Macau 1831;-China art, Alphabeto and Grammatica. (…) I estimate you to have good shoes. Friend thanks, José Leite de Vasconcellos ”.
The role of rabbit
Hugo Cardoso, whose doctoral thesis is called “The Indo-Portuguese Language of Diu”, former territory of the so-called Portuguese India along with Goa and Damão, spoke at the National Library of Hugo Schuchardt's Studies around this Creole and also the language of Batávia/Tugu in Indonesia.
For the professor at FLUL, pioneering in the study of the Creoles is an expression that rhymes with Schuchardt. The German linguist was "absolutely pioneering in this domain, not only in the study of the Luso-Sasitive Creole or even the Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles globally, but in the study of Creole languages ​​in general" and, for this reason, is "a larger figure in the history of linguistics."
Hugo Cardoso also points out that "as regards the Portuguese lexical base creoles, before him, there had been some activity, especially by Adolfo Coelho, who, in 1881, had published" Romanesque or Neo-Latin dialects in Africa, Asia and America, "in which he was a caught in various Portuguese-based Creole." However, in this work, Adolfo Coelho refers only to three Luso-Asiatic Creole: “Ceylon's (at Sri Lanka), Malaca and Macau's-giving some examples that he could get from previous publications (such as Macau's Ta-Ss-Yang-Kuo magazine)”.
The academic has no doubt that “Hugo Schuchardt was surely inspired by Rabbit's work, but his efforts to obtain primary data from many other Asian places greatly expanded the cartography of the Luso-Asian Creole and resulted in the first published news and the first grammatical descriptions of many of them (such as Diu, Cananor, Mahé, Mangolor, Mangar, Mangar etc.) ”.
Future inspirations
According to Hugo Cardoso, the German linguist left works that inspired future academics and many materials from the personal archive. "One effect of his work was to inspire other agents to develop similar work: there stands out the figure of Sebastião Rodolfo Dalgado, who led his own research and made his own publications about the Indo-Portuguese Creoles that Schuchardt had not approached, about Damão, Bombaim, Ceylon and Negapath."
In the case of José de Leite Vasconcelos, who wrote the letter cited at the beginning of this text, "it also corresponded with Schuchardt and reveals, in his linguistic studies, the impact of Schuchardt's work."
Asked by HM about the possible interconnections between the Creole of IUD, Batávia and Macao, Hugo Cardoso states that there are "continuities between the various Luso-Asian Creole, but also many differences." "The Batávia/Tugu Creole is the one that most resembles Creole de Macao, for example, at the Lexicon level. But this is understandable because it has already shown that Macao Creole has an important historical connection with the Creole that developed in Southeast Asia, in particular Malaca."
According to an academic article by Hugo Cardoso himself written in partnership with Tjerk Hagemeijer and Nélia Alexandre, entitled “Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles”, these “were, in most cases, oral languages ​​to the nineteenth century, when the first collections of oral traditions, texts and translations began to emerge, being linked“ to maritime expansion in Africa and Asia, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact between the contact. Portuguese and different African and Asian languages ​​”.
Also according to the same article, "some of these Creoles, namely in Asia, have been extinguished, having only recorded from the transition from the nineteenth century to the twentieth century. With the exception of the Creole of Alta Guinea, the vitality of the living Portuguese Creole is generally decreasing."
In the case of Creoles of Portuguese origin in the southern Asia area, they emerged from the arrival of Vasco da Gama to Calecute, India, in 1498, especially from the phase in which the entire base of the Portuguese empire the East focuses on Goa. According to the same academic article, several Creole were developed, the so-called “Indo-Portuguese” in coastal areas of India, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Burma. "Currently, its presence is much reduced: they survive those of IUD, Damão, Korlai, Cananor and Sri Lanka (Ceylon) - which, despite having, has once been used all over the island, is currently restricted to the cities of Batticaloa and Trinchomalee," is highlighted in the article. The author draws attention to the extinction in 2010 of the Vaipim Creole, in Cochim, due to the "death of what seems to have been the last fluent speaker in this region." There are then the Southeast Asia and East Asia Creole, which includes Macao. Patuá is currently “spoken with native fluency only by some people in Macau and the Macanese diaspora”, is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:19:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Church | Victims of sexual abuse want Leo XIV to assume theme</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/igreja-vitimas-de-abuso-sexual-querem-que-leao-xiv-assuma-tema/</link><description>One of the movement spokesmen that represents victims of sexual abuse in the Catholic Church yesterday asked Pope Leo XIV to put the theme as a priority and defines global rules to deal with cases.
"Now that we have a new Latin American Pope should be given an example in all Latin American episcopades that, by decision and by the Pope, there can be no double standard" among the various Catholic hierarchies around the world, "said Argentine Sebastián Cuattromo, from the adult collective for the rights of the child.
On the day the Pope made the first Sunday greeting in St. Peter's Square, praying Regina Caeli, a group of victims joined the square to ask the Vatican to impose common rules on the whole church.
Cuattromo, 42, set an example of what is happening "in the first world societies and Latin America that acts as a Vatican backyard, where the same [repair] demands are not felt, such as they are felt before European public opinion."
"As a survivor of childhood sexual abuse within the Catholic Church, with other companions survivors of this crime, we hope that the Pope will make an explicit mention of this question and an explicit reference to what he intends to do about it to pay off very large debts that, in our opinion, the Catholic Church still has to the victims," ​​said Cuattromo.
“We victims broke the taboo, silence, denial, concealment, with our struggles, with a huge sacrifice, and reached a level of visibility in public opinion,” which forced the church to face the problem.
Therefore, the global group of victims subscribed to a petition already delivered, in which they require “a true zero tolerance law that is established as canonical law”, which would “imply the immediate expulsion of the religious life of anyone involved in these acts”.
Moreover, they propose a “Truth Commission that should not be directed by the Vatican, but by international human rights organizations with the United Nations standards and with which the Vatican would have to fully cooperate, freeing all the archives he has on the subject”.
Finally, the victims intend a “justice process for the victims, where, among other things, there are concrete actions of reparation and justice for survivors around the world”, with the costs supported by the Church's own goods.

In the first person
In his particular case, Sebastian Cuattromo filed an action against a religious from a Catholic school of Buenos Aires for sexual abuse and won the process in 2012, even before the election to the Pope of then Cardinal Bergoglio, archbishop of the Argentine capital. "Then the city's Catholic hierarchy was against the victims and supported the school, which intended to silence the victims of this offense through a private economic agreement," he recalled.
"They made us feel a profound underestimation of the severity of the crime we were talking about," because, at that moment, "I was a young man who was fighting in solitude, with many doubts, with a lot less, with much anguish and felt an absolute lack of empathy and, instead, deep arrogance," he explained.
After Francis' election, "I invited him publicly and privately to meet with the victims of his country, especially those who had bad experiences," but the Pope "never had the courage or sensitivity of calling us."
For the new Pope, who is also accused of having ignored abuse complaints when he was a prior of the Augustinhos, Cuattromo expects Leo XIV to “assume this theme personally” and to be willing to “go to the last consequences”. Cardinal Robert Francis Prevost, 69, was elected Pope on Thursday, after two days of Conclave, in the Vatican City, and took the name of Leo XIV.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PME | Events promoted by Melco generated $ 1 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/pme-eventos-promovidos-pela-melco-geraram-1-milhao-de-dolares/</link><description>Melco Resorts claims to have generated about $ 1 million for small and medium -sized local businesses through events promoted last year. In the 2024 sustainability report, the game operator also highlights the results in terms of waste management and energy spending
 
The Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment Sustainability Report has just been published last year, which highlights the gains obtained by small and medium -sized (SMEs) with the events promoted by the operator. With regard to the “community engagement and investment” part, it is read that “more than $ 1.02 million for local companies and [NGO] non-governmental organizations in Macao through 21 SME events, with 603 SME and NGO participants” were generated. In addition, in the volunteering area, Melco points out that "about 3,600 participants offered their time and effort in more than 359 volunteering initiatives," "more than $ 17.42 million that were donated to decent causes in our communities."
Quoted by the report, Lawrence Ho, Melco's president and executive director, says that "21 Heart of House initiatives and community events have generated more than $ 1 million for local companies in Macao, providing 603 SMEs and NGO opportunities to connect, expand and grow." According to the official, last year were "in -depth partnerships with PME and NGO".
Regarding the relationship with local SMEs, Melco also highlights the connection with the supply chain, because “86 percent of acquisitions arose from local companies in Macao”, and of this total, “59 percent were local SME acquisitions”. Similar scenario occurred in the other operators that Melco holds in Cyprus and Manila, with local acquisitions around 40 and 76 percent, respectively.
Regarding the company's training actions, Melco says it has invested on average "582 US dollars per full -time worker in learning and development activities, which is equivalent to an average of 38 hours of training." In this context, “100 percent of colleagues participated in training actions”, can be read. In addition, "over 758,000 participants have attended more than 1,400 courses offered by" Melco Learning Academy ", which is equivalent to over 870,000 hours of learning." Also noteworthy is that, in all Melco projects, "women represent 23 percent of the boards of business and 32 percent of the higher paintings."
The report also tells that “63 percent of positions at the vice-presidency level, or above this post, were filled from local communities, increasing to 70 percent in Macao”, can read.
All for the environment
Another of the areas highlighted in Melco's sustainability report concerns environmental policies. One of the areas that is “in progress” is the energy consumption, in order to obtain more reasonableness of consumption. "In 2024, despite an increase of 39 percent in terms of the number of visitors and the rise of 19 percent in the occupation rate of the hotel rooms, along with the addition of a property and a new resort integrated into our portfolio, the energy intensity increased by 10 percent from 2023, but was 19 percent lower than our year of reference 2019."
One of the “achieved” objectives is the energy efficiency measures, which “since 2018 has resulted in an annualized savings of more than 62.5 million kWh, an increase of 9 percent compared to 2023”. Another "achieved" goal concerns the installation of "over 25,000 photovoltaic panels on all properties in Macau, Manila and Cyprus, generating about 10,000 kWh annually." Thus, in the properties of Melco "the electricity consumption from renewable sources increased by 72 percent compared to 2023".
Regarding the group's means of transportation, “buses, electric and hybrid vehicles represent 55 percent of our combined fleet, with loading stations, an increase of 25 percent compared to 2023”.
In terms of materials and waste management, Melco says it has avoided plastic spending in the order of 13.2 million bottles, thanks to the installation of “the Nordaq water filtering system that serves almost every hotel rooms in Melco Integrated Resorts”.
In addition, the example of the City of Dreams venture in Manila is presented where “a circular economy system was established in which food waste is decomposed on site, and the excess donated to a local fifth to cultivate some of the vegetables served to guests”.
In terms of water consumption, the report indicates that “despite the increase in the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate”, “total water consumption and water intensity increased only 6 and 2 percent compared to 2023, respectively, and were 6 and 30 percent lower, respectively, to the 2019 reference year”. However, this is a goal that, according to the company, is still "in progress".
Another objective highlighted in the report was the “annual economy of over 510,820 cubic meters of water through water efficiency measures, an increase of 10 percent compared to 2023.
"As we invest in people and communities, we continue to derive environmental efforts with the same determination. (…) The intensity of energy and water consumption, as well as greenhouse gas emissions, remained significantly below our 2019 base line, even adding a new property and an integrated resort," says Lawrence Ho.
The entrepreneur also referred to the increase "of the amount of valuable materials diverted through recycling and composting in global operations - 58 percent over last year." “In our restoration spaces we also fight food waste, with the 'clean dish challenge' to contribute to a 9 percent reduction in waste in the Macao and Manila restoration areas.”
“Mentality change”
For Lawrence Ho, greater sustainability in Melco requires "a change of mindset" verified in "small actions that, on scale, can have a significant impact."
Regarding the supply chain of the group's integrated hotels and resorts, good results are also highlighted. "Although the numbers do not always show exponential heels, our focus on responsible supply remains unwavering, 18 percent of all seafood bought by weight to be sustainable sources, and 100 percent of our food and drink points in Macao and Manila to serve eggs of outdoor chickens," he reads.
There is thus "an effort that reflects a deeper ambition to incorporate sustainability into acquisitions," said Lawrence Ho, who added that "more than one service, hospitality has to do with the experience it creates, the people it supports and the impact it leaves."
“Every year, Melco challenges himself to go further, believing that luxury and responsibility are not opposite forces, but partners in progress, which is reflected in the way we defend strong governance, we manage our environmental impact, we support our people and communities and lead the responsible game. This commitment to progress shaped our approach in 2024, as a year of recalibration in which we continue to strengthen operations, operations, rekindle the impetus and ensure that our integrated resorts remain at the forefront of excellence, ”he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:08:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Seismos | Macau will have a monitoring station in national partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/sismos-macau-vai-ter-estacao-de-monitorizacao-em-parceria-nacional/</link><description>The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, presented on Wednesday the report of the 2025 government lines for his tutelage, and said to the deputies that a seismo monitoring station will be created in partnership with interior authorities in China will be created
 
The Macao government announced on Wednesday the creation, together with the interior authorities of China, of a seismic monitoring station, as part of the authorities' plans to reinforce disaster prevention. “The meteorological and seismic monitoring network will be optimized, and is foreseen, in collaboration with the competent services of the interior of China, the construction of a seismic monitoring station,” said the secretary for public works and transport, by presenting, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), the lines of government action (LAG) for the guardianship, for 2025.
Raymond Tam will justified the new station with the intention of "increasing the capacity for analysis and evaluation in the scope of natural disasters." The space has realized in the direction of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), will be located in Hengqin.
"Macao's earthly area is small and population density is very high, so it is difficult to find space for the creation of monitoring stations and now with the favorable policies with Guangdong province, we have been able to build a joint monitoring station in the cooperation zone [deepened between Guangdong and Macau]," SMG director Leong Weng Kun said. The official noted that the space should contribute to "increasing prevention capacity and public knowledge about weather information."
Agree
Macao and Zhuhai signed the “comprehensive and deepening cooperation project in the context of meteorology, to reinforce the cooperation and sharing of meteorological detection equipment, computer programs and data sharing, according to a statement released by SMG at that time.
Cooperation is also expected to reinforce the “joint prevention of weather catastrophs alert systems, promote scientific and technological research and the development of artificial intelligence applied to weather activity”.
Macau is often affected between May and November by the passage of Tuffons, being July to September the period in which the highest incidence of tropical storms is recorded. This year, the territory is expected to be affected by between five to eight tropical storms, SMG announced in March.
Light Metro | Secretary admits operating gaps
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam said on Wednesday that the light meter is still short of the expectations of the population. "I have to confess that the services of the Light Metro, namely the electronic payment services, are still short of the expectations of the population of Macao," he said, promising measures for the means of transport to improve "gradually".
Environment | Policies planning will be studied this year
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam announced on Wednesday that this year will be "Study for the Next Planning of Environmental Protection", to support new "environmental policies based on a scientific and prospective view." Still in the area of ​​the environment, the ruler promised measures to achieve the national objective of the “double carbon goal”. As such, concrete emission reduction shares will be driven, including legislative elaboration for the control of emissions from non -road mobile sources, the slaughter of highly polluting vehicles, the improvement of the electric vehicle charging network, the exploitation of the potential application of photovoltaic energy in public spaces and the optimization of the energy structure ”, concluded the report.
Housing | Government admits to review the whole policy
With the reduction of demand for economic housing, the government admits to review all housing policy. "We are reviewing our policy at this time, taking into account the changes recorded. We will evaluate if there is a need to review the five housing class policy, but it is a subject that is still being studied," said Raymond Tam, secretary for transport and public works in the debate on governance lines for this year. The ruler said that "public housing policies will be reviewed and perfected, promoting the construction of social and economic housing and ensuring rational availability, in order to satisfy the housing needs of residents with different levels of income." Lots of zone A of new landfills should be completed between 2026 and 2028.</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:08:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Blackout | Normality resumed yesterday, it still causes because it</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/apagao-normalidade-retomada-ontem-causa-ainda-por-apurar/</link><description>The week has started atypically on the Iberian Peninsula. It was a few minutes from 11:30 am on Monday, when a widespread electricity failure paralyzed Portugal and Spain. Only near 23h the light returned to the Portuguese house, but the dropper
 
It was an apparent normal Monday, but this normality dissipated late in the morning with the electricity failure that gradually led to communication failures and impossibility of using mobile data. Portugal and Spain were without electricity for too many hours on Monday, an unprecedented episode in terms of energy failures.
In the case of Lisbon, the light began to fail a few minutes after 11:30 am, followed by the impossibility of communication via mobile data. Traffic in the center of the Portuguese capital became chaotic, without traffic lights in operation, generating some road accidents. Supermarkets, cafes and restaurants, with no possibility of maintaining normal operation and food properly refrigerated, closed doors. Many people, frightened by the possibility of staying several days without light, ran to supermarkets, sagging canned foods, water carboys, candles and batteries.
In addition to the unusual constraints in people's daily lives, with the suddenly closed meter and congested transport, there were suspended flights and closed airports. The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the Center of Portugal.
The circulation in the Lisbon Metropolitan (ML) was resumed at all at 08:38, Lisbon time, first in the blue and red lines at 08h, in yellow at 08:15 and green at 08:38.
"The Lisbon Metropolitano had a vast team working yesterday night [Monday] and today's dawn [Tuesday] to ensure the replacement of operating systems affected by the widespread energy failure yesterday," ML said in a statement.
Government words
In a note issued by the Portuguese government in the early hours of yesterday morning, it was said that there were already “virtually all services, including the supply of energy, restored,” Presidential Minister António Leitão Amaro told Lusa.
According to the minister, all 6.4 million customers had access to electricity in the early hours of Tuesday morning, except 800 who had faults not related to the blackout.
Leitão Amaro also said that water supply is working throughout the country, with only a few pressure difficulties in "two or three municipalities" that will be "resolved quickly".
Regarding transportation, the minister said that the "trains are working", and it is still necessary to stabilize some points of the operation, but due to the effects of 24 hours strike that took place on Monday.
About airports, “are operational,” said Leitão Amaro, recognizing that in the case of Lisbon airport, which was the most affected by energy failure and should take two days [to this day] to have stabilized flows, although the systems are all operational.
Normalized Schools and Health
The Portuguese ruler also said that, in relation to schools, the guidance issued at dawn to all directors was to open and function normally, except for cases where there may be some specific security ratio.
"The supply of fuels is normalized and did not record, at night, relevant occurrences of security or civil protection" in the country, advanced Leitão Amaro, stressing that the situation is also stabilized in health services.
"Hospitals and health centers are in terms of supply and supply to function normally," he said. "Right now, what we can say is that [energy] systems are stabilized, both in transportation and consumers supply," said the presidency minister.
In Spain there were also several embarrassment, especially at the level of transport. Pedro Sánchez, Spanish Prime Minister, said on Monday, quoted by Lusa, that this episode was unprecedented in the country. The ruler spoke to the country after the second meeting of Spain National Security Council. "All potential causes are analyzed without discarding any hypothesis," he added.
Gigawatts loss
The Spanish government leader revealed that, according to the technicians and experts of the Spanish power grid, 15 generation gigawatts "suddenly lost the system in just five seconds, something that had never happened."
According to explained, to give a dimension of the event, 15 kilowatts of generation correspond to approximately looking for total electricity in the country at the time of blackout (12:33 in Spain, 11h33 in Lisbon). "What has caused this sudden disappearance of supply" is something that experts cannot yet explain, he added.
In the early hours after the blackout, information began to circulate on a possible cyberathel who never confirmed. A few hours after the blackout, Ursula Von Der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on the LinkedIn social network that he had spoken with the prime ministers Pedro Sánchez and Luís Montenegro about the monitoring of the case.
“I reaffirmed that the European Commission has supported and monitored the situation with national and European authorities and together with our electricity coordination group. We will gather efforts and share information to help restore the electricity supply system, agreeing to maintain narrow contact,” reads one of the publications.
Eduardo Prieto, head of operations at Spanish Red Electric, told the Associated Press that the situation was not preceded by something “exceptional and extraordinary”. One of the possible causes pointed to the blackout is a rare atmospheric phenomenon, referred to as “induced atmospheric vibration”, which may have originated “anomalous oscillations” in the high voltage lines of the Spanish energy network. "These oscillations have caused synchronization failures between electrical systems, leading to successive disturbances in interconnected European networks," the Portuguese Energy company Ren to BBC told Monday afternoon. But later Ren denied this information.
Many issues
Another causes may have been technical problems in the electric network itself. Onyema NDUKA, a full -sustainability professor of energy sustainability at the University of London, said electric networks are usually interconnected because the production centers that feed them are located far from cities. This means that a power cut in a part of the grid can "lead to a waterfall effect in other areas."
"Ideally, redundancies are incorporated into the system, such as having several supply points, reserve generators located in different locations, wires and interconnected cables, etc.," he said. The solution is through energy companies to restore electricity to affected customers as soon as possible, but the procedure for doing so “has not yet been revealed,” added NDUKA.
The Portuguese authorities, cited by the AP and the local media, have so far attributed the failure of energy to unspecified technical problems, originating outside the country, but said that the investigation is still underway.
The possibility of a cyberatoque is, for now, away. “Spain has mechanisms to deal with this kind of situations. Once again, I appeal to citizens to collaborate with all authorities and act responsibly and civilly, as we have always done,” wrote Pedro Sánchez on social networks. The Portuguese National Cyberrseness Center also stated in a statement that there is no evidence that the failure was caused by a computer attack.
Speaking to Euronews, Taco Engelaar, Neara Director-General, a specialist in energy infrastructure, said the interconnectivity of national networks and their systems would mean that a failure or attack would have the same net result.
"Such a widespread failure of the network is extremely unusual and can be caused by a number of factors: a physical failure on the network that provokes the power cut, a coordinated cybercar or a dramatic imbalance between demand and the supply that has made the network system exceeds the boundaries," he said.
"If it is a system failure, then the interconnectivity between the different regional and national networks can lead to the large amount of power cuts we are watching today [Monday]," he added. "The same applies to a cybership - many of these systems are linked and sharing assets - to overthrow one can overthrow many," he said. With agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:32:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Criticized opacity in alternative investments</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/jogo-criticada-opacidade-em-investimentos-alternativos/</link><description>Ron Lam accuses the government of “acting on the closed door” compared to investments of 130 billion patacas that concessionaires will spend over 10 years to revitalize the city. Without public budgets, plans and calendar, the deputy understands that society is removed from projects
 
As established in the new game concession contracts, the operators made a commitment to contribute 130 billion Patacas over the 10 years of concession in non-game investments. The measure expected to print “vitality” to the city and stimulate local economic development has passed along with the population and various social sectors, from the optics of Ron Lam.
At today's plenary session of responses to oral interpeairs, the deputy will ask the government what measures will promote to increase the transparency of these projects, both at the budget level, but also on plans and execution calendar.
According to the interpellation released yesterday by the deputy's office, "society still knows nothing about the calendar of these plans and the form of its realization." Giving as an example the International Parade of Macao, in which the Cultural Institute said it did not assume expenses due to “narrower cooperation with leisure companies this year,” Ron Lam criticizes the lack of transparency of authorities who argued that it was not “convenient to disclose the budget value, as it involved investments from private companies”.
Since investments result from commitments made in public contracts, “the use and situation of the respective budget must be treated equivalent to that of the public purse”, argues Ron Lam.
The deputy accuses the government of being “acting on the closed door”, without prior, interchange and subsequent inspection of society on non-game investments. In fact, Ron Lam indicates that investments, which on average exceed 10 billion patacas per year, "have become a government's private portfolio for their plans and activities."
Given its nature, the legislator understands that they should follow the rules of public services, fully public capital companies and public capital companies with dominant influence, being obliged to fully publish information related to the capital involved.
Returning to the case of the Macao International Parade, Ron Lam asks what law the government was based on “to escape public law to information about non-game investments”.
The larger
In view of the scenario set, Ron Lam asks if the executive will define mechanisms that guarantee the disclosure of data on the investments of the dealers, as well as the situation of the execution of the projects.
The deputy also asks which “the service responsible for the inspection and implementation of the non-game plans of the six concessionaires, by evaluating the performance of the respective investments” and whether there is a sanctioning regime if the results did not meet expectations.
Ron Lam takes the opportunity to underline the employment situation of residents and non-residents hired by the concessionaires, denouncing the dismissal of "veteran workers who have not made mistakes, without offering them any job change option." In addition, it states that participating workers in the “specific employment + training plans” were failed to be just cause, and that residents looking for full -time employment at dealers were eventually in part time, after not being hired after employment interviews. For Ron Lam, this situation reflects the position of residents as “complement of the labor imported from the game dealers”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:10:35</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | Xia says that relationship with executive differs from separation of powers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/al-xia-diz-que-relacao-com-executivo-difere-de-separacao-de-poderes/</link><description>At a meeting with the deputies, the Director of the Office for Hong Kong and Macao affairs to the Council of State stated that the relationship between the Executive and the Legislative Assembly is different from the concept of separation of powers from the “West”. Xia Baolong characterized the relationship as a collaboration with the predominance of the executive branch
 
Hong Kong and Macau's workst a director of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Director of the Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office with the Council of State, Xia Baolong, went to the Legislative Assembly (AL) on Sunday for an ideas exchange with all the plenary deputies.
During the meeting, Xia Baolong will have stated that "the way basic law regulates the relationship between the executive and legislative powers is not the same relationship that exists in the separation of powers used by the" West "," said the president of AL. Since the beginning of his passage through Macao, and like previous visits, Xia Baolong is quoted by guardians of high government positions and, in this case, by Kou Hoi In and some deputies.
In statements cited by the Chinese channel of Rádio Macau, the president of AL indicated that Xia Baolong had binded the government's ancestry in relation to the House of Laws.
“[The Director] said we have to further reinforce and optimize the relationship between the executive and legislative powers. The two parties need respect and mutual support so that we can benefit and develop the particularity of our political system to be characterized by the predominance of the executive power,” said Kou Hoi In.
It should be noted that in no article of the basic law of the MSAR, or even the annex that regulates the methodology for the constitution of the AL, the predominance of the Executive Power is indicated in the face of the Legislative Power. In fact, Article 71 of the Basic Law establishes the possibility of the Legislative Assembly approving a motion of censorship “accusing the chief executive of serious violation of the law or abandonment of his duties”. In addition, despite having powers to dissolve the Legislative Assembly, article 54 of the Basic Law indicates two situations of conflict with the Legislative Power that may result in the resignation of the position of the Chief Executive.
Roll
During the meeting with the deputies, Xia Baolong praised the legislative work, in particular the revisions of laws related to national security, electoral laws and the legislation related to the game sector.
Cooperation with Hengqin was one of the most discussed topics, with deputies and the director to agree on the need to reinforce integration between the two territories.
The director pointed out that it is necessary to be aware and prepared “for adversities, do the work of accelerating hengqin-macau integration and the proper diversification of the economy of Macao, and take another step in optimizing the relationship between executive branch and legislative power, in the sense of respect and mutual support, to enhance the institutional advantages of the predominance of the executive branch.
According to a statement released yesterday by AL, the director expressed the desire that Macao, while “Pearl in the palm of the hand” of the homeland, will brush more sickly.
Tariffs | Appeal to the determination of local companies
Hong Kong and Macau's workst a director of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Hong Kong and Macau Affairs Office Director with the Council of State, Xia Baolong, gathered yesterday with more than 20 representatives of the business sector.
In a meeting that lasted more than two hours, the official left words of encouragement and resilience to the adversities caused by the trade war. According to the chairman of the Board of Directors of the Nam Kwong Group, Fu Jianguo, the director presented four specific requirements for the business community of Macao. Firstly, the need to have a spirit of struggle and face the current geopolitical situation at a higher level. Xia Baolong also asked entrepreneurs to have confidence in medium and long term national plans and tell the stories of China, Hong Kong and Macao well.
The president of the Macao Banks Association and president of the Bank of China's Macao branch, Jia Tianbing, said that Xia Baolong will have made hope that Macau will overcome the difficulties of economic development.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Consumption | “Grand Prix” generates almost 700 million in purchases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/consumo-grande-premio-gera-quase-700-milhoes-em-compras/</link><description>The “Great Award for Consumption in Community Zones 2025”, created to increase trade in less tourist areas, has generated almost 700 million patacas in local consumption, highlights a note from the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT).
The activity, which is already in the seventh week of operation, has had satisfactory figures, according to the government: the total amount of electronic benefits issued was 180 million patacas, of which 160 million were used, boosting consumption in Macao total of about 640 million patacas, explains DSEDT.
In addition, by May 4, more than 100,000 seniors carried their “Macau Pass” cards to get the immediate discount benefits in local stores, which have been used more than 22 million patacas, thus boosting, [consumption] at approximately 45 million patacas, it reads in the same note.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>TNR | Government refuses proportion to “unwanted work”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/tnr-governo-recusa-fixar-proporcao-para-trabalhos-indesejados/</link><description>The government will not set a proportion of non-resident workers that companies can hire, namely for work "that few residents want to exercise". In the first quarter of the year, more than 2,500 people were hired with the support of the executive, half was less than 34 years old
 
The government does not consider it “appropriate to rigidly establish a proportion to the number of resident or non-resident workers to hire by the companies, namely for jobs that few residents want to exercise,” said the director of services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), Chan Un Tong, in response to written Song Pek Kei interplies.
The deputy linked to the Fujian community warned of the “many front line jobs sought by residents and licenses”, which are eventually performed by non-resident workers ”(TNR) in game, tourism and leisure companies.
However, the director of Dsal states that “a more flexible and pragmatic adjustment in the appreciation of TNR requests”, “in articulation with the creation of the Macao World Tourism and Leisure Center, as well as the needs of socioeconomic development”.
In this sense, Chan Un Tong stresses that the fundamental principle of labor imports "is to ensure that resident workers have priority in access to employment and that their work rights and interests are not injured." The DSAL Director indicates that in all circumstances, provided that there are interested residents that fulfill the requirements for position performance, companies should always give priority to their hiring.
Fair Days
One of the central points of the written interpellation of Deputy Song Pek Kei was the difficulty in entering the labor market felt by newly elders. The director of DSAL responded with numbers. In the first quarter of this year, 2,570 employment candidates were "hired through the measures of support for the employment of DSAL, of which, about 50 percent were young people aged 34 or less."
Among the pairing events, or hiring plans for tourism and leisure companies, Chan Un Tong stressed the “Young Employment Fair”, which takes place at the end of the school year to attract college students to participate in job interviews.
At the same time, the direction of subsistence services services in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin has moved to Chinese higher education institutions where you are younger in Macao to promote internship and learning plans of Macau, Hengqin and other provinces and inland cities.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:45:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Transport | Song Pek Kei requires improvement of service on holidays</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/transportes-song-pek-kei-exige-melhoria-do-servico-nos-feriados/</link><description>Representative Song Pek Kei brokered the executive about the need to improve the public transport service on holidays, namely with regard to buses and taxis.
The deputy, representative of the community of Fujian, recalled that during the golden work week, May 1st, there were great gatherings of people at bus stops at the various border stations of Macao and the city's sights, even if companies have provided the largest transportation offer, with more careers.
“During the holidays, with the increase in the number of tourists, the government can increase the frequency of buses, so that there is a better response in the peak period and ensures a greater balance between supply and demand from residents and tourists?” Song Pek Kei.
The deputy also asks the authorities to reinforce the combat of tariff abuse by taxi drivers on holidays, as well as disseminating the results of a study elaborated on the future increase in the number of taxis in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:44:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Government | Xia Baolong stresses good start by Sam Hou Fai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/governo-xia-baolong-salienta-bom-comeco-de-sam-hou-fai/</link><description>The Hong Kong and Macao affairs director to the Council of State is on the MSAR until tomorrow. In a meeting with the chief executive, Xia Baolong greeted the “good start” of Sam Hou Fai's governance, “which determines the spirit consecrated in the important speeches of President XI Jinping”.
 
Xia Baolong's agenda on the inspection visit Macau has been intense. In the territory since Thursday, the director of the Hong Kong and Macao Labor Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CCP) and Director of the Hong Kong and Macao Cabinet with the State Council met with Sam Hou Fai on Friday morning.
According to the Social Communication Office (GCS), Xia Baolong said that the chief executive "fully fulfills the spirit consecrated in the important speeches of President XI Jinping given during his visit to Macao, and the policies and plans of the central government."
The CCP representative stressed the “good start” of Sam Hou Fai's governance and mentioned the lines of government action, “with comprehensive content covering all governive areas” and “highlighting a committed and courageous spirit”, deserving “the full recognition and support of the central government”.
For his part, Sam Hou Fai assured that his executive "studied, understood and complemented, actively and full, the spirit consecrated in the speeches of President XI Jinping."
In the afternoon, Xia Baolong met at the government headquarters with “representatives of various local associations with love to the homeland and Macau”, accompanied by the secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong. The government did not reveal the entities involved in this event.
According to the secretary, the CCP representative pointed out that the various sectors of Macao society should converge forces to promote the development of the proper diversification of the economy, and always keep in mind this task and the awareness of "preparing for adversity in prosperous times."
What comes here
On Saturday morning, Xia Baolong took a boat trip along the coast “to observe the maritime areas of Macao”, accompanied by Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, by Sam Hou Fai, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam Vai Man and General Director of Customs Services, Adriano Marques Ho. The Director of the Hong Kong and Macao Cabinet was known to the “Situation of the New Aterros, and the planning related to projects of the International Integrated Bairro of Macau, the Industrial Park of Research and Development of Sciences and Technologies and the landfill off the beaches of Colona.
After the sea tour, Raymond Tam said that "Xia Baolong expressed great attention to the improvement of the environment of the old neighborhoods and the increase in the quality of life of the population."
Xia Baolong's agenda on Saturday morning included “a reception meeting with representatives of the oldest generation who love the homeland and Macau”, namely former members of the National Popular Assembly and the Chinese people's political advisory conference. After this meeting, the official visited “the temple of A-Má, manifesting himself attentive to the exploration and transmission of Macao's history and culture. While he was around, he also took the opportunity to pass the Maritime Museum,“ to find out the evolution of the Maritime History of Macao ”.
In the afternoon, Xia Baolong, accompanied by the chief executive, also observed the various lots of land planned to receive construction projects, and attended the presentation of proposals by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP and the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM.
The official also went to the “Panda Gigante de Macao Pavilion to find out of the pavilion's facilities and equipment and its operation”. The Hong Kong and Macao Staff Director with the Council of State will continue to visit the territory inspection until tomorrow.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:42:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Employment | Leong Sun Iok warns of collecting candidate information</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/emprego-leong-sun-iok-alerta-para-recolha-de-informacao-de-candidatos/</link><description>Leong Sun IOK warns of the increase of companies that research the past of job candidates and argues that the information obtained by former employers is often skewed and unfair. The deputy calls for regulation to the government
 
Deputy Leong Sun IOK intends that the government regulates the collection of information carried out by companies on employment candidates. The request is contained in a written interpellation, in which the legislator linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) warns of the occurrence of various illegalities, without any consequences.
According to the scenario outlined by Leong Sun Iok, when applying for a job, especially through online platforms, interested parties are led to sign forms and to consent that entities research their past.
However, the deputy warns that the practice is illegitimate, uncommon, allowing the creation of informal black lists and the exchange of information between companies. This situation can result in the blocking of job opportunities for former employees who have had different employer entities. "It is a practice that blocks access to employment in an industry, which seriously undermines the right to employment," says the legislator.
Leong Sun Iok also reveals that “over the years he has received a high number of requests and assistance” from people faced from one of the six game dealers and that they have later seen themselves. "Some people who asked me for help told me that they were convinced by supervisors to say goodbye. And if they did not say goodbye to their initiative, they were threatened that they would never find employment in the industry again. All these cases reflect the damage caused by collecting information without any regulation," added the deputy.
However, the practice is not limited to this sector: "In addition to the game dealers, there are a high number of companies in Macao that also requires employment candidates to allow their past to be investigated," he said.
Against the law
Leong Sun IOK also points out that the Labor Relations Law and Decree-Law 101/84/M define that former expirers when issuing a proof of work to a former worker cannot make any unfavorable reference to its past. However, the deputy indicates that the current, even informal practice, contradicts the spirit of the law, ending up being more harmful, because the former employee has no control over information that may not even be true.
"As the verification process lacks transparency and is not controlled by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, it is unfair to employment candidates and can violate the principle of good faith in labor relations," he warns. "How will management regulate information about professional background? It is possible to issue guidelines and change the law to explicitly stipulate that former employers should in no way transmit, make statements or adopt unfavorable behaviors to workers?"</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:22:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Queen's College's cadabulas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/os-cabulas-do-hong-kong-queens-college/</link><description>Last April, during the Unified History Test of China at the Hong Kong Queen's College, several students from one of the classes copied. They shouted the answers to each other, consulted the books and the iPads. The vigilante tried several times to stop them, but failed. The board of the college said that it will only punish prevariculars students according to internal rules.
The college also notified parents about this incident, saying that as only a month left for final exams and, to avoid unnecessary pressures about the students, the test will not be repeated. The results of the China Unified History Test of this class will be canceled and the classification to this discipline will depend on the final exam. For the other classes, the classification of China's History discipline will take into account the results of the unified test and the final exam.
Students often happen to copy the tests. With new technologies, the tools that allow them to “make cheats” change every day. From traditional paper rackets to intelligent devices, the evolution of these tools reflects the erosion of academic integrity through the abuse of technology. In the past, the students wrote the answers to pieces of paper, commonly known to rabids, and took them to the exam room; Or asked to go to the bathroom and so they consulted the materials. With the popularization of intelligent clocks, real -time concerted communication functions allow remotely online cabular. If the vigilante is not aware, students can use smart watches for this purpose while sitting in their places. Real -time -time translation functions have recently appeared that can directly convert English to Chinese texts. The constant evolution of these tools makes the work of vigilantes increasingly difficult.
To get a thief, we need evidence. To get a gussy student, you also have to have tests. However, for vigilantes, it is always very difficult to obtain these evidence; If they can't prove that the student copied, it is complicated to accuse him. In the case of the "Cada on paper", the student can swallow or hide it as they are being exposed, or argue with the vigilante and refuse to deliver the rabula. Teachers are not police officers and are not entitled to review students, so several "jams" escape unpunished for lack of tests and naturally cannot be accused. These cases, to some extent, lead other students to risk.
There is certainly no lack of diligent students, scholars and workers in an exam room. When these students discover the colleagues' strokes, they can choose to report them, but if they do the most likely it is to be ostracized and subject to intimidation. In addition, the highly stressful exam environment makes most students focus on their own answers, and have no time or energy to observe others. Therefore, the reports of colleagues represent a small percentage and the exposure of these cases depends on the vigilantes to be committed and want to discover the offenders.
Copy, use fake certificates and plagiarize are all academic violations of the same nature - dishonesty and bad practices. In recent years, it is not difficult to find these cases in the news. Having this incident in one of Hong Kong's oldest elite colleges, reflects not only the moral deviation of the students, but also the distortion of learning values. The more students make glow, the greater the change of values ​​and the less they will study hard.
The “elite” group created by false achievements may seem knowledgeable, but in fact is devoid of value and will eventually expose their lack of knowledge in their areas in the future. Just think: Can a doctor without skills treat a patient? Can a lawyer defend the client without knowing the law? This hidden danger is like a clock pump. Its destructive power continues to manifest in the next decade or even later, and finally the whole society will pay its price. We have to stop this problem.
Schools have to take proper measures, prescribe the right medicine, improve situations that give it azo and cultivate the correct values ​​in students. Containing the jar requires multi-dimensional efforts.
Firstly, students who copy should be severely punished and this behavior cannot be tolerated. Schools must have rules for dealing with unusual behaviors. For example, if at least two vigilantes see a student swallowing papers, it should be disqualified from the exam. After the punishment must be re -educated. Schools must have subjects that deal with academic integrity and compulsory courses that shape the values ​​of learning.
It is necessary to make students understand that a grade of 60 is not shameful, but it is vital that they realize that a false 100 has to be punished. Since this pedagogical idea becomes consensual, society will no longer judge heroes by their grades, students will be able to maintain their moral values ​​and the entrepreneurial spirit of “knowing shame and then learning to be brave” will reappear. Only after stressing the importance of identifying the “real value” of students can education return to its original purpose of “teaching and sharing knowledge”, the reasons that lead to glow can decrease and the promotion of talented people will no longer be a game that compares large and small number.

Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>New legislatures, old alternatives</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/legislativas-novas-alternativas-velhas/</link><description>We had never watched an election campaign for such poor quality legislative elections. It is perfectly seen that certain politicians have no level to govern and to present to the Portuguese alternatives that provoke them a better life. And there are other politicians who did not expect or were prepared for elections. An election campaign where it is immediately detected that people are not sensitized and are largely disillusioned with their promises never fulfilled.
The people do not want to know if Luís Montenegro have a family business and draw money from potential customers with state calls. The people do not want to know if Pedro Nuno Santos bought a lot in Alentejo or a Maserati.
The people want something concrete. You want your life to improve, not to go to the supermarket and always see the prices to increase; that when filling the deposit of your car finds that the same fuel in Spain is much cheaper; He wants to know when more electric centers are built around Greater Lisbon, so that a national blackout does not harm an entire country and a capital full of thousands of tourists, some sleeping on the floor of the airport -in this regard that the blackout was a shame regarding the dependence of Spain and the fiasco of wind and the endless stations -the people want to see their salaries at the level of Europe and that their salaries and their salaries The 200, 300 and 400 euros pensions end; wants their children and grandchildren to emigrate because there is no accessible housing for young people; Want to see several public homes, at a price accessible to poor elderly, with quality in well-being and good service; wants corruption to abandon state departments, namely in the municipalities where an investor of a charm hotel is waiting for two years for the opening license just because it was refused to deliver a particular peculius to the edil; The people want to stop seeing the vacant lots to serve as a large deal of certain presidents of parish councils; The people want them to end the emergency urgencies and that future mothers do not have to have their children inside an ambulance because the incompetence of a health minister continues not to solve anything about the closure of obstetrics; The people only want politicians to compete that the country are ruled, they are governor to more than four million citizens living in poverty level.
Pre and the election campaign itself has been a disappointment. The television debates had a very low hearing rate. Leader politicians of parties with parliamentary seat have shown a nullity of alternative proposals for a 20 or 30 -year -old future. Malously moderate television debates, where the channel employee intended to be the vedeta and could only interrupt who was there to discuss. The very debate between Montenegro and Nuno Santos was uninteresting, although Montenegro, surprisingly, appeared tense and nervous, and therefore lost the debate.
The election campaign is on the streets of the country and you, dear readers, do not believe: the multitude baths are over. People do not mobilize by loudspeakers who scream to the four winds that is the best for prime minister. The parties pay for “volunteers” that go after the party leaders with flags and shouting alive to the party concerned. No one cares for the passage of a party caravan and, this, is serious. It is a sign that democracy has not fulfilled its role. In such a way, the neo-fascist André Ventura, who even said that he would be a prime minister, had behind him in a certain fifty people, stopped, spoke to journalists in a critical tone against AD and PS, and there went to his “Trumpinha” life……
Then, in this election campaign we have something laughable but shameful. These are the polls. We are already used to never getting it right and being performed with maneuvering normality. This time, shame does not exist. We reached the point of a television station presenting a sort of probing daily, always giving a substantial advantage to AD, when it should be noted that that "information" only aims to maneuver potential voters to vote for AD.
There are polls for various tastes, but an intercampus poll, which presented the Socialist Party ahead, was not released on any television channel, which are in the hands of Cristiano Ronaldo and other millionaires like him. The polls, which maneuver the opinion of the potential voter are the reflection of the type of policy that is today practiced in an election campaign. "A" insults "B". "B" insults "a". "A" insults "C". "C" insults "a". "D" insults "C". "C" insults "d". Do you want you to draw a drawing? I do: Montenegro insults Nuno Santos. Nuno Santos insults Montenegro. Montenegro insults Ventura. Sumura insults Montenegro. Mortagua insults Ventura and Ventura responds in the same way.
And this is political, is it an alternative to have a better country? Don't even think. Portugal is living the worst moment of seriousness and political ethics of its 51 years of democratic regime. It's pity. And no medicine is guessed for the patient.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:21:54</pubDate></item><item><title>ATFPM Right of Response</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/direito-de-resposta-da-atfpm/</link><description>Right of response about the article “Elections | PS returns to denounce alleged atfpm practices”, by journalist Andreia Sofia Silva - Jornal Hoje Macau 9, 2025
Hon. Mr. Director,
Under the right of response to the Press Law, the petitions, managing bodies of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM), for the proper effects concerning the publication mentioned in the subject in an epigraph, in which the alleged involvement of ATFPM “volunteers” in the approach of voters with a Macao post station, in the context of the next Portuguese legislative elections, is mentioned, in the context of the approach of voters, in the context. This way come to request the publication of the following clarification regarding the content of the article “Elections | PS again denounce alleged atfpm practices”, by journalist Andreia Sofia Silva - Jornal Hoje Macau, May 9, 2025:
The ATFPM vehemently rejects falsehoods and innuendo emanating from sources linked to a foreign political party, which have echoed in certain Portuguese social media. The facts disclosed are devoid of veracity and have no direct or indirect relationship with this association.
ATFPM regrets the persistence of the Socialist Party in Vehicular Unfortunate allegations that aim to denigrate the image of this institution, which constitutes an unacceptable interference in the affairs of an association based in the Special Administrative Region of Macao.
The ATFPM expresses its concern in the face of the repeated practice of individuals with links and interests to the referred political party of the Portuguese Republic to invoke falsehoods and impute untrue facts to this association, conduct since 2024. Such a practice, devoid of any foundation, is abusive and deserves the firmer public conviction, since no connection of this organization was not proven to the alleged facts.
ATFPM reiterates its vehement repudiation and informs that it ponders the activation of the appropriate legal measures against the Socialist Party, in view of its attempt to influence and manipulate public opinion in its favor, namely in the china electoral circle.
In addition, the ATFPM considers the appeal, by the Socialist Party, to the Portuguese Media in Portuguese for the dissemination of communications and complaints, which constitutes an indirect form of electoral propaganda, through social communication bodies that receive subsidies from the government of the special administrative region of Macao. This use of Macao's media by the Socialist Party is not common practice among other political parties in Portugal.
Grateful for their attention, we took the opportunity to present to V. Ex., Mr. Director of Jornal Hoje Macau, our best greetings.
Association of Macao Public Function Workers on May 9, 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:20:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Manifestation contained</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/manifestacao-contida/</link><description>During the “golden week” on May 1st (Labor Day), the city center of Macao was flooded by a crowd, however, the environment was contradictory and the Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) continue to fight for survival. In the first quarter of 2025 the global unemployment rate (1.9 percent) and the unemployment rate of the residents (2.5 percent) increased 0.2 percentage points, compared to the indicators of the fourth quarter of 2024.
These numbers indicate that Macau's labor market is impacting economic recession and the influx of foreign workers. The numerous stores that closed in residential areas clearly reflect economic desolation. Although the “large award for consumption in community zones 2025” seems to function as a temporary accelerator, it does not attack the root of the problem.
There is social discontent in relation to the administration of the Government of MSAR, however, on May 1st, except for the situation of a citizen who was taken by the police to be investigated in the prosecutor for protesting without warning the direction of services to the Labor Affairs (DSAL), there were no manifestations or protests. As the public complaints accumulate, the social atmosphere has become visibly silent. And is that good or bad?
The media revealed that the “Power of the People” group had notified the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) of its intention to organize a protest manifestation on May 1, according to the provisions of the “Law of Meeting and Manifestation” Law. Police officers “express their concern repeatedly, promoting several meetings with group members to analyze the situation and take the necessary measures” as well as “warning them of the various possibilities in the face of“ uncontrollable situations ”that would lead them to take on“ joint and and several liability ”or, otherwise, risk the“ law relating to the defense of the state's security ”. They felt the weight of the invisible pressure and reluctantly chose to present a letter where they exposed their views to DSal.
An article from another newspaper praised CPSP for the way he dealt with this case. He claimed that CPSP had significantly perfected its ability to disable “the Protest planned for May 1st”, and believed that CPSP, which supervises protests and manifestations according to the law, had adopted an approach to “pros and cons” to neutralize a mildly inflamed protest, eliminating possible social disturbances that came. On the one hand, the CPSP totally respected the rights of residents to protest and to express themselves and did not explicitly reject the notification presented by the group “Power of the People”. On the other hand, CPSP used persuasion to convince the group to cancel the “May 1 protest”.
Some people become condescending and think that the city gets more peaceful without protests or manifestations, and this thought is the one that worries me the most.
Someone with a minimum of common sense will understand that the accumulation of social discontent is not a motivating force, but a destructive force. The promulgation of the “Right of Meeting and Manifestation Law” has been intended to safeguard residents' freedom to manifest and protest, as guaranteed by the Macao Basic Law, not to ban them.
In the past, the Government of MSAR effectively communicated with the protest and demonstrations organizers and coordinated these events very well. Unfortunately, in recent years, authorities have been very nervous or guided by their own priorities; and often excite the subjects and rush to us to the level of national security. If a slight cough is condemned to cause a highly contagious and fatal virus, a lot of labor is wasted and many resources, and the vitality of society is suffocated!
A forest without any sound is terrifying and a silent river is full of murderous omens. A society cannot survive without any noise.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:47:38</pubDate></item><item><title>History | Launched Chinese edition of the book by Manuel V. Basilio</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/historia-lancada-edicao-chinesa-do-livro-de-manuel-v-basilio/</link><description>It's called “Stories and Memories-Baixo do Monte and surroundings”, it is a book by Manuel V. Basilio and its edition in Chinese will be released on May 19 at the headquarters of the Macao Retired, Retired and Pensioners Association (Apomac). The work, presented in 2023, now wins a new version and has a preface by Lok Po, director of the newspaper or Mun
 
It will be released next Monday, 19, the Chinese edition of another book by Manuel V. Basil, a retired teacher who has been dedicated to various investigations into the history of Macau. This time, this is the book “Stories and Memories-Baixo do Mount and surroundings”, already presented in its Portuguese version in 2023, and now has preface by Lok Po, director of the newspaper or Mun. The launch runs at the headquarters of Apomac - Macao's Retired, Retired and Pensioners Association.
According to a statement from Apomac, since the first launch of the work that “several people encouraged the author to also edit a Chinese language version, given the interest that may be with the Chinese community in the dissemination of one of the most striking periods in the history of Macao - the integration of the Chinese population in the so -called 'Christian city'”, when the effective miscegenation of western and eastern crops created the barrier created by the old wall and doors of the city, all living in harmony as neighbors ”.
We were in the mid -nineteenth century. More specifically, from 1844, the Portuguese administration "authorized all foreigners to buy or build houses and have any terrain in Macao." Thus, "this measure eventually favored years later, the Chinese traders who had some wealth and came to Macao from southern China to escape the Taiping rebellion, also known as the Taiping Civil War, which lasted from 1850 to 1864, having settled here and restarts their activities as entrepreneurs."

According to the same note, the end of the separation between the so -called Christian city and the zone in which the Chinese community lived was thanks “to the end of the coexistence of two jurisdictions in the Macao Peninsula - the Portuguese and the Chinese, respectively, inside and outside the city's wall that, over centuries, separated the two communities”. It was also fundamental for this new phase “the beginning of the so -called colonial period, in which the Portuguese government had territorial autonomy throughout the peninsula to the door door, which later became known as the siege door”.
Election zones
Where did the Chinese were installed when the end of this separation between communities and modes of life? The book describes that "one of the zones preferred by the Chinese traders to reside was precisely the one that was then called Baixa do Monte, because it is near the heart of the city."
"Since then some names of public roads have changed by the desire of their residents. Do you know, by chance, the old name of Travessa dos Anjos? And the reasons why it was changed, and what was the old method used to give names to public roads? Did you know that some Chinese were also awarded with honorific titles by the Portuguese court, and that these titles had an expiration date for one or two lives?" in the note. To all these curiosities and historical facts the book of Manuel V. Basilio intends to respond.
In the case of Baixa do Monte, and according to the information available in the “register of public roads and other places of the city of Macau, 1957, it was a designation for“ the southern hill slope and covering an entire area, vaguely defined, ranging from Fortaleza to the nearby streets of Palha, S. Domingos and Pedro Nolasco da Silva, between Rua de S. Paulo and Calçada do Monte ”.
This was an area “where many Portuguese and macanese families lived”, and to prove this fact, Manuel V. Basil “collected data on several families, especially macanese, who resided in that city from the mid -nineteenth century to the second half of the twentieth century, and whose collection includes, namely, Baptist, Baptist, Valoma, Marques, Xavier families includes families. Crestejo, medicines, Lopes, Morais, Nogueira, Simões, Cameirão, Costa, Silva, Fernandes, Souza, Pires, Gonçalves, Jorge, Eusébio, Placé, Osório, Santos, Rosario and Martins ”.
From 1963, there are families who lived in blocks 3 and 4 of “Kwok Wá Tai Há”, ie “Capitol neighborhood”, next to the sidewalk of truths, and “formed, for decades, an authentic community neighborhood of Macanese”. Currently "just a few macanese reside there."
Biographies and titles
But not only of streets speaks this book. The author also wrote summarized biographies of some individuals and Chinese traders who lived in downtown Mount, namely Chou Iau and Fong Seng, who, in 1880, were awarded the title of Knight by the honorary mercy of King D. Luís I of Portugal, due to the valuable contributions they made to Macau's economic and social life.
The author also makes a brief description of Divinity on Tcha, the temple dedicated to him, along with the sidewalk of truths, as well as the festivities in his honor that are held annually on the 18th day of the fifth month of the lunar calendar.
It also makes a brief summary of the history of some buildings that existed and others that still exist, located in the boundary zone of Baixa do Monte, including the Capitol Theater building, since its inauguration, on April 18, 1931 until its closing, on August 1, 1987, and its later requalification, which became the “Capitol Theater Shopping Center”.
Thus, “Stories and Memories - Baixa do Mount and surroundings” includes “Memories, Experiences, Uses and Customs, as well as stories based on the history of Macao”, as well as valuable information about the toponymy of some Macao zones and their history.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:25:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Venice receives “Parallel Worlds”, from Macao, at the Architecture Biennial</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/veneza-recebe-mundos-paralelos-de-macau-na-bienal-de-arquitectura/</link><description>It was inaugurated last Thursday, in Venice, at the 19th Biennial of Architecture, the show “Parallels”, which represents Macao at the Biennial and which is a project carried out by photographer Iwan Baan with architectural students at the University of St. Joseph (USJ). The curatorship is still with Wang Shu, the last Pritzker award, and Lu Wenyu.
This is a show that reveals the coexistence of “parallel worlds” in Macao, combining “Macao urban landscape images captured by the famous humanistic architecture photographer Iwan Baan and facilities created by teachers and students from the Faculty of Architecture of the China Academy of Arts and the Faculty of Architecture and Design at the University of São José de Macao”. Thus, it is represented “the urban fabric of the city where Chinese and Western cultures, old and new styles have coexisting for over 400 years,” says a note from the Cultural Institute (IC).
There are, in this show, four “parallel worlds”, namely “the deep space of the historic city, the hotel architecture that embodies the merger between East and West, the geometric order of the modern city, representing its vibrant development; and the future projection of a digitized and intangible city, which defines an innovative view for Macau”.
Reveal the heritage
According to the IC, "through aerial photography and a unique perspective, Iwan Baan demonstrated the relationship between architecture, urban landscape and the natural environment of Macau, being highly engaging and narrative." "Young people from the colleges of architecture in the interior of China and Macao brought to the exhibition several creative facilities that provide ideas for the future development of Macao's urban architecture."
Leong Wai Man, president of the IC, said in his speech in Venice that "world cultural heritage focused on the historic center of Macau and the modern buildings around the city show the harmony between the past and the present, constituting a vivid representation of the integration of Chinese and Western cultures," this exposure in Venice "reflects exactly the precious cultural content of Macau."
The exhibition “Parallel Worlds” can be seen until November 23 this year at Arsenale, Campo Della Tana, Castello 2126/A, 30122, in Venice.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:00:51</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM Theater | Symphonic concert about Disney's movie “Frozen” at the end of the month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/teatro-mgm-concerto-sinfonico-sobre-o-filme-frozen-da-disney-no-final-do-mes/</link><description>The MGM Theater welcomes, on May 31st and June 1st, the Symphonic Concert entirely dedicated to the Disney animation movie “Frozen”, thinking about World Children's Day, which is celebrated precisely on the first day of June. The song is in charge of the Macau Orchestra
 
The smallest and fans of Disney's movie "Frozen" will have the opportunity to see and hear a concert entirely to the history and characters of this production, being an initiative to celebrate World Children's Day, the ephemeris celebrated on June 1. The concert, welcomed by the MGM Theater on May 31st and June 1, takes place, respectively, at 20h and 15h.
With co-organization of the Cultural Institute (IC), it is, according to a note of this organism, with “a charming and fantastic concert that will combine live symphonic music with scenic technology, bringing adult children and friends from Macao to the magical cold world”.
The sound is in charge of the Macau Orchestra (OM), which will play live “various iconic songs from the animation soundtrack, synchronized with images projects on a giant 900 square meter and 28 million pixels, installed in the theater, with the 19.1-channel 19.1-channel sound system”.
Thus, with the use of technology, the “fusion of sound and image will create an immersive experience that transports viewers to a fascinating ice and snow kingdom”, verifying “the excellence of international level and international level” in the space chosen for both shows, the MGM Theater. According to the IC note, this show room was officially recognized by Disney as a space to perform Disney concerts in Macao.
Voices and Folding
The concert has a “cast of excellence, bringing together musicians and top singers from Macao and abroad”, being directed by OM assistant conductor Tony Cheng-Te Yeh. The songs of the animation will be played by OM and several “international renowned singers”, such as Alyssa Fox, who played Elsa in the American tour of the Broadway musical “Frozen”; Ray Liu, who folds and sings Anna's voice in the Mandarin version of the animation, RJ Woessner, who gives life to the characters Kristoff and Hans and, CJ Tan as Olaf, as well as the Vocal Vocal Vocal Band group.
The movie “Frozen” premiered in 2013 and “won the world”, having won the Oscar for best animation movie. Highlight for the song, taken from the movie's soundtrack, “Let It Go”, which became a success on the global scale. There are also other great musical hits that came out of the movie "Frozen", such as "Do You Want to Build to Snowman?" and "For the First Time in Forever", which had the power to "captivate hearings of all ages."
“Let It Go” received the Oscar for best original song at the 86th edition of the Academy Awards and raised three important awards on the 57th Grammy Awards.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 03:59:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Cunha Foundation hosts “polyphony” until next week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/fundacao-rui-cunha-acolhe-polifonia-ate-a-proxima-semana/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts until Saturday next week, the 17th, the collective exhibition “Polithonia”, with works by artist Gu Yue and six doctoral students from the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must), co-organizer of the event.
The project makes known 20 works that represent the forms and styles of renowned artist and professor Gu Yue and his disciples Luo Su, Zhu Zhaohui, Wang Kongbin, Ding Song, Guo Weiwei, and Wei Dongsheng.
According to a FRC note, this exhibition presents “a visual banquet that transcends tradition and contemporaneity, the material and digital, the place and the global, through the collision of various media and the resonance of ideas”.
The works include various art forms, “such as installations, oil paintings, lacquer paintings, sand paintings and details to detail brush, displaying Macau's unique artistic ecosystem as a cultural convergence point”, is referred to.
The name of the exhibition originates “in musical terminology, referring to the opposition and symbiosis of multiple voices”. The presentation of the show states that "the mission of art is to create cognitive disorientation", and "through the confrontation between traditional crafts and the new media, and the rapport of local cultural genes and global issues, it breaks the linear narrative and invites the audience to calibrate their cognition in the" glow between brightness and residual shadow. "
Joint work
Professor Gu Yue aligns his work and the investigation with the main theme of the exhibition. The creations of the six doctoral students "start from individual experiences and respond to propositions such as identity, time and memory in the age of digital capital, also forming a multi-wing resonance of thought."
Exhibition is not only a concentrated exhibition of academic achievements, but also a speculative experience on the essence of art. “In this culturally stratified place of Macao, polyphony tries to use art as a prism to reflect the symbiotic possibilities of multiple realities,” describes the team, cited by the same note.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:45:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau maintains shipping by air to the United States</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/macau-mantem-envio-de-encomendas-por-via-aerea-para-estados-unidos/</link><description>The Macau Post Office Director told Lusa yesterday that, unlike neighboring Hong Kong, the region kept ordering orders to the United States (USA), but only by air. On May 2, the US government eliminated the exemption of customs rights on small orders from mainland China and Hong Kong, such as those sent by the giants of Electronic Trade Shein and Temu.
"In practice, now Macau is not included and the mail [which] goes to the United States is walking, except maritime. The rest, we keep normal," said Derby Lau Wai Meng. The Director of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT) explained that the shipping of any goods, from sea to the US, implies a passage through Hong Kong, one of the busiest ports in the world.
That is, there is only the hypothesis of sending orders by air, confirmed Derby Lau. "This case is sensitive," admitted the leader. "I think it's better not to talk [this subject], because the best thing is not to remember us," he added.
Trump in Action
The end of the exemption of customs rights on small orders from mainland China and Hong Kong emerged in an executive order, signed by US President Donald Trump on April 2.
The document asked the US Secretary of Commerce, Howard Lutnick, to submit a report, within 90 days, if the end of the exemption should also cover Macao, "to avoid escape to these measures."
On April 16, Hong Kong's post office announced the suspension of sending orders to the United States in response to the imposition, "abusive", tariffs by US authorities.
A presidential decree issued by Donald Trump, still in the first term, in 2020, eliminated the preferential treatment granted to Hong Kong. The ancient British colony is therefore also affected by the 145 percent surcharge imposed on China.
Chinese Communist Party's main official for Hong Kong and Macao affairs and governments of both regions accused the United States of imposing tariffs in mid -April to sabotage China.
Macao Executive leader Sam Hou Fai criticized the United States for the “abusive imposition of customs taxes on all his business partners,” including China, “under various pretexts”. Yesterday, the US representative for the United States, Jamieson Greer, said Washington and Beijing will suspend the majority of customs rights and negotiate for 90 days.
In the negotiations made in Geneva, the United States and China agreed to reduce the reciprocal customs rights imposed on each other, passing Chinese imports to pay a 30 percent customs right, while US products will pay a 10 percent customs right.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:36:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco | “Employment + Training” plan offers 30 vacancies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/melco-plano-de-emprego-formacao-oferece-30-vagas/</link><description>Enrollment opens today for another specific “Employment + Training” plan launched by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and, this time, by Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, which will make 30 vacancies available to “entertainment ambassador”.
According to a statement released yesterday by DSAL, the plan follows the “first hiring, then training” regime, “providing training in all aspects and professional development opportunities for Macao residents who are interested in exercising game -related entertainment activities”.
Admitted candidates will participate in training actions, organized by Melco, over a year and a half, which include a practical part and real context of work. The training will appeal candidates for “knowledge of activities in theaters and other leisure establishments” and enable them to respond immediately to “safety incidents and crisis control management”.
Registrations end on May 20, in a week. For May 27, a lecture is planned and interviews will be held to candidates.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:22:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Church | Stability in local Christian communities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/igreja-estabilidade-nas-comunidades-cristas-locais/</link><description>Robert Francis Prevost was chosen for days as the new leader of the Catholic Church, having adopted the name of Leo XIV. HM has heard two analysts on any impacts on the functioning of dioceses in Macau and Hong Kong and what is expected is continuity and stability, such as a peaceful relationship with Beijing
 
Only two days lasted the choice of a new Pope after Francis' death. Leo XIV, born Robert Francisc Prevost in Chicago, USA, was the choice of Vatican's conclave cardinals. HM spoke to two analysts to try to understand any impacts or changes in the functioning of the Catholic Church on the dioceses of Macau and Hong Kong, but the course seems to be that of stability.
“I don't think there will be anything concrete. The situation in Hong Kong and Macau is quite well understood and stable. I know that Catholics and people of good will in both places will be praying and wishing Pope Lion all graces, blessings and successes in their pontificate,” said Stephen Morgan, Rector of the University of St. Joseph (USJ).
Already Peter Stilwell, who preceded Morgan in the rectory of USJ and is currently director of the Department of Ecumenical Relations and Interreligious Dialogue of Patriarchate of Lisbon, argues that "the relationship of Hong Kong and Macao with mainland China [regarding religion] is determined by the 90s agreements."
“What will happen, at the end of the 50 years planned for the transition, will depend on many variables in a world and in a country (China) in very quick transformation. However, the Holy See has established with both dioceses [from Macau and Hong Kong] a relationship that maintains them outside any episcopal conference and in a direct relationship with Rome. To answer 'no'. However, the evolution of the agreement as Beijing, about the appointment of the Catholic bishops to the dioceses of mainland China, will be an important factor to observe, ”noted Peter Stilwell.
He also added that "those interested in this evolution, however, will be closely observed how Pope Leo XIV Restructure, or not, the Vatican Secretariat of State - namely, the team that directly accompanies the Dossier of China."
Ancient relationship
Asked about the Vatican State relationship with Beijing with Leo XIV in power, the former USJ rector also does not foresee major changes. "The relationship will continue, discreet, but persistent, as so far. Contact has a 400 -year story, and we should not reduce it to the recent agreement on bishops."
It is an agreement that "takes place between two entities with millennial memory, which think in terms of decades and centuries." "The fact that the new Pope is US nationality will be irrelevant. As head of state, his nationality has now become the Vatican City; and the daily interpeairs he will respond will have the prospect of a religious community that today extends to virtually every country in the world," said Peter Stilwell.
Stephen Morgan believes that Roberto Prevost's choice for Pope has nothing to do with Trump's presence at the White House or political moves in the face of the China-Use relationship.
"His election will have more to do with the fact that he is familiar with the situation of Catholics in the developing world and having had a few years of experience in Roman Courier, where he has established himself as a pair of safe hands he thinks for himself and hears broadly."
Robert Prevost was brought to the Vatican by Pope Francis in 2023 to be responsible for examining the nominations of bishops around the world, one of the most important works of the Catholic Church, thus gaining prominence in the conclave.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:20:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Civil Construction | Dsal organizes courses with a</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/construcao-civil-dsal-organiza-cursos-com-um/</link><description>By the end of this month, the registration process for training courses in the area of ​​construction, held between the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the University of Macau (one). Thus, the “Certificate Course for Security Inspector” and the “Training Course of Civil Construction Security” will take place, with a total of 155 vacancies for both formations.
According to a note from DSAL, these actions are taken in mind that “the construction sector in Macao has been developing quickly”, so “occupational safety and health management measures are fundamental to occupational safety”. The trainees will be entitled to a 2,500 patacas formation allowance paid by DSAL and certificate.
In the case of the Superior Construction Safety Technician Training Course, graduates who are completing the course and have at least two years of professional experience in the area of ​​construction management, can request the license of a higher technician in this area. Both courses are taught by the UM continuous education center.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:19:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Traffic | Changes in Salgado Fish Beco</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/transito-mudancas-no-beco-do-peixe-salgado/</link><description>Beco do Peixe Salgado, near Casa do Mandarim and Rua do Almirante Sérgio, will be the target of traffic changes in order to prohibit road circulation in this street, “in response to citizens' requests and after analysis and evaluation”.
According to a note from the Traffic Affairs Services Directorate (DSAT), the installation for the traffic signaling forbidden to vehicles in the Salgado Peixe Beco will be made tomorrow, 14, and it is aimed to “clarify regulatory measures applicable to this thing”.
Thus, this Wednesday is foreseen the “conditioned circulation in Rua do Peixe Salgado during the intervention”, so DSAT appeals “to the understanding and attention of drivers”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:18:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Andy Wu says concerts are not enough to attract visitors</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/turismo-andy-wu-diz-que-concertos-nao-bastam-para-atrair-visitantes/</link><description>The government says it wants to bet on the organization of large -scale shows to streamline the economy in neighborhoods with less tourism, but Andy Wu, a tourism -related associative leader, says that this is not enough, defending the sale of tickets with associated discounts to take more people to consume in the territory
 
It is not music for the ears of tourism. Na visão de Andy Wu, presidente da Associação da Indústria Turística de Macau, não basta a realização de grandes espectáculos em Macau, nomeadamente concertos, para aumentar o número de consumidores nos bairros comunitários, ou seja, que estão mais afastados dos pontos turísticos.
According to the newspaper or Mun, Andy Wu argued that complementary measures are needed to perform the concerts, namely the sale of tickets combined with associated discounts in local stores, so that people who go to the concert can also consume before the shows.
Regarding the night economy, in bars and nightclubs, Andy Wu has stated that it still cannot be attractive enough for tourists, so it is important to have complementary measures to concerts.
The government said that it is negotiating with ticket sales platforms a partnership to have ticket packages with discounts in stores, which should be a reality in the second half of the year, following many visitors from the interior of China to watch concerts or sports competitions in Macao.
Regarding the discount model to adopt, Andy Wu argued that one can take into account the format of the consumer award for the currently underway community zones, which would allow visitors to use coupons in local commerce. This would be more suitable than leading tourists to consume only in stores adhering to the discount program, he said.
Be effective
Given the negotiations carried out by the executive, Andy Wu referred to the newspaper to expect these partnerships to be launched in due time, namely in June, when the second large concert was held at Cotai, in the outdoor shows, near the Grand Lisbon Palace venture.
Andy Wu has not yet forgotten public transport factor, essential for tourists to have better access to community neighborhoods before and after the shows. The suggestion of experimental creation of exclusive buses, of the genus Shuttle-Bus, was made, with concrete paths between the shows zone and the community neighborhoods, so that visitors move to less known neighborhoods in Macau during the day and see the show at night.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:14:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Mud | More parking for motorcycles and cars</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/taipa-mais-estacionamento-para-motos-e-carros/</link><description>The outdoor public parking park located on Governador Albano de Oliveira Road is reducing to only five the number of heavy vehicle parking spaces, creating places for motorcycles and increasing the number of car seats, also changing the rates to pay. The change comes into force from the 21st of this month.
According to the order published yesterday in Official Bulletin (BO), there are now 73 places for light cars, 50 places for motorcycles and mopeds and only five places reserved for heavy vehicles. In addition, the payment will be made every half an hour, with the bikes paying a level during the day and 50 dollars at night, while the vehicles pay four patacas a day and two patacas at night.
In the case of heavy vehicles, the payment is five patacas during the day, and half of that amount in the night period.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:11:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails about sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those waiting for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of it, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “I never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timothy should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained the guts to the dogmas of the "modern". For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstandings, if they are fortunately fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered a war, the best animals will be beheaded. superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over the referected zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Nissan | Cuts of another 10,000 jobs around the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/nissan-cortes-de-mais-10-mil-empregos-em-todo-o-mundo/</link><description>Nissan automotive construction will suppress more than 10,000 jobs around the world, in addition to the nine thousand already announced in November, several Japanese social communication agencies yesterday reported. According to NHK television, the approximately 19,000 workers who will be dismissed are about 15 percent of the Japanese company's workforce.
The automobile group was deemed to confirm this information, which was also released by the Diário Económico Nikkei. Nissan, in which the French group Renault holds a 35 percent participation, is expected to publish on Tuesday the results for fiscal year of 2024-2025 finished in March.
Nissan is expected to announce a record annual loss in a context of restructuring the company and after the application of more tariffs by the United States. By the end of April, the automotive group had already foreseen net losses between 700 and 750 billion yen (between 4.32 and 4.62 billion euros) in the fiscal year of 2024-2025, about nine times more than it foresaw in February.
The damage is explained, in particular, “by the costs associated with the ongoing relaunch plan,” said the automotive builder at the end of April.
Given the persistence of the slowdown of sales in their main markets - the American and the Chinese - Nissan announced in early November that it intended to suppress 9,000 jobs worldwide and reduce its production capacity by 20 percent.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:38:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | Gold falls more than 3 % after agreement between Washington and Beijing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/tarifas-ouro-cai-mais-de-3-apos-acordo-entre-washington-e-pequim/</link><description>Gold, asset of safe haven in times of uncertainty, fell strongly yesterday, more than 3 percent, endangering the level of $ 3,200, after the United States and China announced a trade agreement.
At 11:00 in Lisbon, the price of gold went down 3.23 percent to $ 3,217.58, although after the announcement of that agreement, a few minutes after 8:00 am, it fell even more pronounced to 3,216.29 dollars. And this after the US and China announced a reduction in tariffs. Specifically, Chinese tariffs will go from 125 percent to 10 percent over US products in the next 90 days.
The US will do the same from 145 percent to 30 percent over Chinese products, as part of the terms agreed over the weekend to lock the new trade war this year. The tariff reductions agreed by China and the US will take effect on May 14.
The above agreement between the two main commercial powers drives the dollar, affecting metal prices in general. Gold also descends with the reduction of geopolitical tensions, following the ceasefire agreed between India and Pakistan, while Russia and Ukraine can meet Thursday in Istanbul to start a diplomatic way to resolve the conflict.
With yesterday's fall, gold is moving away from the current historical maximum of $ 3,414.65, checked on April 21.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:37:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine | China expects lasting and binding peace agreement</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/ucrania-china-espera-acordo-de-paz-duradouro-e-vinculativo/</link><description>China said yesterday that it expects a lasting and binding peace agreement to end the war in Ukraine after Russian President Vladimir Putin's proposal to open direct negotiations between Kiev and Moscow.
"We hope that the parties involved will continue to use dialogue and negotiations to reach a fair, lasting and binding peace agreement that is acceptable to all parties involved," said Lin Jian, spokesman for the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
Vladimir Putin proposed, on Saturday night, that Ukraine started direct negotiations between the parties on Thursday in Istanbul, a city that welcomed, in March 2022, the first and unique negotiations between the parts in more than three years of war.
Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky reacted to the proposal considering it "a first step" of Kremlin to end the war, but insisted that first there must be a ceasefire before Ukraine feels to negotiate.
Russia's proposal was presented a few hours after Ukraine and the European allies demanded from Moscow to agree with a total and unconditional ceasefire for at least 30 days, otherwise it will face new economic sanctions.
This requirement arose after a meeting held on Saturday in Kiev among the heads of state and government of Ukraine, France, Germany, the United Kingdom and Poland, the so -called “coalition of the disposed”. The Russian proposal was also looked at with suspicion by the Ukraine European allies that required any conversations to be preceded by a lasting ceasefire.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:32:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Tibet | Evaluation of damage after 5.5 earthquake on the Richter scale</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/tibete-avaliacao-de-danos-apos-sismo-de-55-na-escala-de-richter/</link><description>A 5.5 degree earthquake on the Richter scale yesterday shook the Chinese region of Tibet, where authorities are still collecting information on possible land damage and landslides, local media said.
The quake was recorded at 5:11 places in Lazi County of the city of Xigaze, with the epicenter at a depth of ten kilometers, according to the center of seismological networks of China.
Firefighters and rescue teams of the affected county have already moved to the Epicenter Zone, where the tremor was strongly felt, according to local agencies, cited by the Official News Agency Xinhua. The same sources have added that they are collecting information about possible lands and injured.
Tibet and other areas of Western China are often the stage of seismos, due to the proximity of the friction point of the Asian-Indian tectonic plate, but due to the low population density of the region, the earthquakes often occur in poorly populated areas.
Still, on January 7, a 6.8 magnitude earthquake in the Tibetan region, with epicenter in Tingri County, near the northern Evereste field, killed 126 people, injured more than 200 and caused the collapse of hundreds of homes and infrastructure.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:31:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Visit | Beijing receives Lula and other Latin American leaders</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/visita-pequim-recebe-lula-e-outros-lideres-latino-americanos/</link><description>Beijing yesterday received several Latin American leaders, starting with the President of Brazil, on the eve of a diplomatic forum aimed at reinforcing relations with the region, in the face of commercial tensions with Washington.
Some Latin American leaders are already in China, such as Luiz Inacio Lula da Silva, who arrived in the capital on Saturday for a five-day state visit. Since returning to power in early 2023, the 79 -year -old has been working to improve the country's relations with both Beijing and Washington.
Symbol of strong bilateral relations, Brazilian exports to China exceeded $ 94 billion in 2024, according to United Nations data. As an agricultural power in South America, Brazil exports mainly soybeans and other raw materials to China. In the opposite direction, the Asian giant sells semiconductors, phones, vehicles and medicines.
Just yesterday, Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi spoke in Beijing with Cuban homologist Bruno Rodriguez Parrilla.
The Asian giant has intensified economic and political cooperation with Latin American countries in recent years and expects them to join forces in the face of the imposition of tariffs on imports by US President Donald Trump.
An approach that will be celebrated today with the opening in Beijing of the summit between China and the community of Latin American and Caribbean states (Celac), a regional intergovernmental organization. The meeting is an opportunity to evaluate the relations between the two blocks in the context of the trade war launched by Trump and Washington's pressure to contain Beijing's influence on Latin America.
Two thirds of the Latin American countries have already adhered to a track, a route, China's main commercial infrastructure construction program (bridges, airports, ports, roads), carried out mainly in developing countries. In a sign of the growing weight of the Asian giant, China has supplanted the United States as the main commercial partner of countries such as Brazil, Peru and Chile.
Presidents Gifts
Other expected participants in the China-Celac Forum include Colombian President Gustavo Petro and Chilean President Gabriel Boric. Last week, Gustavo Petro announced that he would sign, during the trip to China, a letter of intent for the country to join a track, a route.
Chinese leader Xi Jinping should also speak today at the opening of the China-Celac Forum. Chinese foreign assistant minister Miao Deyu said on Sunday that Beijing "has always addressed the development of Latin China-América Relations from a long-term strategic perspective."
"The peoples of Latin America and Caribbean intend to build their own destination, not to serve as a backyard to any country," said Miao, in reference to the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:28:02</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea | Kim Moon-Soo confirmed party presidential candidate in power</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/coreia-do-sul-kim-moon-soo-confirmado-candidato-presidencial-do-partido-no-poder/</link><description>The South Korea Popular Power Party (PPP) yesterday formalized Kim Moon-Soo's record as a candidate for the country's presidentials after he wins a dispute with another competing potential for political formation.
The PPP-Party in Power-was made with the National Election Commission, after the General Assembly of Political Formation rejected a motion on Saturday, which wanted the candidate for the election of June 3 to be former Prime Minister Han Duck-Woo.
Han and Kim tried unsuccessfully over the past week to reach consensus and unite the candidacies to avoid fragmentation of the conservative party's votes, which is expected to suffer at the polls the consequences of the deep political crisis triggered by the declaration of martial law in December by the deposed President Yoon Suk-Yeol.
Han Duck-Woo has been interim president of the country on two different occasions after Yoon's dismissal, and has sought to dissociate himself from the controversial leader and the brief statement of martial law. Kim, for his part, was Minister of Labor, having been appointed presidential candidate in the PPP primaries. However, the former minister's candidacy was questioned with the appearance of Han, who had the support of the PPP board.
"This presidential election is crucial, as it will define a leader capable of overcoming the crisis our nation faces and working for the happiness of the people," Kim told reporters after registering the candidacy in the election agency's offices in Gwacheon, southern Seoul.
Prior to the presidential election of June 3, the party candidate in power has announced that he will focus the strategy in building a large coalition, both inside and outside the party, with the aim of reaching national unity and listening to the voice of the people.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:17:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Interchange elections this Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/filipinas-eleicoes-intercalares-esta-segunda-feira/</link><description>Monday's interchange elections in the Philippines are seen as a referendum to the management of President Ferdinand Marcos Jr., with the polls showing that the coalition of former head of state Rodrigo Duterte is well positioned.
At stake, there are half of the 24 seats of the influential Senate, whose results dominate most of the attention, as well as the entire low of Congress Chamber, as well as 18,000 places in the main municipalities of the country. Marcos Jr., or Bongbong as he is known, has been at the front line of the campaign, with a list of 11 Senate candidates.
These include renowned names of Philippine Politics, such as Erwin Tulfo, a member of the House of Representatives and the most supported candidate for a senator place, according to a Social Weather Stations (SWS) inquiry, and the World Pacquiao World Candidate and former candidate icon.
Candidates supported by the alliance for the new Philippines (Alyansa to Sa Bagong Pilipinas) by Marcos Jr. “continue to lead the polls just a week before the elections”, with eight of them well placed to win a senator place.
"Since we took office in July 2022, the Philippine economy has been recognized worldwide as one of the fastest growing. That's why the Philippines are known today," Marcos Jr. said in a 'preview rally' in Manila, as they are known in the Asian country the great electoral events in which the parties end the campaigns.
Balance in polls
However, polls also show the strength of other candidates supported by the coalition of former President Rodrigo Duterte, accused of crimes against humanity by the bloody drug war and detained since March in The Hague waiting for trial.
Senator Bong Go, who seeks reelection, is the second candidate in the polls, while at local level a poll held by the University of Mindanau pointed out that Duterte could win the presidency of the Davao Chamber, his stronghold in the south of the country, despite not being in the archipelago of more than seven thousand islands. The campaign began marked by the dispute between Marcos Jr. and the Philippine Vice President, Sara Duterte, an alliance formed to gain power in 2022, but shortly after victory began to collapse.
Duterte's arrest came to feed the confrontation between the two fields, surpassing the political lines. Senator Filipina Imee Marcos, the president's older sister and supporter of Duterte, took the break with Bongbong's electoral list.
About 68 million Philippines are called to choose 12 senators, 254 district representatives, 63 party representatives and 17,942 governors, members of provincial assemblies, mayors and counselors. The scrutiny will also cover the legislative seats of the Bangasamoro Muslim Autonomous Region, on the island of Mindanao, the second largest in the archipelago in the south.
Portuguese eyes
The Portuguese MEO Marta Temis (PS) will lead the EU electoral observation mission to these Philippine Legislatures. It is the first mission of the EU to a Philippine elections that “marks a step towards reinforcing relations between the EU and the Philippines,” according to a statement from the European External Action Service.
Marta Temi, who led the PS list to the European Parliament in the June elections last year, was designated by the EU high representative for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy, Kaja Kallas. The mission in the 13th most populous country in the world will be “a huge challenge,” added the MEO.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:15:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | Trump announces “great progress” in negotiations between China and the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/tarifas-trump-anuncia-grandes-progressos-nas-negociacoes-entre-china-e-eua/</link><description>United States President Donald Trump welcomed on Saturday with the "great progress" of negotiations with China in Geneva on tariffs.
"Very good meeting today [Saturday] with China in Switzerland. Many things have been discussed, many things have been approved. A total but constructive way has been negotiated. For the sake of China and the United States, we want China to open to US companies. Big progress has been made on the social network of which it owns.
Conversations between the United States and China delegations about tariffs that threaten to shake the global economy were resumed yesterday in Geneva, after the meeting between US and China representatives, an Associated Press agency said.
As a sign of the importance of what is at stake, the two countries sent Geneva, this weekend, high-level representatives for conversations: Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, and Commerce Representative Jamieson Greer of the United States and the vice-minister, He Lifeng, Chinese.
"The contact established in Switzerland is an important step in promoting the resolution of the difference," wrote the Xinhua news agency before the meeting.
Last month, Donald Trump increased US customs rights over China for a total of 145 percent, and China retaliated at a 125 percent rate on US imports.
So high rates are essentially equivalent to the boycott of each other, disturbing exchanges that last year exceeded $ 660 billion.
On Friday, even before the negotiations began, Trump suggested that Washington could reduce the tariffs imposed on Beijing, stating, in a public social network publication: "80 percent tariffs look good to me! It's with Scott [Bessent]."</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:12:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Lula da Silva goes to China in search of investments in the middle of the trade war</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/lula-da-silva-vai-a-china-em-busca-de-investimentos-no-meio-da-guerra-comercial/</link><description>The Brazilian president visits Beijing today and tomorrow to attract investments, in the middle of the trade war started with the tariffs imposed by the president of the United States, Donald Trump, whose main target is China.
In this visit, which follows the Moscow, where he watched, Friday, the celebrations of Victory Day on Nazism and met with Vladimir Putin, Lula da Silva will meet with Chinese President Xi Jinping and will attend the fourth meeting of the China-Celac Forum (Latin American and Caribbean States Community).
China has been the largest commercial partner in Brazil since 2009 and the government has in advance an entourage composed of ministers to prepare Lula da Silva's visit, whose announced objective is to attract investments from the Asian giant in infrastructure projects, as well as creating alternatives in global trade.
Leonardo Trevisan, professor of economics and international relations at the Pontifical Catholic University (PUC-SP) and the School of Advertising and Marketing (ESPM), stressed that the visit happens at a delicate moment and that China is a fundamental partner for Brazil, but recalled that entrepreneurs and the Brazilian government also work not to lose proximity to the Americans.
"Brazil has never had a concentration in a single country in all Brazilian economic history. China today owns 35 percent of Brazilian exports and 80 percent of our main product, which is soy, and almost 70 percent of oil derivatives (…). China occupies a space in the very relevant Brazilian economic scenario," he said.
"However, even with this space, for various reasons, even for a cultural identity with American reality, today there is also a formal request for Brazilian business leadership with productive structures, with US productive chains," added Trevisan.
Asked if China would today be a partner in the most reliable global scenario for Brazil than the United States, an assessment by the Brazilian international advisor, Celso Amorim, the expert stressed that in the relationship with the Chinese prevails the idea “friends, friends, business apart”.
"Friendship with China is a situation, it is a reality, but business aside. China is today the great buyer of Brazilian exports," he said.
"But taking into account what we have, our history, all our experience, everything we have with American culture, maybe it's a little difficult for us to say that we will suddenly make a spin in this regard," he added.
Sales map
Trevisan pointed out that Brazil did not join the new Silk Route, an international infrastructure project launched by Beijing for over a decade, and noted that, although smaller, Brazilian exports to the United States have higher added value.
"While we sell commodities to China, to the United States we sell products that have value added, products that generate jobs here, products that consume technology, products that somehow make Brazil more updated in global production chains," he explained.
In a recent movement, China has increased Brazilian soybean purchases due to the tariffs imposed against the United States, another major soybean exporter. The replacement of US soybeans has been quoted by US producers' associations that fear losing the Chinese market irreversibly.
Asked if this hinders the Brazilian position in negotiations on 25 percent steel and aluminum rates imposed by the United States, Trevisan assessed no. "The United States understand that we are selling soy, but our industry made it very clear that it intends to continue like this, even with quotas, very close to the American industry," he repeated.
"The United States will probably understand that they are momentary business and that China has offered to buy. Another thing is well -built economic ties over decades with productive chains," he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:09:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and see as soon as I was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of basic and secondary education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Camões Institute - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>João Romão, academic: “Macau is in a highly privileged position”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/02/joao-romao-academico-macau-esta-numa-posicao-altamente-privilegiada/</link><description>Professor at Yasuda Women’s University in Japan, João Romão prepares to launch in June a book entitled “Economic Geography of Tourism”. Speaking to HM, the academic enhances the interconnection between tourism, economy and geography, and lists its possibilities, limitations and effects, including Macao
 
 
In this book it speaks of the concept of “spatial economy”, in connection with tourism and geography. How is this connection?
Economic geography combines the geographical context with economic processes, being studied the spatial distribution of economic activities. The economy of tourism is particularly sensitive to these geographical constraints, as they are the characteristics of each place that enhances the development of certain products or services. These characteristics widely exceed the physical aspects of the territory and also include culture, history, ways of life or even institutions and legal frameworks. The case of casino, something particularly important in Macao, is a good example of the importance of legal aspects to develop certain types of tourism. Economic geography has a wider scope than the spatial economy, more focused on strictly economic aspects. Being evident in tourism this relationship between economics and geography, this book establishes a double approach that systematizes the interdependence of these three aspects it refers. First explores how the concepts and theories of economic geography can apply to tourism. In the second half it makes the opposite route, discussing how the analysis of relevant problems of contemporary tourism justifies the use of economic geography. Examples are the degradation of local resources, environmental impacts, contribution to climate change, acceleration of gentrification processes or disturbance of community modes of life.
Can having an excessively -dependent economy of tourism constitute a problem or salvation?
The two things, and are both cases that economic geography can help to understand. The industrialization of economies is linked to the agglomeration processes of activities that reinforce each other when they reach a certain scale. This allows the massification of production and consumption, with reasonable costs. Contemporary industries, more associated with the integration of digital technologies and creative processes, are less clustered in specialized industrial development zones, but tend to focus on large cities and metropolitan areas. It also follows that rural areas, islands, or sites that have not followed industrialization processes, have more difficulty mobilizing investments, technologies or qualified people to innovate and develop new industries. In such cases, tourism often appears as the possible solution as it can be developed with incorporation of technology and relatively low knowledge. On the other hand, tourism consumption, not being essential to human life, is very sensitive to income fluctuations.
Can you give examples?
This was visible, for example, with the 2007/2009 international crisis. Tourism is also very vulnerable to safety problems or international epidemics, such as COVID-19 has demonstrated to the extreme. Economies too specialized in tourism are very vulnerable to external shocks and less resilient to crises. It is also visible that, being the tourist development often supported by intensive and weak labor services, the specialization in tourism can cause, in the long run, embarrassment in terms of population qualifications, the ability to innovate and integrate technology or to add value to the regional economy.
The book also speaks of “intelligent tourism” and “co-creation of experiences”, using the megados and IA. Is tourism definitely becoming more digital?
Social networks are fundamental instruments for new generations. However, they began to generalize the tools for planning or promotion of travel supported by artificial intelligence. The so-called “intelligent tourism” more generally designates the use of digital technologies to intensify information flows, consolidate the formation of networks and promote more informed and shared decision making, eventually contributing to the so-called “co-creation of experiences”. Tourism digitization has its origins in service distribution systems originally developed by airlines since the 1960s, but it would be the internet to accelerate and globalize digitization.
And social networks.
The emergence of social networks promoted the creation of a more interactive universe, potentially in real time and involving wide numbers of users and various types of supports. The generalization of the use of mobile phones permanently connected to the Internet, even on foreign travel, has further increased this potential for intensive and interactive use of data and information. This "co-creation", however, hides obvious imbalances of power.
Such as?
With regard to tourists, or consumer in general, it is usually the role of providing information, for example through social networks. This information is obtained, accumulated and marketed, sometimes without consent or even without knowledge, to eventually translate into the creation, adaptation or promotion of products and services. This process is particularly important in the case of tourism, because there is usually a long period between the decision to travel and the trip itself. This period of travel exploration and planning is used by tourist marketing companies to try to influence choices. This type of interaction also introduces a difference in the “spatiality” of the provision of tourist services, which are usually produced and consumed at the same time and in the same place, in a direct relationship between producer and consumer. The digitization of tourism anticipates most of these interactions and information flows and transfers them to large technological companies or marketing and distribution.
In a world where more and more travel, the routes are shorter and access to information is immense, how can countries and regions be competitive in the tourist offer?
Contemporary tourism lives in a highly competitive international environment. But just as there is a wide variety of destinations and offerings, there is also a wide range of preferences and consumption, what is called “hyper-personalization”, the result of such abundance of information and opportunity for interaction. The challenge that is placed on destinations is to identify the resources, products and services that can be adjusted to a particular group of consumers, to communicate effectively. This competitiveness greatly goes beyond the strict scope of tourist services because it also requires mobility and transportation services, varied infrastructure, safety, medical support, or easy communication. Anywhere you want to develop your tourist industry have to intervene about all these factors.
The book also addresses how “social processes” shape the development of tourism. In the case of China, for example, do you believe we are watching a change, which will have consequences for Macau?
It seems to me that Macau is in a highly privileged position to develop other forms of tourism. China is the largest issuing market in the world, the widespread rise of income in recent decades allows many million people to explore the opportunity to travel. Macao is a very close and distinct destination, with its historical and cultural particularities. For the Chinese population it was not easy to visit Macau and there is certainly a great interest.
How does the Great Bay project come in this?
The strategy that is being followed by integrating the Great Bay allows you to develop a cosmopolitan and diverse offer that can certainly attract Chinese tourists and other parts of the world. Moreover, these three areas have excellent hotel and tourism schools, which guarantee qualified personnel for tourism management and planning. The element of differentiation that Portuguese culture introduces in this context can certainly contribute to the success of the transition from a casinos focused on other forms that value culture and heritage more.
Is it possible to have sustainable tourism?
The problems and difficulties of tourism sustainability are more visible than in other sectors. This “spatiality” of tourism (where the consumer is obliged to move to the place of consumption) implies that the consequences of this consumption become more evident. These effects are less obvious when it comes to the unsustainability of industrial units or intensive forms of agriculture in relatively isolated areas. As mass reduction and investment reduction strategies also apply to tourism, the consequences of the environment or the quality of life of residents in destinations can be devastating. Sustainability implies a long -term perspective based on the idea that today's decisions do not imply future negative consequences. Sustainable practices depend on the control of the impacts that accumulate over time by individual and independent economic agents.
How can this control be done?
When a hotel or airline defines what ability to install on their services they may eventually estimate the impact that consumers will have on the local environment or economy. They will have more difficulties in anticipating that impacts will be generated in the next 10, 15 or 20 years to investment. And surely it will be impossible to measure how this impact accumulates the impacts caused by other service providers, now or in the future. In other words, although the idea of ​​sustainability is widespread accepted, economic agents do not have mechanisms or instruments in practice. Regulating the use of resources and territories by public entities with a more comprehensive and future perspective can contribute to the sustainability more effectively than the regulation associated with market dynamics, which in many cases has been revealed highly predatory. The Chinese economy is one of these examples and may eventually benefit from it.
And in the concrete case of Macau?
Macao has historically known problems: ultra-urbanized and polluted areas, with large energy consumption and waste production; Great concentration of tourists in a relatively small area of ​​great historical and cultural interest; Great dependence on the game, with the resulting imbalances in the appropriation of tourism benefits. The ongoing transition to new forms of tourism should better solve these problems and state regulation will certainly have better results than based on market dynamics.</description><pubDate>2025-04-02 23:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>José Paulo Esperança, Associate Rector of the City of Macau University: “Languages ​​cannot be controlled”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/jose-paulo-esperanca-reitor-associado-da-universidade-cidade-de-macau-as-linguas-nao-podem-ser-controladas/</link><description>Co-author of the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with Luís Reto and Fernando Luís Machado, José Paulo Esperança reveals to HM that the work edited in 2016 and 2018 is being updated, especially due to the growing global value of the language. The Associate Rector and Professor of the City of Macao University suggests partnerships with Macau under the Editorial Project
 
Launched the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, in co-authorship, about the global value of the language. Plan a new edition or update?
Undoubtedly. We are working in this regard, there was a recent conference in Macao and Professor Luís Reto, former Rector of ISCTE, presented some more current elements that were developed. He has worked on a very important issue, which is the role of Portuguese as a frank language, which was for a few centuries in Asia. The exchange between Dutch and the kingdom of Zion was made in Portuguese, because it was the common language used at that time, before English became the contemporary frank language. Therefore, there is a whole interesting story of Portuguese and the role it had in the first pinyins that existed, with the Chinese and the use of the [Roman] alphabet in Vietname. There are a number of elements that are not, therefore, very publicized, and the work of Atlas is the same, to disclose some economic dimensions of the language.
What are these dimensions?
One is the exchange of foreign trade and investment, which is very facilitated by the language. We also talk about migrations, tourism, students' exchange that is greatly influenced by linguistic proximity. Therefore, today we have a set of elements that are very interesting, and we hope to develop some more important partnerships with Macau.
As?
More at work, Professor Luís Reto is doing, which maintains an investigation team about the value of Portuguese. He has collaborated with the Portuguese Language Museum of São Paulo, for example. It is a museum space that was renewed after the fire that destroyed it. In addition, there is a project with Cascais City Council to develop such a structure, and we hope to do some works with Macau, in order to create three poles for the projection of the Portuguese language. As for Atlas' materials, we would like to have a continued update model, as this data is out of date very quickly. The work was edited in many languages, including Mandarin. This is the moment when we would like to give the book a more historical and deep dimension, with more knowledge about the teaching of Portuguese in the world.
What balance does this teaching do today?
Portuguese is developing a great deal of mother tongue and is effectively one of the most expanding languages ​​due to demographic growth in Africa, with countries such as Angola and Mozambique, which around 2050 will have populations of over 100 million inhabitants, each. The Portuguese thus consolidates itself as a language of the southern hemisphere, but much more from Africa, supplanting Brazil itself as the place of largest number of speakers of the language. All of this generates enormous potential, and this also occurs due to the great exchange of universities and internationalization of teaching. Today there is the possibility of Portuguese being a language of science, there is more publications in this language. This is a great challenge because English is the contemporary language of scientists. We want to contribute to all these dimensions, and Macau can also play an important role there. Macao is indeed a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and can play a significant role.
Is Macao an ideal place to train Portuguese teachers who do not have Portuguese as a mother tongue? Do you fear that the territory loses relevance in this matter before the offer of courses in the interior of China?
I see this question more as complementarity than competition. We have identified about 60 higher education institutions in China that have Portuguese courses, but I think Macau has very interesting conditions to start teaching from primary to secondary education so that children have been able to have learning from an early age. It does not mean that there are no young Chinese who began to learn their tongue in adolescence that they speak fantastically, which surprises me, but it is easier to start earlier and earlier. This will be easier in Macau. What is important is to create conditions for greater economic collaboration to many levels, such as joint research. In this respect, Macau has a very interesting opportunity. At the City of Macau University we are very interested in increasingly collaborating with researchers who visit us and work with our teams.
Can you give me examples?
Brazil is today one of China's great business partners. There is a lot of exchange in both directions, but one of the themes that is little studied, and in which I work hard, is the internationalization of Chinese companies. To what extent do these companies follow a model of internationalization similar to that of other countries that started this process earlier? I speak of the United States of America, the European countries, but also of Japan and others. China has, in fact, different models of presence in countries that are not yet well known, and this is important to realize, so that we know how to facilitate this process of exchange in a world that lives periods of some setback. It is very sad. I always remember a great economist of Portuguese origin, David Ricardo, who clearly explained how world trade is beneficial to everyone and how countries can take advantage of this situation. Therefore, applying tariffs, making such commercial barriers harms countries that are major exporters, such as China or Germany, and countries that today have a cultural export capacity, for example, and are not just importers.
In relation to the new Orthographic Agreement. It continues without a standardization in Macau. Does it worry it?
Languages ​​are dynamic and cannot be controlled. We think today in English, and we realize that there are almost incomprehensible ways to each other, such as the English one in Nigeria or Australia. Americans have difficulty realizing the Australians. In the nineteenth century, Portuguese from Portugal and Brazil were closer, then some disagreement emerged. There was an effort in Brazil to propose an orthographic agreement, and the Portuguese joined, resulting in a series of negotiations. There have always been resistances. I remember that Fernando Pessoa suggested the famous phrase “My homeland is the Portuguese language”. It was curiously a manifestation of some conservatism, because he thought Pharmacy had to continue writing with pH [Pharmacia]. In fact it did not make much sense. Portugal ended up seeking to impose a certain standardization based on the most genetic changes in the spelling agreement. It is not a process that has been running a hundred percent well, and has been universally adopted. African countries have become more defenders of Portuguese from Portugal. There is sometimes some confusion, but I understand that intercomprehension still remains, achieving a homogeneous language, more perhaps than English.
 
Between words and numbers
José Paulo Esperança is a doctorate in Economics from the European University Institute and was president of the ISCTE Department of Finance and Accounting - University Institute of Lisbon. The “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with editions in 2016 and 2018, contains “a large set of indicators that reinforce the idea of ​​the growth of teaching, speakers and the written use of Portuguese in the world”, having been the target of a series of recent initiatives in Macao.
One of them took place on March 17, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, with a session of the “Roda de Ideas” cycle, entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, which was attended by the former ISCTE Rector, Luís Reto, and José Paulo Hope himself. In addition to the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, José Paulo Esperança is the author of other works in the financial area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:08:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the other, the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hate speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the guide circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of specimens produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos also underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitano Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major objective will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name at Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSAR VICTORY AND TOP-10 to Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite Safety Car's entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet beginning, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Motorial Council approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young driver, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There are as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and a MSAR test enthusiast, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The growth and development potential in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into detail, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula cup last year, says that “this big step will undoubtedly benefit local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Assemblies and the FIA ​​2025 conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, the third of the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Touring cars finding begins with greater presence Macaense</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/16/gp-apuramento-dos-carros-de-turismo-comeca-com-maior-presenca-macaense/</link><description>The Macao-Macao Road Sport Challenge Touring Car Championship will start this weekend at the Guangdong International Circuit in the city of Zhaoqing, 200 kilometers northwest of the ride. For this race, which will serve as qualification for the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, will be on the starting grid a dozen Macau pilots, including five Portuguese names
 
Among the sixty subscribers, all equipped with two types of vehicles - Toyota GR86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) - are well -known guys from Macau's motor racing. With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit in November last year. Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the focus on pre-season has been in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
Also back is Célio Alves Dias, after a difficult year in 2024, far short of his expectations. For this, the pilot Macaense bet on changing the chassis of his Toyota Gr86. This year, its objective is to account for the twenty -fifth participation in the largest sports event of an annual character of MSAR, so all the details are important.
Back is also Jerónimo Badaraco (Toyota Gr86), a pilot who, in the Macao Grand Prix last year, reached second place at Macao Road Sport Challenge. After having been modest in the finding events, “Noni” was very strong in the city streets, where he was the best Macaense pilot, in a race won by law Kit Meng.
In debut this year will be Maximian Mannão. Bringing with him a nickname with a huge tradition in Macao's motorsport, the young Maximiano, who competed for several years in the local Karting events and, in 2022, participated in a Formula 4 Chinese Championship race, will make his debut at Macau Road Sport Challenge with a Toyota GR86.
The Macanese presence will be reinforced by Dionísio Albino Pereira, a pilot regularly seen in the coloane Karting events, which will conduct a Toyota GR86 from LW World Racing Team. In 2013, he competed in the Macao - Macau Touring Car Series Tourism Championship, then driving a Honda Integra DC5 from the Pas Macau Racing Team team.
The representation of the territory in these findings will also feature Chi Wang, Carson Tang, IP Tok Meng, Chan Chi Ha, Lo Kai Tin and Lou Check In.
It will be to hurt
In 2024, the Macao-China General Automotive Association (AAMC) was able to place all the drivers of the Macau Tourism Championship in the end of the Grand Prix. This year, it seems that the scenario of organizing two races for local pilots will be impossible. As such, these qualifying races will have a much higher impact, and only half of those now registered will have entry ticket for the largest annual sports event of MSAR.
Another novelty for this year is that all cars will be equipped with tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, as had already happened in the Grand Prix. However, this year there will be a new compound, the same for everyone, which may shuffle the favorite accounts. Centralins will continue to be drawn, as in the past.
Since the number of participants is high, AAMC will divide the pilots into groups A and B, not two but four races in total. Each race will have 15 laps, two of which will be played on Saturday and two on Sunday.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>