<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>World leaders applaud peace agreement between Israel and Hamas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/lideres-mundiais-aplaudem-acordo-de-paz-entre-israel-e-hamas/</link><description>Several world leaders welcomed the peace agreement between Israel and Hamas announced by US President Donald Trump, praising the imminent end of the war in Gaza and the release of hostages after two years of conflict.
Trump announced on Wednesday that Israel and the Islamist movement have accepted the “first phase” of his peace plan, which envisages the partial withdrawal of Israeli troops from the Gaza Strip and the release of 20 hostages still alive in exchange for Palestinian prisoners.
“All hostages will be released very soon and Israel will withdraw its troops to an agreed line as first steps towards a strong, lasting and eternal peace,” Trump wrote on the Truth Social network.
The news was received with enthusiasm by leaders from several countries. Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney congratulated Trump on his “essential leadership” and expressed relief at the imminent release of the hostages. "Peace finally seems possible. We urge all parties to quickly implement the terms of the agreement," he said. Japan also welcomed the understanding, which government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi classified as “an important step to calm the situation”, thanking the United States, Egypt and Qatar for their mediation efforts.
From Canberra, Prime Minister Anthony Albanese and Foreign Minister Penny Wong highlighted that it was “a very necessary step towards peace” and defended a two-state solution, stressing that the plan excludes Hamas from any role in the future administration of Gaza.
United Nations Secretary-General António Guterres described the agreement as “a desperately needed breakthrough” and called for its full implementation, stressing that “it is an opportunity to recognize the right to self-determination of the Palestinian people and move towards a two-state solution”.
Hamas confirmed the understanding, guaranteeing that it “ensures the end of the war, the withdrawal of the Israeli army and the entry of humanitarian aid”, and called on Israel to fulfill its commitments “without delays or changes”. Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu called the deal a “historic achievement” and thanked Trump for his “determined leadership and global efforts,” saying: “With God’s help, we will bring everyone home.”
Euphoria and relief
According to official sources, the release of the hostages is expected to begin on Monday, after the agreement is approved by the Israeli Government, and the military withdrawal will cover around 70 percent of the Gaza territory.
“This is more than Gaza, it is the beginning of peace in the Middle East,” said Trump in an interview with Fox News, assuring that the United States and neighboring countries will support the reconstruction of the enclave. He added: "Other countries in the region will help because they have immense wealth. We will be involved to ensure Gaza is successful and peaceful."
In Tel Aviv, families of the hostages gathered in euphoria in Hostage Square, amid tears and chants of “Nobel for Trump”. “I want to smell my son,” said Einav Zangauker, mother of one of the hostages, emotionally. In Gaza, where the ceasefire was met with a mixture of relief and distrust, displaced people and residents expressed hope of being able to return to their homes.
“We want to return, even if there are no more houses,” said Alaa Abd Rabbo, displaced from the north of the Strip. The agreement brokered by the United States, Qatar, Egypt and Türkiye marks the most significant attempt to end the war since the conflict began in October 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:15:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Overseas Chinese | Lam calls for continuity in promoting Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/chineses-ultramarinos-o-lam-pede-continuidade-na-promocao-de-macau/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, defended the continuation, by the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau, of the work to promote the territory, at a time when the entity celebrated, on Wednesday, 57 years of existence.
According to a statement, O Lam said, in a speech, that the association should promote the specific advantages of Macau as a Sino-Lusophone platform in addition to assuming the bridge between China, Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, as well as Spanish-speaking countries.
Lam also hopes that the association will continue to support local and Mainland Chinese companies in accessing international markets, in addition to supporting the import of certain international projects to China. This is so that Macau can explore the “circle of friends” and partners at an international level, supporting the country’s development in opening up to the outside world.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:31:05</pubDate></item><item><title>UnionPay | First branch opened in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/unionpay-aberta-primeira-filial-em-macau/</link><description>Macau already has a branch of UnionPay International, a subsidiary of China UnionPay, reported the Macau News Agency portal. This is the first bank card organization to make this commitment, and the objective of opening the branch is to expand international business.
Macau became the “second region abroad” to accept transactions with UnionPay cards since the company launched this service in 2004 in the territory. Regarding digital payments, UnionPay's investment took place in 2018 in the territories of Macau and Hong Kong, with the “QuickPass” application and an EMV-compatible QR code being launched in Macau, that is, “Europay, Mastercard and Visa”, which are the three companies behind the global standard for secure card payments. In 2019, Apple Pay was launched in Macau with technological support from UnionPay.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:24:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | Casa de Macau in Lisbon displays “Heritople”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/cinema-casa-de-macau-em-lisboa-exibe-heritople/</link><description>The “CineMacau – Macau Documentary Cinema Cycle” session will take place next Wednesday, October 15th, starting at 4:30 pm, at Casa de Macau in Lisbon. The film “Heritople”, by António Salas Sanmarful, made last year, will be shown, followed by a conversation with the director himself who may be present via video conference.
The cinema sessions at Casa de Macau are organized and curated by Ruka Borges, a director linked to Macau, and Gonçalo Magalhães, member of the Casa's board of directors, who ensure the thematic framework of the films.
The documentary in question was recently produced by António Monteiro (IIM) and directed by António Salas Sanmarful with support from the Macau International Institute, having gained notoriety in promoting Macau as a city and/or territory with a unique hybrid culture, steeped in its heritage and legacy of the East-West relationship, which also highlights the contribution of the Macanese in this odyssey, and describes the organization of the event.
Thus, “Heritople” ends up reinforcing “the importance of Macau as a tangible and intangible heritage of the world given its unique and singular particularities on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the construction of the MSAR as a reality in the context of the People's Republic of China”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:19:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Central Library | 30 proposals received for the creation of a superstructure</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/biblioteca-central-recebidas-30-propostas-para-criacao-de-superestrutura/</link><description>Once the construction of the foundations and basements of the project designed by the Mecanoo studio has been completed, the construction of the superstructure of the New Macau Central Library should take place by the end of the year
 
The public competition for the award of works on the superstructure of the New Macau Central Library resulted in the presentation of 30 proposals. The opening of the documents presented yesterday by the candidates was held yesterday, at the headquarters of the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP).
The public tender was launched on August 21st and defines 620 days as the maximum period for construction of this phase of the project located in Tap Seac. Work on the superstructure should also begin by the end of the year, after the construction of the foundations and basements is completed.
According to the Government, the new project will make it possible to “solve” the “problem of lack of space in the current central library”, in addition to fulfilling the “mission of promoting reading for the entire population, cultural exchange and showcasing local characteristics”.
Proposals will be evaluated based on price (a criterion weighing 50 percent in the decision), execution time (15 percent), experience and quality of works (20 percent), execution program (10 percent) and also taking into account the human resources program plan and proportion of resident workers in management positions (5 percent).
The future library will occupy an area of ​​around 2,960 square meters and the project envisages the construction of four floors in height and a basement, with a gross construction area of ​​around 13,800 square meters. According to official data, this construction area is “ten times larger than that of the old central library”, located on the opposite side of Praça do Tap Seac.
The ground floor and upper floors of the building will contain facilities such as auditoriums, a newspaper and magazine reading area, libraries for adults and children, meeting rooms and multimedia spaces dedicated to teaching.
Troubled project
The construction of the new library in Macau has been planned for more than 10 years, with the processes of choosing the location and preparing the project being marked by several controversies.
Initially, during Fernando Chui Sai On's second term as Chief Executive, an invitation to Portuguese architect Álvaro Siza Vieira was revealed to design the future library. However, due to pressure from local interest groups, the invitation to the Portuguese architect was withdrawn, which led to a public competition.
As part of the first competition, a project from the architect Carlos Marreiros' studio was chosen, with a price of 18.68 million patacas. The library was planned for the old courthouse. However, the works never started, because faced with criticism about the planned location, the Executive decided to choose a new location, the current one, located in Praça do Tap Seac and which involved the demolition of the old Hotel Estoril.
The changes led to another public competition, this time international, which ended with the choice of the Dutch studio Mecanoo. It is this project that is now being built.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:28:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Game is a factor of stability</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/estudo-jogo-e-factor-de-estabilidade/</link><description>The work published at the beginning of the month highlights the importance of gambling for the local economy and warns against adventures in economic diversification that could jeopardize local stability
 
An industry susceptible to being affected by regional and global political and economic uncertainties, but also highly resilient and should be seen as a factor of stability in the territory. These are some conclusions of the study entitled “Regional and Global Uncertainty and the Impacts on the Tourism and Gaming Industry of Macau”, published in the magazine Cogent Economics &amp; Finance by academic Tang Chi Chong.
In the research, published on October 3, it is recognized that regional and global uncertainties “may influence gambling revenues” in Macau, and changes in the economic and political environments will have an impact on gambling revenues. This impact is expected in terms of betting in casinos, especially if the uncertainties occur in places such as the Interior, Hong Kong, Taiwan or South Korea, the Macao SAR's main tourist markets. “Macau’s gaming industry is not isolated from the outside world”, it is acknowledged.
However, the study also concludes that Macau's tourism is highly resilient to negative impacts compared to traditional tourism markets, where gambling is less important. “Macau’s hotel sector is less sensitive to global risks and uncertainties compared to traditional hotel sectors, largely due to the presence of the gaming industry”, it is justified. "However, the impacts of regional and global uncertainty are not significant for Macau's pillar industry. The city's gaming sector demonstrates strong resilience in the face of economic and political instability, both regionally and globally", it was added.
Protect the chicken
In view of these conclusions, the study argues that the gaming industry must be protected, even in an environment in which attempts are made to diversify Macau's economy.
"It is clear that the integration of the gaming industry into Macau's tourism sector increases the overall resilience of the city's tourism and hospitality industry. Economic diversification has been a key policy of the Macau government. However, special attention should be paid to the sensitivity of different industries compared to the gaming sector", he was warned. "If the gaming industry demonstrates high resilience to uncertainty, maintaining it could be a viable strategy to stabilize the economy. Furthermore, resilience to uncertainty could serve as a key criterion for the government in selecting industries for development, as it contributes to economic stability in a context of increasing global economic and political uncertainty," it was added.
Tang Chi Chong is linked to the Macau Polytechnic University, Macau Tourism University and the Hong Kong Polytechnic University.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:27:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Golden Week below expectations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/comercio-semana-dourada-aquem-das-expectativas/</link><description>Although the number of tourists increased by 15.3 percent compared to last year, when it came to opening their wallets, people were more careful. The climate of disappointment was described by the president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau Center and South Districts
 
A Golden Week far from satisfactory. This was how Lei Cheok Kuan, president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau Central and South Districts, defined the most recent holidays. The balance of the days that lasted between October 1st and Wednesday was made by the person responsible in statements to the newspaper Exmoo.
According to Lei Cheok Kuan, the impact on local businesses was “disappointing”, because although the territory received around 1.14 million tourists, the number did not translate into an increase in revenue for local businesses. The association leader acknowledged that reality fell short of expectations, because the gains on the Chinese stock markets since the beginning of the year suggested greater spending power for visitors.
“It wasn’t just in my goldsmith shop [that business was worse], the traders I know in restaurants and retail sales, including those in the Rua dos Ervanários area, also saw business performing worse than in the past”, lamented the president of the association.
Lei Cheok Kuan pointed out that the flow of tourists to the Ruins of São Paulo was high, but that more tourists did not generate more consumption. The person responsible admitted that expenses were below what had happened in May, during national holidays around Labor Day.
As reasons for weaker consumption, the president of the association put forward as hypotheses the impact of the slowdown in the economy in the interior, which makes consumers less spendy. Furthermore, the president pointed out that the consumption model of generation Z has changed, becoming more demanding, which may mean that they cannot find what they are looking for in Macau.
Pedestrian zone disappointed
Regarding the new temporary pedestrian zone on Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo, Lei Cheok Kuan confessed that he had many hopes. The expectation was for a large concentration of tourists in the place and greater consumption.
However, the reality was different than expected. Lei Cheok Kuan pointed out that few traders felt the results of the initiative. Therefore, the person in charge concluded that despite the Government trying to find new methods to support small and medium-sized companies, consumers are increasingly changing their consumption habits, which makes the task more difficult.
However, Lei Cheok Kuan defended the need for traders to adapt and better understand the way young people like to spend money.
During the eight days of Golden Week, the territory received 1.14 million tourists, which represented an increase of 15.3 percent compared to last year. On average, 143.1 thousand people visited the Macao SAR per day, an increase of approximately 1 percent compared to last year.
Accounts done
Macau received more than 1.1 million visitors in the first week of October, during the holidays commemorating China's National Day, the Tourism Services Bureau (DST) announced yesterday. The total number of visitors during Golden Week, from October 1 to 8, was 1,144,351, 16.5 percent more than last year's 982,542, which had one less day (October 1 to 7), according to data published on the DST website.
This year, it was on October 4th that Macau recorded the highest number of visitors, with 191,132 tourists entering the territory. The lowest number of visitors during the “Golden Week” was seen on the eighth day, October 8, with 88,943 entries, according to that direction. This year, the 76th anniversary of the founding of the People's Republic of China was celebrated.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:23:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Education | UM considered the 145th best in the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/educacao-um-considerada-a-145-a-melhor-do-mundo/</link><description>In just over 10 years, Macau's largest public educational institution managed to rise to the top of the best universities worldwide. In a ranking led by the most famous institutions, MUST and Cidade Universidade de Macau also appear
 
The University of Macau (UM) was yesterday considered the 145th best in the world, according to the Times Higher Education 2026 magazine ranking. In the space of 11 years, the public educational institution rose from 500th place to 145th position in the ranking.
On a scale of 0 to 100 points, UM was evaluated by Times Higher Education with a total of 62 points, compared to 59.7 points in the previous year. The area in which the institution achieved the best score was in the “research quality” index with 92.9 points, followed by “international perspectives”, in which it obtained 92.5 points. According to ranking information, more than 51 percent of the institution's students are classified as international students. Despite this, international perspectives were the only area in which the university performed worse than the previous year.
Another aspect in which the institution stood out was in the industry index, which measures financing by companies to the institution, with 87 points.
The areas in which the University of Macau presented a lower quality performance were in teaching (40.2 points) and also in the research environment (40.9 points).
MUST and City
In terms of Macau universities present in the 2026 ranking, the second best ranked is the Macau University of Science and Technology (MUST, in English), which appears between places 251 and 300 in the ranking. From 201st position onwards, the ranking stops specifying the specific position of the institutions and places them in groups of 50 universities, 100 universities or 200 universities.
MUST obtained an overall score between 54.3 and 56.3 points, maintaining the same position since the 2024 ranking. Still, it is below the level reached in 2023 when it managed to enter the group of institutions in positions 201 to 250. The private institution obtained 93.2 points in international perspectives, 84.4 points at industry level, 81.1 points in research quality, 38.8 points in research environment and 34.2 points at teaching level.
Cidade Universidade de Macau made its debut in the ranking this year, joining the group of institutions occupying between 601st and 800th places. The institution recorded a score between 39 and 43.5 points. The aspect in which it stood out best was international perspectives with 93.5 points, followed by research quality with 59.7 points. Teaching achieved 30.8 points, while industry achieved 18.9 points and 17.1 points in the research environment.
This year the ranking was once again led by the University of Oxford, with an overall score of 98.2 points. The best university in the Interior is Tsinghua University in 12th place in the ranking, with 93 points. The University of Hong Kong appears in 33rd position, with 80.5 points.
The best Portuguese institutions are the University of Coimbra, University of Lisbon and University of Porto, all included in the group classified between positions 401 and 500.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:21:09</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau: First names and first questions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/gp-macau-primeiros-nomes-e-primeiras-duvidas/</link><description>October is usually the month of preparations for the Macau Grand Prix. With the championships coming to an end all over the world, attention turns to the Macao SAR's big event, which this year will take place from the 13th to the 16th of November
 
After Marcos Cheong and Vernice Lau raced in the Chinese Formula 4 Championship race, this weekend it is Tiago Rodrigues' turn to pick up the helmet again to compete in the closing race of the Chinese competition season, on the circuit in the neighboring city of Zhuhai. The former Chinese champion of the discipline has been away from single-seater racing since participating in the Middle East Formula 4 Championship at the beginning of the year, but his experience could prove to be an asset in defending the territory's colors at the Guia Circuit.
Twenty of the Mygale M21-F4 single-seaters from the Chinese championship will be overhauled after this race at the Zhuhai International Circuit and handed over to technicians appointed by the French Motor Sport Federation (FFSA), who will put them on the track in the first edition of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup, in Macau. This is the same model used in the French Formula 4 Championship.
Some names of the bikes
Michael Rutter's absence from the entry list for this year's Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix is ​​now a certainty. However, through the specialized press, the first names that will shape the only road race on the Asian continent are beginning to become known.
Practically confirmed are the presence of Davey Todd, winner of last year's edition, and Peter Hickman, the motorcyclist who chases Rutter's record of victories and who should be practically recovered from the injuries suffered in the accident on the Isle of Man. Both will drive the official competitive BMW M1000RR from 8TEN Racing. Rob Hodson, SMT Racing driver, has also guaranteed his presence in the Macao SAR, usually being one of the strong candidates for the Top 5 in the race.
But not only renowned names are tested. Among the debutants already confirmed is ramp driver Maurizio Bottalico. The San Marino driver, who reached the podium at the Manx Grand Prix, follows in the footsteps of other great Italian names in 21st century road racing — such as Stefano Bonetti, Luca Gottardi or Alex Polita — by taking on the most famous and feared race in the East.
According to the Road Racing News portal, there will be more newcomers to the Guia Circuit this year, such as Mitch Rees, a driver with several titles in New Zealand, Ryan Whitehall, a driver from the Isle of Wight, and the new holder of the Frohburger Dreieck lap record in the Supersport category, Paul Jordan.
Questions in the GT
Stéphane Ratel, founder and CEO of SRO Motorsports Group — the company that co-organizes the FIA ​​GT World Cup Macau Grand Prix — has been one of the most critical voices regarding the introduction of torque sensors in GT3 racing. However, the FIA ​​decided in favor of its use in the Guia Circuit World Cup, and the French businessman spoke about the matter for the first time.
"The teams competing in Macau are mostly from Asia, where torque sensors have never been used. The lack of experience could affect the sporting balance, and that's why I opposed their use", said Stéphane Ratel to the German magazine Motorsport Aktuell, adding that he does not believe this is the way forward.
Although the SRO Motorsports Group is co-organizer of the event and has a Balance of Performance (BoP) recognized worldwide, in the last two years the Macau BoP has been determined by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA's BoP was subject to a series of criticisms, with teams and drivers – particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main losers – publicly expressing their displeasure at the differences in pace. For this reason, the FIA ​​decided to introduce these expensive sensors, installed on the cars' transmission shafts, which represent the most accurate tool for measuring the power transmitted to the wheels.
“Some manufacturers supported the idea, but others, like Mercedes, were against it,” said Stéphane Ratel. "As a result, we lost some cars from the entry list. To be clear: I look at this issue pragmatically, not dogmatically. Last year in Macau, three or four manufacturers could have won without these torque sensors. In 2025 we will see if this technology is really useful", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:11:25</pubDate></item><item><title>World leaders applaud peace agreement between Israel and Hamas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/lideres-mundiais-aplaudem-acordo-de-paz-entre-israel-e-hamas/</link><description>Several world leaders welcomed the peace agreement between Israel and Hamas announced by US President Donald Trump, praising the imminent end of the war in Gaza and the release of hostages after two years of conflict.
Trump announced on Wednesday that Israel and the Islamist movement have accepted the “first phase” of his peace plan, which envisages the partial withdrawal of Israeli troops from the Gaza Strip and the release of 20 hostages still alive in exchange for Palestinian prisoners.
“All hostages will be released very soon and Israel will withdraw its troops to an agreed line as first steps towards a strong, lasting and eternal peace,” Trump wrote on the Truth Social network.
The news was received with enthusiasm by leaders from several countries. Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney congratulated Trump on his “essential leadership” and expressed relief at the imminent release of the hostages. "Peace finally seems possible. We urge all parties to quickly implement the terms of the agreement," he said. Japan also welcomed the understanding, which government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi classified as “an important step to calm the situation”, thanking the United States, Egypt and Qatar for their mediation efforts.
From Canberra, Prime Minister Anthony Albanese and Foreign Minister Penny Wong highlighted that it was “a very necessary step towards peace” and defended a two-state solution, stressing that the plan excludes Hamas from any role in the future administration of Gaza.
United Nations Secretary-General António Guterres described the agreement as “a desperately needed breakthrough” and called for its full implementation, stressing that “it is an opportunity to recognize the right to self-determination of the Palestinian people and move towards a two-state solution”.
Hamas confirmed the understanding, guaranteeing that it “ensures the end of the war, the withdrawal of the Israeli army and the entry of humanitarian aid”, and called on Israel to fulfill its commitments “without delays or changes”. Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu called the deal a “historic achievement” and thanked Trump for his “determined leadership and global efforts,” saying: “With God’s help, we will bring everyone home.”
Euphoria and relief
According to official sources, the release of the hostages is expected to begin on Monday, after the agreement is approved by the Israeli Government, and the military withdrawal will cover around 70 percent of the Gaza territory.
“This is more than Gaza, it is the beginning of peace in the Middle East,” said Trump in an interview with Fox News, assuring that the United States and neighboring countries will support the reconstruction of the enclave. He added: "Other countries in the region will help because they have immense wealth. We will be involved to ensure Gaza is successful and peaceful."
In Tel Aviv, families of the hostages gathered in euphoria in Hostage Square, amid tears and chants of “Nobel for Trump”. “I want to smell my son,” said Einav Zangauker, mother of one of the hostages, emotionally. In Gaza, where the ceasefire was met with a mixture of relief and distrust, displaced people and residents expressed hope of being able to return to their homes.
“We want to return, even if there are no more houses,” said Alaa Abd Rabbo, displaced from the north of the Strip. The agreement brokered by the United States, Qatar, Egypt and Türkiye marks the most significant attempt to end the war since the conflict began in October 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:15:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Overseas Chinese | Lam calls for continuity in promoting Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/chineses-ultramarinos-o-lam-pede-continuidade-na-promocao-de-macau/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, defended the continuation, by the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau, of the work to promote the territory, at a time when the entity celebrated, on Wednesday, 57 years of existence.
According to a statement, O Lam said, in a speech, that the association should promote the specific advantages of Macau as a Sino-Lusophone platform in addition to assuming the bridge between China, Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, as well as Spanish-speaking countries.
Lam also hopes that the association will continue to support local and Mainland Chinese companies in accessing international markets, in addition to supporting the import of certain international projects to China. This is so that Macau can explore the “circle of friends” and partners at an international level, supporting the country’s development in opening up to the outside world.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:31:05</pubDate></item><item><title>UnionPay | First branch opened in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/unionpay-aberta-primeira-filial-em-macau/</link><description>Macau already has a branch of UnionPay International, a subsidiary of China UnionPay, reported the Macau News Agency portal. This is the first bank card organization to make this commitment, and the objective of opening the branch is to expand international business.
Macau became the “second region abroad” to accept transactions with UnionPay cards since the company launched this service in 2004 in the territory. Regarding digital payments, UnionPay's investment took place in 2018 in the territories of Macau and Hong Kong, with the “QuickPass” application and an EMV-compatible QR code being launched in Macau, that is, “Europay, Mastercard and Visa”, which are the three companies behind the global standard for secure card payments. In 2019, Apple Pay was launched in Macau with technological support from UnionPay.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:24:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | Casa de Macau in Lisbon displays “Heritople”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/cinema-casa-de-macau-em-lisboa-exibe-heritople/</link><description>The “CineMacau – Macau Documentary Cinema Cycle” session will take place next Wednesday, October 15th, starting at 4:30 pm, at Casa de Macau in Lisbon. The film “Heritople”, by António Salas Sanmarful, made last year, will be shown, followed by a conversation with the director himself who may be present via video conference.
The cinema sessions at Casa de Macau are organized and curated by Ruka Borges, a director linked to Macau, and Gonçalo Magalhães, member of the Casa's board of directors, who ensure the thematic framework of the films.
The documentary in question was recently produced by António Monteiro (IIM) and directed by António Salas Sanmarful with support from the Macau International Institute, having gained notoriety in promoting Macau as a city and/or territory with a unique hybrid culture, steeped in its heritage and legacy of the East-West relationship, which also highlights the contribution of the Macanese in this odyssey, and describes the organization of the event.
Thus, “Heritople” ends up reinforcing “the importance of Macau as a tangible and intangible heritage of the world given its unique and singular particularities on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the construction of the MSAR as a reality in the context of the People's Republic of China”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:19:33</pubDate></item><item><title>“Hush!” | Four dozen bands in two days of full celebration</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/hush-quatro-dezenas-de-bandas-em-dois-dias-de-plena-festa/</link><description>The poster for the next edition of “Hush! Concertos na Praia x Festival do Bem-Estar Desportivo Urbano” is now known, taking place between the 18th and 19th of this month on Hac-Sá beach, Coloane. This Sunday, the 12th, a pre-presentation will take place at Oficinas Navais nº 1, with Lobo and Shing02. There is no shortage of the usual cultural and well-being connection activities
Six stages, 40 local bands and singers, two days. These are the numbers for the next edition of “Hush! Concertos na Praia x Festival do Bem-Estar Desportivo Urbano”, scheduled for the 18th and 19th of October on Hac-Sá beach. However, this weekend, namely Sunday, the public in general and music lovers in particular will be able to enjoy a little of what will come later, with the performance of Lobo and the rapper Shing02 at Oficinas Navais nº1.
Lobo will present a “DJ set”, showing the sounds he has mixed and created in recent years. A radio broadcaster in the 90s, namely at TDM Rádio Macau and the former Rádio Vilaverde, Lobo founded, in 2000, the independent publisher “4daz-le”, “which remains the only one of its kind to date”, describes the organization of “Hush!”.
Also this weekend, but Saturday, the so-called “Festive Prelude” takes place in community neighborhoods, with various community shows, concerts and musical workshops.
What promises to be a “marathon” of concerts showcases “the cultural uniqueness of East Asia” on six stages, namely “Hot Wave”, “Music Chill”, “Hush! Kids – Parque Desportivo Infantil”, “Palco Wellfest”, “Jardim Desportivo” and “Desafio Fitness”. Thus, in addition to music, there will be parallel activities such as “SUP Yoga”, the “Music Glow Run”, described as a “musical parade for parents and children”; gastronomy tents and various workshops.
The aim of this diversity of offer is to “make the public aware of the uniqueness of the cultural fusion between East and West in Macau and “build the role” of the territory “as an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations”.
Lively sand
The main highlight of the festival, however, is the "Hush! Concerts on the Beach", with 40 bands and musicians from Macau taking the stage, in addition to ten international groups, namely SUMMERWARZ, from the interior of China; the Balming Tiger, from South Korea; bassist H.J. Freaks and Muque, a rock group from Japan. Also included is the performance of young ukuleleist Feng E and the female metal band MakeMake, both from Taiwan.
Other names that grace the Hac-Sá stage are Concrete/Lotus, Blademark, Roberto Madan, No Rison, WhyOceans, IRIS MONDO, Ying May Supermarket, Cancer Game and Chong River Fusion, among others.
Taking into account the celebration of the 20th anniversary of "Hush! Concertos na Praia", the organization decided to invite the organizers of other festivals in Asia, namely the well-known Clockenflap Music &amp; Arts Festival in Hong Kong, the Strawberry Music Festival and the Midi Festival in Mainland China, among others. The idea is to establish “a regional exchange platform and provide presentation contacts for local bands”.
On the sports side, the “Urban Sports Wellbeing Festival” brings to Coloane more than 30 professional fitness and yoga instructors from Asia, such as Hong Kong artist and dance instructor Fatboy@ERROR, “Physical: 100 Season 2” champion and South Korean CrossFit “superstar” Amotti, as well as dance trainer Thai, Gun Gun. In total, there will be more than 40 gymnastics and dance classes over two days, designed for beginners or practitioners.
The festival organization, which has the support of entities such as the Cultural Institute or the Institute for Municipal Affairs, prepared free bus transport to Coloane, running between Praia de Hac Sá and Iao Hon, Fai Chi Kei, Taipa. The public can also take the free MGM Cotai bus from any port in Macau, with the exception of Qingmao Port, to MGM Cotai Bus Terminal B1, and then use the free event bus service to travel to Hac Sá Beach. The “Hush!” concerts Entrance is free and tickets must be purchased for the “Urban Sports Welfare Festival”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:18:05</pubDate></item><item><title>NBA | China and Alibaba Cloud sign partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/nba-china-e-alibaba-cloud-assinam-parceria/</link><description>NBA China, the most popular professional sports league on Chinese social media, with 425 million followers, has just signed a partnership with Alibaba Cloud, another Chinese group founded by Jack Ma, to improve the interactivity of basketball fans with the games broadcast, namely the “NBA All-Star”, the NBA playoffs and the finals, using artificial intelligence and the system of cloud computing.
The announcement was made by Joe Tsai, co-founder and executive vice president of the Alibaba group and owner of the Brooklyn Nets team, from New York; and by Mark Tatum, deputy commissioner and director of operations at the NBA [National Basketball Association], the main basketball sports league in the USA and one of the most important worldwide.
In concrete terms, NBA China “will utilize Alibaba Cloud’s AI and cloud computing services to support a wide range of digital fan engagement initiatives”, having developed “a proprietary AI model for NBA China based on Alibaba’s ‘Qwen’ series of models”.
Thus, “the proprietary AI model, adjusted to the league's range of digital assets, will provide NBA China app users with engaging content, including real-time game highlights, historical basketball data, player information and interactive discussions on current basketball topics.”
Also noteworthy is the fact that pre-season games between the Nets and Phoenix Suns teams at NBA China 2025 will take place today and Sunday. The presentation is carried out by “Taobao 88VIP”, with the games taking place today at 8pm at the Venetian Arena, and then on Sunday at 7pm, in the same location.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:13:57</pubDate></item><item><title>AMCM | Monthly drop in deposits and loans</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/amcm-queda-mensal-de-depositos-e-emprestimos/</link><description>Data from the Macau Monetary and Exchange Authority (AMCM) regarding deposits, loans and money supply reveal that, between July and August, there was a drop in deposits and loans made by residents. Domestic loans granted to the private sector fell by 1.1 percent compared to July, reaching 501.9 billion patacas.
In turn, the drop in loans granted abroad was even greater, around 9.1 percent, worth 511.8 billion patacas. Thus, AMCM statistics show that the total volume of loans in banks fell by 5.3 percent between July and August, a drop of 1,013.7 billion patacas.
Regarding deposits, the monthly drop was 0.4 percent, amounting to 813.8 billion patacas, while the drop in deposits by non-residents was much greater, in the order of 7.1 percent, amounting to 338.1 billion patacas.
AMCM data also shows that “public sector deposits in banking activity grew to 220.9 billion patacas, representing a growth of 5.2 percent”. Thus, in general terms, “total deposits in banking activity registered a decrease of 1.3 percent, reaching 1,372.8 billion patacas”. In monthly terms, monetary circulation grew by 0.3 percent, but current deposits fell by six percent.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:19:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Ana Cristina Alves</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>The philosophical questions that will arise throughout this text are based on concrete data, they are not inventions and depend on newspaper reports, but they are certainly not fake news, they just report what has been happening in the second decade of the 21st century in the People's Republic of China.
China is the market leader in robotic technology, including humanoid robotics. Robotics malls are growing in Beijing, one with 4 floors, opened on August 7, 2025, another with 6 floors in Shenzhen. In this large shopping mall, there are robots for all tastes and uses in assisting medicine, industry and everyday activities. They can be bionic, with shapes and movements inspired by biology, or humanoid, reaching levels of sophistication like those seen in a chess player named Wukong. We also find them linked to sport, some play boxing, others football, others practice running, there are artists, for example, painters, musicians and dancers, there are medical assistants, masseurs, nursing technicians and laboratory assistants, and/or dedicated to traditional Chinese medicine, there are them committed to daily tasks, making excellent waiters and cooks, who attentively flip pancakes and prepare barbecues, but also counter staff, there are, in addition, humanoid transporters and drones.
And if there are good ones, that is, used to help and build, obviously there could be bad ones, to hinder and destroy. But this is a conversation for later.
At the World Robotics Conference in August 2025, held in Beijing, a sales balance was carried out for the year 2024 regarding industrial robots, which exceeded 300 thousand units, keeping China in top place in sales of this type of robots for the twelfth consecutive year. In a report made by the President of the Chinese Robotics Institute, Xu Xiaolan (徐晓兰), the country is the largest producer of robotics in the world, with sales of industrial robots having increased from 33,000 in 2015 to 556,000 units in 2024. The production of service robots (domestic services, storage and logistics, commercial services, support for the elderly, the disabled and rehabilitation medical) for more than 10 million units. In statistical terms, and according to data from the International Data Corporation (IDC) for 2024, Chinese manufacturers occupy 84.7% of the global market for commercial service robots.
China leads the world robotics market, through its active creative industry, as it had already done in relation, for example, to toys. The country is responsible for around 80% to 90% of toys sold globally, whether old wooden toys, plush toys, inflatable toys, or electronic toys, with Guangdong, Jiangsu and Shandong being the main bases for purchasing toys, with the centers of Fujian, Zhejiang and Shanghai also being strong in this area. Centers that we also find linked to robotics, at least in the case of Shanghai and Shenzhen.
Can a relationship be established between toys and robotics in the case of China?
Toys are a strong focus of generation Z, short for zoomers, (those from the second half of the 90s until 2010), who fear a bleak future and invest a lot in emotional spending. This generation of the World Wide Web follows the growth of technological devices, being considered digital native.
As I believe, the path for the emergence of robots in China was laid out long before Generation Z appeared on the face of the earth. The Chinese have always loved toys, see their love for stuffed animals, lanterns, old wooden toys and, more recently, all types of electronic toys.
Now, robots, although they are much more than entertainment, have the appearance of toys, with the added advantage of being able to receive a strong emotional investment, combined with enormous practical utility. These “cans”, made from aluminum, steel and titanium, and plastics, such as polypropylene, ABS and polycarbonate, rubbers and elastomers, in addition to numerous electronic components, such as microprocessors, sensors, motors and wiring, are great companions of humans, faithful friends and obedience only limited to their manufacture.
They therefore appear to fulfill several functions and their emergence was only possible due to a close alliance between science and technology, that is, due to the development of technology, which was thematized by great contemporary writers and philosophers in the West, and think of Aldous Huxley (1894-1963) and his futuristic dystopia, entitled Brave New World. 1932), in which a society dominated by genetic engineering is psychologically conditioned, including by drugs (soma), in order to guarantee social well-being and suppress freedom and critical thinking.
Consider, also, works such as Oswald Spengler's (1880-1936), Man and Technique from 1931, which explores the relationship between human beings and technology, ultimately leading to self-destruction through the dissolution of Western culture. But if Western culture can feel, to paraphrase Spengler, “nauseated by machines”, there are others like the philosopher Martin Heidegger (1889-1976), who in The Question of Technique (1954) sees technique as the meaning of a new era for human beings. However, to do so it is necessary to know how to question the technique and not just accept it in an instrumental way at the service of anthropological purposes, when humanism for the philosopher of The Letter to Humanism (1946) has disastrous consequences, because it distances the true man from his essence and Being, which is thus hidden and not revealed.
None of these paths of Western thought have been followed by the Chinese of our times, strongly committed to the utilitarian use of technology. The instrumentalization of it at the service of humanity, or rather, of China, does not raise existential doubts in them, as is attested by the large robotics shopping malls currently available in Beijing or Shenzhen to a public eager for technological innovations.
Chinese robots serve all types of functions; industrial, commercial, scientific, recreational, domestic and emotional assistance. The relative lack of freedom, or the limitation of degrees of freedom (Degrees of Freedom, DOF) also does not seem worrying to them, at least to the point of raising philosophical questions about a dystopian future, viable through the genetic crossing of artificial intelligence with animals, including so-called rational humans.
They only seek to improve the degrees of freedom of robots defined as the number of independent movements of their joints and components, carried out in both the rotational and translational directions, these degrees being in the Humanoid Robotic Technology article, published in May 2025, variable according to the technical improvement of each machine: the greatest degree of freedom is presented by the Era-Star 1 Robot.
Therefore, do not expect great and unusual innovations regarding the degree of freedom of robots, they will be, until you see, limited and submissive to their creators. From a good creator a positive robot will emerge, from a bad creator, a negative one.
A friend with whom I discussed the topic was very surprised by the fact that one of the most populous countries in the world is at the forefront of robotic development, because for him it would be more important to provide employment to a huge population than to seek to replace them in almost all tasks, from scientific to the most routine, such as the transport and delivery of goods.
To understand why this total adherence to intelligent machinery, or as intelligent as its limited freedom allows, it is necessary to go back to the history of China. I propose a journey to the times of the emergence and development of the use of gunpowder. The appearance of gunpowder is associated with Alchemy and Taoist masters, who carried out the first scientific experiments in search of the elixir of longevity, already in the Warring States Period (战国 Zhàn Guó, 475-221 BC), being one of the four great inventions of Ancient China (四大发明Sì dà fāmíng). The first type of gunpowder to emerge was black gunpowder (黑火药Hēi huǒyào), the experiments of the alchemists were very well received and encouraged by the dominant power, then the experiments continued during the Eastern Han dynasty (东汉Dōng Hàn, 25-220), with the treatise by Wei Boyang (魏伯阳), entitled Zhouyi Cantongqi, being famous. (《周易参同契》), and translated as The Concordance of the Three, or that of the Jin dynasty (晋代Jìn dài, 266-420) by the great alchemist Ge Hong (葛洪), whose title is Baopuzi, in Portuguese, The Master Who Embraces Simplicity (《抱朴子·仙药篇》), especially its chapter dedicated to the manufacture of the pill of immortality.
Perhaps when using combustion methods to create the pill, the alchemists discovered gunpowder by chance by mixing sulfur, saltpeter and charcoal. It is certain that the explosion occurred and the dangerous, flammable and detonating element was discovered, but it is no less certain that the masters did not follow this route, which they considered unproductive for the desired objective. Then only much later during the Song dynasty (宋代Sòng dài， 960-1279) is it known that some artisans established fireworks workshops in Kaifeng to produce rockets and fireworks indispensable for all great moments of celebration in China.
The use of gunpowder then followed two very different paths, one pyrotechnic for recreational purposes of the imperial power and associated stately homes, the other for military use.
Why is the story of the discovery of gunpowder brought here? Because this could perhaps contain the three dimensions that we can find in the creation and interest in robots in China. Its creation reveals an enormous scientific interest associated: on the one hand, with philosophical practices aimed at developing life to its limits and perhaps even their absence, which would be achieved by immortality; on the other, it expresses an immense recreational desire with deep emotional investment, and, on the other, a practical utility, which puts robotics at the forefront, both in scientific, military and civil terms.
The new Chinese philosophy, as the oldest genuinely autochthonous one, appears in close connection with science and techniques with mysterious connections to the world of magic for the Taoist masters of yesterday, who are followed by the great doctors, including those of traditional Chinese medicine, who today find precious laboratory assistants carrying out work of great precision and minimal errors, since robots do not They get tired, they don't even bother, they do what is asked of them without any salary demands.
Furthermore, in military terms this arsenal of machinery is an excellent alternative, as it saves lives, as it is complex and autonomous enough to do so.
Obviously, of the many ethical issues associated with this exponential development of the new world of robotics and artificial intelligence, one seems essential, above all and, for now, in terms of biotechnical experimentation and related scientific research, which will be discussed below.  First the example, taken from the development of dynamic electrodes for brain-computer interface, as is happening at the Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences. In brain-computer interface systems, electrodes from electronic devices must be connected to the brain to acquire electroencephalographic signals. These electrodes are made of flexible fiber, similar to a worm, with a magnetic sensor incorporated in the head of the “worm”, to be manipulated according to the orientation of external magnetic fields. These flexible fiber electrodes were introduced into the brains of rabbits and also rats, with the aim of subsequently serving human clinical needs, such as intelligent control of prostheses, localization of epileptic lesions and treatment of chronic neurological disorders.
From an ethical point of view, the question cannot help but be asked: why are human lives more important than all others on our planet? Human beings remain the kings of creation, even within the scope of philosophies such as the Chinese, whose non-humanist tradition, as referred to in Heidegger's Letter to Humanism, is well known.
Are we humans really that valuable?  Science must continue its path, which in China will always be followed from a pragmatic and utilitarian perspective for the benefit of the Chinese and the Chinese nation. But don't think that robotics is there just to serve Chinese society without exchanging favors, as we cannot forget the enormous emotional investment that the population that descends from Dragons makes in these new beings, some more bionic than others, who acquire the status of companions and friends and, in this capacity, have all the pampering that was previously due to the humans and animals they chose to cherish.
The new Chinese philosophy is utilitarian, practical and has new entities in its world of knowledge, such as humanoids, bionic robots and robotics toys. They are highly esteemed and paving the way for a new era, that of cyborgs or better said, the mixed humanity of tomorrow, which will have the greatest chance of living long and, who knows, immortalizing itself.
Bibliographic References
Academy of Chinese Studies (中国文化研究员). 2025.中國古代火藥與火器 ? (Gunpowder and Firearms of Ancient China). Available at: https://chiculture.org.hk/tc/china-five-thousand-years/198, accessed on October 1, 2025.
陈宇轩 (Chen Yuxuan) .2025.  “让传感器动起来 我国科研团队研发出脑机接口动态电极” (Putting sensors in motion: A Chinese research team has developed dynamic electrodes for brain-computer interfaces), 新华网Xinhua, September 18, 2025. Available at: http://www.news.cn/20250918/d47375c582dd4cd7a632cb099d92822d/c.html, accessed on September 24, 2025.
CGTN Africa. 2025 World’s first Robot Mall opens in Beijing’s E-town at Robot Conference. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=awbH5JqdqLs, August 12, 2025, accessed September 25, 2025.
CGTN. 2025. “World’s first robot 6S store to open in China’s Shenzhen”. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NhodG2lUGo, accessed on September 25, 2025.
CGTN Europe 2025 “China explained: Why adults are crazy about toys? Available at:” https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v4-Pf3Jt2x8, accessed September 26, 2025.
Heidegger, Martin. 1987. Letter to Humanism. Revised translation by Pinharanda Gomes, Preface by Doctor José Brandão. Lisbon: Guimarães Editores.
Humanoid Robotics Technology. 2025. Top 10 Chinese Humanoid Robots of 2025. Available at: https://humanoidroboticstechnology.com/articles/top-10-chinese-humanoid-robots-of-2025/, accessed on October 2, 2025.
Huxley, Aldous. 2013. Brave New World. Lisbon: Bertrand.
(潘俊强Pan Junqiang) 2025. 我国连续12年保持全球最大工业机器人市场.  (China has led the world industrial robotics market for twelve consecutive years)人民日报. Available at: https://www.gov.cn/yaowen/liebiao/202508/content_7035025.htm, August 3, 2025. Accessed September 24, 2025.
Sohu. 2022. Minimalist History Series: The Invention of Black Gunpowder (Traceable to the Sui Dynasty). Sohu. Available at https://www.sohu.com/a/593986613_120900450, accessed on October 1, 2025.
Spengler, Oswald. 1993. Man and Technique. Lisbon: Guimarães: Editors.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhang Xuan (713-755), the Tang painter, was the author of a painting that today can be admired through a copy attributed to the Song emperor, Huizong (r.1022-63), where beautiful ladies are seen, richly dressed, coiffed and adorned, performing practical tasks of treating fabrics, which one would usually expect to see being carried out by servants of these ladies. In this precious horizontal scroll (ink, color and gold on silk, 37.7 x 466 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston) where luxury is boasted and which in fact shows the celebration of an annual rite related to the production of silk, which takes place in the Spring, serving as an example for the rest of the Empire, you can see at the end, on the left side, two ladies, one on each side, extending a piece of white silk that a third She is ironing, helped by a young woman.
And although one of the ladies bends slightly in her zeal to spread the fabric, nothing seems to be requiring much effort, they all seem to be carrying out a pleasant activity. From that time when a domestic scene that took place among the elite was recreated at court, a painter, perhaps no less erudite, recreated in a modest horizontal scroll (ink and color on silk, 26.1 x 69.2 cm, at the National Palace Museum, in Beijing), an exciting counterpoint to this scene in which two humble ladies are the protagonists. One on each side of the ends of two threads in the painful task of manufacturing a fabric that could be the one that on the other roll the ladies spend time eliminating the wrinkles. The ladies here are not sweet or beautiful like others, but simple country women who depend on physical strength to turn the spinning wheel that allows the family to survive. The sympathy that the painting shows for the poor and virtuous but inglorious lives of these women is notable, which raises perplexity as to who and why it was created.
Wang Juzheng, who lived during the Northern Song, was born in Hedong (present-day Yongji, Shanxi) in the reign of Emperor Renzong (1023-63), was the son of a painter and other works attributed to him confirm that this is an exception. However, the appreciation with which it was received can be read in the comment that preclar Zhao Mengfu wrote next to it: «It is a small scroll but the brush work is magnificent, it has a high understanding of life. With its wonderful notes it can well be described as a work worthy of the gods.”
And all done with great economy. An older woman will be the grandmother of a boy who plays with a frog stuck on a stick at the beginning of the reel, two old willow trunks and branches, reminding us of the father's absence, a not-so-young woman sitting on a wooden bench moves the spinning wheel and, as soon as you see it, she has a baby on her chest, in front of her the family's small dog plays. In the hands of the tired old woman, two threads carry tremendous weight.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, defended the continuation, by the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau, of the work to promote the territory, at a time when the entity celebrated, on Wednesday, 57 years of existence.
According to a statement, O Lam said, in a speech, that the association should promote the specific advantages of Macau as a Sino-Lusophone platform in addition to assuming the bridge between China, Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, as well as Spanish-speaking countries.
Lam also hopes that the association will continue to support local and Mainland Chinese companies in accessing international markets, in addition to supporting the import of certain international projects to China. This is so that Macau can explore the “circle of friends” and partners at an international level, supporting the country’s development in opening up to the outside world.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhang Xuan (713-755), the Tang painter, was the author of a painting that today can be admired through a copy attributed to the Song emperor, Huizong (r.1022-63), where beautiful ladies are seen, richly dressed, coiffed and adorned, performing practical tasks of treating fabrics, which one would usually expect to see being carried out by servants of these ladies. In this precious horizontal scroll (ink, color and gold on silk, 37.7 x 466 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston) where luxury is boasted and which in fact shows the celebration of an annual rite related to the production of silk, which takes place in the Spring, serving as an example for the rest of the Empire, you can see at the end, on the left side, two ladies, one on each side, extending a piece of white silk that a third She is ironing, helped by a young woman.
And although one of the ladies bends slightly in her zeal to spread the fabric, nothing seems to be requiring much effort, they all seem to be carrying out a pleasant activity. From that time when a domestic scene that took place among the elite was recreated at court, a painter, perhaps no less erudite, recreated in a modest horizontal scroll (ink and color on silk, 26.1 x 69.2 cm, at the National Palace Museum, in Beijing), an exciting counterpoint to this scene in which two humble ladies are the protagonists. One on each side of the ends of two threads in the painful task of manufacturing a fabric that could be the one that on the other roll the ladies spend time eliminating the wrinkles. The ladies here are not sweet or beautiful like others, but simple country women who depend on physical strength to turn the spinning wheel that allows the family to survive. The sympathy that the painting shows for the poor and virtuous but inglorious lives of these women is notable, which raises perplexity as to who and why it was created.
Wang Juzheng, who lived during the Northern Song, was born in Hedong (present-day Yongji, Shanxi) in the reign of Emperor Renzong (1023-63), was the son of a painter and other works attributed to him confirm that this is an exception. However, the appreciation with which it was received can be read in the comment that preclar Zhao Mengfu wrote next to it: «It is a small scroll but the brush work is magnificent, it has a high understanding of life. With its wonderful notes it can well be described as a work worthy of the gods.”
And all done with great economy. An older woman will be the grandmother of a boy who plays with a frog stuck on a stick at the beginning of the reel, two old willow trunks and branches, reminding us of the father's absence, a not-so-young woman sitting on a wooden bench moves the spinning wheel and, as soon as you see it, she has a baby on her chest, in front of her the family's small dog plays. In the hands of the tired old woman, two threads carry tremendous weight.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ana Cristina Alves</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>The philosophical questions that will arise throughout this text are based on concrete data, they are not inventions and depend on newspaper reports, but they are certainly not fake news, they just report what has been happening in the second decade of the 21st century in the People's Republic of China.
China is the market leader in robotic technology, including humanoid robotics. Robotics malls are growing in Beijing, one with 4 floors, opened on August 7, 2025, another with 6 floors in Shenzhen. In this large shopping mall, there are robots for all tastes and uses in assisting medicine, industry and everyday activities. They can be bionic, with shapes and movements inspired by biology, or humanoid, reaching levels of sophistication like those seen in a chess player named Wukong. We also find them linked to sport, some play boxing, others football, others practice running, there are artists, for example, painters, musicians and dancers, there are medical assistants, masseurs, nursing technicians and laboratory assistants, and/or dedicated to traditional Chinese medicine, there are them committed to daily tasks, making excellent waiters and cooks, who attentively flip pancakes and prepare barbecues, but also counter staff, there are, in addition, humanoid transporters and drones.
And if there are good ones, that is, used to help and build, obviously there could be bad ones, to hinder and destroy. But this is a conversation for later.
At the World Robotics Conference in August 2025, held in Beijing, a sales balance was carried out for the year 2024 regarding industrial robots, which exceeded 300 thousand units, keeping China in top place in sales of this type of robots for the twelfth consecutive year. In a report made by the President of the Chinese Robotics Institute, Xu Xiaolan (徐晓兰), the country is the largest producer of robotics in the world, with sales of industrial robots having increased from 33,000 in 2015 to 556,000 units in 2024. The production of service robots (domestic services, storage and logistics, commercial services, support for the elderly, the disabled and rehabilitation medical) for more than 10 million units. In statistical terms, and according to data from the International Data Corporation (IDC) for 2024, Chinese manufacturers occupy 84.7% of the global market for commercial service robots.
China leads the world robotics market, through its active creative industry, as it had already done in relation, for example, to toys. The country is responsible for around 80% to 90% of toys sold globally, whether old wooden toys, plush toys, inflatable toys, or electronic toys, with Guangdong, Jiangsu and Shandong being the main bases for purchasing toys, with the centers of Fujian, Zhejiang and Shanghai also being strong in this area. Centers that we also find linked to robotics, at least in the case of Shanghai and Shenzhen.
Can a relationship be established between toys and robotics in the case of China?
Toys are a strong focus of generation Z, short for zoomers, (those from the second half of the 90s until 2010), who fear a bleak future and invest a lot in emotional spending. This generation of the World Wide Web follows the growth of technological devices, being considered digital native.
As I believe, the path for the emergence of robots in China was laid out long before Generation Z appeared on the face of the earth. The Chinese have always loved toys, see their love for stuffed animals, lanterns, old wooden toys and, more recently, all types of electronic toys.
Now, robots, although they are much more than entertainment, have the appearance of toys, with the added advantage of being able to receive a strong emotional investment, combined with enormous practical utility. These “cans”, made from aluminum, steel and titanium, and plastics, such as polypropylene, ABS and polycarbonate, rubbers and elastomers, in addition to numerous electronic components, such as microprocessors, sensors, motors and wiring, are great companions of humans, faithful friends and obedience only limited to their manufacture.
They therefore appear to fulfill several functions and their emergence was only possible due to a close alliance between science and technology, that is, due to the development of technology, which was thematized by great contemporary writers and philosophers in the West, and think of Aldous Huxley (1894-1963) and his futuristic dystopia, entitled Brave New World. 1932), in which a society dominated by genetic engineering is psychologically conditioned, including by drugs (soma), in order to guarantee social well-being and suppress freedom and critical thinking.
Consider, also, works such as Oswald Spengler's (1880-1936), Man and Technique from 1931, which explores the relationship between human beings and technology, ultimately leading to self-destruction through the dissolution of Western culture. But if Western culture can feel, to paraphrase Spengler, “nauseated by machines”, there are others like the philosopher Martin Heidegger (1889-1976), who in The Question of Technique (1954) sees technique as the meaning of a new era for human beings. However, to do so it is necessary to know how to question the technique and not just accept it in an instrumental way at the service of anthropological purposes, when humanism for the philosopher of The Letter to Humanism (1946) has disastrous consequences, because it distances the true man from his essence and Being, which is thus hidden and not revealed.
None of these paths of Western thought have been followed by the Chinese of our times, strongly committed to the utilitarian use of technology. The instrumentalization of it at the service of humanity, or rather, of China, does not raise existential doubts in them, as is attested by the large robotics shopping malls currently available in Beijing or Shenzhen to a public eager for technological innovations.
Chinese robots serve all types of functions; industrial, commercial, scientific, recreational, domestic and emotional assistance. The relative lack of freedom, or the limitation of degrees of freedom (Degrees of Freedom, DOF) also does not seem worrying to them, at least to the point of raising philosophical questions about a dystopian future, viable through the genetic crossing of artificial intelligence with animals, including so-called rational humans.
They only seek to improve the degrees of freedom of robots defined as the number of independent movements of their joints and components, carried out in both the rotational and translational directions, these degrees being in the Humanoid Robotic Technology article, published in May 2025, variable according to the technical improvement of each machine: the greatest degree of freedom is presented by the Era-Star 1 Robot.
Therefore, do not expect great and unusual innovations regarding the degree of freedom of robots, they will be, until you see, limited and submissive to their creators. From a good creator a positive robot will emerge, from a bad creator, a negative one.
A friend with whom I discussed the topic was very surprised by the fact that one of the most populous countries in the world is at the forefront of robotic development, because for him it would be more important to provide employment to a huge population than to seek to replace them in almost all tasks, from scientific to the most routine, such as the transport and delivery of goods.
To understand why this total adherence to intelligent machinery, or as intelligent as its limited freedom allows, it is necessary to go back to the history of China. I propose a journey to the times of the emergence and development of the use of gunpowder. The appearance of gunpowder is associated with Alchemy and Taoist masters, who carried out the first scientific experiments in search of the elixir of longevity, already in the Warring States Period (战国 Zhàn Guó, 475-221 BC), being one of the four great inventions of Ancient China (四大发明Sì dà fāmíng). The first type of gunpowder to emerge was black gunpowder (黑火药Hēi huǒyào), the experiments of the alchemists were very well received and encouraged by the dominant power, then the experiments continued during the Eastern Han dynasty (东汉Dōng Hàn, 25-220), with the treatise by Wei Boyang (魏伯阳), entitled Zhouyi Cantongqi, being famous. (《周易参同契》), and translated as The Concordance of the Three, or that of the Jin dynasty (晋代Jìn dài, 266-420) by the great alchemist Ge Hong (葛洪), whose title is Baopuzi, in Portuguese, The Master Who Embraces Simplicity (《抱朴子·仙药篇》), especially its chapter dedicated to the manufacture of the pill of immortality.
Perhaps when using combustion methods to create the pill, the alchemists discovered gunpowder by chance by mixing sulfur, saltpeter and charcoal. It is certain that the explosion occurred and the dangerous, flammable and detonating element was discovered, but it is no less certain that the masters did not follow this route, which they considered unproductive for the desired objective. Then only much later during the Song dynasty (宋代Sòng dài， 960-1279) is it known that some artisans established fireworks workshops in Kaifeng to produce rockets and fireworks indispensable for all great moments of celebration in China.
The use of gunpowder then followed two very different paths, one pyrotechnic for recreational purposes of the imperial power and associated stately homes, the other for military use.
Why is the story of the discovery of gunpowder brought here? Because this could perhaps contain the three dimensions that we can find in the creation and interest in robots in China. Its creation reveals an enormous scientific interest associated: on the one hand, with philosophical practices aimed at developing life to its limits and perhaps even their absence, which would be achieved by immortality; on the other, it expresses an immense recreational desire with deep emotional investment, and, on the other, a practical utility, which puts robotics at the forefront, both in scientific, military and civil terms.
The new Chinese philosophy, as the oldest genuinely autochthonous one, appears in close connection with science and techniques with mysterious connections to the world of magic for the Taoist masters of yesterday, who are followed by the great doctors, including those of traditional Chinese medicine, who today find precious laboratory assistants carrying out work of great precision and minimal errors, since robots do not They get tired, they don't even bother, they do what is asked of them without any salary demands.
Furthermore, in military terms this arsenal of machinery is an excellent alternative, as it saves lives, as it is complex and autonomous enough to do so.
Obviously, of the many ethical issues associated with this exponential development of the new world of robotics and artificial intelligence, one seems essential, above all and, for now, in terms of biotechnical experimentation and related scientific research, which will be discussed below.  First the example, taken from the development of dynamic electrodes for brain-computer interface, as is happening at the Shenzhen Institute of Advanced Technology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences. In brain-computer interface systems, electrodes from electronic devices must be connected to the brain to acquire electroencephalographic signals. These electrodes are made of flexible fiber, similar to a worm, with a magnetic sensor incorporated in the head of the “worm”, to be manipulated according to the orientation of external magnetic fields. These flexible fiber electrodes were introduced into the brains of rabbits and also rats, with the aim of subsequently serving human clinical needs, such as intelligent control of prostheses, localization of epileptic lesions and treatment of chronic neurological disorders.
From an ethical point of view, the question cannot help but be asked: why are human lives more important than all others on our planet? Human beings remain the kings of creation, even within the scope of philosophies such as the Chinese, whose non-humanist tradition, as referred to in Heidegger's Letter to Humanism, is well known.
Are we humans really that valuable?  Science must continue its path, which in China will always be followed from a pragmatic and utilitarian perspective for the benefit of the Chinese and the Chinese nation. But don't think that robotics is there just to serve Chinese society without exchanging favors, as we cannot forget the enormous emotional investment that the population that descends from Dragons makes in these new beings, some more bionic than others, who acquire the status of companions and friends and, in this capacity, have all the pampering that was previously due to the humans and animals they chose to cherish.
The new Chinese philosophy is utilitarian, practical and has new entities in its world of knowledge, such as humanoids, bionic robots and robotics toys. They are highly esteemed and paving the way for a new era, that of cyborgs or better said, the mixed humanity of tomorrow, which will have the greatest chance of living long and, who knows, immortalizing itself.
Bibliographic References
Academy of Chinese Studies (中国文化研究员). 2025.中國古代火藥與火器 ? (Gunpowder and Firearms of Ancient China). Available at: https://chiculture.org.hk/tc/china-five-thousand-years/198, accessed on October 1, 2025.
陈宇轩 (Chen Yuxuan) .2025.  “让传感器动起来 我国科研团队研发出脑机接口动态电极” (Putting sensors in motion: A Chinese research team has developed dynamic electrodes for brain-computer interfaces), 新华网Xinhua, September 18, 2025. Available at: http://www.news.cn/20250918/d47375c582dd4cd7a632cb099d92822d/c.html, accessed on September 24, 2025.
CGTN Africa. 2025 World’s first Robot Mall opens in Beijing’s E-town at Robot Conference. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=awbH5JqdqLs, August 12, 2025, accessed September 25, 2025.
CGTN. 2025. “World’s first robot 6S store to open in China’s Shenzhen”. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2NhodG2lUGo, accessed on September 25, 2025.
CGTN Europe 2025 “China explained: Why adults are crazy about toys? Available at:” https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v4-Pf3Jt2x8, accessed September 26, 2025.
Heidegger, Martin. 1987. Letter to Humanism. Revised translation by Pinharanda Gomes, Preface by Doctor José Brandão. Lisbon: Guimarães Editores.
Humanoid Robotics Technology. 2025. Top 10 Chinese Humanoid Robots of 2025. Available at: https://humanoidroboticstechnology.com/articles/top-10-chinese-humanoid-robots-of-2025/, accessed on October 2, 2025.
Huxley, Aldous. 2013. Brave New World. Lisbon: Bertrand.
(潘俊强Pan Junqiang) 2025. 我国连续12年保持全球最大工业机器人市场.  (China has led the world industrial robotics market for twelve consecutive years)人民日报. Available at: https://www.gov.cn/yaowen/liebiao/202508/content_7035025.htm, August 3, 2025. Accessed September 24, 2025.
Sohu. 2022. Minimalist History Series: The Invention of Black Gunpowder (Traceable to the Sui Dynasty). Sohu. Available at https://www.sohu.com/a/593986613_120900450, accessed on October 1, 2025.
Spengler, Oswald. 1993. Man and Technique. Lisbon: Guimarães: Editors.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Study | Trump was the main disseminator of disinformation in the USA in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/estudo-trump-foi-principal-disseminador-de-desinformacao-nos-eua-em-2024/</link><description>North American President Donald Trump was the main disseminator of disinformation in the United States of America (USA) in 2024, concluded a study by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ). “US President Donald Trump was the dominant source and distributor of disinformation” in 2024, say the authors of the study “Disarming Disinformation: United States”.
The study highlights that Trump has drawn on the functions of domestic political forces, rather than foreign state actors, as the main source of disinformation narratives in US political discourse. Furthermore, the existence of WhatsApp groups and other closed digital spaces often act as “information cocoons” that encourage rumors and other forms of misinformation.
In this way, "the viral spread of misinformation and the strategic attack on journalists have emerged as interconnected threats to democracy. In an era of increasing authoritarianism and democratic backsliding, falsehoods are often used as a weapon by state actors to influence public opinion, undermine journalism and intimidate journalists."
The study authors state that these factors are increasingly the North American reality, with Donald Trump “promulgating manifestly false narratives” in recent years.
“The American media faces a profound information crisis, at a time of repression of freedom of expression”, the study reads. In this sense, trust in the mainstream press continues to decline in a climate of increasing attacks on the media by the Trump Government.
The study published by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ) was based on the analysis of 10,000 news and media publications during 2024, as well as a survey of 1,020 Americans.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:38:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists ‘reduce’ the age of the Egyptian temple of Karnak, in Egypt</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/08/cientistas-reduzem-idade-do-templo-egipcio-de-karnak-no-egipto/</link><description>Researchers have carried out the most comprehensive geoarchaeological study of the Karnak temple, near Luxor, and revealed suggestive links to ancient Egyptian mythology and new data about the interaction between the complex's riverine landscape and the people who occupied the site during its almost 3,000 years of use.
The results of the investigation were published on Monday in Antiquity magazine, reported the Efe news agency. Researchers from the University of Southampton, in the United Kingdom, and Uppsala University, in Sweden, participated in the study. Up to 61 sediment samples from the interior and surroundings of the temple and thousands of ceramic fragments found in the Karnak complex, located 500 meters east of the current Nile River, near Luxor, in the ancient Egyptian religious capital of Thebes, were analyzed.
The researchers mapped how the landscape around the site changed throughout its history and found that, before 2520 BC, the site could not have been suitable for permanent occupation due to periodic flooding caused by the Nile's strong currents. Therefore, they placed the earliest occupation at Karnak during the Old Kingdom (between 2591 and 2152 BC).
Pottery fragments found at the site corroborate this discovery, with the oldest dating between 2305 and 1980 BC. Therefore, the conclusions of this international team of researchers provide new evidence about the age of Karnak, which has been hotly debated in archaeological circles for decades.
The origin of everything
The ground on which the temple was founded was formed when river channels advanced west and east, creating an island of high ground in what is now the east-southeast region of the site. This emerging island laid the foundation for the occupation and initial construction of Karnak.
Over the following centuries and millennia, the river channels on both sides of the site diverged further, creating more space for the development of the temple complex, as researchers have now confirmed. This new understanding of the temple's landscape bears striking similarities to an ancient Egyptian creation myth, leading the team to believe that the decision to locate the temple there may have been related to the religious views of its inhabitants.
Ancient Egyptian texts from the Old Kingdom indicate that the 'Creator God' manifested himself as high ground emerging from the lake, and researchers have found that the island where Karnak was founded is the only known area of ​​high ground surrounded by water in the region.
Thus, archaeologists have suggested that the Theban elites chose the location of Karnak to be the abode of a new form of 'Creator God', alluding to Amun-Ra, the supreme god of ancient Egypt, since the location fit perfectly into the mythological setting of the highlands that emerged from the surrounding waters as the origin of the formation of the Universe.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 17:22:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics | Nobel Prize for Macroscopic Quantum Mechanical Tunneling</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/07/fisica-nobel-para-tunelamento-mecanico-quantico-macroscopico/</link><description>The Nobel Prize in Physics was awarded to John Clarke, Michel H. Devoret and John M. Martinis “for the discovery of macroscopic quantum mechanical tunneling and the quantization of energy in an electrical circuit”, announced yesterday the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences.
"An important question in physics is the maximum size of a system capable of demonstrating the effects of quantum mechanics. This year's Nobel Prize laureates carried out experiments with an electrical circuit in which they demonstrated both quantum tunneling and quantized energy levels in a system large enough to be held in the hand", explains the Swedish Academy of Sciences in a statement published on its website.
The British John Clarke carried out his research at the University of California, Berkeley, USA; the American John Martinis at the University of California, Santa Barbara; and the Frenchman Michel Devoret at Yale University and also in California, Santa Barbara.
According to academia, quantum mechanics allows a particle to directly cross a barrier, through a process called tunneling. When a large number of particles are involved, quantum effects usually become negligible. The experiments of the now distinguished scientists demonstrated that quantum properties can be made concrete on a macroscopic scale.
"It is wonderful to be able to celebrate the way in which quantum mechanics, more than a century old, continues to offer new surprises. It is also extremely useful, as it is the basis of all digital technology", said the chairman of the Nobel Committee for Physics, Olle Eriksson, quoted in the statement.
The Swedish academy says that transistors in computer microchips are an example of consolidated quantum technology. The scientists today awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics share a prize of 11 million Swedish kronor (almost one million euros).</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:15:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Chemistry | Nobel Prize for the development of metal-organic structures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/quimica-nobel-para-o-desenvolvimento-de-estruturas-metalorganicas/</link><description>The Nobel Prize in Chemistry was awarded to Susumu Kitagawa, from Kyoto University, Richard Robson, from the University of Melbourne, and Omar M. Yaghi, from the University of California, “for the development of metal-organic structures”, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences announced yesterday.
Susumu Kitagawa, Richard Robson and Omar Yaghi have developed a new form of molecular architecture – metal-organic frameworks – that can be used to collect water from desert air, capture carbon dioxide, store toxic gases or catalyze chemical reactions.
The three laureates created molecular constructs with large spaces through which gases and other chemicals could flow. The president of the Nobel Committee for Chemistry, Heiner Linque, highlighted precisely the fact that these “metal-organic structures have enormous potential, bringing previously unforeseen opportunities for personalized materials with new functions”.
The research that led to the discovery of this new form of molecular architecture began nearly four decades ago, in 1989, when Richard Robson tested the use of the inherent properties of atoms by combining positively charged copper ions with a four-armed molecule.
When combined, they bonded "to form a spacious, well-ordered crystal. It was like a diamond filled with countless cavities," the academy explains. Robson immediately realized the potential of his molecular construction, but it was still unstable and crumbled easily. It was chemists Susumu Kitagawa and Omar Yaghi who managed to provide a solid foundation for this construction method.
Notable applications
Following the discoveries of the three laureates, chemists built tens of thousands of different MOFs. Some of them could contribute to solving some of humanity's biggest challenges, with applications including breaking down traces of pharmaceuticals in the environment, capturing carbon dioxide or collecting water from desert air.
The discovery also allows the separation of perfluoroalkylated and polyfluoroalkylated substances (PFAS) from water. PFAS are a group of synthetic chemical compounds known as “forever chemicals” due to their extreme persistence in the environment and in the human body.
PFAS are used in a wide range of industrial and household products, such as stain- and water-resistant textiles, food packaging, non-stick cookware and firefighting foams. Its accumulation in the environment and potential health risks, including liver damage and other problems, have led to concerns and a search for safer alternatives.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:41:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Linguistics | Published study based on a trip to Macau in the 19th century</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/03/linguistica-publicado-estudo-baseado-numa-viagem-a-macau-no-seculo-xix/</link><description>Academic Anabela Leal de Barros has just published a linguistic study that focuses on the trip of Father Miranda e Oliveira, linked to the Congregation of the Mission, to Macau in 1825. With touches of history, details are revealed about the Portuguese of the time and of Macau. The book will be presented at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center next Wednesday
 
“Journey from Lisbon to Macau – 1825” is the title of the most recent work published by Grão-Falar, written by University of Minho academic Anabela Leal de Barros.
The book makes a critical and interpretative analysis of the Portuguese of the time left in the manuscript of parish priest José Joaquim de Miranda e Oliveira, priest of the Congregation of the Mission. This documentation is kept by the Braga District Archive. However, the work does not just explore the Portuguese of the time, revealing other historical details of Macau, Asia and a sea voyage.
As Anabela Leal de Barros told HM, the work is “as faithful as possible to the spelling of the manuscript”, until now practically unknown.
In this travel diary, Father Miranda e Oliveira “reveals enormous curiosity about all the news and shares with us their names in the languages ​​of the world in which they were baptized, starting with ours”.
This is how he explains situations such as “seasickness, a reality that was still relatively unknown and highly invasive on boats” in those times. The priest named or defined “the mangalhões, the porpoises, the caravels, the black-eyed peas, the flies, the albacores — all sorts of birds and fish that were admired, fished or tasted throughout the trip”, or even the “meteorological phenomena with local names – cacimba, samatra, typhoon”. There are also details about “cultural habits such as the masca, buio in Indonesian; the Philippine seges, the berloches, and the ruling class of the camisolas, as well as the sômas, Chinese vessels”.
The vessel left Lisbon in April 1825 and spent time in the Philippines, arriving in Macau on October 23rd. The arrival “to the island of Caó” and the following day “to Colégio de S. José” is described, to “a city with ‘a magnificent port of commerce’, located ‘on a very pleasant peninsula’, with ‘good waters’ and ‘famous European-style buildings'”.
Linguistic varieties
In the work published by Grão-Falar there are, for example, “rich stories such as that of Orvalhadas de S. João, Caldeirão de Frei Junípero or the habit of seafarers shouting ‘Refresca S. Lourenço!’ so that the wind blows, this being the meaning here of ‘refresh’”.
There are also “allusions to the linguistic variety itself”, as “at various times there is reference to communication with foreigners carried out in Latin, in Indonesian-Dutch and Filipino-Spanish territory; the private teaching of English in the Philippines by members of the Congregation of the Mission; the little knowledge and use of Spanish, even in Manila, and the variation of Tagalog itself, a language in which the priest is concerned about recording the Hail Mary.”
Before arriving at this travel report, Anabela Leal de Barros was already in the intricacies of investigating this type of manuscripts, coming across the story of another priest, “the greatest Portuguese sinologist, Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, who had traveled from the same house as Rilhafoles of the Congregation of the Mission to Macau in 1812”.
According to the author, this parish priest “dedicated the last twenty-nine years of his life to the mission of evangelization in China, and in particular to the research and teaching of Chinese at the Colégio de S. José in Macau”. In his entire life, “this Trás-os-Montes native wrote more than five thousand pages of grammars and dictionaries in Portuguese, Latin and Chinese, expressly dedicated to his students at the College, seven printed in his typography and at least two manuscripts”.
Then, in 2017, António Lázaro, from the History Department of the University of Minho, and director of the Confúcio Institute, made available to Anabela Leal de Barros “a list of references to manuscripts from the Braga District Archive about Macau and China”. A “journey” began, which culminated in the publication of this study.
“This book is the first result of a project of mine to edit and study unpublished travel literature manuscripts whose main objective is exactly this: to contribute to the appreciation and consolidation of the micro-history of the Discoveries and the memory of history, between the 15th and 19th centuries”.
Accompanied on travel
José Joaquim de Miranda e Oliveira took around seven months to arrive in Macau, leaving Lisbon on April 1, 1825, and arriving in Oriente on October 24 of the same year. He left on the ship Vasco da Gama with three other priests from the congregation: João da França de Castro e Moura, Jerónimo José da Mata and José́ Ferreira da Silva.
According to Anabela Leal de Barros, “the manuscript does not appear to have been cleaned by the author himself, given the type of spelling variations and typos and amendments it presents”, having probably been “translated, to safeguard copies, by a Macanese member of the College, since Macau Portuguese, in the 19th century, had characteristics compatible with certain traits, strange in a priest arrived from Portugal, even how young.”
This travel diary “ends on the very day of arrival in Macau, with a very brief presentation of the city and the school, making clear the Catholic perspective of the time in relation to the Chinese cult of ancestors and without failing to draw attention to the mere five thousand Christians among the 40 to 50 thousand inhabitants of the city”.
Political hostilities
José Joaquim de Miranda e Oliveira describes how the bishop of Macau did not receive the delegation, which is “enough to lead us to the hostile context in which the Lazarists, defenders of liberalism, found themselves, which had led Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, a few years earlier, to take refuge in the Philippines, with the school missing two of its teachers”.
Furthermore, “along the journey the priest does not fail to narrate all the moments in which he carries out his daily mission, with the administration of the sacraments, the prayer of responsos and the celebration of masses, but above all he notes the notable lack of priests who reveal the Christianized peoples, particularly in Batavia, now Jakarta, where the community of Portuguese origin, of more than a thousand people, had only an old priest.”
These reports also reveal the concern to “remember the first French martyrs of the Congregation in the attempt to evangelize Madagascar and to report the presence of friars and priests from the different congregations, from Cape Verde to the Philippines, where they are recognized as more important for the solidity of Spanish rule than its army”.
According to Anabela Leal de Barros, the report also alluded, in Java, “to the Lutherans and Mohammedans, as well as to the religions of China and, in Manila, to the persecution of Christians (referring to the ‘dinner’, that is, lunch with a Chinese Christian, ‘and as such persecuted’)”.
Miranda and Oliveira had “a very diplomatic and convivial conduct, ensuring the establishment and maintenance of cordial relations between the various orders and also with the governors and foreign powers present, from the Dutch to the Spanish, who visited everywhere”.
An ongoing project
In those years, it was a dangerous adventure to travel by boat, facing “anthropogenic peoples, piracy, diseases on ships and epidemics”, a “perfectly cinematic vision” already described in Os Lusíadas, by Luís de Camões. Those who embarked on these trips also found themselves alone, “individually and on a small ship little more than a walnut shell, facing an endless sea, for months, at times when it was common for several passengers not to reach their destination, or for not even one ship from a full squadron to return”.
In Miranda and Oliveira's report, “there is no great news” compared to previous reports, but “we are aware of the main difficulties of sea voyages to Asia in the 19th century: the rocks that existed even before the Torre de Belém, which caused many shipwrecks; and seasickness, which even deserves a definition for the many readers who had never set foot on a boat, and to which the captain's face advising the sick ladies going up to the awning and working, as it was the best medicine”.
There is also “the episode of the man falling overboard from the plow that accompanied them on part of the trip, which they were unable to save — a death to which everyone was so exposed, as the narrator refers”. Another potential misfortune in trips of this type also stands out, “the encounter with ships that, not immediately raising any flag, or raising it without giving true confidence, immediately led to the decision to light the hills and open fire, which well reflects the dimension of piracy and the fears it imposed”.
Essentially, “the main character of sea voyages was the wind”, which led the still “young priest” to “evoke the Camonian verses of the storm twice”.
After arriving in Macau, Miranda e Oliveira left for his post in Nanking, “on a journey comparatively longer than the first, received by the Christians with difficulty and secretly”. “In the face of persecution” he ended up succumbing “to the dangers and illnesses of the mainland, at the age of 31, far from all his confreres, on November 1, 1828, just two years after having described the difficult farewell to his spiritual family, in Lisbon”. “His traveling companions had more longevity, one of whom would become Bishop of Macau and the other of Beijing and Porto”, highlights Anabela Leal de Barros.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 01:39:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Ragasa | Sam Hou Fai calls for prevention so that Macau is not left to fate  </title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/23/ragasa-sam-hou-fai-apela-a-prevencao-para-que-macau-nao-fique-entregue-a-sorte/</link><description>The Government met yesterday to discuss civil protection operations due to super typhoon Ragasa. Sam Hou Fai called for prevention and Tai Kin Ip indicated that the casinos will close this afternoon, when signal 8 is issued. CNN said yesterday that, so far, Ragasa is the strongest storm this year worldwide
 
After making landfall yesterday on the island of Calyan in the Philippines, super typhoon Ragasa advanced through the South China Sea, following a trajectory that Macau authorities estimate could pass within 100 kilometers of the territory. CNN indicated yesterday that, so far, this was the worst storm this year globally.
Here, the arrival of the super typhoon led authorities to meet yesterday at the Civil Protection Operations Center with the Chief Executive. Sam Hoi Fai highlighted the importance of preventive work, noting that, based on analyzes by authorities in Mainland China, Hong Kong and Taiwan, Ragasa could be the strongest storm to hit the Macao SAR since Mangkhut, a possibility he classified as “very high”.
According to forecasts from the Meteorological and Geophysical Services, Ragasa could pass less than 100 kilometers from Macau between dawn and Wednesday morning.  Sam Hou Fai understands that society and all government services must be alert, and should not just “have a mentality to count on good luck”. “It is often said that ‘Macau is a blessed land’, but this can result in negligence,” he added.
The Chief Executive explained that Ragasa can cause overlapping “storm surge” phenomena, as occurred with Mangkhut, causing floods with a maximum height of five meters, at the level of the first floor of the Red Market, for example.
"The impact could be significant. Preparation was carried out in advance and interdepartmental communication, hoping that the losses could be reduced to the minimum possible, in order to guarantee the safety and stability of the entire population. I seriously appeal to all traders, public and private institutions, and even associations, to do the preparation work against the catastrophe in advance", he warned.
Casinos may close
On the sidelines of the same meeting, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, said that casinos will close their doors if storm signal 8 is raised, and that authorities will broadcast this scenario in advance, in order to guarantee the personal safety of tourists and employees in the tourism sector.  Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Security, said that his department met with companies and associations to coordinate street cleaning efforts after the typhoon hit. The secretary also called for the evacuation, first of all, of older residents.
In turn, the head of the Department of Family and Community Services at the Institute of Social Action, Lei Lai Peng, pointed out that the organization has prepared the launch of level 2 of the Emergency Evacuation and Reception Mechanism, with the 17 available emergency reception centers being able to be open, with the capacity to receive 24 thousand people.
Regarding the Macau Bridge, Raymond Tam, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, guaranteed that the infrastructure will be closed to traffic during the typhoon's passage, even though the previous results of tests on road traffic during storms were positive.  The secretary justified the closure of the bridge by saying that Ragasa is a “super typhoon” and that he took into account the poor condition of access to the infrastructure.
Raymond Tam also said that if the floods exceed one meter, he will consider the possibility of suspending the electricity supply in the lower areas of the territory, in order to speed up the entire recovery process after the typhoon.
From 3pm this afternoon until tomorrow, between 250 and 280 flights to or from Macau International Airport will be cancelled.  Regarding the return to school, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, assured that the Government will analyze the situation based on official data on floods and intense rains that occurred after the typhoon, provided by the Meteorological and Geophysical Services.
The condition of schools and roads will also be analyzed to decide whether there are conditions for reopening. However, O Lam indicated that schools have flexibility to address issues such as student attendance and testing scheduling.</description><pubDate>2025-09-23 03:12:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | Hong Kong films shown for the second time in Lisbon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/11/cinema-filmes-de-hong-kong-exibidos-pela-segunda-vez-em-lisboa/</link><description>Former Macau resident Vanessa Pimentel is the artistic director of the second edition of the Hong Kong Film Festival, which will take place between the 25th and 28th of September at Cinema Ideal, in Lisbon. “Making Waves – Navigators of Hong Kong” will present films such as “Papa”, the documentary “Four Trails” and the restored copy of “Ah Ying”, from 1983
 
There are six films, four fiction and two documentaries, which promise to show the best that is being done in Hong Kong cinema. This is the second edition of the Hong Kong Film Festival, taking place in Lisbon, at Cinema Ideal, between the 25th and 28th of September, and which has as artistic director Vanessa Pimentel, also a director, former resident of Macau linked to the production company Blue Lotus Lisboa.
In addition to the screenings, the Portuguese public will be able to see actors, directors and producers from Hong Kong up close, proving that it is possible to establish links between Portugal and different cinematographic environments. This year's poster is made up of “Papa”, a 2024 film by director Philip Yung that will be shown on the 25th, a Thursday. “All Shall Be Well” by Ray Yueng follows; “Never Too Late” by Rikki Choy; “Montages of a Modern Motherhood”, by Chan Oliver Siu Kuen; “Four Trails”, a 2023 documentary directed by Robin Lee. To end the festival in beauty, the restored copy of “Ah Ying”, by Allen Fong, a 1983 film, will be screened.
Vanessa Pimentel explained to HM that the exhibition has “a program that starts from Hong Kong”, where it has existed since 2022. “It is an itinerant program that aims to promote Hong Kong cinema, especially cinema made by younger directors in terms of experience, although the programs always contain works by more veteran directors”, she said.
This year, in addition to Lisbon, the Hong Kong Film Festival will visit cities such as Berlin, Paris, Montreal and Udine, in Italy. The event may or may not be linked to Asian film festivals. And it is Vanessa and Blue Lotus' intention to create an Asian film festival in Lisbon, with Macau cinema being part of it.
“In our case, the exhibition is not associated with any festival because it doesn’t exist yet, but I hope to be able to do it,” he said. "I was born and raised in Lisbon, but I come from Macau, and my life in Macau is very linked to all of this. Of course, an Asian film festival in Lisbon has to include Macau, and it couldn't be any other way."
“We do this program with a view to going a little further, and we have our sights set on creating an Asian film festival”, he further said. “We haven't achieved it yet, we have to keep working, but I think we're on the right track.”
Vanessa Pimentel says that, despite no longer living in the territory, she continues to be closely linked to the cinema that takes place here. "I go to Macau at least twice a year, and I have been in constant contact with film people. They are all aware of our program [at the Hong Kong Film Festival] and there is a relationship."
Film to film
We asked the exhibition's artistic director to talk about what the public will be able to see in the small Cinema Ideal room, which operates independently, without connection to large cinema exhibition groups, and which is located in the heart of Bairro Alto.
“Papa”, which opens the festival, is described “as a very strong and good film, which talks about mental health and has an incredible approach”. Vanessa Pimentel describes that this film was awarded in Hong Kong with the distinction of best actor, presenting “a very particular narrative” throughout the plot.
“All Shall Be Well” will be shown again in Lisbon, after its presentation at the International Queer Film Festival, and has already been shown in Berlin. “It’s a very good film, it wasn’t shown again after being in Berlin, I thought it would be interesting to put it on the schedule.”
Vanessa Pimentel also highlights the presentation of the restored copy of “Ah Ying”, which belongs to “the New Wave of Hong Kong Cinema”, and which shows a story that incessantly wanders between “fiction and documentary”. It is a “very interesting film in which the story is inspired by the story of the actress [Hui So Ying] who plays him”.
The second Hong Kong Film Festival will be attended by Hui So Ying. "It's a very big honor because the actress will be going on a giant journey. She is already quite old, but she made herself available as soon as she arrived. It will be very interesting to have a film inspired by her life and have her presence to share that moment with us", described Vanessa Pimentel.
Little known paths
Another highlight of the film exhibition is the screening of the documentary “Four Trails”, which has been “a box office phenomenon”. It is a film about the 298-kilometer race along the four most famous trails in Hong Kong.
The film portrays a daily reality “of regions of Hong Kong that almost no one knows about”. "It's a film about the challenge of sport and people who, not being professional athletes, sign up and run, training all year round. It's interesting to see the challenge they propose and how they live", said Vanessa Pimentel, who also highlights "Never Too Late", "a film about our relationship with the environment". Here one can glimpse “a very Asian and Chinese side of this perspective of what the environment is and what our relationship with nature is like”.
Then there is “Montage of a Modern Motherhood”, a film that “has been playing a lot at festivals”. “It's a film that has a very interesting side, about motherhood and a perspective that, perhaps, may not be so romantic, about the idea that motherhood is not just a bed of roses, having some downside”, says Vanessa Pimentel.
Here the artistic director of the exhibition warns of the fact that the film “may challenge a little”, touching “on things that concern everyone, like this thing about family tradition and sharing in motherhood and fatherhood”.
Vanessa Pimentel assures that the first edition of the exhibition was a success, with “around a thousand people going to the cinema in four days”. "It was surprising to see a lot of new people, older people and also many people of Chinese origin, that is, children of immigrants, possibly from a second generation, who were already born in Lisbon, speak Portuguese and live here with their families. We had sessions with many Chinese people asking questions at the end of the sessions and I had never seen that in Lisbon", he highlighted.
The Hong Kong Film Festival also ends up becoming part of the itinerary of spectators who usually go to festivals. "We also have a very interesting audience, made up of people who like cinema and attend other festivals. It is not common to see a program that, in Lisbon, focuses on Asian cinema. We have Doc Lisboa, or Indie, but in their programming the proportion of this cinema is much smaller. I am not making a criticism here, I think that is perfectly normal", said Vanessa Pimentel.
Between the Hong Kong Film Festival and the future festival, the person responsible says there is “exhibition space” in Lisbon and Portugal, due to the fact that Asian cinema is “very vast and rich, with a very high quantity and quality ratio”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 23:54:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Overseas Chinese | Lam calls for continuity in promoting Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/chineses-ultramarinos-o-lam-pede-continuidade-na-promocao-de-macau/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, defended the continuation, by the General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau, of the work to promote the territory, at a time when the entity celebrated, on Wednesday, 57 years of existence.
According to a statement, O Lam said, in a speech, that the association should promote the specific advantages of Macau as a Sino-Lusophone platform in addition to assuming the bridge between China, Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, as well as Spanish-speaking countries.
Lam also hopes that the association will continue to support local and Mainland Chinese companies in accessing international markets, in addition to supporting the import of certain international projects to China. This is so that Macau can explore the “circle of friends” and partners at an international level, supporting the country’s development in opening up to the outside world.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:31:05</pubDate></item><item><title>National Games | Sam Hou Fai participates in ceremony</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/jogos-nacionais-sam-hou-fai-participa-em-cerimonia/</link><description>The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, traveled to Nansha in Guangzhou City yesterday to attend the flame lighting ceremony of the 15th edition of the National Games and the 12th edition of the National Games for People with Disabilities and the 9th edition of the National Special Olympics Games.
According to the Social Communication Office, it was expected that the flame for the National Games would be lit by leaders from the General Administration of Sports in China, the China Federation for the Disabled, Guangdong Province, Hong Kong and Macau.
This is the first edition organized jointly by these regions. The ceremony was also expected to be attended by Secretary O Lam, as president of the Organizing Committee of the Macau Competition Zone, and Pun Weng Kun, as coordinator of the Preparatory Office for the Organization of the Macau Competition Zone.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:29:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Central Library | 30 proposals received for the creation of a superstructure</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/biblioteca-central-recebidas-30-propostas-para-criacao-de-superestrutura/</link><description>Once the construction of the foundations and basements of the project designed by the Mecanoo studio has been completed, the construction of the superstructure of the New Macau Central Library should take place by the end of the year
 
The public competition for the award of works on the superstructure of the New Macau Central Library resulted in the presentation of 30 proposals. The opening of the documents presented yesterday by the candidates was held yesterday, at the headquarters of the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP).
The public tender was launched on August 21st and defines 620 days as the maximum period for construction of this phase of the project located in Tap Seac. Work on the superstructure should also begin by the end of the year, after the construction of the foundations and basements is completed.
According to the Government, the new project will make it possible to “solve” the “problem of lack of space in the current central library”, in addition to fulfilling the “mission of promoting reading for the entire population, cultural exchange and showcasing local characteristics”.
Proposals will be evaluated based on price (a criterion weighing 50 percent in the decision), execution time (15 percent), experience and quality of works (20 percent), execution program (10 percent) and also taking into account the human resources program plan and proportion of resident workers in management positions (5 percent).
The future library will occupy an area of ​​around 2,960 square meters and the project envisages the construction of four floors in height and a basement, with a gross construction area of ​​around 13,800 square meters. According to official data, this construction area is “ten times larger than that of the old central library”, located on the opposite side of Praça do Tap Seac.
The ground floor and upper floors of the building will contain facilities such as auditoriums, a newspaper and magazine reading area, libraries for adults and children, meeting rooms and multimedia spaces dedicated to teaching.
Troubled project
The construction of the new library in Macau has been planned for more than 10 years, with the processes of choosing the location and preparing the project being marked by several controversies.
Initially, during Fernando Chui Sai On's second term as Chief Executive, an invitation to Portuguese architect Álvaro Siza Vieira was revealed to design the future library. However, due to pressure from local interest groups, the invitation to the Portuguese architect was withdrawn, which led to a public competition.
As part of the first competition, a project from the architect Carlos Marreiros' studio was chosen, with a price of 18.68 million patacas. The library was planned for the old courthouse. However, the works never started, because faced with criticism about the planned location, the Executive decided to choose a new location, the current one, located in Praça do Tap Seac and which involved the demolition of the old Hotel Estoril.
The changes led to another public competition, this time international, which ended with the choice of the Dutch studio Mecanoo. It is this project that is now being built.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:28:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Game is a factor of stability</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/estudo-jogo-e-factor-de-estabilidade/</link><description>The work published at the beginning of the month highlights the importance of gambling for the local economy and warns against adventures in economic diversification that could jeopardize local stability
 
An industry susceptible to being affected by regional and global political and economic uncertainties, but also highly resilient and should be seen as a factor of stability in the territory. These are some conclusions of the study entitled “Regional and Global Uncertainty and the Impacts on the Tourism and Gaming Industry of Macau”, published in the magazine Cogent Economics &amp; Finance by academic Tang Chi Chong.
In the research, published on October 3, it is recognized that regional and global uncertainties “may influence gambling revenues” in Macau, and changes in the economic and political environments will have an impact on gambling revenues. This impact is expected in terms of betting in casinos, especially if the uncertainties occur in places such as the Interior, Hong Kong, Taiwan or South Korea, the Macao SAR's main tourist markets. “Macau’s gaming industry is not isolated from the outside world”, it is acknowledged.
However, the study also concludes that Macau's tourism is highly resilient to negative impacts compared to traditional tourism markets, where gambling is less important. “Macau’s hotel sector is less sensitive to global risks and uncertainties compared to traditional hotel sectors, largely due to the presence of the gaming industry”, it is justified. "However, the impacts of regional and global uncertainty are not significant for Macau's pillar industry. The city's gaming sector demonstrates strong resilience in the face of economic and political instability, both regionally and globally", it was added.
Protect the chicken
In view of these conclusions, the study argues that the gaming industry must be protected, even in an environment in which attempts are made to diversify Macau's economy.
"It is clear that the integration of the gaming industry into Macau's tourism sector increases the overall resilience of the city's tourism and hospitality industry. Economic diversification has been a key policy of the Macau government. However, special attention should be paid to the sensitivity of different industries compared to the gaming sector", he was warned. "If the gaming industry demonstrates high resilience to uncertainty, maintaining it could be a viable strategy to stabilize the economy. Furthermore, resilience to uncertainty could serve as a key criterion for the government in selecting industries for development, as it contributes to economic stability in a context of increasing global economic and political uncertainty," it was added.
Tang Chi Chong is linked to the Macau Polytechnic University, Macau Tourism University and the Hong Kong Polytechnic University.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:27:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Video surveillance | IAS waiting for orders from daycare centers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/videovigilancia-ias-a-espera-de-pedidos-das-creches/</link><description>A representative of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) confirmed, according to the newspaper Ou Mun, that it has not yet received any requests for the installation of video surveillance cameras by daycare centers. The confirmation was made during the meeting of the Central Zone Community Services Advisory Council, where the same representative spoke about the action plan for installing cameras.
It was mentioned by the IAS that some daycare centers will still be preparing the documentation to make the request, and there is also the possibility that some daycare centers may need to know more information about the plan, which is why the IAS intends to hold explanation sessions with the daycare centers' management entities and parents.
In turn, the Council's deputy coordinator, Wu Hang San, cited the words of the IAS representative when he said that there are strict mechanisms when it comes to accessing images captured by video surveillance cameras, and that both parents and daycare center managers can fill out a form and submit it to the IAS to request viewing of the images within 14 days of the occurrence of an incident or episode. concrete. The final decision to transmit the images rests with the IAS, and if the case is in the hands of the police, only these authorities can view the captured images.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:25:54</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC | DSC doctor obtained false certificates to increase salary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/ccac-medico-da-dsc-obteve-falsos-atestados-para-aumentar-salario/</link><description>The Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC) discovered a case of fraud and falsification of documents by a doctor working for the Directorate of Correctional Services (DSC). According to a statement, this doctor “obtained several medical certificates for himself or his parents, in collusion with doctors who worked in public or private medical institutions in Macau”, between 2014 and 2018, managing to earn “for several years, a salary of around 150 thousand patacas”.
The doctor, with a work connection to DSC, his family members and doctors from the private entity involved “have committed the crimes of fraud and document forgery” provided for in the Penal Code, with the CCAC also discovering that the doctor “carried out part-time paid duties without the knowledge and consent of the service where he worked”.
On the part of DSC, disciplinary proceedings were initiated against this employee with the entity “actively collaborating with the CCAC investigation”, and the case was transferred to the Public Ministry for investigation.
The DSC also says that it “attachs high importance to the case and has developed “a comprehensive review of the mechanism for managing absences from work due to illness, as well as reinforcing internal supervision, including visits to workers' homes and checking their illness status together with Health Service professionals”. DSC to “strengthen supervision”, requiring “all workers to fulfill the obligations inherent to the exercise of public functions, with dedication and respect for the law”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:15:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Deputies promise to fight for more labor rights</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/trabalho-deputados-prometem-lutar-por-mais-direitos-laborais/</link><description>Leong Pou U and Lam Lon Wai, deputies elected indirectly by the labor sector, promised yesterday to take office from October 16th to guarantee more labor rights. The promise was made during his appearance on the morning program Forum Macau on the Chinese channel Radio Macau.
Returning to one of the old issues on the Workers' agenda, Lam Lon Wai recalled that annual vacations and mandatory holidays have not been increased for several years. The current deputy expressed the desire that this aspect be changed in the next Legislature. Currently, the number of mandatory vacation days is six days per year.
Lam Lon Wai also hopes that the days of remuneration paid during maternity leave in the private sector will be equivalent to those in the public sector. In the public sector, workers enjoy 90 days of paid maternity leave. However, in the private sector the number is 70 days.
Lam Lon Wai also pointed out that in the next term he will pay greater attention to improving occupational safety in the construction sector. The promise was made after a worker died on a construction site in recent days.
For his part, Leong Pou U stated that he will focus on labor guarantees for workers in emerging industries, and mainly on take-away distributors. For the future deputy, it is imperative to define the responsibilities regarding the employment insurance of these distributors. Leong Pou U also declared his desire to contribute to increasing maternity and paternity leaves.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:04:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Calm in the heart of the storm</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/calmaria-no-coracao-da-tempestade/</link><description>On September 23rd, late in the afternoon, Super Typhoon “Ragasa” approached Macau and the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate issued a typhoon signal number 8, however, everywhere calm reigned. Perhaps this was a unique phenomenon that preceded the storm, because what followed would test the tenacity of the people of Macau.
In the direct elections for the Legislative Assembly, which took place on September 14th, thanks to the strong appeal of the Chief Executive and the constant efforts of the heads of government departments, the majority of public servants responded to the call and fulfilled their “duty” to vote.
With the active cooperation of the largest operators in the gaming industry and the vigorous outreach of the candidate list campaign teams, the combined votes of the six candidate lists running in the direct elections to the Legislative Assembly this time far exceeded the votes obtained by the 14 candidate lists in 2021, resulting in a higher voter turnout in 2025 than in previous elections. Furthermore, there were surprising results: the incumbent deputy José Pereira Coutinho managed to be re-elected and his list came out ahead with 43,367 votes. At the same time, 5,987 blank votes and 7,053 invalid votes were recorded in these elections, setting a record for blank votes and invalid votes since Macau's return to Chinese sovereignty.
When we analyze the results of direct elections we must opt ​​for a pragmatic approach. For example, the calculation of voter turnout cannot be based solely on the number of voters. In 2001, 159,813 voters were registered and voter turnout was 52.34 percent. In 2025, 328,506 voters were already registered and voter turnout was 53.35 percent.
Comparing with voter turnout of 58.39 percent in 2005, 59.91 percent in 2009, 55.02 percent in 2013 and 57.22 percent in 2017, the 2025 result was the third lowest, but still significantly higher than the 42.38 percent that followed the first incident of candidate disqualification. direct elections to the Legislative Assembly in 2021.
The 7,053 invalid votes represented a percentage of 4.02 percent and, although in percentage terms it is lower than that recorded in 2009, where 6,498 invalid votes corresponded to 4.36 percent of the vote, it is the highest ever in absolute terms. With only six candidate lists in 2025, the chance of voters filling out the form incorrectly is no greater than in 2009, when there were 16 candidate lists. Unfortunately, the invalid votes in 2025 were not publicly disclosed as in previous elections, leaving the population unable to understand why these votes were considered invalid.
According to Article 26 of the Macao SAR Basic Law, “permanent residents of the Macau Special Administrative Region have the right to elect and be elected, in accordance with the law”. While Article 95 of the “Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly of the Macao SAR” stipulates that “suffrage constitutes a right and a civic duty”, but does not specify how this civic duty must be fulfilled. The recently added Article 167-A stipulates that “anyone who publicly encourages voters not to vote, vote blank or invalid, is punished with a prison sentence of up to 3 years”. In Macau, voting is not mandatory like in Australia and Argentina. The chairman of the Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly, Mr. Seng Ioi Man, publicly stated after consulting the Administration and Civil Service Bureau, – if a civil servant does not vote for any reason, no disciplinary action will be taken against him in accordance with the Macao SAR Public Service Legal Regime.
Voting is a civic right, which is logically different from the concept of “duty”. A right presupposes freedom of choice, while a “duty” implies a moral and legal obligation. And as in Macau public servants are not required to vote, your vote is an entirely personal choice. Just as Macau's Basic Law guarantees residents the right to strike, this does not imply that they are obliged to participate in strikes. The high number of votes obtained by List 2 – NOVA ESPERAÇÃO can certainly be attributed to the response of many public servants to the Government's call for “fulfillment of civic duty”.
Regardless of the intensity of the typhoon, it is expected that people's lives will soon return to normal, with the combined efforts of the Macao SAR Government and the population. However, after another incident of disqualification of candidates for the 2025 direct elections to the Legislative Assembly, how many choices will voters have in the direct elections to the Legislative Assembly in 2029? Furthermore, the first arrest related to safeguarding national security took place in Macau. The detainee's surname is Au and he will be tried. How to enjoy peace in the heart of the storm is a profound exercise in political philosophy.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:12:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Peace for Ukraine</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/paz-para-a-ucrania/</link><description>"The test of politics is how it ends, not how it begins. Peace must reflect reality, not illusion."
Henry Kissinger
Ukraine, as a candidate country for the European Union (EU), represents one of the greatest challenges and opportunities in the recent history of the European project. The war between Russia and Ukraine, which began in 2022, represents one of the most serious armed conflicts on European soil since World War II. Its consequences are devastating with thousands of deaths, millions of displaced people, destroyed cities, collapsed economies and a deep geopolitical divide between East and West. Peace, although desired by many, continues to seem like a distant horizon. However, history teaches that even the most prolonged and violent conflicts can find resolution, provided there is political will, effective mediation and a solid diplomatic architecture. To understand the possibilities for peace, it is necessary to revisit the root causes of the conflict.
The war did not start in 2022, but has historical, identity and geopolitical roots that date back to the dissolution of the Soviet Union. Ukraine, by asserting its sovereignty and moving closer to Euro-Atlantic structures, has become, in Moscow's eyes, a strategic territory in dispute. The annexation of Crimea in 2014 and Russian support for the separatist republics of Donetsk and Lugansk were the first signs of an escalation that would culminate in a full invasion. Russia justifies its action with arguments of security, protection of Russian-speaking populations and resistance to NATO expansion. Ukraine, in turn, defends its right to self-determination, territorial integrity and the choice of its allies.
This antagonism is fueled by divergent historical narratives, strategic interests and deep mutual distrust. Any peace process will have to face these roots, recognize them and find ways to overcome them without denying the sovereignty of each State. Peace between Russia and Ukraine faces several obstacles, firstly, territorial occupation, as the Russian military presence in Ukrainian territory, including Crimea and parts of Donbass, is one of the main obstacles. Ukraine demands the full withdrawal of occupying forces as a condition of any agreement. Russia, in turn, considers Crimea an integral part of its territory and sees Donbass as a zone of legitimate influence.
Secondly, international recognition, as the international community, in particular Western countries, supports Ukraine and imposes sanctions on Russia. This polarization makes mediation difficult and reinforces block logic. Peace requires a neutral diplomatic space, where both parties can negotiate without excessive external pressure. Thirdly, the human losses and collective traumas as the war generated deep wounds in Ukrainian society. The destruction of cities, massacres, bombings and forced displacement have created a feeling of pain and anger that cannot be ignored. Reconciliation requires justice, memory and reparation. Fourth, political leadership and internal narratives, as in both Russia and Ukraine, political leaders have constructed narratives that make compromise difficult.
Peace can be seen as weakness, as betrayal or as capitulation. It is necessary to create conditions so that leaders can negotiate without losing internal legitimacy. Despite the obstacles, there are factors that can favor the construction of a peace process, first of all, war fatigue as the prolongation of the conflict generates economic, social and political exhaustion. Russia faces sanctions, isolation and internal difficulties. Ukraine lives in a permanent state of emergency. Fatigue can open space for negotiated solutions. Second, international pressure, as Organizations such as the United Nations, the OSCE and neutral countries can play a mediation role.
Multilateral diplomacy, when well structured, can create bridges and facilitate compromises. Third, historical experiences as Europe has examples of reconciliation after intense conflicts such as Germany and France after World War II, the peace agreements in Northern Ireland and German reunification. These models show that peace is possible, even between historical enemies. Fourth, civil society and culture, together with education, can be drivers of rapprochement. Dialogue, exchange and symbolic reconstruction projects can prepare the ground for political peace. Peace between Russia and Ukraine can take different forms depending on the evolution of the conflict and negotiations.
So there is first to consider conditional peace with a ceasefire accompanied by negotiations on territories, security and international guarantees. This model requires mutual commitments and may include demilitarized zones, observation missions and non-aggression agreements. Second, peace with partial recognition with an agreement in which Ukraine recognizes the loss of certain territories in exchange for security guarantees and reconstruction support. This model is controversial and can generate internal divisions, but it has been applied in other contexts. Third, peace as international mediation, in which the creation of an international peace conference, with the participation of neutral countries, multilateral organizations and representatives of civil society. This model allows for a more comprehensive and less polarized approach.
Fourth, peace in stages with a gradual process, with phases of de-escalation, reconstruction, transitional justice and regional integration. This model requires time, patience and long-term commitment. For peace to be lasting, it is necessary to fulfill certain conditions, firstly, respect for sovereignty, as Ukraine must maintain the right to decide its future, its allies and its political model. Russia must recognize this right and commit to non-interference. Second, justice and reparation as crimes committed during the war must be investigated and punished. Victims must be recognized and compensated. Justice is essential for reconciliation. Third, peace must include security guarantees for both countries, with verification mechanisms, military dialogue and cooperation in areas such as arms control. Fourth, Ukraine needs financial, technical and institutional support to rebuild the country.
Russia, in turn, must find ways to reintegrate into the global economy, as long as it respects the principles of international law. Fifth, education for peace as it is not built only with treaties. It is necessary to invest in education, culture and memory, so that new generations understand the value of dialogue and coexistence. The EU, the United States, China and other powers have responsibilities in promoting peace. Europe, in particular, must take an active role, not just as an ally of Ukraine, but as a mediator and promoter of lasting solutions. Peace cannot be imposed but must be built on the basis of mutual respect, justice and cooperation. The international community must avoid the temptation to turn Ukraine into a protracted battleground between blocs.
The objective must be reconstruction, stability and dignity of the people. Thus, peace between Russia and Ukraine is possible, but it requires courage, vision and commitment. Não será um processo rápido nem simples. Wounds are deep, interests are complex, and emotions are intense. The alternative is acceptable to the perpetuation of war. History shows that even the most violent conflicts can find resolution. Europe, which was the scene of so many wars, can also be the space for reconciliation. Peace is not just an agreement but a collective construction, made up of gestures, words, policies and memories. Ukraine and Russia have the right to exist, to prosper and to live in security. Peace between them will be a sign of political maturity, respect for life and hope for the future. It is up to leaders, societies and the international community to transform this horizon into reality.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:33:53</pubDate></item><item><title>The sin of neglect</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/07/o-pecado-da-incuria/</link><description>On the 23rd and 24th of September, Typhoon Ragatsa hit Guangdong Province, in mainland China, and also Hong Kong and Macau, two special administrative regions of China. This super typhoon caused some damage in these three areas. Fortunately, everyone was prepared and the damage was minimal. The most serious incidents were injuries caused to some people.
In Hong Kong, a family decided to go to the jetty to watch the winds and waves. Unfortunately, the mother and son fell overboard. The father immediately jumped in to save them, leaving his 9-year-old daughter behind, alone and crying. Other people there tried to save them immediately, but were unable to do so. Luckily, a fishing boat was passing by and the sailor and his son went to help the victims. The mother and son were unconscious and the father, although conscious, was slightly injured.
Subsequently, Hong Kong Secretary for Security Chris Tang stated that although “wind and wave chasing” (追風逐浪) was not criminalized in Hong Kong, taking children into the storm during a typhoon could constitute “child neglect” (疏忽照顧兒童) and further said that the Hong Kong Government will investigate the matter further. This means that “chasing winds and waves” could be criminalized.
A few weeks ago, we mentioned in this column the lawsuit filed in Shenzhen against people who climbed the mountain during a storm. Currently, Hong Kong only has legislation that punishes entry to beaches closed by the Hong Kong Government, with a maximum fine of 2,000 HKD and 14 days in prison. However, only “entering prohibited areas” is criminalized and not “chasing winds and waves” during a storm. Ultimately, in Hong Kong, “wind and wave chasing” is not a crime.
To completely prevent tragedies caused by “wind and wave chasing” during typhoons, it is necessary to implement legislation that criminalizes it. As we mentioned in the previous column, the act of “chasing winds and waves” is difficult to define and regulate. If staying on the beach during a storm is considered a “wind and wave chasing” offense, many people will be charged. The law must be clear and detailed and its scope must be limited. Otherwise, a law will be created that will be broken by many people, which will certainly not be the legislator's intention. Furthermore, the current enforcement agency is staffed by officials from the Hong Kong Government's Leisure and Cultural Services Department (LCSD), not the police. If there is resistance to employees' recommendations, the situation will be even more chaotic.
Another consideration in criminal legislation is the question of proof. How can you prove that this group of people were “chasing winds” on the coast during a storm? LCSD employees, although they are on duty, also put their lives at risk during inclement weather and simultaneously have to enforce the law. The adverse law enforcement environment requires special attention. In other words, in a high-risk environment, how can we ensure that LCSD staff are safely enforcing the law?
Perhaps Hong Kong could consider using drones to patrol the coast during storms. If any “wind and wave chasing” activity was detected, an audible message could be immediately issued calling for removal from the site. As this crime was recorded on film, if the offenders refused to leave, the Hong Kong Government would naturally have evidence to prosecute them.
The success of this legislation would depend on the future attitude of Hong Kong society, which is why it is difficult to predict at the moment. However, the Hong Kong Government should certainly consider the possibility of forcing offenders to pay the costs of rescue operations. During a storm, rescue teams risk their lives to save those “chasing winds and waves,” and the equipment used is very expensive. It is not unreasonable to ask these “adventurers” to bear the costs.
Legislation to regulate “wind and wave chasing” involves prevention rather than prosecution. These laws are intended to deter these behaviors. Criminal proceedings are only initiated after repeated warnings. Even with the legislation in force, its application is fraught with difficulties. Lastly, we must pay tribute to those who remain on duty during typhoons or carry out rescue operations. Without them, safety would be much lower during typhoons. Regarding the case of the family that fell into the sea in Hong Kong, we must pay tribute to all the rescuers. Your courage and selflessness in saving three people during a storm was admirable.
Macau currently has a “civil defense legal system” (民防法律制度) and has implemented a series of measures to be applied during storms, such as preventive deployment, the evacuation of residents from riverside areas and ensuring supplies for daily needs. Many people were evacuated, demonstrating the robustness of Macau's civil defense system. Furthermore, there were no recorded incidents of “wind and wave chasing” on the coast, proof of the excellent work of the Macau Government in protecting the lives and property of residents. Macau residents take their personal safety very seriously. Therefore, although “chasing winds and waves” is not criminalized in Macau, people are careful. Currently, with unusual weather conditions and frequent and particularly powerful typhoons, Macau society must prioritize awareness and education to ensure that people understand what must be done to protect their lives and property during a storm. Only when everyone pays attention to safety can the impact of typhoons be minimized.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences of the Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:12:49</pubDate></item><item><title>New Foreigners Law increases racism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/06/nova-lei-dos-estrangeiros-aumenta-o-racismo/</link><description>Racism is increasingly an unfortunate reality in Portugal. It's enough to give you an example: in a classroom full of white boys and girls there was a black student, Kikas. The teacher asked the students what they liked most so far in life. Everyone responded and when Kikas spoke about what he liked most, he highlighted that it was his journey around the world. The teacher shouted at him, calling him “Liar!!!”. Kikas responded that he did not accept the insult and informed the teacher that he was the adopted son of a very rich white family and that he had gone touring the world with his parents. Not satisfied, the teacher responded: "Shut up! Guys like you always end up on the street!" and ordered him to leave the room, giving him a disciplinary offense. This is one of the many most deplorable examples of racist attitudes existing in our society.
Last week, the AD/Chega alliance approved a new Foreigners Law in the Assembly of the Republic. There have been more than many criticisms, mainly because this law could increase racism in Portugal. The organization that immediately came to the fore was the organization SOS Racismo, which opposed the new immigrant law, considering it a setback in the protection of the guarantees of fundamental rights and freedoms, as it changed the conditions of residence and obtaining citizenship aimed at immigrants, including CPLP citizens. According to Mariana Carneiro, director of SOS Racismo, the approval of the law with the support of the radical right represents a violation of the Constitution of the Portuguese Republic and European human rights conventions, in addition to the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. The leader of SOS Racismo also denounced that immigration has been treated as a crime, which unfortunately is nothing new, as Portugal has been following this path for a long time. Mariana Carneiro said that the government, sworn in in March 2024, had already adopted a stance increasingly aligned with the extreme right, giving in to racist and xenophobic principles present in Portuguese society. For the director of SOS Racismo, the new law is a blatant attack on people who choose to live and work in our country, while Gold visas receive privileged treatment, while at the same time increasingly restrictive immigration policies are implemented and applied to other immigrants.
The Constitutional Court's clamorous rejection of the initial version of the law on residence permits for foreigners and family reunification was a precious opportunity given by the President of the Republic to the Government to correct the situation in matters that are a test of humanist values, the defense of family principles and a privileged relationship with Portuguese-speaking countries. The solution found by AD and Chega is a legal loophole to circumvent the arguments of the Constitutional Court while maintaining all the political inconveniences of the initial version. The rule maintains the two-year period for requesting family reunification, counting from the granting of the residence permit and not from the request with proof of payment of taxes and Social Security contributions, despite the exceptions of reduction to one year when there are minor children.
The disappearance of the special regime for citizens of CPLP countries is confirmed. Denying the vaunted preference for Lusophony and violating our commitments on mobility within the Lusophone space. On the other hand, we find it strange that the privilege of access to family reunification is maintained for holders of Gold visas, European Blue Cards or for individuals considered highly qualified, prioritizing income over origin or integration into Portuguese society. Proof of having decent housing conditions and means of subsistence continues to be established by ordinance, in clear violation of the principle of reservation of law in matters of fundamental rights. However, all these limitations can be overcome by ministerial order, which opens the door to unlimited discretion and a lack of transparency. There remains a broad possibility of extending the period for considering the request for family reunification by up to 18 months, as well as the possibility of appealing to the courts to order AIMA to comply with decision deadlines, which continues to be severely limited.
To give us an idea of ​​the bad intentions of the law, it is clear that issues such as the aggravated punishment of those who violate the labor rights of foreign workers, the effective control of irregular immigration penalizing traffickers and employees or the employer's responsibility for decent housing for seasonal workers are matters that are absolutely ignored. The same happens with the rules on access to learning the Portuguese language.
In conclusion, we can see that the new Foreigners Law meets the Chega racists and that immigrants are the most significant target to be increasingly harmed, giving strength to neofascists to continue treating immigrants like trash and throwing them out of Portugal and, this, is pure racism.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 05:39:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | Casa de Macau in Lisbon displays “Heritople”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/cinema-casa-de-macau-em-lisboa-exibe-heritople/</link><description>The “CineMacau – Macau Documentary Cinema Cycle” session will take place next Wednesday, October 15th, starting at 4:30 pm, at Casa de Macau in Lisbon. The film “Heritople”, by António Salas Sanmarful, made last year, will be shown, followed by a conversation with the director himself who may be present via video conference.
The cinema sessions at Casa de Macau are organized and curated by Ruka Borges, a director linked to Macau, and Gonçalo Magalhães, member of the Casa's board of directors, who ensure the thematic framework of the films.
The documentary in question was recently produced by António Monteiro (IIM) and directed by António Salas Sanmarful with support from the Macau International Institute, having gained notoriety in promoting Macau as a city and/or territory with a unique hybrid culture, steeped in its heritage and legacy of the East-West relationship, which also highlights the contribution of the Macanese in this odyssey, and describes the organization of the event.
Thus, “Heritople” ends up reinforcing “the importance of Macau as a tangible and intangible heritage of the world given its unique and singular particularities on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the construction of the MSAR as a reality in the context of the People's Republic of China”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:19:33</pubDate></item><item><title>“Hush!” | Four dozen bands in two days of full celebration</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/hush-quatro-dezenas-de-bandas-em-dois-dias-de-plena-festa/</link><description>The poster for the next edition of “Hush! Concertos na Praia x Festival do Bem-Estar Desportivo Urbano” is now known, taking place between the 18th and 19th of this month on Hac-Sá beach, Coloane. This Sunday, the 12th, a pre-presentation will take place at Oficinas Navais nº 1, with Lobo and Shing02. There is no shortage of the usual cultural and well-being connection activities
Six stages, 40 local bands and singers, two days. These are the numbers for the next edition of “Hush! Concertos na Praia x Festival do Bem-Estar Desportivo Urbano”, scheduled for the 18th and 19th of October on Hac-Sá beach. However, this weekend, namely Sunday, the public in general and music lovers in particular will be able to enjoy a little of what will come later, with the performance of Lobo and the rapper Shing02 at Oficinas Navais nº1.
Lobo will present a “DJ set”, showing the sounds he has mixed and created in recent years. A radio broadcaster in the 90s, namely at TDM Rádio Macau and the former Rádio Vilaverde, Lobo founded, in 2000, the independent publisher “4daz-le”, “which remains the only one of its kind to date”, describes the organization of “Hush!”.
Also this weekend, but Saturday, the so-called “Festive Prelude” takes place in community neighborhoods, with various community shows, concerts and musical workshops.
What promises to be a “marathon” of concerts showcases “the cultural uniqueness of East Asia” on six stages, namely “Hot Wave”, “Music Chill”, “Hush! Kids – Parque Desportivo Infantil”, “Palco Wellfest”, “Jardim Desportivo” and “Desafio Fitness”. Thus, in addition to music, there will be parallel activities such as “SUP Yoga”, the “Music Glow Run”, described as a “musical parade for parents and children”; gastronomy tents and various workshops.
The aim of this diversity of offer is to “make the public aware of the uniqueness of the cultural fusion between East and West in Macau and “build the role” of the territory “as an important window for exchange and mutual learning between Chinese and Western civilizations”.
Lively sand
The main highlight of the festival, however, is the "Hush! Concerts on the Beach", with 40 bands and musicians from Macau taking the stage, in addition to ten international groups, namely SUMMERWARZ, from the interior of China; the Balming Tiger, from South Korea; bassist H.J. Freaks and Muque, a rock group from Japan. Also included is the performance of young ukuleleist Feng E and the female metal band MakeMake, both from Taiwan.
Other names that grace the Hac-Sá stage are Concrete/Lotus, Blademark, Roberto Madan, No Rison, WhyOceans, IRIS MONDO, Ying May Supermarket, Cancer Game and Chong River Fusion, among others.
Taking into account the celebration of the 20th anniversary of "Hush! Concertos na Praia", the organization decided to invite the organizers of other festivals in Asia, namely the well-known Clockenflap Music &amp; Arts Festival in Hong Kong, the Strawberry Music Festival and the Midi Festival in Mainland China, among others. The idea is to establish “a regional exchange platform and provide presentation contacts for local bands”.
On the sports side, the “Urban Sports Wellbeing Festival” brings to Coloane more than 30 professional fitness and yoga instructors from Asia, such as Hong Kong artist and dance instructor Fatboy@ERROR, “Physical: 100 Season 2” champion and South Korean CrossFit “superstar” Amotti, as well as dance trainer Thai, Gun Gun. In total, there will be more than 40 gymnastics and dance classes over two days, designed for beginners or practitioners.
The festival organization, which has the support of entities such as the Cultural Institute or the Institute for Municipal Affairs, prepared free bus transport to Coloane, running between Praia de Hac Sá and Iao Hon, Fai Chi Kei, Taipa. The public can also take the free MGM Cotai bus from any port in Macau, with the exception of Qingmao Port, to MGM Cotai Bus Terminal B1, and then use the free event bus service to travel to Hac Sá Beach. The “Hush!” concerts Entrance is free and tickets must be purchased for the “Urban Sports Welfare Festival”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:18:05</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Debate today around the “Art of Batê Saia”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/frc-debate-hoje-em-torno-da-arte-de-bate-saia/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) presents today, starting at 6:30 pm, the round table “The Art of Batê-Skirt”, part of the conference cycle entitled “Being Macanese in the 21st Century – Culture, Tradition, Identity, Challenges”. This is the second event of this lecture cycle.
“The Art of Batê-Skirt” will be a conversation led by José Luís de Sales Marques, president of the Council of Macanese Communities, with the participation of Maria Magalhães de Sousa and Marina Senna Fernandes, two local representatives of the arts of confection, cake decorating and traditional cuisine.
"Bâte Saia? Cuza São? What is that? Beating the skirt? What nonsense! Is it the work of a mainato? They are all predictable expressions of astonishment for those who, not knowing what it is about, come across this advertisement! Well, “bâte skirt” is a traditional Macanese decorative art, the dissemination of which will be the subject of this talk", describes the proposal for the conversation session on Macanese identity today.
The idea is that the public can learn more about the art of “bate skirt”, an ancient local tradition of cutting out tissue paper or lace paper, initially to decorate baskets and cake trays, but which evolved into decorating dolls that decorated festive cakes on special occasions such as baptisms, communions, confirmations, weddings, birthdays, and other important events.
The event aims to address “the way of life of the Macanese, the community or communities, in Macau and in the diaspora, and their daily challenges to maintain the being and feeling of the Macanese reality”. The purpose of the conference, and the next ones in this cycle, is to promote “constructive discussion looking at the present and the future, without forgetting the tradition and the different identity landmarks, especially Gastronomy and Theater in Patuá, both Intangible Heritage of the Macao SAR and the People's Republic of China”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:25:06</pubDate></item><item><title>CURB | Biennial on the use of public spaces in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/curb-bienal-sobre-uso-de-espacos-publicos-em-dezembro/</link><description>CURB – Center for Architecture and Urbanism is preparing to hold, in December, a different event around the so-called “placemaking”, that is, the debate around the various options for planning and managing public spaces. To take place, the “IN SITU Placemaking Biennale” is accepting proposals from architects and designers until the end of the month
It is a “pioneer project” that is not “just a festival”, but rather “a conversation that involves the entire city”. This is how the organization describes the “IN SITU Placemaking Biennale”, scheduled for the 11th to 14th of December, in Macau, and which addresses “placemaking”, a theory around the ideas of improving the management of public space with a multifaceted approach, in which the idea is for everyone to sit down and discuss what is best for a given place or what could be done in the face of a less good reality.
In this way, it is intended that for four days “the iconic streets and squares of Macau will be transformed into a living canvas for design, dialogue and collective imagination”, through the creation of six spatial installations “built ‘in situ’ by international and local talents”, and these installations “will connect and activate iconic public spaces”, transforming them into “spaces to gather, reflect and interact”, he describes the CURB.
The six locations chosen for these interventions are Praça Ponte e Horta, in Porto Interior; Rua de São Lourenço, the intersection between Travessa do Aterro Novo and Rua dos Mercadores, Largo de Aquino, Pátio da Claridade and Largo do Lilau.
Within the objectives, it is also intended to take the public to “experiment”, building, in this sense, an “itinerary throughout the city with workshops, shows, exhibitions and gastronomy, all curated by the community”. With “IN SITU” the aim is also to “rediscover the city”, with “guided tours that will connect dots between the art, heritage and hidden stories of Macau”.
Therefore, the process of collecting proposals from designers and architects is ongoing until the end of the month, looking for “visionary teams to design and build temporary spatial installations that stimulate dialogue and transform the way we experience our city”.
Itineraries with history
With “IN SITU”, CURB wants the “city to become a stage, screen and laboratory”. The six temporary space installations, three of them designed by international teams and three by local teams, will serve to “activate public spaces as places of meeting and reflection”.
In addition to the six installations there will be “workshops, shows, exhibitions, food stalls and cultural initiatives co-created with local associations, ensuring that the festival grows from the community and belongs to the community”. The six installations will also form “an urban itinerary, guiding visitors through Macau’s neighborhoods, revealing both the contemporary design and the hidden layers of heritage”, with tours in Chinese and English.
According to the organization, “more than an exhibition of architecture and design, the Biennale is a participatory experience of ‘placemaking’”.
“Based on collaboration and creativity, the creation of spaces shifts the focus from infrastructure to people's lived experiences, emphasizing how public spaces can strengthen social ties, cultural identity and resilience in a rapidly changing city”, it is explained.
CURB is a non-profit institution created in Macau to “promote research, education, production and dissemination of knowledge in architecture, urbanism and urban culture”. The Center claims to function as “a platform for exchange between academia, civil society, professional practice and government institutions, serving the interests of the community at large through research studies, workshops, conferences, exhibitions, competitions and other initiatives”.
Film on Bridge 9
Another CURB activity takes place this weekend, as part of the “ON THE MOVE” bicycle tour event. Thus, this Saturday, at 6:30 pm, the “Rooftop Parallel Screening” session will take place at Ponte 9 – Creative Platform Rooftop, where “the public will be able to explore the streets of Macau through the screen, this time exploring Ilha Verde and the northern neighborhoods of Toi San and Fai Chi Kei”. This film is the result of the sound and images captured on creative bicycle tours carried out on September 27th. This material was used “by audiovisual artists to create a work of video art and a documentary”, describes CURB in a note.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:23:45</pubDate></item><item><title>UnionPay | First branch opened in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/unionpay-aberta-primeira-filial-em-macau/</link><description>Macau already has a branch of UnionPay International, a subsidiary of China UnionPay, reported the Macau News Agency portal. This is the first bank card organization to make this commitment, and the objective of opening the branch is to expand international business.
Macau became the “second region abroad” to accept transactions with UnionPay cards since the company launched this service in 2004 in the territory. Regarding digital payments, UnionPay's investment took place in 2018 in the territories of Macau and Hong Kong, with the “QuickPass” application and an EMV-compatible QR code being launched in Macau, that is, “Europay, Mastercard and Visa”, which are the three companies behind the global standard for secure card payments. In 2019, Apple Pay was launched in Macau with technological support from UnionPay.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:24:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Golden Week below expectations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/comercio-semana-dourada-aquem-das-expectativas/</link><description>Although the number of tourists increased by 15.3 percent compared to last year, when it came to opening their wallets, people were more careful. The climate of disappointment was described by the president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau Center and South Districts
 
A Golden Week far from satisfactory. This was how Lei Cheok Kuan, president of the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau Central and South Districts, defined the most recent holidays. The balance of the days that lasted between October 1st and Wednesday was made by the person responsible in statements to the newspaper Exmoo.
According to Lei Cheok Kuan, the impact on local businesses was “disappointing”, because although the territory received around 1.14 million tourists, the number did not translate into an increase in revenue for local businesses. The association leader acknowledged that reality fell short of expectations, because the gains on the Chinese stock markets since the beginning of the year suggested greater spending power for visitors.
“It wasn’t just in my goldsmith shop [that business was worse], the traders I know in restaurants and retail sales, including those in the Rua dos Ervanários area, also saw business performing worse than in the past”, lamented the president of the association.
Lei Cheok Kuan pointed out that the flow of tourists to the Ruins of São Paulo was high, but that more tourists did not generate more consumption. The person responsible admitted that expenses were below what had happened in May, during national holidays around Labor Day.
As reasons for weaker consumption, the president of the association put forward as hypotheses the impact of the slowdown in the economy in the interior, which makes consumers less spendy. Furthermore, the president pointed out that the consumption model of generation Z has changed, becoming more demanding, which may mean that they cannot find what they are looking for in Macau.
Pedestrian zone disappointed
Regarding the new temporary pedestrian zone on Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo, Lei Cheok Kuan confessed that he had many hopes. The expectation was for a large concentration of tourists in the place and greater consumption.
However, the reality was different than expected. Lei Cheok Kuan pointed out that few traders felt the results of the initiative. Therefore, the person in charge concluded that despite the Government trying to find new methods to support small and medium-sized companies, consumers are increasingly changing their consumption habits, which makes the task more difficult.
However, Lei Cheok Kuan defended the need for traders to adapt and better understand the way young people like to spend money.
During the eight days of Golden Week, the territory received 1.14 million tourists, which represented an increase of 15.3 percent compared to last year. On average, 143.1 thousand people visited the Macao SAR per day, an increase of approximately 1 percent compared to last year.
Accounts done
Macau received more than 1.1 million visitors in the first week of October, during the holidays commemorating China's National Day, the Tourism Services Bureau (DST) announced yesterday. The total number of visitors during Golden Week, from October 1 to 8, was 1,144,351, 16.5 percent more than last year's 982,542, which had one less day (October 1 to 7), according to data published on the DST website.
This year, it was on October 4th that Macau recorded the highest number of visitors, with 191,132 tourists entering the territory. The lowest number of visitors during the “Golden Week” was seen on the eighth day, October 8, with 88,943 entries, according to that direction. This year, the 76th anniversary of the founding of the People's Republic of China was celebrated.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:23:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Education | UM considered the 145th best in the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/educacao-um-considerada-a-145-a-melhor-do-mundo/</link><description>In just over 10 years, Macau's largest public educational institution managed to rise to the top of the best universities worldwide. In a ranking led by the most famous institutions, MUST and Cidade Universidade de Macau also appear
 
The University of Macau (UM) was yesterday considered the 145th best in the world, according to the Times Higher Education 2026 magazine ranking. In the space of 11 years, the public educational institution rose from 500th place to 145th position in the ranking.
On a scale of 0 to 100 points, UM was evaluated by Times Higher Education with a total of 62 points, compared to 59.7 points in the previous year. The area in which the institution achieved the best score was in the “research quality” index with 92.9 points, followed by “international perspectives”, in which it obtained 92.5 points. According to ranking information, more than 51 percent of the institution's students are classified as international students. Despite this, international perspectives were the only area in which the university performed worse than the previous year.
Another aspect in which the institution stood out was in the industry index, which measures financing by companies to the institution, with 87 points.
The areas in which the University of Macau presented a lower quality performance were in teaching (40.2 points) and also in the research environment (40.9 points).
MUST and City
In terms of Macau universities present in the 2026 ranking, the second best ranked is the Macau University of Science and Technology (MUST, in English), which appears between places 251 and 300 in the ranking. From 201st position onwards, the ranking stops specifying the specific position of the institutions and places them in groups of 50 universities, 100 universities or 200 universities.
MUST obtained an overall score between 54.3 and 56.3 points, maintaining the same position since the 2024 ranking. Still, it is below the level reached in 2023 when it managed to enter the group of institutions in positions 201 to 250. The private institution obtained 93.2 points in international perspectives, 84.4 points at industry level, 81.1 points in research quality, 38.8 points in research environment and 34.2 points at teaching level.
Cidade Universidade de Macau made its debut in the ranking this year, joining the group of institutions occupying between 601st and 800th places. The institution recorded a score between 39 and 43.5 points. The aspect in which it stood out best was international perspectives with 93.5 points, followed by research quality with 59.7 points. Teaching achieved 30.8 points, while industry achieved 18.9 points and 17.1 points in the research environment.
This year the ranking was once again led by the University of Oxford, with an overall score of 98.2 points. The best university in the Interior is Tsinghua University in 12th place in the ranking, with 93 points. The University of Hong Kong appears in 33rd position, with 80.5 points.
The best Portuguese institutions are the University of Coimbra, University of Lisbon and University of Porto, all included in the group classified between positions 401 and 500.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:21:09</pubDate></item><item><title>AMCM | Monthly drop in deposits and loans</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/amcm-queda-mensal-de-depositos-e-emprestimos/</link><description>Data from the Macau Monetary and Exchange Authority (AMCM) regarding deposits, loans and money supply reveal that, between July and August, there was a drop in deposits and loans made by residents. Domestic loans granted to the private sector fell by 1.1 percent compared to July, reaching 501.9 billion patacas.
In turn, the drop in loans granted abroad was even greater, around 9.1 percent, worth 511.8 billion patacas. Thus, AMCM statistics show that the total volume of loans in banks fell by 5.3 percent between July and August, a drop of 1,013.7 billion patacas.
Regarding deposits, the monthly drop was 0.4 percent, amounting to 813.8 billion patacas, while the drop in deposits by non-residents was much greater, in the order of 7.1 percent, amounting to 338.1 billion patacas.
AMCM data also shows that “public sector deposits in banking activity grew to 220.9 billion patacas, representing a growth of 5.2 percent”. Thus, in general terms, “total deposits in banking activity registered a decrease of 1.3 percent, reaching 1,372.8 billion patacas”. In monthly terms, monetary circulation grew by 0.3 percent, but current deposits fell by six percent.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:19:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin | Caution is requested to avoid rental fraud</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/hengqin-pedida-cautela-para-evitar-burlas-no-arrendamento/</link><description>Tips for operating in the rental market on Mountain Island come after the release of a mega case of fraud in rental contracts that generated losses of 3.64 million renminbi
 
With more and more residents choosing to move to Ilha da Montanha, the director of Macau and Hengqin Centaline Real Estate Agency, Roy Ho, advises special care when it comes to renting. Speaking to the newspaper Exmoo, the person responsible for the real estate agency indicated the practices to be adopted to avoid problems, after a mega fraud that affected hundreds of students and losses of 3.64 million renminbis.
According to Roy Ho, when residents intend to rent a home in Hengqin they must carefully check all the certificates and legal documents relating to the apartment before completing the deal. This is a fundamental point to avoid future problems: "It doesn't matter who rents the house, company or individual, it also doesn't matter if the conditions of the apartment are very good. If there are no valid certificates, people should always refuse to rent", he stressed.
Roy highlighted that it is always necessary to ask the owner to show the property's ownership certificate and their identity document. Interested parties are advised to insist that they be shown originals rather than copies. And if the originals are refused, even if it is with the justification of the need to protect personal data, the agent states that the rental must be abandoned.
Bank transfers
Furthermore, to reduce the risk of fraud, Roy advises that tenants make it a priority to choose a more well-known real estate company, for reasons of credibility, rather than resorting to less transparent online businesses.
Roy Ho also appealed to residents not to be attracted by prices that are too good to be true. The presentation of a “cheap price with excellent quality” is seen as one of the scammers’ main lures.
The warnings were left by the director of the Centaline Real Estate Agency of Macau and Hengqin following a mega fraud, revealed in August by the Hengqin Prosecutor's Office. A man impersonated several apartment owners and managed to scam more than 100 students out of 3.64 million renminbi. Among the victims were students from Macau.
The fraudster will have forged the signatures of the apartment owners, with whom he signed rental contracts, and then manipulate the purchase and sale contracts for these properties and appear as the owner. The victims rented based on manipulated contracts because they believed they were dealing with the real owner. In this process, the fraudster will have had the help of some real estate agencies.
Once the lease contract was signed, the fraudster offered special promotions, which led several victims to pay the annual rent in advance. The case was discovered because the false owner did not pay the rent on time to one of the real owners, who evicted the students who lived in the house. The Prosecutor's Office asked for a 10-year prison sentence for the man and a fine of 100,000 renminbi.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:17:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Cancer | Survival rate increases 3 percent in ten years</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/cancro-taxa-de-sobrevivencia-aumenta-3-por-cento-em-dez-anos/</link><description>The Health Services yesterday presented data on cancer cases registered in the last decade. The disease remains very common, but kills fewer people, with the survival rate increasing from 59 percent in 2013 to 62 percent in 2023. Lung cancer, with 15.9 percent of cases, is at the top of the list
 
Yesterday, the Macau Health Services (SS) presented statistical data on the evolution of cancer cases in Macau over ten years (2013-2023). According to TDM Rádio Macau, Alvis Lo, director of the SS, explained that cancer is one of the most common diseases in Macau, but in ten years there has been a positive evolution in terms of the survival rate, which went from 59 percent to 62 percent.
In 2023, a total of 2,445 cases of cancer were recorded in Macau, with 1,201 cases affecting men and 1,244 women. In terms of incidence, we are talking about the occurrence of 238 cases of disease per 100 thousand inhabitants. In the report on statistical data on cancer in 2023, released in August this year by the SS, it is stated that the number of deaths was 874, an annual drop (compared to 2022) of ten percent.
Lung cancer dominates the list, with 15.9 percent of cases, according to doctor Leong Iek Hou, head of the Center for Disease Prevention and Control. This is followed by breast cancer, colorectal, prostate and thyroid cancer. Leong Iek Hou also highlighted some of the potential causes for the greater occurrence of oncological diseases, namely the aging and lifestyle habits of the population. The doctor said that, in terms of the mortality rate caused by cancer, Macau has had positive developments in the last decade.
Looking at the SS's annual report on cancer cases for 2013, that year there were 713 deaths and 1,600 new cases of the disease. At that time, there was already an upward trend in the disease, with 1,093 cases registered in 2003 and an increase of four percent compared to 2013, when 1,600 new cancer cases were registered.
Essential screening
There are success stories in some types of cancer, such as cervical cancer, which in ten years saw a 28 percent reduction in the incidence rate, wrote the newspaper Ou Mun. Chou Mei Fang, director of the Areia Preta Health Center, spoke about this disease, who also described a drop in the mortality rate by four percent.
Screening rates for this type of cancer also appear encouraging, given that in 2023, between 65 and 66 percent of women in Macau have undergone these preventive exams, said Choi Mei Fang, although problems such as the late age at the first exam and the fact that more than half of women do not undergo screening regularly persist.
In a 2024 statement, the SS said that, in five years, the average incidence rate of cervical cancer decreased by almost 30 percent compared to the period before 2011, while the mortality rate decreased by eight percent.
In the case of colorectal cancer, it was said at the press conference that the incidence rate of this type of invasive cancer, in the case of men, fell by six percent in ten years, with the mortality rate decreasing by around 18 percent. Leong Iek Hou said that since the colorectal cancer screening program was created in 2016, more than 35 thousand people had participated by August this year, with more participants registering every year.
Of this group of people, 330 were diagnosed with malignant polyps and 175 with malignant tumors, the majority of whom were in the early stages of the disease, wrote the newspaper Ou Mun.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:11:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Consumption | MUST study indicates decreased trust</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/consumo-estudo-da-must-indica-diminuicao-da-confianca/</link><description>The prices of goods, the employment situation and the standard of living are shaking consumer confidence. MUST also highlights that the interior economy has achieved new “achievements” that leave consumers more excited, while the international situation shows weaker growth
 
The population is increasingly less confident when it comes to consuming, according to the Macau Consumer Confidence Index in the third quarter of 2025, released yesterday by the Macau University of Science and Technology (MUST). In the second quarter of the year, the index pointed to reduced confidence, but the situation has worsened and consumer sentiment is now pessimistic.
On a scale of 0 to 200 points, the global index presents a result of 99.33 points, compared to 101.71 points in the previous quarter. According to MUST, a score below 100 points indicates that there is a lack of confidence in terms of consumption, while a score above 100 points reflects a climate of confidence. “This represents a decrease of 2.38 points, or 2.34 percent, compared to the previous quarter (101.71 points)”, can be read in the institution's statement. “The downward trend accelerated this quarter, causing the index to leave the optimistic range, signaling that consumer confidence has entered a cautious phase”, it was added.
The changes were justified with the external and internal environments. In relation to what is happening in the world, beyond Mainland China, the statement indicates that there is an “increasingly complex and challenging” environment, and points out that the “growth pace of the global economy has weakened” at the same time that “trade barriers continued to increase”.
For researchers, the scenario in China is very different, because “new achievements in high-quality development have been achieved” with the economy maintaining “steady progress with continuous improvements”. Even so, “insufficient demand and persistently low price levels” are recognized.
Inflation and employment are a concern
The overall confidence result was affected by several factors that led the population to be more pessimistic. The biggest drop in confidence in consumption was caused by the average level of prices in the territory. This aspect was evaluated with 97.74 points in the second quarter, but in the third it did not go further and 91.87 points, a difference of 5.87 points.
The level of living standards is another aspect that showed a decline in confidence, although it is still within a positive margin. It was evaluated with 102.73 points, when previously it had been classified with 107.08 points, a reduction of 4.06 points. The greatest distrust is also based on the employment situation, with a pessimistic result of 92.69 points, compared to 96.33 points in the previous quarter, a decrease of 3.78 points.
Investments in shares is another indicator that showed a significant reduction, from 3.26 points to 112.42 points from 116.21 points, but which continues to be positive.
With property prices falling, the index reflects greater consumer confidence. In relation to housing purchases, the index presented 101.99 points, an increase of 2.72 points compared to the score of 99.29 in the previous quarter. Housing consumption confidence therefore remains at an optimistic level.
At the same time, the outlook for the local economy is now better, although it remains in negative territory. This aspect had a score of 94.14 points, an increase of 0.57 points compared to the value of 93.41 in the previous quarter. Despite the growth, consumers are pessimistic about the state of the local economy.
The Macau Consumer Confidence Index for the third quarter of 2025 was based on 829 surveys of residents over 18 years old, carried out between 1 and 15 September.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:09:52</pubDate></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
At a lunch with several guests, I heard a friend, who declared herself a spiritualist, explaining the particularities of her belief, in a calm and balanced way, I would even say, without a hint of “irrationalism”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«If transparency is demanded from politicians, we kill them; if anyone demands fidelity to what the other was or what he says, kill him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, representation is killed. These must therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to bend the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). I believe we will be needed to decipher this frantically complex world that has fallen to us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Men should refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish because of it, tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the land will be destroyed. pride of countries.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were limited, or if it simply lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each one. to be, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the position of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, deferred, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse like a shadow
[deformed
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piela than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>World leaders applaud peace agreement between Israel and Hamas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/lideres-mundiais-aplaudem-acordo-de-paz-entre-israel-e-hamas/</link><description>Several world leaders welcomed the peace agreement between Israel and Hamas announced by US President Donald Trump, praising the imminent end of the war in Gaza and the release of hostages after two years of conflict.
Trump announced on Wednesday that Israel and the Islamist movement have accepted the “first phase” of his peace plan, which envisages the partial withdrawal of Israeli troops from the Gaza Strip and the release of 20 hostages still alive in exchange for Palestinian prisoners.
“All hostages will be released very soon and Israel will withdraw its troops to an agreed line as first steps towards a strong, lasting and eternal peace,” Trump wrote on the Truth Social network.
The news was received with enthusiasm by leaders from several countries. Canadian Prime Minister Mark Carney congratulated Trump on his “essential leadership” and expressed relief at the imminent release of the hostages. "Peace finally seems possible. We urge all parties to quickly implement the terms of the agreement," he said. Japan also welcomed the understanding, which government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi classified as “an important step to calm the situation”, thanking the United States, Egypt and Qatar for their mediation efforts.
From Canberra, Prime Minister Anthony Albanese and Foreign Minister Penny Wong highlighted that it was “a very necessary step towards peace” and defended a two-state solution, stressing that the plan excludes Hamas from any role in the future administration of Gaza.
United Nations Secretary-General António Guterres described the agreement as “a desperately needed breakthrough” and called for its full implementation, stressing that “it is an opportunity to recognize the right to self-determination of the Palestinian people and move towards a two-state solution”.
Hamas confirmed the understanding, guaranteeing that it “ensures the end of the war, the withdrawal of the Israeli army and the entry of humanitarian aid”, and called on Israel to fulfill its commitments “without delays or changes”. Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu called the deal a “historic achievement” and thanked Trump for his “determined leadership and global efforts,” saying: “With God’s help, we will bring everyone home.”
Euphoria and relief
According to official sources, the release of the hostages is expected to begin on Monday, after the agreement is approved by the Israeli Government, and the military withdrawal will cover around 70 percent of the Gaza territory.
“This is more than Gaza, it is the beginning of peace in the Middle East,” said Trump in an interview with Fox News, assuring that the United States and neighboring countries will support the reconstruction of the enclave. He added: "Other countries in the region will help because they have immense wealth. We will be involved to ensure Gaza is successful and peaceful."
In Tel Aviv, families of the hostages gathered in euphoria in Hostage Square, amid tears and chants of “Nobel for Trump”. “I want to smell my son,” said Einav Zangauker, mother of one of the hostages, emotionally. In Gaza, where the ceasefire was met with a mixture of relief and distrust, displaced people and residents expressed hope of being able to return to their homes.
“We want to return, even if there are no more houses,” said Alaa Abd Rabbo, displaced from the north of the Strip. The agreement brokered by the United States, Qatar, Egypt and Türkiye marks the most significant attempt to end the war since the conflict began in October 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:15:10</pubDate></item><item><title>NBA | China and Alibaba Cloud sign partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/nba-china-e-alibaba-cloud-assinam-parceria/</link><description>NBA China, the most popular professional sports league on Chinese social media, with 425 million followers, has just signed a partnership with Alibaba Cloud, another Chinese group founded by Jack Ma, to improve the interactivity of basketball fans with the games broadcast, namely the “NBA All-Star”, the NBA playoffs and the finals, using artificial intelligence and the system of cloud computing.
The announcement was made by Joe Tsai, co-founder and executive vice president of the Alibaba group and owner of the Brooklyn Nets team, from New York; and by Mark Tatum, deputy commissioner and director of operations at the NBA [National Basketball Association], the main basketball sports league in the USA and one of the most important worldwide.
In concrete terms, NBA China “will utilize Alibaba Cloud’s AI and cloud computing services to support a wide range of digital fan engagement initiatives”, having developed “a proprietary AI model for NBA China based on Alibaba’s ‘Qwen’ series of models”.
Thus, “the proprietary AI model, adjusted to the league's range of digital assets, will provide NBA China app users with engaging content, including real-time game highlights, historical basketball data, player information and interactive discussions on current basketball topics.”
Also noteworthy is the fact that pre-season games between the Nets and Phoenix Suns teams at NBA China 2025 will take place today and Sunday. The presentation is carried out by “Taobao 88VIP”, with the games taking place today at 8pm at the Venetian Arena, and then on Sunday at 7pm, in the same location.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:13:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Softbank buys ABB business for 4,610 ME</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/japao-softbank-compra-negocio-da-abb-por-4-610-me/</link><description>The technological revolution enters another chapter with the transfer of the Swiss multinational into Japanese hands
 
Japanese group Softbank announced yesterday that it had reached an agreement with Swiss technology multinational ABB to acquire its robotics business for US$5.375 million, it said in a statement.
The acquisition has the approval of the Board of Directors of the Japanese conglomerate and is pending regulatory approvals in the European Union, China and the United States, with completion expected in the second half of 2026. Softbank expects the acquisition of ABB to “significantly strengthen” its robotics business linked to artificial intelligence (AI), a field in which it has invested.
“Following the acquisition, the existing robotics platform, expertise and local presence will be complemented with the technological foundations of Softbank Group's existing robotics-related investments (…) to accelerate innovation in AI robotics and drive progress and growth towards the realization of artificial super intelligence (AIS),” Softbank said.
These investments refer to SoftBank Robotics, Berkshire Grey, AutoStore Holdings2, Agile Robots and Skild AI. The deal means that ABB has abandoned its original plan to go public separately from its industrial automation business, which competes with other companies such as Japan's Fanuc, Yaskawa and Germany's Kuka in manufacturing industrial robots.
Revolution in sight
According to the details revealed by Softbank, ABB will go ahead with the spin-off of its robotics business into a newly created holding company so that the Japanese group, through a subsidiary, can acquire all the shares in the new company.
“Softbank’s next frontier is physical AI, together with ABB Robotics we will bring together world-class technology and talent under our common vision of fusing artificial superintelligence and robotics, driving a revolutionary evolution,” said Softbank Executive Chairman Masayoshi Son in a statement.
ABB's executive president, Morten Wierod, said, in turn, that the operation “will allow the business to strengthen and expand its position as a technological leader in the sector”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:09:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Nissan | In a climate of restructuring, the new Leaf electric car is launched</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/nissan-em-clima-de-restruturacao-lancado-novo-electrico-leaf/</link><description>Nissan, in the process of restructuring and dealing with financial difficulties, will launch a new version of the Leaf electric vehicle for the Japanese national market next week in Japan. It will be the company's first launch since the preparation of its restructuring plan.
Nissan says the car will have a larger battery than the one installed in previous Leafs and a range of 702 kilometers on a single charge. It also highlights that engine noise and vibration have been reduced to make its performance quieter.
Sugimoto Akira, marketing and sales executive at Nissan in Japan, says he welcomes what he calls the reinvigoration of the electric vehicle market in the country and predicts that, in this way, the manufacturer will return to prominence. The person in charge says the company wants people to say: “Nissan is back with this car.”
Announced in May, the manufacturer's global restructuring plan envisages the closure of seven factories and the elimination of 20,000 jobs. It was later announced that, in the year ended in March, Nissan recorded a net loss of more than 670 billion yen — almost 4.4 billion dollars.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:07:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Rare earths | New rules on technology exports</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/terras-raras-novas-regras-sobre-exportacao-de-tecnologias/</link><description>China announced yesterday the immediate imposition of controls on exports of technologies linked to rare earths, strengthening regulation in a sector central to trade tensions with the United States.
The Asian country is the world's largest producer of these essential minerals for the digital, automotive, energy and defense industries. Rare earths have been a point of friction in recent Sino-US trade negotiations, with Washington accusing Beijing of deliberately delaying the approval of export licenses.
According to a statement from the Chinese Ministry of Commerce, the new controls require prior authorization to export technologies used in the extraction and smelting of rare earths, including processes for assembly, tuning, maintenance, repair and modernization of production lines.
In a separate note, the ministry indicated that additional restrictions will also be imposed on foreign entities that export products made with rare earths or related technologies from China. “Some foreign organizations and individuals have transferred or supplied controlled products originating from Chinese rare earths, directly or indirectly, for use in sensitive sectors such as the military”, explained a spokesperson.
This practice, he added, “seriously harms or poses a potential threat to China's national security” and has had “a negative impact on international peace and stability.” Chinese dominance in the extraction and refining of these minerals gives Beijing a strategic advantage in a context of growing commercial rivalry with the USA.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:06:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Golden Week | Record reached of more than 2,430 million trips</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/semana-dourada-atingido-recorde-de-mais-de-2-430-milhoes-de-viagens/</link><description>China recorded more than 2.43 billion domestic trips during the eight days of the recent “Golden Week” holidays, a new record for this festive period, according to official data released yesterday.
Between October 1st and 8th, an average of 304 million daily trips were recorded, an increase of 6.3 percent compared to the same period of the previous year, according to the Ministry of Transport, cited by the official news agency Xinhua. During the holidays, the country recorded around 888 million tourist trips, 123 million more than during the seven days off during the “Golden Week” of 2024, according to the Ministry of Culture and Tourism.
Domestic tourist spending reached 809 billion yuan, representing year-on-year growth of 15.4 percent. The National Immigration Administration reported that 16.34 million cross-border trips were made during the holiday, 11.5 percent more than last year.
International trips by foreigners increased by 21.6 percent, to 1.43 million, and of the 751 thousand foreigners who entered China, 535 thousand benefited from the visa exemption policy – ​​increases of 19.8 percent and 46.8 percent, respectively, year-on-year.
The holidays began on October 1st, the date that marks the anniversary of the founding of the People's Republic of China, and lasted until Wednesday, one day longer than usual, due to the coincidence with the Mid-Autumn Festival, celebrated this year on October 6th. “Golden Week” is one of the main holiday periods in China and is an important driver for tourism and domestic consumption.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:05:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | 14 foreign organizations declared untrustworthy entities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/comercio-14-organizacoes-estrangeiras-declaradas-entidades-nao-confiaveis/</link><description>Most of the new companies included in the untrustworthy list are based in the United States and are linked to military activities
 
China yesterday included fourteen foreign organizations, most of them based in the United States and linked to the defense sector, on its “list of untrustworthy entities”, in a new episode of growing commercial and technological frictions with Washington. In a statement, the Ministry of Commerce justified the decision with the need to “safeguard the sovereignty, security and national development interests” of the country.
Among the companies targeted are Dedrone by Axon, AeroVironment, BAE Systems, TechInsights and their subsidiaries, as well as the Halifax International Security Forum (Canada), in which former Taiwanese leader Tsai Ing-wen (2016-2024) participated at the end of last year.
The list also includes the North American subsidiary of the Israeli Elbit, in addition to the companies DZYNE Technologies, Epirus, Exelis and VSE Corporation, among others. According to the ministry, sanctioned entities are prohibited from carrying out import and export activities related to China, as well as making new investments in the country.
The statement adds that organizations and people within China will not be able to maintain transactions, cooperation or any type of commercial relationship with these companies, especially with regard to “data transmission or provision of sensitive information”.
Malice and security
In a separate note, the ministry said that several of the companies now included “maintained military technological cooperation with Taiwan, released malicious statements about China and helped foreign governments crack down on Chinese companies.”
“Such actions have seriously harmed China’s national sovereignty, security and development interests,” added the Ministry of Commerce, stressing that Beijing only added “a very small number of foreign entities” that “put at risk” national security.
"Foreign companies that act with integrity and comply with the law have no cause for concern. The Chinese Government, as always, welcomes companies from around the world to invest and develop activities in the country, committing to offering a stable, fair and predictable business environment", concludes the statement.
The decision comes just hours after Beijing announced a new package of restrictions on the export of rare earths, in a context of growing technological and commercial dispute between China and the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:03:12</pubDate></item><item><title>East Timor | EU supports civil society with more than two million euros</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/timor-leste-ue-apoia-sociedade-civil-com-mais-de-dois-milhoes-de-euros/</link><description>The European Union (EU), in partnership with several Timorese non-governmental organizations, yesterday launched three projects to strengthen the capacity of civil society to support vulnerable communities and monitor the implementation of public policies.
"The EU and Timor-Leste share a commitment to ensuring a free civic space, because monitoring and advocacy by civil society organizations is essential for a free society like ours. We are pleased to partner with this coalition to improve development performance and accountability," said European Union Ambassador to Timor-Leste, Thorsten Bargfrede.
European Union partner civil society organizations include CARE, Oxfam, PLAN International, A-HAK, Caucus, Timor-Leste Women's Communications Forum (FOKUPERS), Timor-Leste Non-Governmental Organizations Forum (FONGTIL), Kdadalak Sulimutu Institute (KSI) and Mata Dalan Institute (MDI).
European Union support, worth 2.2 million euros, will be distributed across three projects. :“Strengthening Local Civil Society Organizations for Responsive and Accountable Governance in Human Rights and Gender Equality”, “Strengthening Civil Society to Promote Good Governance” and “Strengthening Civil Society for Diversity: Strengthening Civil Society Leadership to Improve Governance and Sustainable Development”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:31:19</pubDate></item><item><title>At least ten dead in Vietnam due to floods caused by Typhoon Matmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/pelo-menos-dez-mortos-no-vietname-devido-a-cheias-provocadas-pelo-tufao-matmo/</link><description>At least ten people have died and several are still missing in northern Vietnam as a result of the floods caused by Typhoon Matmo, which hit southern China on Monday before weakening, the Vietnamese Government declared yesterday. Vietnamese Prime Minister Pham Minh Chinh visited the city of Thai Nguyen yesterday, capital of the province with the same name and the region with the highest number of deaths, with four fatalities and around 200,000 homes affected.
Knee-deep in water, the Vietnamese politician inspected the area and helped distribute humanitarian aid, according to information published on the government portal. Authorities have mobilized more than 7,600 soldiers and volunteers for emergency relief efforts after the country was hit by seven severe storms since late August.
According to the provisional report, three people also died in Bac Ninh province — 30 kilometers northwest of Hanoi —, another two in Thanh Hoa province and one in Cao Bang province, on the border with China. Emergency teams are looking for at least two people in Thai Nguyen and another in Thanh Hoa.
The floods also caused significant losses to agriculture and considerable damage to infrastructure, while authorities warn the population of the possibility of landslides and river overflows in regions affected by the rains.
Other disasters
In Thailand, the rains caused by Matmo caused at least 22 deaths, and floods were recorded in around twenty provinces in the center, north and northeast of the country on Tuesday, affecting almost 370 thousand people, authorities reported. Typhoons are recurring phenomena in Southeast Asia, when the warm waters of the Pacific Ocean favor the formation of cyclones.
At the end of September, Typhoon Bualoi left at least 58 people dead or missing in Vietnam and, at the end of August, Typhoon Kajiki killed seven people. In September 2024, the country was hit hard by Typhoon Yagi, which killed more than 300 people due to heavy rains and landslides.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:28:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuca Roseta, fado singer: “Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/06/cuca-roseta-fadista-o-fado-e-um-samba-poesia-cantado-vindo-do-coracao/</link><description>During the pandemic, she sang for the Macau public through a video concert, but now, the fado singer gives her heart and soul to a concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra, part of the lineup for the Macau International Music Festival, next Saturday, 11th. In an interview with HM, Cuca Roseta talks about the show's lineup, her 15-year career and the truth found in her compositions.
Performs in Macau on October 11th with the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM). Tell me a little about what we can expect from this show.
Yes, we are finally going to Macau. It will be the first time because we previously did a video concert for Macau during the pandemic, and we were unable to be there physically. We now work with OCM, which is very good, and I am happy with this partnership, for being able to unite, in some way, two cultures. We are a little anxious about that fact.
The concert will have songs such as “Meu”, “Preto e Branco”, “Canção do Mar”, “Não Sei de Onde” and “Finalmente”. What does this alignment bring us?
We already had arrangements made for orchestra by Marinho de Freitas, which are extraordinary arrangements, and which will be adapted to the traditional OCM instruments. These songs are practically all written by me, lyrics and music, and tell different stories, some that I have lived myself or stories that, in some way, I have experienced someone living very closely. They are original fados. “Canção do Mar” is very old and became known in the voices of Dulce Pontes and Amália Rodrigues, and has a new arrangement. We thought it would look beautiful with OCM. Of course, there are songs that we always sing and that never leave the repertoire, linked to traditional phases of my career. There are some songs that people like and request, but we bring a completely different repertoire to what we presented at the time [in Macau, with the video concert], which was very well received. It was a concert that went very well, even though it was via video, and we received wonderful messages.
This year he released the album “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu”, which has an exclusively Brazilian repertoire, with several names in Brazilian music, such as Seu Jorge or Zeca Pagodinho. Why explore this universe, mixing it with the language of Fado?
Yes, but this year I will also release a French album with Amália Rodrigues' agent, who invited me. But “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu” came from an invitation from a great Brazilian producer to record old sambas, which have a lot to do with Fado. Even though it's a Brazilian album, all sambas, it's my saddest album of all, the most melancholic. That's why we went looking for this root of samba to find great poets and great composers that Brazil has, and who have this weight that Fado also has.
As?
Fado has a lot to do with words and composition, in fact, Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart, because there has to be this truth in the interpretation, the idea of ​​truth coming from life's experiences, in transforming the story it tells. This melancholy is in the veins of Portuguese blood and is mixed with art and music. This invitation wanted to put a fado singer to sing seriously and with the weight that Fado brings, and be able to interpret the great poets and sambas. The album [Até a Fé Se Esqueceu] has very old sambas, one of them from 1937. It is, therefore, a very strong and even very beautiful album, with great poems and composers, such as Tom Jobim, Vinicius de Morais, and wonderful partnerships with Seu Jorge and Zeca Pagodinho, who came to Fado. It's an album that made me really proud.

Therefore, it is possible to marry Fado with the joy of samba, which also has a melancholic side, right? Like the melancholy of our Fado.
In fact, when we hear the word samba we think of joy, but in fact the basis of samba is not joy. There is that phrase by Vinicius de Morais, “To make a samba beautifully you need a bit of sadness, otherwise you won’t make a samba”. So that's where the beauty of this work lies, which goes to the roots of samba and shows that there aren't that many differences between the melancholy at the root of samba and the melancholy of Fado. It's a nostalgic and melancholic album, it doesn't bring that joy. It can bring hope, and we can say that some themes bring with them this hope, which we find in Brazilian culture and drums. Because they literally put their sadness on the skirt wheel and on the drums, right? They transform sadness into dance and music, but in this work we don't see that type of samba.
Cuca also has a previous album, “Cabo Verde Nha Cretcheu”, so it can be said that she has explored, in her career, the different Portuguese-speaking sounds, going beyond Fado, mixing sounds?
This album didn't come from my will, and I think [it's a sign] that life takes me, deep down. This album was born from a tour I took across the nine islands of Cape Verde with a live recording of the mornas I sang on each island, as I sang the traditional mornas of each island. Between one island and another there are very different moraines. What I did was, after my Fado concerts, I sang two mornas and then we compiled all the songs in Creole in celebration of the fact that I was the first international artist to do the nine islands in a row. But I was also in Goa and did my concert in Concanim. I find it easy and enjoy learning the traditional songs of the countries where I am going to sing. I already sang in Moscow and learned a Russian song; I learned the songs of Goa, and in Georgia, in Tblisi, I also learned a song. It's a treat I make when I travel around the world taking Fado. But morna is wonderful and there really are similarities between this musical genre, and I wanted to bring this encounter between Fado and morna to Cape Verdeans, and this album came about, which is beautiful.
Once it goes to Macau, can we expect a song in Cantonese, or Mandarin?
Yes. By chance, I had already spoken to my manager to contact someone in this regard, so that we could discover a traditional song that I could learn.
Last year, he celebrated 15 years of career. How do you review your career, which began with the albums “Cuca Roseta” and “Raiz”?
In fact, it was great to celebrate 15 years at MEO Arena [the concert hall in Lisbon], and be able to revisit all the albums since the first. “Raiz” opened up something that is rarer, which is the fado singer composing and writing her lyrics. This was a record that went wonderfully well and, from then on, it was good, because in this search for the truth that Fado has, being able to compose and write your own lyrics always means giving a little more of yourself. Each person composes and writes in their own way, and when they can do it, it is always a bit like the lines on the palm of their hand, that is, it is something unique. In this search that people make to follow standards to achieve success, I believe that success exists when we are not afraid to follow our voice and our instinct, what comes from our heart, tell our stories and sing our melodies without fear. In this way we end up becoming unique. Although it is not usual in Fado for a fado singer to compose and write, it was nice to see that my songs became important to many fans. Sometimes I have great composers and poets [to collaborate with me], but I think [writing and composing] brings out this side of the person being more truthful. My poems can never be compared to those of the great poets I have sung, but I think people feel that I am more in my own skin. In a way, this touches and moves them. Celebrating 15 years of career was the closing of a cycle and the beginning of another, and it was great to return to the “roots”, and realize that that was where the “gunpowder” lay, in the sense of not being afraid of ourselves.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 05:24:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Hui So-ying, protagonist of the film “Ah Ying”: “Representing is being human”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/30/hui-so-ying-protagonista-do-filme-ah-ying-representar-e-ser-se-humano/</link><description>In 1983, Hong Kong cinema, through the lens of Allen Fong, revealed “Ah Ying”, a film that portrays the hard life of a girl who sells fish in the market and dreams of becoming an actress. That girl was Hui So-ying and “Ah Ying” was inspired by her life. HM spoke to the actress on the sidelines of “Making Waves – 2nd Hong Kong Cinema Exhibition”, which took place this weekend in Lisbon
 
How did you get involved in this film project?
The main reason I got involved in this film was because my theater teacher passed away. So I felt like I needed to do something to honor him, because he was the one who taught me how to act. So I tried to be an actress. Later, when [director] Allen Fong met me, he found my life story interesting, and he also ended up meeting some of my family members. Then he asked if they were also interested in participating in the film, which led to many of them also ending up joining the project. The film also shows the environment in which my teacher lived, it is a portrait of experiences and stories lived by me and my teacher.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in those times. How did you prepare for the character?
The beauty of this film is closely related to the collaborations that were made, particularly in photography and costumes. It took many collaborations to create the beauty that exists in the film. It was hard work taking on the character [of Ah Ying], because the story was designed to describe some of my past experiences, and that's what the director wanted to do. But that was difficult for me, because there were some things I didn't want to face, but I had to. Of course, I later realized that, deep down, it was nothing, and I even felt relieved after finishing filming. Thinking about whether the story was a form of art or reality, when I was performing, I had to enter the situation of the moment because, in fact, the [real] episode had already passed, but I had to have certain feelings again during the performance. As an actress, it was a big test.
“Ah Ying” is considered one of the great films of the so-called “New Wave” of Hong Kong cinema. During the screening, did you expect the film to be successful?
I didn't think about it, but throughout the project I thought that Allen Fong was a very daring director, because a film of this kind had never been made in the entire history of Hong Kong cinema. It's a kind of “docudrama”, and he had the strength and courage to innovate the way he filmed it, which, at the time, was unprecedented.
What was the biggest challenge you faced in this film?
It was having to return to my old self. There were things I didn't want to face and I had to face them again, with the same feeling I had at that time.
Many years have passed between 1983 and the present. Looking back, what meaning did this film have for you, as a person and actress?
In fact, after seeing the film, I saw it as just a story. For me, acting is being human, every day is a performance.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in the 1980s and has received a restored version. What do you think this project can bring to a younger audience watching the film today?
This year the film was shown several times, and I always ask the same question, whether people don't understand the film or whether they think it can't be immersive enough. In fact, given my experience, most younger viewers responded that this is not the case, that the film is quite real. I don't think this film is outdated or out of fashion just because times have progressed or society has changed. I don't think so.
“Ah Ying” closed, in Lisbon, the second edition of “Making Waves – Hong Kong Film Festival”. How do you feel about seeing this film shown in Portugal?
I found it interesting. I never thought that the film could be shown at this exhibition, I don't know if it was because there was a restored copy. Before this new version it was more difficult to display it. The public can see a film that shows family relationships experienced in the 80s, and I think that the film can be immersive [in the theme], when it addresses family conflicts, because everyone has a family. Watching the film, you may wonder what your relationship with your family is like. Of course, I also hope you learned more about Hong Kong. But, despite this film taking place in the 80s, it focuses a lot on family and interpersonal relationships.
Is there an episode from filming that left an impression on you?
There were several moments throughout the film, but the one that left the biggest impression on me was the last scene, in the interview, in which I was talking to a chair, but it was as if I were talking to my teacher. When I see this scene again I am always moved, because my teacher has already passed away, but all of this still makes a huge impression on me.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:42:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra: “The heroic relationships” of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/03/jorge-figueira-arquitecto-e-academico-da-universidade-de-coimbra-as-relacoes-heroicas-de-macau/</link><description>He has been writing and thinking about architecture for a long time, and Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra, has been doing so in Macau since then. After a session this week in which he highlighted the former Fai Chi Kei public housing complex, by Manuel Vicente, Jorge Figueira addresses the legacy of Nuno Portas today at the Rui Cunha Foundation
 
Participate today in the conference “Nuno Portas: from Architecture to Urbanism, from Man to City”. What legacy did this Portuguese architect leave?
Nuno Portas is someone who, at the end of the 50s, had a critical activity that was completely innovative and pioneering in the Portuguese context. Then, in the 60s, he had a more international activity, having been the first to publicize the work of Siza Vieira. It was there that he had his first contacts with Spanish and Italian architects, mainly. During those years he also wrote two books that were also unusual, such as “Architecture for Today”, in 1964, and “City as Architecture”, in 1969. They were also an extraordinary way of trying to understand what was happening in terms of international currents in architecture. But later he also had an [important] activity as an architect alongside Nuno Teotónio Pereira, namely in the work on the Church of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, in Lisbon, and in a house in Vila Viçosa. Then, on April 25, 1974, he was appointed Secretary of State for Housing and Urbanism and launched SAAL – Outpatient Services for Local Support, a completely revolutionary social housing program, in keeping with the spirit of the time. Afterwards, Nuno Portas dedicated himself more to urban planning issues and not so much to architecture. He was linked to the beginning of Expo 98. He ended up being someone who, in the last 20 years of his work, began to have more scientific and sociological concerns, and less artistic ones. It's something he had from the beginning, but later it became the center of his activity.
Did Nuno Portas have any relationship with Macau?
I think that the relationships would not be as intense compared to other architects and contexts, but we know that Nuno Portas was in Macau at the invitation of the Government for a conference, between 2001 and 2002. It is interesting because from this passage we have echoes of what happened, such as his surprise when discovering Manuel Vicente's Ellen Liang orphanage, which he did not know about. It was Manuel Vicente's first work in Macau, in the 60s, and we know that Nuno Portas was moved when visiting this work, especially the small chapel that exists in the orphanage. It's interesting because there was no direct relationship between Manuel Vicente and Nuno Portas, they are figures at very different poles, and even opposites. There is also an interesting and positive reference to the Siza plan [Vieira, Plano de Expansão da Cidade de Macau (Areia Preta e Porto Exterior, 1982), which is being built when Nuno Portas visits Macau. It is interesting that he commented on this plan because in the 60s and 70s the relationship between Nuno Portas and Siza Vieira was no longer the same, and the fact that he made complimentary references to Siza is very interesting.
He was a student of Nuno Portas. What other aspects of your career or personality can you highlight?
I also worked with him. He was a cultured man, very intelligent and with an overwhelming memory. He was someone who liked to provoke, but in a good way, to argue, to contradict. I was lucky enough to maintain a decades-long dialogue with him, and it is this personal knowledge that I will pass on. I also notice that he was a man very close to the power in Lisbon, to the parties, but always very independent. He was a personal friend of Jorge Sampaio, he was Secretary of State, but he never had a major political role. On the one hand, this is due to his independence, but on the other he was such a controversial and intelligently restless figure, that I think power was also scared of him.
This week he also spoke at the conference “Lisbon, Porto, Macau, Maputo: Heroic Collective Housing from the 60s &amp; 70s”. How do you describe Macau’s public housing projects in those years?
There are many architects I could talk about, but I focused on the work of Manuel Vicente in Macau, namely the public housing complex in Fai Chi Kei, which was demolished and later gave rise to the project by Rui Leão and Carlota Bruni. I didn't specifically talk about Portuguese or Macanese architects, we also have names like, for example, José Maneiras. Especially because Portuguese architects have always been few in Portugal, and from the 1950s there were around 150, later increasing greatly in number. But I paid [at the conference] a tribute to the Portuguese architects who built during that period, because in a complex territory and with its vicissitudes, different from those that existed in Portugal, they knew how to carry out extraordinary architectural experiments in the field of public housing. I tried to demonstrate what was happening in Lisbon, Porto, Macau and Lourenço Marques, now Maputo, in different ways. In Macau, relationships were established, which I call heroic, in the sense that they were relationships of experimental architecture, in which people had to adapt, have their own spirit. These are architectures that already have a bit of history, as 50 or 60 years have passed, but the examples we find in these cities continue to be remarkable.
What projects do you highlight from these years?
I spoke about the “Pantera Cor-de-Rosa” housing development, by Gonçalo Byrne, in Chelas, Lisbon. I showed “Cinco Fingers”, by Vítor Figueiredo, also from Lisbon, and “Bairro da Bouça”, by Siza Vieira, in Porto. I showed the Fai Chi Kei complex, by Manuel Vicente, and a project by Pancho Guedes in Mozambique. Despite being distant in time, these are architectures that remain fundamental references from a cultural and architectural point of view. There is a kind of narrative luck in being able to talk about such different places, and with such different architects, and show how they had this heroic, experimental, moving, even radical side that the architecture of that period in particular had.
Has Macau had a positive evolution with regard to the supply of public housing?
I arrived in August and have been visiting the territory in recent years, so I have been following this process a little. Macau is, obviously, an extraordinary territory and due to the coexistence of very different cultures when it comes to housing, which here has a scale and expression completely different from that of Portugal. In Portugal there is an aversion to public housing towers, it has always been something unusual and the results that are known have not been successful for various reasons. But in Macau this is exactly what we see, public housing in towers and with a very strong expression. This has to do with the characteristics of the territory and also with a certain culture in China and Hong Kong. This does not mean that everything being built in Macau is good, there are towers and buildings with less interesting solutions or that result from a certain repetition. But there is no city that only has good architecture or good public housing. The challenge is to solve the housing problem on a large scale, something that must be studied and thought about. It is beautiful and overwhelming to see that Macau is a territory that grows day after day and it is exciting to observe this from an architectural point of view as well. That's what I'm doing, working on future projects.
Analysis projects, or academic ones?
Yes, I'm a professor and researcher at the University of Coimbra and a columnist for the newspaper Público, so my job is to analyze and investigate. I've already published a lot about Macau and I want to go back to some points that I left unresolved, so to speak. I am very encouraged by everything I have seen and the people I have spoken to, and perhaps I will increase my work on the territory from an academic and research point of view.
At a time when Portugal has a chronic housing problem, with a lack of public housing, could Macau be an example?
Not directly, because of the typological issue of the housing tower. It might not be a welcome model in the Portuguese context. But without a doubt, Portugal needs to learn from other experiences and other territories and needs to find solutions. Certainly, what is happening in Hong Kong and Macau are experiences that are very interesting to know, not to replicate, but to understand that this is a global problem [the lack of housing].
Remember Nuno Portas
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will host today, starting at 6:30 pm, the conference “Nuno Portas: from architecture to urbanism, from man to city”, with Jorge Figueira. It will be time to talk about a journey that the recently deceased architect began in 1959, with a text about the new generation of the Modern Movement in Portugal. Texts followed in the 60s and 70s with “scientific approaches”, with Nuno Portas wandering between architecture and urbanism, always in a reflective way. Nuno Portas was a “multifaceted figure, best known for launching the SAAL social housing program, which is still the subject of research and an example today”, describes Jorge Figueira in a note. The speaker is linked to the Center for Social Studies and the Department of Architecture of the University of Coimbra.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 23:33:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Anabela Santiago, academic: “China is reformist and moderate”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/anabela-santiago-academica-a-china-e-reformista-e-moderada/</link><description>Anabela Santiago has just defended her doctoral thesis at the University of Aveiro that analyzes how China has positioned itself, in recent decades, as an important actor in “Global Health Governance”. Today, Beijing is looking for “alternative mechanisms” of cooperation in the “Global South” and is trying to build an alternative model to the World Health Organization
 
 
Let’s start with the concept of global health governance (GGS). Is this a more contemporary concept or one related to the post-World War II period and the founding of the World Health Organization (WHO)? Who have been the main actors in this governance until China's growth?
GGS is a concept whose prominence and relevance has grown significantly in the 21st century, largely driven by economic globalization and global interconnection. Although global health has always transcended national borders, requiring multidisciplinary approaches and international cooperation, it has only been since the 1990s that greater awareness has been made of it. Historically, GGS has been predominantly influenced by Western powers and neoliberal values. The main actors in this governance, until China's growth, were historically marked by interventions from entities such as the WHO and non-governmental organizations, predominantly North American and European.
One of the conclusions of his doctoral thesis is that China has gradually positioned itself in this leadership. When and why did this positioning begin?
Yes, China has progressively positioned itself as a key player in the evolution of the GGS system. Although it is not possible to pinpoint an exact start date, China has evolved from a relatively isolated country to a major player in the global political, economic and technological arenas. Its growing economic and political influence also represents a change in the historical dynamics of the GGS, as in the 1960s China tried to play a role in humanitarian health assistance in neighboring countries and in Africa. The thesis highlights that China's experience can be seen as an example of what is achievable when a State chooses its own path instead of a pre-established model, aligning with the prediction of the 21st century as the “Asian Century”.
Did the years of the pandemic influence this position? In what way?
The Covid-19 pandemic has highlighted the need for global health cooperation, as well as the potential consequences of failing to prioritize global health. The thesis explores the evolution of the Health Silk Road before and after the pandemic, indicating that the years of the pandemic allowed for greater awareness of the need for instruments such as the Health Silk Road as platforms for more effective cooperation between Nations. Although not detailed in this specific section, it is implicit that the pandemic has intensified China's role in health diplomacy and health development assistance.
Looking at the internal reforms that China has carried out in the health sector, which ones do you highlight as the most important?
In the thesis, I address the reforms of China's healthcare system and highlight that the Chinese governance model is a unique combination of market-oriented economic reforms and state-led development, incorporating elements of neoliberalism and authoritarianism in political issues in general, with the healthcare sector being no different from the rest. One of China's contributions mentioned, recognized by the WHO, is its primary health care model based on the recognized good practice of “barefoot doctors”. Furthermore, the thesis analyzes the main reform policies and their progress and challenges in the period 2009-2018, which include primary healthcare reforms, hospital and pharmaceutical reform. The “Healthy China 2030” program is also an important and ambitious benchmark for China's domestic health reforms, also covering social determinants.
Is Beijing's intention to create an alternative entity to the WHO, or simply to create an alternative movement that can coexist with the WHO, in the context of its relationship with the Global South? How could this work?
The thesis suggests that China adopts a “dual approach”: while integrating into existing global structures, it simultaneously forges alternative paths, particularly through regional alliances such as the BRICS and partnerships with the Global South. This indicates an intention to create an alternative movement that can coexist with and complement the role of the WHO, rather than a direct alternative entity. China demonstrates a clear commitment to aligning the objectives of the “Belt and Road” initiative with the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals, showing its willingness to present these initiatives as complements to the cooperation mechanisms already existing in the international liberal order. President Xi Jinping's vision of a “Community of Shared Future for Humanity”, which includes the notion of “Global Health Community for All”, also points to a new perspective in the scope of international cooperation.
Masks, vaccines and Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM): what products or instruments are used by China to position itself as an increasingly global actor in GGS?
The thesis highlights that China is an indispensable provider of global public health goods, essential for the supply chain of products, such as masks and vaccines. TCM is also mentioned as one of China's great contributions to global health governance, with its treatments derived from Chinese herbs, some of which were already recognized by the WHO in 2017. Furthermore, Chinese medical assistance and medical teams sent to other regions of the globe are important instruments of Chinese health diplomacy.
In creating an alternative movement or reality to the WHO, could China be taking advantage of the lack of full representation in that same WHO, or gaps in its functioning?
The thesis does not directly address whether China is taking advantage of a lack of full representation in the WHO or gaps in its functioning. However, she emphasizes that the work aims to fill a gap in scientific knowledge regarding the health governance paradigm from a non-Western and liberal perspective, emphasizing China as an actor in the Global South. This suggests that China seeks to strengthen alternative models that can offer more personalized solutions to health challenges, different from those advocated by Western countries, positioning itself as a moderate reformist actor.
How has the European Union's (EU) foreign policy towards China affected or influenced the country's position in global health governance?
In the thesis, the fourth publication, entitled “Challenges on the European Union-China cooperation in higher education from ‘people-to-people dialogue’ perspective: The case of health-related joint projects”, explores cooperation in higher education, in particular that which includes projects related to health. It appears, therefore, that, despite strategic and economic dialogue, the deterioration of EU-China bilateral relations has intensified, with the Commission assuming a decline in enthusiasm due to “China's countermeasures to EU sanctions on human rights, economic coercion and trade measures against the single market, and China's position in the war in Ukraine”. Although challenges and tensions are recognized, cooperation in higher education, including health projects, is seen as part of a broader framework of building a strategic partnership between the EU and China. However, it is clear that there is no long tradition of health cooperation between the EU and China in higher education, and that there are few joint projects compared to the general picture. It is suggested that both the EU and China should make more efforts to align medical study curricula and promote more joint research in areas related to health, infectious diseases, among others.
In the Trump 2.0 era, and without a pandemic, what could China's role be in global health governance?
Although the thesis will be published this year, it focuses on the period leading up to and including the pandemic, where I do not directly speculate on a future scenario of “Trump 2.0” without a pandemic. However, the thesis argues that China is not just a participant but a moderate reformist force in shaping global health norms. Regardless of future political scenarios, its growing economic and political influence, strategic health diplomacy, domestic reforms and initiatives such as the Health Silk Road will continue to shape its role in global health governance. The vision of a “Global Health Community for All” also remains a guiding principle for China's efforts.
Does this power of China in the GGS occur more with bilateral or multilateral agreements?
The thesis suggests that China's power in global health governance is manifested through both bilateral and multilateral agreements, but with an increasing emphasis on certain forms of cooperation that strengthen its role in the Global South and through alternative mechanisms. Although the thesis does not explicitly quantify the predominance between bilateral and multilateral, the focus on regional alliances (BRICS) and partnerships with the Global South (which often involve bilateral agreements and group cooperation initiatives) and the Health Silk Road indicate a hybrid approach.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 23:46:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied this right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on permanence, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (even in 2011 the Municipal Council of Faro wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
What are you talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a soldier in the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Vernice Lao, just 15 years old, made her F4 debut in Chengdu</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/19/vernice-lao-de-apenas-15-anos-estreou-se-na-f4-em-chengdu/</link><description>In an initiative supported by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Marcus Cheong and Vernice Lao participated in the Chengdu race of the Chinese Formula 4 Championship. The two drivers from local karting competed against some of the best single-seater drivers in the region, and for young Vernice Lao, this was an absolute debut in motorsport.
At the newly built Tianfu Chengdu International Circuit, Marcus Cheong returned to the Formula 4 discipline, having already had several forays into the category, having even finished in 12th place in the 2023 Macau Grand Prix Formula 4 Race.
On this return, the Macau driver drove one of the Mygale chassis, the same as those that will be used in the FIA ​​World Cup at the Guia Circuit, at the end of the year, by the Apollo RFN Racing by Blackjack team. In the sister team Asia Racing Team, founded in Macau in 2003, and also supported by AAMC, 15-year-old Vernice Lao took her first steps in motor racing, after two days of testing in Zhuhai with the single-seater built in France.
Rodolfo Ávila, Team Manager of the team of the two drivers from the territory, highlighted "how fantastic it is to see two drivers supported by the AAMC, something that has a special meaning for me, as I also took my first steps in the single-seater competition with the support of the AAMC. Seeing these young talents from Macau following a similar path is extremely gratifying, and their participation has a very special importance for both me and the team."
Consistent results
After Friday's qualifying sessions, in Saturday's first race Marcus Cheong reached sixth place in the CFGP class and finished 12th overall. Vernice Lao ranked 6th in the Formula 4 class for young drivers, occupying 18th position overall. In the second race of the same day, Marcus Cheong repeated the result, again taking 6th place in the CFGP class and 12th place overall. Vernice Lao finished in 23rd place, also securing 6th position in the Formula 4 class.
In the first race on Sunday, Marcus Cheong improved his performance, reaching 5th place in the CFGP class and 10th place overall. In turn, Vernice Lao finished 7th in Formula 4, corresponding to 19th overall. In the final clash of the weekend, Marcus Cheong shone by taking 2nd place in the CFGP class, also obtaining an honorable 6th place in the general classification. As for Vernice Lao, she finished 13th overall, securing a consistent 6th position in the Formula 4 class.
Very positive balance
On a particularly demanding weekend, with variable track conditions, Portuguese Rodolfo Ávila highlighted the performance of the Macau drivers supported by AAMC, Marcus Cheong and Vernice Lao. "Both showed clear progress throughout the weekend and Vernice, in particular, impressed everyone with a clean and confident debut in single-seaters. Competing against such an experienced field, with so little experience in a Formula 4 car, and delivering the performance she achieved was a pleasant surprise", said the 2003 Asian Formula Renault champion.
On social media, Vernice Lao reported that this was “an incredible experience”, adding that “over the weekend we lost a lot, but we ended up achieving a satisfactory result”. The Macao SAR driver acknowledged that “there is still a long way to go” and took the opportunity to thank “the support and encouragement” from the team, the Team Manager and her teammate, in what she classified as “an unforgettable weekend with the Asia Racing Team”.
The next step for the two drivers from the territory is not yet known, but the Chinese Formula 4 Championship ends in the neighboring city of Zhuhai on the weekend of October 11th and 12th. Afterwards, these same cars from the Chinese competition will be reviewed before traveling to Macau, where they will be used in the FIA ​​World Cup.</description><pubDate>2025-09-19 00:42:07</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA presents 10 teams from the FR World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/12/gp-fia-da-a-conhecer-10-equipas-da-taca-do-mundo-fr/</link><description>On Wednesday night, the International Automobile Federation (FIA), in partnership with the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix, published the official list of teams registered for this year's edition of the Macau Grand Prix – FIA FR World Cup.
Although the names of the Formula Regional (FR) drivers who will visit Macau in November have not been released, according to the official statement from the organization, based in Paris, this “carefully selected squad of ten truly international teams will bring together the best regional talents from around the world to compete in this prestigious, unique race on the iconic Guia Circuit”.
This year's edition welcomes two new major teams to the event: the Italian Trident Motorsport, which arrives in Macau after a 2025 season in which it won the FIA ​​Formula 3 Championship, with the Brazilian Rafael Câmara, and the Dutch Van Amersfoort Racing (VAR), a team that has known the Guia Circuit well since 1998 and that, in 2018, suffered a huge scare with the spectacular accident by Sophia Flörsch.
Returning to defend the coveted title in Macau will be R-ace GP, a European team that won in 2024 with Ugo Ugochukwu, a driver who will not be present this year to try to revalidate the title. The French team remains in great form, leading the current FRECA standings and finishing second in the Middle East Formula Regional Championship earlier this year.
Return of SJM Theodore
Also returning are some of the strongest contenders from last year's Macau Grand Prix and the FR scene in general, including a well-known name from the event: SJM Theodore Prema Racing. The Italian team Prema, currently in second place in the FRECA 2025 championship, is one of the most successful teams in grassroots motorsport and is once again partnering with Teddy Yip Jr. at the Macao SAR event.
Also returning are Pinnacle Motorsport, an Irish-owned team; the Australian Evans GP, which achieved fourth place in the last edition; the Japanese TOM’S Racing, one of the most prestigious in Japanese motorsport; the German PHM Racing; and the always competitive French structures Saintéloc Racing and ART Grand Prix.
On the other hand, the Dutch MP Motorsport, the Australian Kiwi Motorsport and the Japanese TGM Grand Prix left the scene. No team from China was selected, but, unlike last year, none attempted to register for the competition.
The official list of entries should only be made known in mid-October, as is tradition for the Grand Prix.
The second edition of the FIA ​​FR World Cup will take place during the week of the Macau Grand Prix, from 13 to 16 November, and will also feature, for the first time, the FIA ​​F4 World Cup, making the event one of the most prestigious global showcases for the junior single-seater categories.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:22:52</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau: First names and first questions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/gp-macau-primeiros-nomes-e-primeiras-duvidas/</link><description>October is usually the month of preparations for the Macau Grand Prix. With the championships coming to an end all over the world, attention turns to the Macao SAR's big event, which this year will take place from the 13th to the 16th of November
 
After Marcos Cheong and Vernice Lau raced in the Chinese Formula 4 Championship race, this weekend it is Tiago Rodrigues' turn to pick up the helmet again to compete in the closing race of the Chinese competition season, on the circuit in the neighboring city of Zhuhai. The former Chinese champion of the discipline has been away from single-seater racing since participating in the Middle East Formula 4 Championship at the beginning of the year, but his experience could prove to be an asset in defending the territory's colors at the Guia Circuit.
Twenty of the Mygale M21-F4 single-seaters from the Chinese championship will be overhauled after this race at the Zhuhai International Circuit and handed over to technicians appointed by the French Motor Sport Federation (FFSA), who will put them on the track in the first edition of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup, in Macau. This is the same model used in the French Formula 4 Championship.
Some names of the bikes
Michael Rutter's absence from the entry list for this year's Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix is ​​now a certainty. However, through the specialized press, the first names that will shape the only road race on the Asian continent are beginning to become known.
Practically confirmed are the presence of Davey Todd, winner of last year's edition, and Peter Hickman, the motorcyclist who chases Rutter's record of victories and who should be practically recovered from the injuries suffered in the accident on the Isle of Man. Both will drive the official competitive BMW M1000RR from 8TEN Racing. Rob Hodson, SMT Racing driver, has also guaranteed his presence in the Macao SAR, usually being one of the strong candidates for the Top 5 in the race.
But not only renowned names are tested. Among the debutants already confirmed is ramp driver Maurizio Bottalico. The San Marino driver, who reached the podium at the Manx Grand Prix, follows in the footsteps of other great Italian names in 21st century road racing — such as Stefano Bonetti, Luca Gottardi or Alex Polita — by taking on the most famous and feared race in the East.
According to the Road Racing News portal, there will be more newcomers to the Guia Circuit this year, such as Mitch Rees, a driver with several titles in New Zealand, Ryan Whitehall, a driver from the Isle of Wight, and the new holder of the Frohburger Dreieck lap record in the Supersport category, Paul Jordan.
Questions in the GT
Stéphane Ratel, founder and CEO of SRO Motorsports Group — the company that co-organizes the FIA ​​GT World Cup Macau Grand Prix — has been one of the most critical voices regarding the introduction of torque sensors in GT3 racing. However, the FIA ​​decided in favor of its use in the Guia Circuit World Cup, and the French businessman spoke about the matter for the first time.
"The teams competing in Macau are mostly from Asia, where torque sensors have never been used. The lack of experience could affect the sporting balance, and that's why I opposed their use", said Stéphane Ratel to the German magazine Motorsport Aktuell, adding that he does not believe this is the way forward.
Although the SRO Motorsports Group is co-organizer of the event and has a Balance of Performance (BoP) recognized worldwide, in the last two years the Macau BoP has been determined by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA's BoP was subject to a series of criticisms, with teams and drivers – particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main losers – publicly expressing their displeasure at the differences in pace. For this reason, the FIA ​​decided to introduce these expensive sensors, installed on the cars' transmission shafts, which represent the most accurate tool for measuring the power transmitted to the wheels.
“Some manufacturers supported the idea, but others, like Mercedes, were against it,” said Stéphane Ratel. "As a result, we lost some cars from the entry list. To be clear: I look at this issue pragmatically, not dogmatically. Last year in Macau, three or four manufacturers could have won without these torque sensors. In 2025 we will see if this technology is really useful", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:11:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorsport | MSAR comics with special premiere in Japan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/26/automobilismo-banda-desenhada-da-raem-com-estreia-especial-no-japao/</link><description>The Macau comic strip, “Heróis do Circuito” (街道), had its first international appearance in a very special way two weeks ago, at the 1000 km of Suzuka, in Japan
The classic endurance race had not been contested since 2019, and, to mark the return of this iconic race in the Land of the Rising Sun, Porsche Motorsport Asia Pacific decided to decorate the three cars it supported with the Stuttgart brand's historic colors. Among them, one of Absolute Racing's Porsche 911 GT3 R was painted yellow and black, in honor of Joest Racing's victory in the 1985 24 Hours of Le Mans, when Portuguese Domingos Piedade was Sporting Director of the German team. With the current sponsors, and not with the French clothing brand NewMan, responsible for the decoration 40 years ago, the inscription in Portuguese stood out on the rear wing of the Porsche 911 GT3 R nº 7: “Heróis do Circuito”.
For those who follow local motor sport closely, the comic strip “Heróis do Circuito” is already part of the territory’s motoring culture. Passionate about the ninth art and a self-confessed devotee of motor sports, MP Man is the “Jean Graton of Macau”. His title, often seen on cars at local Grand Prix races, has this time reached an international stage.
Regarding participation in the most prestigious endurance race for GT3 cars on the Asian continent, MP Man told HM: "Upon receiving this exciting news, I felt surprise and admiration. This recognition not only values ​​the effort and dedication of years, but also opens a door for the presence of an original Macau brand on the international motorsport stages, allowing us to show the world the unique cultural character and creativity of Macau, an honor that fills me with pride and enthusiasm.”
The international debut could not have gone better in sporting terms, as Absolute Racing's #7 Porsche 911 GT3 R, driven by Kévin Estre, Laurens Vanthoor and Patrick Pilet, crossed the line in second place overall, in a race that also scored points for the Intercontinental GT Challenge.
Bring together synergies
Interestingly, the springboard for placing the MSAR cartoon on a top car from Absolute Racing, an Asian team supported by Porsche Motorsport Asia Pacific and with several triumphs in the Macau GT Cup, was a common sponsor: a model car brand from southern China.
"We maintain a close and friendly relationship with the renowned national collector model brand Almost Real. The founder, Liu Xueshen, Mr. Sum, has always enthusiastically supported my comic book, and has now become one of the main sponsors.
With an ambitious vision, they intend to take the work across borders, exploring new horizons", explained the author, responsible for some of the illustrations on display at the Macau Grand Prix Museum. "By becoming sponsors of Absolute Racing, they integrated elements of the Heróis do Circuito brand into the racing car's paintwork, allowing the vehicle, when running on the track, to announce to the world the unique charm of the comic strip.”
For MP Man, who launched the first issue of “Heróis do Circuito” in 2018, the objective is clear: “For racing and comic book fans to pay more attention to the original creation made in Macau and recognize the effort dedicated to this project.”
Looking to the future
Presence at the Suzuka event, which brought together more than 65 thousand spectators, constituted a decisive step in the brand's internationalization.
"Now, “Heroes of the Circuit” has reached a moment of great significance. Like an eagle taking flight, he has successfully joined a team supported by Porsche, participating in an endurance race that brings together the best teams and drivers from all over Asia", says MP Man, who does not hide his ambition to go further. "If one day my brand manages to reach races like Le Mans, or even a Formula 1 Grand Prix, it will be a dream come true! (laughs) This is, without a doubt, my deepest desire. But I also know that dreams do not come true immediately; my work still has a lot to evolve and perfect. I will continue to create with humility, persevering in improving the work, seeking to offer readers ever more experiences exciting.”
Meanwhile, the fourth volume of the “Circuit Heroes” series is about to be published, opening a new chapter, always with its unique charm and captivating narratives that have won the attention and affection of the local public, increasingly establishing itself in the global universe of comics and among motor sports fans.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 07:21:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Charles Leong wins Lamborghini Super Trofeo title</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/09/charles-leong-conquista-titulo-lamborghini-super-trofeo/</link><description>Macau driver Charles Leong Hon Chio became the winner of the PRO class of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia last weekend, at the Sepang International Circuit, in Malaysia. This represents the Macao SAR driver's first title in Grand Tourism (GT) competitions and the first championship title achieved with SJM Theodore Racing.
Despite being ill and with two races remaining in the calendar of the competition organized by the prestigious Italian car brand, Charles Leong and the young Irishman Alex Denning always proved to be extremely fast on the Malaysian track. They won the first race of the weekend, thus achieving their sixth victory of the season, and finished second in the second race. This second place took the number of podiums achieved in 10 races to 10, extending the team's impressive run, which has never finished lower than second place.
With two races still to be contested at the Lamborghini Super Trofeo World Finals, in Misano, Italy, in November, SJM Theodore Racing will be able to focus on maintaining this impressive run of podiums, with the main objective of the season already achieved. Charles Leong and Alex Denning are tied at the top of the driver standings and are expected to complete the season side by side, sharing the same Lamborghini Huracán Super Trofeo EVO2.
Always adding
For Charles Leong, this result is the result of "incredible work by the team. We won the championship thanks to a great collective effort, without major mistakes and with total consistency. For the race, I expected a bigger group, but it was difficult to fight against my opponents with new tires. In the end, I followed my rhythm and we managed the tires to give the best car to Alex. It was a very good weekend."
After finishing in second place in the classification of this same single-brand trophy, the Macau driver adds this title to those he won at a young age in the Formula Renault Asian Championship and the Chinese Formula 4 Championship, in addition to two notable victories in the Formula 4 Macau Grand Prix.
Obviously satisfied with the results obtained by his pupils, Teddy Yip Jr., owner of SJM Theodore Racing, commented: "I want to congratulate the entire team for this achievement, the result of a collective effort throughout the season and previous years. The drivers responded in an exemplary way to the pressure. Thank you to Charles, despite being ill, and to Alex, who performed another fast and consistent stint, securing tenth ‘top-2’ in ten races.”
The Theodore Racing team and SJM have supported Charles Leong since 2021, when he achieved his second Formula 4 triumph at the Guia Circuit. In 2023, he finished very close to teammate Arvid Lindblad in the Macau Grand Prix Formula 4 race, completing a triumphant 1-2 for SJM Theodore PREMA Racing. Absent from last year's edition due to commitments at the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia in Spain, Charles Leong has not yet announced whether he will participate in this year's edition of the Macau Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:01:15</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Michael Rutter misses this year's edition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/08/gp-macau-michael-rutter-falha-edicao-deste-ano/</link><description>Nine-time Macau Grand Prix winner Michael Rutter will miss the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix. The charismatic British driver continues to recover from the serious accident he suffered at the Isle of Man TT, last June, and is not ready to fight for his tenth victory
 
At the beginning of the summer, in the great road classic, Michael Rutter fell off his bike on the last lap of the Supertwin race, at the place known as 31st Milestone, and suffered several fractures in his spine, between the L2 and L5 vertebrae, and was even transferred by helicopter to the hospital. The 53-year-old driver was also diagnosed with a fractured ankle.
After almost three months away from competition, “The Blade”, as he is known in the industry, made his return to motorcycling on the last weekend of August, taking part in the famous Classic TT parade lap, atop a Honda RVF750 RC45, as part of a tribute to the models of the 1980s and 1990s. The most successful motorcyclist ever in Macau, where he won the first After his nine victories in 1998, he got back on a bike for the first time in the Classic TT, where he rode a Honda RC45 on the parade lap dedicated to the 1980s and 1990s. However, Rutter is not yet ready to return to competition, the Irish publication News Letter reported last week.
His last victory was achieved at the Guia Circuit in 2019, although not in the way Rutter would have liked to have increased his achievements, as the result was decided based on positions after just one lap, after two red flag interruptions that led to the definitive cancellation of the race. Still aiming to win a tenth time in Macau, at last year's Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, deeply affected by bad weather, Rutter was disappointed with the result, having qualified with the fourth fastest time, in a race in which the qualifying result determined the final positions of the race.
Before the Isle of Man TT accident, Rutter had told the News Letter that he wanted to travel to Macau at the end of the year. "We'll try again, because it's another race that I really enjoy going to. It's completely unique, it's on the other side of the world, in another time zone, so it's unique", he said without knowing what to expect.
Another big question
Rutter may not be the only “historic” Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix to be left out of this year's edition, as many doubts persist surrounding Peter Hickman, who was also the victim of an accident at the Isle of Man event. The Briton's accident was caused by a mechanical failure: the exhaust fixing broke, causing it to come into contact with the rear tire and causing a puncture that led to the expert's fall. pilot. The winner of four editions suffered serious injuries: fractured collarbone and left shoulder blade, three broken ribs, four fractured vertebrae and facial injuries.
In a post on social media, Hickman said he has been working “very hard” behind the scenes and even recently held a trial at Cadwell Park. Three months after the accident, he returned this weekend to the popular British Superbike Championship at Donington Park. The 38-year-old driver has not yet recovered his best form and the demands of a city circuit, like Macau, are much higher than those of a conventional circuit. Therefore, it will only be known in the coming weeks whether Hickman will try to win his fifth victory on the streets of Macau, in 2025.
The 72nd Macau Grand Prix will take place between the 13th and 16th of November this year. In addition to the 57th Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, the program also includes the Macau Grand Prix - FIA FR World Cup, the Macau GT Cup - FIA GT World Cup, the Guia Race Macau - Kumho FIA TCR World Tour Event of Macau, the Macau Formula 4 Race - FIA Formula 4 World Cup, the GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4) and the Macau Roadsport Challenge.</description><pubDate>2025-09-08 02:43:40</pubDate></item></channel></rss>