<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Security | Japan and the United Kingdom reaffirm cooperation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/seguranca-japao-e-reino-unido-reafirmam-cooperacao/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Japan, Sanae Takaichi, and her British counterpart, Keir Starmer, this Saturday reaffirmed cooperation in security matters on the sidelines of the G20 Leaders' Summit, which ended yesterday in South Africa.
Takaichi and Starmer “agreed to continue to cooperate on security issues” and also “agreed to collaborate closely in the areas of economy and economic security”, said the Japanese Prime Minister's office yesterday, which reported on the results of a meeting between the two leaders in Johannesburg the day before.
In the first meeting between Takaichi and his British counterpart since the governor took office last month, both leaders also reaffirmed their intention to work “closely” with the United States for a “free and open” Indo-Pacific.
The statements come in the context of strong diplomatic tension between Tokyo and Beijing, since Takaichi stated in the Japanese Parliament that a military attack by China against Taiwan could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (Army) (see page 12).
Beijing responded with harsh reprimands and economic reprisals, while demanding that Takaichi recant and advising its citizens not to travel to Japan, which led to hundreds of flight suspensions.
Takaichi refused on Friday to retract his statements regarding Taiwan and maintained that this is the Japanese government's “consistent position”. At the same time, the minister reiterated her desire to maintain beneficial relations with China and launched a new call for dialogue.
Tokyo expressed its availability for a meeting between Takaichi and Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang at the G20 bilateral meetings, as China had said last Monday that there is no planned meeting between the two leaders during the summit.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:48:48</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Miguel de Senna Fernandes calls for more focus on Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/lag-miguel-de-senna-fernandes-pede-mais-foco-em-macau/</link><description>The president of the Association of Macanese, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, defended the importance of regional integration, but highlighted that Macau is going through a “delicate” moment and needs more attention from the Government. Senna Fernandes' position was taken in statements to Canal Macau.
"Macau is integrated into the Greater Bay Area, nothing other than improvements are expected to accelerate the development of the Greater Bay Area. But, we cannot forget that we are in Macau. This is fundamental", began by saying the president of the association, regarding the Lines and Governing Action. “There is no citizen, no matter how noble, no matter how much he defends the Government, no matter how much he applauds the Government in this policy and Macau's contribution to development, there is no citizen who does not have Macau as a priority”, he added.
In a context in which the recovery of tourism covers society in an unequal way, Miguel de Senna Fernandes asked for more attention to Macau, because it is going through a complicated period: “Despite the economic recovery numbers, we cannot forget that there is still a group of citizens to whom this does not reach”, he stressed.
"We need to say the measures, and I'm not saying long-term, but medium-term, to improve the conditions, the future prospects of this layer of workers, of professionals in Macau. Don't just feed the dream of Hengqin, for example. There are people who like to stay in Macau and for them Macau is always the future", he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:01:36</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Pedida maior cobertura de programa anti-burlas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/pj-pedida-maior-cobertura-de-programa-anti-burlas/</link><description>O deputado Chan Lai Kei interpelou o Governo sobre a necessidade de reforçar e aumentar a cobertura do programa anti-burlas da Polícia Judiciária (PJ), tendo em conta os frequentes casos de burla que ocorrem associados a falsos funcionários da plataforma Taobao. 
Therefore, the deputy, with connections to the Fujian community, questioned whether analyzes using artificial intelligence (AI) could be introduced in this program so that alerts could be given to users whenever they find messages with a high risk of fraud. Furthermore, the deputy recalled that there is a face swap technique using AI, which leads elderly people to easily become victims of fraud, which is why he hopes that the PJ will use this anti-fraud program to publicize these types of cases to groups of potential victims of fraud.
Na mesma interpelação, o deputado pergunta ainda como vai o Governo reforçar a cooperação com as regiões vizinhas no que toca à partilha de dados transfronteiriços, a fim de rastrear a origem e fluxo de capital envolvido em burlas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:25:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Barra Slow Festival | Coffee and culture in Naval Workshops</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/barra-slow-festival-cafe-e-cultura-nas-oficinas-navais/</link><description>It's called “Barra Slow Festival” and the first edition is scheduled for next weekend, between the 28th and 30th of November, with the aim of revitalizing the Barra area with activities linked to coffee culture, design and crafts. The public will be able to enjoy events at Naval Workshops nº 1 and nº2, as well as in the square located in the area
This weekend, namely between Friday and Sunday, the first edition of the “Barra Slow Festival 2025” is taking place in Macau, an event that brings various activities linked to coffee, culture and art and aims to attract public attention to the Barra area, known for tourist sites such as the A-Má Temple.
According to an official statement from the event, this is a debut in the territory of events such as “To Play Market × Tokyo Coffee Festival · Macau 2025” and the “Shanghai UNFOLD Art and Design Fair”, as well as initiatives such as “Coffee Rave”, “Macau Chill Collective” and an exhibition by well-known graphic designer Florian Lamm. All these events will be spread across the square in the Barra area and Oficinas Navais nº 1 and nº2, where cultural events usually take place.
According to the same note, the “Barra Slow Festival” integrates “popular contemporary elements, such as coffee culture, creative design, visual exhibitions, limited artisanal products and music”, being a “cultural event with selected concepts”.
The idea of ​​an event in which there is “human warmth” is defended, encouraging the public “to relax and live intensely, recovering the tranquility inherent to life”. In this way, “the Barra neighborhood was chosen [for this initiative], with tents set up inside and outside the historic buildings of the Naval Workshops”.
It is therefore hoped that the general public “can enjoy a cup of coffee, stroll around the area and experience the historical depth of the Barra neighborhood”.
From the outside to the inside
Above all, the “Barra Slow Festival” brings to Macau events already known in Asia, such as the “Tokyo Coffee Festival”, organized by “To Play Market” and which brings together almost 50 famous coffee brands from Japan, the Greater Bay Area and Macau.
“Just a few months ago, the Tokyo Coffee Festival made its debut in Hong Kong, attracting more than 30,000 participants, and both its artisanal coffee and coffee products were highly praised,” highlights the organization. At this premiere in Macau there will be special products for sale and limited editions.
Another highlight of the lineup is the “UNFOLD” Art and Design Fair, organized in Shanghai by Shanghai BANANAFISH. This is an event with the curatorial concept of “unfold, read and present”, being a “communication platform that brings together lovers of culture and art, designers, creative workers and professionals from the creative industry”.
What you can see in Barra, with “UNFOLD”, is a market with 100 stands of brands and design products from around the world, with “creative selections and limited artisanal products”, and ticket holders can also visit the special exhibition by designer Florian Lamm.
Florian's works were selected for the Top 100 Posters in Germany, Austria and Switzerland, and won the Artist Award at the Brno Biennale, the oldest graphic design exhibition in the world.
The “Macau Chill Collective” aims to “bring together the strength of local brands”, inviting “dozens of brands, from well-known cafe owners, creative artisans and creators”. During the festival, the exhibition “Ancient Memories: Impressions of the Shipyard – Historical Photographic Exhibition of the Barra District” will also be held in order to “deepen participants’ understanding of the history of the district”.
O “Barra Slow Festival” tem entrada gratuita e decorre entre as 12h e as 20h, sendo necessário adquirir bilhetes para a Feira de Arte e Design UNFOLD, com um custo de 55 patacas em regime de pré-venda e 78 patacas nos dias do evento. There are also tickets for sale for some events related to coffee culture. Tickets have been on sale since November 2nd on the MacauTicket, Damai and Ctrip platforms. O evento é organizado pela Federação da Indústria e Comércio de Macau, Distrito Central e Sul, coorganizado pela BANANAFISH e TOPYS, e apoiado pelo Instituto de Desenvolvimento Económico e Tecnológico, pela Direcção dos Serviços de Turismo de Macau, pela União Geral das Associações de Bairro de Macau e outras entidades patrocinadoras.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:29:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Oceans | China, Portugal and Brazil create research laboratory</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/oceanos-china-portugal-e-brasil-criam-laboratorio-de-investigacao/</link><description>Among the institutions involved in the new project are the University of São Paulo (USP), the University of Macau (UM) and the Instituto Superior Técnico (IST)
Academic institutions from China, Portugal and Brazil created a new project in Macau on Friday to collaborate on ocean research, including the impact of climate change and changes in marine currents.
“We are going to deepen our knowledge of the oceans and have a more integrated vision, which will allow us to anticipate the future in a safer way”, the coordinator of the Robotics and Engineering Systems Laboratory told Lusa. The objective of the Oceanic Research Center between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries is “to collaborate and share data, resources and talents”, added José Santos-Victor.
In addition to the laboratory associated with Instituto Superior Técnico, the new center includes the University of São Paulo (USP), the University of Macau (UM) and the Chinese state laboratory Laoshan Laboratory, based in Qingdao, in eastern China. “There are several research centers that do excellent work in these various areas”, defended Santos-Victor, giving as an example the research and prediction of the effects of climate change on the oceans.
According to environmental groups, climate change is one of the greatest threats to the oceans, along with pollution and new technologies that open the door to deep-sea mining and more intensive fishing. A priority will be training, with plans for exchanges between researchers and master's or doctoral students between the center's various laboratories, highlighted the Portuguese academic.
New master's degrees
During the inauguration ceremony, UM's rector, Song Yonghua, promised the launch of joint master's degree programs between the universities that are part of the initiative. Ettore Apolonio de Barros, professor at USP, reminded Lusa that the Brazilian university created, in 2024, the USP-China Center, to “promote cooperation with Chinese universities”.
The researcher highlighted the multidisciplinary nature of the center opened in Macau, as “one of the first initiatives” to bring together scientists and engineers to collaborate in the exploration and study of the oceans. The specialist in automated electromechanical systems recalled that the project is “an important development” of the Oceanic Scientific Research Alliance between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries.
The alliance was also created in Macau, in 2022, by 19 universities from China and Portugal, Brazil, Angola and Mozambique, to launch joint research projects on the oceans. The vice-rector of UM, the Portuguese Rui Martins, told Lusa that the alliance was recently strengthened, with the entry of five more institutions, including the University of Hainan, in southern China.
On the Portuguese-speaking side, the Technical University of the Atlantic (Cape Verde), the University of Coimbra, the Institute of Systems and Computer Engineering, Technology and Science (INESC TEC) and INESC P&amp;D Brasil joined.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:19:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | New visitor record for October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/turismo-novo-recorde-de-visitantes-para-mes-de-outubro/</link><description>The territory received around 33.1 million visitors in the first ten months, 14.1 percent more than in the same period last year. It is the second highest value ever, below pre-pandemic records
Macau received 3.47 million visitors in October, 10.8 percent more than in the same period in 2024 and the highest figure ever for this month, it was announced. The number of tourists passing through the territory was the highest for any month of October since the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) began compiling monthly data, in 1998, still during the Portuguese administration.
The region had already registered a historic high for September in the previous month: almost 3.8 million visitors, 9.8 percent more than in the same period in 2024. However, in October almost 61 percent of visitors (2.1 million) arrived on organized tours and spent less than a day in Macau.
In 2024, the Central Government announced a series of measures to support the territory, such as increasing the tax exemption limit for goods for personal use purchased by visitors from China. At the same time, the Chinese authorities expanded the list of places with “individual visas” to visit Hong Kong and Macau to 10 more cities in China.
Additionally, since January 1, residents of the neighboring city of Zhuhai can visit Macau once a week and stay for up to seven days. As a result, the overwhelming majority (89.8 percent) of tourists arriving in Macau in September came from mainland China or Hong Kong, while just over 353,000 were international visitors.
The city received a total of around 33.1 million visitors in the first ten months, 14.1 percent more than in the same period in 2024 and the second highest figure ever for the start of a year.
Below 2019
According to official data, the number of tourists passing through Macau was only surpassed between January and October 2019 – before the Covid-19 pandemic -, a period in which it registered more than 33.4 million visitors. On January 17, the director of Macau Tourism Services said she expected between 38 and 39 million visitors this year.
In August, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes set a target of more than three million international visitors in 2025. In the first ten months of the year, Macau received almost 2.97 million tourists from abroad, 14.9 percent more than in the same period in 2024.
Citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Bahrain and Oman will no longer need a visa to enter the city from July 16th. Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell by 9.5 percent in the first nine months of the year, compared to the same period in 2024.
At the beginning of May, DSEC pointed to the “change in the consumption pattern of visitors” as one of the main reasons for the 1.3 percent drop in Macau's economy between January and March. It was the first time that the territory's Gross Domestic Product shrank, in year-on-year terms, since the end of 2022, when the region began to lift restrictions due to the covid-19 pandemic.
Macau received 34.9 million visitors last year, 23.8 percent more than the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019, before the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:07:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | EU expresses “concern about political issues”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/economia-ue-expressa-preocupacao-com-questoes-politicas/</link><description>Harvey Rouse, head of the European Union (EU) Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau, met with Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, to discuss investment by European companies in the diversification of Macau's economy
The European Union (EU) declined to reveal whether Au Kam San, detained with Portuguese nationality, was mentioned in a meeting with Macau authorities, in which a European representative demonstrated “concern about political issues”. On Thursday, the head of the European Union (EU) Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau, Harvey Rouse, wrote on social media that he had met with Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip.
The two spoke about how European companies can support “the economic diversification” of Macau, which is highly dependent on tourism, and “the continued development” of the neighboring special economic zone of Hengqin (Mountain Island). “I also expressed concern about political issues,” added Briton Rouse.
Asked by Lusa whether he had discussed the detention of former deputy Au Kam San with Anton Tai, the British diplomat did not respond. “We do not comment on the specific content of bilateral meetings,” the EU Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau told Lusa, in a written response.
“In our meetings with the Macau authorities, we regularly raise concerns about political and legal changes in the MSAR [Special Administrative Region of Macau], in line with the EU Annual Report on Macau, including on individual cases,” the delegation added.
On September 11, the European Commission warned that the “insistence on national security by the Macau government” is leading to “limiting the space for pluralistic voices from both politics and society”.
Uncomfortable revisions
In a report, the commission gave as an example the review of electoral laws for the leader of the Government and for the local parliament, to exclude candidates considered unpatriotic. On July 31, Macau police announced the arrest of pro-democracy activist Au Kam San, in the first case under the region's national security law, which came into force in 2009 and whose scope was expanded in 2023.
On September 10, during a visit to Macau, Portuguese Prime Minister Luís Montenegro admitted that he did not speak about Au Kam San with the leader of the local government, Sam Hou Fai, and argued that the case requires “the necessary discretion” and “some modesty”.
On October 21, the president of the Court of Final Instance of Macau, Song Man Lei, declared that the local justice system has an “indispensable duty” to judge “fairly, independently and professionally” national security cases, as well as “to ensure that all acts that offend the security of the State are punished in accordance with the law”.
Recently, after the presentation of the Government Action Lines for 2026, Sam Hou Fai briefly addressed the detention of Au Kam San for the first time. “In August, we had the first case related to the national security law,” he said at a press conference, without mentioning the name of the activist. The accusation is not yet known and there is no information about who will defend the former deputy.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:59:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture | Tensions between China and Japan postpone meeting in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/cultura-tensoes-entre-china-e-japao-adiam-reuniao-em-macau/</link><description>A meeting of the “Cities of Culture of East Asia” was scheduled for today in Macau with ministers from China, South Korea and Japan. However, the initiative was canceled by Beijing, due to growing tension with Japan, following statements by the Japanese Prime Minister
The meeting in Macau between the Ministers of Culture of China, Japan and the Republic of Korea, which was originally scheduled for today, was postponed, without a new date being set. The announcement was made on Thursday by Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning, cited by Xinhua.
According to information from the state agency, the Chinese spokesperson stated “that a Japanese leader openly made highly erroneous statements about Taiwan, which hurt the feelings of the Chinese people, challenged the post-World War II international order and undermined the basis and environment for cooperation between China, Japan and the Republic of Korea.”
Mao Ning also said that the “Japanese leader’s” statements led “to a situation in which there are still no conditions to hold the meeting”.
Although Xinhua does not identify the “Japanese leader”, the target is Sanae Takaichi, Prime Minister of Japan. The first woman to lead the Executive of the country of the rising sun stated, on November 7, in parliament, that an attack from the Interior on the Island of Taiwan would be seen in Japan as a situation that would “threaten the survival” of the country.
In response, Xue Jian, consul general of the People's Republic of China in Osaka, wrote a post on the social network The publication was eventually deleted after a diplomatic protest from Japan.
Rising tension
In light of the diplomatic incident, the Government of China started to demand that Sanae Takaichi publicly retract the statements made in the Japanese parliament, which has been refused.
Without Japanese backtracking, China issued a security alert on tourist travel, which was followed by the governments of Macau and Hong Kong. The Interior did not stop at the warning for tourists and forced airline companies to cancel flights to Japan, travel agencies to cancel hotel stays, blocked imports of Japanese seafood again, postponed the entry of Japanese films into the domestic market and issued a warning to students who intend to study in Japan.
The meeting scheduled for today in Macau aimed to promote “exchange and mutual learning” between the three countries and was presented as a selection of the “Cities of Culture in East Asia”, which includes Macau. The Macao SAR Government portal dedicated to the event also stated that the meeting was “seen as a relevant achievement for humanity” and “a mark of cultural cooperation in East Asia”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:54:01</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Government restricts the use of “Western” devices because they represent a “risk”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/lag-governo-restringe-uso-de-aparelhos-ocidentais-por-representarem-um-risco/</link><description>The Government is betting on Chinese electronic devices, to avoid risks associated with equipment coming from countries with a “hostile stance” towards China. Wong Sio Chak revealed that all public servants, including Portuguese, will take an oath of loyalty to China and Macao by the end of the year
The Government revealed on Friday that the Public Administration is giving priority to Chinese electronic devices, because those coming from Western countries “with a hostile stance towards China” represent “a risk”.
“Instructions have already been issued by the DSAFP [Directorate of Administration and Public Function Services], especially for critical infrastructures,” said the Macau Secretary for Administration and Justice. “We considered, as a priority, the use of devices from our country” in RAM’s government services and departments, highlighted Wong Sio Chak.
The leader admitted to the Legislative Assembly that “there is a risk” in the supply of electronic telecommunications devices. “It is a very sensitive issue and one in which there is also a fragility”, said Wong, pointing the finger at “Western countries, especially some with a hostile stance towards China”.
However, the secretary highlighted, during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for 2026 in the area of ​​Administration and Justice, that the limitations only apply to the public administration of Macau. "We have an open market and we will not restrict the private sector to use foreign devices. Entities and the private sector have the freedom to choose these devices", explained Wong.
On October 19, the Central Government accused the United States of carrying out a cyber-attack against the National Time Service Center (NTSC), responsible for maintaining the accuracy of the country's official time.
The Chinese Ministry of State Security said the “systematic and long-planned” attack began in 2022, through a vulnerability in the SMS (short message) service of a “foreign brand” of mobile phones. The vulnerability made it possible to “covertly attack and gain control of the cell phones of several NTSC employees and steal confidential data stored on them”, said the ministry.
Faithful and loyal
Outro dos pontos de destaque da apresentação de Wong Sio Chak prendeu-se com o juramento de lealdade à China e à RAEM que todos os funcionários públicos, incluindo os de nacionalidade portuguesa, terão de prestar até ao fim do ano. O juramento faz parte de uma revisão dos estatutos do pessoal de direcção e chefia e dos trabalhadores da Administração Pública, que entrou em vigor a 1 de Novembro.
The two revised laws determine that workers already in office have 90 days to take the oath, with refusal automatically implying the annulment of the appointment to the position or dismissal. But the secretary for Administration and Justice said he believes the process will be completed sooner and that “all public service workers will take the oath by the end of this year”.
Wong Sio Chak, who took office on October 16, defended during the presentation of the Governing Action Lines for 2026 that the review “improved the management and accountability regime of management and leadership staff”. On November 1st, 264 directors of public entities and services took an oath in a ceremony, declaring that “they will dedicate themselves with all loyalty to the Macau Special Administrative Region [SAR] of the People's Republic of China”.
In a speech given during the ceremony, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, asked civil service leaders to “firmly safeguard the full governance power of the Chinese Central Government”.
In December 2024, the Legislative Assembly approved, unanimously and without any debate, the law that provides that public servants in Macau can be dismissed if they carry out “acts contrary” to their oath. A month earlier, when presenting the proposal, the then Executive Council spokesman, André Cheong, warned that public servants could be fired due to private conversations or comments published on social media.
The oath will be mandatory for all public officials, including Portuguese ones, but it can be taken in Portuguese, one of Macau's two official languages, along with Chinese.
According to the most recent Public Administration Human Resources Report, in 2023 the region had 34,311 public employees. The document does not mention how many have Portuguese nationality, only mentioning that 257 were born in Portugal. The two proposals also oblige public servants to take the oath in a “sincere and solemn” manner. The sincerity of the oath will be assessed by the hierarchical superior and any dismissal may be appealed to the courts.
Every head
The Government wants to launch, at the beginning of 2026, negotiations with Portugal on an agreement for the reciprocal recognition of civil and commercial judgments.
Macau's Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, said that he intends to “strengthen judicial cooperation abroad and further expand legal exchange”.
According to the LAG report, Macau wants, from the first quarter of 2026, to start negotiating an “agreement on the reciprocal confirmation and enforcement of judicial decisions in civil and commercial matters” with Portugal. However, the document does not mention any date for the conclusion of negotiations and the eventual signing of a final agreement.
Macau and Portugal signed an agreement in 2019 regarding the surrender of fugitive offenders, whose criminal legality was called into question by the Portuguese Bar Association. The protocol is not in force, as it was not voted on in the Assembly of the Republic.
The Macau LAG report also reveals plans to conclude, by the end of 2026, three agreements with Angola for the transfer of convicted people, the delivery of fugitive offenders and mutual legal assistance in criminal cases. These three agreements with Angola have been mentioned in the Macau LAG since November 2023, and that report pointed to the end of 2024 as a target for concluding the negotiations.
Angola and mainland China signed an extradition treaty in 2006, which was only approved by the Angolan Parliament in 2011, and was ratified by the Government of Luanda two years later.
During the discussion in the Angolan Parliament, the then Angolan deputy minister of Justice, João Monteiro, defended the importance of the agreement due to the large migratory movement between the two countries. At the time, authorities estimated that close to 50,000 Chinese lived in Angola, working mainly in construction, in reconstruction projects financed largely by loans granted by China.
João Monteiro guaranteed that the two States agreed that extradition requests cannot include crimes of a political or military nature.
Macau Simplex
Wong Sio Chak reiterated to the deputies an old promise from the Administration and Justice department: administrative simplification. The government priority will aim to speed up processes and licenses, for example, for commercial establishments. In response to a question from Deputy Si Ka Lon, the Secretary for Administration and Justice said that, “as long as there are no major works”, a food and beverage establishment can obtain a license to operate in two days, upon presentation of all the required documents. The government official stressed that behind the flexibility of the administration machine are the concepts of “simplifying, decentralizing and optimizing”.
Get to work
The Secretary for Administration and Justice stated in the Legislative Assembly that the Government will continue efforts to implement the quota system for Public Service workers and reorganize some careers, eliminating those that are outdated and promoting mobility. Wong Sio Chak highlighted that since the launch of the quota management system in the Administration, in 2020, the number of public servants has increased, and that before changing the rules for progression or access between careers in the administrative machinery, the Government will listen to workers.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:52:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Security | Japan and the United Kingdom reaffirm cooperation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/seguranca-japao-e-reino-unido-reafirmam-cooperacao/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Japan, Sanae Takaichi, and her British counterpart, Keir Starmer, this Saturday reaffirmed cooperation in security matters on the sidelines of the G20 Leaders' Summit, which ended yesterday in South Africa.
Takaichi and Starmer “agreed to continue to cooperate on security issues” and also “agreed to collaborate closely in the areas of economy and economic security”, said the Japanese Prime Minister's office yesterday, which reported on the results of a meeting between the two leaders in Johannesburg the day before.
In the first meeting between Takaichi and his British counterpart since the governor took office last month, both leaders also reaffirmed their intention to work “closely” with the United States for a “free and open” Indo-Pacific.
The statements come in the context of strong diplomatic tension between Tokyo and Beijing, since Takaichi stated in the Japanese Parliament that a military attack by China against Taiwan could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (Army) (see page 12).
Beijing responded with harsh reprimands and economic reprisals, while demanding that Takaichi recant and advising its citizens not to travel to Japan, which led to hundreds of flight suspensions.
Takaichi refused on Friday to retract his statements regarding Taiwan and maintained that this is the Japanese government's “consistent position”. At the same time, the minister reiterated her desire to maintain beneficial relations with China and launched a new call for dialogue.
Tokyo expressed its availability for a meeting between Takaichi and Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang at the G20 bilateral meetings, as China had said last Monday that there is no planned meeting between the two leaders during the summit.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:48:48</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Miguel de Senna Fernandes calls for more focus on Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/lag-miguel-de-senna-fernandes-pede-mais-foco-em-macau/</link><description>The president of the Association of Macanese, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, defended the importance of regional integration, but highlighted that Macau is going through a “delicate” moment and needs more attention from the Government. Senna Fernandes' position was taken in statements to Canal Macau.
"Macau is integrated into the Greater Bay Area, nothing other than improvements are expected to accelerate the development of the Greater Bay Area. But, we cannot forget that we are in Macau. This is fundamental", began by saying the president of the association, regarding the Lines and Governing Action. “There is no citizen, no matter how noble, no matter how much he defends the Government, no matter how much he applauds the Government in this policy and Macau's contribution to development, there is no citizen who does not have Macau as a priority”, he added.
In a context in which the recovery of tourism covers society in an unequal way, Miguel de Senna Fernandes asked for more attention to Macau, because it is going through a complicated period: “Despite the economic recovery numbers, we cannot forget that there is still a group of citizens to whom this does not reach”, he stressed.
"We need to say the measures, and I'm not saying long-term, but medium-term, to improve the conditions, the future prospects of this layer of workers, of professionals in Macau. Don't just feed the dream of Hengqin, for example. There are people who like to stay in Macau and for them Macau is always the future", he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:01:36</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Request for greater coverage of anti-scam program</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/pj-pedida-maior-cobertura-de-programa-anti-burlas/</link><description>Deputy Chan Lai Kei questioned the Government about the need to reinforce and increase the coverage of the Judiciary Police (PJ) anti-fraud program, taking into account the frequent cases of fraud that occur associated with fake employees of the Taobao platform.
Therefore, the deputy, with connections to the Fujian community, questioned whether analyzes using artificial intelligence (AI) could be introduced in this program so that alerts could be given to users whenever they find messages with a high risk of fraud. Furthermore, the deputy recalled that there is a face swap technique using AI, which leads elderly people to easily become victims of fraud, which is why he hopes that the PJ will use this anti-fraud program to publicize these types of cases to groups of potential victims of fraud.
In the same question, the deputy also asks how the Government will reinforce cooperation with neighboring regions regarding the sharing of cross-border data, in order to track the origin and flow of capital involved in fraud.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:25:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Barra Slow Festival | Coffee and culture in Naval Workshops</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/barra-slow-festival-cafe-e-cultura-nas-oficinas-navais/</link><description>It's called “Barra Slow Festival” and the first edition is scheduled for next weekend, between the 28th and 30th of November, with the aim of revitalizing the Barra area with activities linked to coffee culture, design and crafts. The public will be able to enjoy events at Naval Workshops nº 1 and nº2, as well as in the square located in the area
This weekend, namely between Friday and Sunday, the first edition of the “Barra Slow Festival 2025” is taking place in Macau, an event that brings various activities linked to coffee, culture and art and aims to attract public attention to the Barra area, known for tourist sites such as the A-Má Temple.
According to an official statement from the event, this is a debut in the territory of events such as “To Play Market × Tokyo Coffee Festival · Macau 2025” and the “Shanghai UNFOLD Art and Design Fair”, as well as initiatives such as “Coffee Rave”, “Macau Chill Collective” and an exhibition by well-known graphic designer Florian Lamm. All these events will be spread across the square in the Barra area and Oficinas Navais nº 1 and nº2, where cultural events usually take place.
According to the same note, the “Barra Slow Festival” integrates “popular contemporary elements, such as coffee culture, creative design, visual exhibitions, limited artisanal products and music”, being a “cultural event with selected concepts”.
The idea of ​​an event in which there is “human warmth” is defended, encouraging the public “to relax and live intensely, recovering the tranquility inherent to life”. In this way, “the Barra neighborhood was chosen [for this initiative], with tents set up inside and outside the historic buildings of the Naval Workshops”.
It is therefore hoped that the general public “can enjoy a cup of coffee, stroll around the area and experience the historical depth of the Barra neighborhood”.
From the outside to the inside
Above all, the “Barra Slow Festival” brings to Macau events already known in Asia, such as the “Tokyo Coffee Festival”, organized by “To Play Market” and which brings together almost 50 famous coffee brands from Japan, the Greater Bay Area and Macau.
“Just a few months ago, the Tokyo Coffee Festival made its debut in Hong Kong, attracting more than 30,000 participants, and both its artisanal coffee and coffee products were highly praised,” highlights the organization. At this premiere in Macau there will be special products for sale and limited editions.
Another highlight of the lineup is the “UNFOLD” Art and Design Fair, organized in Shanghai by Shanghai BANANAFISH. This is an event with the curatorial concept of “unfold, read and present”, being a “communication platform that brings together lovers of culture and art, designers, creative workers and professionals from the creative industry”.
What you can see in Barra, with “UNFOLD”, is a market with 100 stands of brands and design products from around the world, with “creative selections and limited artisanal products”, and ticket holders can also visit the special exhibition by designer Florian Lamm.
Florian's works were selected for the Top 100 Posters in Germany, Austria and Switzerland, and won the Artist Award at the Brno Biennale, the oldest graphic design exhibition in the world.
The “Macau Chill Collective” aims to “bring together the strength of local brands”, inviting “dozens of brands, from well-known cafe owners, creative artisans and creators”. During the festival, the exhibition “Ancient Memories: Impressions of the Shipyard – Historical Photographic Exhibition of the Barra District” will also be held in order to “deepen participants’ understanding of the history of the district”.
The “Barra Slow Festival” has free entry and takes place between 12pm and 8pm. It is necessary to purchase tickets for the UNFOLD Art and Design Fair, with a cost of 55 patacas for pre-sale and 78 patacas on the event days. There are also tickets for sale for some events related to coffee culture. Tickets have been on sale since November 2nd on the MacauTicket, Damai and Ctrip platforms. The event is organized by the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau, Central and Southern District, co-organized by BANANAFISH and TOPYS, and supported by the Institute of Economic and Technological Development, the Macau Tourism Board, the General Union of Neighborhood Associations of Macau and other sponsoring entities.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:29:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Coloane | “Connections Music.Movement.Nature” this weekend at Urban Farm</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/coloane-connections-music-movement-nature-este-fim-de-semana-na-urban-farm/</link><description>After being postponed due to super typhoon Ragasa, the “Connections – Music.Movement.Nature” festival takes place this weekend in the town of Coloane. Live music, crafts, workshops, dance and various types of activities for families will mark two days of communion at the Urban Farm space
“Connections – Music.Movement.Nature” is the result of a community impulse of belonging and sharing of a family bigger than blood and genes, born in the antipodes of a city immersed in materialism and commercialism of the concerts of various types of regional pop that form part of the city's cultural agenda. After two editions in 2018 and 2019, and the postponement due to super typhoon Ragasa, the festival is back this weekend, this time at the Urban Farm space in the town of Coloane.
Built by the community, for the community, this year's “Connections” has a lineup filled with 30 workshops from the most varied areas, 20 DJ performances and performances by Beto Ritchie, Lobo and Náv, an area for food, drinks and crafts by local creators and multiple activities for families.
“Those responsible, who see themselves as ‘a collective creation that combines a conscious way of life with unique experiences’, intend through this initiative to provide ‘Family Activities, Lectures and Workshops, Exploration of Well-Being and Artistic Expression’”, indicates the organization in a statement.
After the events held in 2018 and 2019 in the Ká-Hó Dam area, this year the party moves to a new, larger space, which will allow various activities to take place spread across seven different areas: the “Village”, a picturesque area that resembles a traditional Chinese village, with wooden houses in an oriental garden, will be the area for meals and drinks and the sale of handicrafts. Larry’s Place, Concept H, Lotus Cocktails, Cakes By Rose &amp; Muse, Juk and Happy Stand are responsible for the food and drinks.
In the “Village” there will be 10 stands selling crafts from local creators (Dreama, Cordelia Handmade, Zarja’s Selections, CeraGigi, Dollfie, Wickd Candle Studio, White Lodge Dreamland, Love and Light Handmade Studio, Gems Awakening, Free Spirit Home and the Rui Carreiro Barbeiro stand.
Inhale, exhale
Next door, the “Gypsy Camp”, an area with cushions and resting places, will allow musical exploration with musical instruments such as the asalato, participating in a drum circle, a singing workshop, or attending a handpan concert with the duo Nàv, who curates the area. Nearby, in a Mongolian tent (yurte), there will be a lecture on spiritual themes and individual tarot and soul reading sessions.
Activities for families will take place in the “Family Tent”, offering Meditation for Families sessions, Mandala Dot Painting, Crochet, Circles of Life Painting and Construction of Animal Masks on cardboard.
In the “family tent” Associação Sílaba will provide moments of interactive reading, the launch of “CaixaPiz” and activities for the little ones.
Taking your feet off the ground, the “Treetop” area, a mezzanine built in the top of a tree, was chosen for all body exploration activities and more serene moments of meditation and relaxation. With activities taking place from morning to dusk, the “Treetop” will also host Brazilian Dance and Conscious Dance sessions, as well as Yoga, Gyrokinesis and CoreNature, a fusion of Pilates and Animal Flow. Sound Bath sessions and meditations at sunset and connection to nature are also planned.
Enchanted forest
At the bottom of the Urban Farm property, in the “Concrete” area, graffiti and urban art sessions are scheduled with the collective of local artists Outloud International Street Art Festival.
Finally, in “Woods”, in a clearing in a small forest, there is an open-air electronic music and dance space, which will feature performances by several local and regional DJs. The musical offering will also be present in the “Village” area, with a more organic, lounge selection, focused on world music, as well as a live performance by Beto Ritchie tomorrow at 3pm and Lobo on Sunday at 6pm.
Participants are advised to bring warm clothing, insect repellent, hats, sunscreen, towel, flashlight and portable ashtray. The event organizers announced on social media that entrance donations, which are still on sale, cost between 180 and 280 patacas for tickets for one or both days of the event, and at the door they will cost between 200 and 300 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:28:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Vietnam | At least 90 dead in one week due to torrential rain</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/vietname-pelo-menos-90-mortos-numa-semana-devido-a-chuvas-torrenciais/</link><description>The death toll in Vietnam in a week of torrential rains affecting the country rose to 90 yesterday, compared to 55 fatalities recorded the day before, while 12 people remain missing, authorities reported.
Floods and landslides caused by intense and prolonged rains are affecting provinces in the center and south of the country, with Dak Lak and Khanh Hoa being the hardest hit, with around fifty deaths, according to data released by the Vietnamese Ministry of Agriculture and Environment.
After days of isolation, authorities managed to distribute aid – food, supplies and clothing, among others – in the most affected and remote areas of Dak Lak, which remained without electricity, telephone signal or drinking water for days and whose inhabitants continue to use canoes, boats and surfboards to travel, official media reports.
Images published by the Vietnamese press show houses completely submerged, as well as streets with water accumulated at the height of citizens' waists. The Prime Minister of Vietnam, Pham Minh Chinh, met via videoconference with the governments of several of the affected provinces from South Africa, where he is participating as a guest at the G20 Leaders' Summit, which ended yesterday in Johannesburg.
The damage caused by the storm is estimated at around nine billion dongs (around 297 million euros), according to official assessments. The Vietnamese government will distribute 1.1 billion dongs (around 36.3 million euros) in support for the recovery of the provinces of Khanh Hoa, Dak Lak, Lam Dong and Gia Lai.
Although the rains have eased since Friday, precipitation persists in several parts of the southern half of Vietnam, indicates the Zoom.earth platform, while search and rescue work continues.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:47:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate | Quarterly price increase by 7.7 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/imobiliario-aumento-trimestral-dos-precos-em-77-por-cento/</link><description>Data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC) shows that average house prices, per square meter of useful area, increased by 7.7 percent in the third quarter of this year compared to the previous one. In the Macau peninsula alone this increase was 12.6 percent, recording an average price of 74,590 patacas, “mainly due to new housing complexes being put up for sale in the reference quarter”, highlights DSEC.
On the islands, the 4 percent increase in Coloane stands out, with the average price of autonomous housing units standing at 87,093 patacas, while in Taipa prices fell 4.6 percent, to around 70,110 patacas. The average price of autonomous housing units in constructed buildings stood at MOP65,897, down 3.2 percent quarter-on-quarter.
DSEC also reveals that in the third quarter of this year, based on the stamp tax charged, 1,411 autonomous units and parking spaces were transacted for a value of 6.26 billion patacas. The average price per square meter of useful area of ​​autonomous housing units, in global terms, stood at 74,190 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:22:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhuangzi, in the 4th century BC. C., understood time as a continuum in transformation that should not be contradicted but rather enjoyed in a “happy loitering”, xiaoyao you, flowing with it and to prove this he never stopped observing the mutations in the world of nature.
The literate fans of the brush arts who read him did not fail to witness this incessant gaze. In the Ming dynasty, for example, one of the ways of expressing this attitude, calling on the viewer's involvement, can be seen in paintings such as the ingenious scroll of the Four Seasons (Sishi shanshui, horizontal scroll, ink and color on silk, 35.1 x 569.9 cm, by unknown author, at the Metmuseum) in which when rolled out from right to left, the painting successively reveals recognizable scenes that distinguish the seasons.
The Japanese painter Sesshu Toyo (1420-1506), who spent two years learning about Ming dynasty painting, interpreted the theme of the changing seasons more than once and admirably in four vertical scrolls (ink and color on silk, 149.5 x 75.6 cm, at the Tokyo National Museum).
Painted in the refined style then much admired by the masters of the ancient Song dynasty, Ma Yuan and Xia Gui, everything about them has the flavor of nostalgia. In the first, Primavera for example, shows the recognizable figure of a poet sitting backwards on a mule as he leaves a friend's house. Since the beginning of the dynasty, painters treated the grandeur of the landscape, accentuating what is particular to each season of the year, reviving this style called «Ma-Xia school».
Others, at that time, displayed the passage of the seasons in a different way, focusing on meticulous figures of animals and plants that are the distinct material of each season. A member of a family of painters linked to the court, of whom few paintings are known today, in one of them expressively depicted Spring, when perhaps a new beginning is most felt.
Yin Hong (c.1430-c.1500) in the large vertical scroll Encounter of Birds Under a Willow Tree in Spring (Chunliu juqi, ink and color on silk, 240 x 195.5 cm. at the Cleveland Museum of Art) shows, in detail, on the bank of a river under a willow tree and around a large gongshi, "stone of literati", a variety of flowers and birds, where they stand out for their size and exuberance a couple of peacocks. The peahen, in front, appears to be pushing a pugong ying dandelion, a sign of determination and good luck, just as the willow is of new beginnings, rebirth and fertility. And with the abundant water in the river, they are all appropriate figures to represent Spring.
Anyone who knew how to interpret the scene could let themselves be lulled and, flowing, say like the poet Zhu Yunming (1461-1527): «If there are flowers and there is wine to celebrate, singing,/ How good it is to be a writer and inhabit the precious abundance of time!»</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Japan, Sanae Takaichi, and her British counterpart, Keir Starmer, this Saturday reaffirmed cooperation in security matters on the sidelines of the G20 Leaders' Summit, which ended yesterday in South Africa.
Takaichi and Starmer “agreed to continue to cooperate on security issues” and also “agreed to collaborate closely in the areas of economy and economic security”, said the Japanese Prime Minister's office yesterday, which reported on the results of a meeting between the two leaders in Johannesburg the day before.
In the first meeting between Takaichi and his British counterpart since the governor took office last month, both leaders also reaffirmed their intention to work “closely” with the United States for a “free and open” Indo-Pacific.
The statements come in the context of strong diplomatic tension between Tokyo and Beijing, since Takaichi stated in the Japanese Parliament that a military attack by China against Taiwan could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (Army) (see page 12).
Beijing responded with harsh reprimands and economic reprisals, while demanding that Takaichi recant and advising its citizens not to travel to Japan, which led to hundreds of flight suspensions.
Takaichi refused on Friday to retract his statements regarding Taiwan and maintained that this is the Japanese government's “consistent position”. At the same time, the minister reiterated her desire to maintain beneficial relations with China and launched a new call for dialogue.
Tokyo expressed its availability for a meeting between Takaichi and Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang at the G20 bilateral meetings, as China had said last Monday that there is no planned meeting between the two leaders during the summit.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>José Simões Morais</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/jose-sm/</link><description>In Macau, most commercial establishments have the image of Kuan Tai (Guan Di in Mandarin), who appears with a strong body, red face, long black beard and dressed as a military officer, holding a spear in his right hand.
As a person, he is known as Guan Yu and is related to the fall of the Han dynasty and the struggles to establish the Shu kingdom, in the period that preceded the Three Kingdoms. With the name Chang Sheng (长生), he was born in Xiezhou (today Yuncheng, Shanxi province), on the 24th day of the sixth lunar month in the 60s of the 2nd century.
As an episode from his youth, it is said that one day a nobleman forcibly wanted to possess a girl and Guan Yu, outraged, killed him. Pursued by the authorities, he had to flee and according to legend, in order not to be recognized, Guanyin (known in Macau as Kun Iam) changed the color of his face to red.
Another story says that a rural owner with a lot of power, in order to force everyone to buy water from him, polluted the other sources in the region. Saturated with such infamy, Guan Yu one day killed him and had to flee the city. During this flight, to cross the border (guan), he took the name Guan Yu.
In the late Eastern Han dynasty (25-220), the decadent court in Luoyang was dominated by eunuchs and generals. Guan Yu was wandering as a street vendor in Zhuo Municipality (now Hebei Province) when he met Liu Bei and Zhang Fei. The three swore an oath in the Peach Garden to become brothers in arms, with Guan Yu and Zhang Fei vowing to help Liu Bei, linked to the royal house of Han, in his armed uprising to establish the Shu-Han kingdom.
At that time there were two other different factions that divided the country and thus in the North, the Wei army led by Cao Cao dominated, in the East and South the Wu forces and in the West, the Shu. There were constant battles between them.
Guan Yu, an avid reader of the Classic “Spring-Autumn Annals” (Chunqiu jing) who always accompanied him, had commanded the Shu garrison in Jingzhou for 10 years. In the year 219/220, while engaged in a battle outside the wall against the Wei forces, he was caught in a surprise attack by the Wu army, which was more or less allied with the Shu. The Wu conquered the city and killed Guan Yu, cutting off his head and, as a proof of friendship, handing it over to Cao Cao. Halfway there they learned that the Wei had made a peace agreement with the Shu and so the head was abandoned near Luoyang.
The process of his deification was long. Although he was only God of War during the Ming period, when in 1578 Emperor Wan Li gave him the title of Emperor Guan (Guan Di), already in the Sui dynasty he had a temple dedicated to him in the place where he was buried, with the titles being given by all the following dynasties.
During his life, Guan Yu had the position of Military Officer (Hou). In the Song dynasty he took the place of King (Wang). Due to his loyalty, honesty, piety, benevolence, sense of justice and courage, he became very popular due to the book San Guo Yan Yi, written at the beginning of the Ming dynasty. In this dynasty he was promoted to Emperor (Di) and then, in 1614, to Sage (Sheng) or Military Saint (Wu Di). As a Being so perfect, all professions want him as their patron and thus he is venerated as the God of War, Literature, Wealth and patron of Martial Arts.
In Macau, Guan Di is known as Kuan Tai and the Sam Kai Wui Kun temple, located on Rua Sul of the S. Domingos market, is dedicated to him. There, the image of the God is entirely golden, with no objects in his hands and is accompanied on his left by Chau Chong and on the other side by Kuan Peng. His birthday falls on the 24th of the sixth lunar month, although no festivities are officially held in his honor.
灶神 Zao Shen – the god of the Stove
The god of the Stove, known in Macau as Tchôu-Sân (in Mandarin Zao Shen), is the most important of the domestic deities and twice a month (during the New Moon and the Full Moon) he received offerings, despite his birthday only being celebrated on the third day of the eighth Moon. However, the most important ceremonies performed to this god are those that occur before the week-long journey, when the god leaves home and goes to Heaven to perform the annual report to the Jade Emperor about the family of the residence where he is placed. And that is why this god, also known as the god of the Kitchen, as for simplification he came to be called the god of the Kitchen Chimney, has great power over the lives of the people who form the household. It is in the last week of the lunar year that he ascends to Heaven to meet with the Jade Emperor, where he reports to him the events that took place in the room in his charge, returning on the first day of the year, where he is placed again in the kitchen, behind the stove.
On the eve of the trip, on the twenty-third day of the last lunar month, the inhabitants of the house offer sacrifices to this deity, filling him with sweets so that he only tells good things to the Jade Emperor.
In a ceremony performed only by men, the god of Stove leaves transported on a horse and to make the journey easy and pleasant, one of the male beings in the house takes a candle and burns the image of the god so that it can more easily ascend through smoke to Heaven.
Before being named by the Jade Emperor as God of the Stove, or of the Kitchen, he was a husband who, having spent all his money gambling and selling his wife, years later, while begging on the streets, arrived at his former wife's house. She, recognizing him and taking pity on him, takes him to the kitchen where she gives him something to eat. But her current husband arrives and so she doesn't see him, she hides him in the fireplace. When the maid lights the fire, so as not to compromise the charitable woman, she stays there. The Jade Emperor, seeing his sacrifice, named him the god of the Stove, also known as the god of the Kitchen, or the god of the Home.
There are other versions of both how the man lost the money and how his ex-wife supported him. She, without being recognized by her ex-husband, gave him some cakes and placed a coin in each one. The man, on the way, met another beggar, who, upon seeing the bag with cakes, asked him for one. He discovered the coin in the middle of the cake and, realizing that the other didn't know about the filling, proposed keeping them all, which he managed in exchange for a small amount. When he later found out what he had done, realizing his bad luck, he decided to commit suicide. The Jade Emperor, seeing his kindness, named him god of the Kitchen.
The celebration of this deity's journey to Heaven began in summer, but during the Han dynasty it moved to winter and during the Ming dynasty it was celebrated by the people on the 24th, with sacrifices taking place the day before. Zao Shen is represented in an image containing only his figure, or associated with his consort, or even just characters, which is placed on the first day of the lunar year in the kitchen behind the stove.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhuangzi, in the 4th century BC. C., understood time as a continuum in transformation that should not be contradicted but rather enjoyed in a “happy loitering”, xiaoyao you, flowing with it and to prove this he never stopped observing the mutations in the world of nature.
The literate fans of the brush arts who read him did not fail to witness this incessant gaze. In the Ming dynasty, for example, one of the ways of expressing this attitude, calling on the viewer's involvement, can be seen in paintings such as the ingenious scroll of the Four Seasons (Sishi shanshui, horizontal scroll, ink and color on silk, 35.1 x 569.9 cm, by unknown author, at the Metmuseum) in which when rolled out from right to left, the painting successively reveals recognizable scenes that distinguish the seasons.
The Japanese painter Sesshu Toyo (1420-1506), who spent two years learning about Ming dynasty painting, interpreted the theme of the changing seasons more than once and admirably in four vertical scrolls (ink and color on silk, 149.5 x 75.6 cm, at the Tokyo National Museum).
Painted in the refined style then much admired by the masters of the ancient Song dynasty, Ma Yuan and Xia Gui, everything about them has the flavor of nostalgia. In the first, Primavera for example, shows the recognizable figure of a poet sitting backwards on a mule as he leaves a friend's house. Since the beginning of the dynasty, painters treated the grandeur of the landscape, accentuating what is particular to each season of the year, reviving this style called «Ma-Xia school».
Others, at that time, displayed the passage of the seasons in a different way, focusing on meticulous figures of animals and plants that are the distinct material of each season. A member of a family of painters linked to the court, of whom few paintings are known today, in one of them expressively depicted Spring, when perhaps a new beginning is most felt.
Yin Hong (c.1430-c.1500) in the large vertical scroll Encounter of Birds Under a Willow Tree in Spring (Chunliu juqi, ink and color on silk, 240 x 195.5 cm. at the Cleveland Museum of Art) shows, in detail, on the bank of a river under a willow tree and around a large gongshi, "stone of literati", a variety of flowers and birds, where they stand out for their size and exuberance a couple of peacocks. The peahen, in front, appears to be pushing a pugong ying dandelion, a sign of determination and good luck, just as the willow is of new beginnings, rebirth and fertility. And with the abundant water in the river, they are all appropriate figures to represent Spring.
Anyone who knew how to interpret the scene could let themselves be lulled and, flowing, say like the poet Zhu Yunming (1461-1527): «If there are flowers and there is wine to celebrate, singing,/ How good it is to be a writer and inhabit the precious abundance of time!»</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Ana Cristina Alves</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Por Ana Cristina Alves – Investigadora Auxiliar e Coordenadora do Serviço Educativo do Centro Científico e Cultural
The image that the Portuguese have of themselves as a whole collective differs internally and externally, according to the thinkers and their ways of being in life, which in turn depend on broader cultural frameworks, their own collectivities. It is not expected that a Frenchman's view of the Portuguese and Portugal will be similar to that of a Chinese person, much less that of a Portuguese person, because their perspectives are conditioned by their historical-cultural development, which will define a specific civilizational stance for each thinker and their personal and collective life history. Furthermore, a foreigner's view of Portugal will always be more distant, for better or for worse, than a Portuguese person's close and committed view to the deepest roots of his being, even if he seeks to be as impartial as possible, as is the case of Miguel Torga, a writer and thinker who loved his country very much, but always in the middle, without letting himself be carried away by romantic and nationalist feelings, for example of Teixeira de Pascoes in The Art of Being Portuguese.
Start with external views, those that reach us from beyond the Portuguese sea. Start with the very recent text Astérix na Lusitânia from October 2025 by Fabcaro with drawings by Didier Conrad, impeccably translated into Portuguese by Maria José Pereira and Paula Caetano.
The compatriots, the “pá” people, who oscillate in the book between slang and the lyrical features of Portuguese fado, in the best that Amália has to offer, are presented in a critical and ironic way, sometimes scathing, in a tone coming from the French comic and rationalist school, which says what it thinks, because that is how it exists without worrying about the consequences that its open, frontal and critical thinking may have on the Portuguese people who will read these lines in band. drawn, many of them truly comical, but which certainly reach the emotional and nervous chords of the great heroes of the Lusitanian sea.
Those in a better mood will take advantage of the pretext to laugh at themselves, while the more serious and sullen will have some difficulty digesting the comic strip, whose main feature is playing around the Portuguese sea, but gastronomically. The Portuguese stand out in the work for their taste for fish and fish sauces, being monotonously excellent in the thousand and one ways of preparing cod, which leads, obviously, to the despair of the illustrious Gallic Obélix, who finds himself surrounded by cod and fish sauce (garum) everywhere. Astérix and Obélix come on a mission to Portugal to help free Malmevês, a Portuguese man sentenced to prison for allegedly trying to poison Caesar with garum. They were called by a Portuguese character, whose name is highly revealing, Tristês. Meanwhile, Malmevês has a daughter, with another symptomatic name, Saudade, with whom Obeléx falls in love.
The Lusitanians are left with sadness, longing and melancholy and are not indebted to their beauty, and it is with great regret that the Gauls will have to disguise themselves as Lusitanians to save Malmevês from prison, with the successful mission aided by Gallic intelligence that unmasks the real poisoner and his accomplice.
Although the Portuguese are not presented as beautiful, intelligent, and some have little ethics, because they betrayed the hero of heroes, Viriato, their most positive aspects include interesting cuisine, with the exception of cod and fish sauce, but which includes pastel de nata and good wine, even green wine. Cuisine is undoubtedly the highlight of the narrative, from all perspectives, even that of the Discoveries, which are reduced and condensed in a reference to Vasco da Gama's Tasco “Oh Man, in Vasco da Gama's Tasco you discover new worlds” (Fabcaro, 2025, 36).
The fact that the Portuguese love fado so much makes the atmosphere very sad for Gallic ears, who weave interesting philosophical considerations throughout the text about it, as it is considered to take away soul strength from Portuguese soldiers and people, who in the heat of the battle are appeased by the doleful and sad song that makes the warriors like this: “I suddenly became so melancholic” (Fabcaro, 2025, 28) or “after all, what do we spend our lives chasing after?” (Ibidem). In short, from this comic we take a look at our collective portrait, a sad and melancholic people, very marked by long years of repression, in which the revolutionaries find themselves in jail, like the one who shouts from behind bars "oh man, listen carefully, damned Romans! The united people will never be defeated." (Fabcaro, 2025, 33).
Distinguem-se na Lusitânia umas verdadeiras mulheres de armas como a Gama, quando se diz, “seria impossível levar a missão a bom porto sem a ajuda da Gama” ( Fabcaro, 2025, 47). Por fim, os heróis gauleses partem rumo à Gália, retendo uma outra característica que costuma ser realçada em relação aos portugueses, a suavidade no relacionamento: “Ah estes lusitanos! São tão afáveis no trato…custa ter de partir, não é?” (Fabcaro, 2025, 48).
Não se pode generalizar a imagem filosófica cómica desta banda desenhada a todos os franceses, mas o que fica para alguns é que a ilustre e antiga história portuguesa se resume bem a um notável heroísmo gastronómico, representado por uma mulher forte, a Gama, à frente do Tasco Vasco da Gama e enquanto ela estiver ao leme novos mundos de sabor serão sempre descobertos. Do ponto de vista gaulês é dispensável tanta melancolia e tristeza, mas salva-se no meio deste “estranho modo de ser” a afabilidade que deixa saudades da terra e vontade de regressar.
Due to the characteristics of the Chinese mentality, shaped by centuries of Confucian harmony, one cannot expect the same type of open, free, critical record from a Chinese thinker. On the contrary, the descriptions will be carefully chosen so as not to offend other people's sensibilities, as is the case in the work of the thinker and historian Wu Zhiliang (吴志良), Crónicas de Portugal 葡萄牙印象, the result of the author's stay as a student at the country in 1991. Therefore, and recalling an idea with which the article opened, the reflections of a thinker or creative are conditioned by their own way of seeing that is inserted and rooted in their culture.
For Wu Zhiliang, the Portuguese are still the descendants of the sea heroes who arrived in China and Macau, fearlessly crossing the Atlantic, Indian and Pacific oceans and, in our days, they are the great drivers of the cultural dialogue of the 16th century, providing a meeting of cultures that was extremely beneficial for the Chinese, because it opened them to other worlds, awakening them to a way that is complementary to the Chinese, which he describes as submissive and peaceful. What is most valued in the introduction and conclusion of the successive portraits of Portugal provided by these Chronicles are the new characteristics that the Chinese and other Eastern peoples are confronted with in their relationship with the Portuguese, above all, the active, restless and restless spirit, which crossed "the magic of Allah with the Indian Bodhisattvas, the Chinese Tao and Japanese meditation with the totally restless spirit of the West. At the source of the discovering, spiritualized and empty force, East and the West converge into one in this humble and silent “void”, the root of all things that transforms into an immense and infinite freedom.騷動的精神，來發現力的本源，在那裡，神意味着虛無。在這力的源泉中，東西方交融在一處，我們在“無”這個萬物之本的謙卑和寂寞中，變得無比自由。》(Wu, 1991,1/ 2).
Wu Zhiliang emphasizes throughout the work and, also in the final notes, that the various meetings, including academic ones, provided by institutions in the territory of Macau are an invaluable contribution to friendship and cultural dialogue, this being the correct perspective from the author's point of view to evaluate the role of the Portuguese in the world, which in contemporary times still goes back to its great historical past, much like what happens to Portuguese thinkers and writers, even the most impartial, as is the case of Miguel Torga (1907-1995).
This writer born in São Martinho de Anta, a doctor by profession, knows his people well, their joys and sadness, riches, miseries and overcoming. In a very well-executed portrait of the country in Salazar times, Portugal writes, the first edition of which dates back to Coimbra in 1950, assuming very clear perspectives in relation to the Portuguese historical past at home and beyond its borders. Behind the borders dominates the maritime, versatile, cosmopolitan and adventurous capital of Lisbon against the telluric city of Porto, realistic and focused on its roots. Throughout the work, he weaves timely and incisive considerations about the Portuguese mentality, which lead to an image that today perhaps resonates with adventurous people in the character of the soap opera Senhor Ventura, a work dated 1991. This one takes us to China.
Returning to Portugal, the author debuts the work in Minho where he makes considerations about the way in which the impoverished Portuguese relate to the life of the sea and emigration: "From time to time he may have a fit of rage and try to escape from himself. A hopeless illusion. Where he arrives will always be him, dying of homesickness and dreaming of returning to the adventure with a small reform. As a balm, he will be left with the narcissism of his exploits past experiences and the somatic satisfaction of seeing the worlds he discovered and civilized grow and progress.” (Torga, 2003, 17). Many were emigrants from the old regime who left just like today: the difference is that today they are much better prepared and educated. The Portuguese who emigrate are, for the most part, qualified professionals holding various degrees and national diplomas, boasting solid training and a desire for the rest of the world.
But if people have evolved in social terms, their mentality has not changed that much in terms of the way they relate to their historical past, nor in the taste for risk and adventure that drives them out of the country. The hope will always be that of a better life, although the steps to achieve it are not always well measured. When the author describes Trás-os-Montes, his birthplace, he tells us about the emigrants "Haunted by necessity and the love of adventure, at the age of twenty (if it was not earlier), after militancy, some emigrate to the Arabian overseas. Brazil, Africa and Oceania, they put the whole chimera in a bag of scraps and off they go" (Torga, 2003, 50).
This is a trait of the Portuguese mentality that has remained in a constant regime since the Discoveries, the desire and need to leave not only due to lack of opportunities, but also due to the thirst for adventure, as well as the naturalness of miscegenation, which can be seen in the capital of Portugal since the times of “Dona Filipa de Lencastre giving birth on behalf of the Portuguese herd from abroad” (Torga, 2003, 77), or even further, since the very foundation of the land. derived from the energy of a son of a French father and a Spanish mother.
However, the greatest danger for Portugal and the community as a whole is, according to Torga's perspective, wasting the soul strength of the Portuguese and their characteristics on inconsequential adventures that can contribute nothing to their individual life projects and/or the common good, but which we narcissistically insist on reliving. He tells us about Lisbon "Narcissus that we were also one day, a destiny like that of Cephisus's son awaited us. Lisbon is that flower that destiny transformed us into; the Tagus, the river where we lost ourselves contemplating our own image" (Torga, 2003, 136).
It is precisely this mix of pride, vanity and initiative that the work O Senhor Ventura shows. The protagonist is a man from Penedono, in Alentejo, but with multiple resources and capable of taking on any work. With a powerful and bullish constitution, after an adventurous experience of military service that led him to Macau and a short romance with Júlia, the daughter of the Governor's secretary, he deserted the army and joined the world as a sailor aboard a ship doing cabotage in the China Sea. From there he became an employee in a Ford garage in Beijing, where he befriended Pereira, a man from Minho who cooked very well, and he was his companion on adventures until his death. However, Ventura falls into the good graces of Ford's boss, Mr. Hughes, for being “a man of pulse and initiative” (Torga, 2003, 26). In life, he did a bit of everything, trafficking drugs and weapons, being a pirate, kidnapping, driving 200 trucks to Mongolia and, to his misfortune, he fell in love with a Russian woman with an unrecommended life, Tatiana. Although warned, even by himself, because the couple got along very badly, he wanted to marry her, with whom he had a son, Sérgio. It was then that he decided to get rich by getting involved in drug trafficking, more specifically heroin. This new branch of activity went badly for him, he was discovered by the Chinese authorities and he had to return to Portugal, leaving his son in the care of his wife, who betrayed him as soon as she turned her back. He returned to Alentejo within a period of 5 years so that the Chinese authorities would forget about the matter.
Anyway, he was in Portugal and returned to China when he discovered that his wife had cheated on him. He looked for her everywhere until, already dying, she was the one who found him to close his eyes on his deathbed. The word that best characterizes Mr. Ventura is, according to the author, “Action – was his great word.” (Torga, 2003,64).
The writer is careful to warn about this story: “at each stop I do nothing more than try a small meditation on destiny, which is more collective than individual” (Torga, 2003, 70), adding that the fact that the Alentejo native is returning to the land is an imperative call from destiny, to put him back in touch with his roots, in a new opportunity for life. The protagonist rejects the chance, due to the obsession he felt with his Russian passion and which will lead him to death, ending the author with the following reflection: “Strange hands buried the poor adventurer's withered body the next day in the foreign land where he had to pay the price for his adventures.” (Torga, 2003, 100).
Of the two foreign and most distant images from the Portuguese, one critical and playful by the hands of the French artist Fabrice Caro (Fabcaro), another uplifting and very positive transmitted by the Chinese thinker, Wu Zhiliang, to which is added a third, more realistic and closer transmitted by the Portuguese writer, it cannot be concluded that there is just one true one. The collective portrait can only be obtained together and in a kind of Nietzschean perspectivism from the essential traits of the contemporary Portuguese mentality, shaped, as the French artist saw well, by centuries of erasure, but also by the awareness of the glorious exploits of an intercultural past that continues to the present, according to Wu Zhiliang, or even by the thirst for action and adventure which, when not properly structured and rooted in solid individual and collective plans, can lead to a inopportune dead end.
Bibliographic References
Fabcaro, 2025. Asterix in Lusitânia. Translated by Maria José Pereira and Paula Caetano. Drawings by Didier Conrad. Color by Thierry Mébarki. Alfragide: Asa Editions.
Torga, Miguel. 2003. Portugal. Lisbon: Heirs of Miguel Torga José Manuel Rodrigues and Publicações Dom Quixote.
Torga, Miguel. 1991. Senhor Ventura. Coimbra: Circle of Readers
Wu Zhiliang (吴志良). 1991. Chronicles of Portugal 葡萄牙印象Macau: World Association for Cultural and Artistic Exchanges (Macau) with the sponsorship of Fundação Oriente and Fundação Macau.
This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center, in Lisbon, and the opinions expressed in the article are the sole responsibility of the authors. https://www.cccm.gov.pt</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Decolonization in Timor-Leste left deep traumas in the Portuguese military, argues researcher</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/23/descolonizacao-em-timor-leste-deixou-traumas-profundos-nos-militares-portugueses-defende-investigadora/</link><description>The researcher at the Institute of Contemporary History at Universidade Nova Zélia Pereira stated that the decolonization process in Timor-Leste left deep traumas in the Portuguese military, leading many to silence during the period of Indonesian occupation.
“The decolonization process in Timor, in addition to the trauma of the Indonesian invasion for the Timorese themselves, left profound traumas for the Portuguese military, personal and psychological traumas, consequences for their professional careers, most of them ended up abandoning military life, because they were successively passed over for promotions,” the researcher told Lusa.
“Lemos Pires, when he was promoted to general, there was an internal campaign against him,” he said. General Mário Lemos Pires was the last governor of Portuguese Timor (between November 8, 1974 and November 27, 1975).
Zélia Pereira is coordinating, together with Pedro Aires de Oliveira, professor of History at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences at Universidade Nova, the reissue of the report prepared by the commission for the analysis and clarification of the decolonization process of Timor-Leste, created by former President Ramalho Eanes, which will include declassified testimonies from military and civilian personnel heard in 1975 and 1976.
The project is being financed by the Foundation for Science and Technology, with the support of the commission for the celebration of the 50th anniversary of the 25th of April, as part of a competition for exploratory projects.
"It is such a huge trauma that throughout the entire period of Indonesian occupation, apart from Lemos Pires, no other soldier wanted to speak. After the referendum, some memoirs began to be published and only now more recently have they started to agree to do some interviews", explained the researcher.
According to Zélia Pereira, the testimonies given in 1976, with the “very fresh memory” and the “very vivid trauma” will allow access to a very “detailed, very interesting” set of information. The researcher also hopes that these testimonies will help the Timorese to “better understand a period that was very traumatic for them”.
“We need to understand the following, even today books continue to be published, articles that replicate all the accusations made in 1975. In doctoral and master's theses, because they are based on books published in the 70s, 80s, 2000s, up until the present and which still today are based on ideas and assumptions, which are not all 100% wrong, but which need to have other interpretations”, he highlighted.
History, said Zélia Pereira, is about placing several contexts under analysis simultaneously, because no one owns the truth. “What we want is for this to open up other perspectives, other research perspectives, and heal hurts, reconcile people with their past, regardless of whether they made decisions that didn’t turn out to be the right ones,” he added.
Timor-Leste became independent from Portugal on November 28, 1975, but nine days later, on December 7, it was occupied by Indonesia.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 18:47:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela | Maduro declares that country will never be defeated</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/05/venezuela-maduro-declara-que-pais-jamais-sera-derrotado/</link><description>The President of Venezuela declared yesterday that the country will never be defeated and that the Venezuelan people will respond to what he considered to be a psychological war orchestrated by the United States.
Speaking to the official Venezuelan television station VTV, Nicolás Maduro stated that the authorities and people of Venezuela will respond with work and achievements to the “psychological war”, referring to the North American Administration as “media scoundrels” from Miami. “How do you say ‘imbecile’ in English?” asked Maduro, warning those “who want to do harm” will never be able to defeat Venezuela.
Washington has intensified military operations off Venezuela in recent days, reiterating accusations against Maduro that he promotes drug trafficking.
The North American head of state, Donald Trump, also authorized new attacks against vessels, allegedly belonging to drug trafficking networks, near the Venezuelan coast. Maduro added that Venezuelan security forces have seized 63 tons of drugs since the beginning of the year.
On the other hand, the Venezuelan leader also denounced the attempt to enter Venezuela by two planes linked to drug trafficking. In the same speech, Maduro declared that Venezuela and Russia are making progress in military cooperation, which he described as peaceful and fruitful.
Daily contact
Asked about contacts between Caracas and Moscow in the context of “threats” from the United States, Maduro stated that the government maintains daily communication with Russian President Vladimir Putin on “several developing issues”, including military matters.
On Sunday, the Russian Presidency admitted having maintained contacts with Venezuela regarding a possible request for help from Maduro to Putin. At the same time, the People's Republic of China stated that there is normal cooperation between Beijing and Caracas.
The North American newspaper Washington Post reported that the Venezuelan President asked Russia, China and Iran for help to defend the country from pressure from the United States. For Beijing, this is cooperation between sovereign states and is not directed against third parties.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said at a press conference that China supports strengthening international cooperation to combat “transnational crime” and opposes the use or threat of such force in international relations.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:37:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Pop Mart, maker of Labubu, falls 10.8% in Hong Kong amid doubts about growth</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/24/pop-mart-fabricante-de-labubu-cai-108-em-hong-kong-entre-duvidas-sobre-crescimento/</link><description>Shares in Pop Mart, the Chinese company responsible for the global phenomenon of Labubu figures, sank 10.8% this Thursday, the biggest drop since April, in a new episode of volatility that contrasts with the good sales results released the day before.
The devaluation reflects investors' growing caution regarding the possibility of a slowdown in the company's growth, after several quarters driven by the popularity of its collectible products.
On Wednesday, Pop Mart shares rose 4.23% on the Hong Kong stock exchange, despite the negative tone of the market, following the announcement that revenue in the third quarter increased between 245% and 250%, driven by Labubu's virality on social media and the company's international expansion.
According to data provided by the company, domestic sales grew 190%, while international sales soared 370%, highlighted by increases of 175% in the Asia-Pacific region, more than 740% in Europe and almost 1,270% in the United States. The strong drop recorded today is largely attributed to profit taking, after appreciation of more than 186% since the beginning of the year, and uncertainty about the sustainability of the current growth rate.
The stock fell 8.1% on Tuesday, its worst performance since April, weighed down by fears of a slowdown in sales after months of euphoria. The preliminary release of results helped to temporarily dispel these concerns, but the absence of an official date for the presentation of the accounts maintains uncertainty regarding the company's future evolution. Executive chairman and founder Wang Ning expressed confidence in the long-term resilience of the Labubu character, arguing that cultural icons continue to generate revenue even after peak popularity.
According to the Bloomberg agency, the explosion in demand forced the company itself to revise its internal goals upwards. If at the beginning of 2024 Pop Mart predicted a turnover of 2,800 million dollars (around 2,400 million euros), in August Wang raised this target to 4,200 million dollars (3,600 million euros), pointing to the brand's global momentum as a key factor.
Founded in Beijing in 2010, Pop Mart has established itself as one of the main Asian references in the toy and collectible figures sector, combining exclusive design, limited editions and collaborations with international brands, artists and franchises.
Its business model is based on so-called “surprise boxes”, which encourage repeat purchases and have created a community of fans willing to pay high premiums for rare pieces. Among its main lines is Labubu, a monster with pointy ears and a mischievous smile inspired by Norse mythology, created by Hong Kong artist Lung Ka-sing in 2015 and integrated into the company's portfolio in 2019.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAG | Government restricts the use of “Western” devices because they represent a “risk”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/lag-governo-restringe-uso-de-aparelhos-ocidentais-por-representarem-um-risco/</link><description>The Government is betting on Chinese electronic devices, to avoid risks associated with equipment coming from countries with a “hostile stance” towards China. Wong Sio Chak revealed that all public servants, including Portuguese, will take an oath of loyalty to China and Macao by the end of the year
The Government revealed on Friday that the Public Administration is giving priority to Chinese electronic devices, because those coming from Western countries “with a hostile stance towards China” represent “a risk”.
“Instructions have already been issued by the DSAFP [Directorate of Administration and Public Function Services], especially for critical infrastructures,” said the Macau Secretary for Administration and Justice. “We considered, as a priority, the use of devices from our country” in RAM’s government services and departments, highlighted Wong Sio Chak.
The leader admitted to the Legislative Assembly that “there is a risk” in the supply of electronic telecommunications devices. “It is a very sensitive issue and one in which there is also a fragility”, said Wong, pointing the finger at “Western countries, especially some with a hostile stance towards China”.
However, the secretary highlighted, during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for 2026 in the area of ​​Administration and Justice, that the limitations only apply to the public administration of Macau. "We have an open market and we will not restrict the private sector to use foreign devices. Entities and the private sector have the freedom to choose these devices", explained Wong.
On October 19, the Central Government accused the United States of carrying out a cyber-attack against the National Time Service Center (NTSC), responsible for maintaining the accuracy of the country's official time.
The Chinese Ministry of State Security said the “systematic and long-planned” attack began in 2022, through a vulnerability in the SMS (short message) service of a “foreign brand” of mobile phones. The vulnerability made it possible to “covertly attack and gain control of the cell phones of several NTSC employees and steal confidential data stored on them”, said the ministry.
Faithful and loyal
Another highlight of Wong Sio Chak's presentation was the oath of loyalty to China and the Macao SAR that all public servants, including those of Portuguese nationality, will have to take by the end of the year. The oath is part of a review of the statutes of management and leadership staff and Public Administration workers, which came into force on 1 November.
The two revised laws determine that workers already in office have 90 days to take the oath, with refusal automatically implying the annulment of the appointment to the position or dismissal. But the secretary for Administration and Justice said he believes the process will be completed sooner and that “all public service workers will take the oath by the end of this year”.
Wong Sio Chak, who took office on October 16, defended during the presentation of the Governing Action Lines for 2026 that the review “improved the management and accountability regime of management and leadership staff”. On November 1st, 264 directors of public entities and services took an oath in a ceremony, declaring that “they will dedicate themselves with all loyalty to the Macau Special Administrative Region [SAR] of the People's Republic of China”.
In a speech given during the ceremony, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, asked civil service leaders to “firmly safeguard the full governance power of the Chinese Central Government”.
In December 2024, the Legislative Assembly approved, unanimously and without any debate, the law that provides that public servants in Macau can be dismissed if they carry out “acts contrary” to their oath. A month earlier, when presenting the proposal, the then Executive Council spokesman, André Cheong, warned that public servants could be fired due to private conversations or comments published on social media.
The oath will be mandatory for all public officials, including Portuguese ones, but it can be taken in Portuguese, one of Macau's two official languages, along with Chinese.
According to the most recent Public Administration Human Resources Report, in 2023 the region had 34,311 public employees. The document does not mention how many have Portuguese nationality, only mentioning that 257 were born in Portugal. The two proposals also oblige public servants to take the oath in a “sincere and solemn” manner. The sincerity of the oath will be assessed by the hierarchical superior and any dismissal may be appealed to the courts.
Every head
The Government wants to launch, at the beginning of 2026, negotiations with Portugal on an agreement for the reciprocal recognition of civil and commercial judgments.
Macau's Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, said that he intends to “strengthen judicial cooperation abroad and further expand legal exchange”.
According to the LAG report, Macau wants, from the first quarter of 2026, to start negotiating an “agreement on the reciprocal confirmation and enforcement of judicial decisions in civil and commercial matters” with Portugal. However, the document does not mention any date for the conclusion of negotiations and the eventual signing of a final agreement.
Macau and Portugal signed an agreement in 2019 regarding the surrender of fugitive offenders, whose criminal legality was called into question by the Portuguese Bar Association. The protocol is not in force, as it was not voted on in the Assembly of the Republic.
The Macau LAG report also reveals plans to conclude, by the end of 2026, three agreements with Angola for the transfer of convicted people, the delivery of fugitive offenders and mutual legal assistance in criminal cases. These three agreements with Angola have been mentioned in the Macau LAG since November 2023, and that report pointed to the end of 2024 as a target for concluding the negotiations.
Angola and mainland China signed an extradition treaty in 2006, which was only approved by the Angolan Parliament in 2011, and was ratified by the Government of Luanda two years later.
During the discussion in the Angolan Parliament, the then Angolan deputy minister of Justice, João Monteiro, defended the importance of the agreement due to the large migratory movement between the two countries. At the time, authorities estimated that close to 50,000 Chinese lived in Angola, working mainly in construction, in reconstruction projects financed largely by loans granted by China.
João Monteiro guaranteed that the two States agreed that extradition requests cannot include crimes of a political or military nature.
Macau Simplex
Wong Sio Chak reiterated to the deputies an old promise from the Administration and Justice department: administrative simplification. The government priority will aim to speed up processes and licenses, for example, for commercial establishments. In response to a question from Deputy Si Ka Lon, the Secretary for Administration and Justice said that, “as long as there are no major works”, a food and beverage establishment can obtain a license to operate in two days, upon presentation of all the required documents. The government official stressed that behind the flexibility of the administration machine are the concepts of “simplifying, decentralizing and optimizing”.
Get to work
The Secretary for Administration and Justice stated in the Legislative Assembly that the Government will continue efforts to implement the quota system for Public Service workers and reorganize some careers, eliminating those that are outdated and promoting mobility. Wong Sio Chak highlighted that since the launch of the quota management system in the Administration, in 2020, the number of public servants has increased, and that before changing the rules for progression or access between careers in the administrative machinery, the Government will listen to workers.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:52:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Louvre | France to reinforce security at cultural sites after theft</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/21/louvre-franca-vai-reforcar-seguranca-de-locais-culturais-apos-roubo/</link><description>The French Minister of Internal Affairs, Laurent Nuñez, will reinforce security measures in all cultural establishments, the press office announced yesterday, following a jewelry theft at the Louvre Museum in Paris. The decision was taken after a meeting with his government colleague in charge of Culture, Rachida Dati, said the same ministerial source, cited by the French news agency AFP.
The institution, in the center of the French capital, remained closed yesterday, one day after a group, still at large, managed to steal multiple works of jewelry art. "The Louvre Museum will remain closed today (yesterday) for exceptional reasons. We apologize for the inconvenience", read a message published on the museum's official website.
A group of four men stole jewelry on Sunday morning, in just a few minutes and when the museum was already open and with visitors inside, using a forklift machine, parked on the respective bank of the River Seine, and raising it to the height of a window on the first floor of the building.
The group took eight pieces “of inestimable heritage value”, including the tiara of Empress Eugenie (wife of Napoleon III, emperor from 1852 to 1870) and two necklaces, the French Ministry of Culture reported on Sunday. That jewel alone has 212 pearls and 1,998 diamonds, according to the Louvre's description, while the pieces belonging to Queen Maria Amélia have multiple sapphires and hundreds of diamonds.
This Parisian museum is the largest and most visited in the world, with nine million people enjoying part of the 35,000 works that the institution houses, in its 73 thousand square meters of space.</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 01:53:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuts leave 13.7 million people at risk of extreme hunger</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/16/cortes-levam-137-milhoes-de-pessoas-a-correr-risco-de-fome-extrema/</link><description>Os cortes no financiamento da ajuda humanitária podem expor até 13,7 milhões de pessoas à fome extrema em todo o mundo, alertou ontem o Programa Alimentar Mundial (PAM). “O sistema de ajuda humanitária está sob forte pressão com a retirada dos parceiros das áreas da linha da frente, criando um vazio”, afirmou a agência sediada em Roma num novo relatório intitulado “Uma bóia salva-vidas em perigo”.
The UN agency said that six of its operations – in Afghanistan, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Haiti, Somalia, South Sudan and Sudan – are “facing major disruptions, which will only worsen”. WFP warned that its financing “has never been so challenging”, anticipating “a 40 percent drop” in 2025, “which will translate into a projected budget of US$6.4 billion, compared to US$10 billion in 2024”.
The report does not name any countries, but points to a study published in the medical journal The Lancet, which found that 14 million additional deaths worldwide from disease, nutritional deficiencies and maternal and perinatal conditions could occur by 2030 as a result of cuts in US humanitarian aid alone.
Returns and records
Since US President Donald Trump's return to the White House, Washington has announced massive cuts in its foreign aid, dealing a huge blow to humanitarian operations around the world. "Program coverage has been significantly reduced and rations cut. Vital assistance to families in food disaster situations [Phase 5 of the Integrated Food Security Phase Classification/IPC] is threatened, while preparedness for future impacts has significantly decreased," warns WFP.
Globally, “WFP estimates that its funding gaps could push 10.5 to 13.7 million people currently in acute food insecurity (IPC Phase 3) into a humanitarian emergency (IPC Phase 4),” the organization added. The UN agency said global hunger has now reached record levels, with 319 million people facing acute food insecurity — including 44 million at emergency levels.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 02:52:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Death | António Coelho dies aged 77, but leaves a legacy in Portuguese gastronomy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/14/obito-antonio-coelho-morre-com-77-anos-mas-deixa-legado-na-gastronomia-portuguesa/</link><description>The founder of Restaurante António died on Sunday in Macau, due to heart problems. Behind him, he leaves a mark and an innovative concept for promoting Portuguese food in Asia
A father, a friend and one of the great ambassadors of Portuguese gastronomy in Asia. Chef António Coelho died on Sunday, aged 77, due to heart problems, but leaves behind a professional career spanning almost 40 years and an influence that can be felt in several restaurants and Portuguese food chefs in Macau.
Born in Portugal in 1948, António Coelho's first contact with Macau took place in 1970, when he had to complete his four-year mandatory military service. After two years, the land remained in his memory, but the future chef chose to return to Europe.
Em Portugal, começa por trabalhar na Segurança Social, mudando, mais tarde, para num laboratório de análises clínicas. Foi nesta área que desenvolveu o gosto pela gastronomia, não pelo trabalho, mas pelos vários almoços e jantares em diferentes restaurantes. Cada vez mais interessado na cozinha, António decide empregar-se, em 1984, num restaurante, onde admitiu ter aprendido a cozinhar, de acordo com uma entrevista ao jornal South China Morning Post, de 2018.
The first years of António Coelho's new career were spent in Portugal, where he performed different roles as manager-administrator of the Botequim do Rei restaurant or director of the catering department at the Grande Hotel da Curia. In 1996, he had his first international experience, as director of the restaurant department at the Hotel Trópico, in Cape Verde. The experience lasts one year.
Creating a legacy
Returning to Macau in 1997, António worked for 10 years in different spaces, such as the restaurants Frol de la Mar, Lusitano, Lisbon, and also had a brief stay in Hong Kong, in 2002, at Restaurante Inn. However, the decisive step towards his affirmation as one of the most influential chefs of Portuguese gastronomy in Asia came in 2007, with the opening of Restaurante António.
And the success that followed was not the result of chance, as said by Edgar Rodrigues, a chef who came to Macau to work on the launch of the project: “The success was based on the recipes, the quality of the food, but also the very professionalism”, says Edgar Rodrigues, to HM. "He was very attentive to his customers. If there was an order for clams à bolhão pato, he would have different recipes adapted to the nationality. For example, Koreans don't like coriander, the recipe for them didn't have coriander. Chinese customers like little salt, they were served with little salt, and locals like the more traditional recipe. In a single dish there were several ways of cooking, just to satisfy different customers", he recalls.
Cristiano Tavares, currently chef at the Macalhau restaurant, also came to Macau to work at the António Restaurant. He believes that the chef found a position for Portuguese food that still influences other restaurants today. “I think his success was due to his way of being, he was a politically correct person, he had a way of working that pleased both Chinese, Korean and Japanese tourists”, explained Cristiano Tavares, to HM. "We were a street restaurant with four or five cooks. He managed to do what many large restaurants still cannot do today. Nowadays there are many restaurants with Portuguese food that open in Macau, but follow the example of what he did", he considered.
Quality and spectacle
In addition to the food, Restaurante António customers were seduced by the “show”. This is the vision of Marcelino Marques, António's friend and musician who for several years livened up the space's nights, with traditional Portuguese music.
"The quality of the food made the space popular. He took great care in choosing the food and drinks served. He went to Portugal to choose wines from various regions, such as Douro or Alentejo, all of high quality, which were bottled under the António brand. People knew they weren't going to pay little, not that it was a space with luxury prices, it wasn't, but the quantity served wasn't small", recalled Marcelino Marques.
However, the musician believes that the success was also due to a concept in which the meal was also a spectacle: "People liked listening to Portuguese music, but also being with António. He was an affable, big person and appeared in that white jacket with the flags of Portugal, China and Macau and people liked his presence and asked him to take photographs", he says. "He also opened a bottle of champagne with a sword. He did a whole ceremony and people really liked it. It was a spectacle and a party to see the cork flying out of the bottle. It worked well", he recalled.
Marcelino Marques recalls that the food and the show made the restaurant very famous, especially among Japanese, Korean and Hong Kong tourists. The musician reveals that Japanese tourists booked days in advance. And this factor also contributed to the fact that António offered a glass of port wine at the end of the meal, which also led to the recognition of the Port Wine Confraternity.
The success of Restaurante António led the chef to sell the space to an investment fund, becoming an ambassador for the space. The break with the fund happened in 2020, when he was fired without just cause. The case ended up in court, with António winning the case. In recent years, António took on the position of executive chef at Angela’s Café and Lounge, at the Hotel Lisboeta.
A father, a friend
Due to his work in Macau, António was distinguished, in 2013, by the Macao SAR Government with the MSAR Tourist Merit Medal. Also in 2015, he received the merit medal for Portuguese communities from the Portuguese Government. However, for those who worked with him the most important thing was the relationship that went beyond the strictly professional field.
"He had a big impact on Macau and for me he was like a second father. When I came to Macau I didn't have an easy life and he always held my hand", confessed Rodrigues. "He was always a person who was there for me. And I always saw him as a man of iron. In everything he did, there was a great will", he pointed out.
This is a feeling shared by Cristiano Tavares. "António is my father in Macau. He worked until the last day, always with seriousness, honesty and integrity. He is an example for all the chefs in this area", he said.
For Marcelino Marques, António's death is the loss of a friend. "António was the person who welcomed me to Macau and was capable of doing the same to everyone. He was strict and demanding, but he was an excellent person", he described. "Everyone knew him. He was an affable person and received people like no one else", he added.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAG | Miguel de Senna Fernandes calls for more focus on Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/lag-miguel-de-senna-fernandes-pede-mais-foco-em-macau/</link><description>The president of the Association of Macanese, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, defended the importance of regional integration, but highlighted that Macau is going through a “delicate” moment and needs more attention from the Government. Senna Fernandes' position was taken in statements to Canal Macau.
"Macau is integrated into the Greater Bay Area, nothing other than improvements are expected to accelerate the development of the Greater Bay Area. But, we cannot forget that we are in Macau. This is fundamental", began by saying the president of the association, regarding the Lines and Governing Action. “There is no citizen, no matter how noble, no matter how much he defends the Government, no matter how much he applauds the Government in this policy and Macau's contribution to development, there is no citizen who does not have Macau as a priority”, he added.
In a context in which the recovery of tourism covers society in an unequal way, Miguel de Senna Fernandes asked for more attention to Macau, because it is going through a complicated period: “Despite the economic recovery numbers, we cannot forget that there is still a group of citizens to whom this does not reach”, he stressed.
"We need to say the measures, and I'm not saying long-term, but medium-term, to improve the conditions, the future prospects of this layer of workers, of professionals in Macau. Don't just feed the dream of Hengqin, for example. There are people who like to stay in Macau and for them Macau is always the future", he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:01:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Johnson Ian criticizes excessive TNR</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/trabalho-johnson-ian-critica-excesso-de-tnr/</link><description>Johnson Ian, former candidate for a deputy seat in the Legislative Assembly (AL), argued that the Government did not demonstrate true determination to replace non-resident workers (TNR) with residents in the labor area, in relation to the most recent report on the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for 2026.
In the opinion column published in the newspaper Sou Pou, Johnson Ian recalled that one of the highlights of the LAG report, released last week, is the demand from financial and higher education institutions, among others, for the release of more jobs for Macau residents. However, Johnson Ian pointed out that residents have difficulty finding work in the territory because there are many TNR. The official also states in the same article that residents want to work and even intend to take on lower category jobs, but companies have no desire to recruit them.
Johnson Ian cited official data showing that there are currently 183 thousand TNR, and, in his opinion, the Government should reduce this number of foreign workers, especially in gaming companies, to alleviate the problem of resident unemployment.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:00:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | EU expresses “concern about political issues”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/economia-ue-expressa-preocupacao-com-questoes-politicas/</link><description>Harvey Rouse, head of the European Union (EU) Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau, met with Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, to discuss investment by European companies in the diversification of Macau's economy
The European Union (EU) declined to reveal whether Au Kam San, detained with Portuguese nationality, was mentioned in a meeting with Macau authorities, in which a European representative demonstrated “concern about political issues”. On Thursday, the head of the European Union (EU) Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau, Harvey Rouse, wrote on social media that he had met with Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip.
The two spoke about how European companies can support “the economic diversification” of Macau, which is highly dependent on tourism, and “the continued development” of the neighboring special economic zone of Hengqin (Mountain Island). “I also expressed concern about political issues,” added Briton Rouse.
Asked by Lusa whether he had discussed the detention of former deputy Au Kam San with Anton Tai, the British diplomat did not respond. “We do not comment on the specific content of bilateral meetings,” the EU Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau told Lusa, in a written response.
“In our meetings with the Macau authorities, we regularly raise concerns about political and legal changes in the MSAR [Special Administrative Region of Macau], in line with the EU Annual Report on Macau, including on individual cases,” the delegation added.
On September 11, the European Commission warned that the “insistence on national security by the Macau government” is leading to “limiting the space for pluralistic voices from both politics and society”.
Uncomfortable revisions
In a report, the commission gave as an example the review of electoral laws for the leader of the Government and for the local parliament, to exclude candidates considered unpatriotic. On July 31, Macau police announced the arrest of pro-democracy activist Au Kam San, in the first case under the region's national security law, which came into force in 2009 and whose scope was expanded in 2023.
On September 10, during a visit to Macau, Portuguese Prime Minister Luís Montenegro admitted that he did not speak about Au Kam San with the leader of the local government, Sam Hou Fai, and argued that the case requires “the necessary discretion” and “some modesty”.
On October 21, the president of the Court of Final Instance of Macau, Song Man Lei, declared that the local justice system has an “indispensable duty” to judge “fairly, independently and professionally” national security cases, as well as “to ensure that all acts that offend the security of the State are punished in accordance with the law”.
Recently, after the presentation of the Government Action Lines for 2026, Sam Hou Fai briefly addressed the detention of Au Kam San for the first time. “In August, we had the first case related to the national security law,” he said at a press conference, without mentioning the name of the activist. The accusation is not yet known and there is no information about who will defend the former deputy.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:59:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai highlights national security as the path of the future</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/sam-hou-fai-destaca-seguranca-nacional-como-caminho-do-futuro/</link><description>The Chief Executive highlighted that the Macao SAR must “firmly defend the sovereignty, security and development interests of the country” in the coming years, in order to realize the “spirit of the Fourth Plenary Session of the 20th Central Committee of the Communist Party of China”. The statements were made on Saturday, at a meeting that took place at Forum Macau.
In his closing speech at the event, Sam Hou Fai also highlighted the need to develop “Macau in all aspects”, an objective that he said would only be possible if society knows how to “correctly identify, manage appropriately and actively seek changes”.
In addition to security, the Head of Government indicated that the spirit of the Central Committee plenary session is to “promote the patriotic spirit, boost social vitality and increase the efficiency of governance in accordance with the law”.
In this sense, he promised to “strengthen collaboration mechanisms with associations that love the country and Macau, thus consolidating its foundation of administration in favor of grassroots social communities”. In relation to associations, the Government hopes that they will be bridges for communicating ideas between the Executive and society.
Find more friends
As a third aspect, Sam Hou Fai indicated the need to “proactively seize the opportunities arising from development, promoting the adequate diversification of the economy and the sustainable development of Macau society”.
The Chief Executive did not forget the campaigns to involve the Macao SAR in the global panorama by contributing to the construction of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, participation in the One Belt, One Road initiative, and strengthening “interconnections with the interior and exterior”. These were the ways presented to expand Macau’s “international ‘circle of friends’” and assume “the role of ‘precise interlocutor’ between China and Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:55:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture | Tensions between China and Japan postpone meeting in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/cultura-tensoes-entre-china-e-japao-adiam-reuniao-em-macau/</link><description>A meeting of the “Cities of Culture of East Asia” was scheduled for today in Macau with ministers from China, South Korea and Japan. However, the initiative was canceled by Beijing, due to growing tension with Japan, following statements by the Japanese Prime Minister
The meeting in Macau between the Ministers of Culture of China, Japan and the Republic of Korea, which was originally scheduled for today, was postponed, without a new date being set. The announcement was made on Thursday by Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning, cited by Xinhua.
According to information from the state agency, the Chinese spokesperson stated “that a Japanese leader openly made highly erroneous statements about Taiwan, which hurt the feelings of the Chinese people, challenged the post-World War II international order and undermined the basis and environment for cooperation between China, Japan and the Republic of Korea.”
Mao Ning also said that the “Japanese leader’s” statements led “to a situation in which there are still no conditions to hold the meeting”.
Although Xinhua does not identify the “Japanese leader”, the target is Sanae Takaichi, Prime Minister of Japan. The first woman to lead the Executive of the country of the rising sun stated, on November 7, in parliament, that an attack from the Interior on the Island of Taiwan would be seen in Japan as a situation that would “threaten the survival” of the country.
In response, Xue Jian, consul general of the People's Republic of China in Osaka, wrote a post on the social network The publication was eventually deleted after a diplomatic protest from Japan.
Rising tension
In light of the diplomatic incident, the Government of China started to demand that Sanae Takaichi publicly retract the statements made in the Japanese parliament, which has been refused.
Without Japanese backtracking, China issued a security alert on tourist travel, which was followed by the governments of Macau and Hong Kong. The Interior did not stop at the warning for tourists and forced airline companies to cancel flights to Japan, travel agencies to cancel hotel stays, blocked imports of Japanese seafood again, postponed the entry of Japanese films into the domestic market and issued a warning to students who intend to study in Japan.
The meeting scheduled for today in Macau aimed to promote “exchange and mutual learning” between the three countries and was presented as a selection of the “Cities of Culture in East Asia”, which includes Macau. The Macao SAR Government portal dedicated to the event also stated that the meeting was “seen as a relevant achievement for humanity” and “a mark of cultural cooperation in East Asia”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:54:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Commercial spaces | Bill presented</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/espacos-comerciais-proposta-de-lei-apresentada/</link><description>The Housing Institute (IH) presented to the Council for Public Housing Affairs and associations the proposal to amend the decree-law that regulates the allocation, rental and free transfer of spaces suitable for the exercise of commercial activities that exist in buildings intended for social housing. Regulations regarding the Building Repair Fund were also discussed.
According to a statement released yesterday by IH, “participants basically agreed with the proposed legislative changes”. The institute committed to defining the concrete content of the two proposed legislative changes, taking into account the opinions collected.
IH also recalled that it recently held a meeting with the Council for Public Housing Affairs and three presentation sessions, with the aim of listening to the opinions of members and more than 20 social and professional associations, with the participation of more than 80 people.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Construction | Requests job guarantees for residents</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/construcao-pedidas-garantias-de-emprego-dos-residentes/</link><description>Leong Pou U, elected indirectly, is concerned about the difficulties local construction workers face in finding work. Despite praising the Executive's efforts to reduce the unemployment rate, he calls for more measures aimed at bricklayer jobs
Deputy Leong Pou U questioned the Government about the measures that will be adopted to guarantee priority access for residents to jobs in the construction sector. The question is part of a written question from the deputy linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM).
The legislator begins by indicating that conditions for local workers are increasingly difficult: “Since the beginning of this year, affected by the reduction in private construction projects and public works, construction workers have, in general, faced insufficient working hours, with stagnant wages for several years, which puts pressure on their livelihoods”, he argues.
The deputy also praised the measure taken by Sam Hou Fai's Executive to create the Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion, considering that it is effective in collecting information on job vacancies and needs in various sectors. However, he calls for greater use of this work: “Given the increasing employment pressure faced by construction workers, it is necessary for the Government to take further advantage of the role of the Working Group for the Coordination of Employment Promotion to introduce more targeted measures to help them secure employment”, he pointed out.
In this sense, the deputy wants to know if the Government has defined “guidelines for the priority hiring of local residents in subcontracted public works projects” and if it will require that when there are public works an increasingly greater proportion of local residents is defined. Leong Pou U considers it essential to ensure that the local population is in a situation of full employment.
List of compliments
Despite the warnings about the employment situation in construction, Leong Pou U's written statement praises the Government.
Leong highlights that between July and September, the unemployment rate is 1.8 percent, and that in the case of resident employment it does not exceed 2.4 percent. Positive values ​​for the legislator, who highlights that “the employment situation continued to improve with the decline in unemployment rates” despite the “large influx of recent graduates into the job market”, which shows “the Government's effective efforts in promoting employment among residents”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:06:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Presidents for all tastes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/presidentes-para-todos-os-gostos/</link><description>The electoral campaign for candidates for President of the Republic is on the road. The suitors for the Belém palace are more than many and for all tastes. On January 18th of next year, the Portuguese people are, once again, called to go to the polls to vote for whoever intends to be the new President of Portugal. There are candidates from the extreme right to the extreme left. The vote is secret, but most people already have an idea who they will vote for. One thing is certain: the Portuguese want to continue living in democracy and do not accept xenophobic, racist and neo-Nazi theories. Polls are worth what they are worth. They usually make mistakes in the final result. However, certain television channels have done everything to influence the vote in a certain direction.
Today, I leave you with what we think of each of the candidates.
André Ventura – Um candidato anti-sistema político em vigor, que tem defendido o ódio pelos imigrantes, que preconiza uma mudança nas leis da nacionalidade e até na própria Constituição da República. É visível que apenas se candidata para tentar manter a sua base eleitoral para futuras eleições legislativas, apesar de o seu Partido Chega, ter vindo a perder adeptos. In the television debates he has participated in, he only knows how to shout and present the same arguments that he has announced since he founded the party. It is not even possible that he will be able to participate in a possible second round of the presidential elections.
Marques Mendes – The former television commentator and PSD leader decided to run because his partner Luís Montenegro assured him that he would have the support of the PSD/CDS Democratic Alliance, which currently governs the country. Marques Mendes presents himself as a faction candidate. Without a doubt, supporters of the Montenegro government will vote for him. However, not all PSD activists support this candidacy. For these activists, Marques Mendes is Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa number two, with less knowledge of constitutional legislation. The polls created for his appreciation have already presented him as being ahead of voting intentions. We sincerely do not believe that the people will choose a President who would just go to Belém to defend all of Montenegro's proposals.
Almirante Gouveia e Melo – A candidate who immediately received, upon announcing his candidacy, overwhelming popular support for having been a man of seriousness and organization when the Covid-19 virus pandemic hit. Some once again support a military man for the Presidency of Portugal. Others are radically against the election of a military officer. They say he has no political experience and cannot explain what political area he is in. How can a citizen who becomes an admiral not know politics? How is it that you have not followed the vicissitudes of politics in the 50 years of democracy? Impossible. Gouveia e Melo knows perfectly well what support he has and what ideas he has to be a different President. The problem is that their political opponents know that Gouveia e Melo knows too much, for example, who received “gloves” in the acquisition of the high-tech submarines Arpão and Tridente, and there was no investigation by the Public Ministry when the German participants in the deal were arrested. His opponents want to remove him at all costs, as Gouveia e Melo knows all the ins and outs of those who want to remove him. He is one of the strong candidates to win the elections, in the first or second round.
António José Seguro – An experienced candidate in politics and academic life where he has maintained extensive contact with young people. He was general secretary of the Socialist Party and after the “war” with António Costa he hibernated. After 10 years, he returns bringing with him his seriousness, his political knowledge of the Portuguese reality and his serenity in analyzing national problems. The Socialist Party, or a part of it, was forced to announce that it supported this candidate. Seguro thanked him for the support, but emphasized his independence. Safe since he announced his candidacy for President, he has gradually risen in the voting intentions of the Portuguese, especially among a moderate “centrão” that includes social democrats and socialists. You may be surprised and go on to a second round.
Cotrim Figueiredo – A candidate who was leader of the Liberal Initiative, a party that is more similar to Chega than to the PSD. Cotrim could be a surprise, especially when it comes to voting among young people and women. Personally, he is a cordial person, knowledgeable about political dossiers, with experience in the corridors of the European Parliament and who presents himself as a defender of modern and reformist liberalism. It may surprise in the percentage of votes, but we don't believe it will be enough to contest a second round. The mobilization around Cotrim is being active and influential. Its result will depend greatly on the criticisms it announces against Chega, otherwise, social democratic activists unhappy with Marques Mendes will not support him and may opt to vote for Seguro.
António Filipe – This candidate is a Gentleman. Serious, deputy of the Assembly of the Republic for many years, knowledgeable about the Constitution from the first to the last paragraph, affable and popular. He does not deny his communist roots, but he often disagreed with the guidelines of the Central Committee of his party, the PCP. He is a candidate who has traveled the entire country and who sits in cafes listening to people's complaints. He has achieved a support base larger than that of his own party. We have already heard socialists saying that they will vote for his candidacy. António Filipe is cultured, an excellent commentator, a friend of the unprotected and could obtain a surprising result, despite the polls commissioned by the AD placing him as having no electoral significance. Maybe they are wrong.
Catarina Martins – The candidate supported by the Bloco de Esquerda should have remained in the insignificance that has been registered in her party, which month after month has seen voters flee to Livre. Catarina has no chance of obtaining a good result, because the crisis raging in the Bloc does nothing to help her win over voters. She knows what she's talking about, she points out errors in Montenegro's governance, she defends the poverty-stricken pensioners, but there is no machine in her candidacy that could promote her to a credible candidate capable of achieving a good result.
We will not comment on the candidate of Livre and other pretenders to the “throne” of Belém due to the fact that they have no chance of being elected. In our humble opinion, the elections will be disputed between Gouveia e Melo and Marques Mendes or António José Seguro. And in a second round, if Seguro is present, the entire left will be able to coexist with Álvaro Cunhal's thesis of covering his eyes and putting the cross on Seguro.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:39:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany's Strategic Awakening (I)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/20/o-despertar-estrategico-da-alemanha-i-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the article published in the November 13th edition)
After years of broken promises, Germany is now taking the matter seriously. And, suddenly, German rearmament, in the eyes of the same allies who for so long demanded its absolute necessity, seems hardly reassuring. Smiles and handshakes in public, concern behind the scenes, as it can be seen in out of place words, in apparently unjustified decisions and even in the expression of faces. Otherwise, it would be difficult to explain why, in September 2022, Warsaw formally decided to ask Berlin for reparations for the human and material losses suffered during the Nazi occupation, estimated at around 1,300 billion euros. Friendly price, of course.
Much more direct was Trump during the meeting with Merz at the White House in June 2025 when he stated that "They are spending more money on defense, and that's a good thing. I'm not sure that General MacArthur thought the same, ... you know what I mean? He said, 'Never let Germany rearm.' care.’” This was followed by a friendly pat on the leg from the German Chancellor saying: “Let’s stay tuned, I’ll take care of it.” The episode ended, to Merz's relief, with forced laughter. The feeling of uncertainty is not only felt in Washington and Warsaw, but also in government circles in London and Paris, where the warnings of Margaret Thatcher and François Mitterrand between 1989 and 1991, when the Wall fell and German reunification, were certainly not forgotten. For example, among German officials there is widespread conviction that French President Emmanuel Macron's proposal to extend the French nuclear arsenal to Germany is, in practice, a maneuver to control its trajectory, preserve French military primacy in the European Union and, at the same time, guarantee the vast financial resources on the other side of the Rhine.
Not exactly a gesture of solidarity between allies. The question then arises as to why the West encouraged the strengthening of Berlin's military capabilities for years, only to later, at least in part, regret it? Does this incongruity follow any logic? To respond, it helps to remember a leitmotif that has been circulating in Washington for at least a decade, especially since Barack Obama presented the so-called “Pivot to Asia” (which was a foreign policy strategy launched by President Barack Obama in 2011, which marked a significant shift in the focus of the United States from the Middle East and Europe to Asia-Pacific. The objective was to reinforce the diplomatic, economic and military presence of the United States in the region in the face of the rise of China) that for the United States, it is imperative to transfer the costs to third parties of containing Russian ambitions in Europe, at least on a conventional level.
And in this context, the contribution of the Federal Republic, the continent's largest economy, seems inevitable. The problem is who can guarantee that Berlin, after developing its military capabilities as requested by Washington, will use them in a manner consistent with American interests? It is easy to control those who are fragile and defenseless, much less those who are armed to the teeth. In short, Germany's human and industrial capabilities are indispensable, but leaving them in the hands of the Germans is frightening and not a little scary. Nothing new in the Western bloc as we are facing the same contradiction that, at the beginning of the Cold War, led the United States to build its informal empire in Europe. An architecture designed, in large part, to keep the Germans “subdued”, according to the famous formula of the first secretary general of NATO, Lord Ismay.
Enemies sitting at friends' table. No American, in the second half of the 1940s, would have consented to the reintegration of Germany (even if divided) into the “family of Western nations” if he had not considered it strictly necessary. In fact, before the end of hostilities, President Franklin Delano Roosevelt openly argued that the Germans should face costs “so impressive that they hesitate before starting a new war.” In his eyes, Germany would be “less dangerous for civilization if divided into 107 provinces”. This is also why, in September 1944, during the Quebec conference, Roosevelt agreed to ratify with Winston Churchill a project that envisaged the transformation of the enemy into a “country with a predominantly agricultural and pastoral character”. The plan, developed in the previous months by then Treasury Secretary Henry Morgenthau with the evocative title “Program to Prevent Germany from Starting a Third World War” envisaged, in essence, stripping the Germans of “all their heavy industries”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-20 04:42:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Who's afraid of the gynecologist?</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/19/quem-tem-medo-do-ginecologista/</link><description>As soon as a person with a vulva begins their sexual life, visits to the gynecologist become mandatory. There are those who suggest consultations every year, there are those who recommend intervals every three years — it largely depends on the medical situation. During the consultation, the doctor observes the vulva and the inside of the vagina, performs tests and assesses the health of the private parts. Even though contact with the gynecologist may be frequent, there are those who feel extreme anxiety during these visits. After all, the person is exposed and vulnerable.
In addition to having to share details about your sex life and dealing with awkward silences — easily interpreted as judgmental — there is also the discussion about bodily fluids and the use of a vaginal speculum, sometimes metallic and cold, so that the vagina opens and visibility is better. There is associated discomfort and people describe different levels of discomfort, and even pain. What is certain is that, for many, these interventions can be painful — and, therefore, anxiety soars. There are those who even prefer not to go to the gynecologist at all.
Starting with the vaginal speculum, for example: it has maintained practically the same shape and function for 185 years. Some doctors still use the cold, metallic model, but it is believed that, nowadays, the disposable plastic model is used more often, which, although a little more comfortable, is not the ideal solution. Two women in the Netherlands at the Technical University of Delf developed an alternative with a less aggressive mechanism, which, in initial studies, proved to be very favorable — not only for the comfort of patients, but also for doctors, who reported better visibility. Lilium, as it is called, is, without a doubt, a promising invention, but it may take some time to reach gynecological offices around the world. The material is softer and the shape of the opening is gentler, even allowing patients to control the opening — which may be relevant for those who suffer from extreme anxiety, have had traumatic sexual experiences or even previous negative experiences at the gynecologist.
Some people take the consultation naturally; others avoid it completely. Most, however, resign themselves to the idea that routine consultation is necessary, despite the discomfort it may cause. For the sake of our health, we sometimes subject ourselves to unpleasant procedures — and that's okay: that's how medicine works.
However, there are aspects that can be managed so that going to the gynecologist is not a hassle. This is the part that gives us back some agency in the relationship with the gynecological act. How can we take care of discomfort?
Establish a relationship of trust. For the experience to be smooth, it is essential that the person establishes a relationship of trust with the doctor. It is worth sharing anxieties and fears regarding the visit, explaining what causes discomfort. Together, they can develop strategies that make exams more bearable (for example, in the case of cytology). You can ask the doctor to explain each step of the procedure. Not all professionals are sensitive to these issues, but it is important to find one with whom we feel comfortable and with whom communication is easy and uncomplicated.
If it's your first visit, it's worth asking friends or trusted people for references — and look for doctors who are empathetic and available to listen to concerns.
Accompany yourself with comforting objects or circumstances. When going to your appointment, take something that makes you feel safe and reminds you that the discomfort is temporary. For example, listening to relaxing music before entering or using a familiar perfume or scent. It is important to identify these points of well-being and not be afraid to turn to them in a stressful situation. It may also be helpful to bring a trusted companion to stay with you in the waiting room and greet you when you leave. These moments of safety help keep the uncomfortable experience from leaving you feeling emotionally helpless.
The world of gynecological medicine still has a lot of room to improve when it comes to care and understanding the discomfort that this type of consultation can generate. Even in the reformulation of examination procedures and instruments, there will certainly be advances that take more account of the comfort of people with a vulva.
For now, all we can do is talk about the discomfort with the healthcare professional and look for the one with whom we feel the most trust. Despite the commonplace that going to the gynecologist is “just a little uncomfortable”, we increasingly realize that, for many people, it can be much more than that — and there is nothing like developing strategies that recognize discomfort, but take care of it in the best way possible.</description><pubDate>2025-11-19 01:40:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Pre-prepared food (I)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/18/comida-pre-preparada-i/</link><description>Recently, the press reported that a prominent Chinese businessman, after having dinner at a restaurant belonging to a chain in mainland China, expressed his outrage online, saying that the food he had been served was “pre-prepared” and that he had paid an exorbitant price for it. The restaurant chain responded immediately, stating that the dishes he had been served were not “pre-prepared food, but rather made with products from the restaurant chain’s “Central Kitchen Pre-Processing Technology”.
This incident sparked lively online discussions surrounding the use of pre-prepared food in restaurants and the consumer's right to be informed—issues worthy of public attention.
On March 18, 2024, mainland China issued a “Notice on Strengthening Food Safety Supervision of Pre-prepared Food and Promoting the Development of High-Quality Industry.” The Notice defines pre-prepared food this way:
“Pre-prepared food, also known as pre-packaged dishes, refers to meals made from one or more edible agricultural products and their derivatives, with or without seasonings or other auxiliary ingredients, without preservatives, through industrial pre-processing (such as mixing, marinating, frying, roasting, baking, steaming, etc.), with or without seasoning packets, satisfying the storage, transport and sale conditions indicated on the product label, which dishes must be consumed after heating. Does not include staple foods such as frozen rice, noodles, convenience foods, packaged meals, rice bowls, steamed buns, pastries, roujiamo (Chinese hamburger), bread, hamburgers, sandwiches, pizza, etc.”
In other words, pre-prepared food is food that is cooked in advance, stored and then taken to the restaurant where it will be heated and served to customers.
One point to note is that pre-prepared foods generally have a longer shelf life, which can range from several days to a few months, whereas semi-prepared foods have a much shorter shelf life, typically just one to two days, and require refrigeration.
After reading the description of pre-prepared food in the “Notice”, a question arises: Can food prepared in the central kitchen of the restaurant chain and then transported to other branches be considered pre-prepared food? The “Notice on Strengthening Food Safety Supervision of Pre-Prepared Meals and Promoting High-Quality Development of the Industry” clearly stipulates that central kitchens must comply with legal and regulatory food safety requirements and standards in the catering industry; therefore, they are not pre-prepared foods.
Mainland China previously requested opinions on “National Food Safety Standards for Pre-Prepared Foods,” and it is believed that new regulations will be issued soon. At that time, more standards regarding this matter will appear.
The explanation we gave of the concept of pre-prepared food results from a textual interpretation, but we can, from delicious food, arrive at complex thoughts. Thinking about these questions before eating can be mentally exhausting and reduce the pleasure of the meal. Now let's try to think about what pre-prepared foods are for the average consumer.
For most consumers, any food that is not prepared and cooked in the restaurant itself, and that contains some trace of industrial processing, be it a meal kit or a semi-finished product, is considered pre-prepared food. In other words, “it is not freshly cooked, therefore, it is pre-prepared” this is the common understanding about pre-prepared food.
Do you, dear reader, also share this idea? Do you agree with the widespread perception? Next week, we will continue to debate this topic and explore how Macau should deal with the matter.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor of the Faculty of Management Sciences of the Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-11-18 01:20:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Barra Slow Festival | Coffee and culture in Naval Workshops</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/barra-slow-festival-cafe-e-cultura-nas-oficinas-navais/</link><description>It's called “Barra Slow Festival” and the first edition is scheduled for next weekend, between the 28th and 30th of November, with the aim of revitalizing the Barra area with activities linked to coffee culture, design and crafts. The public will be able to enjoy events at Naval Workshops nº 1 and nº2, as well as in the square located in the area
This weekend, namely between Friday and Sunday, the first edition of the “Barra Slow Festival 2025” is taking place in Macau, an event that brings various activities linked to coffee, culture and art and aims to attract public attention to the Barra area, known for tourist sites such as the A-Má Temple.
According to an official statement from the event, this is a debut in the territory of events such as “To Play Market × Tokyo Coffee Festival · Macau 2025” and the “Shanghai UNFOLD Art and Design Fair”, as well as initiatives such as “Coffee Rave”, “Macau Chill Collective” and an exhibition by well-known graphic designer Florian Lamm. All these events will be spread across the square in the Barra area and Oficinas Navais nº 1 and nº2, where cultural events usually take place.
According to the same note, the “Barra Slow Festival” integrates “popular contemporary elements, such as coffee culture, creative design, visual exhibitions, limited artisanal products and music”, being a “cultural event with selected concepts”.
The idea of ​​an event in which there is “human warmth” is defended, encouraging the public “to relax and live intensely, recovering the tranquility inherent to life”. In this way, “the Barra neighborhood was chosen [for this initiative], with tents set up inside and outside the historic buildings of the Naval Workshops”.
It is therefore hoped that the general public “can enjoy a cup of coffee, stroll around the area and experience the historical depth of the Barra neighborhood”.
From the outside to the inside
Above all, the “Barra Slow Festival” brings to Macau events already known in Asia, such as the “Tokyo Coffee Festival”, organized by “To Play Market” and which brings together almost 50 famous coffee brands from Japan, the Greater Bay Area and Macau.
“Just a few months ago, the Tokyo Coffee Festival made its debut in Hong Kong, attracting more than 30,000 participants, and both its artisanal coffee and coffee products were highly praised,” highlights the organization. At this premiere in Macau there will be special products for sale and limited editions.
Another highlight of the lineup is the “UNFOLD” Art and Design Fair, organized in Shanghai by Shanghai BANANAFISH. This is an event with the curatorial concept of “unfold, read and present”, being a “communication platform that brings together lovers of culture and art, designers, creative workers and professionals from the creative industry”.
What you can see in Barra, with “UNFOLD”, is a market with 100 stands of brands and design products from around the world, with “creative selections and limited artisanal products”, and ticket holders can also visit the special exhibition by designer Florian Lamm.
Florian's works were selected for the Top 100 Posters in Germany, Austria and Switzerland, and won the Artist Award at the Brno Biennale, the oldest graphic design exhibition in the world.
The “Macau Chill Collective” aims to “bring together the strength of local brands”, inviting “dozens of brands, from well-known cafe owners, creative artisans and creators”. During the festival, the exhibition “Ancient Memories: Impressions of the Shipyard – Historical Photographic Exhibition of the Barra District” will also be held in order to “deepen participants’ understanding of the history of the district”.
The “Barra Slow Festival” has free entry and takes place between 12pm and 8pm. It is necessary to purchase tickets for the UNFOLD Art and Design Fair, with a cost of 55 patacas for pre-sale and 78 patacas on the event days. There are also tickets for sale for some events related to coffee culture. Tickets have been on sale since November 2nd on the MacauTicket, Damai and Ctrip platforms. The event is organized by the Federation of Industry and Commerce of Macau, Central and Southern District, co-organized by BANANAFISH and TOPYS, and supported by the Institute of Economic and Technological Development, the Macau Tourism Board, the General Union of Neighborhood Associations of Macau and other sponsoring entities.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:29:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Coloane | “Connections Music.Movement.Nature” this weekend at Urban Farm</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/coloane-connections-music-movement-nature-este-fim-de-semana-na-urban-farm/</link><description>After being postponed due to super typhoon Ragasa, the “Connections – Music.Movement.Nature” festival takes place this weekend in the town of Coloane. Live music, crafts, workshops, dance and various types of activities for families will mark two days of communion at the Urban Farm space
“Connections – Music.Movement.Nature” is the result of a community impulse of belonging and sharing of a family bigger than blood and genes, born in the antipodes of a city immersed in materialism and commercialism of the concerts of various types of regional pop that form part of the city's cultural agenda. After two editions in 2018 and 2019, and the postponement due to super typhoon Ragasa, the festival is back this weekend, this time at the Urban Farm space in the town of Coloane.
Built by the community, for the community, this year's “Connections” has a lineup filled with 30 workshops from the most varied areas, 20 DJ performances and performances by Beto Ritchie, Lobo and Náv, an area for food, drinks and crafts by local creators and multiple activities for families.
“Those responsible, who see themselves as ‘a collective creation that combines a conscious way of life with unique experiences’, intend through this initiative to provide ‘Family Activities, Lectures and Workshops, Exploration of Well-Being and Artistic Expression’”, indicates the organization in a statement.
After the events held in 2018 and 2019 in the Ká-Hó Dam area, this year the party moves to a new, larger space, which will allow various activities to take place spread across seven different areas: the “Village”, a picturesque area that resembles a traditional Chinese village, with wooden houses in an oriental garden, will be the area for meals and drinks and the sale of handicrafts. Larry’s Place, Concept H, Lotus Cocktails, Cakes By Rose &amp; Muse, Juk and Happy Stand are responsible for the food and drinks.
In the “Village” there will be 10 stands selling crafts from local creators (Dreama, Cordelia Handmade, Zarja’s Selections, CeraGigi, Dollfie, Wickd Candle Studio, White Lodge Dreamland, Love and Light Handmade Studio, Gems Awakening, Free Spirit Home and the Rui Carreiro Barbeiro stand.
Inhale, exhale
Next door, the “Gypsy Camp”, an area with cushions and resting places, will allow musical exploration with musical instruments such as the asalato, participating in a drum circle, a singing workshop, or attending a handpan concert with the duo Nàv, who curates the area. Nearby, in a Mongolian tent (yurte), there will be a lecture on spiritual themes and individual tarot and soul reading sessions.
Activities for families will take place in the “Family Tent”, offering Meditation for Families sessions, Mandala Dot Painting, Crochet, Circles of Life Painting and Construction of Animal Masks on cardboard.
In the “family tent” Associação Sílaba will provide moments of interactive reading, the launch of “CaixaPiz” and activities for the little ones.
Taking your feet off the ground, the “Treetop” area, a mezzanine built in the top of a tree, was chosen for all body exploration activities and more serene moments of meditation and relaxation. With activities taking place from morning to dusk, the “Treetop” will also host Brazilian Dance and Conscious Dance sessions, as well as Yoga, Gyrokinesis and CoreNature, a fusion of Pilates and Animal Flow. Sound Bath sessions and meditations at sunset and connection to nature are also planned.
Enchanted forest
At the bottom of the Urban Farm property, in the “Concrete” area, graffiti and urban art sessions are scheduled with the collective of local artists Outloud International Street Art Festival.
Finally, in “Woods”, in a clearing in a small forest, there is an open-air electronic music and dance space, which will feature performances by several local and regional DJs. The musical offering will also be present in the “Village” area, with a more organic, lounge selection, focused on world music, as well as a live performance by Beto Ritchie tomorrow at 3pm and Lobo on Sunday at 6pm.
Participants are advised to bring warm clothing, insect repellent, hats, sunscreen, towel, flashlight and portable ashtray. The event organizers announced on social media that entrance donations, which are still on sale, cost between 180 and 280 patacas for tickets for one or both days of the event, and at the door they will cost between 200 and 300 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:28:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Makeup workshop anticipates show at Casa Garden</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/workshop-de-maquilhagem-antecipa-espectaculo-na-casa-garden/</link><description>On Sunday, starting at 3pm, local makeup artist Mandy Cheuk will teach a workshop at Casa Garden that is an extension of the Surrealist Chinoiserie project: “Golden City of Seres”, which resulted in the presentation of a performance from the Art For All Society (AFA) universe.
"As an experienced makeup artist, Mandy Cheuk's expertise encompasses body painting, special effects for film and television, theatrical performances and artistic direction. Her talent is internationally recognized", describes the AFA.
The workshop, which has a price of 300 patacas per person, or 500 patacas for two people, is born from the last show “Surrealistic Chinoiserie”—Golden City of Seres”, which was presented in the Belgian city of Antwerp last June. The “made in Macau” performance, which started in Antwerp, will return to Macau on December 6th, at 6:30 pm, at Casa Garden. Entry is free.
“Bringing together an elite team of artists from Beijing and Macau, the show weaves a fantastic world through the physical vocabulary of contemporary dance, exclusive artistic makeup, meticulously arranged electronic music and fantasy-filled visual art from Eastern and Western imaginaries”, describes the organization.
All elements
The visual tension created by the complex perfusion of elements comes to life with choreography inspired by classical and traditional Chinese dances and forms of expression typical of contemporary ballet.
The performance is born from the artistic vision of Leong Chi Mou, and is directed and performed by dancers Jay Zheng and Tina Kan, “decorated” by the makeup, body painting and stylistic creation of Mandy Cheuk and the live soundtrack provided by Faye Choi, from the local electronic music band EVADE.
The project, which has the “academic support” of Alice Kuok, attempts through various “contemporary perspectives, to deconstruct and remodel the time-honored aesthetic concept, excavating the transformations and extensions of the historic ‘Silk Road’ in the contemporary context and interrogating the latent desires at its core”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:26:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibition | Creative Macau displays creations between human and machine</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/20/exposicao-creative-macau-exibe-criacoes-entre-o-humano-e-a-maquina/</link><description>The “Human–Machine Co-Creation” exhibition is on display at Creative Macau until December 27, bringing together works by 18 art and design professors and doctoral students in creative research from the University of Macau.
Creative Macau indicates that the creative research carried out by professors and doctoral students in art and design at the University of Macau materializes the collaborative dynamics between human and machine, simultaneously revealing focuses of individuality and spirituality.
The entity states that the essence of artistic creativity lies in the ability to reflect current sociocultural and technological contexts, and convey the individuality of the artist.
“In the contemporary era characterized by digital media and artificial intelligence, a determining paradigm is the concept of ‘man-machine co-creation’. Artistic production and design practices are increasingly mediated by digital technologies, whose influence extends beyond materiality and technical processes, permeating cognitive structures and aesthetic sensibilities”, contextualizes the organization of the exhibition.
The collaborative synergy between human and machine was achieved, according to Creative, in this exhibition. The exhibition consists of creations by Xun Chi, Mengyao Guo, Lampo Leong, Fan Li, Zhenhao Ou, Xipei Ren, Atticus Sims, Ouresis Todorovich, Xiaofeng Wang, Xiaoqian Wang, Yanren Wang, Haozheng Wu, Michael Whittle, Xinxin Xiu, Siyi Xu, Yan Zhang, Yanxiu Zhao and Hongtao Zhou.</description><pubDate>2025-11-20 04:27:09</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Request for greater coverage of anti-scam program</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/pj-pedida-maior-cobertura-de-programa-anti-burlas/</link><description>Deputy Chan Lai Kei questioned the Government about the need to reinforce and increase the coverage of the Judiciary Police (PJ) anti-fraud program, taking into account the frequent cases of fraud that occur associated with fake employees of the Taobao platform.
Therefore, the deputy, with connections to the Fujian community, questioned whether analyzes using artificial intelligence (AI) could be introduced in this program so that alerts could be given to users whenever they find messages with a high risk of fraud. Furthermore, the deputy recalled that there is a face swap technique using AI, which leads elderly people to easily become victims of fraud, which is why he hopes that the PJ will use this anti-fraud program to publicize these types of cases to groups of potential victims of fraud.
In the same question, the deputy also asks how the Government will reinforce cooperation with neighboring regions regarding the sharing of cross-border data, in order to track the origin and flow of capital involved in fraud.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:25:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate | Quarterly price increase by 7.7 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/imobiliario-aumento-trimestral-dos-precos-em-77-por-cento/</link><description>Data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC) shows that average house prices, per square meter of useful area, increased by 7.7 percent in the third quarter of this year compared to the previous one. In the Macau peninsula alone this increase was 12.6 percent, recording an average price of 74,590 patacas, “mainly due to new housing complexes being put up for sale in the reference quarter”, highlights DSEC.
On the islands, the 4 percent increase in Coloane stands out, with the average price of autonomous housing units standing at 87,093 patacas, while in Taipa prices fell 4.6 percent, to around 70,110 patacas. The average price of autonomous housing units in constructed buildings stood at MOP65,897, down 3.2 percent quarter-on-quarter.
DSEC also reveals that in the third quarter of this year, based on the stamp tax charged, 1,411 autonomous units and parking spaces were transacted for a value of 6.26 billion patacas. The average price per square meter of useful area of ​​autonomous housing units, in global terms, stood at 74,190 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:22:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Oceans | China, Portugal and Brazil create research laboratory</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/oceanos-china-portugal-e-brasil-criam-laboratorio-de-investigacao/</link><description>Among the institutions involved in the new project are the University of São Paulo (USP), the University of Macau (UM) and the Instituto Superior Técnico (IST)
Academic institutions from China, Portugal and Brazil created a new project in Macau on Friday to collaborate on ocean research, including the impact of climate change and changes in marine currents.
“We are going to deepen our knowledge of the oceans and have a more integrated vision, which will allow us to anticipate the future in a safer way”, the coordinator of the Robotics and Engineering Systems Laboratory told Lusa. The objective of the Oceanic Research Center between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries is “to collaborate and share data, resources and talents”, added José Santos-Victor.
In addition to the laboratory associated with Instituto Superior Técnico, the new center includes the University of São Paulo (USP), the University of Macau (UM) and the Chinese state laboratory Laoshan Laboratory, based in Qingdao, in eastern China. “There are several research centers that do excellent work in these various areas”, defended Santos-Victor, giving as an example the research and prediction of the effects of climate change on the oceans.
According to environmental groups, climate change is one of the greatest threats to the oceans, along with pollution and new technologies that open the door to deep-sea mining and more intensive fishing. A priority will be training, with plans for exchanges between researchers and master's or doctoral students between the center's various laboratories, highlighted the Portuguese academic.
New master's degrees
During the inauguration ceremony, UM's rector, Song Yonghua, promised the launch of joint master's degree programs between the universities that are part of the initiative. Ettore Apolonio de Barros, professor at USP, reminded Lusa that the Brazilian university created, in 2024, the USP-China Center, to “promote cooperation with Chinese universities”.
The researcher highlighted the multidisciplinary nature of the center opened in Macau, as “one of the first initiatives” to bring together scientists and engineers to collaborate in the exploration and study of the oceans. The specialist in automated electromechanical systems recalled that the project is “an important development” of the Oceanic Scientific Research Alliance between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries.
The alliance was also created in Macau, in 2022, by 19 universities from China and Portugal, Brazil, Angola and Mozambique, to launch joint research projects on the oceans. The vice-rector of UM, the Portuguese Rui Martins, told Lusa that the alliance was recently strengthened, with the entry of five more institutions, including the University of Hainan, in southern China.
On the Portuguese-speaking side, the Technical University of the Atlantic (Cape Verde), the University of Coimbra, the Institute of Systems and Computer Engineering, Technology and Science (INESC TEC) and INESC P&amp;D Brasil joined.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:19:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Royal House | Casino closed on Saturday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/casa-real-casino-encerrou-no-sabado/</link><description>The closure of the Casa Real casino, linked to the concessionaire SJM Resorts, took place on Saturday morning “in accordance with the planned procedures”. The information was revealed by the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate, which coordinated the closure and guaranteed “compliance with legal terms and orderly closure”.
"After the closure of the Casa Real Casino, at 11:59 pm on November 21st, the DICJ immediately suspended the operation of the gaming tables, having ensured active coordination with various services, monitoring the process of removal from the respective venue, among others. The closure of the casino took place in an orderly manner", it was communicated.
“During the closure of the aforementioned casino, the Directorate of Labor Affairs Services sent staff to the site to provide clarifications to the workers in question, and they were provided with information on an open line for further consultation”, it was added.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:11:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation reaches highest value in the last 14 months</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/inflacao-atinge-valor-mais-elevado-dos-ultimos-14-meses/</link><description>Annual inflation in Macau accelerated in October, for the fourth consecutive month, reaching 0.6 percent, the highest value in the last 14 months, it was announced on Friday. The rise in the consumer price index (IPC) in October grew by 0.13 percentage points compared to September, and was the highest value since August 2024 (plus 0.74 percent), according to official data.
According to the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), the acceleration in inflation was mainly due to food products and non-alcoholic drinks (plus 0.7 percent). The cost of meals purchased outside the home rose 1.54 percent. Spending on apartment rent or mortgages rose 0.83 percent and 0.58 percent, respectively.
On October 30, the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM) approved the second interest rate cut in two months. The Legislative Assembly approved, in April 2024, the end of several taxes on the acquisition of housing, to “increase liquidity” in the real estate market, defended the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Lei Wai Nong, at the time.
Jewelry going up
With the recovery in the number of visitors, the region recorded a 29.8 percent increase in the price of jewelry, goldsmithing and watches, popular products among tourists from mainland China.
The cost of tours and hotels for Macau residents' overseas trips increased by 5.87 percent, while expenditure on education and vehicle fuel rose by 1.67 percent and 3.18 percent, respectively. Inflation in Macau accelerated in October, in a period in which the CPI rose again and fell in mainland China, after four months of decline.
In mainland China, by far Macau's largest trading partner, the CPI registered a year-on-year increase of 0.2 percent. China recorded deflation in six of the ten months this year.
Deflation reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly serious, as a fall in the price of assets, normally contracted using credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
The value recorded in September surprised analysts, who predicted that the indicator would remain unchanged compared to October 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:10:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | New visitor record for October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/turismo-novo-recorde-de-visitantes-para-mes-de-outubro/</link><description>The territory received around 33.1 million visitors in the first ten months, 14.1 percent more than in the same period last year. It is the second highest value ever, below pre-pandemic records
Macau received 3.47 million visitors in October, 10.8 percent more than in the same period in 2024 and the highest figure ever for this month, it was announced. The number of tourists passing through the territory was the highest for any month of October since the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) began compiling monthly data, in 1998, still during the Portuguese administration.
The region had already registered a historic high for September in the previous month: almost 3.8 million visitors, 9.8 percent more than in the same period in 2024. However, in October almost 61 percent of visitors (2.1 million) arrived on organized tours and spent less than a day in Macau.
In 2024, the Central Government announced a series of measures to support the territory, such as increasing the tax exemption limit for goods for personal use purchased by visitors from China. At the same time, the Chinese authorities expanded the list of places with “individual visas” to visit Hong Kong and Macau to 10 more cities in China.
Additionally, since January 1, residents of the neighboring city of Zhuhai can visit Macau once a week and stay for up to seven days. As a result, the overwhelming majority (89.8 percent) of tourists arriving in Macau in September came from mainland China or Hong Kong, while just over 353,000 were international visitors.
The city received a total of around 33.1 million visitors in the first ten months, 14.1 percent more than in the same period in 2024 and the second highest figure ever for the start of a year.
Below 2019
According to official data, the number of tourists passing through Macau was only surpassed between January and October 2019 – before the Covid-19 pandemic -, a period in which it registered more than 33.4 million visitors. On January 17, the director of Macau Tourism Services said she expected between 38 and 39 million visitors this year.
In August, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes set a target of more than three million international visitors in 2025. In the first ten months of the year, Macau received almost 2.97 million tourists from abroad, 14.9 percent more than in the same period in 2024.
Citizens of Saudi Arabia, Qatar, Kuwait, Bahrain and Oman will no longer need a visa to enter the city from July 16th. Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor in Macau, excluding casinos, fell by 9.5 percent in the first nine months of the year, compared to the same period in 2024.
At the beginning of May, DSEC pointed to the “change in the consumption pattern of visitors” as one of the main reasons for the 1.3 percent drop in Macau's economy between January and March. It was the first time that the territory's Gross Domestic Product shrank, in year-on-year terms, since the end of 2022, when the region began to lift restrictions due to the covid-19 pandemic.
Macau received 34.9 million visitors last year, 23.8 percent more than the previous year, but still far from the record, 39.4 million, set in 2019, before the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:07:18</pubDate></item><item><title>PLP and China want international arbitration platform</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/plp-e-china-querem-plataforma-de-arbitragem-internacional/</link><description>The Federation of Portuguese-Speaking Lawyers signed a protocol in the special economic zone of Hengqin, neighboring Macau, for cooperation in arbitration between China and the Portuguese-speaking world, the president of the institution told Lusa yesterday.
“In Portugal, conflicts in the courts drag on for several years and, obviously, we know that arbitration is an expeditious means of obtaining justice and, therefore, it is so convenient to have arbitration in operation, arbitration in the Portuguese language, in which the parties can, in essence, resolve their disputes in the language that unites us”, explained Pedro Pais de Almeida.
The official, who is in Macau to participate in the FALP Congress, noted that the agreement was signed on Wednesday with the Macau Bar Association, “several bar associations” from Portuguese-speaking countries and the executive committee for the Management of the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau, in Hengqin.
The Deep Cooperation Zone is a special economic area, covering approximately 106 square kilometers, created in 2021 with a view to economic diversification and regional integration of Macau with the rest of the country.
According to the protocol, which Pedro Pais de Almeida provided to Lusa, the initiative, the Center for Economic and Commercial Services between China and Portuguese/Spanish Speaking Countries (CECPS) – created by the Government of Macau and the executive committee of the Deep Cooperation Zone – aims to “promote cooperation in cross-border arbitration between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”.
“In response to the urgent need of companies to resolve cross-border commercial and investment disputes, CECPS plans to mobilize human and material resources, in collaboration with sectoral partners from Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries, with a view to establishing an international arbitration platform that is intended to serve economic, commercial and investment cooperation between China and the respective countries”, the document reads.
All open
To promote the creation of the platform, it is proposed, among other initiatives, to study how to “integrate the particularities of legal regimes, commercial practices and arbitration and mediation procedures” in China and Portuguese-speaking countries, in addition to establishing a platform for regular dialogue to deepen professional cooperation in the fields of arbitration and mediation.
It is also noted that the initiative remains “open to future participation”, with, for example, associations or law firms, arbitrators, experts and academics being able to participate on a voluntary basis. On Wednesday, the chief executive of Macau, Sam Hou Fai, said that the CECPS has been providing “legal and accounting” services to foreign companies since “the beginning of this year”.
China established the Macau Special Administrative Region (SAR) as a platform for strengthening economic and trade cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries in 2003.
More than two decades later, Macau is expanding its focus to Spanish-speaking countries. A cooperação deve incidir, como indicou o Governo na apresentação geral das Linhas de Acção Governativa para 2025, entre outros sectores, nas áreas das finanças, cultura, turismo e comércio eletrónico transfronteiriço.
The FALP congress began on Wednesday, with a visit to Hengqin, and ends today, with a gala dinner and a tribute to two lawyers who have practiced in Macau for several decades, Jorge Neto Valente and Rui Cunha.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
Num almoço com vários convivas ouço uma amiga, que se declara espírita, a explanar sobre as particularidades da sua crença, de uma forma serena e equilibrada, diria até, sem ponta de “irracionalismo”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«If transparency is demanded from politicians, we kill them; if anyone demands fidelity to what the other was or what he says, kill him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, representation is killed. These must therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to bend the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). I believe we will be needed to decipher this frantically complex world that has fallen to us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Let men refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish, because of it the tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the pride of the countries will be destroyed.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were restricted, or if it merely lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the position of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, in a different way, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
Fui eu e a minha vergonha e o meu remorso como uma sombra
[deformed
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piela than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Security | Japan and the United Kingdom reaffirm cooperation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/seguranca-japao-e-reino-unido-reafirmam-cooperacao/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Japan, Sanae Takaichi, and her British counterpart, Keir Starmer, this Saturday reaffirmed cooperation in security matters on the sidelines of the G20 Leaders' Summit, which ended yesterday in South Africa.
Takaichi and Starmer “agreed to continue to cooperate on security issues” and also “agreed to collaborate closely in the areas of economy and economic security”, said the Japanese Prime Minister's office yesterday, which reported on the results of a meeting between the two leaders in Johannesburg the day before.
In the first meeting between Takaichi and his British counterpart since the governor took office last month, both leaders also reaffirmed their intention to work “closely” with the United States for a “free and open” Indo-Pacific.
The statements come in the context of strong diplomatic tension between Tokyo and Beijing, since Takaichi stated in the Japanese Parliament that a military attack by China against Taiwan could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (Army) (see page 12).
Beijing responded with harsh reprimands and economic reprisals, while demanding that Takaichi recant and advising its citizens not to travel to Japan, which led to hundreds of flight suspensions.
Takaichi refused on Friday to retract his statements regarding Taiwan and maintained that this is the Japanese government's “consistent position”. At the same time, the minister reiterated her desire to maintain beneficial relations with China and launched a new call for dialogue.
Tokyo expressed its availability for a meeting between Takaichi and Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang at the G20 bilateral meetings, as China had said last Monday that there is no planned meeting between the two leaders during the summit.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:48:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Vietnam | At least 90 dead in one week due to torrential rain</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/vietname-pelo-menos-90-mortos-numa-semana-devido-a-chuvas-torrenciais/</link><description>The death toll in Vietnam in a week of torrential rains affecting the country rose to 90 yesterday, compared to 55 fatalities recorded the day before, while 12 people remain missing, authorities reported.
Floods and landslides caused by intense and prolonged rains are affecting provinces in the center and south of the country, with Dak Lak and Khanh Hoa being the hardest hit, with around fifty deaths, according to data released by the Vietnamese Ministry of Agriculture and Environment.
After days of isolation, authorities managed to distribute aid – food, supplies and clothing, among others – in the most affected and remote areas of Dak Lak, which remained without electricity, telephone signal or drinking water for days and whose inhabitants continue to use canoes, boats and surfboards to travel, official media reports.
Images published by the Vietnamese press show houses completely submerged, as well as streets with water accumulated at the height of citizens' waists. The Prime Minister of Vietnam, Pham Minh Chinh, met via videoconference with the governments of several of the affected provinces from South Africa, where he is participating as a guest at the G20 Leaders' Summit, which ended yesterday in Johannesburg.
The damage caused by the storm is estimated at around nine billion dongs (around 297 million euros), according to official assessments. The Vietnamese government will distribute 1.1 billion dongs (around 36.3 million euros) in support for the recovery of the provinces of Khanh Hoa, Dak Lak, Lam Dong and Gia Lai.
Although the rains have eased since Friday, precipitation persists in several parts of the southern half of Vietnam, indicates the Zoom.earth platform, while search and rescue work continues.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:47:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Hamas accuses Israel of violating ceasefire almost 500 times</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/gaza-hamas-acusa-israel-de-ter-violado-quase-500-vezes-cessar-fogo/</link><description>The Hamas Government, which controls the Gaza Strip, denounced yesterday that Israel violated the most recent ceasefire in Gaza, promoted by the United States and in force since October 10, 497 times.
According to the report, 27 of these violations occurred on Saturday, when a new wave of Israeli attacks across the Palestinian enclave caused 24 deaths and 87 injuries. “We condemn in the strongest terms the continued and serious systematic violations of the ceasefire agreement by the Israeli occupation authorities,” Hamas’ political office said in a statement.
Over the 44 days since the signing of the ceasefire, the Gaza Government has recorded the deaths of 342 civilians – most of them children, women and the elderly, according to the Gaza Ministry of Health –, 875 injuries and 35 arbitrary arrests in raids and raids beyond the so-called 'yellow line'.
The ‘yellow line’ is the imaginary demarcation to which Israeli troops retreated, albeit still within Gaza, when the ceasefire came into force. Between that line and Gaza's borders with Israel and Egypt, the entire perimeter, more than 50 percent of the enclave, is under Israeli military control.
The enclave authorities' new report on ceasefire violations includes 142 shootings against civilians, homes, residential neighborhoods and tents of displaced people, 21 vehicle incursions into residential and agricultural areas, crossing the 'yellow line', 228 land, aerial and artillery bombings and 100 demolitions of housing and civil infrastructure.
Yesterday, Hamas accused Israel of violating the truce “under false pretexts” and called on the mediators (United States, Egypt and Qatar) to “intervene urgently and press for these violations to cease immediately”.
“We hold the [Israeli] occupation fully responsible for all humanitarian and security repercussions resulting from these violations and affirm that its continued aggression will undermine any international effort to maintain calm,” adds the statement from the Hamas Government.
On the other side
For its part, the office of Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu said on Saturday it had launched the latest attacks, after an alleged Hamas fighter crossed the 'yellow line' and attacked Israeli soldiers. “In response, Israel eliminated five high-ranking Hamas fighters,” Netanyahu’s office assured.
Since the beginning of the Israeli military offensive, launched after the Hamas attacks on October 7, 2023, 69,733 Gazans have died, including more than 20,000 children, due to Israeli fire, and 170,863 have been injured, according to the Gaza Ministry of Health.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:44:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela | Beijing guarantees support for Maduro</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/venezuela-pequim-garante-apoio-a-maduro/</link><description>The Chinese President assured Saturday that China will continue to support Venezuela to “safeguard its sovereignty and national security, the nation's dignity and social stability”, on the eve of the Venezuelan head of state's birthday.
In a letter sent to Nicolás Maduro, and cited by the Spanish news agency, Efe, Xi Jinping rejected the “interferences of external forces” in the internal affairs of the South American country “under any pretext” and added that “China and Venezuela are close friends, dear brothers and good partners”.
Also in a letter sent by the Russian embassy in Caracas to Maduro, Russian President Vladimir Putin reiterated his commitment to Venezuela in their strategic relationship. “Without a doubt, we will continue close joint work in favor of the continued strengthening of strategic partnership relations between Moscow and Caracas,” Putin stated in the letter, which was released on Saturday by the Venezuelan Foreign Minister.
The Russian President also said he was certain that, under Maduro's mandate, Venezuela “will overcome all trials with dignity and defend its legitimate interests in these turbulent times”.
These statements come in a context of tension between Venezuela and the United States due to the sending of US military troops to the Caribbean Sea, with the argument of combating drug trafficking, but which Maduro considers to be just an attempt to remove him from power.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:35:01</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE | Beijing will “never allow” the return of Japanese militarism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/mne-pequim-nunca-permitira-o-regresso-do-militarismo-japones/</link><description>Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi made it very clear in statements during his visit to Tajikistan that China will not allow any interference by the new right-wing Japanese government in decisions regarding Taiwan
China “will never allow” the return of Japanese “militarism”, warned the head of Chinese diplomacy, Wang Yi, in a meeting with his Tajik counterpart, Sirojiddin Muhriddin, amid an escalation of tensions between Beijing and Tokyo over Taiwan. During the meeting, held on Saturday in Dushanbe, the Chinese Minister of Foreign Affairs expressed gratitude to Tajikistan for its “firm support” on issues that affect “China's fundamental interests”, including the situation in Taiwan.
“China will never allow right-wing forces in Japan to turn back the wheel of history, nor will it allow interference by external forces in the Chinese region of Taiwan or a resurgence of Japanese militarism,” said Wang, according to statements collected by the official Xinhua agency. The minister stressed that Beijing “will work with all parties to defend the international consensus” around the “one-China principle” and is keen to “jointly safeguard the achievements of victory in the Second World War”.
China and Japan are involved in a tense diplomatic dispute after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi, who has been in office for a month, said that a Chinese attack on Taiwan could justify intervention by the Japanese Self-Defense Forces.
After Takaichi's statements, China advised its citizens not to travel to Japan, which caused hundreds of flight cancellations, as well as once again banning the import of Japanese seafood, among other measures.
Stand
The Japanese Prime Minister, in turn, refused last Friday to retract her comments on Taiwan in the Japanese Parliament, considering that it was a “coherent position” of the Japanese government, and reiterated the call for dialogue with China. Beijing considers the island of Taiwan, governed autonomously since 1949, as an “inalienable part” of its territory and does not rule out the use of force to take control of it.
Japan, which broke diplomatic ties with Taipei to establish ties with Beijing in 1972, maintains close unofficial exchanges with the island as well as a security engagement with the United States.
Dispute at the UN
The Chinese government took the diplomatic dispute with Japan to the UN, accusing Tokyo of “launching a threat to use force” against Beijing and warning that it will defend itself against any “act of aggression” in the Taiwan Strait. In a letter sent Friday to UN Secretary-General António Guterres, China's ambassador to the organization, Fu Cong, stated that Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi "made provocative comments about Taiwan in a flagrant manner."
The ambassador warned that if Japan dares to intervene militarily in the Taiwan Strait, this will be considered by Beijing as an “act of aggression”. "China will resolutely exercise its right to self-defense under the UN Charter and international law and firmly defend its sovereignty and territorial integrity," Fu said.
“As a country defeated in World War II, Japan must deeply reflect on its historical crimes, strictly fulfill its political commitment regarding the Taiwan issue, immediately cease provocations and crossing red lines, and retract its erroneous statements,” concluded the Chinese diplomat.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:32:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan reiterates concern about “rapid” and “unilateral” fluctuations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/japao-reitera-preocupacao-com-flutuacoes-rapidas-e-unilaterais/</link><description>The Japanese Government yesterday reiterated its concern about the “rapid” and “unilateral” exchange rate fluctuations of the yen, when the Japanese currency reaches ten-month lows in relation to the dollar and in the face of expectations of an increase in budget expenditure.
Japan is monitoring the currency “with a high sense of urgency”, said Japanese Executive spokesman Minoru Kihara yesterday during the daily press conference, in statements collected by the Japanese news agency Kyodo. The Tokyo Stock Exchange yesterday traded the Japanese currency at around 157 yen per dollar, the lowest level since January.
On Wednesday, Japanese Finance Minister Satsuki Katayama admitted the government's concern about the weakness of the yen, which reached a minimum against the euro the day before, generating expectations of a possible intervention by the authorities to halt sudden movements.
The yen fell to 180 units per euro during trading on the New York Stock Exchange on Monday, the lowest level in relation to the community currency since its introduction in 1999, and fluctuated in the high range of 179 units during the session in Tokyo.
Katayama said it was important for currencies to move in a stable manner, reflecting economic fundamentals, and similar comments were made in the past before Japanese financial authorities intervened in the foreign exchange market to halt sharp movements in the yen.
Katayama's comments on Wednesday came a day after the publication of Japanese gross domestic product (GDP) data, which showed a contraction of 0.4 percent between July and September, the first reduction in six quarters, which led the minister to justify that there were “sufficient reasons to implement stimulus and budgetary measures”, in defense of the position of the government of conservative Sanae Takaichi, which took power in October.
Japanese currency sales operations have intensified in a context of concern about Japan's budgetary health and the impact of the mega stimulus package being finalized by Takaichi's Executive. At the same time, the expected rate increases by the Bank of Japan (BoJ) remain on pause, while the central bank analyzes the impact of US tariffs and the economic policy of the new Japanese Executive, which also contributes to the weakness of the yen.
In search of balance
One of the economists on the BoJ's policy council, Junko Koeda, insisted yesterday, however, on the need for the central bank to continue with the planned increases in the reference interest rate, which remains at 0.5 percent, which would allow the world's fourth largest economy to return to a “state of equilibrium”, Kyodo said.
The Finance Minister held a meeting on Wednesday with the governor of the BoJ, Kazuo Ueda, although, according to the publication Nikkei, which cites close sources, those responsible did not discuss in detail the situation of the yen, which contributed to the sale of the currency.
The central bank has been in favor of increasing debt costs as part of efforts to normalize monetary policy, if the economy and prices evolve in line with established targets, but Ueda warned that the real impact of the tariffs on the Japanese economy has not yet fully materialized, so the BoJ adopted a cautious stance.
To this factor was added the coming to power of Takaichi, known for his moderate budgetary stance and defender of an expansionary monetary policy, who was critical of the path of rate hikes that the BoJ began in March 2024.
The Japanese central bank last raised interest rates last January, but the “normalization” cycle was interrupted after Donald Trump's return to the White House and the aggressive tariff policy that Washington has been pursuing since then.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:39:25</pubDate></item><item><title>East Timor | President against UN headquarters in New York</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/timor-leste-presidente-contra-sede-da-onu-em-nova-iorque/</link><description>On a visit to Italy, where he received an honorary doctorate in Political Science, the Nobel Peace Prize winner defended the urgent reform of the United Nations Security Council and expressed his anguish and indignation at the situation in Gaza.
The President of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta, stated Wednesday, in Messina, Italy, that the United Nations headquarters should not remain in a city belonging to a superpower, as is the case with New York, in the United States.
“Over the last decades, we have learned important lessons”, stated Ramos-Horta, in a speech given at the University of Messina, in Italy, where he is on a working visit, highlighting that one of them is that the headquarters of the United Nations should not remain in the city of a “superpower or a permanent member of the Security Council”, that is, New York, in the United States.
In the speech, given on the occasion of the ceremony awarding the title doctor 'honoris causa' in Political Sciences, the head of State highlighted that another lesson learned is the urgent need to reform the United Nations Security Council.
“Expand its composition to 31 States, eliminate the category of permanent members and replace the veto with a qualified majority of two thirds, to be confirmed on the same day by the General Assembly”, said the Nobel Peace Prize winner, explaining that the Asian and African regions are under-represented and that the Western group is “over-represented”.
In his intervention, José Ramos-Horta also proposed that the choice of the UN Secretary General be made based on “candidacies open to any qualified citizen of a Member State”.
"With proven international experience, strong language skills, intercultural sensitivity and demonstrated responsibility in leadership and governance. Applications could be presented by universities, parliaments or governments, preferably through inter-regional coalitions", he said.
Moral abysses
In his speech, the Timorese President also addressed the situation in the Middle East. "It is impossible to stand in this pulpit without expressing the anguish and indignation caused by the extreme suffering of the Palestinian people. What is happening in Gaza and the West Bank constitutes a moral and political abyss into which we have fallen. The silent complicity of part of the international community, the ambiguous rhetoric and the continuation of arms exports are incompatible with the values ​​we claim to defend", he declared.
The head of state stated that he admires the Jewish people, but that admiration cannot prevent him from seeing “clearly the historical injustice inflicted on the Palestinian people since 1984”.
"Mass expulsions, expropriations, illegal settlements, arbitrary detentions, torture and systematic murders. Today, the accumulated consequences of 80 years of suffering have become unbearable, and human losses have reached levels that our conscience cannot ignore", stated Ramos-Horta.
The Timorese head of state also recalled a conversation with Pope Francis during which he spoke of his frustration and disillusionment with the international community due to indifference and dual criteria.
“His Holiness, with the serenity that characterizes him, simply replied: but we must continue the fight for peace”, he added.
As part of his visit, the Timorese President will be received today, in a private audience, by Pope Leo XIV, and will then have a meeting with Archbishop Paul Richard Gallagher, Secretary for Relations with States and International Organizations of the Holy See.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:34:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan's MNE guarantees that it will resolve differences with China through dialogue</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/mne-do-japao-garante-que-vai-resolver-divergencia-com-china-pelo-dialogo/</link><description>The head of Japanese diplomacy assured that he will try to resolve differences with China through dialogue, after statements by Japan's prime minister about possible intervention in Taiwan angered China.
"Communication at various levels will be essential. It has not yet been decided at which levels the conversations will be held, but by holding them in different forums, we will reduce concerns and problems and increase understanding and cooperation", said Toshimitsu Motegi.
The minister's statements were made to a parliamentary committee about Tuesday's meeting in Beijing between the head of the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs for Asian and Oceanic Affairs and his Chinese counterpart.
The meeting ended without significant progress and sparked controversy on social media after videos were posted on social media that appeared to show the Japanese envoy acting subservient and the Chinese envoy being disrespectful. “This was not at all the situation in which the meeting took place”, assured the head of Japanese diplomacy.
According to Motegi, during the meeting, the Japanese representative refuted the Chinese authorities' claims about the worsening security situation in the archipelago, used as justification to advise Chinese citizens against visiting the island, and Tokyo's position in relation to Taipei.
High voltage
Japan and China are experiencing a period of great diplomatic tension caused by statements after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi, who took office a month ago, said in the national parliament that a Chinese attack on Taiwan could justify intervention by the Japan Self-Defense Forces.
The Chinese government criticized Takaichi and urged Japan to “retract erroneous statements, stop creating problems and take concrete measures to safeguard the political basis of bilateral relations”. China also warned that it will continue to take tough measures if Tokyo does not retract its comments about Taiwan, after announcing the suspension of imports of Japanese seafood.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:32:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate | Government plans new measures against crisis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/21/imobiliario-governo-planeia-novas-medidas-contra-crise/</link><description>Chinese authorities should have a new plan to attack the crisis that has been affecting the real estate market for more than two years. Mortgage support and tax incentives are some of the measures predicted by analysts
The Chinese government is considering approving a new package of measures to revitalize the real estate market, affected by a prolonged crisis, for fear of destabilization of the financial system, Bloomberg revealed yesterday.
According to sources who requested anonymity, cited by the financial news agency, Beijing could support mortgages, reduce associated costs and increase tax incentives for real estate transactions. Possible support for mortgages – an unprecedented measure in China – could attract more buyers to the property market, whose prices have been falling for 29 consecutive months, almost two and a half years.
A first package of measures, approved in 2024, had a positive effect on the sector, but the momentum ended up losing strength. Since the beginning of the year, sales measured by land area have fallen by 6.8 percent year-on-year, and investment in real estate development has decreased by 14.7 percent.
The real estate crisis, which began at the beginning of the decade, affected household wealth, consumption and employment, resulting in a lower capacity to pay mortgages and, therefore, according to the financial rating agency Fitch, a greater risk of default for banks.
At the end of September, Chinese banks held a record US$492 billion in non-performing loans and continued to face strong pressure on interest margins.
Bloomberg also highlights that prices — both for new and used properties — suffered the biggest drops in the space of a year in October. This is despite the Chinese government removing restrictions on buying more than one home — introduced to try to cool the market during the boom years — and implementing support measures, even in metropolises like Beijing and Shanghai.
When?
Faced with economic uncertainty and the devaluation of real estate, Chinese consumers have chosen to reduce their debts. The outstanding balance of mortgages has fallen 3.9 percent since the historic peak, reached in early 2023. Bloomberg guarantees that Beijing has been discussing the new package of measures since the third quarter of 2025, but admitted that it does not know whether there is already a consensus on the specific policies to be implemented or when they will be announced.
The financial situation of Chinese real estate companies worsened after China, in August 2020, restricted bank credit to developers who had accumulated high levels of debt, mainly Evergrande, with liabilities of almost 330 billion dollars.
In recent years, Chinese authorities have launched successive measures to contain the collapse of the real estate sector. State banks opened multimillion-dollar lines of financing, giving priority to the completion of projects whose apartments had already been sold.
The crisis in the sector is seen as one of the main causes of China's economic slowdown, with the weight of real estate in the Gross Domestic Product (GDP), including indirect effects, estimated at around 30 percent, according to analysts.</description><pubDate>2025-11-21 03:30:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Independence | Ramos-Horta: It is “thanks to Xanana” that Timor-Leste is here</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/23/independencia-ramos-horta-e-gracas-ao-xanana-que-timor-leste-esta-aqui/</link><description>The Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, highlighted, in an interview with Lusa, the journey of the current prime minister and former leader of the residence, highlighting that it is “thanks to Xanana [Gusmão]” that Timor-Leste is here today.
“Xanana survived and with an impressive willpower, which few human beings can have, reorganizes the resistance, new attacks against the Indonesians”, said Ramos-Horta, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the declaration of independence, on November 28, 1975, remembering the attacks that the prime minister was the target of.
The Timorese leader lost men and suffered setbacks, but organized the clandestine network and resistance in the occupied cities. Xanana Gusmão was elected leader of the resistance and commander-in-chief of the Armed Forces for the National Liberation of Timor-Leste (FALINTL) in 1981, having launched the National Unity Policy, developed the Clandestine Front and established the National Council of Maubere Resistance, later named the National Council of Timorese Resistance.
"We reached the referendum in 1999 thanks to Xanana, not thanks to anyone else, obviously, the church got involved, because Xanana had the lucidity to talk to D. Martinho da Costa Lopes, abandon Marxism-Leninism. Thanks to Xanana that we are here today", stated the head of state.
Martinho da Costa Lopes was one of the most important figures in the Catholic Church in East Timor during the Indonesian occupation and played a central role in defending the human rights of the Timorese.
José Ramos-Horta also regretted that they now say that Xanana Gusmão is no longer the great man he was during the fight. "I say: gentlemen, now he was also the one who won the maritime border for us. I don't know who would win", he said, referring to the negotiation of maritime borders with Australia, concluded in 2018 and led by the current Prime Minister.
The President also highlighted that Xanana Gusmão was the one who took the historic decision to diversify from the Petroleum Fund in 2009, which “brought 11 billion dollars in return to Timor” and carried out the reconciliation, without persecution or judgment from anyone.
José Ramos-Horta also highlighted that it is Xanana Gusmão who “continues to have the technical competence” to discuss maritime borders with Indonesia, whose negotiation process began this year, as well as to resolve the Greater Sunrise issue, with the agreement expected to be signed at the beginning of next year.
"He wants to resolve all these issues before leaving power. He does not want to leave these very complex dossiers to the new generation", added the President.
Ideas and defenses
José Ramos-Horta stated that he was not in favor of the unilateral declaration of independence, on November 28, 1975, considering that it was made “hastily” given the imminent occupation by Indonesia.
"I was not in favor of the unilateral declaration of independence, I was, but it wasn't on November 28th. More preparation time was needed, because when you make a unilateral declaration of independence without any preparations, the result was what it was. There was no one. No one reacted", said Ramos-Horta, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary.
On November 28, 1975, the current head of state recalls a ceremony without the presence of a “single global personality” and a dark night. "The unilateral declaration of independence was made hastily for reasons determined by the circumstances of the time. The fall of Atabae [municipio de Bobonaro]", said Ramos-Horta.
"The base fell with a large onslaught of regular Indonesian forces, already deep inside Timor-Leste. First Batugadé fell, that was in October, Balibó and Maliana fell, in October and Atabai, fell in the early twenties of November. Soon after, Fretilin declared unilateral independence", explained the President.
The occupation by Indonesia took place on December 7, 1975. “Indonesian forces were already in the national territory before December 7 and the decision in Jakarta had been made in 1974 either Timor-Leste integrates into Indonesia peacefully through some pseudo-democratic act, or Timor-Leste would pass to Indonesian domination by force”, said the Timorese head of state.
The invasion is supported by the United States, Australia and some countries in the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN).
"Obviously, in that context of 1975, the United States would not support Portugal on the issue of Timor-Leste. On the issue of Timor-Leste, Indonesia weighed more, especially in the post-Vietnam war context, in which the United States was discredited and fled. For the United States and for the countries in the region, the communist threat was real and Timor-Leste was isolated, abandoned", highlighted the Nobel Peace Prize winner.
The liberation of Timor-Leste took place on August 30, 1999, when the referendum for self-determination took place, which gave victory to independence, which would eventually take place on May 20, 2002, after a transitional administration by the United Nations.
“Twenty-four years later the country is freed against all the prophets of defeat, all those who preached realism to us, to me, some said atrocious unrealism, others said a lost cause, we heard a lot, including in Portugal”, added Ramos-Horta, highlighting that Timor-Leste managed to prevail.
Defense of the constitutional amendment
José Ramos-Horta defended, in the same interview, a constitutional amendment to adopt the presidential system in the country, because there is a need for “clear authority” and “without duality” and ruled out a re-candidacy for the position.
"I believe that we should make a constitutional amendment and move to the presidential system. The President is the executive, the so-called semi-presidentialism is over", said José Ramos-Horta, in an interview with Lusa as part of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, on November 28, 1975.
Currently, Timor-Leste has a semi-presidential system with a parliamentary bias, with the Government emanating from parliament. According to the head of state, the system chosen in the Constitution, drawn up in 2001 and 2002, “has not been bad at all”, but it has been seen that instead of “instead of being a balancing factor”, it can be a “factor of instability”.
Ramos-Horta exemplified what happened in the eighth Government, after the coalition led by Xanana Gusmão won the legislative elections with an absolute majority. “Xanana is invited to form a Government, they presented the list of rulers and President Lu Olo decides to veto, he did not want to inaugurate nine members”, said the Nobel Peace Prize winner.
"It is necessary to have a clear authority and without this duality, to share power with the President. It doesn't work. It works well in Portugal", highlighted Ramos-Horta. For the Timorese President, “there is no reason” for Timor-Leste to have adopted that model, because “balance is the parliament, the judiciary”.
"These three bodies are the constitution of the State. I think everyone will agree", he said. José Ramos-Horta considered that “it is time”, after around 25 years of the current Constitution, to make “some amendments” and move to the presidential system.
"For me, Xanana Gusmão should continue. We reach 2027, my term ends, new elections in 2028. Between the period of 2027, in which I leave, and 2028, we actively work on a constitutional amendment so that the 2028 election is already based on the new Constitution, that is what I defend", he explained.
When asked by Lusa whether he did not intend to run for a new term, the President stated that he was not “at least motivated”. “I, in 2027, will go to the ceremony of transition of the portfolio to the new President at midnight on May 19, 2027 and I won't even attend the ceremony on the 20th. I'm already in AeroDili on my way to Singapore”, he stated.
Problems of the new generation
In the same conversation, José Ramos-Horta also highlighted some of the country's current problems, namely the fact that the generation after 1975 has not yet found a leader with national affirmation. He highlighted that since 2002, members of this generation have held seats in the Government and parliament.
"The new generation has been there since 2002. The problem is that the new generation has not yet found a single person to assert themselves as a national leader. They have not yet appeared. That is the problem. They are in the Government, in the courts, in parliament, all new generations", said the President in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence.
José Ramos-Horta also questioned who is the leader of the new generation that “has a national dimension”. “There is none, not one, because in a democracy you have to win the electorate”, he said, highlighting that a party is created and that party competes in the elections.
The head of state highlighted, however, that today Timor-Leste already has 210 doctorates and 1,700 masters, graduated from “good universities” and “there are people who know”. Timorese civil society has accused the current Timorese leadership, which continues to focus on figures from the resistance era, of creating obstacles to the emergence of new leaders with the capacity to respond to contemporary challenges.
Asked whether, after 50 years of the unilateral declaration of independence, the Timorese are reconciled, Ramos-Horta stated that among the “factions of [19]75 more than reconciled”. "Some have even died, the majority have died. There is no problem at all. When I see some brilliant being saying 'they are still the divisions of 75', you don't know that the majority have already died, only if they are the souls in the cemetery", said José Ramos-Horta.
According to the President, the divisions result from the democratic struggle. “I find it ridiculous, interesting, sometimes frustrating when I hear that the Timorese are divided,” said the President.
"Very well, let's all unite like it is done in North Korea, or rather, single party, single candidate, it is already known who wins the elections in North Korea, so there is not much headache, everything is simple, 97% votes for Kim Jong-un, then they do the recount and after all it was not 97%, but it was 101%. It's an option, then we are all united", joked Ramos-Horta.
But, he added, the Timorese chose democracy. "A democracy that is praised today and survives the wave of setbacks against democracy in Asia, Latin America, Africa and Europe. We are doing very well with democracy", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 18:59:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuca Roseta, fado singer: “Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/06/cuca-roseta-fadista-o-fado-e-um-samba-poesia-cantado-vindo-do-coracao/</link><description>During the pandemic, she sang for the Macau public through a video concert, but now, the fado singer gives her heart and soul to a concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra, part of the lineup for the Macau International Music Festival, next Saturday, 11th. In an interview with HM, Cuca Roseta talks about the show's lineup, her 15-year career and the truth found in her compositions.
Performs in Macau on October 11th with the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM). Tell me a little about what we can expect from this show.
Yes, we are finally going to Macau. It will be the first time because we previously did a video concert for Macau during the pandemic, and we were unable to be there physically. We now work with OCM, which is very good, and I am happy with this partnership, for being able to unite, in some way, two cultures. We are a little anxious about that fact.
The concert will have songs such as “Meu”, “Preto e Branco”, “Canção do Mar”, “Não Sei de Onde” and “Finalmente”. What does this alignment bring us?
We already had arrangements made for orchestra by Marinho de Freitas, which are extraordinary arrangements, and which will be adapted to the traditional OCM instruments. These songs are practically all written by me, lyrics and music, and tell different stories, some that I have lived myself or stories that, in some way, I have experienced someone living very closely. They are original fados. “Canção do Mar” is very old and became known in the voices of Dulce Pontes and Amália Rodrigues, and has a new arrangement. We thought it would look beautiful with OCM. Of course, there are songs that we always sing and that never leave the repertoire, linked to traditional phases of my career. There are some songs that people like and request, but we bring a completely different repertoire to what we presented at the time [in Macau, with the video concert], which was very well received. It was a concert that went very well, even though it was via video, and we received wonderful messages.
This year he released the album “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu”, which has an exclusively Brazilian repertoire, with several names in Brazilian music, such as Seu Jorge or Zeca Pagodinho. Why explore this universe, mixing it with the language of Fado?
Yes, but this year I will also release a French album with Amália Rodrigues' agent, who invited me. But “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu” came from an invitation from a great Brazilian producer to record old sambas, which have a lot to do with Fado. Even though it's a Brazilian album, all sambas, it's my saddest album of all, the most melancholic. That's why we went looking for this root of samba to find great poets and great composers that Brazil has, and who have this weight that Fado also has.
As?
Fado has a lot to do with words and composition, in fact, Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart, because there has to be this truth in the interpretation, the idea of ​​truth coming from life's experiences, in transforming the story it tells. This melancholy is in the veins of Portuguese blood and is mixed with art and music. This invitation wanted to put a fado singer to sing seriously and with the weight that Fado brings, and be able to interpret the great poets and sambas. The album [Até a Fé Se Esqueceu] has very old sambas, one of them from 1937. It is, therefore, a very strong and even very beautiful album, with great poems and composers, such as Tom Jobim, Vinicius de Morais, and wonderful partnerships with Seu Jorge and Zeca Pagodinho, who came to Fado. It's an album that made me really proud.

Therefore, it is possible to marry Fado with the joy of samba, which also has a melancholic side, right? Like the melancholy of our Fado.
In fact, when we hear the word samba we think of joy, but in fact the basis of samba is not joy. There is that phrase by Vinicius de Morais, “To make a samba beautifully you need a bit of sadness, otherwise you won’t make a samba”. So that's where the beauty of this work lies, which goes to the roots of samba and shows that there aren't that many differences between the melancholy at the root of samba and the melancholy of Fado. It's a nostalgic and melancholic album, it doesn't bring that joy. It can bring hope, and we can say that some themes bring with them this hope, which we find in Brazilian culture and drums. Because they literally put their sadness on the skirt wheel and on the drums, right? They transform sadness into dance and music, but in this work we don't see that type of samba.
Cuca also has a previous album, “Cabo Verde Nha Cretcheu”, so it can be said that she has explored, in her career, the different Portuguese-speaking sounds, going beyond Fado, mixing sounds?
This album didn't come from my will, and I think [it's a sign] that life takes me, deep down. This album was born from a tour I took across the nine islands of Cape Verde with a live recording of the mornas I sang on each island, as I sang the traditional mornas of each island. Between one island and another there are very different moraines. What I did was, after my Fado concerts, I sang two mornas and then we compiled all the songs in Creole in celebration of the fact that I was the first international artist to do the nine islands in a row. But I was also in Goa and did my concert in Concanim. I find it easy and enjoy learning the traditional songs of the countries where I am going to sing. I already sang in Moscow and learned a Russian song; I learned the songs of Goa, and in Georgia, in Tblisi, I also learned a song. It's a treat I make when I travel around the world taking Fado. But morna is wonderful and there really are similarities between this musical genre, and I wanted to bring this encounter between Fado and morna to Cape Verdeans, and this album came about, which is beautiful.
Once it goes to Macau, can we expect a song in Cantonese, or Mandarin?
Yes. By chance, I had already spoken to my manager to contact someone in this regard, so that we could discover a traditional song that I could learn.
Last year, he celebrated 15 years of career. How do you review your career, which began with the albums “Cuca Roseta” and “Raiz”?
In fact, it was great to celebrate 15 years at MEO Arena [the concert hall in Lisbon], and be able to revisit all the albums since the first. “Raiz” opened something that is rarer, which is the fado singer composing and writing her lyrics. This was a record that went wonderfully well and, from then on, it was good, because in this search for the truth that Fado has, being able to compose and write your own lyrics always means giving a little more of yourself. Each person composes and writes in their own way, and when they can do it, it is always a bit like the lines on the palm of their hand, that is, it is something unique. In this search that people make to follow standards to achieve success, I believe that success exists when we are not afraid to follow our voice and our instinct, what comes from our heart, tell our stories and sing our melodies without fear. In this way we end up becoming unique. Although it is not usual in Fado for a fado singer to compose and write, it was nice to see that my songs became important to many fans. Sometimes I have great composers and poets [to collaborate with me], but I think [writing and composing] brings out this side of the person being more truthful. My poems can never be compared to those of the great poets I have sung, but I think people feel that I am more in my own skin. In a way, this touches and moves them. Celebrating 15 years of career was the closing of a cycle and the beginning of another, and it was great to return to the “roots”, and realize that that was where the “gunpowder” lay, in the sense of not being afraid of ourselves.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 05:24:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Hui So-ying, protagonist of the film “Ah Ying”: “Representing is being human”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/30/hui-so-ying-protagonista-do-filme-ah-ying-representar-e-ser-se-humano/</link><description>In 1983, Hong Kong cinema, through the lens of Allen Fong, revealed “Ah Ying”, a film that portrays the hard life of a girl who sells fish in the market and dreams of becoming an actress. That girl was Hui So-ying and “Ah Ying” was inspired by her life. HM spoke to the actress on the sidelines of “Making Waves – 2nd Hong Kong Cinema Exhibition”, which took place this weekend in Lisbon
 
How did you get involved in this film project?
The main reason I got involved in this film was because my theater teacher passed away. So I felt like I needed to do something to honor him, because he was the one who taught me how to act. So I tried to be an actress. Later, when [director] Allen Fong met me, he found my life story interesting, and he also ended up meeting some of my family members. Then he asked if they were also interested in participating in the film, which led to many of them also ending up joining the project. The film also shows the environment in which my teacher lived, it is a portrait of experiences and stories lived by me and my teacher.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in those times. How did you prepare for the character?
The beauty of this film is closely related to the collaborations that were made, particularly in photography and costumes. It took many collaborations to create the beauty that exists in the film. It was hard work taking on the character [of Ah Ying], because the story was designed to describe some of my past experiences, and that's what the director wanted to do. But that was difficult for me, because there were some things I didn't want to face, but I had to. Of course, I later realized that, deep down, it was nothing, and I even felt relieved after finishing filming. Thinking about whether the story was a form of art or reality, when I was performing, I had to enter the situation of the moment because, in fact, the [real] episode had already passed, but I had to have certain feelings again during the performance. As an actress, it was a big test.
“Ah Ying” is considered one of the great films of the so-called “New Wave” of Hong Kong cinema. During the screening, did you expect the film to be successful?
I didn't think about it, but throughout the project I thought that Allen Fong was a very daring director, because a film of this kind had never been made in the entire history of Hong Kong cinema. It's a kind of “docudrama”, and he had the strength and courage to innovate the way he filmed it, which, at the time, was unprecedented.
What was the biggest challenge you faced in this film?
It was having to return to my old self. There were things I didn't want to face and I had to face them again, with the same feeling I had at that time.
Many years have passed between 1983 and the present. Looking back, what meaning did this film have for you, as a person and actress?
In fact, after seeing the film, I saw it as just a story. For me, acting is being human, every day is a performance.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in the 1980s and has received a restored version. What do you think this project can bring to a younger audience watching the film today?
This year the film was shown several times, and I always ask the same question, whether people don't understand the film or whether they think it can't be immersive enough. In fact, given my experience, most younger viewers responded that this is not the case, that the film is quite real. I don't think this film is outdated or out of fashion just because times have progressed or society has changed. I don't think so.
“Ah Ying” closed, in Lisbon, the second edition of “Making Waves – Hong Kong Film Festival”. How do you feel about seeing this film shown in Portugal?
I found it interesting. I never thought that the film could be shown at this exhibition, I don't know if it was because there was a restored copy. Before this new version it was more difficult to display it. The public can see a film that shows family relationships experienced in the 80s, and I think that the film can be immersive [in the theme], when it addresses family conflicts, because everyone has a family. Watching the film, you may wonder what your relationship with your family is like. Of course, I also hope you learned more about Hong Kong. But, despite this film taking place in the 80s, it focuses a lot on family and interpersonal relationships.
Is there an episode from filming that left an impression on you?
There were several moments throughout the film, but the one that left the biggest impression on me was the last scene, in the interview, in which I was talking to a chair, but it was as if I were talking to my teacher. When I see this scene again I am always moved, because my teacher has already passed away, but all of this still makes a huge impression on me.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:42:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra: “The heroic relationships” of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/03/jorge-figueira-arquitecto-e-academico-da-universidade-de-coimbra-as-relacoes-heroicas-de-macau/</link><description>He has been writing and thinking about architecture for a long time, and Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra, has been doing so in Macau since then. After a session this week in which he highlighted the former Fai Chi Kei public housing complex, by Manuel Vicente, Jorge Figueira addresses the legacy of Nuno Portas today at the Rui Cunha Foundation
 
Participate today in the conference “Nuno Portas: from Architecture to Urbanism, from Man to City”. What legacy did this Portuguese architect leave?
Nuno Portas is someone who, at the end of the 50s, had a critical activity that was completely innovative and pioneering in the Portuguese context. Then, in the 60s, he had a more international activity, having been the first to publicize the work of Siza Vieira. It was there that he had his first contacts with Spanish and Italian architects, mainly. During those years he also wrote two books that were also unusual, such as “Architecture for Today”, in 1964, and “City as Architecture”, in 1969. They were also an extraordinary way of trying to understand what was happening in terms of international currents in architecture. But later he also had an [important] activity as an architect alongside Nuno Teotónio Pereira, namely in the work on the Church of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, in Lisbon, and in a house in Vila Viçosa. Then, on April 25, 1974, he was appointed Secretary of State for Housing and Urbanism and launched SAAL – Outpatient Services for Local Support, a completely revolutionary social housing program, in keeping with the spirit of the time. Afterwards, Nuno Portas dedicated himself more to urban planning issues and not so much to architecture. He was linked to the beginning of Expo 98. He ended up being someone who, in the last 20 years of his work, began to have more scientific and sociological concerns, and less artistic ones. It's something he had from the beginning, but later it became the center of his activity.
Did Nuno Portas have any relationship with Macau?
I think that the relationships would not be as intense compared to other architects and contexts, but we know that Nuno Portas was in Macau at the invitation of the Government for a conference, between 2001 and 2002. It is interesting because from this passage we have echoes of what happened, such as his surprise when discovering Manuel Vicente's Ellen Liang orphanage, which he did not know about. It was Manuel Vicente's first work in Macau, in the 60s, and we know that Nuno Portas was moved when visiting this work, especially the small chapel that exists in the orphanage. It's interesting because there was no direct relationship between Manuel Vicente and Nuno Portas, they are figures at very different poles, and even opposites. There is also an interesting and positive reference to the Siza plan [Vieira, Plano de Expansão da Cidade de Macau (Areia Preta e Porto Exterior, 1982), which is being built when Nuno Portas visits Macau. It is interesting that he commented on this plan because in the 60s and 70s the relationship between Nuno Portas and Siza Vieira was no longer the same, and the fact that he made complimentary references to Siza is very interesting.
He was a student of Nuno Portas. What other aspects of your career or personality can you highlight?
I also worked with him. He was a cultured man, very intelligent and with an overwhelming memory. He was someone who liked to provoke, but in a good way, to argue, to contradict. I was lucky enough to maintain a decades-long dialogue with him, and it is this personal knowledge that I will pass on. I also notice that he was a man very close to the power in Lisbon, to the parties, but always very independent. He was a personal friend of Jorge Sampaio, he was Secretary of State, but he never had a major political role. On the one hand, this is due to his independence, but on the other he was such a controversial and intelligently restless figure, that I think power was also scared of him.
This week he also spoke at the conference “Lisbon, Porto, Macau, Maputo: Heroic Collective Housing from the 60s &amp; 70s”. How do you describe Macau’s public housing projects in those years?
There are many architects I could talk about, but I focused on the work of Manuel Vicente in Macau, namely the public housing complex in Fai Chi Kei, which was demolished and later gave rise to the project by Rui Leão and Carlota Bruni. I didn't specifically talk about Portuguese or Macanese architects, we also have names like, for example, José Maneiras. Especially because Portuguese architects have always been few in Portugal, and from the 1950s there were around 150, later increasing greatly in number. But I paid [at the conference] a tribute to the Portuguese architects who built during that period, because in a complex territory and with its vicissitudes, different from those that existed in Portugal, they knew how to carry out extraordinary architectural experiments in the field of public housing. I tried to demonstrate what was happening in Lisbon, Porto, Macau and Lourenço Marques, now Maputo, in different ways. In Macau, relationships were established, which I call heroic, in the sense that they were relationships of experimental architecture, in which people had to adapt, have their own spirit. These are architectures that already have a bit of history, as 50 or 60 years have passed, but the examples we find in these cities continue to be remarkable.
What projects do you highlight from these years?
I spoke about the “Pantera Cor-de-Rosa” housing development, by Gonçalo Byrne, in Chelas, Lisbon. I showed “Cinco Fingers”, by Vítor Figueiredo, also from Lisbon, and “Bairro da Bouça”, by Siza Vieira, in Porto. I showed the Fai Chi Kei complex, by Manuel Vicente, and a project by Pancho Guedes in Mozambique. Despite being distant in time, these are architectures that remain fundamental references from a cultural and architectural point of view. There is a kind of narrative luck in being able to talk about such different places, and with such different architects, and show how they had this heroic, experimental, moving, even radical side that the architecture of that period in particular had.
Has Macau had a positive evolution with regard to the supply of public housing?
I arrived in August and have been visiting the territory in recent years, so I have been following this process a little. Macau is, obviously, an extraordinary territory and due to the coexistence of very different cultures when it comes to housing, which here has a scale and expression completely different from that of Portugal. In Portugal there is an aversion to public housing towers, it has always been something unusual and the results that are known have not been successful for various reasons. But in Macau this is exactly what we see, public housing in towers and with a very strong expression. This has to do with the characteristics of the territory and also with a certain culture in China and Hong Kong. This does not mean that everything being built in Macau is good, there are towers and buildings with less interesting solutions or that result from a certain repetition. But there is no city that only has good architecture or good public housing. The challenge is to solve the housing problem on a large scale, something that must be studied and thought about. It is beautiful and overwhelming to see that Macau is a territory that grows day after day and it is exciting to observe this from an architectural point of view as well. That's what I'm doing, working on future projects.
Analysis projects, or academic ones?
Yes, I'm a professor and researcher at the University of Coimbra and a columnist for the Público newspaper, so my job is to analyze and investigate. I've already published a lot about Macau and I want to go back to some points that I left unresolved, so to speak. I am very encouraged by everything I have seen and the people I have spoken to, and perhaps I will increase my work on the territory from an academic and research point of view.
At a time when Portugal has a chronic housing problem, with a lack of public housing, could Macau be an example?
Not directly, because of the typological issue of the housing tower. It might not be a welcome model in the Portuguese context. But without a doubt, Portugal needs to learn from other experiences and other territories and needs to find solutions. Certainly, what is happening in Hong Kong and Macau are experiences that are very interesting to know, not to replicate, but to understand that this is a global problem [the lack of housing].
Remember Nuno Portas
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will host today, starting at 6:30 pm, the conference “Nuno Portas: from architecture to urbanism, from man to city”, with Jorge Figueira. It will be time to talk about a journey that the recently deceased architect began in 1959, with a text about the new generation of the Modern Movement in Portugal. Texts followed in the 60s and 70s with “scientific approaches”, with Nuno Portas wandering between architecture and urbanism, always in a reflective way. Nuno Portas was a “multifaceted figure, best known for launching the SAAL social housing program, which is still the subject of research and an example today”, describes Jorge Figueira in a note. The speaker is linked to the Center for Social Studies and the Department of Architecture of the University of Coimbra.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 23:33:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied the right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on permanence, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (even in 2011 the Municipal Council of Faro wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
The gentlemen we are talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a member of the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Roadsport | Badaraco took the podium on his birthday, but ended up penalized</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/roadsport-badaraco-subiu-ao-podio-em-dia-de-aniversario-mas-acabou-penalizado/</link><description>On his birthday, Badaraco recovered from 17th to reach second place on the podium. Hours after the party, the bad news arrived, with a penalty relegating him to 15th. Rui Valente was placed off the track, after recovering several positions
On his birthday, Jerónimo Badaraco climbed to second place on the podium of the Roadsport Challenge race, after starting from 17th. However, the worst came later, when the top three, all local drivers, were penalized and relegated in the general classification, for overtaking other cars that had lost their way before the starting line, after the safety car had left.
The Macanese driver had a setback when he was relegated to 15th, after an almost perfect race: “It was very unfair and I think the stewards don't know what they are doing”, said Jerónimo. "I think the decision was not transparent. After the safety car came out, several drivers hit the barriers... of course we thought they weren't going to continue in the race after those crashes and we had to overtake them", he explained. “And even if we had stopped or slowed down in the face of these drivers' missteps, we would have created a much more dangerous situation for everyone, because the cars behind us would have been surprised by our braking, meaning there would have been more accidents”, he explained.
Even so, the Macanese assured HM that the penalty would not ruin his day: “I will continue to enjoy the day, I went up to the podium, drank the champagne, took the photos… More cup, less cup, I will continue to celebrate”, he guaranteed with a laugh.
Hours earlier, Badaraco had already explained that reaching the podium in Guia “is a different feeling” that justifies “80 percent” his choice to drive 26 years ago.
The driver was also satisfied with the race, considering that no one can take away the merit of what he achieved on the track, as he rose from 17th to 2nd: "Before the race I thought a lot about how I was going to approach the start, to recover positions, and I was confident of a good result. The most important thing was not to have given up, after qualifying, and not to have stopped believing that it was possible to reach the podium", explained the Macanese driver. “I know that the Guia Circuit always has a lot of changes throughout the race, there are a lot of safety cars and yellow flags, and I knew I had the experience, and also the calm, to be able to take advantage of the opportunities”, he highlighted.
“They ruined my race”
In turn, Rui Valente gave up and appeared disappointed, due to what he considered to be an excess on the part of the driver who tried to overtake him on the inside, on the curve leading to the São Francisco road. "I don't know what was going through the driver's head who tried to overtake me. I can't understand how he saw a space that simply didn't exist!", said Valente. "I was put out of the race. When I tried to make the turn, he touched me and that was it, my rear end was damaged and I had to go back to the pits to retire", he reported.
When the crash occurred that ended the race, Valente was circulating in the top 10, even after a less successful start, following the exit of the first Safety Car. Despite this aspect, the Macanese came to believe that it was possible to achieve a result in the top five: “I had a good pace, I was confident and I think I would achieve a result in the top five... It's the races...”, he lamented.
The Macanese also took stock of a “complicated” weekend in which he was also involved in another accident during the free practice session. "To be honest, it wasn't one of the weekends I had the most fun in Macau. I had that first touch, which conditioned my qualifying. In the race I actually did well, gaining positions, but they put me off the track...", he highlighted.
At 64 years old, Rui Valente now admits that he may be left out of the next edition of the Grand Prix: “With such a difficult qualifying model for Macau and then with races with so many accidents, I will consider what to do in the future”, he confessed. “I don't want to sit still, I want to stay active and involved in different activities, so if I find an activity that occupies me and makes me feel good, maybe I'll stay out of racing next year”, he said.
Results
1st Leung Tsz Wa Toyota GR86 40m09s237
2nd Adrian Chung Toyota GR86  at 0.148
3rd  Tsang Pak Yin Toyota GR86 at 0.407
(…)
15th Jerónimo Badaraco Toyota GR86 at 29,061
High and Low
High
Jerónimo Badaraco's performance, recovering several positions, shows the importance that experience has on the circuit
Low
The safety car was on the track for too many laps, which greatly reduced the race time</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 05:00:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix Shorts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/curtas-do-grande-premio/</link><description>Spectators | More than 110 thousand passed through the stands
Over the four days of the Macau Grand Prix, more than 110 thousand people passed through the stands of the Guia Circuit, an increase compared to last year, which was marked by the passage of a typhoon. According to official figures, the good weather helped and on Thursday there were more than 15 thousand spectators, on Friday around 28 thousand and on Saturday 35 thousand. Yesterday, on the day of the main races, the number of spectators was over 32 thousand.
Tobacco | Harmony Racing fined
Driver Ye Yifei's Harmony Racing team was fined 500 euros after one of its members was caught smoking in the garage. According to the stewards' sanction, the team member was smoking when he was approached by those responsible. When he was caught, he immediately put out his cigarette, inside a glass, containing five other butts.
Great Bay | Lu Wenlong has become superior
Lu Wenlong (Lotus Emira) was the winner of the GT Cup-Greater Bay Race, finishing ahead of Han Lichao (Toyota GR Supra GT4 Evo2) and Liu Kai Shun (Lotus Emira). The experienced Leong Ian Veng (BMW M4 GT4) was the best driver in Macau, finishing in fourth place, very close to the podium. In what he admitted was a farewell to Guia, Darryl O’Young (Mercedes AMG GT4 EVO), who competed in the GT Cup for several years, did nothing more than withdraw. The Hong Kong driver crashed the Mercedes when he went head-on at the entrance to the San Francisco climb.
Organization | Satisfactory event
The coordinator of the Organizing Committee considered that the event ran satisfactorily and that it contributed, together with the National Games, to creating a festive atmosphere in Macau. Lei Si Leng highlighted the value of the seven races in the program for the Grand Prix, which he said was wonderful.
When asked about a possible return of Formula 3, the official stated that the organization will continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​to choose the races that best suit Macau. At the same time, he left the guarantee that the plan involves continuing to receive drivers of training age and that they are expected to establish themselves as the future of motorsport.</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 04:56:12</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA will continue to invest in Formula Regional in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/gp-fia-vai-continuar-a-apostar-na-formula-regional-em-macau/</link><description>The fact that the FIA ​​switched from Formula 3 to Formula Regional (FR) continues to be a recurring theme when the topic is the Macau Grand Prix. Although the show's premier race did not disappoint in this year's edition, somewhat erasing the bad image left last year, there is still a widespread feeling that the international federation deprived the Grand Prix of its favorite race.
At the end of the 72nd edition, the Coordinator of the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix, Lei Si Leng, when questioned again by the local press about a possible return of Formula 3, stated that the organization will continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​to choose the races that best suit Macau. At the same time, the director of the Macau Sports Institute left the guarantee that the plan involves continuing to receive drivers of training age and who assert themselves as the future of motorsport.
“We have been communicating closely with the FIA ​​to find out which races can be held in Macau and the FIA ​​has selected the best drivers to come and compete here”, he said, adding that he hopes “that the best drivers can come to Macau and that we continue to collaborate with the FIA ​​to organize the most suitable races for Macau”.
On the FIA ​​side, there is the conviction that FR is the discipline that best adapts to the characteristics of the Guia Circuit, a layout that remains practically unchanged after seven decades of existence. The discontent that still exists is considered natural. “Motor sport is traditional, and I don't remember any change that was well received at the beginning, even good changes” admitted Emanuele Pirro, the current president of the FIA ​​Single Seater Commission, in conversation with journalists in Macau.
The former Italian driver, a connoisseur of the Guia Circuit and winner of the Guia Race with BMW, took advantage of his time in the Macao SAR to remember that “if we look at the history of Macau, it started with Formula 2, or Formula Pacific, and then moved on to Formula 3. In 1984, a journalist could have asked: 'why don't we race in Formula 2 anymore?' I think it's inevitable. Everything has a price. For us to have the privilege of having a circuit that has remained unchanged since Throughout its history, the price to pay is to use cars that continue to be reasonably safe. And I think Formula Regional offers a good balance in terms of speed.”
In a rare interview with the specialized magazine INSIDE, the former coordinator of the Grand Prix, José Manuel Costa Antunes, warned against letting the level of the race drop. "Today, with the transition to Formula Regional and Formula 4, which is not a problem, they are just different cars, we see more inexperienced drivers", said the man who was at the helm of the event for the longest time, touching on a sensitive topic: "Some people can simply buy a seat. That is worrying. As fans, we want real races, not red flags. We owe it to the history of the Grand Prix to recover that selection process, to ensure that only the best compete here."
Numbers support the decision
Looking at the time sheets, it can be concluded that the records for the main FR race were around 2m16s, around ten seconds slower than the times recorded in the last year of the FIA F3 single-seaters, in 2023. In historical terms, these times place the FR cars on a level similar to that of the Formula 3 cars of the late 1990s. However, from a safety point of view, the speeds reached in the “Sprint” for Curva Lisboa continues to be the main concern since Sophia Flörsch’s accident in 2018. With the suction cone, speeds above 290 km/h were common in 2023 with the Dallara F3, but the change to FR cars reduced these values to around 260 km/h.
In 2026, the new Formula Regional car, the Tatuus T-326, is expected to arrive in Macau, which is equipped with a three-cylinder, 1.6-liter Toyota ATM163T engine, prepared by Autotecnica Motori, which is more powerful and efficient. The chassis was designed according to the latest FIA specifications, in order to provide improvements in terms of performance, safety and aerodynamics, facilitating overtaking and promoting more lively racing. However, although lap times are expected to drop again, top speeds will probably not be dramatically higher.
It should be noted that the change to FR was not motivated solely by security concerns. When the FIA ​​granted Formula One Management (FOM) the commercial and promotional rights for Formula 3, the territory's race became a non-championship race of an international competition, limited to the participation of the same teams that competed in the championship. This change was received unfavorably by the promoter himself, as he never played a truly intervening role within the Grand Prix. Furthermore, holding the race in Macau, in November, involved particularly demanding logistics, with a negative impact on the planning and execution of pre-season tests.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:37:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorsport | GP will continue on the TCR World Tour in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/19/automobilismo-gp-continuara-no-tcr-world-tour-em-2026/</link><description>The Macau Grand Prix will once again form part of the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour calendar next season and, once again, as the season-ending event of a competition that will increase its presence in Asia in 2026
Marcelo Lotti, president of the WSC Group, confirmed to the press, during the weekend of the 72nd Macau Grand Prix, that next year's calendar should include a race in South Korea – home country of the tire brand and championship sponsor, Kumho, as well as Hyundai, the brand with the most cars on the starting grids of the world competition -, a second race in the People's Republic of China and the traditional end-of-season round at the Guia Circuit.
To increase the presence on the Asian continent, without affecting the teams' budgets, Australia will be left out of the calendar. The championship promoter will also not move forward with the possibility of organizing a second race on the American continent, with a visit to Mexico being a certainty. Already on the “old continent”, the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour will maintain its three events, with the Portuguese city circuit of Vila Real hosting one of these events in July.
For Marcello Lotti, “the Macau Grand Prix is ​​our equivalent to Monaco”, and for the Italian businessman, “all championships need an event like this”. Despite the smaller number of entrants that this year's event gathered in the territory, “leaving Macau is obviously out of the question”.
The 2026 Kumho FIA TCR World Tour season calendar is expected to be revealed to the public on December 13, when the FIA ​​World Council meets in Tashkent, Republic of Uzbekistan, at the same time as the FIA's annual awards ceremony.
Number questions
The list of participants for the Guia Race Macau – Kumho FIA TCR World Tour Event of Macau had only seventeen of the twenty-four cars initially registered. This would have been one of the smallest starting grids ever for the highly popular Guia Race, whose first edition took place in 1972. In part, this number below expectations was due to the absence, for unknown reasons, of teams and drivers from TCR China, one of the strongest national tourism championships in the world.
Meanwhile, Marcello Lotti said during the Grand Prix weekend that TCR is preparing to welcome a new brand to the championship. However, this announcement, scheduled for next Friday, is not expected to have an impact on the starting grids of the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour, as it will be a car group that already has a presence in the championship and will replace one of its brands with another. The Italian businessman also said he was in negotiations with a second brand.
Asia's influence on today's biggest Touring Car championship is not just limited to the Koreans from Kumho and Hyundai, as the competition also features the Chinese brand Link &amp; Co, at an official level, and the Japanese counterpart Honda. At a time when electric cars, SUVs and city cars are the focus of big brands, Asian manufacturers are still among the few that invest in cars, with fuel engines, with dimensions suitable for Touring events.</description><pubDate>2025-11-19 01:34:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau GT Cup | Fuoco avenges the 2024 disaster and wins without a hitch</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/taca-gt-macau-fuoco-vinga-desastre-de-2024-e-vence-sem-espinhas/</link><description>The Italian driver finally managed to take the Ferrari to the highest place on the podium, and overtook Raffaele Marciello, the driver he collided with last year at Curva do Lisboa, when he was leading, and which earned him a retirement.
Antonio Fuoco (Ferrari 296 GT3) was the winner of the Macau GT Cup, a race that he dominated from the beginning to the end. The Italian thus avenged last year's retirement, after being forced to retire, when he was leading, after a contact with Raffaele Marciello (BMW M4 GT3), at Curva do Lisboa.
"I think it's very special to win in Macau, especially after what happened last year. But this is part of racing, and the main thing was to come back this year, and manage to do everything well", said Fuoco. "The team did everything for us to come back and win (…) I tried to make a strong start, and push hard in the last corner to open up an advantage over the rest. I pushed a lot and at a certain point I was losing control of the car in the Mandarin Curve, but everything went well", he said.
Fuoco also praised the new qualifying format, with a second session only for the best qualified: “it was a lot of fun, I think it was a good change”, he considered.
In second place was Raffaele Marciello, who had won last year, but who in this edition never showed the pace to threaten Ferrari's dominance. However, the Swiss was once again involved in collisions, this time with Alessio Picariello (Porsche 911 GT3 R), who ended up in the barriers.
“I tried to recover at the beginning and I almost managed (…) but the Ferraris had a good start and it was a difficult race”, said the driver. “The car was very difficult to drive, so at a certain point I had to realize that the important thing was to reach the end”, he added.
Porsche with different fortunes
Porsche also secured a presence on the podium, through German Laurin Heinrich (Porsche 911 GT3 R). “I knew that starting from eighth place on the grid it would be very difficult to recover, but I think I benefited when I lost a position in the qualifying race, because that way I was on the most favorable side of the starting grid”, he reported.
Heinrich also acknowledged that he did not have the pace to achieve more than the lowest place on the podium. "I tried to put pressure on Raffaele Marciello, but I felt there was no progress for him, so I knew I could only do better if he made a big mistake, which he didn't. The race went like this also to make sure there was no pressure from behind", he pointed out.
Heinrich also regretted the touch on teammate Ayhancan Guven, which caused the Turk to be left out of the race: "On the one hand I'm happy with the podium, but I'm also sad about what happened. I think my colleague had a good pace and deserved more", he lamented.
High and Low
High
On a track where it is not always easy to complete laps, the new qualifying model brings more excitement to the race
Low
Edoardo Mortara knows the Guia circuit like few others, however, the Italian's race was marked by the Lamborghini's lack of pace, driver errors and bad luck
Classification
1st Antonio Fuoco  Ferrari 296 GT3 27m29s598
2nd Raffaele Marciello BMW M4 GT3 at 3,960
3rd Laurin Heinrich Porsche 911 GT3 R a 4,609
Ye Yifei popularity phenomenon
Ye Yifei (Ferrari 296 GT3) returned to Macau, in the year in which he became the first Chinese driver to win the 24 Hours of Le Mans, the greatest achievement so far in motorsport in the Middle Kingdom. Despite racing in Macau with an Italian license, the Chinese driver was welcomed as a national hero and was one of the most sought after drivers in the paddock to take photographs and sign autographs. The driver even dreamed of victory, after starting from second place on the starting grid, but a less successful start meant he did not go beyond fifth place in the end. Nothing that would affect his popularity, given that after the race he continued to be the most sought after among fans.</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 04:54:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorcycles | Todd crowned King of Guia after driving recital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/motas-todd-coroado-o-rei-da-guia-depois-de-recital-de-conducao/</link><description>After a year in which he was declared the winner without a race, Davey Todd showed that he is currently the fastest driver on the Guia Circuit, dominating throughout the weekend. In the end, he regretted not having set a new circuit record
Davey Todd (BMW M1000RR) was the winner of the 57th edition of the Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, on a weekend in which he did not give his competition any chance. After being declared the winner of last year's edition, without there being a race due to rain, the Englishman returned and removed all doubts about the fact that he is currently the fastest driver in the category.
“It was a fantastic result,” said Todd, moments after the victory. "I knew I had a good pace, that I was strong, but that Peter was also going to be fast in the race. Fortunately, I managed to push from the start, gain a significant advantage in the first few laps, and in the end I just had to manage", he explained.
As happened last year, rain once again interfered with the organization's plans and qualifying, which was originally scheduled for Friday morning, was moved to Saturday, right before the main race.
Todd secured pole position and during the race he never let go of that place again, building a considerable advantage lap by lap, enough to cross the finish line in a wheelie.
However, the winner regretted not having taken advantage of Saturday's high pace to set a new circuit record. "I think I'm disappointed with the fact that I was close to breaking the circuit record, but, during the race, I didn't know what times I was running. I was very close, so I could have beaten that record", he lamented. “But we are here to win the race, it is not to break records, so the most important thing has been achieved”, he stressed.
In recovery
In second place was four-time Macau winner Peter Hickman (BMW M1000RR), who had to deal with gear problems on the first lap. Recovering from a major accident, the Englishman started from third and took advantage of Erno Kostamo's (BMW M1000RR) mistake, who went ahead at Curva do Lisboa, taking the middle spot on the podium.
In the end, Hickman acknowledged that he had a good pace, but was far from ideal shape: "I need to work more on my body, to gain endurance. At this point, I have the necessary strength, but I get tired quickly. I'll have to work in the winter", acknowledged Hickman.
The driver also admitted that he was scared in the first laps by Erno Kostamo's driving. “To be honest I was a little scared with the way Erno was running, because he started with a really strong pace, but he was also making big mistakes,” revealed Hickman. "Luckily he didn't fall, because if he fell I would have fallen with him. This also allowed him to gain some advantage at the beginning", he acknowledged. “Then, when he went ahead at Curva do Lisboa, I managed to have a free track, and I managed to do my race”, he indicated.
Happy running
Mistakes aside, the Finn was one of the great entertainers of the race. He started from second place, lost position at the beginning and until the Hotel Lisboa curve, still on the first lap, he managed to regain it.
Then, due to the error, he dropped to fifth place and in just over a lap he rose to third. Therefore, despite the incidents, Kostamo said he was happy with the result: "In three laps I pushed the pace a lot. It's true that I made a big mistake at Curva do Lisboa, when I missed the braking point, which was crazy", he reported. “But I’m happy with the result and for having set the fastest lap of the race,” he said.
Classification
1st  Davey Todd BMW M1000RR 29m07s289
2nd Peter Hickman BMW M1000RR at 10,021
3rd Erno Kostamo BMW M1000RR at 24,706
High and Low
High
Peter Hickman's performance shows that the pilot is recovering after the serious accident he suffered
Low
The cancellation of the qualifying session on Friday morning once again reduced track time for the Motorcycle Grand Prix</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 04:52:35</pubDate></item></channel></rss>