<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Hong Kong | Four Activists released after serving time</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/hong-kong-quatro-activistas-libertados-apos-cumprirem-pena/</link><description>Four pro-democracy activists were released yesterday in Hong Kong, after serving four years and two months, as they participated in unofficial primary elections for the opposition in 2020.
Former parliamentarians Claudia Mo, Kwok Ka-Ki, Jeremy Tam and Gary Fan were released during the dawn of three different arrests.
The safety operation was significant, with nearby police patrols and access restrictions on several roads before the operation. The release of the dissidents occurred after the court discounted the time since they were detained since the end of February 2021, waiting for trial.
After attending in court in March 2021, they were denied their request to leave on bail while awaiting trial for “conspiracy to subvert the power of the State”, according to the National Security Act.
According to a new law, passed a year ago, prisoners convicted of national security crimes have to meet more rigorous requirements to ensure early release, which makes their release unlikely.
This is the liberation of the first group of 45 Democrats convicted in the largest national security trial in the Chinese semi -autonomous region, completed in November.
In an initial decision issued on May 30, the Court of first instance considered the 14 guilty after a long process, which began after Beijing imposed the National Security Act in June 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:07:40</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Secretary says that it is up to the patients to react against mental illnesses</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/lag-2025-secretaria-diz-que-cabe-aos-doentes-reagirem-contra-doencas-mentais/</link><description>LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, defended yesterday that culture consumption and sports can help solve many problems of the population's mental forum, arguing that it is often up to the patients themselves to have another reaction to the problem.
"Everyone pays attention to the issue of psychological health, and this is one of the topics with which the government cares about this sixth term. There is a more active life, mental health is a long term work and we have to have short, medium and long term measures, but it also has to do with one's own attitude," he said.
“We know that culture and sports are important in our lives, and with sport you can, for example, live with others in a group. With the efforts of all public departments, we will reinforce policies from children's age, always thinking about interaction with parents. There are different pressures at all ages, from young people who reach higher education, they look for their first job and even the elderly. Sport can help digest all this.
More vacancies
LAM also said that recently reinforced response reinforcement measures were created. “Sport will be reinforced for everyone and in short -term schools, and health centers have created services for this area with more than ten thousand vacancies created. The Institute of Social Action has worked a lot and today we have eight open line platforms for different generations of people.”
Last year alone 90 people lost their lives due to suicide, according to health services data (SS). More external consultations were created in nine health centers, as well as financial support to two closely working associations with the community. Recently, Alvis Lo, director of the SS, said that “Community psychological services teams” were created to strengthen proximity to latent cases and provide psychiatry consultations in the community and in elderly homes.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:55:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Beaches and pools | TIME BALNEAR TURNING TOMORROW</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/praias-e-piscinas-epoca-balnear-arranca-amanha/</link><description>The bathing season will start tomorrow and extend until October 31, according to a statement issued yesterday by the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA).
According to the shared message, Dsama “has delineated in advance the bathing zones with buoys on the beaches of Hác and Cheoc Van” and will send “nursing swimmers and nursing staff” to the beaches, where they will provide “emergency medical services”, if necessary, during the bathing season.
"Citizens and bathers should pay attention to the beaches on the beaches, the rules on the safe use of the beaches and the published warnings, as well as their own state of health," was appealed by Dsama. "In case of unwilling or injury, they should avoid entering the waters and, at the same time, should avoid contact with sea creatures on the beaches and sea," he was added.
Dsama also warned that people should not fire, install camping tents, ride bikes or drive motor vehicles, so as not to disturb the other beaches users.
Authorities also admitted the possibility of the number of people on the beaches to have a sudden increase in occupational day holidays, so they ask people who before moving to the beaches consult online information, to closely plan the travels.
Also the four outdoor pools affected to the Sports Institute (ID) will open tomorrow, keeping the same operating system with three daily sessions. The facilities in question are the pool Dr. Sun Iat Sen, the pool of the Taipa Central Park, the Park of Hác-Sá pool and the Cheoc-Van pool.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Horta da Mitra | Inaugurated new staircase with paintings</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/horta-da-mitra-inaugurada-nova-escadaria-com-pinturas/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) invited local artists to paint a stone staircase in the Horta da Mitra neighborhood, specifically the stairs of Tomás da Rosa Street, right in the center of the Macau Peninsula. The paintings are part of the work with the name “The Roda do Time of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood” and, according to the IC, “enriches the local urban landscape with the portrait of historical changes in the neighborhood over a century”.
The guest artists are Lam Ka Hou, Jian Jun Cheng, Liang Jing Siang, NG Ka Mei, Un UT Keong and Ho Kon Pang, and this project was developed in partnership with the Taipa Village Cultural Association. In addition, this initiative “received the support of associations and community representatives”.
This mural painted on the stairs describes “various iconic cultural symbols and typical traits” of this zone, such as the Banana and Birds Grove in the past, explaining the origins of the name “Horta da Mitra neighborhood” or cultural events and spaces, such as the Lion market and dances in the TAC FOC Temple.
The mural "takes advantage of the gap of steps to create a three -dimensional effect, in which each mirror is adorned with colorful flowers and illustrations, displaying the vitality and human touch of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood."
Since 2021, the IC has developed several murals projects in partnership with local artists, thus highlighting “the history of origins [these places] through a fusion of cultural creativity and art”. These murals, located in places such as Travessa da Assunção, Largo do Pagoda da Barra, the outer wall of Nam Kwong warehouses on Almirante Sérgio Street, as well as Travessa da Boa Vista and the ladder of the Taipa, “became famous photography points on social networks for Macao cultural tourism,” says IC.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:59:43</pubDate></item><item><title>DRUG | Five cases involving “oil oil”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/droga-registados-cinco-casos-a-envolver-petroleo-do-espaco/</link><description>With the registration of cases of oil consumption of the space to rise to five, the authorities continue to prepare the illegalization of this drug. In addition, the purchase of displeasure tests and other equipment to combat the new phenomenon is prepared
 
The Judicial Police (PJ) subdirector, I am Sio Keong, said that until yesterday five cases related to oil oil in the territory had been detected. The number was advanced in statements to Radio Macau's Chinese channel during the Macau Forum program, with the authorities promising to take the necessary measures to fight the spread of this drug.
Among the five cases detected, all were related to the consumption of oil oil through electronic cigarettes and in two cases the existence of the drug was identified using reagent tests.
I am Sio Keong has also assured that authorities are preparing the criminalization of this drug, with the alteration of the legislation, and that they are preparing the purchase of reactive tests and other equipment, so that they can act faster when the prohibition of the new drug comes into force.
The drug called Petroleum of Space received this name because users, after consumption, feel they are in space. The main component of the drug is Ethomidate anesthetic. It is an increasingly popular drug in Hong Kong, where it has been prohibited, but there have also been cases of consumption in the interior and in Taiwan.
In the neighboring region, the authorities promised a “zero tolerance” policy, with several anti-petroleum advertising campaigns of the space, after three deaths occurred due to the consumption of this saracuous.
Frequent changes
Prior to Sou Sio Keong's statements, the revision of the Prohibition of Production, Trafficking and Unlawful Consumption of Strepening and Psychotropic Substances had been announced by the Secretary of Security Office, Chang Cheong, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ella Law.
According to the information shared at the beginning of the month, the government's proposal is practically completed, now being discussed within the Executive Council, and then entering the Legislative Assembly. In addition to ethomidate, the new list of prohibited substances will also include metomidate, propoxate and isopropoxate. The proposal must be approved in the Legislative Assembly without difficulties.
The latest revision of the drug prohibition and trafficking law took place in summer last year, when the 2-Methyl-AP-237, ethazene, ethonitazepyne, protonitazne and ADB-Bubinaca substances were prohibited.
On the fringes of drug discussion, I am Sio Keong also warned of the existence of more burlans, and now using Artificial Intelligence (IA), which can make detection more difficult. For this reason, I am indicated that the PJ has made new alert videos, explaining that the new tools can simulate the voice and image of people known to the victims.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:47:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal / blackout | Macau attentive to student security</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/portugal-apagao-macau-atento-a-seguranca-de-estudantes/</link><description>Macao authorities said yesterday that they are closely monitoring the impact of widespread energy cut in Portugal and Spain due to concerns about the safety of the students at MSAR. DSEDJ recommended that they would be in safe places, maintaining contact with family members
 
The government of Macao is aware of the impact of the electricity cut that paralyzed the Iberian Peninsula on Monday and in contact with students of MSAR in Portugal and Spain. Yesterday morning, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) issued a statement to state that "students should monitor official information, prioritize their security and maintain contact with families." Yesterday morning, the body led by Kong Chi Meng indicated that "so far, no requests for students have been registered."
Still, DSEDJ has sent alerts by mobile phone to recommend that students remain in safe places and follow the updates of local authorities and educational institutions they attend.
Although the supply of electricity has been restored, DSEDJ emphasizes that "the governments of Portugal and Spain declared the state of emergency." As such, if students in affected areas face emergency situations, they should contact the local police or the Chinese embassy or embassy, ​​through the 24 -hour line of the Global Protection and Emergency Service of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
The same statement also suggests as contact alternatives in open lines for 24 -hour tourism, Macao Economic and Commercial Delegation in Lisbon and DSEDJ itself.
Return to Normality
A widespread cut in electric supply affected on Monday, since 11:33 (18:33 in Macao), Portugal and Spain, which continued yesterday without explaining by the authorities. Closed airports, traffic congestion and traffic in large cities were some of the consequences of "blackout".
The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the center of the country. The E-Redes Electricity Distribution Network Operator reported that until midnight Monday (7 am yesterday in Macau) were partially linked 424 substations, feeding about 6.2 million customers, but cannot predict full replacement.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:42:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment | Joey Lao relativizes “light climb” of the rate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/desemprego-joey-lao-relativiza-leve-subida-da-taxa/</link><description>The 0.2 percent rising unemployment in the first quarter of this year does not worry Joey Lao, who considers normal fluctuation and below Hong Kong and Singapore levels. However, the president of the Macao Economic Association warns of the operative problems of small and medium enterprises
 
In the first three months of this year, the global unemployment rate increased by 0.2 percentage points compared to the last quarter of 2024, setting at 1.9 percent. The unemployment rate of residents had a similar climb, reaching 2.5 percent in the period under analysis.
The president of the Macao Economic Association and former Deputy Joey Lao considers that the rate fluctuation, which remains at a level of full employment, is normal.
The idea was shared in an opinion published yesterday in the newspaper or Mun, in which the economist argues that, in general, Macau's labor market maintains "good health" and that, therefore, the population need not be overwhelmed by the situation.
Despite the slight climb of unemployment, Joey Lao stressed that the global rate remains below 2 percent, a level far lower than that verified in neighboring regions. The leader of the Macao Economic Association gave as an example the unemployment rate in Hong Kong, which set at 3.2 percent in the first three months of 2025. At the same time, the general unemployment rate and the unemployment rate of Singapore residents was 2.9 percent and 3.1 percent, respectively, rising over the last three months of last year.
Good bases
The former deputy points out that the Macao government has been able to maintain unemployment at safe levels, despite the high degree of uncertainty that affects the global economy and disruption in foreign trade, showing that the economic base of Macao and the labor market maintain stability.
In the opinion article published yesterday, the economist shows greater concern about the operative difficulties of small and medium enterprises. As such, Joey Lao stressed that the government has shown that he knows the challenges faced by this segment of the business fabric and therefore release a 2025 bank credit interest bonus plan and support SMEs to reformulate their business and become more competitive.
In addition, the former deputy also stated that the government of Sam Hou Fai guaranteed in the lines of government action that, to ensure the stability of the labor market, priority will be given to residents in access to employment.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:38:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Big Bay | Sam Hou Fai considers jiangmen example below</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/grande-baia-sam-hou-fai-considera-jiangmen-exemplo-a-seguir/</link><description>The chief executive ended the visit from two days to three cities of the Great Bay, even having passed through his hometown, Zhongshan, who praised due to accelerated development
 
On a visit to Jiangmen, the chief executive said the experiences of the interior city of China are examples that Macau should follow. Sam Hou Fai's statements were cited in a statement issued by the Social Communication Office (GCS), about the trip of the leader from the large bay.
Upon being received on Monday afternoon by Chen Anming, secretary of the Jiangmen Municipal Committee of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Sam Hou Fai stated that "the city of Jiangmen is well known for their human resources and the historical cultural richness of the overseas Chinese." MSAR political leader stressed that Macau also has a large community of Chinese born outside China and should follow “Jiangmen's successful experiences” to promote this type of tourism.
Regarding cooperation between cities, the ruler of MSAR indicated "that both parties can take advantage of the common resources to develop together and create high quality tourist products in the area of ​​world cultural heritage."
On the other hand, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the “rich land resources”, Jiangmen 'good transport network ”out of the big bay and a well -installed industrial base that, considered, to create“ a great prospect of full advance ”.
Given the prospects for growth of Jiangmen, the chief executive stated that Macau "expects, jointly and hand in hand, to grasp the opportunities generated by the development of the great bay, to enjoy the current deepened base between the two cities, to take advantage of the use of each of the cities" and "create a new chapter of highly qualified development."
Other stops
Before moving to Jiangmen, the entourage led by Sam Hou Fai stopped in Zhongshan, his homeland, where he met with Guo Wenhai, secretary of the Zhongshan Municipal Committee of the Chinese Communist Party and president of the Zhongshan Municipal Popular Assembly Committee.
According to the official statement, Sam Hou Fai stressed at the meeting that Macau and Zhongshan "have a deep connection in historical terms, with frequent contact exchanges" and "have" maintained a friendly relationship. "
The chief executive also praised the hometown of having "developed quickly, presenting good trends in progress, both social and economic, with potential cooperation with Macao in various areas."
Sam Hou Fai also said "he also hopes that companies in the two locations can grab opportunities and work hand in hand in expanding their business."</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:35:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Blackout | Normality resumed yesterday, it still causes because it</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/apagao-normalidade-retomada-ontem-causa-ainda-por-apurar/</link><description>The week has started atypically on the Iberian Peninsula. It was a few minutes from 11:30 am on Monday, when a widespread electricity failure paralyzed Portugal and Spain. Only near 23h the light returned to the Portuguese house, but the dropper
 
It was an apparent normal Monday, but this normality was dissipated late in the morning with the electricity failure that gradually led to communication failures and impossibility of using mobile data. Portugal and Spain were without electricity for too many hours on Monday, an unprecedented episode in terms of energy failures.
In the case of Lisbon, the light began to fail a few minutes after 11:30 am, followed by the impossibility of communication via mobile data. Traffic in the center of the Portuguese capital became chaotic, without traffic lights in operation, generating some road accidents. Supermarkets, cafes and restaurants, with no possibility of maintaining normal operation and food properly refrigerated, closed doors. Many people, frightened by the possibility of staying several days without light, ran to supermarkets, sagging canned foods, water carboys, candles and batteries.
In addition to the unusual constraints in people's daily lives, with the suddenly closed meter and congested transport, there were suspended flights and closed airports. The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the Center of Portugal.
The circulation in the Lisbon Metropolitan (ML) was resumed at all at 08:38, Lisbon time, first in the blue and red lines at 08h, in yellow at 08:15 and green at 08:38.
"The Lisbon Metropolitano had a vast team working yesterday night [Monday] and today's dawn [Tuesday] to ensure the replacement of operating systems affected by the widespread energy failure yesterday," ML said in a statement.
Government words
In a note issued by the Portuguese government in the early hours of yesterday morning, it was said that there were already “virtually all services, including the supply of energy, restored,” Presidential Minister António Leitão Amaro told Lusa.
According to the minister, all 6.4 million customers had access to electricity in the early hours of Tuesday morning, except 800 who had faults not related to the blackout.
Leitão Amaro also said that water supply is working throughout the country, with only a few pressure difficulties in "two or three municipalities" that will be "resolved quickly".
Regarding transportation, the minister said that the "trains are working", and it is still necessary to stabilize some points of the operation, but due to the effects of 24 hours strike that took place on Monday.
About airports, “are operational,” said Leitão Amaro, recognizing that in the case of Lisbon airport, which was the most affected by energy failure and should take two days [to this day] to have stabilized flows, although the systems are all operational.
Normalized Schools and Health
The Portuguese ruler also said that, in relation to schools, the guidance issued at dawn to all directors was to open and function normally, except for cases where there may be some specific security ratio.
"The supply of fuels is normalized and did not record, at night, relevant occurrences of security or civil protection" in the country, advanced Leitão Amaro, stressing that the situation is also stabilized in health services.
"Hospitals and health centers are in terms of supply and supply to function normally," he said. "Right now, what we can say is that [energy] systems are stabilized, both in transportation and consumers supply," said the presidency minister.
In Spain there were also several embarrassment, especially at the level of transport. Pedro Sánchez, Spanish Prime Minister, said on Monday, quoted by Lusa, that this episode was unprecedented in the country. The ruler spoke to the country after the second meeting of Spain National Security Council. "All potential causes are analyzed without discarding any hypothesis," he added.
Gigawatts loss
The Spanish government leader revealed that, according to the technicians and experts of the Spanish power grid, 15 generation gigawatts "suddenly lost the system in just five seconds, something that had never happened."
According to explained, to give a dimension of the event, 15 kilowatts of generation correspond to approximately looking for total electricity in the country at the time of blackout (12:33 in Spain, 11h33 in Lisbon). "What has caused this sudden disappearance of supply" is something that experts cannot yet explain, he added.
In the early hours after the blackout, information began to circulate on a possible cyberathel who never confirmed. A few hours after the blackout, Ursula Von Der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on the LinkedIn social network that he had spoken with the prime ministers Pedro Sánchez and Luís Montenegro about the monitoring of the case.
“I reaffirmed that the European Commission has supported and monitored the situation with national and European authorities and together with our electricity coordination group. We will gather efforts and share information to help restore the electricity supply system, agreeing to maintain narrow contact,” reads one of the publications.
Eduardo Prieto, head of operations at Spanish Red Electric, told the Associated Press that the situation was not preceded by something “exceptional and extraordinary”. One of the possible causes pointed to the blackout is a rare atmospheric phenomenon, referred to as “induced atmospheric vibration”, which may have originated “anomalous oscillations” in the high voltage lines of the Spanish energy network. "These oscillations have caused synchronization failures between electrical systems, leading to successive disturbances in interconnected European networks," the Portuguese Energy company Ren to BBC told Monday afternoon. But later Ren denied this information.
Many issues
Another causes may have been technical problems in the electric network itself. Onyema NDUKA, a full -sustainability professor of energy sustainability at the University of London, said electric networks are usually interconnected because the production centers that feed them are located far from cities. This means that a power cut in a part of the grid can "lead to a waterfall effect in other areas."
"Ideally, redundancies are incorporated into the system, such as having several supply points, reserve generators located in different locations, wires and interconnected cables, etc.," he said. The solution is through energy companies to restore electricity to affected customers as soon as possible, but the procedure for doing so “has not yet been revealed,” added NDUKA.
The Portuguese authorities, cited by the AP and the local media, have so far attributed the failure of energy to unspecified technical problems, originating outside the country, but mentioned that the investigation is still underway.
The possibility of a cyberatoque is, for now, away. “Spain has mechanisms to deal with this kind of situations. Once again, I appeal to citizens to collaborate with all authorities and act responsibly and civilly, as we have always done,” wrote Pedro Sánchez on social networks. The Portuguese National Cyberrseness Center also stated in a statement that there is no evidence that the failure was caused by a computer attack.
Speaking to Euronews, Taco Engelaar, Neara Director-General, a specialist in energy infrastructure, said the interconnectivity of national networks and their systems would mean that a failure or attack would have the same net result.
"Such a widespread failure of the network is extremely unusual and can be caused by a number of factors: a physical failure on the network that provokes the power cut, a coordinated cybercar or a dramatic imbalance between demand and the supply that has made the network system exceeds the boundaries," he said.
"If it is a system failure, then the interconnectivity between the different regional and national networks can lead to the large amount of power cuts we are watching today [Monday]," he added. "The same applies to a cybership - many of these systems are linked and sharing assets - to overthrow one can overthrow many," he said. With agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:32:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Four Activists released after serving time</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/hong-kong-quatro-activistas-libertados-apos-cumprirem-pena/</link><description>Four pro-democracy activists were released yesterday in Hong Kong, after serving four years and two months, as they participated in unofficial primary elections for the opposition in 2020.
Former parliamentarians Claudia Mo, Kwok Ka-Ki, Jeremy Tam and Gary Fan were released during the dawn of three different arrests.
The safety operation was significant, with nearby police patrols and access restrictions on several roads before the operation. The release of the dissidents occurred after the court discounted the time since they were detained since the end of February 2021, waiting for trial.
After attending in court in March 2021, they were denied their request to leave on bail while awaiting trial for “conspiracy to subvert the power of the State”, according to the National Security Act.
According to a new law, passed a year ago, prisoners convicted of national security crimes have to meet more rigorous requirements to ensure early release, which makes their release unlikely.
This is the liberation of the first group of 45 Democrats convicted in the largest national security trial in the Chinese semi -autonomous region, completed in November.
In an initial decision issued on May 30, the Court of first instance considered the 14 guilty after a long process, which began after Beijing imposed the National Security Act in June 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:07:40</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Secretary says that it is up to the patients to react against mental illnesses</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/lag-2025-secretaria-diz-que-cabe-aos-doentes-reagirem-contra-doencas-mentais/</link><description>LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, defended yesterday that culture consumption and sports can help solve many problems of the population's mental forum, arguing that it is often up to the patients themselves to have another reaction to the problem.
"Everyone pays attention to the issue of psychological health, and this is one of the topics with which the government cares about this sixth term. There is a more active life, mental health is a long term work and we have to have short, medium and long term measures, but it also has to do with one's own attitude," he said.
“We know that culture and sports are important in our lives, and with sport you can, for example, live with others in a group. With the efforts of all public departments, we will reinforce policies from children's age, always thinking about interaction with parents. There are different pressures at all ages, from young people who reach higher education, they look for their first job and even the elderly. Sport can help digest all this.
More vacancies
LAM also said that recently reinforced response reinforcement measures were created. “Sport will be reinforced for everyone and in short -term schools, and health centers have created services for this area with more than ten thousand vacancies created. The Institute of Social Action has worked a lot and today we have eight open line platforms for different generations of people.”
Last year alone 90 people lost their lives due to suicide, according to health services data (SS). More external consultations were created in nine health centers, as well as financial support to two closely working associations with the community. Recently, Alvis Lo, director of the SS, said that “Community psychological services teams” were created to strengthen proximity to latent cases and provide psychiatry consultations in the community and in elderly homes.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:55:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Beaches and pools | TIME BALNEAR TURNING TOMORROW</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/praias-e-piscinas-epoca-balnear-arranca-amanha/</link><description>The bathing season will start tomorrow and extend until October 31, according to a statement issued yesterday by the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA).
According to the shared message, Dsama “has delineated in advance the bathing zones with buoys on the beaches of Hác and Cheoc Van” and will send “nursing swimmers and nursing staff” to the beaches, where they will provide “emergency medical services”, if necessary, during the bathing season.
"Citizens and bathers should pay attention to the beaches on the beaches, the rules on the safe use of the beaches and the published warnings, as well as their own state of health," was appealed by Dsama. "In case of unwilling or injury, they should avoid entering the waters and, at the same time, should avoid contact with sea creatures on the beaches and sea," he was added.
Dsama also warned that people should not fire, install camping tents, ride bikes or drive motor vehicles, so as not to disturb the other beaches users.
Authorities also admitted the possibility of the number of people on the beaches to have a sudden increase in occupational day holidays, so they ask people who before moving to the beaches consult online information, to closely plan the travels.
Also the four outdoor pools affected to the Sports Institute (ID) will open tomorrow, keeping the same operating system with three daily sessions. The facilities in question are the pool Dr. Sun Iat Sen, the pool of the Taipa Central Park, the Park of Hác-Sá pool and the Cheoc-Van pool.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Horta da Mitra | Inaugurated new staircase with paintings</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/horta-da-mitra-inaugurada-nova-escadaria-com-pinturas/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) invited local artists to paint a stone staircase in the Horta da Mitra neighborhood, specifically the stairs of Tomás da Rosa Street, right in the center of the Macau Peninsula. The paintings are part of the work with the name “The Roda do Time of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood” and, according to the IC, “enriches the local urban landscape with the portrait of historical changes in the neighborhood over a century”.
The guest artists are Lam Ka Hou, Jian Jun Cheng, Liang Jing Siang, NG Ka Mei, Un UT Keong and Ho Kon Pang, and this project was developed in partnership with the Taipa Village Cultural Association. In addition, this initiative “received the support of associations and community representatives”.
This mural painted on the stairs describes “various iconic cultural symbols and typical traits” of this zone, such as the Banana and Birds Grove in the past, explaining the origins of the name “Horta da Mitra neighborhood” or cultural events and spaces, such as the Lion market and dances in the TAC FOC Temple.
The mural "takes advantage of the gap of steps to create a three -dimensional effect, in which each mirror is adorned with colorful flowers and illustrations, displaying the vitality and human touch of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood."
Since 2021, the IC has developed several murals projects in partnership with local artists, thus highlighting “the history of origins [these places] through a fusion of cultural creativity and art”. These murals, located in places such as Travessa da Assunção, Largo do Pagoda da Barra, the outer wall of Nam Kwong warehouses on Almirante Sérgio Street, as well as Travessa da Boa Vista and the ladder of the Taipa, “became famous photography points on social networks for Macao cultural tourism,” says IC.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:59:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City | 30 years of the movie “Toy Story” celebrated on exhibition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/studio-city-30-anos-do-filme-toy-story-celebrados-em-exposicao/</link><description>The Studio City venture at Cotai presents until October 31st an exhibition dedicated to celebrating the 30th anniversary of the movie “Toy Story” from Disney and Pixar studios. According to a statement, the exhibition space has become "into a Toy Story world, providing visitors of all ages a special adventure with facilities that promise interactive experiences and show unique collection objects."
Right at the entrance of Studio City, stands out the six-meter-high Woody character who “welcomes visitors with his characteristic smile”, followed by the giant recreation of the character Andy's bedroom, in the main atrium of the venture, “decorated with furniture and large toys, making visitors feel as if they had shrunk to the size of a toy”.
The “Rescuing Woody” installation, inspired by the movie “Toy Story 2”, leads visitors to participate in a search for the character, while “Toy Story Carnival” features “two game cabins and a pop-up store with an exclusive product selection”.
Also noteworthy is that the Studio City ferris wheel has five cabins specially decorated in the image of “Toy Story”, with the characters Woody, Buzz Lightyear, Lotso, Aliens and Hamm. Studio City's restoration spaces also provide special menus thinking about the animation movie.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:58:09</pubDate></item><item><title>HSBC | HSBC profit drops 32% until March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/hsbc-lucro-do-hsbc-cai-32-ate-marco/</link><description>Banco HSBC, the largest in Europe, yesterday announced profits of $ 6,930 million in the first quarter of the year, in a 32 percent reduction in homologous terms when it had extraordinary gains.
According to the results sent yesterday to the Hong Kong Exchange, where it is quoted, the group performed above the analysts' predictions, which anticipated a net result of $ 5,390 million.
The reduction of profit in the first three months is explained by the extraordinary impact observed in the same period when sales of the activities in Canada and Argentina. Tax -free, the result fell 25 percent to $ 9,500 million, but was also above the $ 7,830 million estimated by analysts.
In turn, the financial margin fell 4.6% percent to $ 8,300 million. Quoted in a statement, HSBC CEO Georges Elhedery considered that the results reflect a “dynamics of gains, discipline in the execution of strategy” and “confidence in the ability to meet objectives”.
The bank also warned of “increasing macroeconomic uncertainty” due to commercial tariffs applied by the US executive, led by Donald Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:06:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Excursionists grow 9.1 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/turismo-excursionistas-crescem-91-por-cento/</link><description>Between January and March, the number of tour to Macau increased by 9.1 percent, compared to the same period, for a value of 550,000 people, according to data revealed yesterday by Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
At the beginning of the year, the trend of most excionalists came from the interior, from where 477,000 tour of the 550,000 arrived, a proportion of 86.7 percent of the total.
At the international market level, 60,000 tour, which represented an annual growth of 19.8 percent. In this market, more than half of the excursionists came from South Korea, a total of 33,000, which represented a growth of 43.5 percent.
During this period, hotel establishments made a total of 44,000 rooms available, a 5.8 percent reduction compared to the first quarter of 2024, justifying that some of the largest tourist enterprises have been doing room renewal works. The average occupancy rate of guest rooms was 90.1 percent, a growth of 5.2 percentage points.
The average period of permanence of guests in Macau remained 1.7 nights, meaning that in this chapter there were no changes compared to the previous year.
Still in the first quarter of the year, the number of departures of Macao residents who traveled abroad through travel agency services was 124 million, an increase of 8.7 percent in annual terms. About 31 thousand exits of residents took place on excursions, of which 27,000 had the destination the interior.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:46:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Duarte Drumond Braga</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/duarte-drumond-braga/</link><description>Arrested to a long and distant oriental princess myth, it seemed to enjoy an impalpable resentment. Half Lispector, Half Pearl Buck, had yet to be the boat of the Empire. It was even further. He then returned to tea with sadness in Benfica. Braga was his first China, Macao the second, no China.
But the Portuguese do not forgive who is different. It had no face of either Quinta do Lago, nor Moimenta da Beira. He was wearing a booth in his green buttons. It remembered a uniform of the cultural revolution. So how did you want to identify class and provenance immediately? In Braga, wouldn't there be any other China to wear?
Nobody:                   ; Portuguese literature from 50 to 80: uninteresting fictions without reference after uninteresting fictions with references. Ah, very telluric, with towers, houses and other totems. Bad weather in the tower, the house of.
However, all the women's struggles, the other's knowledge, Palpar do Si - everything is already in it, before us, waiting to be found. We arrived almost to contemporary identities et alii.
So far from the pastry Agustina with his Pataratice of Entre Douro and Minho (this yard from the northernmost palace) and so close to authors that they seem provincial but they are nothing, like Pascoaes.
However, Ondina's books get dust in the library. The keys to know China or to know the world (almost the same thing) are in the keychain. And how much pedagogy of China (a belt, a road, a rounding around the world we could also form) could not give us, how much another world?
And why don't you read Wenceslau de Moraes too? Here there is no excuse of being a woman. Is it talking about Japan? Would it be better to talk about Telheiras? But isn't it Japan, or perhaps Tibet, the true meaning of Portuguese culture? To die the world? Could it be. For when a Tibetan Ondina, a Malay Wenceslau?
People like it is to talk about their mental palace terreiros: Lisbon, or Times Square. The true, these days, will never want to know, but from now on years - and then it will be too late. It is always too far, already said the Xana of Radio Macau. Et pour cause.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Kumashiro Yuhi (1712-1772), the Japanese who lived in Nagasaki at the time of Sakoku "The Chained Country", the self-insulation policy imposed by the Edo period Shogugawa (1603-1867), has been impressed by the few foreign paintings that only by the port of his city were allowed to enter.
Born in a family of Chinese language interpreters (Totsuji), a function to which he was also destined, he soon peaked that his affinity, besides the words of the great country on the other side, had this visual art. With his immense richness of meanings, stories and possibilities of expression of the most sensitive emotions aroused by the life that passed before his eyes.
Despite the closing policy, Chan's painting monks had arrived before, which in 1661 had founded the Manpukuji temple, transmitting their particular and sophisticated understanding of painting. At this time and at the request of the local authorities, he came to his city a painter of Deqing /Zhejiang) called Shen Quan (1682-1760) whose singular approach to art was in an unexpected cross between historical, scientific knowledge and an artistic representation that integrated decorative aspects and elements of the freedom of literature painting.
Exemplary from Kumashiro's adhesion to the culture learned from Shen Quan is the horizontal painting mounted on a vertical roll, Xiwangmu, the 'Queen Mother of the West in flight' (ink and silk color, 64 x 99.3 cm, in the British museum) where modes of making different and codified visual elements of this foreign mythology are cited.
Under a pine tree, tree of the literati, embraced by a peach linked to the idea of ​​the long life, a servant with a deer who, because his stems are reborn after falling, symbolizes perseverance, extends a peach to the mother that hangs between ethereal clouds over the waters. And in the different way as they are represented, among others, the style in force at the end of the Yuan dynasty.
Shen Quan arrived in Nagasaki, according to the detailed local reports, on December 3, 1731 and left the eighteen of September 1733, but this short time was sufficient to leave his legacy in the form of a nanped "school" from his stage name. Painters who adopted his demanding conception of painting that balanced naturalism with artificialism.
In its vertical roller blossom apple tree, roses from China and a pair of birds (ink and color on silk, 94 x 107.3 cm, Metmuseum) are figurative elements whose names form a homophony in an ideogram to wish "long life for your parents". It looms the elegant Chinensis rose that is not distinguished by the perfume but its seductive incessant flowering. Renewing its beauty from late spring to the first frosts.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Four pro-democracy activists were released yesterday in Hong Kong, after serving four years and two months, as they participated in unofficial primary elections for the opposition in 2020.
Former parliamentarians Claudia Mo, Kwok Ka-Ki, Jeremy Tam and Gary Fan were released during the dawn of three different arrests.
The safety operation was significant, with nearby police patrols and access restrictions on several roads before the operation. The release of the dissidents occurred after the court discounted the time since they were detained since the end of February 2021, waiting for trial.
After attending in court in March 2021, they were denied their request to leave on bail while awaiting trial for “conspiracy to subvert the power of the State”, according to the National Security Act.
According to a new law, passed a year ago, prisoners convicted of national security crimes have to meet more rigorous requirements to ensure early release, which makes their release unlikely.
This is the liberation of the first group of 45 Democrats convicted in the largest national security trial in the Chinese semi -autonomous region, completed in November.
In an initial decision issued on May 30, the Court of first instance considered the 14 guilty after a long process, which began after Beijing imposed the National Security Act in June 2020.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Four pro-democracy activists were released yesterday in Hong Kong, after serving four years and two months, as they participated in unofficial primary elections for the opposition in 2020.
Former parliamentarians Claudia Mo, Kwok Ka-Ki, Jeremy Tam and Gary Fan were released during the dawn of three different arrests.
The safety operation was significant, with nearby police patrols and access restrictions on several roads before the operation. The release of the dissidents occurred after the court discounted the time since they were detained since the end of February 2021, waiting for trial.
After attending in court in March 2021, they were denied their request to leave on bail while awaiting trial for “conspiracy to subvert the power of the State”, according to the National Security Act.
According to a new law, passed a year ago, prisoners convicted of national security crimes have to meet more rigorous requirements to ensure early release, which makes their release unlikely.
This is the liberation of the first group of 45 Democrats convicted in the largest national security trial in the Chinese semi -autonomous region, completed in November.
In an initial decision issued on May 30, the Court of first instance considered the 14 guilty after a long process, which began after Beijing imposed the National Security Act in June 2020.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Kumashiro Yuhi (1712-1772), the Japanese who lived in Nagasaki at the time of Sakoku "The Chained Country", the self-insulation policy imposed by the Edo period Shogugawa (1603-1867), has been impressed by the few foreign paintings that only by the port of his city were allowed to enter.
Born in a family of Chinese language interpreters (Totsuji), a function to which he was also destined, he soon peaked that his affinity, besides the words of the great country on the other side, had this visual art. With his immense richness of meanings, stories and possibilities of expression of the most sensitive emotions aroused by the life that passed before his eyes.
Despite the closing policy, Chan's painting monks had arrived before, which in 1661 had founded the Manpukuji temple, transmitting their particular and sophisticated understanding of painting. At this time and at the request of the local authorities, he came to his city a painter of Deqing /Zhejiang) called Shen Quan (1682-1760) whose singular approach to art was in an unexpected cross between historical, scientific knowledge and an artistic representation that integrated decorative aspects and elements of the freedom of literature painting.
Exemplary from Kumashiro's adhesion to the culture learned from Shen Quan is the horizontal painting mounted on a vertical roll, Xiwangmu, the 'Queen Mother of the West in flight' (ink and silk color, 64 x 99.3 cm, in the British museum) where modes of making different and codified visual elements of this foreign mythology are cited.
Under a pine tree, tree of the literati, embraced by a peach linked to the idea of ​​the long life, a servant with a deer who, because his stems are reborn after falling, symbolizes perseverance, extends a peach to the mother that hangs between ethereal clouds over the waters. And in the different way as they are represented, among others, the style in force at the end of the Yuan dynasty.
Shen Quan arrived in Nagasaki, according to the detailed local reports, on December 3, 1731 and left the eighteen of September 1733, but this short time was sufficient to leave his legacy in the form of a nanped "school" from his stage name. Painters who adopted his demanding conception of painting that balanced naturalism with artificialism.
In its vertical roller blossom apple tree, roses from China and a pair of birds (ink and color on silk, 94 x 107.3 cm, Metmuseum) are figurative elements whose names form a homophony in an ideogram to wish "long life for your parents". It looms the elegant Chinensis rose that is not distinguished by the perfume but its seductive incessant flowering. Renewing its beauty from late spring to the first frosts.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Electricity cut affects Portugal, Spain and parts of southern France</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/corte-de-electricidade-afecta-portugal-espanha-e-partes-do-sul-de-franca/</link><description>A flaw of electricity affected, at 11:33 (18h33 in Macao), Portugal, Spain and some areas of southern France.
In the first moments, information and speculation about the cause of the blackout were disseminated, namely in relation to a possible large-scale cyberataque, a hypothesis that was not excluded in the first instance by the General Secretariat of Internal Administration.
Until the closing of this issue, the cause was not yet clear, nor was there an estimate for the return of electricity, but Prime Minister Luís Montenegro said he had hope that the light supply would be resumed yesterday, according to Lisbon time (7 less for Macau). However, there were news in Portuguese media that pointed to the return of electricity in various parts of the country, as well as in Spain.
The Expresso newspaper cited data collected by the operators of the electricity network in the Iberian peninsula that pointed to tension imbalances as an explanation for the "blackout" rather than a cyberatheck designed to affect energy infrastructures. Until the closing of this edition, the Portuguese government did not rule out any explanation for the incident.
The e-nodes warned that the forecast of electricity replacement remained indefinite and could be prolonged, without advance an estimate. "Given the problems of the network that persist the forecast of energy replacement remains undefined and may be prolonged," said the operator of the electricity distribution network in mainland Portugal, in a statement.
E-Redes reiterated that the supply of electricity in Portugal was being affected by upstream constraints of the distribution network, in the very high voltage network in Spain.
According to REN - national power grid, yesterday's blackout may have been caused by abnormal temperature fluctuations in Spain. The news was advanced by the BBC, which mentions an atmospheric phenomenon.
Pandemonium scenario
The incident caused chaos in the country. At airports, check-ins became manuals and began to be announced on flights at first, but were eventually canceled. TAP has issued a statement to appeal to passengers so as not to go to airports, as operation is temporarily conditioned due to blackout.
Rail traffic was also totally interrupted throughout the Iberian Peninsula. In the hospitals, emergency generators and emergency services and surgeries have been prioritized to respond to urgent cases.
In addition to the Emergency Meeting of the Council of Ministers, the National Operational Coordination Center, which is part of the entities in the context of protection and relief operations, gathered to follow the situation and adopt the necessary procedures due to the lack of energy in mainland Portugal.
The telephone and computer systems of the National Institute of Emergency Medical was operating until the closing of this edition using generators and the fuel supply posts interrupted the services.
On the other hand, the Águas de Portugal (ADP) group appealed to water consumption only for essential uses, “very moderate”, and said there were only “punctual failures”. Heard by Lusa regarding the widespread cutting of electricity and a possible water failure, the company's official source warned that there may be consumer constraints, although without advanced more concrete data.
ADP, which brings together more than a dozen water suppliers on the continent, "appeals to the use of water for the essentials only." "ADP is following the situation in all companies," the source said. The company, he added, intends to ensure that essential services have water and recalled that reservoirs have water but it takes energy to transport it, and that even the buildings themselves need energy to get water to consumers taps.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Facilitated automatic passage from foreign visitors</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/28/lag-2025-facilitada-passagem-automatica-de-visitantes-estrangeiros/</link><description>In the presentation of this year's security lines for security, Wong Sio Chak referred to the idea of ​​facilitating the entry into Macau to foreign visitors, with the creation of more automatic passage points
 
The Secretary for Security announced on Friday, plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors through the use of automatic electronic channels.
During the presentation of the Governing Action Lines Report (LAG) to 2025 in the area of ​​Security, Wong Sio Chak stated that the territory will extend the use of automatic passage points to foreign citizens without resident or work authorization.
To facilitate “exterior exchanges”, authorities will expand autoservice equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, the leader explained.
To the deputies at the Legislative Assembly, the secretary added that the government will continue to optimize iris recognition technology in border controls and to study its extension to non-residents this year.
"We are also studying ways to widen the number of users eligible for automatic passage channels, allowing more foreign tourists to benefit from faster immigration processes and more fluid circulation in the large bay," Wong said.
Speech and company
In his speech, the secretary stated that "regarding the creation of a higher level of opening abroad, the input and output services will continue to be optimized and the facilitation measures of the border passage, to ensure a safe, effective, efficient and comfortable passage."
Thus, "with a view to promoting the exchange with the outside, the automatic passage channels will also have foreigners, so that they deal with the input and exit inspection formalities through these channels."
According to official data, Macau received, in 2024, 34.9 million visitors, 23.8 percent than the previous year, but only 2.42 million were international tourists. In October last year, the Chinese Foreign Ministry extended the Portuguese visa exemption policy, thus inserting Portugal into a list that already covered another 16 European countries.
The measure, which allows the Portuguese to stay in China for tourism, business or traffic for a maximum of 15 days, in force at least until December 31, 2025.
In the same month, Continental China had announced the expansion, from 90 to 180 days, from the permanence period for foreign residents of Macao on multiple entries in the country.
The measure includes permanent and non-permanent foreign residents of Macao that move “to the interior of China for short-term tourism, trade, visit to family members, visits and other activities”.
From July, the Chinese National Immigration Administration (NIA) had already allowed foreign permanent residents from Macao and Hong Kong to request authorization to enter the interior of China, valid for a maximum of five years. The measure covers members of the Portuguese community who are permanent residents in Macao and, until then, were required to ask for a visa to travel to the other side of the border.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:26:03</pubDate></item><item><title>April 25 | The Revolution of Cloves seen by the Chinese press</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/25/25-de-abril-a-revolucao-dos-cravos-vista-pela-imprensa-chinesa/</link><description>The fall of the Estado Novo on April 25, 1974 was reported by the Chinese language press in Macao. Community concerns were revealed, namely about the permanence of the Noble Governor of Carvalho for stability and good business environment, as well as the “status quo” of Macau in the context of decolonization
 
The echoes of the April 25, 1974 revolution were late in Macao, but this did not mean absence of news in the following days, including the local Chinese press.
HM consulted some of the news of the Chinese newspapers of the time over this period, translated to Portuguese by employees of the Press Censorship Commission (CCI), the public body that worked in Macao during the Portuguese dictatorial regime. This material is today to keep the Historical-Diplomatic Archive of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Lisbon.
Its reading allows not only to realize some of the events that succeeded the revolution, but also the perceptions and concerns that the Chinese community had on what happened in Portugal.
The Chinese wanted to maintain the stability and continuation of business. And if the Noble Governor of Carvalho, in power since 1966, had been, for many, connoted with the fascist regime, and therefore had to leave, the truth is that many wanted their permanence to ensure social peace.
As read in the book “Macao in the years of the 1974-1979 Portuguese Revolution”, by Garcia Leandro, former Portuguese governor, “Macao's Chinese sought, above all, stability to be able to continue quietly to their business, and did not want conflicts or misunderstandings with Beijing or Canton”.
Administration was “weak, very badly supported technically and to be easily corrupted”, so there were “strong reasons for the local MFA [Movement of the Forces] and the CDM [Macao Democratic Center] want to change, especially for the permanent corruption and the sense of excessive weakness of the Portuguese administration, which seemed nothing to decide without preview of Chinese representatives”.
MFA explanations
Shortly after April 25, Macau was visited by two MFA representatives, namely Major Rebelo Gonçalves and Garcia Leandro himself, to explain the revolution and objectives of MFA to Portugal and the colonies, not just to the population but to journalists.
One of the meetings, with local journalists, was described by the Tai Chung newspaper on May 6, 1974. "Rebelo Gonçalves received the reporters and narrated them in detail the coup d'état. On the day (of the event), the song" Who sends the people "served as a sign of action." The CCI translator attributed to the song “Grandola, Vila Morena”, by José Afonso, chosen to be the second password of the revolution on the radio, the name “Who Mandates is the people”, in reference to the verse of the letter “The people are the one who orders the most”. The news continued, quoting Rebelo Gonçalves: he said "that the coup d'état was the desire of the people, so it achieved success in the period of one day."
Support to Nobre de Carvalho
Fallen the regime in Lisbon, and exiled Marcelo Caetano, the issue of the Governor's permanence at the head of the destinations of Macao was quickly asked. However, Nobre de Carvalho received popular support to continue, as described from the news of the newspaper SI Man, October 4, 1974.
"Portugal does not intend to modify Macau's status quo, a Portuguese delegate told Chinese traders. This delegate manifests himself pleased with the governor's re-competition campaign, promoted by several social sectors. However, Mr. General Nobre de Carvalho had already requested the dismissal of the position of governor for health reasons."
In addition, a group was created “for the collection of signatures in favor of the renewal of Mr. General Nobre de Carvalho in the position of Governor of Macao”, which were handed over to Garcia Leandro, still as MFA official. This one received "two boxes containing signatures-cadenic books." "Opinions of entities of industrial and commercial circles were transmitted, hoping that the governor can remain in Macao, which given his wide experiences and knowledge of conditionalisms, can overcome the difficulties resulting from the economic decline that now happens around the world."
But if the desire for many was the continuity of Nobre Carvalho, the departure of many civil servants began to be connoted with the change of regime. As referred to in the news of the Jornal Si Man, May 11, 1974. “The head of health and assistance services, Dr. António Joaquim Paulino, will return on the 27th of this month to mainland Portugal, which is reported to fall from Marcelo Caetano's government. The competent authorities refused to comment on the departure of Dr. Paulino.”
The newspaper also added: "However, news from Fidente Fonte reported: It is believed that the unappropriate return to Lisbon of Dr. Paulino, whose service commission in this province has not yet ended, is related to the coup (continental).
Still in early May, there were still many questions unanswered, and the newspaper SI Man associated the departure of Vasco Rocha Vieira from the territory, at the time of the military command of the Military Command, with the absence of explanations for the political situation. “A fortnight has passed a fortnight after the coup d'état in Portugal has been fully clarified that the political situation of that country was fully clarified. Although Macau is little affected by the event, the chief of staff of Portuguese troops parked in Macao, Major Rocha Vieira yesterday, which led many people to conjecture and suspect the junta of national salvation. Portuguese government had already started acting in Macau. ”
Ho Yin's explanations
Tai Chung Pou newspaper reported, on May 22, 1974, that "some Portuguese declared in Hong Kong that they were unhappy with the measures taken by the governor and the government of Macao", followed "for the metropolis to ask for the granting of freedom to the Portuguese of Macao."
Ho Yin, a striking entrepreneur and figure of the local Chinese community, who dialogue directly with the governor representing the Chinese authorities, explained in a session with “foreign reporters, as well as those of Hong Kong and Macau” about April events. These “visited Mr. Ho Yin, asking him for opinion,” describes Tai Chung Pou.
And once again, Ho Yin appealed his spirits, noting that noble Carvalho had all the legitimacy to continue as governor. "Since the Portuguese coup d'état, registered on April 25, Macau, given its special circumstances, has been felt, to date, very quiet, not undergoing any change. Mr. Governor, General Nobre de Carvalho, who has been in Macao for over seven years, has deep knowledge of the conditions of this city, having resolved many matters through conversations and wrowning great efforts to this city," Ho Yin told the journalists, according to the journalists, according to the journalists. newspaper report.
At the same meeting, the possibility of dissolution of the Legislative Assembly, proposal of the CDM, was questioned. But Ho Yin pushed any sudden political change.
“It is known that the Macao Democratic Center, consisting of some Portuguese, requested the dissolution of the Legislative Assembly and the Municipal Council [Leal Senate], as well as the remodeling of some public services. Some inhabitants thought that the assertions of that center would affect the social order, but they came to know that they were only the opinion of a small number of Portuguese, when the city is still the city quiet, after a few days. ”
The newspaper adds that Nobre de Carvalho publicly explained "that Al would not be dissolved, so the population of Macao became carefree and entrusted in the prosperity of this city." In addition, “tourists from Hong Kong, as well as abroad, also think Macao is quiet and is not affected at all,” read in Tai Chung Pou.
The Seng Pou newspaper also reported this meeting between Ho Yin and journalists, in which the Chinese community leader commented on the benefits of a democratic regime.
"Given their peculiar circumstances and due to the fact that the Portuguese and Chinese respected themselves and live in peace for a long time, Macau has not suffered any repercussions resulting from that Portuguese coup," Ho Yin said, stressing that "as for the freedom of the word, it has always existed in Macau."
However, the entrepreneur appealed to some containment in the political criticism made. "Democracy and freedom that are now verified in mainland Portugal are happiness to the Portuguese people. And the Portuguese and Chinese have lived in the past in peace, and it is expected to continue to succeed in the future. In the then, criticism of private people or public offices must be founded, since any thoughtless attack would make complications to the question, and affect its tranquility and prosperity."
Macau without decolonization
One of the questions emanating from April 25, 1974 was the most urgent process of decolonization in the so -called Portuguese Africa where the colonial war was due since 1961. First of all, the authorities clarified that Macau would be left out of this process, because “the Popular Republic of China was careful that in 1972, in the UN decolonization committee, to make it very clear that the future of these two European possessions [Macao and Hong and Hong Kong] would not be part of the agenda of the activities of that body, being the subject treated bilaterally, ”reads in the book of Garcia Leandro.
In the September 11, 1974 edition, the Tai Chung Pou newspaper wrote that “the head of the Macao Government Office, Lieutenant Colonel Henrique Manuel Lages Ribeiro, pointed out that news emanating from the news agency Reuters had been misunderstood, and that Macau has a peculiar position”, because “the way to solve his future is different from other Portuguese overseas territories.”
The words of Almeida Santos are cited, the Portuguese Minister of Interterritorial Coordination, who said “that it would be allowed to all Portuguese overseas territories to choose the form of independence as a means to solve their own problem, with the exception of Macao that, being a very special territory, requires a special way to solve your problem”. In the translation of this news, there is also a note written by the editor itself: "This means that there is no problem of independence in Macau."
The visits by Rebelo Gonçalves and Garcia Leandro Macau took place in “Finals of May, early June 1974. Almeida Santos was in Macao in September of this year and it was at this stage that Garcia Leandro was chosen governor of Macao, taking office on 13 November of this year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:18:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Blackout | Normality resumed yesterday, it still causes because it</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/apagao-normalidade-retomada-ontem-causa-ainda-por-apurar/</link><description>The week has started atypically on the Iberian Peninsula. It was a few minutes from 11:30 am on Monday, when a widespread electricity failure paralyzed Portugal and Spain. Only near 23h the light returned to the Portuguese house, but the dropper
 
It was an apparent normal Monday, but this normality was dissipated late in the morning with the electricity failure that gradually led to communication failures and impossibility of using mobile data. Portugal and Spain were without electricity for too many hours on Monday, an unprecedented episode in terms of energy failures.
In the case of Lisbon, the light began to fail a few minutes after 11:30 am, followed by the impossibility of communication via mobile data. Traffic in the center of the Portuguese capital became chaotic, without traffic lights in operation, generating some road accidents. Supermarkets, cafes and restaurants, with no possibility of maintaining normal operation and food properly refrigerated, closed doors. Many people, frightened by the possibility of staying several days without light, ran to supermarkets, sagging canned foods, water carboys, candles and batteries.
In addition to the unusual constraints in people's daily lives, with the suddenly closed meter and congested transport, there were suspended flights and closed airports. The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the Center of Portugal.
The circulation in the Lisbon Metropolitan (ML) was resumed at all at 08:38, Lisbon time, first in the blue and red lines at 08h, in yellow at 08:15 and green at 08:38.
"The Lisbon Metropolitano had a vast team working yesterday night [Monday] and today's dawn [Tuesday] to ensure the replacement of operating systems affected by the widespread energy failure yesterday," ML said in a statement.
Government words
In a note issued by the Portuguese government in the early hours of yesterday morning, it was said that there were already “virtually all services, including the supply of energy, restored,” Presidential Minister António Leitão Amaro told Lusa.
According to the minister, all 6.4 million customers had access to electricity in the early hours of Tuesday morning, except 800 who had faults not related to the blackout.
Leitão Amaro also said that water supply is working throughout the country, with only a few pressure difficulties in "two or three municipalities" that will be "resolved quickly".
Regarding transportation, the minister said that the "trains are working", and it is still necessary to stabilize some points of the operation, but due to the effects of 24 hours strike that took place on Monday.
About airports, “are operational,” said Leitão Amaro, recognizing that in the case of Lisbon airport, which was the most affected by energy failure and should take two days [to this day] to have stabilized flows, although the systems are all operational.
Normalized Schools and Health
The Portuguese ruler also said that, in relation to schools, the guidance issued at dawn to all directors was to open and function normally, except for cases where there may be some specific security ratio.
"The supply of fuels is normalized and did not record, at night, relevant occurrences of security or civil protection" in the country, advanced Leitão Amaro, stressing that the situation is also stabilized in health services.
"Hospitals and health centers are in terms of supply and supply to function normally," he said. "Right now, what we can say is that [energy] systems are stabilized, both in transportation and consumers supply," said the presidency minister.
In Spain there were also several embarrassment, especially at the level of transport. Pedro Sánchez, Spanish Prime Minister, said on Monday, quoted by Lusa, that this episode was unprecedented in the country. The ruler spoke to the country after the second meeting of Spain National Security Council. "All potential causes are analyzed without discarding any hypothesis," he added.
Gigawatts loss
The Spanish government leader revealed that, according to the technicians and experts of the Spanish power grid, 15 generation gigawatts "suddenly lost the system in just five seconds, something that had never happened."
According to explained, to give a dimension of the event, 15 kilowatts of generation correspond to approximately looking for total electricity in the country at the time of blackout (12:33 in Spain, 11h33 in Lisbon). "What has caused this sudden disappearance of supply" is something that experts cannot yet explain, he added.
In the early hours after the blackout, information began to circulate on a possible cyberathel who never confirmed. A few hours after the blackout, Ursula Von Der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on the LinkedIn social network that he had spoken with the prime ministers Pedro Sánchez and Luís Montenegro about the monitoring of the case.
“I reaffirmed that the European Commission has supported and monitored the situation with national and European authorities and together with our electricity coordination group. We will gather efforts and share information to help restore the electricity supply system, agreeing to maintain narrow contact,” reads one of the publications.
Eduardo Prieto, head of operations at Spanish Red Electric, told the Associated Press that the situation was not preceded by something “exceptional and extraordinary”. One of the possible causes pointed to the blackout is a rare atmospheric phenomenon, referred to as “induced atmospheric vibration”, which may have originated “anomalous oscillations” in the high voltage lines of the Spanish energy network. "These oscillations have caused synchronization failures between electrical systems, leading to successive disturbances in interconnected European networks," the Portuguese Energy company Ren to BBC told Monday afternoon. But later Ren denied this information.
Many issues
Another causes may have been technical problems in the electric network itself. Onyema NDUKA, a full -sustainability professor of energy sustainability at the University of London, said electric networks are usually interconnected because the production centers that feed them are located far from cities. This means that a power cut in a part of the grid can "lead to a waterfall effect in other areas."
"Ideally, redundancies are incorporated into the system, such as having several supply points, reserve generators located in different locations, wires and interconnected cables, etc.," he said. The solution is through energy companies to restore electricity to affected customers as soon as possible, but the procedure for doing so “has not yet been revealed,” added NDUKA.
The Portuguese authorities, cited by the AP and the local media, have so far attributed the failure of energy to unspecified technical problems, originating outside the country, but mentioned that the investigation is still underway.
The possibility of a cyberatoque is, for now, away. “Spain has mechanisms to deal with this kind of situations. Once again, I appeal to citizens to collaborate with all authorities and act responsibly and civilly, as we have always done,” wrote Pedro Sánchez on social networks. The Portuguese National Cyberrseness Center also stated in a statement that there is no evidence that the failure was caused by a computer attack.
Speaking to Euronews, Taco Engelaar, Neara Director-General, a specialist in energy infrastructure, said the interconnectivity of national networks and their systems would mean that a failure or attack would have the same net result.
"Such a widespread failure of the network is extremely unusual and can be caused by a number of factors: a physical failure on the network that provokes the power cut, a coordinated cybercar or a dramatic imbalance between demand and the supply that has made the network system exceeds the boundaries," he said.
"If it is a system failure, then the interconnectivity between the different regional and national networks can lead to the large amount of power cuts we are watching today [Monday]," he added. "The same applies to a cybership - many of these systems are linked and sharing assets - to overthrow one can overthrow many," he said. With agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:32:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Death | Community recalls Pope Francis' dialogue capacity</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/23/obito-comunidade-recorda-capacidade-de-dialogo-de-papa-francisco/</link><description>It was 12 years ahead of the destinations of the Catholic Church. Pope Francis died on Monday morning at the age of 88. He also participated in the Easter Sunday celebrations at the Vatican, already quite debilitated. The local Catholic community recalls its legacy of dialogue and management capacity of various crises in the church
 
Jorge Mario Bergoglio will be forever known as Pope Francis. He died on Monday at the age of 88 hours after celebrating his last Easter before a Vatican crowd. Pope Francis failed to survive the complications of bilateral pneumonia, which forced a prolonged hospitalization for weeks.
The news of Pope Francis' dead was the world and the condolence messages and tribute multiplied globally. The local Catholic community was no exception. "No doubt the Catholic community of Macau was very staring Pope Francis a lot, thanks to his smile, no doubt it was a great teaching for the local community. People have always shown a great affection for the Pope," Father Daniel Carvalho told HM.
The priest highlighted the fact that Francis was the first Pope from Latin America, more precisely from Argentina, which was "a big news for the church." Contrary to the austere image of his predecessor, Jorge Mario Bergoglio quickly conquered the sympathy of believers and non-decisions for the simplicity and dialogue capacity with various social groups and minorities.
"He was a Pope who did not stand out for his intellectuality, but for pastoral work. He proved to be a person of much dialogue, someone merciful, and very close to the simplest, suffering people. He was an extremely accessible pope, showing a side of the church that humanity may not be used to seeing. A nearest, missionary church, open to dialogue."
Asked about the future leader of the Catholic Church, Father Daniel Carvalho says it is difficult to point out a possible name for now.
"The Catholic Church today has about 120 cardinals, so when the conclave happens there is always an election, and the candidate who gets two thirds of the votes is elected Papa. It is very difficult to get in the figure that will be the next Pope. There are always several possibilities. It is very likely that it is someone from the line of Pope Francis, because many of the current cardinals have been chosen by him.
Religion “For All”
Stephen Morgan, Rector of the University of St. Joseph (USJ), recalled Pope Francis' words in Lisbon last year during the world's youth days as to the fact that “Catholicism is for everyone, everyone”. "He was able to communicate this, and I think he was also concerned with ensuring that at the highest levels of governance, the church was representative and globally."
For Stephen Morgan, Pope Francis “had a communication and connection with people”, and created roots among the Catholic Church in countries in the south of the globe.
"Many cardinals have been ordered in places like Myanmar, Timor-Leste or even Mongolia, in a kind of recognition of the global nature of Catholicism, and perhaps it is something in Latin America, from the global southern America, could promote."
Over the course of 12 years of pontificate, Pope Francis approached the LGBT community and had to deal with the scandal of sexual abuse within the church. Francisco's position in this field is another point highlighted by Stephen Morgan. "He has done a huge number of things in terms of the church's internal governance, creating mechanisms of liability. I am not sure if the liability has already happened, but these mechanisms, in the crisis of sexual abuse or management of church goods, were really very important. He had an ability to relate to" modern "people because of his informal style," said the USJ rector.
As for the future leadership of the Catholic Church, Stephen Morgan also says there are still many possibilities open, taking into account the high number of papal voters. Moreover, "one of the characteristics of this Pope's pontificate was the fact that he did not meet with cardinals many times, and his predecessors tend to meet with the cardinals much more often." "Pope Francis did not do so, so they do not truly know themselves. It can be a very short conclave, with most to say," I know no one, but I know this person. "It may be Tolentino Mendonça, for example. It can take a long time to know each other," he explained.
According to Al Jazeera, in January this year there were 252 cardinals, and 138 have election power of the new leader of the Catholic Church. The new Pope will comply with the 267th pontificate.
There are several names that may succeed Francis: In addition to the Portuguese Tolentino Mendonça, there is the Cardinals Peter Erddo, Pietro Parolin, Cardinal Secretary of State; Peter Turkson, from Ghana; Luís Tagle, from the Philippines; Mário Grech and Matteo Zuppi.
“It is worth mentioning that about 50 percent of the current cardinals come from the global south. Therefore, the idea that the new Pope can be an Asian or African, not a Latin American, is high. But who knows?” He leaves in the air Stephen Morgan.
Next journey
Pope Francis' funeral will be held within nine days and the conclave to elect his successor within a month, the Vatican announced yesterday after the pontiff's death. This Sunday, Francisco was able to speak, sitting in a wheelchair, in the context of the “Urbi et Orbi” Blessing ceremony: “Urbi”, as it is directed to Rome, and “Orbi”, also directing itself to the whole world.
In his message, he deals with an advisor, he denounced the “despicable humanitarian situation” in Gaza, and an appeal was made to ceasefire. Pope Francis also warned of "the climate of growing anti -Semitism that is spreading around the world." "I appeal to belligerents to cease fire, liberate hostages and give precious help to hungry people who yearn for a future of peace," Francisco said in the message.
"Pope Francis' self-determined mission was to transform the Catholic Church into a 'campaign hospital' to meet the people where they are, without judging them, healing them with free remedies. So many Catholics loved him deeply," said Stephen Morgan.
The Diocese of Macau yesterday issued an official note about the Pope's death, recalling that he "was called to his father's house at the Vatican in Rome at the age of 88."
“Throughout his earthly ministry, Pope Francis ardently proclaimed the infinite mercy of God, sowed hope among the faithful, traveled many lands and took care of the most fragile, becoming an exemplary model of pastoral leadership,” is referred to in the note, following a comment by Bishop Stephen Lee.
“In this sacred time of the eighth of Easter, Dom Stephen Lee, Bishop of Macau, along with all the brothers and sisters in Christ, raises fervent prayers by the eternal rest of Pope Francis' soul and that he may be received in the glory of the heavenly kingdom. mourning ”, is referred to. The diocese says it will announce the memorial ceremonies of Francisco's death.
The note also accounts for the chronology of Francisco's life, namely the birth, on December 17, 1936, in Buenos Aires, with the name of Jorge Mario Bergoglio; and the entrance to the Jesuits in 1958, having been ordered priest in 1969. In 2001 he was ordered cardinal, and about 12 years later he was chosen as a Pope.
Beijing condolences
China yesterday presented condolences for the death of Pope Francis at the age of 88, and said he intends to continue to develop his relations with the Vatican. Francisco was the first South American and Jesuit Pope in history.
"China presents its condolences for the death of Pope Francis," said Guo Jiakun, spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry at a press conference. The Holy See and China do not maintain official diplomatic relations, since the Vatican is one of about ten countries that recognize Taiwan. However, in 2018, the Pontificate of Francisco signed a historic agreement with the Chinese government about the complex question of the appointment of Catholic bishops in China.
"In recent years, China and Vatican have kept constructive contacts and friendly exchanges," said Guo Jiakun. "China is willing to make joint efforts with the Vatican to promote continuous improvement of relationships," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-23 00:57:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Countries react to the death of Pope Francis at the age of 88</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/paises-reagem-a-morte-do-papa-francisco-aos-88-anos/</link><description>Pope Francis died yesterday at 7:35 am, European time, at the home of Santa Marta's house in the Vatican. The 88 -year -old Catholic Church leader had recently been in serious condition for complications of bilateral pneumonia, but recovered in time to be present at Easter Sunday celebrations at the Vatican.
However, several country leaders reacted to the death of Francis, one of them the president of Timor-Leste, José Ramos-Horta. Quoted by Lusa, Ramos-Horta said that it was not only the Catholics who lost with the death of Pope Francis, but all religions and humanity.
"All religions, all humanity, lost someone of great importance," said President Timorese, in a video message in Tetum, from Sofia, Bulgaria, where he is on an official visit.
In the message, the Nobel Peace Nobel Prize, considers that "Pope Francis was one of the most impact on the history of the world," which "embraced the poor, the fragile." "A Pope who did not hesitate to speak against the world powers that promote war instead of peace," said Ramos-Horta, noting that Francis also denounced the powers that ignore the poor and explore the weak.
Timorese head of state also recalled Pope Francis' words when he finished a visit to Dili in September 2024. "He held in my hand and said to take good care of this dear people," he recalled.
One of the last trips made by Pope Francis was Timor-Leste during which he met with the Timorese President with the religious authorities, civil society, and a diplomatic corps accredited in the country.
The Timorese asked to continue to build and consolidate the country's institutions to "be completely able to serve the people of Timor-Leste" and that "citizens are actually represented."
"The faith that has enlightened and sustained in the past continue to inspire your gift and your future," said the Pope, remembering that now Timor-Leste has a "new horizon, with clean sky, but with new challenges to face and new problems to solve."
India reacted
Another political leader who reacted to the Pope's death was Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who pointed out Francis as "example of compassion, humility and courage."
"Deeply sad about the death of his holiness, Pope Francis. In this moment of pain and memory, I convey my sincere condolences to the world Catholic community," said Narendra Modi on social networks.
"Pope Francis will always be remembered as an example of compassion, humility, and spiritual courage by millions of people around the world. Since a young age, he has dedicated himself to realizing the ideals of Christ. It diligently served the poor and the oppressed," he added.
Modi followed his message with several photographs taken during a meeting with Francis, showing the two hugging, and thanked him for the “affection for the people of India”, where about 26 million Christians reside.
The Indian leader had several meetings with the Pope, the last of which last June, on the sidelines of the G7 summit in Italy. At a previous meeting in 2021, the Indian Prime Minister invited the Argentine Pontiff to visit India.
However, in the US, there was also a reaction to death by the US Vice President JD Vance. “My heart is with the millions of Christians from all over the world who loved him,” wrote Vance, who is currently visiting India on social networks. "I was happy to see it yesterday [Sunday], although I was obviously very sick," he added, quoted by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
The president of the Philippines, the country with the most Catholics in Asia, today lamented Pope Francis' death and said the Philippines joined the mourning for the loss of the head of the Catholic Church.
“A man of deep faith and humility, Pope Francis led not only with wisdom, but also with an open heart to all, especially the poor and forgotten,” said Ferdinand Marcos Jr. in a message on social networks. With over 118 million inhabitants, the Philippines have more than 78% of Catholics and many faithful from other Christian confessions.
"Pope Francis taught us that being a good Christian means giving kindness and mutual care. His humility brought many back to the church," Marcos said in the condolence message quoted by the Spanish news agency Efe.
"As we regret his death, we honor a life that brought hope and compassion to so many and which inspired us to love each other as Christ loved us. It is a deeply sad day," he added. Manila Cathedral will celebrate a Mass on Tuesday at 09:00 local, presided by Cardinal José Advincula, in honor of Francisco, who became head of the Catholic Church in 2013.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:56:10</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Hengqin will have a center for Lusophone and Hispanic trade</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/lag-2025-hengqin-tera-um-centro-para-comercio-lusofono-e-hispanico/</link><description>Hengqin will have a center to promote trade relations with Portuguese and Spanish -speaking countries. The news was announced by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, in the presentation of the report of the government lines for this year
 
The government announced on Friday, the establishment of a center to promote economic services between China and the Portuguese and Spanish languages ​​in the neighboring special Economic Zone of Hengqin.
The idea is to provide companies in these countries services in the “linguistic, legal, fiscal, verification of compliance with the norms, training, arbitration and mediation”, said, in the Legislative Assembly, the Secretary for the Administration and Justice of Macao, André Cheong Weng Chon.
André Cheong's words, as part of the presentation of the Government Action Lines (LAG) for this year regarding the administration and justice portfolio, meet what government leader Sam Hou Fai, announced on Monday by declaring the intention to “promote exchange and cooperation”, through Macao, China and the universe of Spanish-speaking countries.
The Macau Forum was created in 2003 and, more than two decades later, the chief executive decides to extend the focus to Castilian -speaking countries. Cooperation should focus, as indicated in the general presentation of the LAG, among other sectors, in the areas of finance, culture, tourism and transfronic electronic trade.
"These are close countries in terms of culture and language, which are part of the Latin world. And we take into account the experiences of the past, culture, the entire political, social system of these countries," said André Cheong.
As a toast
Noting that the new space has mixed management, from Macao and the in -depth cooperation zone, the official also said that the “Commercial Support Center does not override the [Macao] Forum”.
Last week, Sam Hou Fai, Macao's first leader to dominate the Portuguese language, also suggested that he was going to take a visit to Portugal, scheduled for after the Portuguese legislative elections of 18 May, to move to Spain and “start contacts”.
The deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin is a project launched by Beijing in 2021, jointly managed by Guangdong province and Macau, with an area of ​​about 106 square kilometers.
However, a number of problems persist in this special area, noticed André Cheong, referring “the insufficiency in the development of the real economy, the high rate of eviction of commercial buildings, as well as the lack of circulation of people and commercial activity”.
In the second phase of the construction of this area, said the secretary, Macau and the province of Guangdong will reinforce “the interconnection of infrastructure”, “the articulation of rules and mechanisms” and the “approach of residents of Macao and Hengqin”.
Iam | Reformation intends to simplify organic structure
After changes to the Institute's Board of Directors for Municipal Affairs (AMI), namely the departure of José Tavares from the position of President, here are new changes.
On Friday, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, said that "the current institutional organization [of AMI] does not meet the work needs of the institute itself nor to live up to the expectations of citizens", so that this year will be done "the work of restructuring in a phased way".
The objective is “to rationalize and simplify the internal organic structure, adjusting the functions based on the principles of centralized management, the reinforcement of coordination and the simplification of procedures, in order to avoid layer management and to increase the efficiency of the municipal management of IAM”.
Public function | Birth subsidy passes to 6,580 patacas
Secretary André Cheong announced on Friday that the birth allowance for civil service workers will go from index 60 to 70, which means it becomes 6,580 patacas. "The MSAR has adjusted the birth allowance, but not for the civil service, which remains in index 60. We suggest that this allowance be adjusted to 70, equivalent to about 6,580 patacas," he said.
It is recalled that the government has also announced, in these lines of governing action, the creation of the childhood allowance, which is expected to reach 15,000 children up to three years old. These children will receive 1,500 monthly patacas, ie 18 thousand patacas per year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:14:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment | Joey Lao relativizes “light climb” of the rate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/desemprego-joey-lao-relativiza-leve-subida-da-taxa/</link><description>The 0.2 percent rising unemployment in the first quarter of this year does not worry Joey Lao, who considers normal fluctuation and below Hong Kong and Singapore levels. However, the president of the Macao Economic Association warns of the operative problems of small and medium enterprises
 
In the first three months of this year, the global unemployment rate increased by 0.2 percentage points compared to the last quarter of 2024, setting at 1.9 percent. The unemployment rate of residents had a similar climb, reaching 2.5 percent in the period under analysis.
The president of the Macao Economic Association and former Deputy Joey Lao considers that the rate fluctuation, which remains at a level of full employment, is normal.
The idea was shared in an opinion published yesterday in the newspaper or Mun, in which the economist argues that, in general, Macau's labor market maintains "good health" and that, therefore, the population need not be overwhelmed by the situation.
Despite the slight climb of unemployment, Joey Lao stressed that the global rate remains below 2 percent, a level far lower than that verified in neighboring regions. The leader of the Macao Economic Association gave as an example the unemployment rate in Hong Kong, which set at 3.2 percent in the first three months of 2025. At the same time, the general unemployment rate and the unemployment rate of Singapore residents was 2.9 percent and 3.1 percent, respectively, rising over the last three months of last year.
Good bases
The former deputy points out that the Macao government has been able to maintain unemployment at safe levels, despite the high degree of uncertainty that affects the global economy and disruption in foreign trade, showing that the economic base of Macao and the labor market maintain stability.
In the opinion article published yesterday, the economist shows greater concern about the operative difficulties of small and medium enterprises. As such, Joey Lao stressed that the government has shown that he knows the challenges faced by this segment of the business fabric and therefore release a 2025 bank credit interest bonus plan and support SMEs to reformulate their business and become more competitive.
In addition, the former deputy also stated that the government of Sam Hou Fai guaranteed in the lines of government action that, to ensure the stability of the labor market, priority will be given to residents in access to employment.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:38:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Big Bay | Sam Hou Fai considers jiangmen example below</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/grande-baia-sam-hou-fai-considera-jiangmen-exemplo-a-seguir/</link><description>The chief executive ended the visit from two days to three cities of the Great Bay, even having passed through his hometown, Zhongshan, who praised due to accelerated development
 
On a visit to Jiangmen, the chief executive said the experiences of the interior city of China are examples that Macau should follow. Sam Hou Fai's statements were cited in a statement issued by the Social Communication Office (GCS), about the trip of the leader from the large bay.
Upon being received on Monday afternoon by Chen Anming, secretary of the Jiangmen Municipal Committee of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Sam Hou Fai stated that "the city of Jiangmen is well known for their human resources and the historical cultural richness of the overseas Chinese." MSAR political leader stressed that Macau also has a large community of Chinese born outside China and should follow “Jiangmen's successful experiences” to promote this type of tourism.
Regarding cooperation between cities, the ruler of MSAR indicated "that both parties can take advantage of the common resources to develop together and create high quality tourist products in the area of ​​world cultural heritage."
On the other hand, Sam Hou Fai highlighted the “rich land resources”, Jiangmen 'good transport network ”out of the big bay and a well -installed industrial base that, considered, to create“ a great prospect of full advance ”.
Given the prospects for growth of Jiangmen, the chief executive stated that Macau "expects, jointly and hand in hand, to grasp the opportunities generated by the development of the great bay, to enjoy the current deepened base between the two cities, to take advantage of the use of each of the cities" and "create a new chapter of highly qualified development."
Other stops
Before moving to Jiangmen, the entourage led by Sam Hou Fai stopped in Zhongshan, his homeland, where he met with Guo Wenhai, secretary of the Zhongshan Municipal Committee of the Chinese Communist Party and president of the Zhongshan Municipal Popular Assembly Committee.
According to the official statement, Sam Hou Fai stressed at the meeting that Macau and Zhongshan "have a deep connection in historical terms, with frequent contact exchanges" and "have" maintained a friendly relationship. "
The chief executive also praised the hometown of having "developed quickly, presenting good trends in progress, both social and economic, with potential cooperation with Macao in various areas."
Sam Hou Fai also said "he also hopes that companies in the two locations can grab opportunities and work hand in hand in expanding their business."</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:35:05</pubDate></item><item><title>HKZM Bridge | Foreign crossings rise 70%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/ponte-hkzm-travessias-de-estrangeiros-sobem-70/</link><description>From the beginning of the year, until Sunday, more than 172,000 foreign passengers have used the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge, a volume that represents an annual climb of 70 percent. In total, more than 10 million people used the bridge in the same period, almost 19 percent than last year
 
The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, the world's largest maritime crossing, recorded more than 172,000 foreign passengers by Sunday, an increase of 70 percent compared to the same period of 2024.
"This increase is largely due to the expansion of visa exemption policies by China, and Zhuhai's land border post is the only one in the Chinese continental territory that offers direct road access to Hong Kong International Airport," Chinese state news agency Xinhua said.
Until Sunday, the total number of trips through the bridge had increased by 18.9 percent in homologous terms, exceeding 10 million passengers, a goal reached 25 days earlier than in 2024.
According to Xinhua, the travels of residents in the interior of China increased 30.3 percent to 4.18 million, while the car crossings recorded in Hong Kong and Macao through the Zhuhai border post rose 32.4 percent to almost 1.2 million this year, with a daily average of 10,000, according to data provided by customs authorities.
The land in the sea
The bridge, which connects the three regions, is the longest maritime crossing in the world, with a length of about 55 kilometers, which include an underground tunnel of almost seven kilometers between two artificial islands to facilitate navigation in the Pearl River delta.
The construction of the bridge started in 2009, but was affected by delays, the death of more than 20 workers and budgetary skids. The final cost of the infrastructure is estimated at $ 16.4 billion, more than 25 percent than initially expected.
The infrastructure opened in 2018, which reduced the travel time between Macao and Hong Kong by about half, was pointed out by the China government as an important symbol of the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay Integration Policy.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:59:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Key projects will cost more than 40 billion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/economia-projectos-chave-vao-custar-mais-de-40-mil-milhoes/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai advanced with an estimate at the cost of the four projects designed to diversify the economy at a press conference exclusively for some local and average means of the Great Bay. The Chief Executive called for young people to “get out of their comfort zone” and seek opportunities in the interior of China
 
Before leaving for an official visit to Zhuhai, Zhongshan and Jiangmen, the chief executive announced details about the so-called four key projects to diversify the economy, presented in the LAG Lines (LAG) for this year. At a press conference for national media, and some selected places, Sam Hou Fai presented cost estimates for three of the four major infrastructures that will be built over the next decade.
The project that seems to have the highest invoice is the city (university) city of International Education of Macao de Hengqin which, according to local press, could cost 20 billion to the public coffers. The project, which will be built on Mountain Island, will advance with the University of Macao at the front, while the “Macao's first higher education institution implementing the pedagogical extension model in the cooperation zone in Hengqin”. The objective is the further enlargement of other public and private institutions of Macao and seek to obtain authorization to build more state reference laboratories.
According to LAG, the project aims to “create a pedagogical environment that is uniform with that of Macao, and to configure a Macao Integration Pilot Project with HENGQIN within higher education”.
The project of Macao's international and cultural neighborhood is the second most expensive on the list, with an estimated cost of 12 billion patacas. Still without a chosen place, Sam Hou Fai mentioned the Oceanus Park area and the surroundings of the Macao Tower as possibilities. "We have to build something that is iconic in the Asia-Pacific region and even worldwide. It should also reflect the cultural exchange between the West and the East in Macao and promote the main elements of Chinese culture and our historical heritage," said the Chief Executive, according to the TDM Macao channel. The public tender for this project should be launched in the second half of this year, and should last two to three years.
The project will integrate cultural, tourist and commercial elements, highlighting the Macao National Museum of Culture, the Macao International Center for Performative Arts and the International Museum of Contemporary Art.

The air from the outside
The remaining key projects are the Macao International Air Transport Hub (Porto) on the west bank of Rio das Pérolas and the Macao Sciences and Technologies Industrial Park of Research and Development. For the latter, Sam Hou Fai did not advance with an estimate of the cost.
The air transport hub has two expected phases. The first, it aims to increase the capacity and resources in terms of international airlines at Macau airport and the second, to take advantage of cooperation with Zhuhai Airport. This project has an estimated cost of 6 billion patacas.
The chief executive also left a message for the youth of Macao, advising the bet on job opportunities in the Great Bay. "We have to get out of our comfort zone and break free from the ancient mindset to be content to be comfortable in our corner. Through Hengqin, we can get into the great bay and understand the global development of the country," said the ruler.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:58:05</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Secretary says that it is up to the patients to react against mental illnesses</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/lag-2025-secretaria-diz-que-cabe-aos-doentes-reagirem-contra-doencas-mentais/</link><description>LAM, secretary for social affairs and culture, defended yesterday that culture consumption and sports can help solve many problems of the population's mental forum, arguing that it is often up to the patients themselves to have another reaction to the problem.
"Everyone pays attention to the issue of psychological health, and this is one of the topics with which the government cares about this sixth term. There is a more active life, mental health is a long term work and we have to have short, medium and long term measures, but it also has to do with one's own attitude," he said.
“We know that culture and sports are important in our lives, and with sport you can, for example, live with others in a group. With the efforts of all public departments, we will reinforce policies from children's age, always thinking about interaction with parents. There are different pressures at all ages, from young people who reach higher education, they look for their first job and even the elderly. Sport can help digest all this.
More vacancies
LAM also said that recently reinforced response reinforcement measures were created. “Sport will be reinforced for everyone and in short -term schools, and health centers have created services for this area with more than ten thousand vacancies created. The Institute of Social Action has worked a lot and today we have eight open line platforms for different generations of people.”
Last year alone 90 people lost their lives due to suicide, according to health services data (SS). More external consultations were created in nine health centers, as well as financial support to two closely working associations with the community. Recently, Alvis Lo, director of the SS, said that “Community psychological services teams” were created to strengthen proximity to latent cases and provide psychiatry consultations in the community and in elderly homes.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:55:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Islands Hospital | Promised reinforcement of health professionals</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/hospital-das-ilhas-prometido-reforco-de-profissionais-de-saude/</link><description>Yesterday's debate on the report of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) in the area of ​​Social Affairs and Culture focused on Health, namely in the lack of response from the Islands Hospital, the Peking Union Medical College Hospital.
"We know that there is a lot of pressure on the emergency service. How can there be a better distribution of workers between the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center and the Peking Union Hospital? How can our medical team be balanced with the centralization of resources," said Deputy Ella Lei.
The head of the new hospital promised a better distribution of human resources. "We have a plan in which we define to 2026 and 2027 providing a macro health service. We foresee that by 2027 our hospital staff is composed of another 1,200 people, 200 of whom will be doctors. Of course we hope to hire more places for doctors. At this time we have 150 experts. After the gradual construction of our hospital we will have greater demand from Macau and Hong Kong health professionals," he said.
Alvis Lo, director of health services, said the new hospital pay attention “to community health care and the pressure felt by the public hospital”. "We have colleagues who have left our [public] system and we have to recruit more personal to collect the departure of people for the reform. I hope the situation [human resources] can be improved," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:53:21</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | A quarter of the population of Macau will be elderly until 2041</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/lag-2025-um-quarto-da-populacao-de-macau-sera-idosa-ate-2041/</link><description>It was up to the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture yesterday to present the report of the Governing Action Lines for this year. LAM underlined the population aging scenario, hoping that up to 2041 almost 25 percent of the population will be elderly, affecting the distribution of public financial resources
 
The government said yesterday that it provides for a “superb birth rate” this decade and near a quarter of the elderly population by 2041.
"In 2029, we will enter a phase of superb birth rate. And with this phenomenon, we can already understand that this will have implications in our work force, our teaching and distribution of our resources," said the secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, when presenting, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), the lines of government action (LAG) for guardianship.
Macao registered last year 3,607 births, 105 less in terms, registering a birth rate-number of newborns by a thousand inhabitants-5.3, according to official data.
In addition, the territory registered in 2024 a fertility rate of 0.58 children, the lowest ever in Macao. Also known as fertility rate, this is an estimate of the average number of children that a woman will have until the end of the reproductive period.
The fertility rate of 0.58 is even lower than the estimate made in a report released in July by the United Nations Economic and Social Affairs Department (UNDESA): 0.68 births per woman.
In this report, the Undesa pointed out that the estimate of 0.68 was the lowest in the world. "And all our families support paradigm will also be different," Lam announced, who first went to Al as secretary of the government. The new government, which took office in December, wants to “encourage procreation”, bet on education and strengthen support to families, reinforced Lam.
“A lot of work” for doing
The secretary recalled that this year will be instituted a childhood assistance allowance, in the amount of 1,500 monthly patacas, for children under three and residents of Macao. The birth allowance “was increased” to a total of 6,500, recalled the official, also referring to the “Medically Assisted Reproduction Support Program”.
In AL, LAM indicated that until, at the end of this decade, Macao will exceed “the criterion of super -aging”. And exposed numbers: by 2024, the elderly (65 years or older) represented 14.6 percent of the total population; By 2029 should be 21.4 percent and up to 2041 almost a quarter of the population (24.8 percent).
In this sense, the secretary recalled that “there is a lot of work to do”, namely in relation to senior homes. The average waiting time to enter such an institution is 16 months, noted, stressing that more homes will be created, including private.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:51:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump and the politicization of time and climate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/trump-e-a-politizacao-do-tempo-e-do-clima/</link><description>The disagreements between Trump and meteorologists are not new. Already in the first administration he directed by him there were disagreements that echoed in the US and international press. Its intrusion in predictions about the evolution of Hurricane Dorian in 2019 caused the “American Meteorological Society” (AMS) and the “National Weather Association” (NWA) to diffuse a joint statement that there would be likely damage caused by the weather in the state of Alabama, as Mr. Trump had vatified.
Perhaps for this reason, the then president of the United States of America may have been hating meteorologists and, by dragging, climatologists. Note that being a meteorologist is different from being a climatologist. The meteorologist, among other functions, analyzes the current time and foresees its evolution for the following days, while the climatologist studies the average time of a particular region, or even on a global scale and, using computational models, prepares antevisions of what could happen in the medium and long term, and the period is covered to reach dozens of years.
While characterizing time in a particular place or region it is necessary to know the various weather parameters (temperature, moisture, atmospheric pressure, wind, cloudiness, precipitation, etc.) at a given time or a short period, to characterize the climate with the predominant time for relatively long periods. According to the world weather organization, this period should be at least thirty years.
Returning to the different between Trump and meteorologists, their interpretation in the functions of these professionals and the institutions where they develop their activity may be the reflection of their vengeful character or by the fact that it is simple, not being able to love the storms (or intensify them), or determine when phenomena such as El-Niño, La Niña, monsoons, etc., should be beginning or ends.
On the other hand, with the help of the oligarchs that have gained power in the US, the second country that most emits greenhouse gases (GHG) can certainly influence the climate. As? You can ask. The answer is simple. It is proven that the combustion of fossil fuels (oil, natural gas and mineral coal) is largely responsible for increasing the concentration of GHGs in the atmosphere, the main cause of climate change since the beginning of the industrial age. Since Trump is reversing all laws in the US that advocates the reduction of the use of such fuels, the gee concentration will continue to increase significantly, which will contribute to accentuating these changes.
The weather will probably resent the measures being taken, including the cutting of funds in all that relates to the study of climate change and their consequences. The intensification of “drill, baby, drill”, as he likes to repeat, will contribute to the imbalance that the climate is being targeted. The various components of the climate system, especially the atmosphere, the biosphere, the cryiosfera and the hydrosphere will continue to suffer the consequences of the non -accepting of the recommendations of thousands of scientists, through the IPCC, the Kyoto Protocol, the 29 COP (Conference of the Parties) agreement, etc. The atmosphere is increasingly impregnated with GEE, the biosphere is degrading with the increasingly frequent forest fires; The oceans increase in salinity caused by acid rain and the absorption of carbon dioxide; The Criosfera ice fusion rate is increasing, which has the most serious consequence of increasing sea level.
The unknown to the current US administration deals with the issues associated with climate and environment is such that, on the Official “Website” of the White House, an “Executive Order” with the title “Reinvigoring America’s Beautiful Clean Choal Industry and Amending Executive Order 14241”, dated April 8, 2025, in which one of the most polluting industries is designated by “Beautiful Industry Charcoal clean".
Megha Satyanarayana, chief editor of the opinion section of Scientific American magazine, recently asked "Why is the Trump Administration Politicizing Weather?"  In her response, she associates the financial interest with Trump's attitudes and the oligarchy that has gained power. According to her, they are ending the disagreeing voices of the easy and fast profit policy that is based on the exploration of fossil fuels. The ongoing dismissal of scientists who develop their activity in the National Weather Service (NWS), department of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), is part of this effort to end the discordant voices of their policy. Hundreds of employees were failed in NOAA as a consequence of the application of the “2025 project”, which is no more than a series of measures aimed at reducing the number and size of state agencies, according to a conservative perspective.
In its painful view, Trump administration does not see that, putting into practice this project, it is limiting the efficiency of an institution that has undoubtedly contributed to the safeguarding of lives and goods in a highly efficient way. Based on the information from the weather stations, the weather satellites and communications, the radars, the weather and climate forecast models, weather services are contributing to the prosperity of the countries where they operate. Millions of lives have been saved thanks to meteorological warning systems, based on which alerts about the evolution and approach of highly serious phenomena are prepared, such as tropical and extractic cyclones. An example of what the absence of weather information can cause, was what happened on September 8, 1900, when a hurricane hit the South Coast near Galveston in the Gulf of Mexico (Sorry Mr. Trump). At that time these storms were not yet designated by proper names, nor were sophisticated systems of meteorological warnings. About six thousand people succumbed victims to strong winds and the storm tide associated with the hurricane.
This would not happen today, thanks to the progress that, however, national weather services have benefited. The creation of the worldwide meteorological organization in 1950, the increase in the number of weather stations, the use of weather radars and satellites, the progress of telecommunications and the efficiency of the time-friendly physical-material models, made not today possible consequences of such phenomena of this type. And all this thanks to the commitment, largely, the professionals of Meteorology. And it is these same professionals who currently suffer the destructive fury of the “project 2025”.
Universities are also being victims of the state's cutting. Among these Sobresai the University of Harvard, where 161 Nobel Prizes were formed, including Albert Arnold Gore Jr., the 45th US Vice President (1993-2001), which was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2007 (together with the IPCC), due to the work developed in the dissemination of knowledge about climate change.
According to IPCC reports, there is a close relationship between increased concentration of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere and the frequency and intensity of heat waves, droughts and forest fires. The implementation of the “project 2025” may make a kind of “boomerang” effect contribute to climate deterioration, which will imply that the second most polluting country also suffers the consequences.
Meteorologist</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:03:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Happiness in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/felicidade-em-macau/</link><description>Executive Chief Sam Hoi-Fai has just announced the government lines for 2025, which contains several highlights: first, 10,000 patacas pecuniary checks continue to be distributed. Second, the pension for the elderly will increase from 3,740 monthly patacas to 3,900, the elderly subsidy increases from 9,000 annual patacas to 10,000, the voucher of the health care reimbursement program rises from 600 patacas to 700. In addition, the childhood assistance in the amount of 1,500 monthly patacas was first atrible. Several social support increased, but we didn't all listed them here.
Social support has increased, allowing the beneficiaries to have a better life, which makes everyone happy. Did the government increase several subsidies just because residents so demanded it? The answer is, of course not. Social security systems have created a diverse support network for residents.
Increasing benefits increases everyone's feeling of safety: pensions function like a hot blanket, the health system is solid support and the unprotected assistance program is like a long river in helping the weaker. These systems are not dehumanized legal provisions, but the master walls of peace of mind. These master walls try to ensure that everyone can get the essentials. Happiness is not only due to the social security system, but also from people's interactions. This kind of interaction gives us that happiness is waiting for us, and that we can find it for ourselves.
In some old tea houses, we often see customers to talk to owners for hours. Owners know that Uncle Zhang wants three parts of sugar and that Aunt Li avoids chopped green onions and prepare the food and drinks in time, waiting for old friends. Do these owners prepare food for the purpose of making money? Of course. What they want is exactly the same as customers. Owners hope to be happy as well as their customers. They all care about each other.
The small area of ​​Macau shortens our way away. If we take more than 15 minutes to drive to our destination, we say we go away. But can we think this issue from another perspective? Precisely because Macau is not big, when we left home for a day, the sun still shines when we arrive at Hac Sa Beach. A half-hour car trip drives us away from the confusion and the noise and we give us to a quiet beach. We left footprints in the sand, ate pears and smelled the salty smell of the sea. At night we can look at the stars and talk to the loved one.
Another advantage of a small town is that it is full of human warmth. In the morning, during the end-time transport, grandparents who do not know each other, sitting on several lines, tell stories about their grandchildren turning back and forth. These energetic conversations cross the noise and reach everyone's ears. The front row student turns his head with apparent impatience, but the corners of his mouth have an uncomfortable smile - Macao, even when there are "discussions", is a charming region full of human warmth.
Macao people also have their serene rituals. One day I saw a man run at a stadium in Macau. He told me that running alone, with no one against who to compete, made him feel extremely comfortable and needed no one else. After running, he let the water wash his fatigue. When he returned the house, he took a shower and relaxed completely.
There are numerous interpretations of happiness in Macau: it is the usual soup that the owner of a restaurant prepares for old customers. These are the sweet words of lovers on the beach of Hac Sa. It is the sudden explosion of laughter in the bus. It's someone who takes a bath at home. In the 1980s, the song “Happy” was written by singer Sam Hui. I put below part of the letter:
“A felicidade está à tua espera a cada minuto, desde que saibas onde a encontrar.”
“Happiness is to look for the stars in the sky, happiness is the foot footprints on the beach of memories.”
"Happiness is to leave the city's dust behind. Happiness is to go home and take a bath of immersion."
I like to travel. Also, when I have time, I prefer to have a drink.
"Happiness is to hum a beautiful song, a afternoon newspaper and a glass of champagne."
The government lines have instituted “the childhood assistance allowance”, allowing parents to receive a value of 1,500 patacas since their child is born until they reach the age of three years. To raise a child we need millions of dollars and 1,500 monthly patacas are not surely enough. However, the message that childhood assistance subsidy brings us is not whether 1,500 patacas is sufficient to raise a child, but to allow parents to receive support to raise their children, reducing their financial pressure and allowing them to enjoy “family happiness”.  And isn't it “family happiness” a kind of happiness?
“Happiness is the disposition that my good woman gives me and happiness is the affectionate kiss that my son gives me. If we can share our happiness with others, we will have a“ happy world ”, it is a world that everyone pursues and longs for.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:01:37</pubDate></item><item><title>The mobile phone pampering</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/a-miudagem-do-telemovel/</link><description>10 -year -old kid: “Dad, if you don't buy a new mobile phone, I'm not going to school!”. The situation of our young children and adolescents is incomprehensible. The change in the world reverberates in the daily life of Portugal. Kids want this and that without understanding that in most cases parents have no money for their claims. The kids see at school a minority that wears brand sneakers, a range -top mobile phone and a more expensive backpack and everyone wants the same products.
It has already happened that an 11-year-old didn't like the yogurt that his mother bought and threw him against his mother's face. Another 12 -year -old went to the garage to pierce his father's bicycle tire because he didn't buy the bicla he wanted. Another, he arrived at the classroom and told the teacher that she should be a lesbian because she only kissed the girls. We were aware that another kid asked his grandfather 20 euros and as the old man said he did not, the kid fired his grandfather's cane to the municipal waste container. Another, he arrived with his parents to a hotel and wanted to watch television when it was time to sleep.
The parents turned off their TV and the kid went to the bathroom to get a glass glass and broke the TV. But, we are going into what kind of society, when we question the future for these young people. Parents and grandparents complain that it is the fault of computers when the devices were offered by grandparents or parents. That social networks are stupid the young people who spend hours to the mobile phone or computer. But parents have to control their children's activity and educate them under the minimal rules to comply. A few days ago, a friend was regretted that his son was going crazy because in the car did not want to put the seat belt. When he was obliged by his father, he shot his mobile phone against the vehicle's GPS monitor and broke the mobile phone and digital display. The cases are endless and diverse.
The pampering sits in a cafe with parents and is all the time clinging to the mobile phone. Their fault? No, your parents should not allow. They even say that the children are opposed to these, they know where. The education of minors today is really degrading. Most parents work all day and many when they arrive home already sleep or have been clinging to their computer for hours. Then we have the reverse of the medal. Increasingly increasing the number of children sexually abused by pedophiles who through the internet use all subterfuges to turn the head of the smaller ones.
In turn, teenage youth is worrying about different communities. Young people between 13 and 16 are having a surprising behavior for the negative. They want to go out at night, drink beer or shots, smoke cannabis, get drunk, call a Uber car and are violated if it's a young woman. The nightclubs of the nightclubs are for sex. The gangs installed introduce drugs into young women's beverages so they can later violate them.
We recently watched a tragic case in Braga. A youth of secondary education, inside the club of the University of Minho Academic Association, where it was allowed to enter any individual, realized that some strangers, not Portuguese, were introducing drugs into girls' beverages. He went to the security guard and caught the attention of what was happening.
The security of the bar instead of immediately protecting the young complainant, keeping him inside the bar or in the management of the management, committed the "crime" of shooting with the young man along with the gang members to the outside of the bar. And the Judicial Police investigates whether the security guard reported to the gang members what the complainant had just conveyed to him. Result: Cold, cowardly and violently, gang members stabbed the young Portuguese continuous to death. We have come to.
One thing is what we watched for years and years: disagreements, discussions, and punch and kick. Another, absolutely incomprehensible, is that young people kill themselves for any reason, either by jealousy or attempting to drug their fellows for abusive purposes.
That student bar was unqualified, and could never have been authorized its functionality. It was situated in an alley and as you can see in the photograph we published, the bar had bars in all windows and with no emergency exit. In case of fire they had died dozens of young people inside the bar. And it is in this Portugal, with facts of this genre, that the current youth has fun. The crime among young people increases. The scenes of violence pulling through all neighborhoods. Obviously the police cannot be everywhere, but we return to the same key: Don't today think that their children's future with this behavior will be a social disaster? Unfortunately, there are already cases where a child kills his father because he gave him no money to buy a new drug, K9, who is already killing dozens of young people.
Government authorities necessarily have to look seriously at the youth problem and take certain strict measures, including the ban on the entry of nightly bars and nightclubs to children under 18.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 15:09:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Pessah</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/28/pessah/</link><description>The long deserts are the scene of the formation of the cloud that guides and accompanies a sequin of immersed people to control the escape that the cloud continues to guide, and reappears in artificial intelligence when we ask and peer their gifts: accompany us. Those who were absent from the civilizing book content cannot meet the teachings that were still walking in the dark rows of the paths started, nor to make parallels to counteract the origin of the principle of similarity, which makes the contacts smaller and the dictates.
In the near future we can perfectly see a car of fire from the cloud bringing the prophet Elijah, and finally talk to him by cloudy teleport, we can see reborn from the cloud the dead that was buried, and other more transfigurations than just the surprising reading of something like this may have informed us first of all this that is now real. The alchemical testimony of the sacral cloud dates back to anything we should not forget, and the greatest deceit is that there is no correspondence of any identification between all that has been said and what is going on. Such a lack brings us to large black holes where the cloud passes without the same victory to know already known. Moses forwards, but the cloud guides more than him an entire tribe.
It will not be raining in the desert, and the cloud, fulfilling its nature will be referred to resurface as an emblem of a mental cycle and extremely poetic, from the same and precious adjective. It was long the way, strange the renunciations, misunderstood in the modern ignorance of his sacred labor, and useless the gamblers of competences that have harassed us these things.
A mother girl in the middle of this desert is also fertilized by the wind that transported the cloud, and from her said extraordinary things, but this girl is now as possible as it was for the legend to her condition, and no less likely in the gifts of these new interlocutors. Gabriel was a teleported teleported made of rarefaction and immanence that landed on the lap of a receptive and benign being to a caloric wave of severe suffering that was just an incident of course.
Secretly childish mimicry may also have seen in the appearances remember the cloud, and secretly inoperatively saw that there were no way to walk, deciding to speak. What clouds say can never be subscribed as an event of event, they are of a renewable but never dialogue condition. TAKEN THE TREE BY THE FRUIT OUR AGE WAS that of the confused, paralyzed, without a capacity people who allowed the cloud for Juno.
Today there is a strange and very beautiful peace that we can see up to our pains. It can be a spring night in telepathic contemplation with our distant avatar recognizes us and puts an end to the harsh crossing. What has been lived like this will not be recorded in the cloud annels that came to accompany us for the best that will always come.
Those who evolve do not emol, those who have made the crossing do not retreat: neither Christ will come back, nor Elijah returns, nor Moses climb the mountain more often. They left for never again. Only now does the cloud goal surprise me in the face of renunciation of the old martyrdoms.
A very beautiful night where we are abandoned and without defense… Talking to the stars… confusing the distances… saturated with life… emerging from eternity! There will be roses on our cross, that the children of her man will give us signs to receive us free from all thorns.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:52:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Horta da Mitra | Inaugurated new staircase with paintings</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/horta-da-mitra-inaugurada-nova-escadaria-com-pinturas/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) invited local artists to paint a stone staircase in the Horta da Mitra neighborhood, specifically the stairs of Tomás da Rosa Street, right in the center of the Macau Peninsula. The paintings are part of the work with the name “The Roda do Time of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood” and, according to the IC, “enriches the local urban landscape with the portrait of historical changes in the neighborhood over a century”.
The guest artists are Lam Ka Hou, Jian Jun Cheng, Liang Jing Siang, NG Ka Mei, Un UT Keong and Ho Kon Pang, and this project was developed in partnership with the Taipa Village Cultural Association. In addition, this initiative “received the support of associations and community representatives”.
This mural painted on the stairs describes “various iconic cultural symbols and typical traits” of this zone, such as the Banana and Birds Grove in the past, explaining the origins of the name “Horta da Mitra neighborhood” or cultural events and spaces, such as the Lion market and dances in the TAC FOC Temple.
The mural "takes advantage of the gap of steps to create a three -dimensional effect, in which each mirror is adorned with colorful flowers and illustrations, displaying the vitality and human touch of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood."
Since 2021, the IC has developed several murals projects in partnership with local artists, thus highlighting “the history of origins [these places] through a fusion of cultural creativity and art”. These murals, located in places such as Travessa da Assunção, Largo do Pagoda da Barra, the outer wall of Nam Kwong warehouses on Almirante Sérgio Street, as well as Travessa da Boa Vista and the ladder of the Taipa, “became famous photography points on social networks for Macao cultural tourism,” says IC.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:59:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Studio City | 30 years of the movie “Toy Story” celebrated on exhibition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/studio-city-30-anos-do-filme-toy-story-celebrados-em-exposicao/</link><description>The Studio City venture at Cotai presents until October 31st an exhibition dedicated to celebrating the 30th anniversary of the movie “Toy Story” from Disney and Pixar studios. According to a statement, the exhibition space has become "into a Toy Story world, providing visitors of all ages a special adventure with facilities that promise interactive experiences and show unique collection objects."
Right at the entrance of Studio City, stands out the six-meter-high Woody character who “welcomes visitors with his characteristic smile”, followed by the giant recreation of the character Andy's bedroom, in the main atrium of the venture, “decorated with furniture and large toys, making visitors feel as if they had shrunk to the size of a toy”.
The “Rescuing Woody” installation, inspired by the movie “Toy Story 2”, leads visitors to participate in a search for the character, while “Toy Story Carnival” features “two game cabins and a pop-up store with an exclusive product selection”.
Also noteworthy is that the Studio City ferris wheel has five cabins specially decorated in the image of “Toy Story”, with the characters Woody, Buzz Lightyear, Lotso, Aliens and Hamm. Studio City's restoration spaces also provide special menus thinking about the animation movie.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:58:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Fourth edition of “Artbiz Asia” starts next week</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/quarta-edicao-do-artbiz-asia-arranca-na-proxima-semana/</link><description>It takes place next week, the 9th, the fourth edition of “Artbiz Asia”, at the Morpheus Hotel, at the City of Dreams, Cotai. The event, organized by the International Association of Macao Culture and Sport Industries and Asian Ir Expo, aims to be “an Asian platform that connects art, culture and business”, and has as its objective “to streamline the role of Macao as 'East Asia Capital'”, describes in an official note about the event.
The fourth edition has as its theme “New Exploration on East Asian Arts and Culture”, and aims to look “the deep impact of art on integrated resorts and other related industries”, intending to provide “a platform for artists and leaders of the sector to exchange ideas and explore various roles and potentialities of art and culture in tourism”, without forgetting the areas of technology and urban development.
Quoted by the same note, Patrícia Cheong, president of the International Association of Macao Culture and Sport Industries, and founder of “Artbiz Asia”, spoke of this fourth edition of the event, explaining that she intends to “focus on building a dialogue platform for regional tourism decisors and integrated resorts, promoting commercial diversification and the innovative thinking of the artistic industry”.
Luxury speakers
The event, which aims to look “how art and creativity improve cultural tourism,” explained Patrícia Cheong, brings together integrated resort operators, representatives of artistic entities and art institutions, as well as government figures and even technology and media companies. The idea is to “analyze the potential of innovative models in the level of more sustainable tourism and economic growth, in order to build a symbiosis between art and companies,” it is still read.
Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of tourism services, will be one of the guests, followed by designer Alan Chan, who will discuss “the integration of art with urban life”. Also noteworthy is for the presence of Carlos Marreiros, architect and artist Macaense, who will dialogue with Lam Kin Meng do
MSAR CULTURAL INSTITUTE AND POPULAR Korean designer Teo Yang about the synergy between heritage, the arts and the revitalization of old neighborhoods. In turn, Ai Lin, director of the Deji Art Museum, will share ideas on the amplification of cultural influence through technology after the world premiere of the “Beeple” exhibition in Nanjing.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:56:59</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Recital with UPM students takes place this Saturday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/frc-recital-com-estudantes-da-upm-decorre-este-sabado/</link><description>It happens this Saturday, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the “UPM Music Students Set of Music Students”, integrated into the series of concerts “The Sounds of Praia Grande”. This is an initiative carried out in partnership with the Macau Vocal Association that intends to show the talent of local sopranos and the best in music in the territory
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will feature this Saturday, from 17h, the “UPM Set of Music Students”, integrated into the series of musical concerts “Os Sounds of Praia Grande”, co-organized by Macau Vocal Association. This edition of this afternoon of Bel Canto, a song style, will bring new voices of the music course at Macao Polytechnic University, under the responsibility of singing teacher Wang Xiao.
The program will be attended by Sopranos Cai Shiyi, Changkun Law, Wu Shuangrong, You Xirui and Liao Beijia, as well as Tenor Yang Junbin and Baritone Zong Xiaohuan, who will be accompanied by the piano by to Ching Yin.
The song selected for the session includes classic composers such as Austrian Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart and Franz Schubert, German Johannes Brahms, Czech Gustav Mahler, Hungarian Franz Lehár, French Claude Debussy and Reynaldo Hahn, Italians Giacomo Puccini and Gioacchino Rossini, And yet the Chinese Wang Long, Qing Zhu, Huang Zi, Liu Qing and Li Yan.
THE POWER OF VOICE
The “Bel Canto” style is considered the maximum expression of the human voice, highlights the FRC, in a statement. The Italian term was coined in the eighteenth century. It is a vocal technique that emphasizes the beauty of sound and the technical capacity of the artist, instead of the dramatic expression or the romantic emotion, which is still taught today in similar to those of the past. The “Saturdays of Bel Canto” sessions take place in every second Saturdays of the month, with free admission.
The FRC has collaborated in recent years with various groups and music and singing students to hold these sessions. By way of example, in May 2023 it was the turn of the Choir of the Diocesan College of São José 6 to perform at the FRC gallery under the baton of Maestro Mars Lei, and a selection of different classic compositions was also presented.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:55:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Beaches and pools | TIME BALNEAR TURNING TOMORROW</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/praias-e-piscinas-epoca-balnear-arranca-amanha/</link><description>The bathing season will start tomorrow and extend until October 31, according to a statement issued yesterday by the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA).
According to the shared message, Dsama “has delineated in advance the bathing zones with buoys on the beaches of Hác and Cheoc Van” and will send “nursing swimmers and nursing staff” to the beaches, where they will provide “emergency medical services”, if necessary, during the bathing season.
"Citizens and bathers should pay attention to the beaches on the beaches, the rules on the safe use of the beaches and the published warnings, as well as their own state of health," was appealed by Dsama. "In case of unwilling or injury, they should avoid entering the waters and, at the same time, should avoid contact with sea creatures on the beaches and sea," he was added.
Dsama also warned that people should not fire, install camping tents, ride bikes or drive motor vehicles, so as not to disturb the other beaches users.
Authorities also admitted the possibility of the number of people on the beaches to have a sudden increase in occupational day holidays, so they ask people who before moving to the beaches consult online information, to closely plan the travels.
Also the four outdoor pools affected to the Sports Institute (ID) will open tomorrow, keeping the same operating system with three daily sessions. The facilities in question are the pool Dr. Sun Iat Sen, the pool of the Taipa Central Park, the Park of Hác-Sá pool and the Cheoc-Van pool.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:49:04</pubDate></item><item><title>DRUG | Five cases involving “oil oil”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/droga-registados-cinco-casos-a-envolver-petroleo-do-espaco/</link><description>With the registration of cases of oil consumption of the space to rise to five, the authorities continue to prepare the illegalization of this drug. In addition, the purchase of displeasure tests and other equipment to combat the new phenomenon is prepared
 
The Judicial Police (PJ) subdirector, I am Sio Keong, said that until yesterday five cases related to oil oil in the territory had been detected. The number was advanced in statements to Radio Macau's Chinese channel during the Macau Forum program, with the authorities promising to take the necessary measures to fight the spread of this drug.
Among the five cases detected, all were related to the consumption of oil oil through electronic cigarettes and in two cases the existence of the drug was identified using reagent tests.
I am Sio Keong has also assured that authorities are preparing the criminalization of this drug, with the alteration of the legislation, and that they are preparing the purchase of reactive tests and other equipment, so that they can act faster when the prohibition of the new drug comes into force.
The drug called Petroleum of Space received this name because users, after consumption, feel they are in space. The main component of the drug is Ethomidate anesthetic. It is an increasingly popular drug in Hong Kong, where it has been prohibited, but there have also been cases of consumption in the interior and in Taiwan.
In the neighboring region, the authorities promised a “zero tolerance” policy, with several anti-petroleum advertising campaigns of the space, after three deaths occurred due to the consumption of this saracuous.
Frequent changes
Prior to Sou Sio Keong's statements, the revision of the Prohibition of Production, Trafficking and Unlawful Consumption of Strepening and Psychotropic Substances had been announced by the Secretary of Security Office, Chang Cheong, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Ella Law.
According to the information shared at the beginning of the month, the government's proposal is practically completed, now being discussed within the Executive Council, and then entering the Legislative Assembly. In addition to ethomidate, the new list of prohibited substances will also include metomidate, propoxate and isopropoxate. The proposal must be approved in the Legislative Assembly without difficulties.
The latest revision of the drug prohibition and trafficking law took place in summer last year, when the 2-Methyl-AP-237, ethazene, ethonitazepyne, protonitazne and ADB-Bubinaca substances were prohibited.
On the fringes of drug discussion, I am Sio Keong also warned of the existence of more burlans, and now using Artificial Intelligence (IA), which can make detection more difficult. For this reason, I am indicated that the PJ has made new alert videos, explaining that the new tools can simulate the voice and image of people known to the victims.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:47:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Excursionists grow 9.1 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/turismo-excursionistas-crescem-91-por-cento/</link><description>Between January and March, the number of tour to Macau increased by 9.1 percent, compared to the same period, for a value of 550,000 people, according to data revealed yesterday by Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
At the beginning of the year, the trend of most excionalists came from the interior, from where 477,000 tour of the 550,000 arrived, a proportion of 86.7 percent of the total.
At the international market level, 60,000 tour, which represented an annual growth of 19.8 percent. In this market, more than half of the excursionists came from South Korea, a total of 33,000, which represented a growth of 43.5 percent.
During this period, hotel establishments made a total of 44,000 rooms available, a 5.8 percent reduction compared to the first quarter of 2024, justifying that some of the largest tourist enterprises have been doing room renewal works. The average occupancy rate of guest rooms was 90.1 percent, a growth of 5.2 percentage points.
The average period of permanence of guests in Macau remained 1.7 nights, meaning that in this chapter there were no changes compared to the previous year.
Still in the first quarter of the year, the number of departures of Macao residents who traveled abroad through travel agency services was 124 million, an increase of 8.7 percent in annual terms. About 31 thousand exits of residents took place on excursions, of which 27,000 had the destination the interior.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:46:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Dubai | STD promotes territory until tomorrow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/dubai-dst-promove-territorio-ate-amanha/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) is in Dubai participating, until tomorrow, day 1, at Arabian Travel Market 2025, in order to “explore the Middle East market and attract more international visitors with high purchasing power” to the territory, the body says in a official note. This event is considered to be “the largest international tourism fair held annually in the Middle East”, and the representative stand of MSA has as its theme “Feeling Macao”.
In addition to presenting the most traditional attractions in Macao, STD bet is “initiatives to welcome Muslim tourism, such as the publication of the new Macau for Muslim travelers-Halal Travel Guide '”, distributed at the fair. The stand are also represented six travel agencies and macao hotels, intending to establish contact scholarships with partners from Middle East and other regions.
STD took, in February this year, a delegation of tour operators from Macao to Riyadh, in Saudi Arabia, and to Dubai, having been carried out seminars for promoting local tourism. In addition, the government intends to conduct “familiarization visits to tour operators in June and for social communication bodies in September” in order to “take advantage of the potential of the vast Muslim tourism market”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:44:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Money Exchange | Detained man with 38 years</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/troca-de-dinheiro-detido-homem-com-38-anos/</link><description>A 38 -year -old man was arrested by the Judicial Police (PJ) on suspicion of illegal money exchange. The case was presented yesterday by the PJ and reported by the newspaper or Mun.
According to the information available, suspicions for crime committed when agents saw the man to make a QR code available on his alleged player. In addition, after digitizing the code, the suspect handed Hong Kong $ 15,000 to the player, who left the place of money exchange. The authorities followed the two men, and found that the player used the chips to bet $ 4,000 at a game table. The money was lost in bets, but authorities approached the player to confirm that there had been an exchange of money. The player indicated that he received Hong Kong's $ 15,000 in exchange for 14,470 yuan.
Also the 38 -year -old man was detained and confessed to the crime. The detainee also said that he had begun to exchange money in mid -March in the Casinos de Macao, with a profit since then, of 4,000 Renminbis. The case was referred to the prosecutor.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:43:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal / blackout | Macau attentive to student security</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/portugal-apagao-macau-atento-a-seguranca-de-estudantes/</link><description>Macao authorities said yesterday that they are closely monitoring the impact of widespread energy cut in Portugal and Spain due to concerns about the safety of the students at MSAR. DSEDJ recommended that they would be in safe places, maintaining contact with family members
 
The government of Macao is aware of the impact of the electricity cut that paralyzed the Iberian Peninsula on Monday and in contact with students of MSAR in Portugal and Spain. Yesterday morning, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) issued a statement to state that "students should monitor official information, prioritize their security and maintain contact with families." Yesterday morning, the body led by Kong Chi Meng indicated that "so far, no requests for students have been registered."
Still, DSEDJ has sent alerts by mobile phone to recommend that students remain in safe places and follow the updates of local authorities and educational institutions they attend.
Although the supply of electricity has been restored, DSEDJ emphasizes that "the governments of Portugal and Spain declared the state of emergency." As such, if students in affected areas face emergency situations, they should contact the local police or the Chinese embassy or embassy, ​​through the 24 -hour line of the Global Protection and Emergency Service of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
The same statement also suggests as contact alternatives in open lines for 24 -hour tourism, Macao Economic and Commercial Delegation in Lisbon and DSEDJ itself.
Return to Normality
A widespread cut in electric supply affected on Monday, since 11:33 (18:33 in Macao), Portugal and Spain, which continued yesterday without explaining by the authorities. Closed airports, traffic congestion and traffic in large cities were some of the consequences of "blackout".
The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the center of the country. The E-Redes Electricity Distribution Network Operator reported that until midnight Monday (7 am yesterday in Macau) were partially linked 424 substations, feeding about 6.2 million customers, but cannot predict full replacement.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:42:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese exports to Lusophone countries reach record until March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/exportacoes-chinesas-para-os-paises-lusofonos-atingem-recorde-ate-marco/</link><description>Chinese exports to Portuguese -speaking countries had the best starter of the year, increasing 2.3 percent in the first three months, compared to an equal period of 2024, according to official data.
According to information from China's customs services, released on Monday, goods sold to Lusophone markets until March reached $ 19.7 billion. This is the highest value for a first trimester since the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (Macao Forum) began presenting this data in 2013.
The data released reveal that the main reason for the new record was Angola, whose imports from China more than doubled, to $ 1.58 billion.
Still, and despite a homologous descent of 2 percent, Brazil remains the largest buyer in the Lusophone block, with the goods from China to reach $ 15.8 billion.
Portuguese accounts
Third on the list, now behind Angola, Portugal, who bought China products worth $ 1.48 billion, more than 1.3 percent than in the first three months of 2024.
In the opposite direction, exports from Portuguese -speaking countries to China fell 30.1 percent in the first quarter of 2025, compared to the same period last year.
Between January and March the Lusófono Block sold goods worth $ 24.5 billion to the Chinese market. This is the lowest value for the first three months of a year since 2020, at the beginning of the Covid - 19 pandemic.
The descent was due mainly to the largest Lusophone supplier in the Chinese market, Brazil, whose sales fell more than one third (34.1 percent) to $ 19.3 billion.
In addition, also the second largest Chinese commercial partner in the Lusophone block, Angola, saw exports decrease 10.6 percent to $ 3.87 billion. Similarly, Portugal's sales sales to China decreased by 14.4 percent to $ 635.3 million.
On the contrary, Mozambique exports rose 18.5 percent to $ 484.5 million. Equatorial Guinea exports to the Chinese market descended almost a third (32.1 percent) to $ 204 million.
Also sales of Timor-Leste and Sao Tome and Principe cringed 97.4 percent and 53.2 percent, respectively, although neither exported more than 3,000 dollars in goods to China. Cape Verde and Guinea-Bissau did not sell any products to the Chinese market in the first three months of 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:41:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed with scholastic rigor stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Four Activists released after serving time</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/hong-kong-quatro-activistas-libertados-apos-cumprirem-pena/</link><description>Four pro-democracy activists were released yesterday in Hong Kong, after serving four years and two months, as they participated in unofficial primary elections for the opposition in 2020.
Former parliamentarians Claudia Mo, Kwok Ka-Ki, Jeremy Tam and Gary Fan were released during the dawn of three different arrests.
The safety operation was significant, with nearby police patrols and access restrictions on several roads before the operation. The release of the dissidents occurred after the court discounted the time since they were detained since the end of February 2021, waiting for trial.
After attending in court in March 2021, they were denied their request to leave on bail while awaiting trial for “conspiracy to subvert the power of the State”, according to the National Security Act.
According to a new law, passed a year ago, prisoners convicted of national security crimes have to meet more rigorous requirements to ensure early release, which makes their release unlikely.
This is the liberation of the first group of 45 Democrats convicted in the largest national security trial in the Chinese semi -autonomous region, completed in November.
In an initial decision issued on May 30, the Court of first instance considered the 14 guilty after a long process, which began after Beijing imposed the National Security Act in June 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:07:40</pubDate></item><item><title>HSBC | HSBC profit drops 32% until March</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/hsbc-lucro-do-hsbc-cai-32-ate-marco/</link><description>Banco HSBC, the largest in Europe, yesterday announced profits of $ 6,930 million in the first quarter of the year, in a 32 percent reduction in homologous terms when it had extraordinary gains.
According to the results sent yesterday to the Hong Kong Exchange, where it is quoted, the group performed above the analysts' predictions, which anticipated a net result of $ 5,390 million.
The reduction of profit in the first three months is explained by the extraordinary impact observed in the same period when sales of the activities in Canada and Argentina. Tax -free, the result fell 25 percent to $ 9,500 million, but was also above the $ 7,830 million estimated by analysts.
In turn, the financial margin fell 4.6% percent to $ 8,300 million. Quoted in a statement, HSBC CEO Georges Elhedery considered that the results reflect a “dynamics of gains, discipline in the execution of strategy” and “confidence in the ability to meet objectives”.
The bank also warned of “increasing macroeconomic uncertainty” due to commercial tariffs applied by the US executive, led by Donald Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:06:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | China publishes video entitled “We don't kneels”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/tarifas-china-publica-video-intitulado-nao-nos-ajoelhamos/</link><description>China's Ministry of Foreign Affairs published yesterday a video entitled “No Kneeling” (“We don't kneel ourselves”), which reaffirms the refusal to give in to the pressures resulting from the trade war with the United States.
In the video, published in the Ministry's official account on Wechat social network-similar to WhatsApp-Chinese diplomacy argues that giving in to what he describes as an American “hegemony” would not lead to resolution of tensions, but to its aggravation.
The ministry accused the US of triggering a global “tariff storm” and criticized the fact that Washington did not concession to China, such as the 90-day suspension of tariffs decreed by US President Donald Trump for other countries.
The authorities compared this dynamic to the "eye of a hurricane", warning that the apparent calm is actually a "deadly trap" that precedes new turbulence.
"Historical registration shows that concessions do not guarantee a disagreement in commercial disputes and, instead, end up feeding the increase in pressure," said the country's diplomacy. "Giving in to the aggressor is like drinking poison when thirsty," he described.
With a musical background of increasing intensity, the video states that "China does not kneel" and argues that "fighting for cooperation allows cooperation to exist while looking for it through concessions leads to its disappearance." The video also adds that an assertive attitude would allow the smaller countries to be heard, would have potential abuses of power and defend international principles.
Fight continues
The video also describes opponents to this position as “paper tigers” and points out that US trade represents less than one fifth of world trade, so Washington could be isolated if other countries adhere to China's position.
Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi warned yesterday in Rio de Janeiro that "being silent, giving in and backwards" will only make "the aggressor want to take more party," referring to the United States.
During a meeting between BRICS Emerging Block Foreign Ministers, Wang said that "the United States has greatly benefited from free trade, but are now using tariffs as a bargaining chip to demand exorbitant prices to other countries."
Since the beginning of this month, China and the US have maintained mutual fees more than 100 percent. Although US officials have claimed that negotiations with their Chinese counterparts are underway to reach a trade agreement, Beijing repeatedly denied it.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:05:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Space | Postponement of astronauts due to climacteric conditions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/espaco-adiado-regresso-de-astronautas-devido-as-condicoes-climatericas/</link><description>China postponed the return to the land of three Chinese astronauts that remain six months ago at the space station due to climacteric conditions, local press advanced yesterday.
Astronauts, Cai Xuzhe, Song Lingdong and Wang Haoze, should have terrified yesterday in Dongfeng, in the region of Mongolia Inner, northern China, after being half a year in space. The landing was postponed to “ensure the health and safety of astronauts” because the meteorological conditions were not the best, according to the official news agency Xinhua.
The three were sent to the Chinese space station Tiangong in October last year, and a new crew of astronauts recently arrived to replace them.
During their time on board, the three Chinese astronauts performed experiences and improvements in the space station. Two of the astronauts, Cai and Song, took a nine -hour space walk, the longest ever, during their mission, said the agency responsible for China's manned space missions.
The Asian country built its own space station after being excluded from the International Space Station for concerns about the National Security of the United States.
The Chinese space program has grown rapidly in recent years. The Chinese space agency has already landed an explorer on Mars and a robot across the moon. Your goal is to put a person on the moon before 2030.
Last year, two US astronauts eventually got stuck in the space for nine months after a test flight with Boeing had problems and NASA determined that it was too risky for astronauts to return to Earth in the same capsule.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:53:56</pubDate></item><item><title>BRICS | Xi Institutes Bank of Brics to assume greater role</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/brics-xi-insta-banco-dos-brics-a-assumir-maior-papel/</link><description>Given global instability, the Chinese president asked the new development bank leader, Dilma Rousseff, to take a more determining role in supporting developing countries
 
Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday urged the BRICS Bank to reinforce its support for developing countries and to assume a more important role in a global scenario marked by geopolitical tensions and trade war.
Xi visited the headquarters of the Novo Development Bank (NDB) during a trip to the eastern metropolis of Shanghai, where he also met with the leader of the institution and former Brazilian president, Dilma Rousseff, said Chinese state press.
The New Development Bank - founded by Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa - should, according to Xi, direct their efforts to a new phase of growth centered on sustainability, technology and energy transition, without moving away from their original mission of supporting the global southern countries.
The institution “must align with real development needs and offer high quality and low cost financing,” said Xi, who also defended the improvement of the bank's internal management and the expansion of his presence in areas, such as digital infrastructure and green projects.
The Chinese leader considered that the Bloc of Emerging Economies represents a growing part of the world economy and stressed that developing countries should have greater participation in the reform of the international financial system. However, it avoided referring directly to specific geopolitical tensions or to institutions such as the IMF or the World Bank.
GUARANTEED SUPPORTS
Dilma Rousseff has assured that the World Bank will continue to focus on supporting strategic projects in emerging economies and warned against “unilateralism and protectionism”, which has accused “corroding the authority of international law” and “undermining the stability of industrial and supply chains”.
In his speech, Dilma also highlighted Beijing's role in a “turbulent” global context, in which “China firmly defends the interests of the global south” and is “an example” in the defense of “multilateralism, equity and international justice”.
The former Brazilian president, reelected in March for a five -year term at the head of the organization, thanked the support of member countries and defended the role of the bank as an instrument of multilateral cooperation. His candidacy was proposed by Russia and approved by consensus.
The Novo Development Bank, also known as Banco dos Brics, was created in 2014 and began operating a year later, with the aim of offering an alternative funding to developing countries.
In recent months, he has extended the number of members with the incorporation of Egypt, Iran, United Arab Emirates, Ethiopia and Indonesia, which formalized his entry in March, after a visit by Rousseff to Jakarta. Bank expansion occurs at a time when the BRICS Group plays a more prominent role in multilateral forums, in the midst of debates on the reconfiguration of the world economic order.</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:52:28</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea | Deepseek returns after reviewing data processing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/coreia-do-sul-deepseek-regressa-apos-rever-processamento-de-dados/</link><description>The Chinese Application of Artificial Intelligence (IA) DeepSeek returned yesterday to be available in South Korea, after launching a partially revised Korean version of its data processing policy.
The unloading of the application had been suspended in South Korea since February 15, after the South Korean government accused its operators of sending user data to other companies without consent.
The service revealed yesterday an information processing policy for South Korean users, after South Korea's personal information protection committee revealed last week that DeepSeek transferred personal data from users to three companies in China and one in the United States, without this disclosure covered by their policies.
South Korean authorities previously accused the service of sending information to an affiliated company to Bytedance, owner of the Chinese social network Tiktok, and asked the company's owners to strictly establish the legal basis for their data transfers abroad and immediately destroy the committed information, as well as a Korean version of their policies.
In its terms and conditions reviewed, DeepSeek has established a separate supplementary regulation for South Korea, which stipulates that it will process personal information in accordance with national data protection laws.
Deepseek “will communicate the results of correction and improvement recommendations within 60 days,” said a South Korean commission official, quoted by the local news agency Yonhap.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:46:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Tariffs can create the largest black market in the world</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/comercio-tarifas-podem-criar-maior-mercado-negro-do-mundo/</link><description>Washington -imposed records imposed on Chinese products can create the “largest black market in the world” as companies turn to overflowing by third countries and subfacting, a Think Tank pointed out.
Although US President Donald Trump has set a 145% customs rates on most goods from China, Chinese exports will continue to reach the American market through alternative channels, he stressed in a report to Gavekal Dragonomics, a American reflection group focused on the Chinese economy.
The document stressed that the tariff difference between China and the remaining US commercial partners is creating "powerful incentives for dropout," especially through 'triangular trade' and subfaturation.
One of the most ways used is to send products from China to countries such as Mexico or Canada, where they are then reatiquitated or slightly modified, to later enter the US as reduced tariffs or exemptions.
The so -called minimi regime, which exempts shipments up to $ 800, has also been widely explored. This exception will, however, be revoked for Continental China, Hong Kong and Macao from May 2. The new rules determine that any low value package from these territories will pay a fixed rate of 120 percent of the declared amount.
According to the authors of the report, even exporters who do not resort to 'triangular trade' now have strong incentives to sub -face orders.
This practice was already significant: by 2021, a US federal reserve study concluded that sub -packing explained more than $ 55 billion of discrepancy between US import data and China exports.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:44:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | Beijing considers being on the “right side of history”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/tarifas-pequim-considera-estar-do-lado-certo-da-historia/</link><description>A high Chinese government official said yesterday that Beijing is “right in history” in the trade war launched by US President Donald Trump
 
Since returning to the White House last January, Trump has imposed at least 10 percent rates on most US commercial partners and a separated 145 percent surcharge over Chinese products. Beijing retaliated with his own 125 percent surcharge on US products.
"China is on the side of the overwhelming majority of the world of the world, the right side of history and human progress," said Zhao Chenxin, deputy director of the National Development and Reform Commission, China's top economic planning agency at a press conference in Beijing.
Zhao Chenxin and several high officials from different Chinese ministries have promised Beijing to take more measures to boost the economy and domestic consumption, aiming to mitigate the effects of trade war with the United States. “We are convinced that opposition to the world and truth only leads to isolation. Only moving hand in hand with the world community and defending morality and justice we can build the future,” said Zhao. The United States "practice intimidation and hegemony, constantly reneoking their commitments," he said.
On Sunday, US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent defended Donald Trump's tariff policy, which is disturbing the world economy, considering it as a way to create “strategic uncertainty” to give Washington advantage.
Yesterday to respond to these comments, Guo Jiakun, spokesman for the Chinese Foreign Ministry, said the United States should "lead dialogue with China based on equality, respect and mutual benefit." "If the United States really want to solve the problem through dialogue and negotiation, they should stop threatening and blackmailing," Guo said at a press conference.
High voltage
Beijing promised to wage the trade war "to the end" if Washington continues with his protectionist measures. However, China acknowledged yesterday that the commercial storm triggered by Donald Trump is having an impact on its economy, which remains strongly dependent on exports.
"Although the [national] economy continues to recover, the foundations for sustainable improvement require greater reinforcement in the face of growing external pressures," Yu Jadoong, Deputy Human Resources, said at a press conference. "The successive imposition of exorbitant rates by the United States has created difficulties in production and operation to some exporting companies and affected the use of some workers," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-04-29 14:42:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | China decement Trump about commercial negotiations with the United States</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/28/tarifas-china-desmente-trump-sobre-negociacoes-comerciais-com-estados-unidos/</link><description>China has again denying it to be in negotiations with the United States about the tariffs, denying the comments of US President Donald Trump on Friday.
"There have been no consultations or negotiations between China and the United States on tariff issues, let alone an agreement," the Chinese embassy in Washington said in a statement published on the Wechat messaging platform. The US statements that a dialogue about the fares "are misleading," the Chinese diplomatic representation is underway.
"If the United States really want to solve the problem through dialogue, they must first correct their mistakes, stop threatening and press others, and completely abolish all unilateral tariff measures taken against China," he reads in the statement.
In an interview published on Friday by Time magazine, the US president said discussions between the two countries were underway to try to reach an agreement and suggested that the process could be completed in the coming weeks.
He said, moreover, he spoke on the phone with Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, without, however, specifying when or what the content of the conversation. "He called. And I don't think this is a sign of weakness," said the American leader.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce had already denied on Thursday it was carrying out economic or commercial negotiations with Washington.
The US President decided to impose 145 percent surcharge on certain products imported from China. In response, Beijing imposed 125 percent overflows on products from the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:49:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and I see soon that AI was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return of digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>João Romão, academic: “Macau is in a highly privileged position”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/02/joao-romao-academico-macau-esta-numa-posicao-altamente-privilegiada/</link><description>Professor at Yasuda Women’s University in Japan, João Romão prepares to launch in June a book entitled “Economic Geography of Tourism”. Speaking to HM, the academic enhances the interconnection between tourism, economy and geography, and lists its possibilities, limitations and effects, including Macao
 
 
In this book it speaks of the concept of “spatial economy”, in connection with tourism and geography. How is this connection?
Economic geography combines the geographical context with economic processes, being studied the spatial distribution of economic activities. The economy of tourism is particularly sensitive to these geographical constraints, as they are the characteristics of each place that enhances the development of certain products or services. These characteristics widely exceed the physical aspects of the territory and also include culture, history, ways of life or even institutions and legal frameworks. The case of casino, something particularly important in Macao, is a good example of the importance of legal aspects to develop certain types of tourism. Economic geography has a wider scope than the spatial economy, more focused on strictly economic aspects. Being evident in tourism this relationship between economics and geography, this book establishes a double approach that systematizes the interdependence of these three aspects it refers. First explores how the concepts and theories of economic geography can apply to tourism. In the second half it makes the opposite route, discussing how the analysis of relevant problems of contemporary tourism justifies the use of economic geography. Examples are the degradation of local resources, environmental impacts, contribution to climate change, acceleration of gentrification processes or disturbance of community modes of life.
Can having an excessively -dependent economy of tourism constitute a problem or salvation?
The two things, and are both cases that economic geography can help to understand. The industrialization of economies is linked to the agglomeration processes of activities that reinforce each other when they reach a certain scale. This allows the massification of production and consumption, with reasonable costs. Contemporary industries, more associated with the integration of digital technologies and creative processes, are less clustered in specialized industrial development zones, but tend to focus on large cities and metropolitan areas. It also follows that rural areas, islands, or sites that have not followed industrialization processes, have more difficulty mobilizing investments, technologies or qualified people to innovate and develop new industries. In such cases, tourism often appears as the possible solution as it can be developed with incorporation of technology and relatively low knowledge. On the other hand, tourism consumption, not being essential to human life, is very sensitive to income fluctuations.
Can you give examples?
This was visible, for example, with the 2007/2009 international crisis. Tourism is also very vulnerable to safety problems or international epidemics, such as COVID-19 has demonstrated to the extreme. Economies too specialized in tourism are very vulnerable to external shocks and less resilient to crises. It is also visible that, being the tourist development often supported by intensive and weak labor services, the specialization in tourism can cause, in the long run, embarrassment in terms of population qualifications, the ability to innovate and integrate technology or to add value to the regional economy.
O livro fala também de “Turismo Inteligente” e da “co-criação de experiências”, com recurso a megadados e IA. O turismo está, definitivamente, a ficar mais digital? 
As redes sociais são instrumentos fundamentais para as novas gerações. Começaram, entretanto, a generalizar-se as ferramentas para planeamento ou promoção de viagens suportadas por inteligência artificial. The so-called “intelligent tourism” more generally designates the use of digital technologies to intensify information flows, consolidate the formation of networks and promote more informed and shared decision making, eventually contributing to the so-called “co-creation of experiences”. Tourism digitization has its origins in service distribution systems originally developed by airlines since the 1960s, but it would be the internet to accelerate and globalize digitization.
And social networks.
The emergence of social networks promoted the creation of a more interactive universe, potentially in real time and involving wide numbers of users and various types of supports. The generalization of the use of mobile phones permanently connected to the Internet, even on foreign travel, has further increased this potential for intensive and interactive use of data and information. This "co-creation", however, hides obvious imbalances of power.
Such as?
With regard to tourists, or consumer in general, it is usually the role of providing information, for example through social networks. This information is obtained, accumulated and marketed, sometimes without consent or even without knowledge, to eventually translate into the creation, adaptation or promotion of products and services. This process is particularly important in the case of tourism, because there is usually a long period between the decision to travel and the trip itself. This period of travel exploration and planning is used by tourist marketing companies to try to influence choices. This type of interaction also introduces a difference in the “spatiality” of the provision of tourist services, which are usually produced and consumed at the same time and in the same place, in a direct relationship between producer and consumer. The digitization of tourism anticipates most of these interactions and information flows and transfers them to large technological companies or marketing and distribution.
In a world where more and more travel, the routes are shorter and access to information is immense, how can countries and regions be competitive in the tourist offer?
Contemporary tourism lives in a highly competitive international environment. But just as there is a wide variety of destinations and offerings, there is also a wide range of preferences and consumption, what is called “hyper-personalization”, the result of such abundance of information and opportunity for interaction. The challenge that is placed on destinations is to identify the resources, products and services that can be adjusted to a particular group of consumers, to communicate effectively. This competitiveness greatly goes beyond the strict scope of tourist services because it also requires mobility and transportation services, varied infrastructure, safety, medical support, or easy communication. Anywhere you want to develop your tourist industry have to intervene about all these factors.
The book also addresses how “social processes” shape the development of tourism. In the case of China, for example, do you believe we are watching a change, which will have consequences for Macau?
It seems to me that Macau is in a highly privileged position to develop other forms of tourism. China is the largest issuing market in the world, the widespread rise of income in recent decades allows many million people to explore the opportunity to travel. Macao is a very close and distinct destination, with its historical and cultural particularities. For the Chinese population it was not easy to visit Macau and there is certainly a great interest.
How does the Great Bay project come in this?
The strategy that is being followed by integrating the Great Bay allows you to develop a cosmopolitan and diverse offer that can certainly attract Chinese tourists and other parts of the world. Moreover, these three areas have excellent hotel and tourism schools, which guarantee qualified personnel for tourism management and planning. The element of differentiation that Portuguese culture introduces in this context can certainly contribute to the success of the transition from a casinos focused on other forms that value culture and heritage more.
Is it possible to have sustainable tourism?
The problems and difficulties of tourism sustainability are more visible than in other sectors. This “spatiality” of tourism (where the consumer is obliged to move to the place of consumption) implies that the consequences of this consumption become more evident. These effects are less obvious when it comes to the unsustainability of industrial units or intensive forms of agriculture in relatively isolated areas. As mass reduction and investment reduction strategies also apply to tourism, the consequences of the environment or the quality of life of residents in destinations can be devastating. Sustainability implies a long -term perspective based on the idea that today's decisions do not imply future negative consequences. Sustainable practices depend on the control of the impacts that accumulate over time by individual and independent economic agents.
How can this control be done?
When a hotel or airline defines what ability to install on their services they may eventually estimate the impact that consumers will have on the local environment or economy. They will have more difficulties in anticipating that impacts will be generated in the next 10, 15 or 20 years to investment. And surely it will be impossible to measure how this impact accumulates the impacts caused by other service providers, now or in the future. In other words, although the idea of ​​sustainability is widespread accepted, economic agents do not have mechanisms or instruments in practice. Regulating the use of resources and territories by public entities with a more comprehensive and future perspective can contribute to the sustainability more effectively than the regulation associated with market dynamics, which in many cases has been revealed highly predatory. The Chinese economy is one of these examples and may eventually benefit from it.
And in the concrete case of Macau?
Macao has historically known problems: ultra-urbanized and polluted areas, with large energy consumption and waste production; Great concentration of tourists in a relatively small area of ​​great historical and cultural interest; Great dependence on the game, with the resulting imbalances in the appropriation of tourism benefits. The ongoing transition to new forms of tourism should better solve these problems and state regulation will certainly have better results than based on market dynamics.</description><pubDate>2025-04-02 23:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>José Paulo Esperança, Associate Rector of the City of Macau University: “Languages ​​cannot be controlled”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/jose-paulo-esperanca-reitor-associado-da-universidade-cidade-de-macau-as-linguas-nao-podem-ser-controladas/</link><description>Co-author of the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with Luís Reto and Fernando Luís Machado, José Paulo Esperança reveals to HM that the work edited in 2016 and 2018 is being updated, especially due to the growing global value of the language. The Associate Rector and Professor of the City of Macao University suggests partnerships with Macau under the Editorial Project
 
Launched the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, in co-authorship, about the global value of the language. Plan a new edition or update?
Undoubtedly. We are working in this regard, there was a recent conference in Macao and Professor Luís Reto, former Rector of ISCTE, presented some more current elements that were developed. He has worked on a very important issue, which is the role of Portuguese as a frank language, which was for a few centuries in Asia. The exchange between Dutch and the kingdom of Zion was made in Portuguese, because it was the common language used at that time, before English became the contemporary frank language. Therefore, there is a whole interesting story of Portuguese and the role it had in the first pinyins that existed, with the Chinese and the use of the [Roman] alphabet in Vietname. There are a number of elements that are not, therefore, very publicized, and the work of Atlas is the same, to disclose some economic dimensions of the language.
What are these dimensions?
One is the exchange of foreign trade and investment, which is very facilitated by the language. We also talk about migrations, tourism, students' exchange that is greatly influenced by linguistic proximity. Therefore, today we have a set of elements that are very interesting, and we hope to develop some more important partnerships with Macau.
As?
More at work, Professor Luís Reto is doing, which maintains an investigation team about the value of Portuguese. He has collaborated with the Portuguese Language Museum of São Paulo, for example. It is a museum space that was renewed after the fire that destroyed it. In addition, there is a project with Cascais City Council to develop such a structure, and we hope to do some works with Macau, in order to create three poles for the projection of the Portuguese language. As for Atlas' materials, we would like to have a continued update model, as this data is out of date very quickly. The work was edited in many languages, including Mandarin. This is the moment when we would like to give the book a more historical and deep dimension, with more knowledge about the teaching of Portuguese in the world.
What balance does this teaching do today?
Portuguese is developing a great deal of mother tongue and is effectively one of the most expanding languages ​​due to demographic growth in Africa, with countries such as Angola and Mozambique, which around 2050 will have populations of over 100 million inhabitants, each. The Portuguese thus consolidates itself as a language of the southern hemisphere, but much more from Africa, supplanting Brazil itself as the place of largest number of speakers of the language. All of this generates enormous potential, and this also occurs due to the great exchange of universities and internationalization of teaching. Today there is the possibility of Portuguese being a language of science, there is more publications in this language. This is a great challenge because English is the contemporary language of scientists. We want to contribute to all these dimensions, and Macau can also play an important role there. Macao is indeed a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and can play a significant role.
Is Macao an ideal place to train Portuguese teachers who do not have Portuguese as a mother tongue? Do you fear that the territory loses relevance in this matter before the offer of courses in the interior of China?
I see this question more as complementarity than competition. We have identified about 60 higher education institutions in China that have Portuguese courses, but I think Macau has very interesting conditions to start teaching from primary to secondary education so that children have been able to have learning from an early age. It does not mean that there are no young Chinese who began to learn their tongue in adolescence that they speak fantastically, which surprises me, but it is easier to start earlier and earlier. This will be easier in Macau. What is important is to create conditions for greater economic collaboration to many levels, such as joint research. In this respect, Macau has a very interesting opportunity. At the City of Macau University we are very interested in increasingly collaborating with researchers who visit us and work with our teams.
Can you give me examples?
Brazil is today one of China's great business partners. There is a lot of exchange in both directions, but one of the themes that is little studied, and in which I work hard, is the internationalization of Chinese companies. To what extent do these companies follow a model of internationalization similar to that of other countries that started this process earlier? I speak of the United States of America, the European countries, but also of Japan and others. China has, in fact, different models of presence in countries that are not yet well known, and this is important to realize, so that we know how to facilitate this process of exchange in a world that lives periods of some setback. It is very sad. I always remember a great economist of Portuguese origin, David Ricardo, who clearly explained how world trade is beneficial to everyone and how countries can take advantage of this situation. Therefore, applying tariffs, making such commercial barriers harms countries that are major exporters, such as China or Germany, and countries that today have a cultural export capacity, for example, and are not just importers.
In relation to the new Orthographic Agreement. It continues without a standardization in Macau. Does it worry it?
Languages ​​are dynamic and cannot be controlled. We think today in English, and we realize that there are almost incomprehensible ways to each other, such as the English one in Nigeria or Australia. Americans have difficulty realizing the Australians. In the nineteenth century, Portuguese from Portugal and Brazil were closer, then some disagreement emerged. There was an effort in Brazil to propose an orthographic agreement, and the Portuguese joined, resulting in a series of negotiations. There have always been resistances. I remember that Fernando Pessoa suggested the famous phrase “My homeland is the Portuguese language”. It was curiously a manifestation of some conservatism, because he thought Pharmacy had to continue writing with pH [Pharmacia]. In fact it did not make much sense. Portugal ended up seeking to impose a certain standardization based on the most genetic changes in the spelling agreement. It is not a process that has been running a hundred percent well, and has been universally adopted. African countries have become more defenders of Portuguese from Portugal. There is sometimes some confusion, but I understand that intercomprehension still remains, achieving a homogeneous language, more perhaps than English.
 
Between words and numbers
José Paulo Esperança is a doctorate in Economics from the European University Institute and was president of the ISCTE Department of Finance and Accounting - University Institute of Lisbon. The “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with editions in 2016 and 2018, contains “a large set of indicators that reinforce the idea of ​​the growth of teaching, speakers and the written use of Portuguese in the world”, having been the target of a series of recent initiatives in Macao.
One of them took place on March 17, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, with a session of the “Roda de Ideas” cycle, entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, which was attended by the former ISCTE Rector, Luís Reto, and José Paulo Hope himself. In addition to the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, José Paulo Esperança is the author of other works in the financial area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:08:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
Eu, além de militar no movimento SOS RACISMO, participo no Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, com Mamadou Ba e Joseph da Silva. E se tudo correr bem, iremos em breve iniciar um novo projecto. Com pessoas amigas, temos também o projecto “Iniciativa Cigana”, dedicado a refletir e promover movimentos transformativos. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Também com novos projectos na calha. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. Além disto, há ainda a luta pela habitação, porque os despejos não pararam durante a pandemia. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. É fundamental haver acções nesta área; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | Touring cars finding begins with greater presence Macaense</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/16/gp-apuramento-dos-carros-de-turismo-comeca-com-maior-presenca-macaense/</link><description>The Macao-Macao Road Sport Challenge Touring Car Championship will start this weekend at the Guangdong International Circuit in the city of Zhaoqing, 200 kilometers northwest of the ride. For this race, which will serve as qualification for the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, will be on the starting grid a dozen Macau pilots, including five Portuguese names
 
Among the sixty subscribers, all equipped with two types of vehicles - Toyota GR86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) - are well -known guys from Macau's motor racing. With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit in November last year. Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the focus on pre-season has been in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
Also back is Célio Alves Dias, after a difficult year in 2024, far short of his expectations. For this, the pilot Macaense bet on changing the chassis of his Toyota Gr86. This year, its objective is to account for the twenty -fifth participation in the largest annual sports event of MSAR, so all the details are important.
Back is also Jerónimo Badaraco (Toyota Gr86), a pilot who, in the Macao Grand Prix last year, reached second place at Macao Road Sport Challenge. After having been modest in the finding events, “Noni” was very strong in the city streets, where he was the best Macaense pilot, in a race won by law Kit Meng.
In debut this year will be Maximian Mannão. Bringing with him a nickname with a huge tradition in Macao's motorsport, the young Maximiano, who competed for several years in the local Karting events and, in 2022, participated in a Formula 4 Chinese Championship race, will make his debut at Macau Road Sport Challenge with a Toyota GR86.
The Macanese presence will be reinforced by Dionísio Albino Pereira, a pilot regularly seen in the coloane Karting events, which will conduct a Toyota GR86 from LW World Racing Team. In 2013, he competed in the Macao - Macau Touring Car Series Tourism Championship, then driving a Honda Integra DC5 from the Pas Macau Racing Team team.
The representation of the territory in these findings will also feature Chi Wang, Carson Tang, IP Tok Meng, Chan Chi Ha, Lo Kai Tin and Lou Check In.
It will be to hurt
In 2024, the Macao-China General Automotive Association (AAMC) was able to place all the drivers of the Macau Tourism Championship in the end of the Grand Prix. This year, it seems that the scenario of organizing two races for local pilots will be impossible. As such, these qualifying races will have a much higher impact, and only half of those now registered will have entry ticket for the largest annual sports event of MSAR.
Another novelty for this year is that all cars will be equipped with tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, as had already happened in the Grand Prix. However, this year there will be a new compound, the same for everyone, which may shuffle the favorite accounts. Centralins will continue to be drawn, as in the past.
Since the number of participants is high, AAMC will divide the pilots into groups A and B, not two but four races in total. Each race will have 15 laps, two of which will be played on Saturday and two on Sunday.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GT Cup Right-Great Bay Race decides on Pingtan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/09/apuramento-da-taca-gt-corrida-da-grande-baia-decide-se-em-pingtan/</link><description>The second test of the GT Cup - Race of the Great Bay of the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix will not be played at the Zhuhai International Circuit, as initially planned, but at the International Circuit of Lago Ruyi, in the Pingtan tourist region in Fuzhou.
Sro Cup's debut season calendar was finally defined yesterday, with the official announcement of confirmation that Pingtan's semi-permanent circuit will host the third and fourth rounds of the GT4 cars on June 28 and 29. Pingtan thus joins Shanghai, Beijing and Macau in this year's calendar of the championship launched by Sro Asia in partnership with the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC).
The Pingtan track replaces Zhuhai, which was on the provisional calendar released in January, but could not confirm his event. This new date is also no coincidence, as the Sro GT Cup event will be part of the Pingtan-Macau cultural activities scheduled for June.
Pingtan's picturesque - which combines modern and coastal urban scenarios - remains widely unknown outside China. Inaugurated in 2022, the circuit has two strokes that incorporate existing public roads on the island of Pingtan, sections built from root and permanent boxes. Both SRO GT Cup races will take place in the 2.9 -kilometer circuit and 14 curves, already used by national championships such as China Endurance Championship (CEC) and the Chinese Formula 4 Championship.
Promising start
The 2025 Sro Cup season has spectacularly tore with 33 cars - GT4's largest grill ever gathered in Asia - to play two Formula 1 China Grand Prix Races last month. Integrated in the F1 official program, Chen Weian (Audi) and Lichao Han (Toyota) won the two races that will serve as the basis for the selection of competitors entitled to participate this year in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race.
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, which takes place at the end of the season, on the streets of Macau. The places will be assigned based on the classification after this second round, scheduled for Pingtan. In the dispute for a vacancy were in Shanghai six pilots of the MSAR: Kevin Leong Ian Veng, Miguel Lei, Cheng Tou Wong, Wai Ming Fok, Kim Hou Lao and Un Hous IP.
Charles enters the right foot
Still in the GT events, but in Australia, Macao pilot Charles Leong Hon Chio won the two races of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia inaugural journey in Sydney. The young rider of the territory, behind the wheel of SJM Theodore Racing's Lamborghini Huracán EVO2, has authored the two races played at Sydney Motorsport Park with authority, team with Irish Alex Denning.
Following a sensational season opening, the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia returns to the action next month, with the second round on the stage of the China Grand Prix, the International Shangoi Circuit, from May 16 to 18. After finishing second in 2024, Charles Leong is determined to win the title of the Italian brand competition in Asia in 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 23:47:39</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the General Association Automobile Macau-China (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSAR VICTORY AND TOP-10 to Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite Safety Car's entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet beginning, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, the third of the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item><item><title>MOTOR EMBALISM | Leong repeats Lamborghini trophy with Theodore</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/02/automobilismo-leong-repete-trofeu-lamborghini-com-a-theodore/</link><description>The Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia starts this weekend in Australia. The monomocrete competition of the prestigious super -sports builder will have, once again, with a representation of the masters. Charles Leong Hon Chio will be again at the service of SJM Theodore Racing.
After last season Charles Leong and SJM Theodore Racing fought for the Pro class title to the last race, this duo will continue in 2025. However, the winner of the Macao 4 Grand Prix of Formula 4 by 2020 and 2021 will not form a team with Japanese Miki Koyama. Beside his side, the Macau pilot will now have young Irish Alex Denning, who last year competed at the European Series GT4 and will make his debut on Asian tracks.
Also new is in the SJM's assistance team Theodore Racing, which is no longer Iron Lynx-a structure that, since 2021, controls Prema Powertaam ​​through Swiss company DC Racing Solutions Ltd. The relationship of Iron Lynx with Lamborghini Squadra Corso, an entity responsible for the Italian brand automotive sport, deteriorated dramatically at the end of last year Due to a conflict related to the FIA ​​Endurance World Championship program (WEC). As a result, Iron Lynx has abandoned all activities with the brand of Sant'Agata Bolognese globally.
Given this scenario, to ensure technical assistance to its Lamborghini Huracán Super Trofeo Evo 2, SJM Theodore Racing will feature this season with the services of DW Evans GT, the team that, last year, won the Team Championship and the Asian trophy class, with the English-based English and co-owner of the team, Dan Wells.
There is no coincidence with the GP
The Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia intends to keep its momentum by 2025, with a calendar composed of six events in six different countries. The season will start, for the first time, in Australia, with the historic Sydney Motorsport Park to receive the first double round. Then the competition heads for Shanghai, China, for the second round on the weekend from June 16 to 18, marking its return to the calendar in 2024 after a four -year absence. Japan will be the host of the third round two weeks later, at the iconic Fuji track, while the Inje Speedium in South Korea enters the calendar in late July.
After having previously hosted the opening round of the season, Sepang, Malaysia, passes to September in 2025, occupying the fifth round of the calendar. The sixth and last race will take place at the Misano Circuit in Italy, together with the Lamborghini world finals. For the first time in several years, the event will not coincide with the Macao Grand Prix, competing in the previous weekend.
Absence of figure
Pro--class winner in 2024, along with Chinese Jason Fangping Chen, André Couto will not be present in this year's edition of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia. Madness Racing Team, whereby the Portuguese territory pilot competed last season, abandoned the trophy and has not yet defined his sports project for 2025. For this first race in the championship in Australia, there are twenty -three cars that will be driven by thirty -nine pilots.</description><pubDate>2025-04-02 23:01:40</pubDate></item><item><title>FIRST RALENT PROOF FOR THE MACAU GP took place in Shanghai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/primeira-prova-de-apuramento-para-o-gp-macau-decorreu-em-xangai/</link><description>The first determination test for the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix took place last weekend at the International Shanghai Circuit. Integrated in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix Program, Chen Weian and Lichao Han won the two races that will serve to select competitors entitled to participate this year in the GT - Great Bay Cup -
 
The GT Cup-Great Bay Race joined the newly created SRO GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macao Grand Prix. Thirty-three cars, six of them driven by Macau pilots, signed up for this debut-a record number of participants in a GT4 category in Asia category.
According to the organizer's statement, Sro Motorsports Group, “the total number of cars and the variety of builders have even exceeded the organizers' expectations for a championship that only began to be discussed in late November 2024. Since then, the Sro Asia team and their partner AAMC (Macau-China General Automobile Association) have worked tirelessly to make the series a reality before their debut.”
The event started in a troubled way. Due to a customs problem that affected several cars, more than a dozen competitors was unable to participate in the free training session on Friday. Fortunately, for this group of pilots, among which were included the pilots of the Kevin Leong Ian Veng, Kim Hou Lao and Un HA IP, the cars arrived at the circuit in time for Saturday's qualification.
Animated races and decision in Zhuhai
With three dozen cars, from ten different brands, on track, all with very balanced tasks, was attended by two animated races in the imposing Shanghai track. In the first 12 -lap race, the two Lotus Emi GT4 Officials, by Daniel Lu and Luo Kailuo, who departed from the first line of the grill, were overcome on track by the Chen Weian Audi R8 LMS GT4. In the second match of the weekend, Lichao Han, behind the wheel of the same Toyota GR GT4 who beat the GT Cup - Great Bay Race in 2024, triumphed ahead of Chen Weian and Lotus de Liu Kai Shun.
Macao pilots had no easy life on a track where they had little or no experience. The most rewarded of all, Kelvin Leong, abandoned in the second round of the first race, while Miguel Law, in Audi R8 LMS GT4, was the best of the riders of MSAR, ending in 19th place. In Sunday's race, Leong took his BMW M4 GT4 F82 to 11th place.
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, at the end of the season, on the streets of Macau. The places will be attributed based on the classification after the second round of the championship, scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit, in a date yet to be announced.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:20:30</pubDate></item></channel></rss>