<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Gaza | Hamas warns that it is not worth negotiating new truce</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/gaza-hamas-avisa-que-nao-vale-a-pena-negociar-nova-tregua/</link><description>A high Hamas employee said yesterday that the Palestinian group considers it useless at this stage negotiations for a truce in Gaza, and appealed to the world to press Israel to end the “hunger war” at the enclave.
"It is not worth starting negotiations or examining new ceasefire proposals while the Hunger War and the Gaza Extermination War continues," France-Presse (AFP) Bassem Naïm, a member of the Hamas political office, told the agency. "The world must press the government of Netanyahu to end the crimes of hunger, thirst and murder," he added.
The statements appear a day after the Israelite government announced a new military campaign in the Gaza Strip, which provides for the conquest of the territory. The Gaza Strip, where the inhabitants have been displaced several times, has been under a blockade of Israel since March 2 and crosses a serious humanitarian crisis.
Gaza Civil Defense spokesman Mahmoud Baçal said yesterday that three Palestinians were killed following Israeli bombing at dawn in different parts of the Gaza Strip. The Israelite army resumed the enclave offensive on March 18, ending a two -month truce.
The war was triggered by Hamas's unprecedented attack on Israel on October 7, 2023, which caused the death of 1,218 people on the Israeli side, mostly civilians, according to an AFP count based on official data.
Of the 251 kidnapped people, 58 remain arrested in Gaza, 34 of which were declared killed by the Israelite army. Hamas also maintains the remains of an Israeli soldier killed during a previous war in Gaza in 2014. The Israeli retaliation campaign made at least 52,567 killed in Gaza, most of Civil, according to Hamas Ministry of Health, considered UN reliable.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:17:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Elderly | Recognizes difficulties in social companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/idosos-ias-reconhece-dificuldades-de-empresas-sociais/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) recognizes that the new trade environment has negatively affected the only two social companies that have among its functions to hire elderly workers. The current scenario was outlined in response to an interpetement of Deputy Lei Chan U, linked to the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations (Faom).
"Currently, the two social companies for the elderly who came into operation are from the area of ​​restoration, providing 16 full -time and six part -time vacancies for the elderly," he was explained. "The two projects of social company went into operation during the pandemic period. Due to the impact of the pandemic and market environment, the daily operation and development of social companies were relatively affected. After the pandemic, society and the economy of Macao gradually recovered, however, in the face of the constant change of the business environment of Macau, the operation of companies, including the elderly companies, faced many challenges and pressures."
Despite various strategies to relaunch the business, such as promotions or extending opening hours, IAS President Hon Wai admits that the situation has known few improvements. However, IAS indicates that the future deceiving plan of action for support services to the elderly, which is expected to take effect next year, should have more measures to encourage the hiring of the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:39:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Auditors of Macau company accused of accounting accounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/auditores-de-empresa-de-macau-acusados-de-falsificacao-de-contas/</link><description>Four Wellink CPA auditors and consultants are accused of having falsified Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited accounts so that this Macao company could enter the Hong Kong bag. The case was revealed yesterday through a Hong Kong Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) and is also being investigated in Macao.
According to the results of the investigation that took place since 2021, auditors and consultants Lam Shui-Mei, Siu Yuen-Shan, Cha Wai-Lun and Wong Yat-Chung falsified Huarchi Global accounts to show fictitious economic growth and be admitted to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange.
In addition, the four asked for the help of three family members, identified as Li Man-Heung, Li Kit-Chit and Wong Wing-Man, to subscribe to the company's first public offering. According to the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC), which assisted the ICAC in investigations, those involved in the purchase of shares received $ 1.5 million from Hong Kong.
As a result, the four are accused of two conspiracy crimes to defraud the Hong Kong bag, while the three family members are accused of a conspiracy crime to defraud the Hong Kong bag. The seven will be present throughout this day to a Hong Kong court. However, the ICAC has admitted that investigations are still running and that there may be other accusations.
Investigation in Macau
In Macao, searches were performed at the headquarters of Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited in the Plaza Civil Building.
The president of the group appears identified in the 2021 company annual report as Lou Cheok Meng. The identity was not confirmed by the Macao corruption commissioner, who in a statement of the case confirmed that he was running an independent investigation in Macau.
"This construction company is a local Macao company and its official is also a resident of Macao, so CCAC has established an investigation process following the respective indications of crime," he was reported. In addition, CCAC reported that the case continues to be investigated in the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:15:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese musical instrument conference in Mafra</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/conferencia-de-instrumentos-musicais-chineses-em-mafra/</link><description>The eighth edition of the Music Festival “Lisbon Conference Chinese Music and Musical Instruments” [Lisbon Conference on Chinese Music and Musical Instruments] takes off until Sunday between Lisbon and Mafra, being a supported and funded event, including linked to Macao, as is the case of Jorge Álvares Foundation and Macau Foundation, among others.
More specifically, today, tomorrow and Friday, 9 the event takes place at the National Palace of Mafra. This year's theme is “Expanding Horizons: Embracing The Wide Variety of Asian Music and Dance” [Expand the horizons: embracing the wide variety of music and Asian dance].
The idea is that in the coming days you talk and hear not only Chinese music, but also the Asian sounds and know more about the musical instruments that make these sounds. Today is the panel “Traditional and Popular Performing Arts of Asia” [Traditional and Popular Performative Arts of Asia], which will talk about Chinese folk music thanks to the intervention of Frank Kouwenhoven, researcher at Leiden University. Three academic interventions are followed by Naxi's folk songs in southwest China.
Also noteworthy for the panel dedicated to Macau, namely “Macau: Crossroads for Chinese and European Music” [Macao: A Crossroads for Chinese and European music], with interventions by Xiao Ling Shao, who will speak of the “art of Portuguese music in Macau” and Enio de Souza, who will make a “approach to musical instruments in the Chinese temples of Macao”. Highlight for the lecture starring José Pinto de Sá and Rui Magno Pinto on “Memory of Portuguese Classical Music Concerts in Macau”.
The musical part also happens today, from 19h [Time of Lisbon], at the Casa da Música Francisco Alves Gato, in Mafra, with a concert with the musicians Superena insert Adler, François Picard and Je Jinhua, among others, with various Asian instruments.
Popular sounds
Tomorrow, Thursday, it is the turn of the debate around the music to do in Mafra, starting at 10am [Time of Lisbon] with three personalities from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, China, who speak of “Investigation in the theories of the composition of Chinese music”. This is followed by the lecture by Rakesh Kumar, from South Africa, who will speak of the “Afro-Indian Siddi Goma-Dhamal Performances: Bridging The Past and Present, The Local and Global [Afro-Indian performances Siddi Goma-Dhamal: Bringing the past and the gift, the place and the global].
Again from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, China, Feng Changchun emerges talking about “empathy through time and space - the poetry of Li Yu and the art of the composition of the modern Chinese song”. In turn, Maureen Russell of the UCLA Ethnomusicology Department - University of California, Los Angeles, will talk about musical archives in “Sharing Soundscapes: The Bake / Jairazbhoy Digital Archive of South Asian Traditional Music and Arts”.
This Saturday, parallel sessions take place at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon on Chinese and Asian music in general terms. One of the panels about musical history before and after 1949 ″, in which Zhang Xiaodong, from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, will present a “Study on Historical Development and Yueqin Performance Formats”, an instrument of Chinese strings. Another example of a lecture is the session starring Lisa Beebe, from the University of Wisonsin-Whitewater, about the presence of Vietnamese instruments in Canada.
Jonathan Stock also addresses the theme “Thematic and Multivocal Approach to the History of Music in the Republic of China (1912-1949)”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:13:13</pubDate></item><item><title>CITIGROUP | Trade war is still passing by</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/citigroup-guerra-comercial-ainda-esta-a-passar-ao-lado/</link><description>In early May, the great gamblers moved to the casinos of the territory. Citigroup admits that it may have somehow assisted revenge expenses, that is, intense consumption after periods of deprivation
 
In the early days of May, the impact of trade war between the US and China was not felt but casino tables. The scenario was outlined by the Citigroup Investment Bank, in the latest report on the game sector.
The May 1st holiday coincides with the Golden Week in the countryside, one of the main vacation periods, and despite the most complicated economic environment worldwide, players, including VIP, did not fail to come to Macao.
According to Citigroup, quoted by the GGR Asia portal, the “current commercial conflicts between China and the United States seem not to be discouraging players to enjoy gaming offers and non -Macao's playing elements,” he is written.
Analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau even go further and consider that the observations made in the casinos were to leave “the jaw drop”, given the number of players. For this reality contributed the number of great gamblers, those who make bets over $ 1 million of Hong Kong per play, which were present at the tables.
Analysts even hypothesized that they have assisted “revenge expenses”, an expression used to describe intense and high consumption after moments of deprivation. "It was the first time we came across more than a VIP player to bet several million dollars of Hong Kong the same day," they noted. "This probably suggests that current commercial conflicts between China and the US are not so far affecting players' preferences," Citi suggested.
Full house
However, it was not only in terms of VIP players that the game market showed a great vitality. The same happened at the mass level, with Citigroup indicating that the number of visitors, in the order of 220 thousand per day, presented averages higher than those of the Lunar New Year, another of the high seasons of tourism.
Given these values, Citigroup indicates that the numbers show that there is a certain “lack of elasticity of demand for the game”, that is, that the demand for the game tends to suffer few variations, despite being affected by negative factors.
In terms of market share among the six dealers, and taking into account the highest segment in the mass market, the premium segment, analysts pointed out that Sands China, Wynn Macau and MGM China get 63 percent of the market, with galaxy, Melco and SJM to get the remaining 37 percent. This trend was considered as within the expected.
The bank also indicated that MGM China “jumped to first place with a quota of approximately 30 percent of observed premium mass bets” due to the presence of a great gambler who was betting about $ 2.9 million from Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:47:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A | Air quality monitoring station in the gutter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/zona-a-estacao-de-monitorizacao-da-qualidade-do-ar-na-calha/</link><description>An air quality monitoring station in zone A of new landfills will be built. Regarding air quality, the SMG director referred to the descent of the atmospheric pollutants concentration in 2023, according to data from the large bay monitoring network. This although the quality air got worse in Macao in 2023 and 2024
 
After a sequence of dangerous or unhealthy air quality days, which even motivated the alert of meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) for the population to avoid going out, the body's director reported improvements in the air quality verified in 2023 at regional level.
In a response to the written interpellation of Congressman Leong Weng Kun, he highlights the results of the regional levels and the work of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau air quality monitoring network to the Rio das Pearl Delta region. ”
According to the SMG director, the 2023 report of the interregional network points out that “the annual average concentration values ​​of various atmospheric pollutants recorded by 2023 fell between 17 and 86 percent over peak levels”. Leong Weng Kun concludes that "emission reduction measures implemented by the three regions were effective in improving regional air quality."
However, the annual statistics of the 2023 and 2024 environment of Macau paint a very different scenario. In 2023, more days were recorded with poor air quality compared to the previous year. In fact, the days with “unhealthy” and “moderate” air were much superior to those with “good” quality. The panorama worsened last year, according to environmental statistics the number of days with “unhealthy” and “very unhealthy” air quality increased to 2023.
Beyond oxygen
The SMG director also emphasizes the study prepared by the three regions to understand the causes of ozone in the large bay region and the transmission characteristics at the interregional level.
Despite the descent of air quality, Leong Weng Kun states that "in recent years, the Government of MSAR has implemented a number of measures to improve air quality, including reducing atmospheric pollutants through incentive and regulation measures, aiming at ozone precursors." The official gives the examples of the prohibition of import and transit of paints for construction, inks for vehicles and stickers for decoration works high with volatile organic compounds.
Regarding the monitoring of atmospheric pollution, Leong Weng Kun reveals that the preparatory work is currently “currently under way” to build an air quality monitoring station in zone A of new urban landfills ”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:41:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Local Accommodation | Lo Choi in recognizes challenges, but asks study</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/alojamento-local-lo-choi-in-reconhece-desafios-mas-pede-estudo/</link><description>The deputy linked to the community of Jiangmen points out that, despite the ban on local accommodation in Macau, there are ads everywhere and that a simple search on the internet has offers for almost all tastes
 
Lo Choi in wants to know if the new government has plans to study the viability of local accommodation in Macao. The issue is part of an interpellation written by the deputy linked to the Jiangmen community, released on the Legislative Assembly portal.
According to Lo Choi In, illegal pensions are currently found in a mixed regime, in which although they are prohibited, they have not been criminalized, which has made them present in Macao. In addition, it indicates, the increase in the number of a new type of tourists in the interior of China has also contributed to the search for these spaces to continue to grow.
In this context, where the deputy asks if it would not be better to study the legal viability of local accommodation, since it becomes increasingly impossible to combat the phenomenon. "The law of the prohibition of illegal accommodation of accommodation did not criminalize the offer of local accommodation in Macao. The legislative intention went to leave margin so that in the future it could advance to legalization," said the deputy, who voted in favor of the proposal. "However, the law imposes an administrative sanction for the offer of local accommodation of 800 thousand patacas, which also reflects the concern of the community with illegal accommodation," he acknowledged. "Does competent services can take the initiative to join some academic institutions, community interest groups and study the viability of local accommodation to examine and explore the advantages and disadvantages to Macao?"
À frente de todos
Lo Choi also considers that despite the problems of illegal accommodation this is an increasingly present reality
The deputy mentions that in recent times her cabinet has increasingly received complaints from residents, because in the buildings where they live, especially in the high times of tourism, it is increasingly frequent to see tourists from the interior of China to enter and get out of travel luggage. There were also complaints about tourists who address residents to ask where local accommodation is, without being aware that it is an illegal practice.
In addition to the increase in the number of complaints received, LO indicates that online search on general search engines or accommodation offer show several illegal housing available in Macao.
Given this growth, and given the illegalization, the deputy asks the government to intensify efforts to combat the phenomenon and to make a campaign for tourists to realize the risks they take, in case of accidents, for being these accommodation.
Lo Choi In also asks the government to make the mechanisms more effective for denouncing illegal housing, especially through online media, which it considers to be the most effective.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:29:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Banking / SME | Prudence with credit due to economic climate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/banca-pme-prudencia-com-credito-devido-a-clima-economico/</link><description>The bank sector squeezed the credit assignment criteria to small and medium enterprises in the new interest bonus plan launched two weeks ago by the government. Andy Wu asks entrepreneurs to make a rigorous assessment of the risks of resorting to loans, at a time when the badoral credit continues at high levels
 
Yesterday two weeks ago the government launched another Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (SME), which will take place until April 22, 2026. After other similar plans, companies and sector representatives indicate that bank criteria for loan approval became more demanding compared to the plans applied during the pandemic period.
The current plan foresees five million Patacas as a maximum amount of credits to be granted to each commercial entrepreneur, with a maximum three -year bonus period and the maximum limit of the annual bonus rate of 4 percent.
A businessman, who did not want to identify to the newspaper or Mun, said he analyzed the criteria and details of the plan, being interested in relieving the liquidity pressure of the company. However, the entrepreneur noted that the requirements are more rigorous than those related to similar loans in 2021 and 2022. Although he thinks that he meets the approval criteria, the entrepreneur indicated to the world not being sure if he will be able to borrow.
Also in anonymity condition, a bank sector professional indicated to the newspaper or Mun that banking institutions only took plans 2021 and 2022 as a reference, but that financial and economic environments have changed since then, forcing banks to change risk assessment criteria.
As we arrived here
Despite greater or less focus on social responsibility aspects, or fiduciary duties before shareholders, the professional heard by the newspaper or Mun considers that, in general, Macao banks assume a partnership position with the SMEs as part of their operative mission.
As such, the source indicates that if companies have a registration without bad credit, credit requests will be accepted.
At the same newspaper, the president of the Federal General Commercial Association of Small and Medium Enterprises of Macau, Andy Wu, suggested to the government, banking and trade and business associations that reinforce the dissemination of the criteria, formalities and deadlines of the interest bonus plan. The official said he understood the prudence of the bank and indicated to expect the entrepreneurs to be considered in the credit request, the assessment of risks and the operative capacity.
The Malparado credit hit last February the highest value since 1990, the year the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) began compiling this data. The latest AMCM data released last week for March and the first quarter of 2025 reveal that despite having down 2.7 percent, the debt to Macao banks was about 56.1 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:22:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature | The interest of linguist Hugo Schuchardt in Patuá de Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/literatura-o-interesse-do-linguista-hugo-schuchardt-no-patua-de-macau/</link><description>Hugo Schuchardt had a genuine interest in Luso-Asian Creole languages, with particular emphasis on Patuá, spoken by the Macanese community. The linguist, who was born in 1842, was the subject of a lecture conducted by researcher Hugo Cardoso, linked to the University of Lisbon
 
Porto, 1883. José Leite de Vasconcelos writes a letter to the German linguist Hugo Schuchardt who had been developing studies, albeit at a distance, about the languages ​​spoken in Asia originated in Portuguese, the so -called Creoles. The letter, written according to the spell agreement of the time, however digitized and today to keep the Archive of the University of Graz, Austria, comes in the context of Schuchardt's own requests to Vasconcelos Milk on the Creole that was then spoken in Macao, known as Patuá.
“My respectable friend: I can only respond to you today. Here in Porto there are no books that say, but I wrote to Lisbon to my friend Vianna and he replied that the Balsmanha does not appear, and that in Macao's story there comes nothing about the dialect port. From Macau. Usual.
I have already asked for information about the Creoles, but I have not yet got anything; This study also interests me about regarding Portuguese. I look forward to the 2 new booklets that promises me. (…) Without anymore I am a friend, J. Vasconcelos Leite, Porto, S. Victor, 25 ”.
Hugo Schuchardt's interest in Luso-Asian Creole has been studied by Hugo Cardoso, a researcher and professor at the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon (FLUL), a Creole specialist who developed investigation at the University of Macao.
The academic recently led a lecture at the National Library in Lisbon over the linguist born in Gotha, Germany, in 1842 and died in Graz, Austria, in 1927, being considered one of the most important linguists of the late nineteenth and early twentieth century. The session was called “Hugo Schuchardt and the search for the Luso-Asian Creole”.
Despite Schuchardt's interest on Macao's Creole, he did not publish any academic work on the subject, as he told HM Hugo Cardoso. "Schuchardt did not publish any work on Macau. However, when he covered his correspondence, it is clear that Macau was also on his radar, since he discusses the Macao Creole with several of his correspondents, including Vasconcelos milk and Gonçalves Viana," he said.
After the German linguist, Hugo Cardoso highlights, “there were actually several people who leaned over Macau Creole, including Danilo Barreiros, José dos Santos Ferreira (Adé), Graciete Batalha, Ana Maria Amaro and, more recently, Prof. Raúl Gaião and Prof. Mário Pinharanda Nunes”. Also noteworthy is the study of Marie Arana-ward "about the Creole spoken by the descendants of Macanese in Hong Kong."
This is another change of correspondence with Vasconcelos milk, dated December 28, 1889, in which books and dictionaries about Portuguese and Chinese are mentioned. “Exmo. Friend: I hurried to respond to your ticket, since you are in a hurry. What I know from China-Portuguese is as follows: J. A. Gonçalves,-Portuguese Dictionary and China-Portuguese. Macau 1831;-China art, Alphabeto and Grammatica. (…) I estimate you to have good shoes. Friend thanks, José Leite de Vasconcellos ”.
The role of rabbit
Hugo Cardoso, whose doctoral thesis is called “The Indo-Portuguese Language of Diu”, former territory of the so-called Portuguese India along with Goa and Damão, spoke at the National Library of Hugo Schuchardt's Studies around this Creole and also the language of Batávia/Tugu in Indonesia.
For the professor at FLUL, pioneering in the study of the Creoles is an expression that rhymes with Schuchardt. The German linguist was "absolutely pioneering in this domain, not only in the study of the Luso-Sasitive Creole or even the Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles globally, but in the study of Creole languages ​​in general" and, for this reason, is "a larger figure in the history of linguistics."
Hugo Cardoso also points out that "as regards the Portuguese lexical base creoles, before him, there had been some activity, especially by Adolfo Coelho, who, in 1881, had published" Romanesque or Neo-Latin dialects in Africa, Asia and America, "in which he was a caught in various Portuguese-based Creole." However, in this work, Adolfo Coelho refers only to three Luso-Asiatic Creole: “Ceylon's (at Sri Lanka), Malaca and Macau's-giving some examples that he could get from previous publications (such as Macau's Ta-Ss-Yang-Kuo magazine)”.
The academic has no doubt that “Hugo Schuchardt was surely inspired by Rabbit's work, but his efforts to obtain primary data from many other Asian places greatly expanded cartography of the Luso-sinical Creole and resulted in the first published news and the first grammatical descriptions of many of them (such as Diu, Cananor, Mahé, Mangar, Mangar, Mangar etc.) ”.
Future inspirations
According to Hugo Cardoso, the German linguist left works that inspired future academics and many materials from the personal archive. "One effect of his work was to inspire other agents to develop similar work: there stands out the figure of Sebastião Rodolfo Dalgado, who led his own research and made his own publications about the Indo-Portuguese Creoles that Schuchardt had not approached, about Damão, Bombaim, Ceylon and Negapath."
In the case of José de Leite Vasconcelos, who wrote the letter cited at the beginning of this text, "it also corresponded with Schuchardt and reveals, in his linguistic studies, the impact of Schuchardt's work."
Asked by HM about the possible interconnections between the Creole of IUD, Batávia and Macao, Hugo Cardoso states that there are "continuities between the various Luso-Asian Creole, but also many differences." "The Batávia/Tugu Creole is the one that most resembles Creole de Macao, for example, at the Lexicon level. But this is understandable because it has already shown that Macao Creole has an important historical connection with the Creole that developed in Southeast Asia, in particular Malaca."
According to an academic article by Hugo Cardoso himself written in partnership with Tjerk Hagemeijer and Nélia Alexandre, entitled “Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles”, these “were, in most cases, oral languages ​​to the nineteenth century, when the first collections of oral traditions, texts and translations began to emerge, being linked“ to maritime expansion in Africa and Asia, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact between the contact. Portuguese and different African and Asian languages ​​”.
Also according to the same article, "some of these Crioulos, namely in Asia, were extinguished, having only recorded from the transition from the nineteenth century to the twentieth century. With the exception of the Creole of Alta Guinea, the vitality of the living Portuguese Creole is generally decreasing."
In the case of Creoles of Portuguese origin in the southern Asia area, they emerged from the arrival of Vasco da Gama to Calecute, India, in 1498, especially from the phase in which the entire base of the Portuguese empire the East focuses on Goa. According to the same academic article, several Creole were developed, the so-called “Indo-Portuguese” in coastal areas of India, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Burma. "Currently, its presence is much reduced: they survive those of IUD, Damão, Korlai, Cananor and Sri Lanka (Ceylon) - which, despite having, has once been used all over the island, is currently restricted to the cities of Batticaloa and Trinchomalee," is highlighted in the article. The author draws attention to the extinction in 2010 of the Vaipim Creole, in Cochim, due to the "death of what seems to have been the last fluent speaker in this region." There are then the Southeast Asia and East Asia Creole, which includes Macao. Patuá is currently “spoken with native fluency only by some people in Macau and the Macanese diaspora”, is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:19:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Hamas warns that it is not worth negotiating new truce</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/gaza-hamas-avisa-que-nao-vale-a-pena-negociar-nova-tregua/</link><description>A high Hamas employee said yesterday that the Palestinian group considers it useless at this stage negotiations for a truce in Gaza, and appealed to the world to press Israel to end the “hunger war” at the enclave.
"It is not worth starting negotiations or examining new ceasefire proposals while the Hunger War and the Gaza Extermination War continues," France-Presse (AFP) Bassem Naïm, a member of the Hamas political office, told the agency. "The world must press the government of Netanyahu to end the crimes of hunger, thirst and murder," he added.
The statements appear a day after the Israelite government announced a new military campaign in the Gaza Strip, which provides for the conquest of the territory. The Gaza Strip, where the inhabitants have been displaced several times, has been under a blockade of Israel since March 2 and crosses a serious humanitarian crisis.
Gaza Civil Defense spokesman Mahmoud Baçal said yesterday that three Palestinians were killed following Israeli bombing at dawn in different parts of the Gaza Strip. The Israelite army resumed the enclave offensive on March 18, ending a two -month truce.
The war was triggered by Hamas's unprecedented attack on Israel on October 7, 2023, which caused the death of 1,218 people on the Israeli side, mostly civilians, according to an AFP count based on official data.
Of the 251 kidnapped people, 58 remain arrested in Gaza, 34 of which were declared killed by the Israelite army. Hamas also maintains the remains of an Israeli soldier killed during a previous war in Gaza in 2014. The Israeli retaliation campaign made at least 52,567 killed in Gaza, most of Civil, according to Hamas Ministry of Health, considered UN reliable.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:17:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Elderly | Recognizes difficulties in social companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/idosos-ias-reconhece-dificuldades-de-empresas-sociais/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) recognizes that the new trade environment has negatively affected the only two social companies that have among its functions to hire elderly workers. The current scenario was outlined in response to an interpetement of Deputy Lei Chan U, linked to the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations (Faom).
"Currently, the two social companies for the elderly who came into operation are from the area of ​​restoration, providing 16 full -time and six part -time vacancies for the elderly," he was explained. "The two projects of social company went into operation during the pandemic period. Due to the impact of the pandemic and market environment, the daily operation and development of social companies were relatively affected. After the pandemic, society and the economy of Macao gradually recovered, however, in the face of the constant change of the business environment of Macau, the operation of companies, including the elderly companies, faced many challenges and pressures."
Despite various strategies to relaunch the business, such as promotions or extending opening hours, IAS President Hon Wai admits that the situation has known few improvements. However, IAS indicates that the future deceiving plan of action for support services to the elderly, which is expected to take effect next year, should have more measures to encourage the hiring of the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:39:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Auditors of Macau company accused of accounting accounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/auditores-de-empresa-de-macau-acusados-de-falsificacao-de-contas/</link><description>Four Wellink CPA auditors and consultants are accused of having falsified Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited accounts so that this Macao company could enter the Hong Kong bag. The case was revealed yesterday through a Hong Kong Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) and is also being investigated in Macao.
According to the results of the investigation that took place since 2021, auditors and consultants Lam Shui-Mei, Siu Yuen-Shan, Cha Wai-Lun and Wong Yat-Chung falsified Huarchi Global accounts to show fictitious economic growth and be admitted to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange.
In addition, the four asked for the help of three family members, identified as Li Man-Heung, Li Kit-Chit and Wong Wing-Man, to subscribe to the company's first public offering. According to the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC), which assisted the ICAC in investigations, those involved in the purchase of shares received $ 1.5 million from Hong Kong.
As a result, the four are accused of two conspiracy crimes to defraud the Hong Kong bag, while the three family members are accused of a conspiracy crime to defraud the Hong Kong bag. The seven will be present throughout this day to a Hong Kong court. However, the ICAC has admitted that investigations are still running and that there may be other accusations.
Investigation in Macau
In Macao, searches were performed at the headquarters of Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited in the Plaza Civil Building.
The president of the group appears identified in the 2021 company annual report as Lou Cheok Meng. The identity was not confirmed by the Macao corruption commissioner, who in a statement of the case confirmed that he was running an independent investigation in Macau.
"This construction company is a local Macao company and its official is also a resident of Macao, so CCAC has established an investigation process following the respective indications of crime," he was reported. In addition, CCAC reported that the case continues to be investigated in the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:15:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese musical instrument conference in Mafra</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/conferencia-de-instrumentos-musicais-chineses-em-mafra/</link><description>The eighth edition of the Music Festival “Lisbon Conference Chinese Music and Musical Instruments” [Lisbon Conference on Chinese Music and Musical Instruments] takes off until Sunday between Lisbon and Mafra, being a supported and funded event, including linked to Macao, as is the case of Jorge Álvares Foundation and Macau Foundation, among others.
More specifically, today, tomorrow and Friday, 9 the event takes place at the National Palace of Mafra. This year's theme is “Expanding Horizons: Embracing The Wide Variety of Asian Music and Dance” [Expand the horizons: embracing the wide variety of music and Asian dance].
The idea is that in the coming days you talk and hear not only Chinese music, but also the Asian sounds and know more about the musical instruments that make these sounds. Today is the panel “Traditional and Popular Performing Arts of Asia” [Traditional and Popular Performative Arts of Asia], which will talk about Chinese folk music thanks to the intervention of Frank Kouwenhoven, researcher at Leiden University. Three academic interventions are followed by Naxi's folk songs in southwest China.
Also noteworthy for the panel dedicated to Macau, namely “Macau: Crossroads for Chinese and European Music” [Macao: A Crossroads for Chinese and European music], with interventions by Xiao Ling Shao, who will speak of the “art of Portuguese music in Macau” and Enio de Souza, who will make a “approach to musical instruments in the Chinese temples of Macao”. Highlight for the lecture starring José Pinto de Sá and Rui Magno Pinto on “Memory of Portuguese Classical Music Concerts in Macau”.
The musical part also happens today, from 19h [Time of Lisbon], at the Casa da Música Francisco Alves Gato, in Mafra, with a concert with the musicians Superena insert Adler, François Picard and Je Jinhua, among others, with various Asian instruments.
Popular sounds
Tomorrow, Thursday, it is the turn of the debate around the music to do in Mafra, starting at 10am [Time of Lisbon] with three personalities from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, China, who speak of “Investigation in the theories of the composition of Chinese music”. This is followed by the lecture by Rakesh Kumar, from South Africa, who will speak of the “Afro-Indian Siddi Goma-Dhamal Performances: Bridging The Past and Present, The Local and Global [Afro-Indian performances Siddi Goma-Dhamal: Bringing the past and the gift, the place and the global].
Again from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, China, Feng Changchun emerges talking about “empathy through time and space - the poetry of Li Yu and the art of the composition of the modern Chinese song”. In turn, Maureen Russell of the UCLA Ethnomusicology Department - University of California, Los Angeles, will talk about musical archives in “Sharing Soundscapes: The Bake / Jairazbhoy Digital Archive of South Asian Traditional Music and Arts”.
This Saturday, parallel sessions take place at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon on Chinese and Asian music in general terms. One of the panels about musical history before and after 1949 ″, in which Zhang Xiaodong, from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, will present a “Study on Historical Development and Yueqin Performance Formats”, an instrument of Chinese strings. Another example of a lecture is the session starring Lisa Beebe, from the University of Wisonsin-Whitewater, about the presence of Vietnamese instruments in Canada.
Jonathan Stock also addresses the theme “Thematic and Multivocal Approach to the History of Music in the Republic of China (1912-1949)”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:13:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Must | “Hug of Love” and other works, by Leong Kit Man, on display</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/must-abraco-do-amor-e-outras-obras-de-leong-kit-man-em-exposicao/</link><description>The University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must, in the English acronym) hosts until Sunday the show of Leong Kit Man, with several paintings, where the creation “Hug of Love” stands out. These are works funded by the Young Talent Support Program of Artistic Creation of the National Arts Fund of China, in its edition of 2024, curated by Julia Kwan
 
Leong Kit Man, a young local artist, exposes his work "Hug of Love" until this Sunday at the University of Science and Technology of Macau (Must, in the English acronym). It is a large painting, with 4.8 by 4.8 meters, the result of an artistic project funded by the Youth Talent Support Program of Artistic Creation of the China National Arts Fund of 2024.
According to a Must statement, this is a painting where flowers and birds gain prominence, breaking “with the traditional composition of topographic painting”.
According to a curator's note, Julia Lam Tsz Kwan, the artist “unites [in painting] human landscapes and a centenary tree in a vision through segmented color blocks, with diverse elements, including the ancestral tree that symbolizes the life cycle, nests that symbolize homes, creation of pups that represent the adoption and inheritance, and precede plates that evoke prayers”. All of these elements “mean human growth”, read in the same note.
In addition to this great picture, the public can also see “six original large -scale paintings of flowers and birds, along with preparatory designs, sketches and color studies of the artist”. The show also includes “a special digital animation” framed with the painting “Hug of Love”. This set of works indicates that “beyond the technical inheritance, the evolution of Chinese painting is in line with the continuous pioneering of new artistic expressions”. All of these works can be seen free of charge on the fourth floor of Must's block.
Style
In the same note, it is noteworthy that Leong Kit Man has been looking for more than a decade for over a decade, “merging the gongbi-style meticulous brush, with textures material, in order to obtain a distinct style, while exploiting and expanding infinite possibilities of the oriental [artistic] media”.
It should be noted that the Gongbi style is, in Chinese painting, synonymous with detail and precision in how the various elements are portrayed, in order to give a sense of great realism to those who look at the works. For this style of painting, specific brushes are used in order to obtain certain types of lines and contours, according to the objective that the artist wants to achieve.
Mo Xiaoye, exhibition advisor and professor at the Department of Fine Arts at Zhejiang University of Science and Technology, said that the play “Hug of Love” represents “from a single perspective, the Macau Peninsula seen from far from Cotai”. For the academic, this painting also allows “a highly creative and successful rereading of Macau's topographic painting, breaking with conventional formats”.
The artist herself explains that this work "has as its backdrop the urban landscape of Macao dramatically transformed 25 years after the transfer [Portuguese administration from Macau to China], with a centenary tree as a central piece to look at us, who passed through it."
Doctorate in Fine Arts from the National Academy of Arts of China, artist, academic and curator, Leong Kit Man is assistant teacher of Fine Arts and Master's Supervisor and PhD at the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of Must.
The artist also had works selected for the China National Art Exhibition in 2014, 2019, and 2024. Highlight for the work “Emplendor Efémeus”, which was chosen to join the Exhibition of Select Works of the National Exhibition of Fine Arts of 2019 in Beijing. The artist won several awards at Macau's annual visual arts exhibition.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:11:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Victory Day | China sends guard of honor to parades in Moscow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/dia-da-vitoria-china-envia-guarda-de-honra-para-desfiles-em-moscovo/</link><description>The China army will send a guard of honor to the Victory Day parades in Moscow, where Chinese President Xi Jinping should attend the Russian homologist Vladimir Putin in Red Square.
The China Ministry of Defense announced on Monday that it will send a guard of honor to participate in the military parades in the capitals of Russia and Belarus, to mark the 80th anniversary of the defeat of Germany Nazi, which is celebrated this Friday.
Beijing sent Moscow Honor Guards to a Victory Day commemorative parade in 2015, but this will be the first time a Chinese guard of honor will participate in a similar event in Minsk.
According to Chinese analysts, the gesture aims to demonstrate support for the International Order of Post World War, which Beijing considers to be under threat. Videos released on Chinese social networks showed the rehearsals of Chinese soldiers in Minsk and Moscow last week.
As part of the preparations for the Moscow Parade, Chinese soldiers rehearsed the “Guerrilla Song” in Red Square on Sunday, described the Global Times, the Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper. The patriotic song describes the difficulties faced by Chinese soldiers during the Japanese invasion.
Official News Agency Xinhua said this year is important to China and Russia, as well as “all those who love peace around the world,” as it also marks the 80th anniversary of the end of the invasion of Japan in China.
Xinhua added that China and Russia will "defend written history with blood and lives, and oppose any attempt or behavior that seeks to deny, distort or falsify the history of World War II." Beijing had already announced that Xi will visit Russia between Wednesday and Saturday, and will maintain a “strategic dialogue” with Putin.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:08:14</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP | Detained harassment passenger</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/cpsp-detido-assediar-passageira-de-autocarro/</link><description>A man, about 20, was arrested by the Public Security Police (CPSP), after taking advantage of the fact that an bus is full to harass a passenger. The case happened on Wednesday April 30. According to the PSP, that day, the man rubbed the pelvic zone against women's hips for several minutes.
The 20 -year -old didn't react immediately, and let the man leave the bus. However, he eventually filed a complaint to the police, moments later. The resident was identified using the bus recording system and the city's video surveillance.
Asked by the authorities, after being arrested, the man confessed to the practice of the facts. In addition to these suspicions, in the criminal record, the man has a conviction for the crime of illicit recordings in 2018 and another debut conviction of private life in 2021.
Alcohol | Man caught with 1.26 g/l in the blood
A man, about 40, was arrested after being caught driving at a 1.26 grams per liter of blood. The case took place on May 1, was presented yesterday by the Public Security Police (CPSP) and quoted by the newspaper or Mun.
The driver was caught while circulating on Avenida da Ponte da Amizade, around 5am, and was stopped in a police routine operation. When stopped, CPSP agents smelled alcohol and asked the driver to take the alcohol test.
As the result was 1.26 grams per liter of blood, the man admitted to being alcohol during a dinner in the black sand, so the case was referred to the prosecutor.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:51:39</pubDate></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 2025
In Chinese proverbial lessons I discovered great affinities between spontaneous Chinese popular philosophy, which runs from mouth to mouth, and the Christian proverbial wisdom, also made so that believers, in every corner of the globe, could memorize, repeat and disseminate.
Nothing like the other's knowledge to bring and dispel prejudice, being one of the most usual that Chinese are extremely pragmatic and cold. But when we come across proverbs such as “love others as yourself,” in a direct translation and faithful to the original “爱人如己” (ài Rú Rú Jǐ), such leads us to think twice, it seems not to be here just a matter of respect, uncharged and formal, but rather a strong feeling for the other, not any, only a deep affection, of those we understand well that we are good, we will be well, we will be well, we will be well, we will be better. Then he runs a love of the Christian way for China without Christ ever been. Such finding can lead us to the assumption of the existence of universal structures, not only logical, including as regards affections, therefore sentimental. After all, selfishness may not be a dominant tendency, there is everything: selfish, aggressive and competitive people, as others will be naturally altruistic, compassionate and cooperatives, ready to recognize the universality of the feeling of love, which crosses borders rather than erecting them, bringing people closer to the most diverse social classes, ethnic groups, geographies, as in "love has no borders", in a direct translation "" (Àiqíng wú jiējí zhī fēn), here is particularly emphasized social borders.
The content of the message gains full sense when one realizes that love to oneself takes place in a culture that many consider wrong and prejudiced only to focus on the whole, in the community.  Attention to the person, the particular and the style and feeling of each, lives, in philosophies such as Taoist for centuries with the valorization of the collectivity, this ultimate tendency manifestly inculcated and worked by Confucianism.  Love to itself, care for the individual body and mind, is emphasized in the so -called Proverbial “well -understood love and virtue must begin with us”, which has the following correspondence in Chinese “爱德从己起” (to Cong Jǐ qǐ).
Anyone who imagines that in proverbial wisdom there is only place to praise and sing relational love, since the Chinese do not have any religious philosophy that chants spiritual love above all, in the Christian way of St. Augustine, will be surprised to find the following proverb "where there is no other gentleman", that in a direct translation of the Chinese is "the love above all" 爱情至上 爱情至上 爱情至上ZHì Shàng).
If in doubt, there is another saying of complementary meaning and in which the idea of ​​the integrity and unity of this powerful affection, which moves mountains in the Christian sense, when it reads 爱情专一 （（（（iqíng zhuān yī）, in a possible translation "love cannot be broken", "one person cannot have a heart in two parts at the same time."
From a psychological point of view, the acceptance of the other in loving terms will have to be complete, so their tastes, affections, relationships, and objects cannot be rejected, as is clear from the lesson "Who loves Beltrão, loves their dog", in a relative correspondence for "爱屋及乌" (ài wū jí wū), which in a literal translation would be "love the house and the crums."
As is well known, proverbs are susceptible to various interpretations, so they say polysemic, but if they are perspective as a whole, and only then as pieces of a puzzle, there seems to be many doubts with regard to the proverb philosophy and psychology of Chinese love, which is echoed in the country's scholarly philosophies.
In Chapter 67 of the Book of the road and virtue (《道德经》), also known by the name of the Patriarch of Taoism, Lazi (老子), is the first of the three guiding virtues of the Wise Way, love, as you can read in the translation of Claudia Ribeiro (2004, 139):
I have three treasures
What entesouro and retains:
The first is love (CI),
The second frugality,
The third is not daring to be the vanguard of the world.
(…)
For love,
In combat, it triumphs,
And in defense it is firm.
The sky will come to aid
And, with love, will protect
(我有三寶/寶而持之/一曰慈/二曰儉/三曰不敢為天下先 (……) 夫慈以戰則勝//以守則固/以慈衛之 1)
It is noted that while in proverbial philosophy the synogram used for love is 爱/愛 2 (AI), in the scholarly philosophy of the Patriarch of Taoism the term employment is 慈 (CI), that is, love with a strong relational and spiritual burden; Although they are different words, both refer to love, the first concerns the most physical and concrete feeling, centered on the heart of the person and the clutches that hold it;  The second to that most relational and general indicates that love comes from inside the heart (内心 nèixīn), where it has the roots, emerging like any plant. However, the truth is that both terms focus on people, or rather in their hearts, affectionate connection with others, such a strong connection that draws the attention of heaven (天 tiān), maximum impersonal power, it ensures victory on all battle fronts, whether in the forefront or rear, when fighting and defended itself for love.
Already the patriarch of Confucianism, Confucius (孔子), in the Chapter Twelve, later entitled the deep face, of the Analects (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 22) defines the main virtue of the school, benevolence or humanity, (仁 Rén) as an act of love to others, maintaining the term of the traditional vernacular 爱 (AI): “Fan Chi asked what was the benevolence was what answered, "love people". " (樊遲問仁 ， 子曰 「愛人 3。 ”) It is in this context of love of neighbor, that one of the main maxims of Confucian philosophy must be understood, which arises in the same chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 2)“ Do not make the others what they do not want for you ”(己所不欲勿施於人 jǐ suǒ bù yù shunk yú rén).
The essentials in Confucian philosophy will then guarantee love of others in terms of respect or humanity towards others, in order to ensure the normal functioning of society, without extreme sacrifices or exaggerated explorations, given to the proverb containment of confusion in relation to feelings, they are important and useful but should not extravate the boundaries of rationality, that is, even the best of them, will have to be measured, controlled and ritualized in the name of harmony collective. Therefore, the love that moves friendships, especially intellectuals, is the most praised, as we remembered at the end of this chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 24):
Zeng Zi stated: “A gentleman resorts to knowing to make friends and friends to cultivate benevolence4” (曾子曰：君以文會友 ， 以友輔仁。)
Finally, also the Buddhist philosophy, especially from the Chan (禅 Chán) or Zen meditation line, praises the love of humanity, but indirectly, drawing attention to the heart and the identification of Buddha with the heart, the way of the Daoxin Patriarch (道信) and its maximum proverbially known “the heart is Buddha and Buddha is the heart” (非心不问佛 ， 问佛不非心 fēi xīn bùwèn fu, wèn fi bù fēi xīn). Here you come to love indirectly, only an enlightened heart can love the Buddha, as it is not surprising in the picture of this philosophy, after all what is Buddha but the very love that expresses itself not in a selfish, sick, self -centered heart, but in a heart capable of establishing relationships, healthy, altruistic and without empty, but not indifferent to the other?  This confirms it the social and humanitarian actions of Via Mahayana Buddhism, which was accepted in China and unfolds in collective works such as the construction of educational institutions, hospitals, centers of social solidarity, in a proselytist action at all similar to the history of the Christian Church and its missionaries around the world.
Bibliographic references
Lansheng, Jiang (Comp.) 1997. 100 Excerpts from Zen Buddhist Texts. Hong Hong Kong: Commercial Press.
NGAN, António André. 1998. SINE-SHORE CONGRELLANCE OF PROVERBS AND IDIOMATIC PHRASES. 中葡對照成語集. Macau: Macao Adult Association.
RIBEIRO, Claudia (Trad). 2004. 《道德經》 The Book of Road and Power. Bilingual edition. Mem-Martins: European American Publications.
Xin Guanjie (辛冠洁) (org. And trad.) 1994. 《論語》 .Tradument for contemporary Chinese falls xiqin (蔡希勤) and English translation of Lai Bo (赖波) and Xia Yuhe (夏玉和). Beijing: Sinolingue.
References:
Text in classic Chinese.
Love in simplified and traditional Chinese.
Text in classic Chinese.
A gentleman in ancient Chinese times was a gentleman and a potential ruler.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Bai Juyi (772-846), the poet of the Tang Dynasty attentive to the slightest changes in everyday life, in the poem in which he celebrates the renewal of the house he had just bought in spring, ends with the verses:
«If there is something that suits my spirit,
There are ten thousand complications seem forgotten.
Assuming that beyond the gate of my residence,
Something happens - I will know nothing about it. »
And this gate of a house or monastery, often cluttering a garden, a mentally ordered space, more than a physical limit marked a spiritual border.
Over the centuries of the imperial regime this ideal of feeling far away, it would endure in the lives of literati who would like to live free as hermits, but could not withdraw from cities due to their obligations with the imperial government.
This was also the case of his contemporary Pei du (765-839), who wrote in a poem:
«On the way to my gate
A clear river is seen,
Old trees grow uniforms
around the stalk roof eaves.
The red dust flies
But it doesn't come so far,
And every once in a while you listen to
the chilre of a bird. »
Eminent painter and theorist Dong Qichang (1555-1636) cited many years later PEI DU verses in the vertical landscape roll (ink on paper, 130.5 x 39.2 cm in Smithonian) made for a friend who visited him in Shanghai, shortly after the new year of 1617.
In it, there is neither a gate nor any person but on the banks of the river that dominates the representation, in the foreground, a willow-chronicle marks the presence of an absence. This same willow who will be found later in various paintings of one of the Qianlong court painters.
As in the 1770 landscape (paint on paper, 26.3 x 33.3 cm at the Cernuschi museum) where the use of low ink brush and an empty housing evokes the apparent simplicity of Dong Qichang painting, but with a calculated geometric disposition of the various planes.
Zhejiang's Fang Cong (c.1749-1790) had arrived at the Court in 1736 with other painters that would stand out as Zhang Zhongchang or Ding Guanpeng and deserve the approval of Qianlong, noted in poems that the emperor wrote about his paintings.
About a snow landscape, made on a sheet of album (ink and color on paper, 26 x 32.8 cm, at the Cernuschi museum) is perceived the advantage of being sheltered behind the gate but the beauty of the white scenario causes a disturbing indecision.
Just like the designated willow-songer Liu, which was used in farewells, given the homophony with a word meaning "stays", although the person will leave. Even protected inside houses, sometimes enclosed a courtyard by all sides (Siheyuan), behind the gate the spirit flies that there is something out there that is important and should not be lost.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Duarte Drumond Braga</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/duarte-drumond-braga/</link><description>Arrested to a long and distant oriental princess myth, it seemed to enjoy an impalpable resentment. Half Lispector, Half Pearl Buck, had yet to be the boat of the Empire. It was even further. He then returned to tea with sadness in Benfica. Braga was his first China, Macao the second, no China.
But the Portuguese do not forgive who is different. It had no face of either Quinta do Lago, nor Moimenta da Beira. He was wearing a booth in his green buttons. It remembered a uniform of the cultural revolution. So how did you want to identify class and provenance immediately? In Braga, wouldn't there be any other China to wear?
Nobody:                   ; Portuguese literature from 50 to 80: uninteresting fictions without reference after uninteresting fictions with references. Ah, very telluric, with towers, houses and other totems. Bad weather in the tower, the house of.
However, all the women's struggles, the other's knowledge, Palpar do Si - everything is already in it, before us, waiting to be found. We arrived almost to contemporary identities et alii.
So far from the pastry Agustina with his Pataratice of Entre Douro and Minho (this yard from the northernmost palace) and so close to authors that they seem provincial but they are nothing, like Pascoaes.
However, Ondina's books get dust in the library. The keys to know China or to know the world (almost the same thing) are in the keychain. And how much pedagogy of China (a belt, a road, a rounding around the world that we could also form) could not give us, how much another world?
And why don't you read Wenceslau de Moraes too? Here there is no excuse of being a woman. Is it talking about Japan? Would it be better to talk about Telheiras? But isn't it Japan, or perhaps Tibet, the true meaning of Portuguese culture? To die the world? Could it be. For when a Tibetan Ondina, a Malay Wenceslau?
People like it is to talk about their mental palace terreiros: Lisbon, or Times Square. The true, these days, will never want to know, but from now on years - and then it will be too late. It is always too far, already said the Xana of Radio Macau. Et pour cause.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Bai Juyi (772-846), the poet of the Tang Dynasty attentive to the slightest changes in everyday life, in the poem in which he celebrates the renewal of the house he had just bought in spring, ends with the verses:
«If there is something that suits my spirit,
There are ten thousand complications seem forgotten.
Assuming that beyond the gate of my residence,
Something happens - I will know nothing about it. »
And this gate of a house or monastery, often cluttering a garden, a mentally ordered space, more than a physical limit marked a spiritual border.
Over the centuries of the imperial regime this ideal of feeling far away, it would endure in the lives of literati who would like to live free as hermits, but could not withdraw from cities due to their obligations with the imperial government.
This was also the case of his contemporary Pei du (765-839), who wrote in a poem:
«On the way to my gate
A clear river is seen,
Old trees grow uniforms
around the stalk roof eaves.
The red dust flies
But it doesn't come so far,
And every once in a while you listen to
the chilre of a bird. »
Eminent painter and theorist Dong Qichang (1555-1636) cited many years later PEI DU verses in the vertical landscape roll (ink on paper, 130.5 x 39.2 cm in Smithonian) made for a friend who visited him in Shanghai, shortly after the new year of 1617.
In it, there is neither a gate nor any person but on the banks of the river that dominates the representation, in the foreground, a willow-chronicle marks the presence of an absence. This same willow who will be found later in various paintings of one of the Qianlong court painters.
As in the 1770 landscape (paint on paper, 26.3 x 33.3 cm at the Cernuschi museum) where the use of low ink brush and an empty housing evokes the apparent simplicity of Dong Qichang painting, but with a calculated geometric disposition of the various planes.
Zhejiang's Fang Cong (c.1749-1790) had arrived at the Court in 1736 with other painters that would stand out as Zhang Zhongchang or Ding Guanpeng and deserve the approval of Qianlong, noted in poems that the emperor wrote about his paintings.
About a snow landscape, made on a sheet of album (ink and color on paper, 26 x 32.8 cm, at the Cernuschi museum) is perceived the advantage of being sheltered behind the gate but the beauty of the white scenario causes a disturbing indecision.
Just like the designated willow-songer Liu, which was used in farewells, given the homophony with a word meaning "stays", although the person will leave. Even protected inside houses, sometimes enclosed a courtyard by all sides (Siheyuan), behind the gate the spirit flies that there is something out there that is important and should not be lost.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A high Hamas employee said yesterday that the Palestinian group considers it useless at this stage negotiations for a truce in Gaza, and appealed to the world to press Israel to end the “hunger war” at the enclave.
"It is not worth starting negotiations or examining new ceasefire proposals while the Hunger War and the Gaza Extermination War continues," France-Presse (AFP) Bassem Naïm, a member of the Hamas political office, told the agency. "The world must press the government of Netanyahu to end the crimes of hunger, thirst and murder," he added.
The statements appear a day after the Israelite government announced a new military campaign in the Gaza Strip, which provides for the conquest of the territory. The Gaza Strip, where the inhabitants have been displaced several times, has been under a blockade of Israel since March 2 and crosses a serious humanitarian crisis.
Gaza Civil Defense spokesman Mahmoud Baçal said yesterday that three Palestinians were killed following Israeli bombing at dawn in different parts of the Gaza Strip. The Israelite army resumed the enclave offensive on March 18, ending a two -month truce.
The war was triggered by Hamas's unprecedented attack on Israel on October 7, 2023, which caused the death of 1,218 people on the Israeli side, mostly civilians, according to an AFP count based on official data.
Of the 251 kidnapped people, 58 remain arrested in Gaza, 34 of which were declared killed by the Israelite army. Hamas also maintains the remains of an Israeli soldier killed during a previous war in Gaza in 2014. The Israeli retaliation campaign made at least 52,567 killed in Gaza, most of Civil, according to Hamas Ministry of Health, considered UN reliable.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PME | Events promoted by Melco generated $ 1 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/pme-eventos-promovidos-pela-melco-geraram-1-milhao-de-dolares/</link><description>Melco Resorts claims to have generated about $ 1 million for small and medium -sized local businesses through events promoted last year. In the 2024 sustainability report, the game operator also highlights the results in terms of waste management and energy spending
 
The Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment Sustainability Report has just been published last year, which highlights the gains obtained by small and medium -sized (SMEs) with the events promoted by the operator. With regard to the “community engagement and investment” part, it is read that “more than $ 1.02 million for local companies and [NGO] non-governmental organizations in Macao through 21 SME events, with 603 SME and NGO participants” were generated. In addition, in the volunteering area, Melco points out that "about 3,600 participants offered their time and effort in more than 359 volunteering initiatives," "more than $ 17.42 million that were donated to decent causes in our communities."
Quoted by the report, Lawrence Ho, Melco's president and executive director, says that "21 Heart of House initiatives and community events have generated more than $ 1 million for local companies in Macao, providing 603 SMEs and NGO opportunities to connect, expand and grow." According to the official, last year were "in -depth partnerships with PME and NGO".
Regarding the relationship with local SMEs, Melco also highlights the connection with the supply chain, because “86 percent of acquisitions arose from local companies in Macao”, and of this total, “59 percent were local SME acquisitions”. Similar scenario occurred in the other operators that Melco holds in Cyprus and Manila, with local acquisitions around 40 and 76 percent, respectively.
Regarding the company's training actions, Melco says it has invested on average "582 US dollars per full -time worker in learning and development activities, which is equivalent to an average of 38 hours of training." In this context, “100 percent of colleagues participated in training actions”, can be read. In addition, "over 758,000 participants have attended more than 1,400 courses offered by" Melco Learning Academy ", which is equivalent to over 870,000 hours of learning." Also noteworthy is that, in all Melco projects, "women represent 23 percent of the boards of business and 32 percent of the higher paintings."
The report also tells that “63 percent of positions at the vice-presidency level, or above this post, were filled from local communities, increasing to 70 percent in Macao”, can read.
All for the environment
Another of the areas highlighted in Melco's sustainability report concerns environmental policies. One of the areas that is “in progress” is the energy consumption, in order to obtain more reasonableness of consumption. "In 2024, despite an increase of 39 percent in terms of the number of visitors and the rise of 19 percent in the occupation rate of the hotel rooms, along with the addition of a property and a new resort integrated into our portfolio, the energy intensity increased by 10 percent from 2023, but was 19 percent lower than our year of reference 2019."
One of the “achieved” objectives is the energy efficiency measures, which “since 2018 has resulted in an annualized savings of more than 62.5 million kWh, an increase of 9 percent compared to 2023”. Another "achieved" goal concerns the installation of "over 25,000 photovoltaic panels on all properties in Macau, Manila and Cyprus, generating about 10,000 kWh annually." Thus, in the properties of Melco "the electricity consumption from renewable sources increased by 72 percent compared to 2023".
Regarding the group's means of transportation, “buses, electric and hybrid vehicles represent 55 percent of our combined fleet, with loading stations, an increase of 25 percent compared to 2023”.
In terms of materials and waste management, Melco says it has avoided plastic spending in the order of 13.2 million bottles, thanks to the installation of “the Nordaq water filtering system that serves almost every hotel rooms in Melco's integrated resorts”.
In addition, the example of the City of Dreams venture in Manila is presented where “a circular economy system was established in which food waste is decomposed on site, and the excess donated to a local fifth to cultivate some of the vegetables served to guests”.
In terms of water consumption, the report indicates that “despite the increase in the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate”, “total water consumption and water intensity increased only 6 and 2 percent compared to 2023, respectively, and were 6 and 30 percent lower, respectively, to the 2019 reference year”. However, this is a goal that, according to the company, is still "in progress".
Another objective highlighted in the report was the “annual economy of over 510,820 cubic meters of water through water efficiency measures, an increase of 10 percent compared to 2023 ″.
"As we invest in people and communities, we continue to derive environmental efforts with the same determination. (…) The intensity of energy and water consumption, as well as greenhouse gas emissions, remained significantly below our 2019 base line, even adding a new property and an integrated resort," says Lawrence Ho.
The entrepreneur also referred to the increase "of the amount of valuable materials diverted through recycling and composting in global operations - 58 percent over last year." “In our restoration spaces we also fight food waste, with the 'clean dish challenge' to contribute to a 9 percent reduction in waste in the Macao and Manila restoration areas.”
“Mentality change”
For Lawrence Ho, greater sustainability in Melco requires "a change of mindset" verified in "small actions that, on scale, can have a significant impact."
Regarding the supply chain of the group's integrated hotels and resorts, good results are also highlighted. "Although the numbers do not always show exponential heels, our focus on responsible supply remains unwavering, 18 percent of all seafood bought by weight to be sustainable sources, and 100 percent of our food and drink points in Macao and Manila to serve eggs of outdoor chickens," he reads.
There is thus "an effort that reflects a deeper ambition to incorporate sustainability into acquisitions," said Lawrence Ho, who added that "more than one service, hospitality has to do with the experience it creates, the people it supports and the impact it leaves."
“Every year, Melco challenges himself to go further, believing that luxury and responsibility are not opposite forces, but partners in progress, which is reflected in the way we defend strong governance, we manage our environmental impact, we support our people and communities and lead the responsible game. This commitment to progress shaped our approach in 2024, as a year of recalibration in which we continue to strengthen operations, operations, rekindle the impetus and ensure that our integrated resorts remain at the forefront of excellence, ”he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:08:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Seismos | Macau will have a monitoring station in national partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/sismos-macau-vai-ter-estacao-de-monitorizacao-em-parceria-nacional/</link><description>The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, presented on Wednesday the report of the 2025 government lines for his tutelage, and said to the deputies that a seismo monitoring station will be created in partnership with interior authorities from China will be created.
 
The Macao government announced on Wednesday the creation, together with the interior authorities of China, of a seismic monitoring station, as part of the authorities' plans to reinforce disaster prevention. “The meteorological and seismic monitoring network will be optimized, and is foreseen, in collaboration with the competent services of the interior of China, the construction of a seismic monitoring station,” said the secretary for public works and transport, by presenting, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), the lines of government action (LAG) for the guardianship, for 2025.
Raymond Tam will justified the new station with the intention of "increasing the capacity for analysis and evaluation in the scope of natural disasters." The space has realized in the direction of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), will be located in Hengqin.
"Macao's earthly area is small and population density is very high, so it is difficult to find space for the creation of monitoring stations and now with the favorable policies with Guangdong province, we have been able to build a joint monitoring station in the cooperation zone [deepened between Guangdong and Macau]," SMG director Leong Weng Kun said. The official noted that the space should contribute to "increasing prevention capacity and public knowledge about weather information."
Agree
Macao and Zhuhai signed the “comprehensive and deepening cooperation project in the context of meteorology, to reinforce the cooperation and sharing of meteorological detection equipment, computer programs and data sharing, according to a statement released by SMG at that time.
Cooperation is also expected to reinforce the “joint prevention of weather catastrophs alert systems, promote scientific and technological research and the development of artificial intelligence applied to weather activity”.
Macao is often affected between May and November by the passage of Tuffons, being July to September the period in which the highest incidence of tropical storms is recorded. This year, the territory is expected to be affected by between five to eight tropical storms, SMG announced in March.
Light Metro | Secretary admits operating gaps
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam said on Wednesday that the light meter is still short of the expectations of the population. "I have to confess that the services of the Light Metro, namely the electronic payment services, are still short of the expectations of the population of Macao," he said, promising measures for the means of transport to improve "gradually".
Environment | Policies planning will be studied this year
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam announced on Wednesday that this year will be "Study for the Next Planning of Environmental Protection", to support new "environmental policies based on a scientific and prospective view." Still in the area of ​​the environment, the ruler promised measures to achieve the national objective of the “double carbon goal”. As such, concrete emission reduction shares will be driven, including legislative elaboration for the control of emissions from non -road mobile sources, the slaughter of highly polluting vehicles, the improvement of the electric vehicle charging network, the exploitation of the potential application of photovoltaic energy in public spaces and the optimization of the energy structure ”, concluded the report.
Housing | Government admits to review the whole policy
With the reduction of demand for economic housing, the government admits to review all housing policy. "We are reviewing our policy at this time, taking into account the changes recorded. We will evaluate if there is a need to review the five housing class policy, but it is a subject that is still being studied," said Raymond Tam, secretary for transport and public works in the debate on governance lines for this year. The ruler said that "public housing policies will be reviewed and perfected, promoting the construction of social and economic housing and ensuring rational availability, in order to satisfy the housing needs of residents with different levels of income." Lots of zone A of new landfills should be completed between 2026 and 2028.</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:08:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Blackout | Normality resumed yesterday, it still causes because it</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/apagao-normalidade-retomada-ontem-causa-ainda-por-apurar/</link><description>The week has started atypically on the Iberian Peninsula. It was a few minutes from 11:30 am on Monday, when a widespread electricity failure paralyzed Portugal and Spain. Only near 23h the light returned to the Portuguese house, but the dropper
 
It was an apparent normal Monday, but this normality was dissipated late in the morning with the electricity failure that gradually led to communication failures and impossibility of using mobile data. Portugal and Spain were without electricity for too many hours on Monday, an unprecedented episode in terms of energy failures.
In the case of Lisbon, the light began to fail a few minutes after 11:30 am, followed by the impossibility of communication via mobile data. Traffic in the center of the Portuguese capital became chaotic, without traffic lights in operation, generating some road accidents. Supermarkets, cafes and restaurants, with no possibility of maintaining normal operation and food properly refrigerated, closed doors. Many people, frightened by the possibility of staying several days without light, ran to supermarkets, sagging canned foods, water carboys, candles and batteries.
In addition to the unusual constraints in people's daily lives, with the suddenly closed meter and congested transport, there were suspended flights and closed airports. The restoration of energy took place gradually throughout Monday, starting with the Center of Portugal.
The circulation in the Lisbon Metropolitan (ML) was resumed at all at 08:38, Lisbon time, first in the blue and red lines at 08h, in yellow at 08:15 and green at 08:38.
"The Lisbon Metropolitano had a vast team working yesterday night [Monday] and today's dawn [Tuesday] to ensure the replacement of operating systems affected by the widespread energy failure yesterday," ML said in a statement.
Government words
In a note issued by the Portuguese government in the early hours of yesterday morning, it was said that there were already “virtually all services, including the supply of energy, restored,” Presidential Minister António Leitão Amaro told Lusa.
According to the minister, all 6.4 million customers had access to electricity in the early hours of Tuesday morning, except 800 who had faults not related to the blackout.
Leitão Amaro also said that water supply is working throughout the country, with only a few pressure difficulties in "two or three municipalities" that will be "resolved quickly".
Regarding transportation, the minister said that the "trains are working", and it is still necessary to stabilize some points of the operation, but due to the effects of 24 hours strike that took place on Monday.
About airports, “are operational,” said Leitão Amaro, recognizing that in the case of Lisbon airport, which was the most affected by energy failure and should take two days [to this day] to have stabilized flows, although the systems are all operational.
Normalized Schools and Health
The Portuguese ruler also said that, in relation to schools, the guidance issued at dawn to all directors was to open and function normally, except for cases where there may be some specific security ratio.
"The supply of fuels is normalized and did not record, at night, relevant occurrences of security or civil protection" in the country, advanced Leitão Amaro, stressing that the situation is also stabilized in health services.
"Hospitals and health centers are in terms of supply and supply to function normally," he said. "Right now, what we can say is that [energy] systems are stabilized, both in transportation and consumers supply," said the presidency minister.
In Spain there were also several embarrassment, especially at the level of transport. Pedro Sánchez, Spanish Prime Minister, said on Monday, quoted by Lusa, that this episode was unprecedented in the country. The ruler spoke to the country after the second meeting of Spain National Security Council. "All potential causes are analyzed without discarding any hypothesis," he added.
Gigawatts loss
The Spanish government leader revealed that, according to the technicians and experts of the Spanish power grid, 15 generation gigawatts "suddenly lost the system in just five seconds, something that had never happened."
According to explained, to give a dimension of the event, 15 kilowatts of generation correspond to approximately looking for total electricity in the country at the time of blackout (12:33 in Spain, 11h33 in Lisbon). "What has caused this sudden disappearance of supply" is something that experts cannot yet explain, he added.
In the early hours after the blackout, information began to circulate on a possible cyberathel who never confirmed. A few hours after the blackout, Ursula Von Der Leyen, president of the European Commission, said on the LinkedIn social network that he had spoken with the prime ministers Pedro Sánchez and Luís Montenegro about the monitoring of the case.
“I reaffirmed that the European Commission has supported and monitored the situation with national and European authorities and together with our electricity coordination group. We will gather efforts and share information to help restore the electricity supply system, agreeing to maintain narrow contact,” reads one of the publications.
Eduardo Prieto, head of operations at Spanish Red Electric, told the Associated Press that the situation was not preceded by something “exceptional and extraordinary”. One of the possible causes pointed to the blackout is a rare atmospheric phenomenon, referred to as “induced atmospheric vibration”, which may have originated “anomalous oscillations” in the high voltage lines of the Spanish energy network. "These oscillations have caused synchronization failures between electrical systems, leading to successive disturbances in interconnected European networks," the Portuguese Energy company Ren to BBC told Monday afternoon. But later Ren denied this information.
Many issues
Another causes may have been technical problems in the electric network itself. Onyema NDUKA, a full -sustainability professor of energy sustainability at the University of London, said electric networks are usually interconnected because the production centers that feed them are located far from cities. This means that a power cut in a part of the grid can "lead to a waterfall effect in other areas."
"Ideally, redundancies are incorporated into the system, such as having several supply points, reserve generators located in different locations, wires and interconnected cables, etc.," he said. The solution is through energy companies to restore electricity to affected customers as soon as possible, but the procedure for doing so “has not yet been revealed,” added NDUKA.
The Portuguese authorities, cited by the AP and the local media, have so far attributed the failure of energy to unspecified technical problems, originating outside the country, but mentioned that the investigation is still underway.
The possibility of a cyberatoque is, for now, away. “Spain has mechanisms to deal with this kind of situations. Once again, I appeal to citizens to collaborate with all authorities and act responsibly and civilly, as we have always done,” wrote Pedro Sánchez on social networks. The Portuguese National Cyberrseness Center also stated in a statement that there is no evidence that the failure was caused by a computer attack.
Speaking to Euronews, Taco Engelaar, Neara Director-General, a specialist in energy infrastructure, said the interconnectivity of national networks and their systems would mean that a failure or attack would have the same net result.
"Such a widespread failure of the network is extremely unusual and can be caused by a number of factors: a physical failure on the network that provokes the power cut, a coordinated cybercar or a dramatic imbalance between demand and the supply that has made the network system exceeds the boundaries," he said.
"If it is a system failure, then the interconnectivity between the different regional and national networks can lead to the large amount of power cuts we are watching today [Monday]," he added. "The same applies to a cybership - many of these systems are linked and sharing assets - to overthrow one can overthrow many," he said. With agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 00:32:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature | The interest of linguist Hugo Schuchardt in Patuá de Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/literatura-o-interesse-do-linguista-hugo-schuchardt-no-patua-de-macau/</link><description>Hugo Schuchardt had a genuine interest in Luso-Asian Creole languages, with particular emphasis on Patuá, spoken by the Macanese community. The linguist, who was born in 1842, was the subject of a lecture conducted by researcher Hugo Cardoso, linked to the University of Lisbon
 
Porto, 1883. José Leite de Vasconcelos writes a letter to the German linguist Hugo Schuchardt who had been developing studies, albeit at a distance, about the languages ​​spoken in Asia originated in Portuguese, the so -called Creoles. The letter, written according to the spell agreement of the time, however digitized and today to keep the Archive of the University of Graz, Austria, comes in the context of Schuchardt's own requests to Vasconcelos Milk on the Creole that was then spoken in Macao, known as Patuá.
“My respectable friend: I can only respond to you today. Here in Porto there are no books that say, but I wrote to Lisbon to my friend Vianna and he replied that the Balsmanha does not appear, and that in Macao's story there comes nothing about the dialect port. From Macau. Usual.
I have already asked for information about the Creoles, but I have not yet got anything; This study also interests me about regarding Portuguese. I look forward to the 2 new booklets that promises me. (…) Without anymore I am a friend, J. Vasconcelos Leite, Porto, S. Victor, 25 ”.
Hugo Schuchardt's interest in Luso-Asian Creole has been studied by Hugo Cardoso, a researcher and professor at the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon (FLUL), a Creole specialist who developed investigation at the University of Macao.
The academic recently led a lecture at the National Library in Lisbon over the linguist born in Gotha, Germany, in 1842 and died in Graz, Austria, in 1927, being considered one of the most important linguists of the late nineteenth and early twentieth century. The session was called “Hugo Schuchardt and the search for the Luso-Asian Creole”.
Despite Schuchardt's interest on Macao's Creole, he did not publish any academic work on the subject, as he told HM Hugo Cardoso. "Schuchardt did not publish any work on Macau. However, when he covered his correspondence, it is clear that Macau was also on his radar, since he discusses the Macao Creole with several of his correspondents, including Vasconcelos milk and Gonçalves Viana," he said.
After the German linguist, Hugo Cardoso highlights, “there were actually several people who leaned over Macau Creole, including Danilo Barreiros, José dos Santos Ferreira (Adé), Graciete Batalha, Ana Maria Amaro and, more recently, Prof. Raúl Gaião and Prof. Mário Pinharanda Nunes”. Also noteworthy is the study of Marie Arana-ward "about the Creole spoken by the descendants of Macanese in Hong Kong."
This is another change of correspondence with Vasconcelos milk, dated December 28, 1889, in which books and dictionaries about Portuguese and Chinese are mentioned. “Exmo. Friend: I hurried to respond to your ticket, since you are in a hurry. What I know from China-Portuguese is as follows: J. A. Gonçalves,-Portuguese Dictionary and China-Portuguese. Macau 1831;-China art, Alphabeto and Grammatica. (…) I estimate you to have good shoes. Friend thanks, José Leite de Vasconcellos ”.
The role of rabbit
Hugo Cardoso, whose doctoral thesis is called “The Indo-Portuguese Language of Diu”, former territory of the so-called Portuguese India along with Goa and Damão, spoke at the National Library of Hugo Schuchardt's Studies around this Creole and also the language of Batávia/Tugu in Indonesia.
For the professor at FLUL, pioneering in the study of the Creoles is an expression that rhymes with Schuchardt. The German linguist was "absolutely pioneering in this domain, not only in the study of the Luso-Sasitive Creole or even the Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles globally, but in the study of Creole languages ​​in general" and, for this reason, is "a larger figure in the history of linguistics."
Hugo Cardoso also points out that "as regards the Portuguese lexical base creoles, before him, there had been some activity, especially by Adolfo Coelho, who, in 1881, had published" Romanesque or Neo-Latin dialects in Africa, Asia and America, "in which he was a caught in various Portuguese-based Creole." However, in this work, Adolfo Coelho refers only to three Luso-Asiatic Creole: “Ceylon's (at Sri Lanka), Malaca and Macau's-giving some examples that he could get from previous publications (such as Macau's Ta-Ss-Yang-Kuo magazine)”.
The academic has no doubt that “Hugo Schuchardt was surely inspired by Rabbit's work, but his efforts to obtain primary data from many other Asian places greatly expanded cartography of the Luso-sinical Creole and resulted in the first published news and the first grammatical descriptions of many of them (such as Diu, Cananor, Mahé, Mangar, Mangar, Mangar etc.) ”.
Future inspirations
According to Hugo Cardoso, the German linguist left works that inspired future academics and many materials from the personal archive. "One effect of his work was to inspire other agents to develop similar work: there stands out the figure of Sebastião Rodolfo Dalgado, who led his own research and made his own publications about the Indo-Portuguese Creoles that Schuchardt had not approached, about Damão, Bombaim, Ceylon and Negapath."
In the case of José de Leite Vasconcelos, who wrote the letter cited at the beginning of this text, "it also corresponded with Schuchardt and reveals, in his linguistic studies, the impact of Schuchardt's work."
Asked by HM about the possible interconnections between the Creole of IUD, Batávia and Macao, Hugo Cardoso states that there are "continuities between the various Luso-Asian Creole, but also many differences." "The Batávia/Tugu Creole is the one that most resembles Creole de Macao, for example, at the Lexicon level. But this is understandable because it has already shown that Macao Creole has an important historical connection with the Creole that developed in Southeast Asia, in particular Malaca."
According to an academic article by Hugo Cardoso himself written in partnership with Tjerk Hagemeijer and Nélia Alexandre, entitled “Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles”, these “were, in most cases, oral languages ​​to the nineteenth century, when the first collections of oral traditions, texts and translations began to emerge, being linked“ to maritime expansion in Africa and Asia, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact between the contact. Portuguese and different African and Asian languages ​​”.
Also according to the same article, "some of these Crioulos, namely in Asia, were extinguished, having only recorded from the transition from the nineteenth century to the twentieth century. With the exception of the Creole of Alta Guinea, the vitality of the living Portuguese Creole is generally decreasing."
In the case of Creoles of Portuguese origin in the southern Asia area, they emerged from the arrival of Vasco da Gama to Calecute, India, in 1498, especially from the phase in which the entire base of the Portuguese empire the East focuses on Goa. According to the same academic article, several Creole were developed, the so-called “Indo-Portuguese” in coastal areas of India, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Burma. "Currently, its presence is much reduced: they survive those of IUD, Damão, Korlai, Cananor and Sri Lanka (Ceylon) - which, despite having, has once been used all over the island, is currently restricted to the cities of Batticaloa and Trinchomalee," is highlighted in the article. The author draws attention to the extinction in 2010 of the Vaipim Creole, in Cochim, due to the "death of what seems to have been the last fluent speaker in this region." There are then the Southeast Asia and East Asia Creole, which includes Macao. Patuá is currently “spoken with native fluency only by some people in Macau and the Macanese diaspora”, is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:19:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Electricity cut affects Portugal, Spain and parts of southern France</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/29/corte-de-electricidade-afecta-portugal-espanha-e-partes-do-sul-de-franca/</link><description>A flaw of electricity affected, at 11:33 (18h33 in Macao), Portugal, Spain and some areas of southern France.
In the first moments, information and speculation about the cause of the blackout were disseminated, namely in relation to a possible large-scale cyberataque, a hypothesis that was not excluded in the first instance by the General Secretariat of Internal Administration.
Until the closing of this issue, the cause was not yet clear, nor was there an estimate for the return of electricity, but Prime Minister Luís Montenegro said he had hope that the light supply would be resumed yesterday, according to Lisbon time (7 less for Macau). However, there were news in Portuguese media that pointed to the return of electricity in various parts of the country, as well as in Spain.
The Expresso newspaper cited data collected by the operators of the electricity network in the Iberian peninsula that pointed to tension imbalances as an explanation for the "blackout" rather than a cyberatheck designed to affect energy infrastructures. Until the closing of this edition, the Portuguese government did not rule out any explanation for the incident.
The e-nodes warned that the forecast of electricity replacement remained indefinite and could be prolonged, without advance an estimate. "Given the problems of the network that persist the forecast of energy replacement remains undefined and may be prolonged," said the operator of the electricity distribution network in mainland Portugal, in a statement.
E-Redes reiterated that the supply of electricity in Portugal was being affected by upstream constraints of the distribution network, in the very high voltage network in Spain.
According to REN - national power grid, yesterday's blackout may have been caused by abnormal temperature fluctuations in Spain. The news was advanced by the BBC, which mentions an atmospheric phenomenon.
Pandemonium scenario
The incident caused chaos in the country. At airports, check-ins became manuals and began to be announced on flights at first, but were eventually canceled. TAP has issued a statement to appeal to passengers so as not to go to airports, as operation is temporarily conditioned due to blackout.
Rail traffic was also totally interrupted throughout the Iberian Peninsula. In hospitals, emergency generators and emergency services and surgeries have been prioritized to respond to urgent cases.
In addition to the Emergency Meeting of the Council of Ministers, the National Operational Coordination Center, which is part of the entities in the context of protection and relief operations, gathered to follow the situation and adopt the necessary procedures due to the lack of energy in mainland Portugal.
The telephone and computer systems of the National Institute of Emergency Medical was operating until the closing of this edition using generators and the fuel supply posts interrupted the services.
On the other hand, the Águas de Portugal (ADP) group appealed to water consumption only for essential uses, “very moderate”, and said there were only “punctual failures”. Heard by Lusa regarding the widespread cutting of electricity and a possible water failure, the company's official source warned that there may be consumer constraints, although without advanced more concrete data.
ADP, which brings together more than a dozen water suppliers on the continent, "appeals to the use of water for the essentials only." "ADP is following the situation in all companies," the source said. The company, he added, intends to ensure that essential services have water and recalled that reservoirs have water but it takes energy to transport it, and that even the buildings themselves need energy to get water to consumers taps.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>LAG 2025 | Facilitated automatic passage from foreign visitors</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/28/lag-2025-facilitada-passagem-automatica-de-visitantes-estrangeiros/</link><description>In the presentation of this year's security lines for security, Wong Sio Chak referred to the idea of ​​facilitating the entry into Macau to foreign visitors, with the creation of more automatic passage points
 
The Secretary for Security announced, on Friday, plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors through the use of automatic electronic channels.
During the presentation of the Governing Action Lines Report (LAG) to 2025 in the area of ​​security, Wong Sio Chak stated that the territory will extend the use of automatic passage points to foreign citizens without resident or work authorization.
To facilitate “exterior exchanges”, authorities will expand autoservice equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, the leader explained.
To the deputies at the Legislative Assembly, the secretary added that the government will continue to optimize iris recognition technology in border controls and to study its extension to non-residents this year.
"We are also studying ways to widen the number of users eligible for automatic passage channels, allowing more foreign tourists to benefit from faster immigration processes and more fluid circulation in the large bay," Wong said.
Speech and company
In his speech, the secretary stated that "regarding the creation of a higher level of opening abroad, the input and output services will continue to be optimized and the facilitation measures of the border passage, to ensure a safe, effective, efficient and comfortable passage."
Thus, "with a view to promoting the exchange with the outside, the automatic passage channels will also have foreigners, so that they deal with the input and exit inspection formalities through these channels."
According to official data, Macau received, in 2024, 34.9 million visitors, 23.8 percent than the previous year, but only 2.42 million were international tourists. In October last year, the Chinese Foreign Ministry extended the Portuguese visa exemption policy, thus inserting Portugal into a list that already covered another 16 European countries.
The measure, which allows the Portuguese to stay in China for tourism, business or traffic for a maximum of 15 days, in force at least until December 31, 2025.
In the same month, Continental China had announced the expansion, from 90 to 180 days, from the permanence period for foreign residents of Macao on multiple entries in the country.
The measure includes permanent and non-permanent foreign residents of Macao that move “to the interior of China for short-term tourism, trade, visit to family members, visits and other activities”.
From July, the Chinese National Immigration Administration (NIA) had already allowed foreign permanent residents from Macao and Hong Kong to request authorization to enter the interior of China, valid for a maximum of five years. The measure covers members of the Portuguese community who are permanent residents in Macao and, until then, were required to ask for a visa to travel to the other side of the border.</description><pubDate>2025-04-28 00:26:03</pubDate></item><item><title>April 25 | The Revolution of Cloves seen by the Chinese press</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/25/25-de-abril-a-revolucao-dos-cravos-vista-pela-imprensa-chinesa/</link><description>The fall of the Estado Novo on April 25, 1974 was reported by the Chinese language press in Macao. Community concerns were revealed, namely about the permanence of the Noble Governor of Carvalho for stability and good business environment, as well as the “status quo” of Macau in the context of decolonization
 
The echoes of the April 25, 1974 revolution were late in Macao, but this did not mean absence of news in the following days, including the local Chinese press.
HM consulted some of the news of the Chinese newspapers of the time over this period, translated to Portuguese by employees of the Press Censorship Commission (CCI), the public body that worked in Macao during the Portuguese dictatorial regime. This material is today to keep the Historical-Diplomatic Archive of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Lisbon.
Its reading allows not only to realize some of the events that succeeded the revolution, but also the perceptions and concerns that the Chinese community had on what happened in Portugal.
The Chinese wanted to maintain the stability and continuation of business. And if the Noble Governor of Carvalho, in power since 1966, was, for many, connoted with the fascist regime, and therefore had to leave, the truth is that many wanted their permanence to ensure social peace.
As read in the book “Macao in the years of the 1974-1979 Portuguese Revolution”, by Garcia Leandro, former Portuguese governor, “Macao's Chinese sought, above all, stability to be able to continue quietly to their business, and did not want conflicts or misunderstandings with Beijing or Canton”.
Administration was “weak, very badly supported technically and to be easily corrupted”, so there were “strong reasons for the local MFA [Movement of the Forces] and the CDM [Macao Democratic Center] want to change, especially for the permanent corruption and the sense of excessive weakness of the Portuguese administration, which seemed nothing to decide without preview of Chinese representatives”.
MFA explanations
Shortly after April 25, Macau was visited by two MFA representatives, namely Major Rebelo Gonçalves and Garcia Leandro himself, to explain the revolution and objectives of MFA to Portugal and the colonies, not just to the population but to journalists.
One of the meetings, with local journalists, was described by the Tai Chung newspaper on May 6, 1974. "Rebelo Gonçalves received the reporters and narrated them in detail the coup d'état. On the day (of the event), the song" Who sends the people "served as a sign of action." The CCI translator attributed to the song “Grandola, Vila Morena”, by José Afonso, chosen to be the second password of the revolution on the radio, the name “Who Mandates is the people”, in reference to the verse of the letter “The people are the one who orders the most”. The news continued, quoting Rebelo Gonçalves: he said "that the coup d'état was the desire of the people, so it achieved success in the period of one day."
Support to Nobre de Carvalho
Fallen the regime in Lisbon, and exiled Marcelo Caetano, the issue of the Governor's permanence at the head of the destinations of Macao was quickly asked. However, Nobre de Carvalho received popular support to continue, as described from the news of the newspaper SI Man, October 4, 1974.
"Portugal does not intend to modify Macau's status quo, a Portuguese delegate told Chinese traders. This delegate manifests himself pleased with the governor's re-competition campaign, promoted by several social sectors. However, Mr. General Nobre de Carvalho had already requested the dismissal of the position of governor for health reasons."
In addition, a group was created “for the collection of signatures in favor of the renewal of Mr. General Nobre de Carvalho in the position of Governor of Macao”, which were handed over to Garcia Leandro, still as MFA official. This one received "two boxes containing signatures-cadenic books." "Opinions of entities of industrial and commercial circles were transmitted, hoping that the governor can remain in Macao, which given his wide experiences and knowledge of conditionalisms, can overcome the difficulties resulting from the economic decline that now happens around the world."
But if the desire for many was the continuity of Nobre Carvalho, the departure of many civil servants began to be connoted with the change of regime. As referred to in the news of the Jornal Si Man, May 11, 1974. “The head of health and assistance services, Dr. António Joaquim Paulino, will return on the 27th of this month to mainland Portugal, which is reported to fall from Marcelo Caetano's government. The competent authorities refused to comment on the departure of Dr. Paulino.”
The newspaper also added: "However, news from Fidente Fonte reported: It is believed that the unappropriate return to Lisbon of Dr. Paulino, whose service commission in this province has not yet ended, is related to the coup (continental).
Still in early May, there were still many questions unanswered, and the newspaper SI Man associated the departure of Vasco Rocha Vieira from the territory, at the time of the military command of the Military Command, with the absence of explanations for the political situation. “A fortnight has passed a fortnight after the coup d'état in Portugal has been fully clarified that the political situation of that country was fully clarified. Although Macau is little affected by the event, the chief of staff of Portuguese troops parked in Macao, Major Rocha Vieira yesterday, which led many people to conjecture and suspect the junta of national salvation. Portuguese government had already started acting in Macau. ”
Ho Yin's explanations
Tai Chung Pou newspaper reported, on May 22, 1974, that "some Portuguese declared in Hong Kong that they were unhappy with the measures taken by the governor and the government of Macao", followed "for the metropolis to ask for the granting of freedom to the Portuguese of Macao."
Ho Yin, a striking entrepreneur and figure of the local Chinese community, who dialogue directly with the governor representing the Chinese authorities, explained in a session with “foreign reporters, as well as those of Hong Kong and Macau” about April events. These “visited Mr. Ho Yin, asking him for opinion,” describes Tai Chung Pou.
And once again, Ho Yin appealed his spirits, noting that Nobre Carvalho had all the legitimacy to continue as governor. "Since the Portuguese coup d'état, registered on April 25, Macau, given its special circumstances, has been felt, to date, very quiet, not undergoing any change. Mr. Governor, General Nobre de Carvalho, who has been in Macao for over seven years, has deep knowledge of the conditions of this city, having resolved many matters through conversations and wrowning great efforts to this city," Ho Yin told the journalists, according to the journalists, according to the journalists. newspaper report.
At the same meeting, the possibility of dissolution of the Legislative Assembly, proposal of the CDM, was questioned. But Ho Yin pushed any sudden political change.
“It is known that the Macao Democratic Center, consisting of some Portuguese, requested the dissolution of the Legislative Assembly and the Municipal Council [Leal Senate], as well as the remodeling of some public services. Some inhabitants thought that the assertions of that center would affect the social order, but they came to know that they were only the opinion of a small number of Portuguese, when the city is still the city quiet, after a few days. ”
The newspaper adds that Nobre de Carvalho publicly explained "that Al would not be dissolved, so the population of Macao became carefree and entrusted in the prosperity of this city." In addition, “tourists from Hong Kong, as well as abroad, also think Macao is quiet and is not affected at all,” read in Tai Chung Pou.
The Seng Pou newspaper also reported this meeting between Ho Yin and journalists, in which the Chinese community leader commented on the benefits of a democratic regime.
"Given their peculiar circumstances and due to the fact that the Portuguese and Chinese respected themselves and live in peace for a long time, Macau has not suffered any repercussions resulting from that Portuguese coup," Ho Yin said, stressing that "as for the freedom of the word, it has always existed in Macau."
However, the entrepreneur appealed to some containment in the political criticism made. "Democracy and freedom that are now verified in mainland Portugal are happiness to the Portuguese people. And the Portuguese and Chinese have lived in the past in peace, and it is expected to continue to succeed in the future. In the then, criticism of private people or public offices must be founded, since any thoughtless attack would make complications to the question, and affect its tranquility and prosperity."
Macau without decolonization
One of the questions emanating from April 25, 1974 was the most urgent process of decolonization in the so -called Portuguese Africa where the colonial war was due since 1961. First of all, the authorities clarified that Macau would be left out of this process, because “the Popular Republic of China was careful that in 1972, in the UN decolonization committee, to make it very clear that the future of these two European possessions [Macao and Hong and Hong Kong] would not be part of the agenda of the activities of that body, being the subject treated bilaterally, ”reads in the book of Garcia Leandro.
In the September 11, 1974 edition, the Tai Chung Pou newspaper wrote that “the head of the Macao Government Office, Lieutenant Colonel Henrique Manuel Lages Ribeiro, pointed out that news emanating from the news agency Reuters had been misunderstood, and that Macau has a peculiar position”, because “the way to solve his future is different from other Portuguese overseas territories.”
The words of Almeida Santos are cited, the Portuguese Minister of Interterritorial Coordination, who said “that it would be allowed to all Portuguese overseas territories to choose the form of independence as a means to solve their own problem, with the exception of Macao that, being a very special territory, requires a special way to solve your problem”. In the translation of this news, there is also a note written by the editor itself: "This means that there is no problem of independence in Macau."
The visits by Rebelo Gonçalves and Garcia Leandro Macau took place in “Finals of May, early June 1974. Almeida Santos was in Macao in September of this year and it was at this stage that Garcia Leandro was chosen governor of Macao, taking office on 13 November of this year.</description><pubDate>2025-04-25 00:18:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Elderly | Recognizes difficulties in social companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/idosos-ias-reconhece-dificuldades-de-empresas-sociais/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action (IAS) recognizes that the new trade environment has negatively affected the only two social companies that have among its functions to hire elderly workers. The current scenario was outlined in response to an interpetement of Deputy Lei Chan U, linked to the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations (Faom).
"Currently, the two social companies for the elderly who came into operation are from the area of ​​restoration, providing 16 full -time and six part -time vacancies for the elderly," he was explained. "The two projects of social company went into operation during the pandemic period. Due to the impact of the pandemic and market environment, the daily operation and development of social companies were relatively affected. After the pandemic, society and the economy of Macao gradually recovered, however, in the face of the constant change of the business environment of Macau, the operation of companies, including the elderly companies, faced many challenges and pressures."
Despite various strategies to relaunch the business, such as promotions or extending opening hours, IAS President Hon Wai admits that the situation has known few improvements. However, IAS indicates that the future deceiving plan of action for support services to the elderly, which is expected to take effect next year, should have more measures to encourage the hiring of the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:39:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Local Accommodation | Lo Choi in recognizes challenges, but asks study</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/alojamento-local-lo-choi-in-reconhece-desafios-mas-pede-estudo/</link><description>The deputy linked to the community of Jiangmen points out that, despite the ban on local accommodation in Macau, there are ads everywhere and that a simple search on the internet has offers for almost all tastes
 
Lo Choi in wants to know if the new government has plans to study the viability of local accommodation in Macao. The issue is part of an interpellation written by the deputy linked to the Jiangmen community, released on the Legislative Assembly portal.
According to Lo Choi In, illegal pensions are currently found in a mixed regime, in which although they are prohibited, they have not been criminalized, which has made them present in Macao. In addition, it indicates, the increase in the number of a new type of tourists in the interior of China has also contributed to the search for these spaces to continue to grow.
In this context, where the deputy asks if it would not be better to study the legal viability of local accommodation, since it becomes increasingly impossible to combat the phenomenon. "The law of the prohibition of illegal accommodation of accommodation did not criminalize the offer of local accommodation in Macao. The legislative intention went to leave margin so that in the future it could advance to legalization," said the deputy, who voted in favor of the proposal. "However, the law imposes an administrative sanction for the offer of local accommodation of 800 thousand patacas, which also reflects the concern of the community with illegal accommodation," he acknowledged. "Does competent services can take the initiative to join some academic institutions, community interest groups and study the viability of local accommodation to examine and explore the advantages and disadvantages to Macao?"
Ahead of all
Lo Choi also considers that despite the problems of illegal accommodation this is an increasingly present reality
The deputy mentions that in recent times her cabinet has increasingly received complaints from residents, because in the buildings where they live, especially in the high times of tourism, it is increasingly frequent to see tourists from the interior of China to enter and get out of travel luggage. There were also complaints about tourists who address residents to ask where local accommodation is, without being aware that it is an illegal practice.
In addition to the increase in the number of complaints received, LO indicates that online search on general search engines or accommodation offer show several illegal housing available in Macao.
Given this growth, and given the illegalization, the deputy asks the government to intensify efforts to combat the phenomenon and to make a campaign for tourists to realize the risks they take, in case of accidents, for being these accommodation.
Lo Choi In also asks the government to make the mechanisms more effective for denouncing illegal housing, especially through online media, which it considers to be the most effective.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:29:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Light Metro | Leong Sun Iok wants to accelerate bar connection plan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/metro-ligeiro-leong-sun-iok-quer-acelerar-plano-de-ligacao-a-barra/</link><description>Deputy Leong Sun IOK defended the need to connect the light meter between the bar and the east line to be completed as soon as possible. This is how the legislator reacted to the congestion of public transport and traffic during the days of the golden week.
Speaking cited by Jornal do Cidadão, the deputy considered that this connection has enormous potential to divert tourists from the siege gates and intend to go to Cotai, or tourists who are in the Cotai and intend to travel to the center of the peninsula.
The East Line will make the connection between the siege doors and the mud, through zone A of the new landfills. However, this line is still under construction and should not be operational before 2028.
At the same time, Leong Sun Iok stated that bar connecting works can be accelerated because the construction sector is currently going through difficulties, which means that there are resources available to advance with the work. From the perspective of the deputy linked to the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations, this is still a way to promote the use of local residents.
In statements to the Chinese language publication, Leong Sun Iok also praised the stance of the new secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam, considering that he showed openness to change various aspects of the light meter and have shown understanding of current problems, which must be corrected, such as the limits on electronic payments or recurring service failures.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:25:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Banking / SME | Prudence with credit due to economic climate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/banca-pme-prudencia-com-credito-devido-a-clima-economico/</link><description>The bank sector squeezed the credit assignment criteria to small and medium enterprises in the new interest bonus plan launched two weeks ago by the government. Andy Wu asks entrepreneurs to make a rigorous assessment of the risks of resorting to loans, at a time when the badoral credit continues at high levels
 
Yesterday two weeks ago the government launched another Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (SME), which will take place until April 22, 2026. After other similar plans, companies and sector representatives indicate that bank criteria for loan approval became more demanding compared to the plans applied during the pandemic period.
The current plan foresees five million Patacas as a maximum amount of credits to be granted to each commercial entrepreneur, with a maximum three -year bonus period and the maximum limit of the annual bonus rate of 4 percent.
A businessman, who did not want to identify to the newspaper or Mun, said he analyzed the criteria and details of the plan, being interested in relieving the liquidity pressure of the company. However, the entrepreneur noted that the requirements are more rigorous than those related to similar loans in 2021 and 2022. Although he thinks that he meets the approval criteria, the entrepreneur indicated to the world not being sure if he will be able to borrow.
Also in anonymity condition, a bank sector professional indicated to the newspaper or Mun that banking institutions only took plans 2021 and 2022 as a reference, but that financial and economic environments have changed since then, forcing banks to change risk assessment criteria.
As we arrived here
Despite greater or less focus on social responsibility aspects, or fiduciary duties before shareholders, the professional heard by the newspaper or Mun considers that, in general, Macao banks assume a partnership position with the SMEs as part of their operative mission.
As such, the source indicates that if companies have a registration without bad credit, credit requests will be accepted.
At the same newspaper, the president of the Federal General Commercial Association of Small and Medium Enterprises of Macau, Andy Wu, suggested to the government, banking and trade and business associations that reinforce the dissemination of the criteria, formalities and deadlines of the interest bonus plan. The official said he understood the prudence of the bank and indicated to expect the entrepreneurs to be considered in the credit request, the assessment of risks and the operative capacity.
The Malparado credit hit last February the highest value since 1990, the year the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM) began compiling this data. The latest AMCM data released last week for March and the first quarter of 2025 reveal that despite having down 2.7 percent, the debt to Macao banks was about 56.1 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:22:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Taxis | Requested more offer for those who have difficulties</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/taxis-pedida-mais-oferta-para-quem-tem-dificuldades/</link><description>Wong Kit Cheng advocates the need to have a higher offer of taxis prepared to transport people with motor difficulties, according to a recent interpellation of the deputy linked to the Association of Women. In the document, Wong indicates that only one percent of the total available taxis can transport people with special needs.
By comparison, Wong indicated that in Hong Kong there is a proportion of 25.9 percent taxis capable of carrying people with special needs. However, even in the Hong Kong scenario, Wong indicated that the government has set a goal to increase this proportion.
Still in relation to transport, the local deputy criticized the taxi service called by telephone. According to the legislator, the large majority of people trying to call a taxi is not met or sees the service refused for lack of vehicles. The deputy appealed to the government to correct this aspect, in the future public tender.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:12:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Worker Day | Detained in the first protest in six years</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/dia-do-trabalhador-detido-em-primeiro-protesto-em-seis-anos/</link><description>Police detained on the day of the worker a man protesting the number of migrant workers in Macao, invoking violation of the Law of Meeting and Manifestation Law. Also the Power of the People's Association canceled a demonstration, after the authorities suggested not wanting to debut the application of the law on the security of the state
 
On May 1, Labor Day, a man was arrested by agents of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) when manifested against the importation of non-resident workers.
CPSP source told Lusa that man showed 'slogans' (slogans) and chanting chants to demand the reduction of migrant workers at the door of the management services for the first public protest on May 1, 2019, before the COVID-19 pandemic.
A video that circulates on social networks shows the man to put eight sheets of paper on the floor with the message “Government, cut on migrant workers! next to the flags of Macao and China.
The Mishes was employed at the end of March nearly 183,400,000 migrant workers, still far from the maximum peak of 196,538, hit in late 2019 at the beginning of the pandemic. According to the CPSP, the agents made repeated warnings for violations of the Law of Meeting and Manifestation Law, but the man refused to obey and was taken to the squad to be identified.
During the pandemic, security forces refused to approve the course of any protest, invoking reasons for “order and safety” or public health. Authorities raised anti-standard restrictions at the end of 2023, but the protests did not return to the city streets.
These prohibitions arrived at the UN Human Rights Committee, which in 2022 evaluated "an increasing number of information of improper restrictions on the exercise of freedom of peaceful manifestations."
It would be a pity
The Power of the People's Association, which also requires a reduction in the number of migrant workers, canceled a manifestation planned for Labor Day due to “police pressure,” the All About Macau newspaper reported on Thursday.
The association said it expected 20,000 participants, but canceled the event after police claimed that it could violate the National Security Act.
Group President Lam Weng Ioi said he filed a formal statement of demonstration in April, but was summoned to repeated police meetings to "analyze the situation" and "avoid uncontrollable circumstances." Lam claimed that the authorities raised questions about the “joint responsibility of the organizers” and the warning of “National Security”, which led the group to present a written appeal.
Speaking to the Macao TDM channel, the associative leader said that the authorities advanced various possibilities such as the intervention of “people with bad intentions” that could take advantage of the activities to create confusion, or from participants who could compromise public order, and that the association would be responsible for any disorder or irregularity. "We said we were going to have a special team to maintain order. However, police officers doubted our ability to control local order," Lam Weng Ioi told public television.
The authorities also suggested that the manifestation of Labor Day could infringe national security laws. "It was mentioned, indirectly, (the violation of) law on the defense of state security. I was told that there was no detention, previously, based on this law and that they did not want us to be the first case of law on the defense of state security," said the president of the Power of the People Association.
The PSP confirmed that it had received a statement notification for May 1, but said the organizer removed it voluntarily.
Au Kam San disagree
Following the case of the individual detained for protesting the importation of non-resident workers to Macao, at the gates of the management of services for labor affairs, on the day of the worker, former deputy Au Kam San argued that the act concerned was not a demonstration. As such, the action of public security police officers was not correct.
In a Facebook publication, the former deputy disagreed with the police argument that the subject had not prior notice to the demonstration because he is only an individual and a small-scale protest and that the concept of manifestation depends on the number of people involved. Even so, it pointed out that there is no necessary authorization for notice of demonstration, a fundamental right provided for in the basic law of masters.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:11:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Customs | Two rescue boats went into operation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/alfandega-dois-barcos-de-salvamento-entraram-em-funcionamento/</link><description>On Wednesday, Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, accompanied by the Commander General of Unit Police Services, Leong Man Cheong, and the Director General of Customs Services (SA), Adriano Marques Ho, performed the traditional blessing ceremony of two new rescue vessels.
The vessels feature a Wave-Piercing Catamaran hull, with a soldier aluminum structure, measuring 32 meters long and 10 meters wide, with a maximum displacement of 173 tons, a maximum speed of 30 knots and a maximum silence of 1.55 meters.
In terms of rescue capacity, the vessels are equipped with four water cannons (two main 115 meters range and two seconds with 75 meters) and four fire pumps, totaling a combined flow of 2,200 cubic meters per hour. Boats “can carry 60 people rescued in their designated compartment, while the stern is equipped with four self-derived savior ferries with a full capacity for 200 people,” the SAs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:37:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence on Sex in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/a-inteligencia-artificial-sobre-o-sexo-em-macau/</link><description>I had the experience of asking the most popular artificial intelligence platform that themes about sex, sexuality and gender would make sense to discuss in Macau. The answer brought three proposals that, although not very surprising, I found it interesting. Of course the platform used some creative and intellectual freedom - which I didn't ask for - to invent sources, quotes and points of view. Basically, he went to seek what is already known about Taiwan and Hong Kong, about the growing opening to LGBTQI+themes, and tried to make parallels with Macao. He mentioned the rainbow of Macau/澳門彩虹/Rainbow of Macau as the most active association in defending LGBTQI+ rights in the territory, and even invented interviews with its founder, with fictional quotes.
The first proposal that artificial intelligence suggested is about Macao young people and their opening to non-binary and plural gender identities as a way of navigating western and oriental cultural identities, and monitoring generational changes. Worldwide we have seen an emancipation movement in this area, with many young people to discuss these issues openly. If in some countries institutions and policies follow these changes (and in others until retreat), in Macao the pit may be higher, taking into account its geographical situation. I went looking for studies that deepened the subject and found one who asked young people from Macau between 18 and 25 years old. The authors have analyzed how adherence to polyculturalism, the idea that crops are interconnected and influence each other, associated with lower levels of sexual prejudice, including negative attitudes towards LGBTQ+people. The study suggests that the cultural diversity of Macao, and the belief that cultures mingle, can create a predisposition to also accept sexual diversity. But I would say that it is still necessary to explore more about these issues, listening to real testimonies about the experiences of young people living in Macao.
The second proposal - which I have mentioned here without account - has to do with the lack of accessible, inclusive and focused sex education, promoting more knowledge and pleasure in Macao and worldwide. If a few months ago I gave the example of Hong Kong, where it was suggested to play Badminton as a way to manage sexual abstinence, I would say that Macau is not much more open to talking about sex than that. This lack of discussion creates a series of complications that, due to the absence of data in the region, do not even know the true dimension of the problem. The absence of comprehensive and inclusive sex education increases the risk of sexual violence, discrimination and propagation of sexually transmitted infections.
The third proposal surprised me, because it is a theme in which I rarely think: the growth of LGBTQia+ tourism in Asia and the opportunity that Macau has to bet on this niche. Since the hotel industry is the pillar of the economy of Macao, it would make sense to embrace this opportunity, as they have already made Thailand and Taiwan, creating LGBTQIA+spaces, or with specific events, such as Pride Month celebrations. According to some data produced online, this type of tourism is profitable and growing.
Artificial intelligence even has interesting ideas, although something generic. But I confess that I was pleased to realize that the algorithm is in tune to defend the rights of sexual minorities and has an inclusive discourse. It becomes dangerous, however, when it begins to invent data and information just so that the argument sounds good. Still, in general, it can be a useful tool for discussing these issues without judgment. As the platform itself says, it has the potential to “combat myths, spread ethical concepts and include perspectives of marginalized groups, democratizing access to more complete and positive sex education.” In this suggestion of content creation, it seemed aligned with these values.
If you will ever replace the work of people like me, who write on these topics, or the work of sexual educators… maybe it's too early to draw conclusions. Sensitive and thinking people still have a lot to contribute.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:14:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Saint Valentine's Day in the Czech Republic</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/dia-de-sao-valentim-na-republica-checa/</link><description>Em Macau, muitas pessoas sabem que o 1.º de Maio é o Dia do Trabalhador e é um feriado oficial. O mesmo se passa na China continental, marcando o 1.º de Maio o início de um longo feriado. However, few know that in the Republic checked May 1st is the "Day of St. Valentine".
On Valentine's Day, Czech lovers follow tradition and kiss under the cherry trees, singing songs to love. And the kiss why?
According to Czech folklore, if a girl is not kissed under a cherry tree on St. Valentine's day, she will "wither" next year, losing "youth and charm." Therefore, a kiss means "protection and blessings."
And what is “protection in love”? In mid -2015, Sean Lau, the winner of the Hong Kong's best actor's best actor award for his work in the movie “Overheard 3”, presented the “Space Nave Theory”. He used a simple phrase to show how his wife Amy Kwok protected him:
“When I enter a spaceship and travel anywhere in the universe, you always find a way to bring me back to Earth safely.”
The meaning of this phrase is simple and clear. If you are where you are, face what to face, you always bring me back safely. You are always by my side, making me be loved, hot, happy and in peace.
Apart from the “spacecraft theory”, there is another sean Lau phrase that is part of the “passionate quotes for my wife”:
"One day you no longer want to love love, you just want someone who doesn't leave you."
Does true love require two people to stay together? In March 2025, news was released in Taiwan, China, saying that a woman had published an online article, where she said she had a boyfriend six years ago, but eventually found out that he was getting married to another. And this happened because her boyfriend loved her so much and didn't want her to go through the suffering caused by her relationship with her mother-in-law, so she decided to marry a woman from whom her parents liked, but he didn't like and assured his girlfriend that his "relationship" would not be affected. After marrying another woman, she would date forever with her beloved.
Love implies "protection and blessings." Is it in favor of the “spacecraft theory” or “Nora/mother -in -law theory”?
What are "blessings"? In Taiwan, China, the host of the television program “Yu Meiren”, (Yu Yunjie) had no contact with her in -laws for a long time. Once went to court due to a disagreement between mother and husband. Finally, the judge stated that his 16 -year marriage had come to an end. Later, Yu Meiren has lost a lot of weight, but now it is more beautiful than before and at his disposal has changed. She stated:
"The French believe that in love we should accept those who come and we should not retain those who want to leave. 'When love happens, we must be ourselves, follow our hearts and act without schemes. When love is over, we must respect the other and not try to arrest or force it, which means that" letting out is the best of blessings. "
Do you agree with the phrase “letting go is the best of blessings, the blessing is the best relief”? Hong Kong Cine Cine Cine Cenilia Cheung once expressed some disappointment after the divorce:
"In love there is only one thing that can hurt us, it is the unwillingness. When we cannot live with ourselves, we inflicted pain."
Perhaps that “protection and blessings” have different meanings for each person, but for me,
"I have to say this only once. After all these years, I still love you."
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:37:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade with the enemy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/comercio-com-o-inimigo/</link><description>- This is the title of a tale of José Rodrigues Miguéis to which we owe the language we speak, but beware, not contemplated among the prerogatives of the jungle of current writing too ufan in the telling of their stories that interest us nothing. The clerks think they are phenomenal things since they feel a lot, they gesture a lot, and they just do not cry since the gift of tears has been subtracted to them, and it is because of these things laughingly empowered that the beautiful oblates, small poems, break like an escape plan when we want to dissociate us from these dry, mental and embarrassed pains. These people no longer cry, have psychological problems, imaginary dramas, and a long and torrential boring with the emplumated egos. But what about this trade with the enemy in the time of taxation?
- José Rodrigues Miguéis was the son of Galician, and we know of the labor expression that is associated with this territory, even today in Portuguese there is that old saying: - work like a Galician! - Now, in this old time, the Portuguese also worked a lot, but due to faint practices seemed to be stopped. This tale begins at Solar dos Machados with an almost chimerical literary group in no less chimeric travel literature where we seem to meet Garrett on the other side of the stained glass window, where they still thought they were still atactic. He describes with unrivaled social dimension the abrasion of farmers and decaying noblewoman in the abundantly rich landscapes where everyone did not pass a nursery of poor.
"If we think we are being sanctioned, let us forget:" The great wealth of once_ who paid the garrust cloaks, this one disappeared, ravaged from the markets. Everything now is a picturesque façade for tourists, and nostalgia of better times… that no one already remembers having known ». Neither taxed nor sanctioned, which we are in the Machados Solar waiting for any gold that will always come, that our productivity is bad and the Galician helps us interpret the disabling reality, and that Trump also does not flour in Iberian windmills.
"We do not actually know which cracks were born so many fascism, but it doesn't matter now." They were born here where they had already inhabited, and a reverse of untimely precepts were enough to bring them again very 'Hugo Boss' to the ridiculous atavios and a great absence of hope. What awaits them in the new dilettantism is anything we should observe as a sociological practice, and never forget to kiss the cadaverous hand of a Castro Inês. Of course, Miguéis did not stay here, a short circuit with the Estado Novo took it exactly to the United States, and very interesting is now to think that some singular premonition threw him right now to a domain that bureaucratic realism could not guess.
- Let's have to understand each other with the enemy. Great haunrs are opportunities that rectify what we are no longer valid for because we are hard -working towards a common good, that this is trade, this thing that needs many mappings but bizarrely someone takes and wrapping. Miguéis can be very advantageous to us in this emblematic tale hidden in time, which when joining the Portuguese Communist Party shortly before leaving for America, perhaps in the insuffle of premonitory legacy.
- Dear Europe, this one, also thought that the war was over, then it would only be football, finance and commerce, but here is not when it now walks all over there with “emergency kits” in an uninterrupted tea time that claims to be summit.
Dear Europe, this one, also thought the war was over, would then be just football, finance and commerce, but behold, but when it is now all over there with “emergency kits” in an uninterrupted tea time that claims to be cimeiras.</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:34:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump and the politicization of time and climate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/30/trump-e-a-politizacao-do-tempo-e-do-clima/</link><description>The disagreements between Trump and meteorologists are not new. Already in the first administration he directed by him there were disagreements that echoed in the US and international press. Its intrusion in predictions about the evolution of Hurricane Dorian in 2019 caused the “American Meteorological Society” (AMS) and the “National Weather Association (NWA) to diffuse a joint statement that there would likely be damage caused by the weather in the state of Alabama, as Mr. Trump had vatified.
Perhaps for this reason, the then president of the United States of America may have been hating meteorologists and, by dragging, climatologists. Note that being a meteorologist is different from being a climatologist. The meteorologist, among other functions, analyzes the current time and foresees its evolution for the following days, while the climatologist studies the average time of a particular region, or even on a global scale and, using computational models, prepares antevisions of what could happen in the medium and long term, and the period is covered to reach dozens of years.
While characterizing time in a particular place or region it is necessary to know the various weather parameters (temperature, moisture, atmospheric pressure, wind, cloudiness, precipitation, etc.) at a given time or a short period, to characterize the climate with the predominant time for relatively long periods. According to the world weather organization, this period should be at least thirty years.
Returning to the different between Trump and meteorologists, their interpretation in the functions of these professionals and the institutions where they develop their activity may be the reflection of their vengeful character or by the fact that it is simple, not being able to love the storms (or intensify them), or determine when phenomena such as El-Niño, La Niña, monsoons, etc., should be beginning or ends.
On the other hand, with the help of the oligarchs that have gained power in the US, the second country that most emits greenhouse gases (GHG) can certainly influence the climate. As? You can ask. The answer is simple. It is proven that the combustion of fossil fuels (oil, natural gas and mineral coal) is largely responsible for increasing the concentration of GHGs in the atmosphere, the main cause of climate change since the beginning of the industrial age. Since Trump is reversing all laws in the US that advocates the reduction of the use of such fuels, the gee concentration will continue to increase significantly, which will contribute to accentuating these changes.
The weather will probably resent the measures being taken, including the cutting of funds in all that relates to the study of climate change and their consequences. The intensification of “drill, baby, drill”, as he likes to repeat, will contribute to the imbalance that the climate is being targeted. The various components of the climate system, especially the atmosphere, the biosphere, the cryiosfera and the hydrosphere will continue to suffer the consequences of the non -accepting of the recommendations of thousands of scientists, through the IPCC, the Kyoto Protocol, the 29 COP (Conference of the Parties) agreement, etc. The atmosphere is increasingly impregnated with GEE, the biosphere is degrading with the increasingly frequent forest fires; The oceans increase in salinity caused by acid rain and the absorption of carbon dioxide; The Criosfera ice fusion rate is increasing, which has the most serious consequence of increasing sea level.
The unknown with which the current US administration deals with the issues associated with the climate and environment is such that, on the Official “Website” of the White House, an “Executive Order” with the title “Reinvigoring America’s Beautiful Clean Coal Industry and Amending Order 14241”, dated April 8, 2025, in which one of the most polluting industries is designated by “Beautiful Industry Charcoal clean".
Megha Satyanarayana, chief editor of the opinion section of Scientific American magazine, recently asked "Why is the Trump Administration Politicizing Weather?"  In her response, she associates the financial interest with Trump's attitudes and the oligarchy that has gained power. According to her, they are ending the disagreeing voices of the easy and fast profit policy that is based on the exploration of fossil fuels. The ongoing dismissal of scientists who develop their activity in the National Weather Service (NWS), department of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), is part of this effort to end the discordant voices of their policy. Hundreds of employees were failed in NOAA as a consequence of the application of the “2025 project”, which is no more than a series of measures aimed at reducing the number and size of state agencies, according to a conservative perspective.
In its painful view, Trump administration does not see that, putting into practice this project, it is limiting the efficiency of an institution that has undoubtedly contributed to the safeguarding of lives and goods in a highly efficient way. Based on the information from the weather stations, the weather satellites and communications, the radars, the weather and climate forecast models, weather services are contributing to the prosperity of the countries where they operate. Millions of lives have been saved thanks to meteorological warning systems, based on which alerts about the evolution and approach of highly serious phenomena are prepared, such as tropical and extractic cyclones. An example of what the absence of weather information can cause, was what happened on September 8, 1900, when a hurricane hit the South Coast near Galveston in the Gulf of Mexico (Sorry Mr. Trump). At that time these storms were not yet designated by proper names, nor were sophisticated systems of meteorological warnings. About six thousand people succumbed victims to strong winds and the storm tide associated with the hurricane.
This would not happen today, thanks to the progress that, however, national weather services have benefited. The creation of the worldwide meteorological organization in 1950, the increase in the number of weather stations, the use of weather radars and satellites, the progress of telecommunications and the efficiency of the time-friendly physical-material models, made not today possible consequences of such phenomena of this type. And all this thanks to the commitment, largely, the professionals of Meteorology. And it is these same professionals who currently suffer the destructive fury of the “project 2025”.
Universities are also being victims of the state's cutting. Among these Sobresai the University of Harvard, where 161 Nobel Prizes were formed, including Albert Arnold Gore Jr., the 45th US Vice President (1993-2001), which was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2007 (together with the IPCC), due to the work developed in the dissemination of knowledge about climate change.
According to IPCC reports, there is a close relationship between increased concentration of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere and the frequency and intensity of heat waves, droughts and forest fires. The implementation of the “project 2025” may make a kind of “boomerang” effect contribute to climate deterioration, which will imply that the second most polluting country also suffers the consequences.
Meteorologist</description><pubDate>2025-04-30 01:03:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese musical instrument conference in Mafra</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/conferencia-de-instrumentos-musicais-chineses-em-mafra/</link><description>The eighth edition of the Music Festival “Lisbon Conference Chinese Music and Musical Instruments” [Lisbon Conference on Chinese Music and Musical Instruments] takes off until Sunday between Lisbon and Mafra, being a supported and funded event, including linked to Macao, as is the case of Jorge Álvares Foundation and Macau Foundation, among others.
More specifically, today, tomorrow and Friday, 9 the event takes place at the National Palace of Mafra. This year's theme is “Expanding Horizons: Embracing The Wide Variety of Asian Music and Dance” [Expand the horizons: embracing the wide variety of music and Asian dance].
The idea is that in the coming days you talk and hear not only Chinese music, but also the Asian sounds and know more about the musical instruments that make these sounds. Today is the panel “Traditional and Popular Performing Arts of Asia” [Traditional and Popular Performative Arts of Asia], which will talk about Chinese folk music thanks to the intervention of Frank Kouwenhoven, researcher at Leiden University. Three academic interventions are followed by Naxi's folk songs in southwest China.
Also noteworthy for the panel dedicated to Macau, namely “Macau: Crossroads for Chinese and European Music” [Macao: A Crossroads for Chinese and European music], with interventions by Xiao Ling Shao, who will speak of the “art of Portuguese music in Macau” and Enio de Souza, who will make a “approach to musical instruments in the Chinese temples of Macao”. Highlight for the lecture starring José Pinto de Sá and Rui Magno Pinto on “Memory of Portuguese Classical Music Concerts in Macau”.
The musical part also happens today, from 19h [Time of Lisbon], at the Casa da Música Francisco Alves Gato, in Mafra, with a concert with the musicians Superena insert Adler, François Picard and Je Jinhua, among others, with various Asian instruments.
Popular sounds
Tomorrow, Thursday, it is the turn of the debate around the music to do in Mafra, starting at 10am [Time of Lisbon] with three personalities from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, China, who speak of “Investigation in the theories of the composition of Chinese music”. This is followed by the lecture by Rakesh Kumar, from South Africa, who will speak of the “Afro-Indian Siddi Goma-Dhamal Performances: Bridging The Past and Present, The Local and Global [Afro-Indian performances Siddi Goma-Dhamal: Bringing the past and the gift, the place and the global].
Again from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, China, Feng Changchun emerges talking about “empathy through time and space - the poetry of Li Yu and the art of the composition of the modern Chinese song”. In turn, Maureen Russell of the UCLA Ethnomusicology Department - University of California, Los Angeles, will talk about musical archives in “Sharing Soundscapes: The Bake / Jairazbhoy Digital Archive of South Asian Traditional Music and Arts”.
This Saturday, parallel sessions take place at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon on Chinese and Asian music in general terms. One of the panels about musical history before and after 1949 ″, in which Zhang Xiaodong, from the Shanghai Conservatory of Music, will present a “Study on Historical Development and Yueqin Performance Formats”, an instrument of Chinese strings. Another example of a lecture is the session starring Lisa Beebe, from the University of Wisonsin-Whitewater, about the presence of Vietnamese instruments in Canada.
Jonathan Stock also addresses the theme “Thematic and Multivocal Approach to the History of Music in the Republic of China (1912-1949)”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:13:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Must | “Hug of Love” and other works, by Leong Kit Man, on display</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/must-abraco-do-amor-e-outras-obras-de-leong-kit-man-em-exposicao/</link><description>The University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must, in the English acronym) hosts until Sunday the show of Leong Kit Man, with several paintings, where the creation “Hug of Love” stands out. These are works funded by the Young Talent Support Program of Artistic Creation of the National Arts Fund of China, in its edition of 2024, curated by Julia Kwan
 
Leong Kit Man, a young local artist, exposes his work "Hug of Love" until this Sunday at the University of Science and Technology of Macau (Must, in the English acronym). It is a large painting, with 4.8 by 4.8 meters, the result of an artistic project funded by the Youth Talent Support Program of Artistic Creation of the China National Arts Fund of 2024.
According to a Must statement, this is a painting where flowers and birds gain prominence, breaking “with the traditional composition of topographic painting”.
According to a curator's note, Julia Lam Tsz Kwan, the artist “unites [in painting] human landscapes and a centenary tree in a vision through segmented color blocks, with diverse elements, including the ancestral tree that symbolizes the life cycle, nests that symbolize homes, creation of pups that represent the adoption and inheritance, and precede plates that evoke prayers”. All of these elements “mean human growth”, read in the same note.
In addition to this great picture, the public can also see “six original large -scale paintings of flowers and birds, along with preparatory designs, sketches and color studies of the artist”. The show also includes “a special digital animation” framed with the painting “Hug of Love”. This set of works indicates that “beyond the technical inheritance, the evolution of Chinese painting is in line with the continuous pioneering of new artistic expressions”. All of these works can be seen free of charge on the fourth floor of Must's block.
Style
In the same note, it is noteworthy that Leong Kit Man has been looking for more than a decade for over a decade, “merging the gongbi-style meticulous brush, with textures material, in order to obtain a distinct style, while exploiting and expanding infinite possibilities of the oriental [artistic] media”.
It should be noted that the Gongbi style is, in Chinese painting, synonymous with detail and precision in how the various elements are portrayed, in order to give a sense of great realism to those who look at the works. For this style of painting, specific brushes are used in order to obtain certain types of lines and contours, according to the objective that the artist wants to achieve.
Mo Xiaoye, exhibition advisor and professor at the Department of Fine Arts at Zhejiang University of Science and Technology, said that the play “Hug of Love” represents “from a single perspective, the Macau Peninsula seen from far from Cotai”. For the academic, this painting also allows “a highly creative and successful rereading of Macau's topographic painting, breaking with conventional formats”.
The artist herself explains that this work "has as its backdrop the urban landscape of Macao dramatically transformed 25 years after the transfer [Portuguese administration from Macau to China], with a centenary tree as a central piece to look at us, who passed through it."
Doctorate in Fine Arts from the National Academy of Arts of China, artist, academic and curator, Leong Kit Man is assistant teacher of Fine Arts and Master's Supervisor and PhD at the Faculty of Humanities and Arts of Must.
The artist also had works selected for the China National Art Exhibition in 2014, 2019, and 2024. Highlight for the work “Emplendor Efémeus”, which was chosen to join the Exhibition of Select Works of the National Exhibition of Fine Arts of 2019 in Beijing. The artist won several awards at Macau's annual visual arts exhibition.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:11:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Biennial | IC accepts submission of proposals until the 23rd</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/bienal-de-macau-ic-aceita-submissao-de-propostas-ate-ao-dia-23/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) accepts, until May 23, proposals for this year's edition of “Macao Art: International Art Biennial of Macau 2025”, which will be held between July 19 and October 12 this year, highlights an IC statement.
Thus, “local individuals and organizations linked to the arts can participate through the presentation of exposure proposals, in order to jointly promote the field of contemporary art, as well as build a platform for the exchange of international art, open and diverse”. The idea is to highlight “the results achieved in the local artistic formation and the creative energy of Macao”.
The selection of the proposals will fit Feng Boyi, the main curator of “Art Macau 2025”, taking into account criteria such as “the curatorial concept of the exposure proposal, the quality of the works, the degree of adequacy to the theme, the team's qualifications, the feasibility of the proposal and the place of the exhibition”.
“Art Macau 2025” will have six sections, entitled “Main Exhibition, Public Art Exhibition, City Pavilion, Special Exhibition, Local Curator Project and Collateral Exhibition”, this year being dedicated to the theme “Hello, what do you do here?”.
The idea is to create “an international artistic and cultural party, to promote the development of local arts”, providing “an open and diversified exchange platform” that serves to “cultivate local curatorial talents and show the results of contemporary artistic creations”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:34:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Taipa Village | Frank Lei Exhibition on Exhibition from Tomorrow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/vila-da-taipa-exposicao-de-frank-lei-em-exibicao-a-partir-de-amanha/</link><description>The Vila da Taipa Cultural Association presents tomorrow “Frank Law: Cuba 92”, an exhibition of photography dedicated to the artist based in Macau and deceased in 2022. Here is the opportunity to see images of Cuba 1992, never before shown, in which it is a tribute to Frank Lei
 
He was born in Beijing and since he had lived in Macau. Frank Law, a man dedicated to the arts and photography, died in 2022 victim of prolonged illness, but is now entitled to a tribute through the display of his work. This is the exhibition “Frank Law: Cuba 92”, evident from tomorrow, and until July 9, at the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association, with unpublished images captured by law in Cuba, in 1992.
According to a statement from the organization, Frank Lei passed away leaving "a vast set of photographic works that remain little known to the general public." In this way, this show was born of the joint effort of family, friends and, above all, Alan Ieong Chon Weng, one of the founders of the Dialect group, dedicated to photography.
“In 1992, Frank Law first traveled to Cuba, visiting not only the capital, Havana, but also Santiago de Cuba, in the eastern part of the island, demonstrating his deep attention and exploitation of Cuban culture and community,” says the organization, not only the artist launched not only an exhibition, but also a book with these images, with the name “Cuba Cuba”.
This project included “selected works, filmed in color diaper”, constituting “the core of a narrative that presented a vibrant and living impression of the island nation”. In addition, Frank Law files on Cuba "include a set of unpublished black and white photographs, monochrome images that capture everyday life and the emotions of the Cuban people from a more subtle and contained perspective."
Now, with this new exhibition, the display of these black and white images never revealed to the public "offers a new window in time and space, allowing the viewer to know the island's landscape that so much captivated the soul of Frank and which constitutes the invisible side of his trip to Cuba."
"The initiative to bring to light these works is a recognition of the relevance of photography to document human realities and the circumstances of people's lives. Spectators have the opportunity to revisit Frank's works not only, but also to embrace the emotions they evoke about the survival of a society and a country as a Cuba," the organization highlights.
Quoted by the same note, João Ó, architect and president of the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association, said it was “an honor to collaborate with Dialect to present this unprecedented collection of black and white photographs of Frank to Cuba's trip”.
“The selection of photographs pays tribute to Frank's singular dedication to artistic and cultural creative industries over the years and shows the passion for Cuban culture that has impregnated his heart and soul,” he adds.
A man from Macau
Born in Beijing, Frank came to Macau at the age of ten. He graduated in journalism and worked as a reporter in the newspaper or Mun after the degree. Then he fell in love with the French cinema of the so-called “New Vacancy”, having gone to Paris to study cinema and video at the University of Sorbonne in 1991. In the same year, he was admitted at École Nationale Supérieure des Arts Décoratifs de Paris, where he studied photography, and also won the first award in the International Photography Contest “Life on the Street”, organized by the Musée de La Photographie.
Frank Lei exposed his images on the Grand Palais de Paris, being part of the permanent collection of Musée de la photographie. In 1992, Frank traveled to Cuba to work in artistic projects and even waved to President Fidel Castro, highlights the organization of the exhibition.
He then returned to Macau, where he taught at the School of Arts of the Macao Polytechnic Institute, today Macao Polytechnic University.
“Cinema, photography, music and literature were Frank's passions throughout his life and, right after his return to Macau, embraced Buddhism, bringing a simple and vegetarian lifestyle,” he says.
Frank Law was exposing his work in France, Macau and Hong Kong. In 1995, he founded the Macao Pedra Commune Artistic Group. In 2004, two years after his first exhibition about Cuba, it was found that Frank suffered from cancer in his brain. After treatment, he returned to the then Macao Polytechnic Institute, continued to work in the ox warehouse and began drawing extensively during his recovery.
In 2006, he published the photographic anthology “walking and observing” with Pin-to Books. He continued to photograph and create paintings, organizing individual exhibitions and small painting exhibitions, and traveled to New York, South Korea and France for exchanges and photographic shows.
In early 2017, Frank was invited to Strasbourg Art Photography, a permanent festival of photography in France, for a photographic exhibition and an exchange. After the disease, Frank Law died on May 18, 2022.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:32:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Auditors of Macau company accused of accounting accounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/auditores-de-empresa-de-macau-acusados-de-falsificacao-de-contas/</link><description>Four Wellink CPA auditors and consultants are accused of having falsified Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited accounts so that this Macao company could enter the Hong Kong bag. The case was revealed yesterday through a Hong Kong Independent Commission Against Corruption (ICAC) and is also being investigated in Macao.
According to the results of the investigation that took place since 2021, auditors and consultants Lam Shui-Mei, Siu Yuen-Shan, Cha Wai-Lun and Wong Yat-Chung falsified Huarchi Global accounts to show fictitious economic growth and be admitted to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange.
In addition, the four asked for the help of three family members, identified as Li Man-Heung, Li Kit-Chit and Wong Wing-Man, to subscribe to the company's first public offering. According to the Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC), which assisted the ICAC in investigations, those involved in the purchase of shares received $ 1.5 million from Hong Kong.
As a result, the four are accused of two conspiracy crimes to defraud the Hong Kong bag, while the three family members are accused of a conspiracy crime to defraud the Hong Kong bag. The seven will be present throughout this day to a Hong Kong court. However, the ICAC has admitted that investigations are still running and that there may be other accusations.
Investigation in Macau
In Macao, searches were performed at the headquarters of Huarchi Global Group Holdings Limited in the Plaza Civil Building.
The president of the group appears identified in the 2021 company annual report as Lou Cheok Meng. The identity was not confirmed by the Macao corruption commissioner, who in a statement of the case confirmed that he was running an independent investigation in Macau.
"This construction company is a local Macao company and its official is also a resident of Macao, so CCAC has established an investigation process following the respective indications of crime," he was reported. In addition, CCAC reported that the case continues to be investigated in the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:15:52</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP | Detained harassment passenger</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/cpsp-detido-assediar-passageira-de-autocarro/</link><description>A man, about 20, was arrested by the Public Security Police (CPSP), after taking advantage of the fact that an bus is full to harass a passenger. The case happened on Wednesday April 30. According to the PSP, that day, the man rubbed the pelvic zone against women's hips for several minutes.
The 20 -year -old didn't react immediately, and let the man leave the bus. However, he eventually filed a complaint to the police, moments later. The resident was identified using the bus recording system and the city's video surveillance.
Asked by the authorities, after being arrested, the man confessed to the practice of the facts. In addition to these suspicions, in the criminal record, the man has a conviction for the crime of illicit recordings in 2018 and another debut conviction of private life in 2021.
Alcohol | Man caught with 1.26 g/l in the blood
A man, about 40, was arrested after being caught driving at a 1.26 grams per liter of blood. The case took place on May 1, was presented yesterday by the Public Security Police (CPSP) and quoted by the newspaper or Mun.
The driver was caught while circulating on Avenida da Ponte da Amizade, around 5am, and was stopped in a police routine operation. When stopped, CPSP agents smelled alcohol and asked the driver to take the alcohol test.
As the result was 1.26 grams per liter of blood, the man admitted to being alcohol during a dinner in the black sand, so the case was referred to the prosecutor.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:51:39</pubDate></item><item><title>CITIGROUP | Trade war is still passing by</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/citigroup-guerra-comercial-ainda-esta-a-passar-ao-lado/</link><description>In early May, the great gamblers moved to the casinos of the territory. Citigroup admits that it may have somehow assisted revenge expenses, that is, intense consumption after periods of deprivation
 
In the early days of May, the impact of trade war between the US and China was not felt but casino tables. The scenario was outlined by the Citigroup Investment Bank, in the latest report on the game sector.
The May 1st holiday coincides with the Golden Week in the countryside, one of the main vacation periods, and despite the most complicated economic environment worldwide, players, including VIP, did not fail to come to Macao.
According to Citigroup, quoted by the GGR Asia portal, the “current commercial conflicts between China and the United States seem not to be discouraging players to enjoy gaming offers and non -Macao's playing elements,” he is written.
Analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau even go further and consider that the observations made in the casinos were to leave “the jaw drop”, given the number of players. For this reality contributed the number of great gamblers, those who make bets over $ 1 million of Hong Kong per play, which were present at the tables.
Analysts even hypothesized that they have assisted “revenge expenses”, an expression used to describe intense and high consumption after moments of deprivation. "It was the first time we came across more than a VIP player to bet several million dollars of Hong Kong the same day," they noted. "This probably suggests that current commercial conflicts between China and the US are not so far affecting players' preferences," Citi suggested.
Full house
However, it was not only in terms of VIP players that the game market showed a great vitality. The same happened at the mass level, with Citigroup indicating that the number of visitors, in the order of 220 thousand per day, presented averages higher than those of the Lunar New Year, another of the high seasons of tourism.
Given these values, Citigroup indicates that the numbers show that there is a certain “lack of elasticity of demand for the game”, that is, that the demand for the game tends to suffer few variations, despite being affected by negative factors.
In terms of market share among the six dealers, and taking into account the highest segment in the mass market, the premium segment, analysts pointed out that Sands China, Wynn Macau and MGM China get 63 percent of the market, with galaxy, Melco and SJM to get the remaining 37 percent. This trend was considered as within the expected.
The bank also indicated that MGM China “jumped to first place with a quota of approximately 30 percent of observed premium mass bets” due to the presence of a great gambler who was betting about $ 2.9 million from Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:47:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Birth | Minus 100 births in three months</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/natalidade-menos-100-nascimentos-em-tres-meses/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) reveal that the birth rate does not give signs of increasing.
This is because in the first quarter of the year there were 750 births, a drop of 106 compared to the last quarter of 2024. Still in the first quarter, the number of births decreased 237 compared to the fourth quarter of 2024.
Macao's total population was, in March, of 687,900 people, plus 1,500, compared to the end of the same quarter of 2024, mainly due to the number of non -resident workers domiciled in Macao, DSEC highlights. As for the percentage distribution of the population by gender, the female population, with 369,600 people, was higher than male 318,300 people, representing 53.7 percent of the total population.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:45:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar | Reduction of requests for help to Macau since April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/myanmar-reducao-de-pedidos-de-ajuda-a-macau-desde-abril/</link><description>The number of requests for support in the context of the earthquake at Myanmar, which occurred on March 28, has been downloading. This is what a statement from the health services of Macau says, which participates in rescue actions.
Last Friday, a joint meeting was chaired by Htuntin, a subdirector of the Public Health Department of the Ministry of Health of Myanmar, where he said that “the number of daily care of the international health team, which ascended at 400 per day in the seven days of earthquake, experienced a significant increase, reaching 1,700 at peak”.
However, "from April 12, a decrease and subsequent stabilization in the number of care has been observed, as emergency teams from various countries continue to provide support to victims."
Currently, “only nine percent of the injured are directly related to the earthquake”, it refers to the same note. Macau participates in these actions through China's international medical emergency team (Macau), one of seven international teams that remain active at Myanmar.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:43:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A | Air quality monitoring station in the gutter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/zona-a-estacao-de-monitorizacao-da-qualidade-do-ar-na-calha/</link><description>An air quality monitoring station in zone A of new landfills will be built. Regarding air quality, the SMG director referred to the descent of the atmospheric pollutants concentration in 2023, according to data from the large bay monitoring network. This although the quality air got worse in Macao in 2023 and 2024
 
After a sequence of dangerous or unhealthy air quality days, which even motivated the alert of meteorological and geophysical services (SMG) for the population to avoid going out, the body's director reported improvements in the air quality verified in 2023 at regional level.
In a response to the written interpellation of Congressman Leong Weng Kun, he highlights the results of the regional levels and the work of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau air quality monitoring network to the Rio das Pearl Delta region. ”
According to the SMG director, the 2023 report of the interregional network points out that “the annual average concentration values ​​of various atmospheric pollutants recorded by 2023 fell between 17 and 86 percent over peak levels”. Leong Weng Kun concludes that "emission reduction measures implemented by the three regions were effective in improving regional air quality."
However, the annual statistics of the 2023 and 2024 environment of Macau paint a very different scenario. In 2023, more days were recorded with poor air quality compared to the previous year. In fact, the days with “unhealthy” and “moderate” air were much superior to those with “good” quality. The panorama worsened last year, according to environmental statistics the number of days with “unhealthy” and “very unhealthy” air quality increased to 2023.
Beyond oxygen
The SMG director also emphasizes the study prepared by the three regions to understand the causes of ozone in the large bay region and the transmission characteristics at the interregional level.
Despite the descent of air quality, Leong Weng Kun states that "in recent years, the Government of MSAR has implemented a number of measures to improve air quality, including reducing atmospheric pollutants through incentive and regulation measures, aiming at ozone precursors." The official gives the examples of the prohibition of import and transit of paints for construction, inks for vehicles and stickers for decoration works high with volatile organic compounds.
Regarding the monitoring of atmospheric pollution, Leong Weng Kun reveals that the preparatory work is currently “currently under way” to build an air quality monitoring station in zone A of new urban landfills ”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:41:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Zone A | Worker and excavator fall into the sea</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/zona-a-trabalhador-e-escavadora-caiem-ao-mar/</link><description>The consortium of the companies Top Builders and state China Road and Bridge Corporation is responsible for the works of connecting to the peninsula, for which it will receive 608.8 million patacas. The proposal of these companies exceeded 80 million other participants in the contest
 
Photo:
A worker and a large excavator fell into the sea on Friday morning after the collapse of a provisional bridge for the construction of the A3 connection between zone A of the new urban landfills and the Macao Peninsula. The accident was captured in images, which ended up shared on social networks.
The claim happened in less than 20 seconds. The man was thrown into the sea because he was inside the excavating machine that had made the temporary structure not stand. It was eventually saved with the help of their colleagues, who shot him a float, already after being able to get out of the machine, still in the sea.
Hours later, in a statement, the Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP), the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) and the Directorate for Labor Services (DSAL) confirmed the accident and the existence of slight injuries.
"At the shipping and construction of the access road (A3) between zone A of the new urban landfills and the Macao Peninsula, there was an incident in which a building machine and its operator fell into the sea, due to the partial collapse of the provisional easel bridge, and the operator left the sea by himself and was transported to the hospital by the contractor." “It is preliminary to the operator involved was slightly injured and was conscious after the incident, and will undergo a detailed medical inspection,” he was added.
The authorities also considered that the incident had “great importance” and asked for a total suspension of the work.
In turn, DSSA has ensured that the worker will help compensation for the successful, since it suffered mild injuries, while DSOP has required the “contractor and the supervisory entity to fully collaborate with the administration in the investigation of the causes of the incident”. Sanctions were also promised, if it considered that there was a responsibility of the two parties.
MILLION WORK
The construction of the A3 connection between the zone A of the new urban landfills and the Macao Peninsula has as its contractor the consortium consisting of the companies Top Builders and the state China Road and Bridge Corporation.
These won the public tender for the construction of the work for 608.8 million patacas, promising to do the work in 855 days. The proposal was the fourth cheapest of the 10 presented, and all had a time of doing the 855 -day work. However, at least one of the proposals, presented by the consortium consisting of the Ming Shun Building and Building Investment Company and Long Chon Construction and Engineering Society promised to do the same work by 528.0 million patacas, a difference of over 80 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:24:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim committed himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those waiting for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of it, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “I never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification as to their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstandings, if they are fortunately fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered a war, the best animals will be beheaded. superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
A máquina de costura da pobre viúva morta à baioneta…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Hamas warns that it is not worth negotiating new truce</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/gaza-hamas-avisa-que-nao-vale-a-pena-negociar-nova-tregua/</link><description>A high Hamas employee said yesterday that the Palestinian group considers it useless at this stage negotiations for a truce in Gaza, and appealed to the world to press Israel to end the “hunger war” at the enclave.
"It is not worth starting negotiations or examining new ceasefire proposals while the Hunger War and the Gaza Extermination War continues," France-Presse (AFP) Bassem Naïm, a member of the Hamas political office, told the agency. "The world must press the government of Netanyahu to end the crimes of hunger, thirst and murder," he added.
The statements appear a day after the Israelite government announced a new military campaign in the Gaza Strip, which provides for the conquest of the territory. The Gaza Strip, where the inhabitants have been displaced several times, has been under a blockade of Israel since March 2 and crosses a serious humanitarian crisis.
Gaza Civil Defense spokesman Mahmoud Baçal said yesterday that three Palestinians were killed following Israeli bombing at dawn in different parts of the Gaza Strip. The Israelite army resumed the enclave offensive on March 18, ending a two -month truce.
The war was triggered by Hamas's unprecedented attack on Israel on October 7, 2023, which caused the death of 1,218 people on the Israeli side, mostly civilians, according to an AFP count based on official data.
Of the 251 kidnapped people, 58 remain arrested in Gaza, 34 of which were declared killed by the Israelite army. Hamas also maintains the remains of an Israeli soldier killed during a previous war in Gaza in 2014. The Israeli retaliation campaign made at least 52,567 killed in Gaza, most of Civil, according to Hamas Ministry of Health, considered UN reliable.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:17:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Victory Day | China sends guard of honor to parades in Moscow</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/dia-da-vitoria-china-envia-guarda-de-honra-para-desfiles-em-moscovo/</link><description>The China army will send a guard of honor to the Victory Day parades in Moscow, where Chinese President Xi Jinping should attend the Russian homologist Vladimir Putin in Red Square.
The China Ministry of Defense announced on Monday that it will send a guard of honor to participate in the military parades in the capitals of Russia and Belarus, to mark the 80th anniversary of the defeat of Germany Nazi, which is celebrated this Friday.
Beijing sent Moscow Honor Guards to a Victory Day commemorative parade in 2015, but this will be the first time a Chinese guard of honor will participate in a similar event in Minsk.
According to Chinese analysts, the gesture aims to demonstrate support for the International Order of Post World War, which Beijing considers to be under threat. Videos released on Chinese social networks showed the rehearsals of Chinese soldiers in Minsk and Moscow last week.
As part of the preparations for the Moscow Parade, Chinese soldiers rehearsed the “Guerrilla Song” in Red Square on Sunday, described the Global Times, the Chinese Communist Party's official newspaper. The patriotic song describes the difficulties faced by Chinese soldiers during the Japanese invasion.
Official News Agency Xinhua said this year is important to China and Russia, as well as “all those who love peace around the world,” as it also marks the 80th anniversary of the end of the invasion of Japan in China.
Xinhua added that China and Russia will "defend written history with blood and lives, and oppose any attempt or behavior that seeks to deny, distort or falsify the history of World War II." Beijing had already announced that Xi will visit Russia between Wednesday and Saturday, and will maintain a “strategic dialogue” with Putin.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:08:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Travel increases 6.4 percent during May holidays</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/turismo-viagens-aumentam-64-por-cento-durante-feriados-de-maio/</link><description>China registered about 314 million domestic trips during the extended weekend of International Workers Day (May 1), a homologous growth of 6.4 percent, according to data released yesterday.
Tourist expenses also increased this year, the Ministry of Culture and Tourism said, reaching 180.3 billion Yuan, an increase of 8 percent compared to the previous year. Authorities had already foreseen an increase in tourist activity during vacation from May 1-5, with reservations pointing to a preference for long -range trips within the country.
The Asian country registered about 10.89 million entry and exit trips during the holiday, an increase of 28.7 percent over the same period of 2024, according to the National Immigration Administration.
The tourism sector, one of the most affected by the Covid-19 pandemic and the covid zero policy, which has closed the borders of the Asian country for three years, is one of the great hopes of the Chinese government to boost consumption and strengthen sectors such as restoration, transport and retail trade.
In March, the government released an action plan with guidance to ensure a favorable environment for consumption, for which it designed proposals such as the protection of labor rights in terms of rest and vacation, the improvement of commercial infrastructure and the reduction of consumer restrictions.
According to official data, the world's second largest economy met 5 percent growth in 2024, but analysts continue to point out problems such as weak internal and international demand, trade war, insufficient stimuli, a prolonged real estate crisis and the lack of confidence of consumers and private sector.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:05:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Beijing expresses deep concern about Israel's plan to widen offensive</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/gaza-pequim-exprime-profunda-preocupacao-com-plano-de-israel-de-alargar-ofensiva/</link><description>China expressed profound concern yesterday with the situation in the Gaza Strip and expressed its opposition to the plans announced by the Israeli government to expand military operation at the Palestinian enclave.
"China is deeply concerned about the current situation in Gaza and opposes the continuation of Israel's military operations in that region," Lin Jian's Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman said yesterday during a press conference in Beijing.
Lin appealed to all parties to effectively implement the ceasefire agreements and resume "the right way" towards a political solution to the conflict.
Israel's Security Office approved in the early hours of Monday a new document that foresees, among other points, the permanent occupation of territories in the track, the forced displacement of the population to the south and a new system of humanitarian aid distribution, rejected by the UN and all humanitarian organizations present on the ground.
As part of its broader position, China defended last week before the International Court, that Israel "has no sovereignty" about the occupied territories and, therefore, cannot veto the work of organisms such as the United Nations Palestinian Refugee Assistance Agency (Unrwa), which he called the "spine column" of humanitarian aid in Gaza.
Beijing has insisted that the solution is due to the respect of international law, the end of collective punishment to the civilian population and the defense of the principle of the two states. The Israeli attacks on Gaza have caused more than 52,200 dead in the year and a half of conflict triggered by Hamas attacks to Israel in October 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:03:21</pubDate></item><item><title>EU | XI asks for Union against “unilateral intimidation” and reinforcement of partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/ue-xi-pede-uniao-contra-intimidacao-unilateral-e-reforco-de-parceria/</link><description>On a day of celebration of the 50th anniversary of diplomatic relations, the Chinese president calls for the reinforcement of bilateral relations between China and the Old Continent in response to the new challenges posed by the US Administration
Chinese President Xi Jinping said yesterday that China and the European Union should “oppose unilateral harassment” on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations, which coincides with commercial tensions with the United States.
Xi stressed that the relationship between China and the EU is “one of the most influential bilateral relations in the world” and framed this bond in a global scenario marked by uncertainty. "Humanity is again in a historic crossroads," said the Chinese leader, who highlighted the role of bilateral cooperation as an international reference model.
"A healthy and stable relationship between China and the EU not only benefits both parties, but enlightens the path of the world," he said.
XI said it attributed great importance to the development of Brussels relations and expressed his desire to work with the president of the European Council, António Costa, and the president of the European Commission, Ursula Von de Leyen, to “deepen strategic communication, expand mutual opening and properly manage friction and disagreement”.
The message, released yesterday, also included a response from European leaders, who highlighted the evolution of the bilateral relationship and expressed their willingness to “face shared challenges together and promote peace, safety and sustainable development,” said Chinese diplomacy.
XI's appeal comes at a time when Beijing seeks to reinforce cooperation with Brussels to the growing pressure that is being targeted by Washington.
Mutual Benefits
China has repeatedly criticized the economic measures imposed by the United States - such as customs tariffs or technological restrictions - and has appealed to the EU to maintain an independent policy based on multilateralism and mutual benefit.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang also exchanged messages with Costa and Von der Leyen, reaffirming Beijing's commitment to a "stable, constructive and mutual benefit" relationship. The anniversary celebration also coincided with the announcement of the full resuming of the legislative dialogue between Beijing and the European Parliament, after the mutual survey of the restrictions imposed in 2021.
The Chinese Foreign Ministry reaffirmed yesterday that cooperation with the EU “weighs more than competition” at a time when both parties seek to preserve a common agenda in the face of increasing commercial tensions with the United States.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 02:01:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | HRW requires release from activist father</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/hong-kong-hrw-exige-libertacao-de-pai-de-activista/</link><description>The Human Rights Watch organization yesterday called for the release of the Hong Kong Anna Kwok human rights defender, detained in late April, and denounced the harassment of territory authorities to family members of activists. Hong Kong police detained the father of the rooted activist in the United States Anna Kwok, "and accused him of a national security crime," he began writing in a statement to Human Rights Watch (HRW), which requires the release of Kwok Yin-Sang and being "immediately withdrawn all charges."
Hong Kong National Security Police announced on Friday the arrest of Kwok's father and brother, accused of trying to manage the activist's financial resources. According to police sources, this is the first time that the controversial national security law is applied that criminalizes assistance to “designated fugitives” in the management of the assets that hold.
According to the EFE agency on Friday, Hong Kong authorities detained 35 and 68-yearly Anna Kwok's brother and father in Tseung Kwan O district on April 30 and accused the last of trying to raise funds from an insurance policy on the name of their daughter, presenting documents with allegedly false signatures.
Anna Kwok, 28, lives in the United States and is a executive director of the Hong Kong Democracy Council, a US -based non -profit organization and created to promote freedoms in China.
Although the father remains detained, his brother, an employee of the insurance company who manages Kwok's policies, was released under bail and is being investigated for possible abuse of office to facilitate the operation. Also according to EFE, the authorities have reiterated the warning that anyone who collaborates with “designated fugitives” incurs heavy penalties that can go up to seven years in prison.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:40:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Xanana Gusmão asks Timorese to encourage children to learn Portuguese</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/xanana-gusmao-pede-a-timorenses-para-incentivarem-filhos-a-aprender-portugues/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Timor-Leste, Xanana Gusmão, asked yesterday from parents to encourage children to learn Portuguese, a language that is part of the Timorese identity. "To fathers and mothers, I ask you to encourage your children to learn Portuguese, because, according to our history, it is the Portuguese that represents our identity, not English, nor Indonesian," said Xanana Gusmão.
The Timorese Prime Minister spoke at the Government Palace under the celebrations of the World Day of Portuguese Language and the Culture of the Community of Portuguese-Speaking Countries (CPLP) during an activity made by the Portuguese Embassy and the Timorese Ministry of Education, who gathered hundreds of students from the Learning and Formation Center (Cafe Schools), in a march to deliver books to Gusmão Xanana.
The head of the Timorese government recalled that for 24 years of Indonesian occupation, the Portuguese language was not taught and that it is necessary to overcome that inheritance so that Timor-Leste does not risk being absorbed again by Indonesia.
“Students should study and learn the Portuguese language, because it is the identity of Timor-Leste,” said Xanana Gusmão to the Timorese students, also asking them to thank Portugal for sending teachers.
"For us, Timorese, teaching Portuguese is a little difficult, because we do not master the language well, but we thank the Portuguese government for the creation of coffee schools," he added.
The project of the Learning and School Training Center or the Cafe Schools began in 2014, and is already present in the 12 Timorese Municipalities and the Oedusi Enclave, on the Indonesian side of Timor Island, and the extent of those educational establishments for administrative posts in the country is also foreseen.
Those schools, where classes are given by Portuguese and Timorese teachers, are currently attended by more than 11,100 Timorese students. Cafe has two large pillars, namely quality teaching in the classroom and the complementary training of Timorese teachers.
Share the future
In those schools, the classes are taught in Portuguese, but students also have classes in Tetum, the second official language of Timor-Leste. Education Minister Dulce Soares stressed that Portuguese is a language of “affection, knowledge and future”.
“This is where we share stories, build learning and open new ways,” said Dulce Soares, stressing that the Portuguese language represents diversity, creativity, identity and hope. "Promoting the Portuguese language is also to promote education, cooperation and development," he added.
World CPLP World Language and Culture Day was also marked in the National Parliament with a ceremony, which included the attribution of poetry prizes to students, who won a contest to promote Portuguese learning.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:39:05</pubDate></item><item><title>China and Japan exchange accusations about Diaoyu Islands</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/china-e-japao-trocam-acusacoes-sobre-ilhas-diaoyu/</link><description>China and Japan accused Sunday of an intrusion on Saturday in the airspace of islands played by the two countries in the East China Sea.
The uninhabited islands, known as Diaoyu in China and Senkaku in Japan, are administered by Tokyo but claimed by Beijing, being a point of regular tension between the two countries. Chinese diplomacy announced Sunday that it presented a formal protest to the Japan embassy in Beijing, arguing that "a civil plane entered illegally in airspace around the Diaoyu islands."
"The Diaoyu islands and the affiliated islands are a territory belonging to China, and we install Japan immediately ceasing all illegal activities," said Chinese Coast Guard spokesman Liu Dejun. Liu said “a ship-based helicopter” was mobilized to warn and expel the Japanese plane, according to France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
Japanese Foreign Deputy Minister Takehiro Funakoshi, in turn, presented a "vigorous protest" to the Chinese ambassador in Tokyo. He cited the "intrusion of four Chinese coastal guard ships in the Japanese territorial waters around the Senkaku islands and the violation of Japanese airspace by a helicopter."
According to the Japan Ministry of Defense, the Chinese helicopter invaded Japanese airspace for about 15 minutes.
"The [Japanese] self -defense forces reacted by sending fighters," said the ministry, also quoted by AFP. According to Japanese public broadcaster NHK and other local media, it is the first time a helicopter of Chinese authorities violates Japanese airspace on dispute islands.
Sides
Tensions between China and other countries that claim territories in the Sea of ​​China led Japan to develop ties with the Philippines and the United States. Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba and Filipino President Ferdinand Marcos agreed on Tuesday to deepen security ties between the two countries.
They also agreed to oppose “attempts to alter the 'status quo' in the East China Sea and the southern China Sea by strength or coercion,” in a reference to China.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:29:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia | Xi Jinping visiting the country from Wednesday to Saturday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/russia-xi-jinping-de-visita-ao-pais-de-quarta-feira-a-sabado/</link><description>The visit of the Chinese president, along with other world leaders such as Lula da Silva, is part of the celebration of the day of victory over Germany Nazi in World War II. Ukraine and the international situation should be on the agenda of the XI meeting with Putin
 
Russia announced Sunday that Chinese President Xi Jinping will visit the country from Wednesday to Saturday in the 80th anniversary of World War II victory against Germany Nazi, also addressing the Ukrainian conflict.
According to a statement issued Sunday by Kremlin and quoted by France-Presse (AFP), Xi Jinping will also participate in bilateral discussions on “the development of world partnership relations and strategic interaction” and “current problems in the order of International and Regional Day”.
"It is expected that a series of bilateral documents, between governments and ministries, be signed," added the Kremlin. The visit takes place at a time of commercial confrontation between Beijing and Washington, reaffirming the alliance between Russia and China.
In addition to Xi Jinping, leaders from about 20 countries are expected to attend the military parade on May 9 in Red Square, including Brazilian President Lula da Silva and other traditional international allies of Moscow.
One of whom is Cuban President Miguel Díaz-Canel, who arrived Sunday in St. Petersburg, where he was received by local governor Alexandr Beglov.
Threat exchange
On Saturday, Kremlin accused Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky of threatening the celebrations of World War II on May 9 after stating that Kiev could not ensure the safety of international leaders in Moscow.
Volodymyr Zelensky “made an unmistakable threat to world leaders” who will participate in the ceremony, Russian diplomacy spokesman Maria Zakharova said on social networks, according to Russian news agency Tass.
Zakharova commented on statements made on Friday night by Zelensky about the celebrations of the 80th anniversary of the victory over Germany Nazi, presided by Vladimir Putin. Zelensky said Kiev could not guarantee the safety of the international leaders present, suggesting that Moscow can do something to blame Ukraine.
"We do not know what Russia will do on that date. You can take several measures, such as fires or explosions, and then accuse us," said the Ukrainian President.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:28:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and I see soon that AI was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return of digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>João Romão, academic: “Macau is in a highly privileged position”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/02/joao-romao-academico-macau-esta-numa-posicao-altamente-privilegiada/</link><description>Professor at Yasuda Women’s University in Japan, João Romão prepares to launch in June a book entitled “Economic Geography of Tourism”. Speaking to HM, the academic enhances the interconnection between tourism, economy and geography, and lists its possibilities, limitations and effects, including Macao
 
 
In this book it speaks of the concept of “spatial economy”, in connection with tourism and geography. How is this connection?
Economic geography combines the geographical context with economic processes, being studied the spatial distribution of economic activities. The economy of tourism is particularly sensitive to these geographical constraints, as they are the characteristics of each place that enhances the development of certain products or services. These characteristics widely exceed the physical aspects of the territory and also include culture, history, ways of life or even institutions and legal frameworks. The case of casino, something particularly important in Macao, is a good example of the importance of legal aspects to develop certain types of tourism. Economic geography has a wider scope than the spatial economy, more focused on strictly economic aspects. Being evident in tourism this relationship between economics and geography, this book establishes a double approach that systematizes the interdependence of these three aspects it refers. First explores how the concepts and theories of economic geography can apply to tourism. In the second half it makes the opposite route, discussing how the analysis of relevant problems of contemporary tourism justifies the use of economic geography. Examples are the degradation of local resources, environmental impacts, contribution to climate change, acceleration of gentrification processes or disturbance of community modes of life.
Can having an excessively -dependent economy of tourism constitute a problem or salvation?
The two things, and are both cases that economic geography can help to understand. The industrialization of economies is linked to the agglomeration processes of activities that reinforce each other when they reach a certain scale. This allows the massification of production and consumption, with reasonable costs. Contemporary industries, more associated with the integration of digital technologies and creative processes, are less clustered in specialized industrial development zones, but tend to focus on large cities and metropolitan areas. It also follows that rural areas, islands, or sites that have not followed industrialization processes, have more difficulty mobilizing investments, technologies or qualified people to innovate and develop new industries. In such cases, tourism often appears as the possible solution as it can be developed with incorporation of technology and relatively low knowledge. On the other hand, tourism consumption, not being essential to human life, is very sensitive to income fluctuations.
Can you give examples?
This was visible, for example, with the 2007/2009 international crisis. Tourism is also very vulnerable to safety problems or international epidemics, such as COVID-19 has demonstrated to the extreme. Economies too specialized in tourism are very vulnerable to external shocks and less resilient to crises. It is also visible that, being the tourist development often supported by intensive and weak labor services, the specialization in tourism can cause, in the long run, embarrassment in terms of population qualifications, the ability to innovate and integrate technology or to add value to the regional economy.
The book also speaks of “intelligent tourism” and “co-creation of experiences”, using the megados and IA. Is tourism definitely becoming more digital?
Social networks are fundamental instruments for new generations. However, they began to generalize the tools for planning or promotion of travel supported by artificial intelligence. The so-called “intelligent tourism” more generally designates the use of digital technologies to intensify information flows, consolidate the formation of networks and promote more informed and shared decision making, eventually contributing to the so-called “co-creation of experiences”. Tourism digitization has its origins in service distribution systems originally developed by airlines since the 1960s, but it would be the internet to accelerate and globalize digitization.
And social networks.
The emergence of social networks promoted the creation of a more interactive universe, potentially in real time and involving wide numbers of users and various types of supports. The generalization of the use of mobile phones permanently connected to the Internet, even on foreign travel, has further increased this potential for intensive and interactive use of data and information. This "co-creation", however, hides obvious imbalances of power.
Such as?
With regard to tourists, or consumer in general, it is usually the role of providing information, for example through social networks. This information is obtained, accumulated and marketed, sometimes without consent or even without knowledge, to eventually translate into the creation, adaptation or promotion of products and services. This process is particularly important in the case of tourism, because there is usually a long period between the decision to travel and the trip itself. This period of travel exploration and planning is used by tourist marketing companies to try to influence choices. This type of interaction also introduces a difference in the “spatiality” of the provision of tourist services, which are usually produced and consumed at the same time and in the same place, in a direct relationship between producer and consumer. The digitization of tourism anticipates most of these interactions and information flows and transfers them to large technological companies or marketing and distribution.
In a world where more and more travel, the routes are shorter and access to information is immense, how can countries and regions be competitive in the tourist offer?
Contemporary tourism lives in a highly competitive international environment. But just as there is a wide variety of destinations and offerings, there is also a wide range of preferences and consumption, what is called “hyper-personalization”, the result of such abundance of information and opportunity for interaction. The challenge that is placed on destinations is to identify the resources, products and services that can be adjusted to a particular group of consumers, to communicate effectively. This competitiveness greatly goes beyond the strict scope of tourist services because it also requires mobility and transportation services, varied infrastructure, safety, medical support, or easy communication. Anywhere you want to develop your tourist industry have to intervene about all these factors.
The book also addresses how “social processes” shape the development of tourism. In the case of China, for example, do you believe we are watching a change, which will have consequences for Macau?
It seems to me that Macau is in a highly privileged position to develop other forms of tourism. China is the largest issuing market in the world, the widespread rise of income in recent decades allows many million people to explore the opportunity to travel. Macao is a very close and distinct destination, with its historical and cultural particularities. For the Chinese population it was not easy to visit Macau and there is certainly a great interest.
How does the Great Bay project come in this?
The strategy that is being followed by integrating the Great Bay allows you to develop a cosmopolitan and diverse offer that can certainly attract Chinese tourists and other parts of the world. Moreover, these three areas have excellent hotel and tourism schools, which guarantee qualified personnel for tourism management and planning. The element of differentiation that Portuguese culture introduces in this context can certainly contribute to the success of the transition from a casinos focused on other forms that value culture and heritage more.
Is it possible to have sustainable tourism?
The problems and difficulties of tourism sustainability are more visible than in other sectors. This “spatiality” of tourism (where the consumer is obliged to move to the place of consumption) implies that the consequences of this consumption become more evident. These effects are less obvious when it comes to the unsustainability of industrial units or intensive forms of agriculture in relatively isolated areas. As mass reduction and investment reduction strategies also apply to tourism, the consequences of the environment or the quality of life of residents in destinations can be devastating. Sustainability implies a long -term perspective based on the idea that today's decisions do not imply future negative consequences. Sustainable practices depend on the control of the impacts that accumulate over time by individual and independent economic agents.
How can this control be done?
When a hotel or airline defines what ability to install on their services they may eventually estimate the impact that consumers will have on the local environment or economy. They will have more difficulties in anticipating that impacts will be generated in the next 10, 15 or 20 years to investment. And surely it will be impossible to measure how this impact accumulates the impacts caused by other service providers, now or in the future. In other words, although the idea of ​​sustainability is widespread accepted, economic agents do not have mechanisms or instruments in practice. Regulating the use of resources and territories by public entities with a more comprehensive and future perspective can contribute to the sustainability more effectively than the regulation associated with market dynamics, which in many cases has been revealed highly predatory. The Chinese economy is one of these examples and may eventually benefit from it.
And in the concrete case of Macau?
Macao has historically known problems: ultra-urbanized and polluted areas, with large energy consumption and waste production; Great concentration of tourists in a relatively small area of ​​great historical and cultural interest; Great dependence on the game, with the resulting imbalances in the appropriation of tourism benefits. The ongoing transition to new forms of tourism should better solve these problems and state regulation will certainly have better results than based on market dynamics.</description><pubDate>2025-04-02 23:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>José Paulo Esperança, Associate Rector of the City of Macau University: “Languages ​​cannot be controlled”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/01/jose-paulo-esperanca-reitor-associado-da-universidade-cidade-de-macau-as-linguas-nao-podem-ser-controladas/</link><description>Co-author of the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with Luís Reto and Fernando Luís Machado, José Paulo Esperança reveals to HM that the work edited in 2016 and 2018 is being updated, especially due to the growing global value of the language. The Associate Rector and Professor of the City of Macao University suggests partnerships with Macau under the Editorial Project
 
Launched the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, in co-authorship, about the global value of the language. Plan a new edition or update?
Undoubtedly. We are working in this regard, there was a recent conference in Macao and Professor Luís Reto, former Rector of ISCTE, presented some more current elements that were developed. He has worked on a very important issue, which is the role of Portuguese as a frank language, which was for a few centuries in Asia. The exchange between Dutch and the kingdom of Zion was made in Portuguese, because it was the common language used at that time, before English became the contemporary frank language. Therefore, there is a whole interesting story of Portuguese and the role it had in the first pinyins that existed, with the Chinese and the use of the [Roman] alphabet in Vietname. There are a number of elements that are not, therefore, very publicized, and the work of Atlas is the same, to disclose some economic dimensions of the language.
What are these dimensions?
One is the exchange of foreign trade and investment, which is very facilitated by the language. We also talk about migrations, tourism, students' exchange that is greatly influenced by linguistic proximity. Therefore, today we have a set of elements that are very interesting, and we hope to develop some more important partnerships with Macau.
As?
More at work, Professor Luís Reto is doing, which maintains an investigation team about the value of Portuguese. He has collaborated with the Portuguese Language Museum of São Paulo, for example. It is a museum space that was renewed after the fire that destroyed it. In addition, there is a project with Cascais City Council to develop such a structure, and we hope to do some works with Macau, in order to create three poles for the projection of the Portuguese language. As for Atlas' materials, we would like to have a continued update model, as this data is out of date very quickly. The work was edited in many languages, including Mandarin. This is the moment when we would like to give the book a more historical and deep dimension, with more knowledge about the teaching of Portuguese in the world.
What balance does this teaching do today?
Portuguese is developing a great deal of mother tongue and is effectively one of the most expanding languages ​​due to demographic growth in Africa, with countries such as Angola and Mozambique, which around 2050 will have populations of over 100 million inhabitants, each. The Portuguese thus consolidates itself as a language of the southern hemisphere, but much more from Africa, supplanting Brazil itself as the place of largest number of speakers of the language. All of this generates enormous potential, and this also occurs due to the great exchange of universities and internationalization of teaching. Today there is the possibility of Portuguese being a language of science, there is more publications in this language. This is a great challenge because English is the contemporary language of scientists. We want to contribute to all these dimensions, and Macau can also play an important role there. Macao is indeed a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, and can play a significant role.
Is Macao an ideal place to train Portuguese teachers who do not have Portuguese as a mother tongue? Do you fear that the territory loses relevance in this matter before the offer of courses in the interior of China?
I see this question more as complementarity than competition. We have identified about 60 higher education institutions in China that have Portuguese courses, but I think Macau has very interesting conditions to start teaching from primary to secondary education so that children have been able to have learning from an early age. It does not mean that there are no young Chinese who began to learn their tongue in adolescence that they speak fantastically, which surprises me, but it is easier to start earlier and earlier. This will be easier in Macau. What is important is to create conditions for greater economic collaboration to many levels, such as joint research. In this respect, Macau has a very interesting opportunity. At the City of Macau University we are very interested in increasingly collaborating with researchers who visit us and work with our teams.
Can you give me examples?
Brazil is today one of China's great business partners. There is a lot of exchange in both directions, but one of the themes that is little studied, and in which I work hard, is the internationalization of Chinese companies. To what extent do these companies follow a model of internationalization similar to that of other countries that started this process earlier? I speak of the United States of America, the European countries, but also of Japan and others. China has, in fact, different models of presence in countries that are not yet well known, and this is important to realize, so that we know how to facilitate this process of exchange in a world that lives periods of some setback. It is very sad. I always remember a great economist of Portuguese origin, David Ricardo, who clearly explained how world trade is beneficial to everyone and how countries can take advantage of this situation. Therefore, applying tariffs, making such commercial barriers harms countries that are major exporters, such as China or Germany, and countries that today have a cultural export capacity, for example, and are not just importers.
In relation to the new Orthographic Agreement. It continues without a standardization in Macau. Does it worry it?
Languages ​​are dynamic and cannot be controlled. We think today in English, and we realize that there are almost incomprehensible ways to each other, such as the English one in Nigeria or Australia. Americans have difficulty realizing the Australians. In the nineteenth century, Portuguese from Portugal and Brazil were closer, then some disagreement emerged. There was an effort in Brazil to propose an orthographic agreement, and the Portuguese joined, resulting in a series of negotiations. There have always been resistances. I remember that Fernando Pessoa suggested the famous phrase “My homeland is the Portuguese language”. It was curiously a manifestation of some conservatism, because he thought Pharmacy had to continue writing with pH [Pharmacia]. In fact it did not make much sense. Portugal ended up seeking to impose a certain standardization based on the most genetic changes in the spelling agreement. It is not a process that has been running a hundred percent well, and has been universally adopted. African countries have become more defenders of Portuguese from Portugal. There is sometimes some confusion, but I understand that intercomprehension still remains, achieving a homogeneous language, more perhaps than English.
 
Between words and numbers
José Paulo Esperança is a doctorate in Economics from the European University Institute and was president of the ISCTE Department of Finance and Accounting - University Institute of Lisbon. The “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, with editions in 2016 and 2018, contains “a large set of indicators that reinforce the idea of ​​the growth of teaching, speakers and the written use of Portuguese in the world”, having been the target of a series of recent initiatives in Macao.
One of them took place on March 17, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, with a session of the “Roda de Ideas” cycle, entitled “The Potential of the Portuguese Language in the Contemporary World”, which was attended by the former ISCTE Rector, Luís Reto, and José Paulo Hope himself. In addition to the “New Atlas of the Portuguese Language”, José Paulo Esperança is the author of other works in the financial area.</description><pubDate>2025-04-01 03:08:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSar and Top-10 Victory for Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite Safety Car's entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet beginning, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, the third of the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the guide circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of copies produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos also underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitano Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major goal will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name in Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Touring cars</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/16/gp-apuramento-dos-carros-de-turismo-comeca-com-maior-presenca-macaense/</link><description>The Macao-Macao Road Sport Challenge Touring Car Championship will start this weekend at the Guangdong International Circuit in the city of Zhaoqing, 200 kilometers northwest of the ride. For this race, which will serve as qualification for the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, will be on the starting grid a dozen Macau pilots, including five Portuguese names
 
Among the sixty subscribers, all equipped with two types of vehicles - Toyota GR86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) - are well -known guys from Macau's motor racing. With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit in November last year. Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the focus on pre-season has been in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
Also back is Célio Alves Dias, after a difficult year in 2024, far short of his expectations. For this, the pilot Macaense bet on changing the chassis of his Toyota Gr86. This year, its objective is to account for the twenty -fifth participation in the largest annual sports event of MSAR, so all the details are important.
Back is also Jerónimo Badaraco (Toyota Gr86), a pilot who, in the Macao Grand Prix last year, reached second place at Macao Road Sport Challenge. After having been modest in the finding events, “Noni” was very strong in the city streets, where he was the best Macaense pilot, in a race won by law Kit Meng.
In debut this year will be Maximian Mannão. Bringing with him a nickname with a huge tradition in Macao's motorsport, the young Maximiano, who competed for several years in the local Karting events and, in 2022, participated in a Formula 4 Chinese Championship race, will make his debut at Macau Road Sport Challenge with a Toyota GR86.
The Macanese presence will be reinforced by Dionísio Albino Pereira, a pilot regularly seen in the coloane Karting events, which will conduct a Toyota GR86 from LW World Racing Team. In 2013, he competed in the Macao - Macau Touring Car Series Tourism Championship, then driving a Honda Integra DC5 from the Pas Macau Racing Team team.
The representation of the territory in these findings will also feature Chi Wang, Carson Tang, IP Tok Meng, Chan Chi Ha, Lo Kai Tin and Lou Check In.
It will be to hurt
Em 2024, a Associação Geral Automóvel de Macau-China (AAMC) conseguiu colocar todos os pilotos do Campeonato de Carros de Turismo de Macau no fim-desemana do Grande Prémio. This year, it seems that the scenario of organizing two races for local pilots will be impossible. Como tal, estas corridas de apuramento terão um impacto muito maior, e apenas metade dos agora inscritos terá bilhete de entrada para o maior evento desportivo de carácter anual da RAEM.
Another novelty for this year is that all cars will be equipped with tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, as had already happened in the Grand Prix. However, this year there will be a new compound, the same for everyone, which may shuffle the favorite accounts. Centralins will continue to be drawn, as in the past.
Since the number of participants is high, AAMC will divide the pilots into groups A and B, not two but four races in total. Each race will have 15 laps, two of which will be played on Saturday and two on Sunday.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GT Cup Right-Great Bay Race decides on Pingtan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/09/apuramento-da-taca-gt-corrida-da-grande-baia-decide-se-em-pingtan/</link><description>The second test of the GT Cup - Race of the Great Bay of the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix will not be played at the Zhuhai International Circuit, as initially planned, but at the International Circuit of Lago Ruyi, in the Pingtan tourist region in Fuzhou.
Sro Cup's debut season calendar was finally defined yesterday, with the official announcement of confirmation that Pingtan's semi-permanent circuit will host the third and fourth rounds of the GT4 cars on June 28 and 29. Pingtan thus joins Shanghai, Beijing and Macau in this year's calendar of the championship launched by Sro Asia in partnership with the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC).
The Pingtan track replaces Zhuhai, which was on the provisional calendar released in January, but could not confirm his event. This new date is also no coincidence, as the Sro GT Cup event will be part of the Pingtan-Macau cultural activities scheduled for June.
Pingtan's picturesque - which combines modern and coastal urban scenarios - remains widely unknown outside China. Inaugurated in 2022, the circuit has two strokes that incorporate existing public roads on the island of Pingtan, sections built from root and permanent boxes. Both SRO GT Cup races will take place in the 2.9 -kilometer circuit and 14 curves, already used by national championships such as China Endurance Championship (CEC) and the Chinese Formula 4 Championship.
Promising start
The 2025 Sro Cup season has spectacularly tore with 33 cars - GT4's largest grill ever gathered in Asia - to play two Formula 1 China Grand Prix Races last month. Integrated in the F1 official program, Chen Weian (Audi) and Lichao Han (Toyota) won the two races that will serve as the basis for the selection of competitors entitled to participate this year in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race.
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, which takes place at the end of the season, on the streets of Macau. The places will be assigned based on the classification after this second round, scheduled for Pingtan. In the dispute for a vacancy were in Shanghai six pilots of the MSAR: Kevin Leong Ian Veng, Miguel Lei, Cheng Tou Wong, Wai Ming Fok, Kim Hou Lao and Un Hous IP.
Charles enters the right foot
Still in the GT events, but in Australia, Macao pilot Charles Leong Hon Chio won the two races of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia inaugural journey in Sydney. The young rider of the territory, behind the wheel of SJM Theodore Racing's Lamborghini Huracán EVO2, has authored the two races played at Sydney Motorsport Park with authority, team with Irish Alex Denning.
Following a sensational season opening, the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia returns to the action next month, with the second round on the stage of the China Grand Prix, the International Shangoi Circuit, from May 16 to 18. After finishing second in 2024, Charles Leong is determined to win the title of the Italian brand competition in Asia in 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-04-09 23:47:39</pubDate></item></channel></rss>