<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Israel bombs Rafah alleging that Hamas attacked military unit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/israel-bombardeia-rafah-alegando-que-hamas-atacou-unidade-militar/</link><description>Israel launched a series of air strikes against the city of Rafah, in the Gaza Strip, after accusing Hamas of attacking a military engineering unit, security sources cited by the Israeli press said yesterday.
Pending an official statement from the Israel Defense Forces and the Islamist group Hamas, military sources confirmed to the Israeli website Walla and the Times of Israel that air and ground attacks had been carried out in Rafah, claiming that it was a response to an attack on an Israeli military excavator tasked with destroying the Islamist organization's tunnels.
Although there is still no official information about the existence of deaths or injuries, Israeli military sources told Israeli television that two alleged Hamas militants were killed. It is also unknown whether this crossfire could jeopardize the ceasefire that came into force on October 10, but the Israeli Minister of National Security, Itamar Ben Givr, has already urged the Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, to resume the offensive against the Gaza Strip.
“I ask the Prime Minister to order the Israel Defense Forces (IDF) to fully resume fighting in the Gaza Strip with all its personnel,” said the minister, who was convicted in the past for inciting hatred against Palestinians, vandalism and support for terrorism. According to a source from Hamas' armed wing, the group had launched an operation in Rafah to eliminate the leader of the rival militia, known as 'Popular Forces', Yasser Abu Shabab.
However, Israeli soldiers intervened to support Shabab, which resulted in crossfire and caused the Israeli excavator to explode. The United States warned on Saturday that it had “credible information” about an “imminent attack” by Hamas against Palestinian civilians, in a “clear violation” of the ceasefire.
Chaos installed
Yesterday morning, the Islamist group rejected the accusation and blamed Israel for arming and financing other militias, which, it said, carried out “murders, kidnappings, robberies of humanitarian aid trucks and robberies against civilians”.
According to Hamas, its members in Gaza are, “with broad civil and popular support”, pursuing these gangs and holding them accountable “according to clear legal mechanisms, to protect citizens and preserve public and private property”.
Just one day after the ceasefire, Hamas militants began cracking down on all clans and militias that allegedly collaborated with Israel during the past two years' war, including public executions of alleged collaborators, images of which went viral.
The ceasefire in Gaza – proposed by the United States and agreed between Israel and Hamas – has been in force since October 10, providing for three phases: the release of hostages, the disarmament of Hamas and the gradual reconstruction of the territory, under international supervision. The second stage, centered on “demilitarization”, remains the most controversial and the one that Israel considers essential to put an end to the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:52:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Takeaway | Request for worker protection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/takeaway-pedida-proteccao-de-trabalhadores/</link><description>Deputy Leong Hong Sai questions the Government about whether it has plans to legislate the status of workers on online food delivery platforms. The matter was raised by the deputy linked to the Residents, through a written interpellation published on Friday.
In the document, Leong points out as a problem the fact that distributors are considered “independent workers”, but they are nevertheless subject to complying with the employer's orders, as in a traditional employment relationship. “Currently, several online food and order delivery platforms in Macau define their workers as ‘independent workers’ or ‘partners’, thus excluding them from legal labor protections,” he accused. “It is understood that some platforms allocate orders through algorithms and implement incentive schemes, preventing platform workers from enjoying the autonomy typical of traditional independent work,” he added.
The deputy therefore asks the Executive to create a legal statute to ensure the labor protection of distributors. “Will authorities review existing regulations governing employment relationships to comprehensively regulate online food and parcel delivery platforms?” he asks. “Furthermore, will they make appropriate adjustments in response to changes in the labor market to promptly clarify the legal status, responsibilities and rights of both companies and platform workers?”, he asks.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:22:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Fengshen | Typhoon expected to pass 400km from Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/fengshen-tufao-devera-passar-a-400km-de-macau/</link><description>Tropical cyclone Fengshen is expected to pass around 400 kilometers south of Macau on Wednesday, according to the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate (DSMG). At that time, according to yesterday's forecasts, the tropical cyclone should gain strength and transform into a typhoon.
“Therefore, depending on the development of Fengshen and changes in wind strength in Macau, a Tropical Storm Signal will be issued from Monday night (today)”, it was pointed out. Since yesterday, it was also predicted that the wind would begin to intensify due to “a northeast monsoon”, and authorities believed that there would be a “significant increase, with the wind reaching levels 6 to 7 on the Beaufort Scale”.
Temperatures | Descent to 18 degrees
From today until Wednesday, temperatures are expected to drop to 18 degrees, according to information released yesterday by the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (DSMG). “Regarding the weather, precipitation is expected, with the minimum temperature dropping to around 18 degrees Celsius, between Monday and Wednesday (20 to 22)”, it was indicated.
"Due to the significant drop in temperatures next week, and the strong wind associated with cloudy weather with precipitation, the thermal sensation of cold will be lower than the actual temperature. DSMG urges the population to pay attention to the most recent meteorological information", it was added.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:31:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Agualusa says that a bad writer will never write a good book</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/agualusa-diz-que-mau-escritor-nunca-escrevera-bom-livro/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:34:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Caritas | More than 3,500 requests for help received by the end of September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/caritas-recebidos-mais-de-3-500-pedidos-de-ajuda-ate-fim-de-setembro/</link><description>The number of support requests shows a stabilization trend in recent years. And given the lack of “very serious” poverty problems, Cáritas Macau also extended its support program to Pakistan and Bangladesh
Cáritas Macau received 3,509 requests for support for the Food Bank by the end of September, the organization's secretary-general said yesterday, indicating that this year's final values ​​should not differ from those of 2024.
“We expect it [in 2025] to exceed four thousand, like last year”, noted Paul Pun Chi Meng to Lusa, pointing out that, in 2024, 4,936 requests reached the humanitarian organization, which, in turn, represents a drop of 2.5 percent compared to 2023 (5,065). In an annual comparison, the first nine months of 2025 present values ​​similar to those recorded in the same period of 2023 and 2024: 3,589 and 3,596, respectively.
Even so, there is a slight decline this year, which could be related to the “existence of other support resources” or “greater ease in applying for social housing”, noted Pun, implying that easier access to public housing could ease the bills at the end of the month.
The program, aimed at low-income people and financed by the authorities, foresees that the Bank's support will result in food aid for a period of ten weeks, with a second request being possible within 12 months. Among non-resident workers, highlighted Paul Pun, there is also a group that uses social assistance organizations. Last Saturday, close to a thousand people received support in the form of food baskets.
Aid in Pakistan and Bangladesh
The secretary general of Cáritas also explained that as Macau does not face “very serious poverty” problems, the organization is supporting disadvantaged families in Bangladesh and Pakistan, providing aid to 2,100 people. Last week, Pun returned from Sylhet, a city in northeastern Bangladesh that he has visited several times since 2023, the year in which Cáritas Macau became involved in a program to “improve the health and nutrition of disadvantaged children”.
With donations of around 15 thousand dollars per year, aid has already reached 400 people, said the person in charge. “We hope that, through training, in terms of care for newborns, mothers, they can achieve a better life”, pointed out the general secretary of Cáritas Macau, also noting that, on the table is the possibility of providing resources for the professional training of teenagers who dropped out of school.
About a month ago, Paul Pun was also in Lahore, the second largest city in Pakistan, with nearly 14 million inhabitants and which has been affected, in recent years, by several floods.
Cáritas Macau's assistance to the “Informal education and development of young people and women” program, with the transfer of up to 35 thousand dollars per year (around 30 thousand euros), has already touched the lives of 1,200 children and 500 teenagers in Lahore, according to the leader of the humanitarian organization.
"The children do not have schools [in these places]. They participate in this informal education program so that they have an opportunity to reach the standards and one day be able to enter school", he said. In addition to supporting the education of teenagers – “especially boys” – in areas such as IT, the program also includes skills training “by young women”.
To Lusa, Paul Pun said that international assistance from Cáritas Macau arrives “via several channels”, namely through donations and the organization Good Fortune Charity Shop, the social enterprise of Cáritas Macau, which collects donated goods for charitable sale.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:29:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice | Portugal may send new judges to Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/justica-portugal-pode-enviar-novos-juizes-para-macau/</link><description>Despite having prevented Carlos Carvalho from remaining in the territory and maintaining uncertainty about the future of Rui Ribeiro, who chose to return to Portugal, the Superior Council of the Judiciary of Portugal guarantees openness to sending new magistrates to the Macao SAR
The president of the Supreme Court of Justice (STJ) stated that Portugal is available, if Macau shows interest, in sending new judges. The statements were made at a time when a Portuguese magistrate is about to leave the Macao SAR. Judge Rui Ribeiro, of the Court of Second Instance, confirmed to Lusa, on the sidelines of a public event, that he will leave Macau at the end of October, bringing forward the end of the commission, which ended in May 2026.
The magistrate stressed that the Macau judicial authorities “did everything” to make him change his mind, but explained that he preferred to return to Portugal now given the uncertainty regarding a possible renewal of the special license by the Superior Council of Judiciary (CSM).
With the announced departure of Rui Ribeiro, only one Portuguese judge remains in the Macau courts: Jerónimo Alberto Gonçalves Santos, president of a collective court at the Base Judicial Court (TJB). The leader of the STJ, João Cura Mariano, who inherently also presides over the CSM, told journalists that, during a visit to Macau, he wanted to find out if the territory was interested in having Portuguese magistrates.
“We are going to try to see what they can really convey that is useful and whether they are necessary, because if they are necessary, new judges will come”, he assured the journalists.
João Cura Mariano said that this would be a “subject to discuss” in yesterday's meetings with the president of the Court of Final Instance (TUI), Song Man Lei, and with Sam Hou Fai, leader of the Macau Government and former president of the TUI. “I think it is very useful, because, being a former president of the court [Sam Hou Fai] he will be aware of the needs that exist”, said the Portuguese judge advisor.
National difficulties
But the president of the STJ highlighted that Portuguese justice is having “some difficulty in contributing judges”, due to the lack of qualified and experienced human resources. “Just now we removed a judge who had been here for many years and we needed him”, recalled João Cura Mariano.
In 2024, the CSM rejected the stay of Portuguese TJB judge Carlos Carvalho, who had been in Macau for 16 years and had been invited by the Independent Commission for the Nomination of Judges in the territory to continue for another two years. The council did not authorize the renewal of Carlos Carvalho's special license and promoted him to judge, with placement at the Court of Appeal.
Even so, João Cura Mariano assured that he was willing to help, “despite the difficulties that currently exist in Portugal in recruiting judges”. The president of the STJ highlighted the example of Timor-Leste, where there are currently “many Portuguese judges collaborating in the Timorese judicial system”, because “they are very necessary”.
The judge was in Macau to participate, on Sunday, in the 13th edition of the forum that brings together presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-speaking countries and territories.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:25:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Bridges | Advisor suggests tolls and generates chorus of criticism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/pontes-conselheiro-sugere-portagens-e-gera-coro-de-criticas/</link><description>On October 10th, Leong Chi Hang, member of the Consultative Council of Community Services of the Islands, suggested the introduction of toll payments on the four bridges that cross between the Macau peninsula and Taipa. The opinion sparked controversy on social media and even led a listener to call in to the morning show on Radio Macau's Chinese channel.
 
Councilor Leong Chi Hang, member of the Consultative Council for Community Services of the Islands, defended at a meeting of this body, on October 10th, that tolls should be paid on the four bridges that cross between the Macau peninsula and the islands.
This suggestion was made during the period of interventions before the agenda of the aforementioned organization, with Leong Chi Hang, who is also vice-president of the Taipa Community Development Promotion Association, arguing that it is necessary for the Government to improve and reform the bridge management system due to frequent traffic jams in these road infrastructures.
"I suggest that an electronic collection system be created with tolls on these four bridges, and the collection would be made according to different periods, vehicles. An additional fee could be added in times of greater circulation", he said.
According to Leong Chi Hang, the objective of charging tolls would be to balance the flow of vehicles on the four bridges by adjusting the toll charges, as for some people the increased costs of crossing the bridge by car may make them opt more for public transport. In this way, priority will be given to public transport and more environmentally friendly travel.
Fired fuse
This opinion was publicized on social media during the Advisory Council meeting, especially in Facebook groups, which generated a wave of critical opinions.
And the wave of protest did not stop on social media: on Friday a resident, surnamed Ma, called the morning program Forum Macau on the Chinese channel Radio Macau, criticizing this measure, arguing that, to alleviate the traffic situation on bridges, procedures for dealing with road accidents should be simplified.
"I don't think [charging tolls] is a viable suggestion, as bridges are always filled with traffic and an additional charge is still being advocated. Traffic jams often occur on bridges not due to an excess of cars, but rather due to the occurrence of road accidents. Why can't we simplify procedures similar to what happens in Mainland China?", he asked.
This listener argued that “if [a road accident] does not involve criminal proceedings, and it is enough to take photographs of the accident, the vehicles involved in the accident can be removed from the scene” more quickly.
Ma also complained about the fact that Macau continues to maintain an outdated system for dealing with road accidents, even though the territory has recently adopted digital solutions, such as the installation of video surveillance cameras, which end up not being well used to deal with this type of cases.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:24:08</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | André Cheong promises presidency to meet expectations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/al-andre-cheong-promete-presidencia-a-cumprir-expectativas/</link><description>At the beginning of the new legislature, deputies received “three expectations” from the Chief Executive, one of which involves “working together” with the Government, but also exercising law enforcement functions.
When performing the duties of president of the Legislative Assembly, André Cheong promises to keep in mind the Chief Executive's expectations for the work of the legislative body. The statements were made by the new president of the hemicycle, in an interview with TDM's Chinese-language channels.
"As president of the Legislative Assembly I feel that the weight of responsibility is greater. I will strictly comply with the provisions of the law and regulations to carry out my duties as president", stated the new president of the AL, quoted by Canal Macau. “At the same time, I will take into account the three expectations established by the Chief Executive for the new composition of the Legislative Assembly, leading the team well in legislative work and in the scope of supervision”, he added.
André Cheong was elected president of the AL on Friday and had the vote of all deputies, including his own. It was the first time, at least since 2019, that a deputy was unanimously elected president.
The president of the AL also intends to implement greater cooperation between the Government and the hemicycle's technicians. “For important law proposals related to the well-being of the population, the Government needs considerable preparation time”, he indicated. "We hope to encourage AL technical teams to get involved earlier in the preparatory phase of government departments. For example, preliminary technical discussions and exchanges can result in more fluid technical communication when these important bills are being analyzed by the Legislative Assembly", he pointed out.
Three desires
After the start of the new Legislature, last Thursday, the Chief Executive held a meeting with deputies. On this occasion, according to the official version, given that the meeting took place behind closed doors, Sam Hou Fai told the legislators that he has three expectations for the functioning of the hemicycle. The first involves “further enhancing the leadership role of the Legislative Assembly in political terms”, in what he explained as a role in promoting nationalism and maintaining harmony in the long term.
Secondly, he also asked deputies to “further enhance the role of the Legislative Assembly in drafting legislation and monitoring”, which he explained involved deputies “working together with the executive body” to create and review legislation considered key for the Executive, such as the diversification of the economy.
Finally, the AL was asked to be a “fundamental interlocutor” in collecting opinions from “public opinion”, while also indicating that it expected deputies to guide “society to form an environment for positive, objective and rational discussion” and “promote the broadest possible social consensus to support the Macao SAR Government”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:55:15</pubDate></item><item><title>São Januário | First artificial heart implanted in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/sao-januario-implantado-primeiro-coracao-artificial-em-macau/</link><description>The first surgery to implant an artificial heart was recently carried out at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ) of Health Services (SS), in collaboration with the cardiothoracic surgery team of the First Affiliated Hospital of Jinan University.
The procedure was carried out on a 68-year-old woman who suffered from terminal heart failure, and, according to a statement from the SS, “the condition presented was complex and the surgical intervention challenging”. It was “the first surgical procedure to implant a completely magnetically levitated artificial heart, developed autonomously in Mainland China”. Carrying out this surgery in the territory represents, for the authorities, “significant progress in cardiac surgery in Macau”.
For the SS, “the successful completion of the first artificial heart implant surgery in Macau represents a significant advance in the treatment of terminal heart failure in the region”, in addition to this technological advance “fills a significant gap in medical care, offering a viable and safe alternative for patients who are not eligible for heart transplantation or who cannot wait for a surgical intervention”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:53:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel bombs Rafah alleging that Hamas attacked military unit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/israel-bombardeia-rafah-alegando-que-hamas-atacou-unidade-militar/</link><description>Israel launched a series of air strikes against the city of Rafah, in the Gaza Strip, after accusing Hamas of attacking a military engineering unit, security sources cited by the Israeli press said yesterday.
Pending an official statement from the Israel Defense Forces and the Islamist group Hamas, military sources confirmed to the Israeli website Walla and the Times of Israel that air and ground attacks had been carried out in Rafah, claiming that it was a response to an attack on an Israeli military excavator tasked with destroying the Islamist organization's tunnels.
Although there is still no official information about the existence of deaths or injuries, Israeli military sources told Israeli television that two alleged Hamas militants were killed. It is also unknown whether this crossfire could jeopardize the ceasefire that came into force on October 10, but the Israeli Minister of National Security, Itamar Ben Givr, has already urged the Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, to resume the offensive against the Gaza Strip.
“I ask the Prime Minister to order the Israel Defense Forces (IDF) to fully resume fighting in the Gaza Strip with all its personnel,” said the minister, who was convicted in the past for inciting hatred against Palestinians, vandalism and support for terrorism. According to a source from Hamas' armed wing, the group had launched an operation in Rafah to eliminate the leader of the rival militia, known as 'Popular Forces', Yasser Abu Shabab.
However, Israeli soldiers intervened to support Shabab, which resulted in crossfire and caused the Israeli excavator to explode. The United States warned on Saturday that it had “credible information” about an “imminent attack” by Hamas against Palestinian civilians, in a “clear violation” of the ceasefire.
Chaos installed
Yesterday morning, the Islamist group rejected the accusation and blamed Israel for arming and financing other militias, which, it said, carried out “murders, kidnappings, robberies of humanitarian aid trucks and robberies against civilians”.
According to Hamas, its members in Gaza are, “with broad civil and popular support”, pursuing these gangs and holding them accountable “according to clear legal mechanisms, to protect citizens and preserve public and private property”.
Just one day after the ceasefire, Hamas militants began cracking down on all clans and militias that allegedly collaborated with Israel during the past two years' war, including public executions of alleged collaborators, images of which went viral.
The ceasefire in Gaza – proposed by the United States and agreed between Israel and Hamas – has been in force since October 10, providing for three phases: the release of hostages, the disarmament of Hamas and the gradual reconstruction of the territory, under international supervision. The second stage, centered on “demilitarization”, remains the most controversial and the one that Israel considers essential to put an end to the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:52:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Takeaway | Request for worker protection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/takeaway-pedida-proteccao-de-trabalhadores/</link><description>Deputy Leong Hong Sai questions the Government about whether it has plans to legislate the status of workers on online food delivery platforms. The matter was raised by the deputy linked to the Residents, through a written interpellation published on Friday.
In the document, Leong points out as a problem the fact that distributors are considered “independent workers”, but they are nevertheless subject to complying with the employer's orders, as in a traditional employment relationship. “Currently, several online food and order delivery platforms in Macau define their workers as ‘independent workers’ or ‘partners’, thus excluding them from legal labor protections,” he accused. “It is understood that some platforms allocate orders through algorithms and implement incentive schemes, preventing platform workers from enjoying the autonomy typical of traditional independent work,” he added.
The deputy therefore asks the Executive to create a legal statute to ensure the labor protection of distributors. “Will authorities review existing regulations governing employment relationships to comprehensively regulate online food and parcel delivery platforms?” he asks. “Furthermore, will they make appropriate adjustments in response to changes in the labor market to promptly clarify the legal status, responsibilities and rights of both companies and platform workers?”, he asks.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:22:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Fengshen | Typhoon expected to pass 400km from Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/fengshen-tufao-devera-passar-a-400km-de-macau/</link><description>Tropical cyclone Fengshen is expected to pass around 400 kilometers south of Macau on Wednesday, according to the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate (DSMG). At that time, according to yesterday's forecasts, the tropical cyclone should gain strength and transform into a typhoon.
“Therefore, depending on the development of Fengshen and changes in wind strength in Macau, a Tropical Storm Signal will be issued from Monday night (today)”, it was pointed out. Since yesterday, it was also predicted that the wind would begin to intensify due to “a northeast monsoon”, and authorities believed that there would be a “significant increase, with the wind reaching levels 6 to 7 on the Beaufort Scale”.
Temperatures | Descent to 18 degrees
From today until Wednesday, temperatures are expected to drop to 18 degrees, according to information released yesterday by the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (DSMG). “Regarding the weather, precipitation is expected, with the minimum temperature dropping to around 18 degrees Celsius, between Monday and Wednesday (20 to 22)”, it was indicated.
"Due to the significant drop in temperatures next week, and the strong wind associated with cloudy weather with precipitation, the thermal sensation of cold will be lower than the actual temperature. DSMG urges the population to pay attention to the most recent meteorological information", it was added.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:31:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Agualusa says that a bad writer will never write a good book</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/agualusa-diz-que-mau-escritor-nunca-escrevera-bom-livro/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:34:42</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM | Creative Macau hosts exhibition with student works</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/upm-creative-macau-acolhe-mostra-com-trabalhos-dos-alunos/</link><description>The Creative Macau gallery hosts, until November 8th, the exhibition “Prototype – Exhibition of Works by Students of the Degree in Media Arts”, from the Macau Polytechnic University. There are 30 works by more than 20 students who attend this course and who show all their creativity here
Creative Macau hosts a new exhibition composed of works of art by students from the Macau Polytechnic University. This is “Prototype” – Exhibition of Works by Students of the Degree Course in Media Arts at the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) 2025″, and can be seen until November 8th, with free entry.
The exhibition presents more than 30 works of art by around 20 students who attend the degree program at UPM, with the public being able to see “a curated selection of notable works by students from the first to the third year” of the aforementioned course, explains a note from Creative Macau.
You will be able to see a “diversity of work, ranging from interactive digital experiences to physical creations, reflecting the program's balanced emphasis on both theoretical foundations and practical application”. Thus, “through practical work in various courses, students acquired proficiency in a wide range of design tools and production techniques, transforming abstract ideas into fully realized works.”
“Important milestone”
Creative Macau further describes that this exhibition, and the opportunity that students have to show the results of their work, “constitutes an important milestone in their academic journey”. “By sharing these creations with the public, we hope to stimulate a broader dialogue and exchange about media arts, emerging technologies and the cultural future they continue to shape”, it is further stated.
Creative Macau – Creative Industries Center was founded in 2003 and has been managed by the Macau Institute of European Studies. Over the years, Creative Macau has supported projects and artistic works in 12 areas of the creative industries, including advertising, architecture, design, fashion or crafts. “Its objective is to help these industries reach their full economic potential, adding value and promoting recognition in society”, it is further described.
In the case of the degree in Media Arts at UPM, the objective is to “train high-quality media arts professionals through a curriculum that emphasizes multidisciplinary learning in the areas of arts, design and technology”. The aim here is that “students develop communication skills, international vision, intercultural understanding and innovative thinking, while at the same time acquiring knowledge and skills in media arts in the areas of interaction in games, technological art and video storytelling”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:33:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan's Liberal Party close to securing new coalition deal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/partido-liberal-do-japao-perto-de-garantir-novo-acordo-de-coligacao/</link><description>The Liberal Democratic Party (PLD), in power in Japan, is close to forming a government coalition, which would leave leader Sanae Takaichi just two deputies away from securing election as prime minister.
The main Japanese media reported yesterday that the agreement with the Innovation Party of Japan (Ishin) could be closed as early as Monday, the day before parliament meets to choose Shigeru Ishiba's successor. The outgoing prime minister resigned in September from the leadership of the Government and the PLD, which, in primaries held at the beginning of October, chose the conservative and nationalist Takaichi as the candidate to be the first woman to lead Japan.
According to the Japanese news agency Kyodo, the PLD and Ishin have agreed to form a coalition without the opposition party guaranteeing seats in the new Government. In return, the PLD would commit to complying with a series of proposals, including reducing the number of deputies, eliminating the tax on food consumption and eliminating political donations from companies and organizations. Today, a final meeting with the PLD is expected.
Fragile leadership
The newspaper reported that the opposition party is reluctant to occupy positions in Takaichi's possible government and prefers to first ensure that the new PLD leader complies with the terms of the agreement. If elected, the conservative would lead one of the weakest governments in Japan's political history, with a clear minority in both chambers of parliament, which would force her to cooperate with the opposition to pass any law.
Ishin's support is essential for Takaichi, especially after the Buddhist party Komeito, with which the PLD was allied for 26 years, abandoned the ruling coalition. The centrist Komeito withdrew from the alliance due to published news about alleged secret PLD funds, having also criticized Sanae Takaichi due to supposed changes in the leader's stance regarding visits to Yasukuni.
Diplomatic fears
Takaichi, known for her hard-line stance towards China, has visited the Shinto shrine numerous times in the past, especially when she was minister, considered a symbol of the country's militaristic past. But, on Friday, on the first day of the Yasukuni Autumn Festival, 64 years old, he was absent and sent only one offering, because, according to Japanese media, he feared that a visit could upset neighboring countries.
Previous visits by senior Japanese officials to the shrine have angered Beijing and Seoul. China and the Korean peninsula were the scene of atrocities committed by the Japanese military in the first half of the 20th century. No sitting Japanese prime minister has visited the shrine in Tokyo since 2013, when Shinzo Abe's visit sparked fury among neighboring countries and rebukes from the United States.
The shrine pays tribute to the approximately 2.5 million Japanese soldiers killed in combat, but also to Japanese officers and politicians convicted of war crimes by an international tribunal after World War II. The LDP has governed Japan almost permanently since 1955, despite frequent leadership changes.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:50:19</pubDate></item><item><title>UM joins the UNESCO Chair dedicated to Portuguese heritage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/um-junta-se-a-catedra-unesco-dedicada-ao-patrimonio-portugues/</link><description>The University of Macau (UM) announced its membership of the UNESCO Chair in Intercultural Dialogue on Heritage of Portuguese Influence, a project launched by the University of Coimbra (UC).
Num comunicado divulgado na sexta-feira à noite, a UM defendeu que a entrada no projecto “imprime uma nova dinâmica no desenvolvimento da investigação sobre património cultural” em Macau. The collaboration with UC will promote “international academic exchange in Macau”, as well as strengthen “ties” with higher education institutions in Portuguese-speaking countries, UM added.
The institution's formal accession to the UNESCO Chair took place in a ceremony organized by the two institutions in Macau, on Wednesday, with the presence of Rui Martins, vice-rector of UM, and João Nuno Calvão da Silva, vice-rector of UC. Rui Martins argued that UM's entry “will further enrich the academic resources and cultural perspective” of the already “wide network of partners” established by the UNESCO Chair.
The UC created the project in 2018, to explore “the multicultural results resulting from the influence of Portuguese-speaking culture”, such as architecture, arts, language, literature, landscape and urbanism, said the statement. At the time, the UNESCO Chair already involved fifty teachers and researchers in a partnership with several European, Brazilian and African institutions.
Comprehensive effort
The list included the University of Bologna Studies (Italy), the Universidade Federal Fluminense (Brazil), the universities Eduardo Mondlane and Lúrio (Mozambique), the University Paris Nanterre (France) and MEIA – Mindelo Escola Internacional de Arte (Cape Verde).
Rui Martins, a Portuguese academic who has long lived in Macau, highlighted that the UNESCO Chair is an international project “that integrates research, training and cooperation for development”. In the case of UM, the Department of Integrated Resorts and Tourism Management of the Faculty of Business Management will “actively demonstrate its professional competence” in research into cultural heritage, guaranteed Martins.
The UNESCO Chair is coordinated by researcher Walter Rossa, who on Wednesday spoke about “the political significance” of research on cultural heritage within the organization's policies.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Sun Yang, who lived in the time of Spring and Autumn (771-476 BC) because he was considered an exemplary judge in choosing a good horse, earned the honorific title of Bole from a king, «the happy eldest» and his praised ability to choose gave rise to the popular saying that says that «good horses capable of running a thousand li in a day (qianlima) are many, a Bole is rare». This would soon be adopted as a metaphor for all areas where it was necessary or vital to know how to choose talent, especially hidden talent such as in the selection of government employees.
But this skill, specifically referring to horses, was especially valued in the time of the dynasty founded by the Mongol knights of the Yuan. The most notable painters of that time, such as Zhao Mengfu, portrayed several of the dynasty's most famous horses. And a court painter around the year 1342 showed, with indifference, a horse offered to the emperor, as was customary in the tax system with foreign countries, but which would remain as unexpected visual proof of the stay in the territory of a mission headed by the Florentine Franciscan Giovanni de Marignolli (c. 1290- 1358) who had arrived in Khanbaliq (present-day Beijing) as legate of the Pope in 1339-40, following the unprecedented reception of Giovanni da Montecorvino OFM (1247-1328) at the Yuan court, which even allowed him to build churches in the streets of the capital.
This horizontal scroll made only in ink, a copy of which was probably made in the Ming dynasty and is in the Palace Museum in Beijing, is attributed to the court painter Zhou Lang, who created in another painting an unforgettable portrait of a poet whose memory is largely due to the testimony of a contemporary capable of recognizing her unique talent.
Zhou Lang made the portrait of Du Qiuniang, «the Autumn Maiden» (791-835), with an ancient flute in his hands in a figurative style respecting the «spirit of the ancients» as Zhao Mengfu wanted, and on the model of the ladies of the Tang dynasty. From the portrait in this horizontal scroll (ink and color on silk, 32.3 x 285 cm in the Palace Museum in Beijing) was an exhortation to a prince, which would last and can be translated as: «I ask you, Lord: do not be dazzled / by the lives of those who carry gold / in the seams of their dresses/ My advice, Lord, / is that your green years / be well lived. / Pick the flowers when they bloom, / not when they are already falling, / Don’t wait until there are no longer / flowers on the broken branches.”
It is known about the author that she was educated in the arts of dance and music and impressed a general who was defeated by an emperor and took her to his court and, following political conflicts, returned to her native Nanking. And it was there that, aged and impoverished, the poet Du Mu (803-52) found her, who wrote a poem about her and her brief biography.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Death | António Coelho dies aged 77, but leaves a legacy in Portuguese gastronomy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/14/obito-antonio-coelho-morre-com-77-anos-mas-deixa-legado-na-gastronomia-portuguesa/</link><description>The founder of Restaurante António died on Sunday in Macau, due to heart problems. Behind him, he leaves a mark and an innovative concept for promoting Portuguese food in Asia
A father, a friend and one of the great ambassadors of Portuguese gastronomy in Asia. Chef António Coelho died on Sunday, aged 77, due to heart problems, but leaves behind a professional career spanning almost 40 years and an influence that can be felt in several restaurants and Portuguese food chefs in Macau.
Born in Portugal in 1948, António Coelho's first contact with Macau took place in 1970, when he had to complete his four-year mandatory military service. After two years, the land remained in his memory, but the future chef chose to return to Europe.
In Portugal, he started working at Social Security, later moving to a clinical analysis laboratory. It was in this area that he developed his taste for gastronomy, not through work, but through various lunches and dinners in different restaurants. Increasingly interested in cooking, António decided to take a job, in 1984, in a restaurant, where he admitted to having learned to cook, according to an interview with the South China Morning Post newspaper, in 2018.
The first years of António Coelho's new career were spent in Portugal, where he performed different roles as manager-administrator of the Botequim do Rei restaurant or director of the catering department at the Grande Hotel da Curia. In 1996, he had his first international experience, as director of the restaurant department at the Hotel Trópico, in Cape Verde. The experience lasts one year.
Creating a legacy
Returning to Macau in 1997, António worked for 10 years in different spaces, such as the restaurants Frol de la Mar, Lusitano, Lisbon, and also had a brief stay in Hong Kong, in 2002, at Restaurante Inn. However, the decisive step towards his affirmation as one of the most influential chefs of Portuguese gastronomy in Asia came in 2007, with the opening of Restaurante António.
And the success that followed was not the result of chance, as said by Edgar Rodrigues, a chef who came to Macau to work on the launch of the project: “The success was based on the recipes, the quality of the food, but also the very professionalism”, says Edgar Rodrigues, to HM. "He was very attentive to his customers. If there was an order for clams à bolhão pato, he would have different recipes adapted to the nationality. For example, Koreans don't like coriander, the recipe for them didn't have coriander. Chinese customers like little salt, they were served with little salt, and locals like the more traditional recipe. In a single dish there were several ways of cooking, just to satisfy different customers", he recalls.
Cristiano Tavares, currently chef at the Macalhau restaurant, also came to Macau to work at the António Restaurant. He believes that the chef found a position for Portuguese food that still influences other restaurants today. “I think his success was due to his way of being, he was a politically correct person, he had a way of working that pleased both Chinese, Korean and Japanese tourists”, explained Cristiano Tavares, to HM. "We were a street restaurant with four or five cooks. He managed to do what many large restaurants still cannot do today. Nowadays there are many restaurants with Portuguese food that open in Macau, but follow the example of what he did", he considered.
Quality and spectacle
In addition to the food, Restaurante António customers were seduced by the “show”. This is the vision of Marcelino Marques, António's friend and musician who for several years livened up the space's nights, with traditional Portuguese music.
"The quality of the food made the space popular. He took great care in choosing the food and drinks served. He went to Portugal to choose wines from various regions, such as Douro or Alentejo, all of high quality, which were bottled under the António brand. People knew they weren't going to pay little, not that it was a space with luxury prices, it wasn't, but the quantity served wasn't small", recalled Marcelino Marques.
However, the musician believes that the success was also due to a concept in which the meal was also a spectacle: "People liked listening to Portuguese music, but also being with António. He was an affable, big person and appeared in that white jacket with the flags of Portugal, China and Macau and people liked his presence and asked him to take photographs", he says. "He also opened a bottle of champagne with a sword. He did a whole ceremony and people really liked it. It was a spectacle and a party to see the cork flying out of the bottle. It worked well", he recalled.
Marcelino Marques recalls that the food and the show made the restaurant very famous, especially among Japanese, Korean and Hong Kong tourists. The musician reveals that Japanese tourists booked days in advance. And this factor also contributed to the fact that António offered a glass of port wine at the end of the meal, which also led to the recognition of the Port Wine Confraternity.
The success of Restaurante António led the chef to sell the space to an investment fund, becoming an ambassador for the space. The break with the fund happened in 2020, when he was fired without just cause. The case ended up in court, with António winning the case. In recent years, António took on the position of executive chef at Angela’s Café and Lounge, at the Hotel Lisboeta.
A father, a friend
Due to his work in Macau, António was distinguished, in 2013, by the Macao SAR Government with the MSAR Tourist Merit Medal. Also in 2015, he received the merit medal for Portuguese communities from the Portuguese Government. However, for those who worked with him the most important thing was the relationship that went beyond the strictly professional field.
"He had a big impact on Macau and for me he was like a second father. When I came to Macau I didn't have an easy life and he always held my hand", confessed Rodrigues. "He was always a person who was there for me. And I always saw him as a man of iron. In everything he did, there was a great will", he pointed out.
This is a feeling shared by Cristiano Tavares. "António is my father in Macau. He worked until the last day, always with seriousness, honesty and integrity. He is an example for all the chefs in this area", he said.
For Marcelino Marques, António's death is the loss of a friend. "António was the person who welcomed me to Macau and was capable of doing the same to everyone. He was strict and demanding, but he was an excellent person", he described. "Everyone knew him. He was an affable person and received people like no one else", he added.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Chemistry | Nobel Prize for the development of metal-organic structures</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/quimica-nobel-para-o-desenvolvimento-de-estruturas-metalorganicas/</link><description>The Nobel Prize in Chemistry was awarded to Susumu Kitagawa, from Kyoto University, Richard Robson, from the University of Melbourne, and Omar M. Yaghi, from the University of California, “for the development of metal-organic structures”, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences announced yesterday.
Susumu Kitagawa, Richard Robson and Omar Yaghi have developed a new form of molecular architecture – metal-organic frameworks – that can be used to collect water from desert air, capture carbon dioxide, store toxic gases or catalyze chemical reactions.
The three laureates created molecular constructs with large spaces through which gases and other chemicals could flow. The president of the Nobel Committee for Chemistry, Heiner Linque, highlighted precisely the fact that these “metal-organic structures have enormous potential, bringing previously unforeseen opportunities for personalized materials with new functions”.
The research that led to the discovery of this new form of molecular architecture began nearly four decades ago, in 1989, when Richard Robson tested the use of the inherent properties of atoms by combining positively charged copper ions with a four-armed molecule.
When combined, they bonded "to form a spacious, well-ordered crystal. It was like a diamond filled with countless cavities," the academy explains. Robson immediately realized the potential of his molecular construction, but it was still unstable and crumbled easily. It was chemists Susumu Kitagawa and Omar Yaghi who managed to provide a solid foundation for this construction method.
Notable applications
Following the discoveries of the three laureates, chemists built tens of thousands of different MOFs. Some of them could contribute to solving some of humanity's biggest challenges, with applications including breaking down traces of pharmaceuticals in the environment, capturing carbon dioxide or collecting water from desert air.
The discovery also allows the separation of perfluoroalkylated and polyfluoroalkylated substances (PFAS) from water. PFAS are a group of synthetic chemical compounds known as “forever chemicals” due to their extreme persistence in the environment and in the human body.
PFAS are used in a wide range of industrial and household products, such as stain- and water-resistant textiles, food packaging, non-stick cookware and firefighting foams. Its accumulation in the environment and potential health risks, including liver damage and other problems, have led to concerns and a search for safer alternatives.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:41:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Trump was the main disseminator of disinformation in the USA in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/09/estudo-trump-foi-principal-disseminador-de-desinformacao-nos-eua-em-2024/</link><description>North American President Donald Trump was the main disseminator of disinformation in the United States of America (USA) in 2024, concluded a study by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ). “US President Donald Trump was the dominant source and distributor of disinformation” in 2024, say the authors of the study “Disarming Disinformation: United States”.
The study highlights that Trump has drawn on the functions of domestic political forces, rather than foreign state actors, as the main source of disinformation narratives in US political discourse. Furthermore, the existence of WhatsApp groups and other closed digital spaces often act as “information cocoons” that encourage rumors and other forms of misinformation.
In this way, "the viral spread of misinformation and the strategic attack on journalists have emerged as interconnected threats to democracy. In an era of increasing authoritarianism and democratic backsliding, falsehoods are often used as a weapon by state actors to influence public opinion, undermine journalism and intimidate journalists."
The study authors state that these factors are increasingly the North American reality, with Donald Trump “promulgating manifestly false narratives” in recent years.
“The American media faces a profound information crisis, at a time of repression of freedom of expression”, the study reads. In this sense, trust in the mainstream press continues to decline in a climate of increasing attacks on the media by the Trump Government.
The study published by the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ) was based on the analysis of 10,000 news and media publications during 2024, as well as a survey of 1,020 Americans.</description><pubDate>2025-10-09 00:38:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuts leave 13.7 million people at risk of extreme hunger</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/16/cortes-levam-137-milhoes-de-pessoas-a-correr-risco-de-fome-extrema/</link><description>Cuts in humanitarian aid funding could expose up to 13.7 million people to extreme hunger around the world, the World Food Program (WFP) warned yesterday. “The humanitarian aid system is under severe pressure as partners withdraw from frontline areas, creating a void,” the Rome-based agency said in a new report titled “A lifebuoy in danger.”
The UN agency said that six of its operations – in Afghanistan, the Democratic Republic of Congo, Haiti, Somalia, South Sudan and Sudan – are “facing major disruptions, which will only worsen”. WFP warned that its financing “has never been so challenging”, anticipating “a 40 percent drop” in 2025, “which will translate into a projected budget of US$6.4 billion, compared to US$10 billion in 2024”.
The report does not name any countries, but points to a study published in the medical journal The Lancet, which found that 14 million additional deaths worldwide from disease, nutritional deficiencies and maternal and perinatal conditions could occur by 2030 as a result of cuts in US humanitarian aid alone.
Returns and records
Since US President Donald Trump's return to the White House, Washington has announced massive cuts in its foreign aid, dealing a huge blow to humanitarian operations around the world. "Program coverage has been significantly reduced and rations cut. Vital assistance to families in food disaster situations [Phase 5 of the Integrated Food Security Phase Classification/IPC] is threatened, while preparedness for future impacts has significantly decreased," warns WFP.
Globally, “WFP estimates that its funding gaps could push 10.5 to 13.7 million people currently in acute food insecurity (IPC Phase 3) into a humanitarian emergency (IPC Phase 4),” the organization added. The UN agency said global hunger has now reached record levels, with 319 million people facing acute food insecurity — including 44 million at emergency levels.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 02:52:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Scientists ‘reduce’ the age of the Egyptian temple of Karnak, in Egypt</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/08/cientistas-reduzem-idade-do-templo-egipcio-de-karnak-no-egipto/</link><description>Researchers have carried out the most comprehensive geoarchaeological study of the Karnak temple, near Luxor, and revealed suggestive links to ancient Egyptian mythology and new data about the interaction between the complex's riverine landscape and the people who occupied the site during its almost 3,000 years of use.
The results of the investigation were published on Monday in Antiquity magazine, reported the Efe news agency. Researchers from the University of Southampton, in the United Kingdom, and Uppsala University, in Sweden, participated in the study. Up to 61 sediment samples from the interior and surroundings of the temple and thousands of ceramic fragments found in the Karnak complex, located 500 meters east of the current Nile River, near Luxor, in the ancient Egyptian religious capital of Thebes, were analyzed.
The researchers mapped how the landscape around the site changed throughout its history and found that, before 2520 BC, the site could not have been suitable for permanent occupation due to periodic flooding caused by the Nile's strong currents. Therefore, they placed the earliest occupation at Karnak during the Old Kingdom (between 2591 and 2152 BC).
Pottery fragments found at the site corroborate this discovery, with the oldest dating between 2305 and 1980 BC. Therefore, the conclusions of this international team of researchers provide new evidence about the age of Karnak, which has been hotly debated in archaeological circles for decades.
The origin of everything
The ground on which the temple was founded was formed when river channels advanced west and east, creating an island of high ground in what is now the east-southeast region of the site. This emerging island laid the foundation for the occupation and initial construction of Karnak.
Over the following centuries and millennia, the river channels on both sides of the site diverged further, creating more space for the development of the temple complex, as researchers have now confirmed. This new understanding of the temple's landscape bears striking similarities to an ancient Egyptian creation myth, leading the team to believe that the decision to locate the temple there may have been related to the religious views of its inhabitants.
Ancient Egyptian texts from the Old Kingdom indicate that the 'Creator God' manifested himself as high ground emerging from the lake, and researchers have found that the island where Karnak was founded is the only known area of ​​high ground surrounded by water in the region.
Thus, archaeologists have suggested that the Theban elites chose the location of Karnak to be the abode of a new form of 'Creator God', alluding to Amun-Ra, the supreme god of ancient Egypt, since the location fit perfectly into the mythological setting of the highlands that emerged from the surrounding waters as the origin of the formation of the Universe.</description><pubDate>2025-10-08 17:22:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics | Nobel Prize for Macroscopic Quantum Mechanical Tunneling</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/07/fisica-nobel-para-tunelamento-mecanico-quantico-macroscopico/</link><description>The Nobel Prize in Physics was awarded to John Clarke, Michel H. Devoret and John M. Martinis “for the discovery of macroscopic quantum mechanical tunneling and the quantization of energy in an electrical circuit”, announced yesterday the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences.
"An important question in physics is the maximum size of a system capable of demonstrating the effects of quantum mechanics. This year's Nobel Prize laureates carried out experiments with an electrical circuit in which they demonstrated both quantum tunneling and quantized energy levels in a system large enough to be held in the hand", explains the Swedish Academy of Sciences in a statement published on its website.
The British John Clarke carried out his research at the University of California, Berkeley, USA; the American John Martinis at the University of California, Santa Barbara; and the Frenchman Michel Devoret at Yale University and also in California, Santa Barbara.
According to academia, quantum mechanics allows a particle to directly cross a barrier, through a process called tunneling. When a large number of particles are involved, quantum effects usually become negligible. The experiments of the now distinguished scientists demonstrated that quantum properties can be made concrete on a macroscopic scale.
"It is wonderful to be able to celebrate the way in which quantum mechanics, more than a century old, continues to offer new surprises. It is also extremely useful, as it is the basis of all digital technology", said the president of the Nobel Committee for Physics, Olle Eriksson, quoted in the statement.
The Swedish academy says that transistors in computer microchips are an example of consolidated quantum technology. The scientists today awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics share a prize of 11 million Swedish kronor (almost one million euros).</description><pubDate>2025-10-07 23:15:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Linguistics | Published study based on a trip to Macau in the 19th century</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/03/linguistica-publicado-estudo-baseado-numa-viagem-a-macau-no-seculo-xix/</link><description>Academic Anabela Leal de Barros has just published a linguistic study that focuses on the trip of Father Miranda e Oliveira, linked to the Congregation of the Mission, to Macau in 1825. With touches of history, details are revealed about the Portuguese of the time and of Macau. The book will be presented at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center next Wednesday
 
“Journey from Lisbon to Macau – 1825” is the title of the most recent work published by Grão-Falar, written by University of Minho academic Anabela Leal de Barros.
The book makes a critical and interpretative analysis of the Portuguese of the time left in the manuscript of parish priest José Joaquim de Miranda e Oliveira, priest of the Congregation of the Mission. This documentation is kept by the Braga District Archive. However, the work does not just explore the Portuguese of the time, revealing other historical details of Macau, Asia and a sea voyage.
As Anabela Leal de Barros told HM, the work is “as faithful as possible to the spelling of the manuscript”, until now practically unknown.
In this travel diary, Father Miranda e Oliveira “reveals enormous curiosity about all the news and shares with us their names in the languages ​​of the world in which they were baptized, starting with ours”.
This is how he explains situations such as “seasickness, a reality that was still relatively unknown and highly invasive on boats” in those times. The priest named or defined “the mangalhões, the porpoises, the caravels, the black-eyed peas, the flies, the albacores — all sorts of birds and fish that were admired, fished or tasted throughout the trip”, or even the “meteorological phenomena with local names – cacimba, samatra, typhoon”. There are also details about “cultural habits such as the masca, buio in Indonesian; the Philippine seges, the berloches, and the ruling class of the camisolas, as well as the sômas, Chinese vessels”.
The vessel left Lisbon in April 1825 and spent time in the Philippines, arriving in Macau on October 23rd. The arrival “to the island of Caó” and the following day “to Colégio de S. José” is described, to “a city with ‘a magnificent port of commerce’, located ‘on a very pleasant peninsula’, with ‘good waters’ and ‘famous European-style buildings'”.
Linguistic varieties
In the work published by Grão-Falar there are, for example, “rich stories such as that of Orvalhadas de S. João, Caldeirão de Frei Junípero or the habit of seafarers shouting ‘Refresca S. Lourenço!’ so that the wind blows, this being the meaning here of ‘refresh’”.
There are also “allusions to the linguistic variety itself”, as “at various times there is reference to communication with foreigners carried out in Latin, in Indonesian-Dutch and Filipino-Spanish territory; the private teaching of English in the Philippines by members of the Congregation of the Mission; the little knowledge and use of Spanish, even in Manila, and the variation of Tagalog itself, a language in which the priest is concerned about recording the Hail Mary.”
Before arriving at this travel report, Anabela Leal de Barros was already in the intricacies of investigating this type of manuscripts, coming across the story of another priest, “the greatest Portuguese sinologist, Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, who had traveled from the same house as Rilhafoles of the Congregation of the Mission to Macau in 1812”.
According to the author, this parish priest “dedicated the last twenty-nine years of his life to the mission of evangelization in China, and in particular to the research and teaching of Chinese at the Colégio de S. José in Macau”. In his entire life, “this Trás-os-Montes native wrote more than five thousand pages of grammars and dictionaries in Portuguese, Latin and Chinese, expressly dedicated to his students at the College, seven printed in his typography and at least two manuscripts”.
Then, in 2017, António Lázaro, from the History Department of the University of Minho, and director of the Confúcio Institute, made available to Anabela Leal de Barros “a list of references to manuscripts from the Braga District Archive about Macau and China”. A “journey” began, which culminated in the publication of this study.
“This book is the first result of a project of mine to edit and study unpublished travel literature manuscripts whose main objective is exactly this: to contribute to the appreciation and consolidation of the micro-history of the Discoveries and the memory of history, between the 15th and 19th centuries”.
Accompanied on the trip
José Joaquim de Miranda e Oliveira took around seven months to arrive in Macau, leaving Lisbon on April 1, 1825, and arriving in Oriente on October 24 of the same year. He left on the ship Vasco da Gama with three other priests from the congregation: João da França de Castro e Moura, Jerónimo José da Mata and José́ Ferreira da Silva.
According to Anabela Leal de Barros, “the manuscript does not appear to have been cleaned by the author himself, given the type of spelling variations and typos and amendments it presents”, having probably been “translated, to safeguard copies, by a Macanese member of the College, since Macau Portuguese, in the 19th century, had characteristics compatible with certain traits, strange in a priest arrived from Portugal, even how young.”
This travel diary “ends on the very day of arrival in Macau, with a very brief presentation of the city and the school, making clear the Catholic perspective of the time in relation to the Chinese cult of ancestors and without failing to draw attention to the mere five thousand Christians among the 40 to 50 thousand inhabitants of the city”.
Political hostilities
José Joaquim de Miranda e Oliveira describes how the bishop of Macau did not receive the delegation, which is “enough to lead us to the hostile context in which the Lazarists, defenders of liberalism, found themselves, which had led Joaquim Afonso Gonçalves, a few years earlier, to take refuge in the Philippines, with the school missing two of its teachers”.
Furthermore, “along the journey the priest does not fail to narrate all the moments in which he carries out his daily mission, with the administration of the sacraments, the prayer of responsos and the celebration of masses, but above all he notes the notable lack of priests who reveal the Christianized peoples, particularly in Batavia, now Jakarta, where the community of Portuguese origin, of more than a thousand people, had only an old priest.”
These reports also reveal the concern to “remember the first French martyrs of the Congregation in the attempt to evangelize Madagascar and to report the presence of friars and priests from the different congregations, from Cape Verde to the Philippines, where they are recognized as more important for the solidity of Spanish rule than its army”.
According to Anabela Leal de Barros, the report also alluded, in Java, “to the Lutherans and Mohammedans, as well as to the religions of China and, in Manila, to the persecution of Christians (referring to the ‘dinner’, that is, lunch with a Chinese Christian, ‘and as such persecuted’)”.
Miranda and Oliveira had “a very diplomatic and convivial conduct, ensuring the establishment and maintenance of cordial relations between the various orders and also with the governors and foreign powers present, from the Dutch to the Spanish, who visited everywhere”.
An ongoing project
In those years, it was a dangerous adventure to travel by boat, facing “anthropogenic peoples, piracy, diseases on ships and epidemics”, a “perfectly cinematic vision” already described in Os Lusíadas, by Luís de Camões. Those who embarked on these trips also found themselves alone, “individually and on a small ship little more than a walnut shell, facing an endless sea, for months, at times when it was common for several passengers not to reach their destination, or for not even one ship from a full squadron to return”.
In Miranda and Oliveira's report, “there is no great news” compared to previous reports, but “we are aware of the main difficulties of sea voyages to Asia in the 19th century: the rocks that existed even before the Torre de Belém, which caused many shipwrecks; and seasickness, which even deserves a definition for the many readers who had never set foot on a boat, and to which the captain's face advising the sick ladies going up to the awning and working, as it was the best medicine”.
There is also “the episode of the man falling overboard from the plow that accompanied them on part of the trip, which they were unable to save — a death to which everyone was so exposed, as the narrator refers”. Another potential misfortune in trips of this type also stands out, “the encounter with ships that, not immediately raising any flag, or raising it without giving true confidence, immediately led to the decision to light the hills and open fire, which well reflects the dimension of piracy and the fears it imposed”.
Essentially, “the main character of sea voyages was the wind”, which led the still “young priest” to “evoke the Camonian verses of the storm twice”.
After arriving in Macau, Miranda e Oliveira left for his post in Nanking, “on a journey comparatively longer than the first, received by the Christians with difficulty and secretly”. “In the face of persecution” he ended up succumbing “to the dangers and illnesses of the mainland, at the age of 31, far from all his confreres, on November 1, 1828, just two years after having described the difficult farewell to his spiritual family, in Lisbon”. “His traveling companions had more longevity, one of whom would become Bishop of Macau and the other of Beijing and Porto”, highlights Anabela Leal de Barros.</description><pubDate>2025-10-03 01:39:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Bridges | Advisor suggests tolls and generates chorus of criticism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/pontes-conselheiro-sugere-portagens-e-gera-coro-de-criticas/</link><description>On October 10th, Leong Chi Hang, member of the Consultative Council of Community Services of the Islands, suggested the introduction of toll payments on the four bridges that cross between the Macau peninsula and Taipa. The opinion sparked controversy on social media and even led a listener to call in to the morning show on Radio Macau's Chinese channel.
 
Councilor Leong Chi Hang, member of the Consultative Council for Community Services of the Islands, defended at a meeting of this body, on October 10th, that tolls should be paid on the four bridges that cross between the Macau peninsula and the islands.
This suggestion was made during the period of interventions before the agenda of the aforementioned organization, with Leong Chi Hang, who is also vice-president of the Taipa Community Development Promotion Association, arguing that it is necessary for the Government to improve and reform the bridge management system due to frequent traffic jams in these road infrastructures.
"I suggest that an electronic collection system be created with tolls on these four bridges, and the collection would be made according to different periods, vehicles. An additional fee could be added in times of greater circulation", he said.
According to Leong Chi Hang, the objective of charging tolls would be to balance the flow of vehicles on the four bridges by adjusting the toll charges, as for some people the increased costs of crossing the bridge by car may make them opt more for public transport. In this way, priority will be given to public transport and more environmentally friendly travel.
Fired fuse
This opinion was publicized on social media during the Advisory Council meeting, especially in Facebook groups, which generated a wave of critical opinions.
And the wave of protest did not stop on social media: on Friday a resident, surnamed Ma, called the morning program Forum Macau on the Chinese channel Radio Macau, criticizing this measure, arguing that, to alleviate the traffic situation on bridges, procedures for dealing with road accidents should be simplified.
"I don't think [charging tolls] is a viable suggestion, as bridges are always filled with traffic and an additional charge is still being advocated. Traffic jams often occur on bridges not due to an excess of cars, but rather due to the occurrence of road accidents. Why can't we simplify procedures similar to what happens in Mainland China?", he asked.
This listener argued that “if [a road accident] does not involve criminal proceedings, and it is enough to take photographs of the accident, the vehicles involved in the accident can be removed from the scene” more quickly.
Ma also complained about the fact that Macau continues to maintain an outdated system for dealing with road accidents, even though the territory has recently adopted digital solutions, such as the installation of video surveillance cameras, which end up not being well used to deal with this type of cases.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:24:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Takeaway | Request for worker protection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/takeaway-pedida-proteccao-de-trabalhadores/</link><description>Deputy Leong Hong Sai questions the Government about whether it has plans to legislate the status of workers on online food delivery platforms. The matter was raised by the deputy linked to the Residents, through a written interpellation published on Friday.
In the document, Leong points out as a problem the fact that distributors are considered “independent workers”, but they are nevertheless subject to complying with the employer's orders, as in a traditional employment relationship. “Currently, several online food and order delivery platforms in Macau define their workers as ‘independent workers’ or ‘partners’, thus excluding them from legal labor protections,” he accused. “It is understood that some platforms allocate orders through algorithms and implement incentive schemes, preventing platform workers from enjoying the autonomy typical of traditional independent work,” he added.
The deputy therefore asks the Executive to create a legal statute to ensure the labor protection of distributors. “Will authorities review existing regulations governing employment relationships to comprehensively regulate online food and parcel delivery platforms?” he asks. “Furthermore, will they make appropriate adjustments in response to changes in the labor market to promptly clarify the legal status, responsibilities and rights of both companies and platform workers?”, he asks.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:22:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Ponte-Cais no. 11 | Government moves forward with land recovery</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/ponte-cais-n-o-11-governo-avanca-com-recuperacao-de-terreno/</link><description>The Government ordered the occupants of the land at Ponte-Cais no. 11 to vacate the space, considering that the “temporary occupation license” expired around 44 years ago. The information is contained in a notice from the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU), dated October 3rd.
According to the document, the license to occupy the Ponte-Cais no. 11 land was issued on April 14, 1980 and had a deadline of December 31, 1980. However, after the deadline, there was never any request to renew the license.
“According to the letter sent by the Directorate of Maritime Affairs and Water Services on August 18, 2025, there is no document that reveals the registration of a request for renewal of the said license, which is why it automatically expired due to the expiration of the term”, can be read in the notice. The occupants, one of whom was identified as Chan Meng, have now been given a period of 45 days, from the publication of the notice, to vacate the land.
The document also clarifies that if the eviction does not occur voluntarily within 45 days, the authorities have the power to proceed coercively. The land is located on Rua das Lorchas with Ponte-Cais no. 11 in good condition. The lot has an area of ​​199 square meters.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:57:11</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2026 | More than 3,500 opinions collected</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/lag-2026-mais-de-3-500-opinioes-recolhidas/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai, Chief Executive of the Macao SAR, told journalists that 3,548 opinions and suggestions were collected regarding the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for next year. Quoted in an official note, regarding the opening, this weekend, of the Government headquarters to the population, Sam Hou Fai explained that the work of collecting opinions was carried out for a month and ended on Friday.
The official also said that in terms of the number of opinions and suggestions, there was “an increase compared to previous years”.
The opening of the Government Headquarters to the public took place on Saturday and Sunday and, according to the same official note, “some residents stated that it was worth visiting the Government Headquarters, noting that this was not their first visit and that, this time, they had the pleasure of meeting the Chief Executive, taking photographs and chatting friendly, feeling his solidarity”.
There were also tourists visiting the Executive headquarters, who mentioned “the charm and specific architectural characteristics of the Government Headquarters Protocol Palace”. Opinions were also recorded regarding the “themed flower exhibition in the garden”, which was considered “beautiful, and the shows on site were appealing”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:56:12</pubDate></item><item><title>AL | André Cheong promises presidency to meet expectations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/al-andre-cheong-promete-presidencia-a-cumprir-expectativas/</link><description>At the beginning of the new legislature, deputies received “three expectations” from the Chief Executive, one of which involves “working together” with the Government, but also exercising law enforcement functions.
When performing the duties of president of the Legislative Assembly, André Cheong promises to keep in mind the Chief Executive's expectations for the work of the legislative body. The statements were made by the new president of the hemicycle, in an interview with TDM's Chinese-language channels.
"As president of the Legislative Assembly I feel that the weight of responsibility is greater. I will strictly comply with the provisions of the law and regulations to carry out my duties as president", stated the new president of the AL, quoted by Canal Macau. “At the same time, I will take into account the three expectations established by the Chief Executive for the new composition of the Legislative Assembly, leading the team well in legislative work and in the scope of supervision”, he added.
André Cheong was elected president of the AL on Friday and had the vote of all deputies, including his own. It was the first time, at least since 2019, that a deputy was unanimously elected president.
The president of the AL also intends to implement greater cooperation between the Government and the hemicycle's technicians. “For important law proposals related to the well-being of the population, the Government needs considerable preparation time”, he indicated. "We hope to encourage AL technical teams to get involved earlier in the preparatory phase of government departments. For example, preliminary technical discussions and exchanges can result in more fluid technical communication when these important bills are being analyzed by the Legislative Assembly", he pointed out.
Three desires
After the start of the new Legislature, last Thursday, the Chief Executive held a meeting with deputies. On this occasion, according to the official version, given that the meeting took place behind closed doors, Sam Hou Fai told the legislators that he has three expectations for the functioning of the hemicycle. The first involves “further enhancing the leadership role of the Legislative Assembly in political terms”, in what he explained as a role in promoting nationalism and maintaining harmony in the long term.
Secondly, he also asked deputies to “further enhance the role of the Legislative Assembly in drafting legislation and monitoring”, which he explained involved deputies “working together with the executive body” to create and review legislation considered key for the Executive, such as the diversification of the economy.
Finally, the AL was asked to be a “fundamental interlocutor” in collecting opinions from “public opinion”, while also indicating that it expected deputies to guide “society to form an environment for positive, objective and rational discussion” and “promote the broadest possible social consensus to support the Macao SAR Government”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:55:15</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG 2026 | Macau in a “key phase” of diversification, says secretary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/17/lag-2026-macau-numa-fase-chave-de-diversificacao-diz-secretario/</link><description>The Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, recently met with several associations in order to obtain their opinions for the preparation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for next year. Quoted in an official note, Tai Kin Ip considered that “Macau is at a key stage in promoting economic diversification”, having promised, within the scope of these meetings, “to further optimize the business environment”.
Another of the guarantees left by the government official refers to “support for small and medium-sized companies to improve their quality, stabilize local employment, create more development opportunities for residents and continually improve measures to guarantee the well-being of the population”.
The General Association of Women of Macau, General Association of Fukien Countrymen of Macau, Macau Institution People's Alliance, General Union of Residents' Associations of Macau, Commercial Association of Macau, Industrial Association of Macau, Macau Youth Federation, Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau and General Association of Overseas Chinese of Macau met with Tai Kin Ip.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 07:14:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Government reformulation | Chan Tsz King admits he has little experience in the area</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/17/reformulacao-governativa-chan-tsz-king-assume-ter-pouca-experiencia-na-area/</link><description>The new Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, admitted yesterday that he had little experience for the position he has held since yesterday, replacing Wong Sio Chak. “For me, this is a very big challenge because I have never had contact with the security area and have little experience in this area”, he said, according to statements reproduced by TDM. The new secretary highlighted the quality of the team he will work with, which has “experienced personnel”, namely the director general of the Customs Services and Unitary Police Services.
Furthermore, Chan Tsz King highlighted that “the issue of national security is very important for Macau society”, awaiting “long-term developments and legal diplomas that are being produced”.
Regarding the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for next year, for this guardianship, Chan Tsz King said that they are already being prepared. “For my part, the main thing is to adjust to this area and master the details.”
Chan Tsz King was a commissioner of the Commissariat against Corruption (CCAC), between 2019 and 2024, but began his career in public service as a delegate of the Public Prosecutor's Office in 1997. He was then promoted to the position of deputy prosecutor in March 2000, having been seconded to carry out duties in the Public Prosecutor's Service at the Courts of Second and Final Instances from January 2012 to December 2019.
The new Secretary for Security was born in Hong Kong in 1970 and has higher education completed in Portugal, namely at the Faculty of Arts of the University of Lisbon in Portugal, completed in 1989, and a Law course completed at the Autonomous University of Lisbon in Portugal in 1995.
MP | Tong Hio Fong talks “great responsibility”
Tong Hio Fong, who assumed the role of Public Prosecutor (MP) of the Macao SAR yesterday, as part of the government reform, thanked the “confidence of the Central Government and the Chief Executive” in assuming an “important and highly responsible position”. The official also added that he will “contribute to the development of the Macao SAR”, describing the territory as a successful example of the practice of one country, two systems, with “long-term stability and prosperity being ensured by the rule of law”. In turn, Tong Hio Fong said that the MP “is an important institution to defend the rule of law, being responsible for defending the dignity of the law, protecting the rights of citizens and combating illegal activities”. As Prosecutor, he promised to focus “on the principle of the rule of law, apply the law rigorously and fairly and strengthen inspection of judicial activities”, as well as “increase judicial efficiency”.
Administration | Wong Sio Chak collects opinions on markets
Upon assuming a vast portfolio, that of Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, former Secretary for Security, promised that, in the coming weeks, he will listen to the population's opinions regarding the functioning of markets. "In the near future I will visit the communities, in particular the markets. I will continue to do this [listen to opinions]. The means to receive the public's opinions are always unimpeded", he told the press.
To journalists, Wong Sio Chak thanked the work carried out by his predecessor, André Cheong, ensuring that he will now focus on four areas that he believes are priorities, such as the reform of Public Administration, strengthening the construction of “One country, two systems”, greater efficiency in governance and promoting integration in the Greater Bay Area and the Hengqin Deep Cooperation Zone.
"Regardless of government or local services, it is easy to appear bad habits, such as sectarianism, bureaucracy or isolated actions. These situations also occur in Macau and we need to change that. We need to facilitate horizontal communication [within the Public Service] and increase the effectiveness of cooperation", he added.
Wong Sio Chak argued that it is necessary to “increase staff capacity, explore their potential and make good use of talent, optimizing the allocation of employees”. In this way, the government official considers that “it is necessary to create more concrete training actions, especially in the capacity building of services”.
Wong Sio Chak, was born in Guangdong province in 1968 and graduated in Law from Peking University. After a long career in the Judiciary Police, he was appointed Secretary for Security in 2014.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 07:11:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Populism has fallen into the well</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/o-populismo-caiu-no-poco/</link><description>André Ventura had announced that in the local elections he would win the presidency of around 30 councils. In 308, he obtained the “resounding” result of three Municipal Chambers. The polls that we unfortunately still have showed that victory would belong to AD, second place to Chega and third to the Socialist Party. Television commentators were full of praising the polls and pointing out that Chega's result would be normal because the PS had been in absolute decline since the last legislative elections. They were wrong, once again.
Polls and commentators. The Socialist Party rose from the ashes and achieved a very positive result. Overall, they did not lose by much and in terms of results from parties alone, without coalitions, the socialists obtained almost twice as many Municipal Chambers as the PSD. It has been proven that without radical populism, without xenophobia, without racism and without the cries of André Ventura, Chega is a flop at a local level, especially in the interior of the country. Populism has fallen into the well and we will see when the “firefighters” can bring it to the surface. Chega won in Entroncamento without knowing exactly why, it won in a Madeiran town where half a dozen people live and it won in Albufeira because the owners of the bars and hotels managed to convince the entire clientele and neighborhood to vote for the neo-Nazis. The voters of Albufeira will cry drool and snot because Chega recommends in its Algarve program that bars close at two in the morning and the owners of these nightlife establishments demand that they close at four in the morning. Local discontent will prevail and will certainly translate into the next elections. This, in Albufeira, because in the rest of the Algarve Chega thought of winning everything. Not even that kind of tavern keeper who is always shouting in Parliament and wiping sweat from his bald head managed to win in Faro.
The global map is divided between the AD/IL and the pink party. Cavakistan ended after several decades. You saw that there was always that Ruas, who dyes his hair and mustache wanting to look like he was 30 years old, he had a defeat like he never expected. In Lisbon and Porto, the case has already caused a lot of talk. The victories of AD and its Liberal Initiative counterparts in Lisbon, and in Porto with the verbal support of Rui Moreira, the mayor who ended his controversial mandates, were obtained by a minimal margin and until midnight on election Sunday the television stations were only talking about a technical draw. It was sad to see Luís Montenegro, in his capacity as prime minister versus president of the PSD, on election day calling for votes for his fellow candidates, going absolutely against the law. Montenegro claimed victory, but it could have been a little more humble because the municipal victory was tangential and lost many important Chambers such as Braga and Coimbra.
The people, this time, showed great civic sense and abstention was one of the lowest in electoral history. At many polling stations the queues were huge and the wait was very long. It was the translation that abstention would download. Even so, the fraud did not cease to exist. In one region of the country, the old illegality of a party having had voting slips printed similar to those given to voters and then proposing that their appeased parties carry a ballot in their pocket with a cross in the party in question and when they brought the blank ballot that the polling station had delivered, they would receive two thousand euros. Not bad for a few thousand “mercenaries”.
The people are fed up with elections, but nothing about the matter is going to end. The spearheads of the candidates for President of the Republic are already on the road. The variety is huge, but almost all in the same direction. On the center right we have Admiral Gouveia e Melo with Marques Mendes. Even further to the right appears the “bocas” André Ventura and Cotrim Figueiredo, who was leader of the Liberal Initiative. On the moderate left side, António José Seguro appeared and it was only last Saturday that the Socialist Party decided to officially support the candidate António José Seguro. Too late. And even so, the leftmost socialist wing will vote for António Filipe of the PCP, in the good style of Álvaro Cunhal, who suggested that sometimes you have to cover your eyes to vote for someone who doesn't belong to the party.
This time, the polls seem to be getting it right. A polling company, in which we have the greatest confidence, obtained in a national survey carried out last week, that there will be a second round between Gouveia e Melo and António José Seguro. However, when the respondents were faced with the final decision in the second round, victory fell to the admiral.
Because, just as we wrote last Monday, Luís Montenegro, with this municipal victory, will not resign, even if the Public Ministry opens a judicial inquiry against the current prime minister regarding the case of his family company Spinumviva. The man has been in politics for many years and knows everything about how to defend himself against suspicions of alleged scammers. Portugal will continue to be governed by a politician under serious suspicion, but that in no way affects his unhealthy desire to be head of the Executive.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:51:20</pubDate></item><item><title>What direction for Macau in 2026?</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/17/que-rumo-para-macau-em-2026/</link><description>Only people from abroad will be surprised by the announcement of the list of seven deputies appointed by the Chief Executive to the 8th legislature of the Legislative Assembly. As one commentator highlighted, the personnel change is part of a “chess game”, aimed at further improving the constitutional structure with a predominance of the executive branch, under the principle of “One Country, Two Systems”, and at strengthening the functions of the administrative, legislative and judicial bodies, as well as deepening their constructive interaction.
Given the effectiveness of the consultative policy that has long been in force in Macau, the chance of Cheong Weng Chon (appointed by the Chief Executive to be a deputy of the Legislative Assembly) being elected President or Vice-President of the 8th legislature of the Legislative Assembly on October 16th, in the first session of the Plenary, is very high. It is difficult to imagine how Cheong, who was Secretary for Administration and Justice, could avoid embarrassing situations in the upcoming sectoral debates on the Lines of Government Action, especially when they focus on the area of ​​administration and justice, if he simply limited himself to being a deputy. If elected President of the Assembly, embarrassing situations can be avoided.
The three former Chief Executives of Macau, Ho Hau Wah, Chui Sai On and Ho Iat Seng, were all part of the Legislative Assembly. Ho Iat Seng, with his experience as President of the Assembly, understood very well the type of problems generated in administrative departments. After taking office as Chief Executive, Ho actually carried out in-depth work to optimize the efficiency of the administrative structure. After Macau's return to Chinese sovereignty, Cheong Weng Chon was Director of the Justice Affairs Bureau, Commissioner against Corruption, Secretary for Administration and Justice and Head of the Executive Committee of the Guangdong-Macao In-depth Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, so he is well versed in administrative matters. His frequent interactions with the Legislative Assembly during the law-making process allowed him to gain a good understanding of the capabilities and performance of deputies. If Cheong leads the 8th term of the Legislative Assembly, he will undoubtedly set a precedent for the full realization of the predominance of the executive branch under the principle of “One Country, Two Systems”.
Macau, a small city with about 700,000 inhabitants and an area of ​​33.3 square kilometers, was entrusted with the task of transforming the In-depth Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau on Hengqin Island, into the new trade center of the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area and the new platform for China's opening up to the outside world. As long as annual gaming revenue can remain at MOP240 billion, the SAR Government can make ends meet and provide for the basic needs of Macau residents. The problems facing public servants and small and medium-sized businesses can be resolved. A focus is needed on creating an environment that promotes business in public spaces, developing more employment opportunities for residents and investing in economic construction.
The direction Macau will take in 2026 will be influenced by changes in neighboring areas. Barring unforeseen circumstances, Sanae Takaichi, who follows in the footsteps of former Prime Minister Shinzo Abe, will be the first woman to hold that position and will be elected at an extraordinary session of the Japanese Diet called for October 15. News indicates that US President Donald Trump will visit Japan between October 27th and 29th to meet with the Emperor and the new Prime Minister. Furthermore, the fourth plenary session of the 20th. Central Committee of the Communist Party of China (CPC) will take place in Beijing from October 20th to 23rd. This chain of interactions, which was certainly not planned, suggests the inerception of a powerful hand. At the reception commemorating the 80th anniversary of China's victory in the War of Resistance against Japanese Aggression, President Xi Jinping stated that China is a force for world peace. If this strength comes into play, Macau can still sail smoothly into 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 07:38:01</pubDate></item><item><title>In Memoriam by Chef António Coelho</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/16/in-memoriam-do-chef-antonio-coelho/</link><description>“I love Portuguese food. I love the traditional and authentic cuisine. It’s the one I learned in Portugal. For me, that’s very important because I prefer the traditional things.”
Chef António Neves Coelho
The guardian of Portuguese-Macanese cuisine and dear friend, Chef António das Neves Coelho, left us on October 12, 2025, at Hospital Conde de São Januário. Major figure of Portuguese gastronomy in Macau, mentor to generations, defender of culinary authenticity and symbol of institutional resilience. His departure represents an irreparable loss for the gastronomic culture of the Macao SAR and for the emotional memory of all who shared his table, kitchen and dreams with him. Chef António grew up amidst the aromas of olive oil, garlic and red wine. From an early age, he revealed a rare vocation for cooking, not just as a technique, but as a cultural narrative.
His training took place in emblematic houses of Portuguese gastronomy, where he learned to respect the ingredients, times and affections that make up the culinary tradition. His international career took him to three continents and, finally, to Macau, where he completed his military service and found his true stage. From 1997 onwards, he established himself as Executive Chef and operations manager in reference spaces, becoming one of the main ambassadors of Portuguese and Macanese cuisine. Macau was not only his professional destination but his spiritual home. António understood that Macanese cuisine is not just a fusion of flavors, but also of stories. With sensitivity and rigor, he became a defender of the preservation of traditional recipes, the valorization of local ingredients and the formation of multicultural teams with a spirit of mission.
He founded his own brand, where he worked as culinary director and general manager for more than a decade at António Restaurante, receiving 12 Michelin recommendations, among others. His leadership was marked by a rare combination of technical demands, human empathy and strategic vision. His cuisine was made of olive oil and affection, of technique and tenderness, of rigor and poetry. Its contribution was recognized by two highly prestigious distinctions such as the Medal of Tourist Merit, awarded by the Government of the Macao SAR, in recognition of its role in the development of the hospitality sector and local gastronomic culture and the Medal of Merit of Portuguese Communities, awarded by the Government of Portugal, for its action as a cultural bridge between continents and for the promotion of Portuguese identity abroad.
These honors were not just trophies but testimonies of his dedication to the public cause, culture and excellence. In 2024, Chef António took on the leadership of a new gastronomic project at Angela Café &amp; Lounge at Lisboeta Macau. There, he created a menu that celebrated the Portuguese and Macanese essence, with dishes such as codfish à lagareiro, seafood rice and desserts with a conventual touch. The space has become a meeting point between tradition and modernity, between tourists and locals, between memory and the future. His team, formed and inspired by him, continues to represent the pillars of his vision with dedication, creativity and commitment to excellence. Chef António's death represents a human and institutional loss of great significance. But his legacy remains alive in the memory of the customers who tasted his dishes; in the training of professionals who learned from him; in the institutional identity of the spaces he helped to build and in the gastronomic culture of Macau and the Portuguese diaspora
His work does not end with his departure but continues in each preserved recipe, in each technical gesture transmitted and in each ethical value defended. More than a Chef, António was the guardian of the Portuguese-Macanese gastronomic soul. His life was a bridge between continents, flavors and generations. His cuisine was made of memory and innovation, of technique and tenderness, of rigor and poetry. May his memory continue to live on in every dish served, in every story told and in every young professional who dares to dream of a cuisine that respects the past and transforms the present.
Before his departure, Chef António left his legatee a precious set of recipes that are not mere technical records, but authentic trophies of Portuguese cuisine, honed over decades of practice, reflection and passion. This legacy is not just a gastronomic collection but a cultural heritage, a letter of intent and a mission to fulfill.  Each recipe represents a chapter of your life, a shared memory, a silent tribute to the roots that formed you. These are dishes that carry the flavor of childhood, the rigor of classical training, the boldness of reinvention and the tenderness of maturity. These are formulas that are not limited to ingredients and quantities as they contain gestures, silences, waiting times, and above all, intention.
The legatee, chosen with discernment and trust, did not just receive a recipe book. He received a culinary testament, a map of values ​​and institutional responsibility. It will now be up to you to execute, preserve and reinterpret these creations with fidelity and courage, keeping the flame of authenticity alive without falling into the rigidity of repetition. In the Portuguese tradition, the transmission of recipes is an act of intimacy and respect. It's not just about teaching but about trust. Chef António understood this deeply. For this reason, the recipes he left were not disseminated en masse, nor transformed into a commercial product. They were given to those who knew how to understand his spirit, to those who shared his daily kitchen with him and to those who demonstrated technical ability and human sensitivity.
These recipes include classic dishes and conventual desserts reinterpreted with local ingredients. But they also include new creations, designed for special occasions, themed menus and cultural tributes. These are dishes that never reached the public, but that can now be revealed with the care they deserve. Executing these recipes is not just reproducing flavors but embodying a philosophy. The legatee will have to maintain a balance between fidelity and evolution, technique and emotion, tradition and contemporaneity. You will have to respect the times, the gestures, the silences that Chef António taught. You will have to understand that each dish is also a message, a memory and an affirmation of identity. More than cooking, it will have to cure in a museological and emotional sense. Curate the legacy, protect it from trivialization and present it with dignity. You will have to train others, transmit the values ​​you received, ensure that the legacy does not disappear over time, but multiplies with meaning.
This work is not just gastronomic but curatorial, educational and diplomatic. It is a way of affirming that cuisine is also culture, that the dish is also a document and that the flavor is also memory. The recipes left by Chef António are seeds. It is now up to the legatee and the institution involved to cultivate them with respect, water them with knowledge and make them flourish with creativity. Each time one of these recipes is served, it will be as if Chef António were present not as a shadow, but as a light. This legacy is a rare gift. And like any precious gift, it requires care, time and love. May it be honored with the same generosity with which it was conceived. May it be shared with the same elegance with which it was lived. May it be perpetuated with the same passion with which it was created. Because in the kitchen, as in life, what remains is not what is repeated, it is what is respected.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 02:49:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Sex and emotions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/15/o-sexo-e-as-emocoes/</link><description>Sex can awaken a range of emotions. From positive to negative — including neutral — emotions often emerge in a haphazard way, without us being able to give them immediate meaning. There are those who even experience emotional combinations that place side by side emotions that at first glance would be opposites: pleasure and shame. These responses, however, are culturally shaped. Sex, deep down, is a microcosm of human emotional life, where body, culture and identity intersect.
Attachment theory, often described as the theory of love, shows how the search for security, or its absence, shapes our emotional response in relationships with others. The body has hormonal mechanisms associated with pleasure, which make us feel safe, but also others that can perpetuate our sense of insecurity. The way emotional responses are created depends largely on context and our past experiences. Therefore, emotions often become a lens through which we look at the world.
The psychology of emotions has crossed two important lineages to understand these mechanisms. One of them is medicine, where emotion results from physiological construction and regulation. The other comes from anthropology, which has explored how culture shapes our emotional responses. For example, intercultural studies have shown that in more individualistic societies, where anger is a form of expression of breaking relationships with others – in an attempt to impose limits – the physiological response is stronger than in collectivist societies. In societies where the group configuration has a more determining weight on the sense of self, anger is just an indicator that there is disharmony in the group relationship, and the physiological response and inflammation levels are lower. Anger is not perceived as a radical break from the collective, and therefore the experience of anger is, in some way, more sustained.
This cultural dimension becomes even more evident when we analyze the way in which various gender expressions construct their emotional worlds. Although popular culture tells us that there are differences between 'men' and 'women', the truth is that there is much more variability within each group than between them, which makes it difficult to justify a clear distinction. This division is culturally fueled and manifests itself in everyday gestures. Studies show that when women arrive at an emergency room with palpitations, they are more quickly diagnosed with anxiety than with a heart attack. The same does not happen with men, from whom a lesser emotional manifestation is expected, and therefore symptoms such as palpitations are rarely confused with anxiety.
Thus, it becomes almost expected for women to express excessive emotions and for men to repress them — which distorts our notion of what is ‘normal’ or ‘deviant’. It is worth bringing here an essential distinction in the theory of emotions: there are primary emotions, which are more immediate and more faithful to our internal states, and secondary emotions, which are in some way a complexification of the first, fed by beliefs, narratives and cultures. If at a certain moment I feel angry, and if my life experience has taught me that anger is an inappropriate emotion, other emotions quickly take over, such as shame or guilt.
All of this is relevant to better understanding emotions during sex. In the reductive binarism of custom, generalist beliefs persist that impose performance pressure on men and feelings of guilt on women — dynamics that are also reflected in same-sex relationships. When we realize that the emotions that emerge do not correspond to what culture defines as 'normal', we begin to monitor and censor what we feel. Without a deep understanding of emotions, the body and the context in which they are inserted, we end up complicating our lives. For example, the emotions that follow sex vary as much as the experiences themselves. Some feel a peaceful well-being, a feeling of closeness and tenderness — the so-called afterglow. Others experience the opposite: a certain melancholy or emptiness, known as post-sex dysphoria. These emotional states seem to depend less on the physical act and more on the meaning that each person attributes to it — connection, validation, curiosity or loneliness. Emotions are closely linked to the meanings we attribute to things.
It is the deeper conversations about emotions that free us from the artificial limits that prevent full emotional honesty. Only by understanding these processes — which translate social contexts and cultural narratives into physiological and emotional responses that the body carries — can we better understand sex, its pleasures and its difficulties. And if we treat sex as a conversation between bodies and emotions — perhaps we can listen to ourselves, and others, with more presence and empathy.</description><pubDate>2025-10-15 00:44:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Agualusa says that a bad writer will never write a good book</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/agualusa-diz-que-mau-escritor-nunca-escrevera-bom-livro/</link><description>A bad writer “will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, said writer José Eduardo Agualusa this Saturday at FOLIO – Óbidos International Literary Festival, arguing that this instrument does not pose a danger to authors and may even have some potential.
“I believe that a bad writer will never write a good novel using artificial intelligence”, but “perhaps a good writer will be able to write a better novel once he knows how to use this instrument”, he added.
At a panel of authors in which he assured that artificial intelligence does not scare him, the Angolan writer considered that this instrument “is still used in a trivial way” by many people, but that when “if you know how to use it well, you will probably discover greater potential”.
Even so, he considers that there is no danger of “writers being replaced”, because artificial intelligence “mimics, reproduces the writer’s style”, but “the imitation of the style is normally ridiculous”. In other chapters “that instrument is very useful”, he said, giving as an example the Angolan chronicle in the newspapers, which “improved a lot, because it corrects very well”.
“In the case of Angola it is very clear, suddenly the chroniclers started to write better, any emergency we ask for and the weekly column comes out”. However, in the long narrative, in the novel, “the AI ​​still has a big challenge” and, even if one day it manages to write “a mediocre novel” it will have to have “someone behind it, with creativity”.
Conversations on FOLIO
José Eduardo Agualusa spoke at the 12th panel of FOLIO, in a conversation with Brazilian writer Giovana Madalosso, where both argued that literature is not in danger, despite movements of censorship and cancellation of writers in countries like Brazil. Because “more and more people are reading. More and more people are reading better”, said Agualusa.
The FOLIO ended yesterday. This year marked the tenth year of existence with more than 460 initiatives, including more than a hundred conversations between authors and the public, 15 author tables, gatherings, seminars, book launches, concerts and prize giving.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:34:42</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM | Creative Macau hosts exhibition with student works</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/upm-creative-macau-acolhe-mostra-com-trabalhos-dos-alunos/</link><description>The Creative Macau gallery hosts, until November 8th, the exhibition “Prototype – Exhibition of Works by Students of the Degree in Media Arts”, from the Macau Polytechnic University. There are 30 works by more than 20 students who attend this course and who show all their creativity here
Creative Macau hosts a new exhibition composed of works of art by students from the Macau Polytechnic University. This is “Prototype” – Exhibition of Works by Students of the Degree Course in Media Arts at the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) 2025″, and can be seen until November 8th, with free entry.
The exhibition presents more than 30 works of art by around 20 students who attend the degree program at UPM, with the public being able to see “a curated selection of notable works by students from the first to the third year” of the aforementioned course, explains a note from Creative Macau.
You will be able to see a “diversity of work, ranging from interactive digital experiences to physical creations, reflecting the program's balanced emphasis on both theoretical foundations and practical application”. Thus, “through practical work in various courses, students acquired proficiency in a wide range of design tools and production techniques, transforming abstract ideas into fully realized works.”
“Important milestone”
Creative Macau further describes that this exhibition, and the opportunity that students have to show the results of their work, “constitutes an important milestone in their academic journey”. “By sharing these creations with the public, we hope to stimulate a broader dialogue and exchange about media arts, emerging technologies and the cultural future they continue to shape”, it is further stated.
Creative Macau – Creative Industries Center was founded in 2003 and has been managed by the Macau Institute of European Studies. Over the years, Creative Macau has supported projects and artistic works in 12 areas of the creative industries, including advertising, architecture, design, fashion or crafts. “Its objective is to help these industries reach their full economic potential, adding value and promoting recognition in society”, it is further described.
In the case of the degree in Media Arts at UPM, the objective is to “train high-quality media arts professionals through a curriculum that emphasizes multidisciplinary learning in the areas of arts, design and technology”. The aim here is that “students develop communication skills, international vision, intercultural understanding and innovative thinking, while at the same time acquiring knowledge and skills in media arts in the areas of interaction in games, technological art and video storytelling”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:33:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Brazilian writer Ozias Filho talks about the role of literature</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/escritor-brasileiro-ozias-filho-fala-do-papel-da-literatura/</link><description>Brazilian writer Ozias Filho stated on Friday that literature is a political and resistance act and that poetry produced by artificial intelligence will never be equal, because it lacks the “intangible and irreplaceable” experience. Ozias Filho was speaking during the XIII Meeting of Portuguese Language Writers, which ran until Saturday in the Cape Verdean capital, in a panel dedicated to literature and development.
The photographer and book editor, who was born in Rio de Janeiro, but has lived in Portugal for several years, stated that today we are experiencing “a remarkable paradox: we have never had so much access to information, but never, on the other hand, have we been so exposed to disorder and manipulation”. “Fake news, the algorithms that shape our perception and the ephemeral nature of digital interactions have transformed language into a true battlefield,” he said.
For Ozias Filho, literature is “an act of resistance against any power instituted by force, a weapon for the conscience that, once awakened, will no longer remain silent”. "Reading is apprehending the world and understanding its context. And it is not enough to live in a dictatorship to understand the meaning of this thought", he stated.
In Ozias Filho's opinion, today we live “under the aegis of the dictatorship of immediacy, consumerism, lies and historical revisionism”. “It is no coincidence that reading, learning, education and culture are often devalued in dictatorial regimes”, he observed, adding: “Even when reading is encouraged in these systems, it is because it fulfills and conveys the ideology of the current power”.
Artificial poetry
Ozias Filho then addressed one of the themes of this meeting of writers in his speech, artificial intelligence, asking the question: “Can a machine create poetry?”. "Yes, artificial intelligence is capable of producing metered verses, coherent metaphors and even poems that move. It can reproduce the form, but it lacks something intangible and irreplaceable: experience."
And he concluded that "an algorithm does not feel grief, loss, does not know resistance, does not experience passion or longing, nor does it fight against oppression. It can simulate, but it will never possess the soul, the result of a singular, imperfect and contradictory human experience."
Teresa Moure, from Galicia, Joaquim Ng Pereira (Macau/China), Daniel Medina and Vera Duarte, both from Cape Verde, also participated in this panel. The meeting began with the presentation of the UCCLA-Lisbon City Council Literary Revelation Award, this year awarded to actor Cláudio da Silva, who was born in Angola and lives in Portugal. The presentation was given by Germano de Almeida, the Cape Verdean writer who won the Camões Prize in 2018.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:32:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Photography | Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro distinguished at Budapest International Photo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/17/fotografia-goncalo-lobo-pinheiro-distinguido-no-budapest-international-foto/</link><description>Portuguese photojournalist Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro, based in Macau for over 15 years, was awarded the Gold award in the Editorial/Political category of the prestigious Budapest International Foto Awards (BIFA), with a photo report on the visit of the President of the People's Republic of China, Xi Jinping, to Macau, during the celebrations of the 25th anniversary of the MSAR.
Created for Agência Lusa, the photographic series documents key moments of the presidential visit, with images that capture the solemn atmosphere of the official ceremonies and the political symbolism of the occasion.
"I am very happy with this achievement. This photographic series documents key moments of President Xi Jinping's visit to Macau to mark the 25th anniversary of the MSAR. With images of the President and the authorities who accompanied him, the report portrays the formal atmosphere of the celebrations, highlighting the political weight of the visit", said the photojournalist, former editor of HM, quoted in a statement.
The photographs, marked by rigorous framing and close observation, reveal the choreography of State protocol, the symbolism of unity and the persistent ties between Macau and mainland China at this historical moment.
“Through careful compositions and a close look, I sought to reflect the ceremonial staging and the importance of the moment for Macau and its relationship with Beijing.”
The award reinforces the international recognition of press photography produced in Macau and highlights the fundamental role of photojournalism in documenting political events of global importance, highlights the same note.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 07:22:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Fengshen | Typhoon expected to pass 400km from Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/fengshen-tufao-devera-passar-a-400km-de-macau/</link><description>Tropical cyclone Fengshen is expected to pass around 400 kilometers south of Macau on Wednesday, according to the Meteorological and Geophysical Services Directorate (DSMG). At that time, according to yesterday's forecasts, the tropical cyclone should gain strength and transform into a typhoon.
“Therefore, depending on the development of Fengshen and changes in wind strength in Macau, a Tropical Storm Signal will be issued from Monday night (today)”, it was pointed out. Since yesterday, it was also predicted that the wind would begin to intensify due to “a northeast monsoon”, and authorities believed that there would be a “significant increase, with the wind reaching levels 6 to 7 on the Beaufort Scale”.
Temperatures | Descent to 18 degrees
From today until Wednesday, temperatures are expected to drop to 18 degrees, according to information released yesterday by the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (DSMG). “Regarding the weather, precipitation is expected, with the minimum temperature dropping to around 18 degrees Celsius, between Monday and Wednesday (20 to 22)”, it was indicated.
"Due to the significant drop in temperatures next week, and the strong wind associated with cloudy weather with precipitation, the thermal sensation of cold will be lower than the actual temperature. DSMG urges the population to pay attention to the most recent meteorological information", it was added.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:31:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Caritas | More than 3,500 requests for help received by the end of September</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/caritas-recebidos-mais-de-3-500-pedidos-de-ajuda-ate-fim-de-setembro/</link><description>The number of support requests shows a stabilization trend in recent years. And given the lack of “very serious” poverty problems, Cáritas Macau also extended its support program to Pakistan and Bangladesh
Cáritas Macau received 3,509 requests for support for the Food Bank by the end of September, the organization's secretary-general said yesterday, indicating that this year's final values ​​should not differ from those of 2024.
“We expect it [in 2025] to exceed four thousand, like last year”, noted Paul Pun Chi Meng to Lusa, pointing out that, in 2024, 4,936 requests reached the humanitarian organization, which, in turn, represents a drop of 2.5 percent compared to 2023 (5,065). In an annual comparison, the first nine months of 2025 present values ​​similar to those recorded in the same period of 2023 and 2024: 3,589 and 3,596, respectively.
Even so, there is a slight decline this year, which could be related to the “existence of other support resources” or “greater ease in applying for social housing”, noted Pun, implying that easier access to public housing could ease the bills at the end of the month.
The program, aimed at low-income people and financed by the authorities, foresees that the Bank's support will result in food aid for a period of ten weeks, with a second request being possible within 12 months. Among non-resident workers, highlighted Paul Pun, there is also a group that uses social assistance organizations. Last Saturday, close to a thousand people received support in the form of food baskets.
Aid in Pakistan and Bangladesh
The secretary general of Cáritas also explained that as Macau does not face “very serious poverty” problems, the organization is supporting disadvantaged families in Bangladesh and Pakistan, providing aid to 2,100 people. Last week, Pun returned from Sylhet, a city in northeastern Bangladesh that he has visited several times since 2023, the year in which Cáritas Macau became involved in a program to “improve the health and nutrition of disadvantaged children”.
With donations of around 15 thousand dollars per year, aid has already reached 400 people, said the person in charge. “We hope that, through training, in terms of care for newborns, mothers, they can achieve a better life”, pointed out the general secretary of Cáritas Macau, also noting that, on the table is the possibility of providing resources for the professional training of teenagers who dropped out of school.
About a month ago, Paul Pun was also in Lahore, the second largest city in Pakistan, with nearly 14 million inhabitants and which has been affected, in recent years, by several floods.
Cáritas Macau's assistance to the “Informal education and development of young people and women” program, with the transfer of up to 35 thousand dollars per year (around 30 thousand euros), has already touched the lives of 1,200 children and 500 teenagers in Lahore, according to the leader of the humanitarian organization.
"The children do not have schools [in these places]. They participate in this informal education program so that they have an opportunity to reach the standards and one day be able to enter school", he said. In addition to supporting the education of teenagers – “especially boys” – in areas such as IT, the program also includes skills training “by young women”.
To Lusa, Paul Pun said that international assistance from Cáritas Macau arrives “via several channels”, namely through donations and the organization Good Fortune Charity Shop, the social enterprise of Cáritas Macau, which collects donated goods for charitable sale.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:29:35</pubDate></item><item><title>UM joins the UNESCO Chair dedicated to Portuguese heritage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/um-junta-se-a-catedra-unesco-dedicada-ao-patrimonio-portugues/</link><description>The University of Macau (UM) announced its membership of the UNESCO Chair in Intercultural Dialogue on Heritage of Portuguese Influence, a project launched by the University of Coimbra (UC).
In a statement released on Friday night, UM argued that joining the project “imposes a new dynamic in the development of research on cultural heritage” in Macau. The collaboration with UC will promote “international academic exchange in Macau”, as well as strengthen “ties” with higher education institutions in Portuguese-speaking countries, UM added.
The institution's formal accession to the UNESCO Chair took place in a ceremony organized by the two institutions in Macau, on Wednesday, with the presence of Rui Martins, vice-rector of UM, and João Nuno Calvão da Silva, vice-rector of UC. Rui Martins argued that UM's entry “will further enrich the academic resources and cultural perspective” of the already “wide network of partners” established by the UNESCO Chair.
The UC created the project in 2018, to explore “the multicultural results resulting from the influence of Portuguese-speaking culture”, such as architecture, arts, language, literature, landscape and urbanism, said the statement. At the time, the UNESCO Chair already involved fifty teachers and researchers in a partnership with several European, Brazilian and African institutions.
Comprehensive effort
The list included the University of Bologna Studies (Italy), the Universidade Federal Fluminense (Brazil), the universities Eduardo Mondlane and Lúrio (Mozambique), the University Paris Nanterre (France) and MEIA – Mindelo Escola Internacional de Arte (Cape Verde).
Rui Martins, a Portuguese academic who has long lived in Macau, highlighted that the UNESCO Chair is an international project “that integrates research, training and cooperation for development”. In the case of UM, the Department of Integrated Resorts and Tourism Management of the Faculty of Business Management will “actively demonstrate its professional competence” in research into cultural heritage, guaranteed Martins.
The UNESCO Chair is coordinated by researcher Walter Rossa, who on Wednesday spoke about “the political significance” of research on cultural heritage within the organization's policies.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Justice | Portugal may send new judges to Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/20/justica-portugal-pode-enviar-novos-juizes-para-macau/</link><description>Despite having prevented Carlos Carvalho from remaining in the territory and maintaining uncertainty about the future of Rui Ribeiro, who chose to return to Portugal, the Superior Council of the Judiciary of Portugal guarantees openness to sending new magistrates to the Macao SAR
The president of the Supreme Court of Justice (STJ) stated that Portugal is available, if Macau shows interest, in sending new judges. The statements were made at a time when a Portuguese magistrate is about to leave the Macao SAR. Judge Rui Ribeiro, of the Court of Second Instance, confirmed to Lusa, on the sidelines of a public event, that he will leave Macau at the end of October, bringing forward the end of the commission, which ended in May 2026.
The magistrate stressed that the Macau judicial authorities “did everything” to make him change his mind, but explained that he preferred to return to Portugal now given the uncertainty regarding a possible renewal of the special license by the Superior Council of Judiciary (CSM).
With the announced departure of Rui Ribeiro, only one Portuguese judge remains in the Macau courts: Jerónimo Alberto Gonçalves Santos, president of a collective court at the Base Judicial Court (TJB). The leader of the STJ, João Cura Mariano, who inherently also presides over the CSM, told journalists that, during a visit to Macau, he wanted to find out if the territory was interested in having Portuguese magistrates.
“We are going to try to see what they can really convey that is useful and whether they are necessary, because if they are necessary, new judges will come”, he assured the journalists.
João Cura Mariano said that this would be a “subject to discuss” in yesterday's meetings with the president of the Court of Final Instance (TUI), Song Man Lei, and with Sam Hou Fai, leader of the Macau Government and former president of the TUI. “I think it is very useful, because, being a former president of the court [Sam Hou Fai] he will be aware of the needs that exist”, said the Portuguese judge advisor.
National difficulties
But the president of the STJ highlighted that Portuguese justice is having “some difficulty in contributing judges”, due to the lack of qualified and experienced human resources. “Just now we removed a judge who had been here for many years and we needed him”, recalled João Cura Mariano.
In 2024, the CSM rejected the stay of Portuguese TJB judge Carlos Carvalho, who had been in Macau for 16 years and had been invited by the Independent Commission for the Nomination of Judges in the territory to continue for another two years. The council did not authorize the renewal of Carlos Carvalho's special license and promoted him to judge, with placement at the Court of Appeal.
Even so, João Cura Mariano assured that he was willing to help, “despite the difficulties that currently exist in Portugal in recruiting judges”. The president of the STJ highlighted the example of Timor-Leste, where there are currently “many Portuguese judges collaborating in the Timorese judicial system”, because “they are very necessary”.
The judge was in Macau to participate, on Sunday, in the 13th edition of the forum that brings together presidents of the Supreme Courts of Justice of Portuguese-speaking countries and territories.</description><pubDate>2025-10-20 01:25:30</pubDate></item><item><title>São Januário | First artificial heart implanted in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/sao-januario-implantado-primeiro-coracao-artificial-em-macau/</link><description>The first surgery to implant an artificial heart was recently carried out at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center (CHCSJ) of Health Services (SS), in collaboration with the cardiothoracic surgery team of the First Affiliated Hospital of Jinan University.
The procedure was carried out on a 68-year-old woman who suffered from terminal heart failure, and, according to a statement from the SS, “the condition presented was complex and the surgical intervention challenging”. It was “the first surgical procedure to implant a completely magnetically levitated artificial heart, developed autonomously in Mainland China”. Carrying out this surgery in the territory represents, for the authorities, “significant progress in cardiac surgery in Macau”.
For the SS, “the successful completion of the first artificial heart implant surgery in Macau represents a significant advance in the treatment of terminal heart failure in the region”, in addition to this technological advance “fills a significant gap in medical care, offering a viable and safe alternative for patients who are not eligible for heart transplantation or who cannot wait for a surgical intervention”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:53:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire leads to two hospitalizations and evacuation of 50 people</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/17/incendio-leva-a-duas-hospitalizacoes-e-retirada-de-50-pessoas/</link><description>Two people had to be admitted to Kiang Wu Hospital, after a fire broke out on Wednesday night, in the Si Keng Building, on Rua da Alegria. In addition to the injured, there was also a need to remove 50 residents from the building, according to information released yesterday by the newspaper Ou Mun.
Those hospitalized are two residents aged around 60, one male and one female, who reportedly showed signs of being unwell after inhaling smoke from the fire. Despite their indisposition, their clinical situation was considered stable.
The remaining residents also managed to leave the building by their own means and did not present any type of discomfort or injuries. The flames began to break out at around 11:44 pm, when authorities were alerted to the situation. The arrival at the scene of both the Fire Department (CB) and the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) took place minutes later, at a time when several of the building's inhabitants were already on the street.
At the scene, firefighters had to climb to the third floor, where the fire originated. Fighting the flames took a few minutes. Traces indicate that the flames broke out next to a vase with flowers, and then reached the living room of the apartment on the third floor. During the fight against the fire, authorities closed Rua da Alegria and Estrada do Repouso to traffic for several minutes.
Firefighters used water to fight the fire, which resulted in a burned area measuring 2.5 meters long and 1 meter wide.
From the origins
According to the newspaper Ou Mun, the CB suspects that the flames originated from a short circuit in a washing machine, positioned next to the vase with flowers. In addition to the burned area, the washing machine, a purifier, an air conditioner and other appliances and goods were also destroyed.
According to the most recent data, in the first six months of the year, the CB was called to intervene in 406 fires. Among these, firefighters had to use hoses to extinguish the flames on 85 occasions. In the remaining 321 fires, the flames were extinguished without using a hose.
Official information also revealed that 78 of the 406 fires originated from burnt food.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hengqin | Portuguese restaurant opens across the border</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/17/hengqin-restaurante-portugues-abre-do-outro-lado-da-fronteira/</link><description>It’s called “Vivo” and it’s a Mediterranean cuisine restaurant that opens its doors tomorrow in Hengqin. João Maria Pegado, one of the project's partners and previously linked to sport, is now focusing on the restaurant sector and has high expectations given the tourist demand on the island.
A Mediterranean cuisine restaurant officially opens tomorrow in Hengqin. Located in the Huafa shopping center, the Vivo restaurant is a project by two Portuguese people who saw an opportunity to bring two geographies closer together – China and southern Europe. It's not about fusion cuisine. Still, several traditions coexist in this restaurant: Portuguese, Spanish and Italian cuisine, prepared by a chef from Shanghai with Chinese raw materials.
“We are in China, we want to invest in fresh Chinese products”, one of the partners, João Maria Pegado, tells Lusa. So much so that, for now, there is no traditional octopus à lagareiro on the menu. You have to continue browsing local markets until you find the ideal product, explains Pegado.
"We could go to Macau to get frozen octopus, but our main objective was to work with fresh products in China. In terms of cost, it makes it much more profitable, but we also want to take advantage and create this fusion between Chinese products and Portuguese dishes", he says. Vivo has been in ‘soft opening’ mode since July 18th. And João Maria Pegado does not complain about the journey he has taken so far, despite the difficulty of the language.
More and more
To Lusa, Pegado says he will soon compete for support from the Macau Government, at a time when authorities are encouraging investment in the Macau-Guangdong Deep Cooperation Zone, in Hengqin. And this region attracts more and more visitors to Macau, says the investor. In this area managed by both sides of the border, the movement of drivers from Macau is now permitted, for example, upon request for a license, recalls Pegado.
But there are other attractions: gasoline is cheaper – “the cars in Macau come to fill up at the weekend, we [Portuguese] are like in Badajoz” – supermarkets are more affordable, more space and more green areas. "An open space where you can relax without being in the middle of the city. That's the big reason why people leave Macau for Hengqin on the weekend and sometimes even during the week, at lunchtime", he reflects.
Hengqin also seems to be a more economical option for Chinese people visiting Macau, where, according to data for August, the average price of a hotel room is 1,461 patacas. "Hengqin has increasingly become a point of concentration, of sleeping, used by many visitors. Many of the buildings that were built as offices, the Government gave licenses (…) to build Airbnb-style hotels [local accommodation]", he said.
Hong Kong and Macau are, for now, the origin of the majority of the restaurant's visitors, but João Maria Pegado also hopes to reach more consumers from the interior of China. “There are still few people who know what Mediterranean [the concept] means”, he highlights, noting, however, that, for many of those who have visited Vivo, black paella has been a recurring choice.
This dish is joined by other specialties of the house, such as fisherman's rice, guilloche prawns or barbecue chicken, says Pegado, who left a career linked to sport to dedicate himself to the restaurant business.
“It’s special”, he admits. “I felt that there was a lack of a Western food restaurant, and that it could be successful in that area (…). I have lived in Hengqin for three years and it is a place that I really appreciate, it allows me to be close to Macau, the city where I grew up and with which I feel identified”, he concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 07:15:46</pubDate></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
At a lunch with several guests, I heard a friend, who declared herself a spiritualist, explaining the particularities of her belief, in a calm and balanced way, I would even say, without a hint of “irrationalism”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«If transparency is demanded from politicians, we kill them; if anyone demands fidelity to what the other was or what he says, kill him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, representation is killed. These must therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to bend the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). I believe we will be needed to decipher this frantically complex world that has fallen to us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Men should refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish because of it, tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the land will be destroyed. pride of countries.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were limited, or if it simply lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each one. to be, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, in a different way, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse like a shadow
[deformed
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will indeed be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piella than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel bombs Rafah alleging that Hamas attacked military unit</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/israel-bombardeia-rafah-alegando-que-hamas-atacou-unidade-militar/</link><description>Israel launched a series of air strikes against the city of Rafah, in the Gaza Strip, after accusing Hamas of attacking a military engineering unit, security sources cited by the Israeli press said yesterday.
Pending an official statement from the Israel Defense Forces and the Islamist group Hamas, military sources confirmed to the Israeli website Walla and the Times of Israel that air and ground attacks had been carried out in Rafah, claiming that it was a response to an attack on an Israeli military excavator tasked with destroying the Islamist organization's tunnels.
Although there is still no official information about the existence of deaths or injuries, Israeli military sources told Israeli television that two alleged Hamas militants were killed. It is also unknown whether this crossfire could jeopardize the ceasefire that came into force on October 10, but the Israeli Minister of National Security, Itamar Ben Givr, has already urged the Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu, to resume the offensive against the Gaza Strip.
“I ask the Prime Minister to order the Israel Defense Forces (IDF) to fully resume fighting in the Gaza Strip with all its personnel,” said the minister, who was convicted in the past for inciting hatred against Palestinians, vandalism and support for terrorism. According to a source from Hamas' armed wing, the group had launched an operation in Rafah to eliminate the leader of the rival militia, known as 'Popular Forces', Yasser Abu Shabab.
However, Israeli soldiers intervened to support Shabab, which resulted in crossfire and caused the Israeli excavator to explode. The United States warned on Saturday that it had “credible information” about an “imminent attack” by Hamas against Palestinian civilians, in a “clear violation” of the ceasefire.
Chaos installed
Yesterday morning, the Islamist group rejected the accusation and blamed Israel for arming and financing other militias, which, it said, carried out “murders, kidnappings, robberies of humanitarian aid trucks and robberies against civilians”.
According to Hamas, its members in Gaza are, “with broad civil and popular support”, pursuing these gangs and holding them accountable “according to clear legal mechanisms, to protect citizens and preserve public and private property”.
Just one day after the ceasefire, Hamas militants began cracking down on all clans and militias that allegedly collaborated with Israel during the past two years' war, including public executions of alleged collaborators, images of which went viral.
The ceasefire in Gaza – proposed by the United States and agreed between Israel and Hamas – has been in force since October 10, providing for three phases: the release of hostages, the disarmament of Hamas and the gradual reconstruction of the territory, under international supervision. The second stage, centered on “demilitarization”, remains the most controversial and the one that Israel considers essential to put an end to the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:52:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan's Liberal Party close to securing new coalition deal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/partido-liberal-do-japao-perto-de-garantir-novo-acordo-de-coligacao/</link><description>The Liberal Democratic Party (PLD), in power in Japan, is close to forming a government coalition, which would leave leader Sanae Takaichi just two deputies away from securing election as prime minister.
The main Japanese media reported yesterday that the agreement with the Innovation Party of Japan (Ishin) could be closed as early as Monday, the day before parliament meets to choose Shigeru Ishiba's successor. The outgoing prime minister resigned in September from the leadership of the Government and the PLD, which, in primaries held at the beginning of October, chose the conservative and nationalist Takaichi as the candidate to be the first woman to lead Japan.
According to the Japanese news agency Kyodo, the PLD and Ishin have agreed to form a coalition without the opposition party guaranteeing seats in the new Government. In return, the PLD would commit to complying with a series of proposals, including reducing the number of deputies, eliminating the tax on food consumption and eliminating political donations from companies and organizations. Today, a final meeting with the PLD is expected.
Fragile leadership
The newspaper reported that the opposition party is reluctant to occupy positions in Takaichi's possible government and prefers to first ensure that the new PLD leader complies with the terms of the agreement. If elected, the conservative would lead one of the weakest governments in Japan's political history, with a clear minority in both chambers of parliament, which would force her to cooperate with the opposition to pass any law.
Ishin's support is essential for Takaichi, especially after the Buddhist party Komeito, with which the PLD was allied for 26 years, abandoned the ruling coalition. The centrist Komeito withdrew from the alliance due to published news about alleged secret PLD funds, having also criticized Sanae Takaichi due to supposed changes in the leader's stance regarding visits to Yasukuni.
Diplomatic fears
Takaichi, known for her hard-line stance towards China, has visited the Shinto shrine numerous times in the past, especially when she was minister, considered a symbol of the country's militaristic past. But, on Friday, on the first day of the Yasukuni Autumn Festival, 64 years old, he was absent and sent only one offering, because, according to Japanese media, he feared that a visit could upset neighboring countries.
Previous visits by senior Japanese officials to the shrine have angered Beijing and Seoul. China and the Korean peninsula were the scene of atrocities committed by the Japanese military in the first half of the 20th century. No sitting Japanese prime minister has visited the shrine in Tokyo since 2013, when Shinzo Abe's visit sparked fury among neighboring countries and rebukes from the United States.
The shrine pays tribute to the approximately 2.5 million Japanese soldiers killed in combat, but also to Japanese officers and politicians convicted of war crimes by an international tribunal after World War II. The LDP has governed Japan almost permanently since 1955, despite frequent leadership changes.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:50:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Cambodia | 64 South Koreans deported for criminal practices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/camboja-deportados-64-sul-coreanos-por-praticas-criminosas/</link><description>Seoul estimates that around a thousand South Korean citizens are treated as slaves and work in centers in Cambodia dedicated to committing internet fraud.
South Korean police confirmed Saturday that Cambodia deported 64 South Korean citizens accused of involvement in centers that practice internet fraud. South Korea sent a team to Cambodia on Wednesday, where it believes around a thousand South Koreans are working in these centers, to discuss dozens of cases of abductions through fraudulent job offers.
Seoul then announced, on Friday night, that it was chartering a flight to bring back around 60 citizens, “voluntary and non-voluntary participants” in the fraud schemes, who were detained by the Cambodian police. The group landed on Saturday morning at Incheon Airport, a South Korean police official told the France-Presse news agency. Police authorities were seen preparing to transport them in black security vans.
Most of the South Korean returnees were detained in Cambodia during crackdowns on fraud centers and will face police investigations at home, Seoul's national security director Wi Sung-lac said.
On Friday, the South Korean government banned South Koreans from traveling to Cambodia, amid an increase in the number of people allegedly abducted by human trafficking networks and organized crime groups based in Cambodia. Criminal groups forced South Korean citizens to commit fraud involving cryptocurrencies via the Internet, in an environment similar to that of a prison.
According to diplomatic sources from Seoul and the UN, South Korean citizens are held as slaves and have been subjected to acts of torture by organized crime groups. Seoul's warning also recommends South Korean citizens to leave certain areas of Cambodia.
Capital encounters
The warning was issued on the day that South Korean Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs Kim Jina met with Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Manet in Phnom Penh. The meeting in Cambodia's capital took place after the death of a South Korean student who was allegedly forced to work in a fraud center in Cambodia.
Phnom Penh said on Thursday that in recent months it has deported 180 South Korean citizens involved in cybercrime and another 60 are awaiting repatriation. According to a United Nations report, at least 200,000 people are currently held in fraud centers in Cambodia, while in Myanmar (formerly Burma), another epicenter of this phenomenon, the number amounts to around 120,000.
Seoul's decision came in the same week that the UK and US governments announced joint sanctions against Cambodia-based conglomerate Prince Group. The president of the group of companies, Chen Zhi, is accused of setting up a cybercrime and human trafficking network.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:49:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics | Nobel Prize winner Chen Ning Yang has died</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/fisica-morreu-chen-ning-yang-vencedor-do-premio-nobel/</link><description>Chinese physicist Chen Ning Yang, winner of the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1957 and considered one of the most influential researchers of the 20th century in modern physics, died Saturday at the age of 103 in Beijing, Xinhua announced.
Chen Ning Yang, born in the eastern Chinese city of Hefei in 1922, received the Nobel Prize in Physics, together with the researcher and his compatriot Tsung Dao Lee, for research into the law of conservation of parity, a fundamental principle of nuclear physics.
The two researchers fled China during the war against Japan (1937-1945) and developed their professional careers in the United States, where Chen Ning Yang was a professor at Princeton University and Tsung Dao Lee at Columbia University, when they received the award.
For this reason and because they both acquired North American nationality – China does not recognize dual nationality – for many years Yang was not considered a “Chinese” Nobel winner.
Chen Ning Yang returned to China as a professor at the prestigious Tsinghua University in Beijing in 2003, which highlighted him as “the most influential physicist” of the current era and recalled that, after the thawing of relations with Washington in 1971, he was the first Chinese scientist residing in the United States to be able to return to his country.
In 2015, 51 years after obtaining US citizenship, he renounced it. "Yang was one of the greatest theoretical physicists of the 20th century. He was closer to Einstein than his contemporaries," said Shi Yu, professor at the Shanghai Institute of Advanced Studies, quoted Saturday by the Hong Kong newspaper South China Morning Post.
In addition to his academic work, the physicist became a national celebrity when he married in 2004, at the age of 84, Weng Fan, a 28-year-old student. Months earlier, at the end of 2003, his first wife, Tu Chih-li, whom he had married in 1950, had died.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:47:32</pubDate></item><item><title>South Sea | Beijing asks Philippines to abandon fantasies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/mar-do-sul-pequim-pede-as-filipinas-que-abandonem-fantasias/</link><description>Maritime disputes in the region provoked another clash between Chinese vessels and the Philippines
Beijing on Saturday urged the Philippines to abandon what it described as “unrealistic illusions” and farces, following a collision between ships from the two countries last Sunday in the disputed South China Sea.
“The facts are very clear and the Philippines has no reason to justify or deny its intrusions, provocations and improper actions,” said the Chinese Defense Ministry spokesperson, quoted by the official Chinese news agency Xinhua. Zhang Xiaogang accused Manila of carrying out an “illegal intrusion” into the archipelago known in China as Nansha and denounced the Philippines' recent claim to sovereignty over Nansha and the island of Huangyan.
“The scope of Philippine territory has been defined by a series of international treaties, and the islands of Huangyan and Nansha, which belong to China, are not included in it,” the spokesperson argued. The Chinese government promised new “resolute measures” to defend sovereignty over the islands and maritime rights, in the face of what it said was the “deliberate distortion” of “historical and legal facts” by the Philippines.
On October 12, a Chinese Coast Guard ship and a Philippine authorities vessel collided near Thitu Island, known in the Philippines as Ragasa, in the South China Sea. The Chinese Coast Guard attributed responsibility for the incident to the Philippines, saying that three vessels from Manila approached Chinese patrol vessels and that one of them caused the collision.
Voice of America
Two days later, US State Department Deputy Spokesperson Tommy Pigott condemned the clash “and China's use of water cannons” against the Philippine Bureau of Fisheries and Aquatic Resources vessel. Pigott accused Beijing of intensifying “increasingly coercive” actions as part of its “broad territorial and maritime claims” in this disputed area, which also involves other Southeast Asian countries.
These dangerous actions continue, according to the official, “to undermine regional stability” and “contradict previous commitments to resolve disputes peacefully”. The spokesperson reiterated Washington's support for Manila and recalled that the Mutual Defense Treaty between the two countries covers any armed attack “against the Armed Forces, public vessels or Philippine aircraft, including those of the Coast Guard, at any point in the South China Sea”.
The disputed waters of the South China Sea are crossed by crucial trade routes and experts believe the seabed could contain important oil and gas reserves. Beijing has repeatedly taken action against Philippine vessels, accusing them of entering waters it claims are Chinese territory.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:45:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Kuomingtang elects Cheng Li-wun as new leader</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/taiwan-kuomingtang-elege-cheng-li-wun-como-nova-lider/</link><description>Taiwan's main opposition party, the Kuomingtang Nationalists (KMT), has chosen a former congresswoman as its new president.
Cheng Li-wun — the only candidate in the race who positioned herself as a reformist — defeated former Taipei Mayor Hau Lung-bin and four other candidates for leadership of the pro-Beijing party by a large margin on Saturday. At a press conference after the victory, Cheng said the nationalists would uphold the principles of equality, respect and mutual benefits in the conduct of foreign relations.
"We must not let Taiwan become a troublemaker. Secondly, we must not let Taiwan be sacrificed to geopolitics," he said, adding that the KMT would also be a peacemaker. Nationalists maintain strong political influence in Taiwan, despite having lost three consecutive presidential elections to the DPP, which advocates a move away from China.
The KMT holds enough seats to form a majority bloc with its allies in parliament. With his inauguration scheduled for November, Cheng Li-wun could influence how Taiwan deals with Beijing and other important national and international policies and issues. Cheng will also be the party leader in the 2026 local elections. The KMT must also prepare a candidate to challenge William Lai Ching-te's DPP in the 2028 elections.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:44:38</pubDate></item><item><title>AirChina | Plane diverted to Shanghai after fire in battery stored in luggage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/air-china-aviao-desviado-para-xangai-apos-fogo-numa-bateria-guardada-em-bagagem/</link><description>An Air China plane was diverted safely to Shanghai Saturday after a battery stored in a passenger's carry-on luggage caught fire, the airline said.
The incident occurred on board the flight from the city of Hangzhou, in eastern China, to Incheon International Airport, near Seoul, South Korea. “A lithium battery stored in a passenger's hand luggage in the overhead compartment of flight CA139 spontaneously caught fire,” the airline said, in a statement published on the Chinese social network Weibo.
“The crew immediately dealt with the situation based on procedures, and no one was injured,” the document states, adding that the plane was diverted to Shanghai Pudong International Airport “to ensure the safety of the flight.” An image taken by a passenger and published by national state media outlet Jimu News shows flames in an upper compartment, where black smoke is visible and at least one passenger trying to put out the fire.
According to data from Flightradar24, which monitors global air traffic, the flight took off from Hangzhou at 09:47 local time (and flew over the sea, approximately equidistant from the east coast of China and the Japanese island of Kyushu, before landing in Shanghai shortly after 11:00 local time.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:38:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Three Chinese citizens convicted by Mozambique of violating mining suspension</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/tres-cidadaos-chineses-condenados-por-mocambique-violarem-suspensao-de-mineracao/</link><description>The judicial court of the district of Sussundenga, in the Mozambican province of Manica, on Friday sentenced three individuals of Chinese nationality to a sentence of three months in prison for violating the mining suspension in that province.
Convicted of the crime of disobedience, having been caught exploring for gold “during a period in which activities were temporarily suspended globally in the province of Manica”, the three men will also have to pay a daily fine of seven thousand meticais (93.84 euros), said the judge in the case, Eugénia Conceição.
According to the court's reasoning, Chinese citizens were found extracting gold by a multisectoral team that included the police for the protection of natural resources and the environment, and, during their mining activity, they threw polluting waste directly into a river.
The Mozambican executive decided, on September 30, to suspend all mining licenses in the province of Manica and created an interministerial commission to review the licensing regime, reinforce supervision and advance environmental recovery measures with the active participation of perpetrators, local authorities, populations and other relevant entities.
Law of the jungle
This suspension comes after the Mozambican President, Daniel Chapo, announced, on September 17, that mining is causing an “environmental disaster”, having admitted the possibility of a total suspension of the activity. The suspension of mining licenses in Manica comes after the executive assessed the report of the operational command of the Defense and Security Forces (FDS), which was in that province between the 17th and 19th of July to investigate the environmental situation in relation to mining.
“Uncontrolled mining” carried out by licensed operators was found on the ground in Manica, with companies operating without an environmental recovery plan and waste containment systems, in addition to violations of workers’ rights.
The Government classified the environmental situation in Manica as critical, pointing to “serious pollution” of the rivers that present “reddish, turbid and opaque waters,” resulting from direct washing of ores and dumping of waste from this activity without any treatment.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:37:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Security | China accuses US of cyber attack against time management center</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/19/seguranca-china-acusa-eua-de-ciberataque-contra-centro-que-gere-o-horario/</link><description>Chinese authorities accuse the NSA of carrying out cyber attacks against the National Time Service Center that put activities such as the financial system, transport or space launches at risk.
 
The Chinese Ministry of State Security (MSS) yesterday accused the United States of carrying out a cyber attack against the National Time Service Center, the institution responsible for maintaining the accuracy of the country's official time.
In an article published in a messaging application, the MSS, which is China's main intelligence agency, claims to have recently discovered “irrefutable evidence” of a “major cyberattack” orchestrated by the US National Security Agency (NSA) against the aforementioned institution to “steal secrets, infiltrate and sabotage”.
The ministry explains that the National Time Service Center (NTSC) provides essential services for sectors such as energy, transport and defense, and that a cyber attack could result in network failures, problems for the financial system, blackouts, transport interruptions or space launch failures.
According to China, the US' “systematic and long-planned” attack against the NTSC began in 2022 through a vulnerability in the SMS service (short messages) of a “foreign brand” of cell phones, which allowed it to “covertly attack and gain control of the cell phones of several NTSC employees and steal confidential data stored on them”.
A year later, the NSA used stolen credentials to access the NTSC computer network and spy and, in June 2024, launched “high-intensity cyber attacks against several internal network systems” of the institution, the Chinese secret services claim.
“National security authorities responded to the attacks by gathering evidence of U.S. cyberattacks, ordering the NTSC to conduct an investigation, interrupting the chain of attacks, and improving prevention capabilities to eliminate potential threats,” the article states.
Continuous war
In recent years, China and the US have accused each other of numerous cyber attacks, and the MSS reiterated this accusation yesterday: “Spy agencies, led by the NSA, have acted recklessly, carrying out continuous cyber attacks against China, Southeast Asia, Europe and South America.”
In this case, the accusation comes days before a new round of face-to-face negotiations between Beijing and Washington to try to ease renewed trade tensions between the world's two main economic powers.
Furthermore, the presidents of China and the USA, Xi Jinping and Donald Trump respectively, are expected to meet later this month during the APEC (Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation) leaders' summit, which will take place in South Korea.</description><pubDate>2025-10-19 23:36:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuca Roseta, fado singer: “Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/06/cuca-roseta-fadista-o-fado-e-um-samba-poesia-cantado-vindo-do-coracao/</link><description>During the pandemic, she sang for the Macau public through a video concert, but now, the fado singer gives her heart and soul to a concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra, part of the lineup for the Macau International Music Festival, next Saturday, 11th. In an interview with HM, Cuca Roseta talks about the show's lineup, her 15-year career and the truth found in her compositions.
Performs in Macau on October 11th with the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM). Tell me a little about what we can expect from this show.
Yes, we are finally going to Macau. It will be the first time because we previously did a video concert for Macau during the pandemic, and we were unable to be there physically. We now work with OCM, which is very good, and I am happy with this partnership, for being able to unite, in some way, two cultures. We are a little anxious about that fact.
The concert will have songs such as “Meu”, “Preto e Branco”, “Canção do Mar”, “Não Sei de Onde” and “Finalmente”. What does this alignment bring us?
We already had arrangements made for orchestra by Marinho de Freitas, which are extraordinary arrangements, and which will be adapted to the traditional OCM instruments. These songs are practically all written by me, lyrics and music, and tell different stories, some that I have lived myself or stories that, in some way, I have experienced someone living very closely. They are original fados. “Canção do Mar” is very old and became known in the voices of Dulce Pontes and Amália Rodrigues, and has a new arrangement. We thought it would look beautiful with OCM. Of course, there are songs that we always sing and that never leave the repertoire, linked to traditional phases of my career. There are some songs that people like and request, but we bring a completely different repertoire to what we presented at the time [in Macau, with the video concert], which was very well received. It was a concert that went very well, even though it was via video, and we received wonderful messages.
This year he released the album “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu”, which has an exclusively Brazilian repertoire, with several names in Brazilian music, such as Seu Jorge or Zeca Pagodinho. Why explore this universe, mixing it with the language of Fado?
Yes, but this year I will also release a French album with Amália Rodrigues' agent, who invited me. But “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu” came from an invitation from a great Brazilian producer to record old sambas, which have a lot to do with Fado. Even though it's a Brazilian album, all sambas, it's my saddest album of all, the most melancholic. That's why we went looking for this root of samba to find great poets and great composers that Brazil has, and who have this weight that Fado also has.
As?
Fado has a lot to do with words and composition, in fact, Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart, because there has to be this truth in the interpretation, the idea of ​​truth coming from life's experiences, in transforming the story it tells. This melancholy is in the veins of Portuguese blood and is mixed with art and music. This invitation wanted to put a fado singer to sing seriously and with the weight that Fado brings, and be able to interpret the great poets and sambas. The album [Até a Fé Se Esqueceu] has very old sambas, one of them from 1937. It is, therefore, a very strong and even very beautiful album, with great poems and composers, such as Tom Jobim, Vinicius de Morais, and wonderful partnerships with Seu Jorge and Zeca Pagodinho, who came to Fado. It's an album that made me really proud.

Therefore, it is possible to marry Fado with the joy of samba, which also has a melancholic side, right? Like the melancholy of our Fado.
In fact, when we hear the word samba we think of joy, but in fact the basis of samba is not joy. There is that phrase by Vinicius de Morais, “To make a samba beautifully you need a bit of sadness, otherwise you won’t make a samba”. So that's where the beauty of this work lies, which goes to the roots of samba and shows that there aren't that many differences between the melancholy at the root of samba and the melancholy of Fado. It's a nostalgic and melancholic album, it doesn't bring that joy. It can bring hope, and we can say that some themes bring with them this hope, which we find in Brazilian culture and drums. Because they literally put their sadness on the skirt wheel and on the drums, right? They transform sadness into dance and music, but in this work we don't see that type of samba.
Cuca also has a previous album, “Cabo Verde Nha Cretcheu”, so it can be said that she has explored, in her career, the different Portuguese-speaking sounds, going beyond Fado, mixing sounds?
This album didn't come from my will, and I think [it's a sign] that life takes me, deep down. This album was born from a tour I took across the nine islands of Cape Verde with a live recording of the mornas I sang on each island, as I sang the traditional mornas of each island. Between one island and another there are very different moraines. What I did was, after my Fado concerts, I sang two mornas and then we compiled all the songs in Creole in celebration of the fact that I was the first international artist to do the nine islands in a row. But I was also in Goa and did my concert in Concanim. I find it easy and enjoy learning the traditional songs of the countries where I am going to sing. I already sang in Moscow and learned a Russian song; I learned the songs of Goa, and in Georgia, in Tblisi, I also learned a song. It's a treat I make when I travel around the world taking Fado. But morna is wonderful and there really are similarities between this musical genre, and I wanted to bring this encounter between Fado and morna to Cape Verdeans, and this album came about, which is beautiful.
Since it goes to Macau, can we expect a song in Cantonese, or Mandarin?
Yes. By chance, I had already spoken to my manager to contact someone in this regard, so that we could discover a traditional song that I could learn.
Last year, he celebrated 15 years of career. How do you review your career, which began with the albums “Cuca Roseta” and “Raiz”?
In fact, it was great to celebrate 15 years at MEO Arena [the concert hall in Lisbon], and be able to revisit all the albums since the first. “Raiz” opened up something that is rarer, which is the fado singer composing and writing her lyrics. This was a record that went wonderfully well and, from then on, it was good, because in this search for the truth that Fado has, being able to compose and write your own lyrics always means giving a little more of yourself. Each person composes and writes in their own way, and when they can do it, it is always a bit like the lines on the palm of their hand, that is, it is something unique. In this search that people make to follow standards to achieve success, I believe that success exists when we are not afraid to follow our voice and our instinct, what comes from our heart, tell our stories and sing our melodies without fear. In this way we end up becoming unique. Although it is not usual in Fado for a fado singer to compose and write, it was nice to see that my songs became important to many fans. Sometimes I have great composers and poets [to collaborate with me], but I think [writing and composing] brings out this side of the person being more truthful. My poems can never be compared to those of the great poets I have sung, but I think people feel that I am more in my own skin. In a way, this touches and moves them. Celebrating 15 years of career was the closing of a cycle and the beginning of another, and it was great to return to the “roots”, and realize that that was where the “gunpowder” lay, in the sense of not being afraid of ourselves.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 05:24:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Hui So-ying, protagonist of the film “Ah Ying”: “Representing is being human”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/30/hui-so-ying-protagonista-do-filme-ah-ying-representar-e-ser-se-humano/</link><description>In 1983, Hong Kong cinema, through the lens of Allen Fong, revealed “Ah Ying”, a film that portrays the hard life of a girl who sells fish in the market and dreams of becoming an actress. That girl was Hui So-ying and “Ah Ying” was inspired by her life. HM spoke to the actress on the sidelines of “Making Waves – 2nd Hong Kong Cinema Exhibition”, which took place this weekend in Lisbon
 
How did you get involved in this film project?
The main reason I got involved in this film was because my theater teacher passed away. So I felt like I needed to do something to honor him, because he was the one who taught me how to act. So I tried to be an actress. Later, when [director] Allen Fong met me, he found my life story interesting, and he also ended up meeting some of my family members. Then he asked if they were also interested in participating in the film, which led to many of them also ending up joining the project. The film also shows the environment in which my teacher lived, it is a portrait of experiences and stories lived by me and my teacher.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in those times. How did you prepare for the character?
The beauty of this film is closely related to the collaborations that were made, particularly in photography and costumes. It took many collaborations to create the beauty that exists in the film. It was hard work taking on the character [of Ah Ying], because the story was designed to describe some of my past experiences, and that's what the director wanted to do. But that was difficult for me, because there were some things I didn't want to face, but I had to. Of course, I later realized that, deep down, it was nothing, and I even felt relieved after finishing filming. Thinking about whether the story was a form of art or reality, when I was performing, I had to enter the situation of the moment because, in fact, the [real] episode had already passed, but I had to have certain feelings again during the performance. As an actress, it was a big test.
“Ah Ying” is considered one of the great films of the so-called “New Wave” of Hong Kong cinema. During the screening, did you expect the film to be successful?
I didn't think about it, but throughout the project I thought that Allen Fong was a very daring director, because a film of this kind had never been made in the entire history of Hong Kong cinema. It's a kind of “docudrama”, and he had the strength and courage to innovate the way he filmed it, which, at the time, was unprecedented.
What was the biggest challenge you faced in this film?
It was having to return to my old self. There were things I didn't want to face and I had to face them again, with the same feeling I had at that time.
Many years have passed between 1983 and the present. Looking back, what meaning did this film have for you, as a person and actress?
In fact, after seeing the film, I saw it as just a story. For me, acting is being human, every day is a performance.
The film portrays life in Hong Kong in the 1980s and has received a restored version. What do you think this project can bring to a younger audience watching the film today?
This year the film was shown several times, and I always ask the same question, whether people don't understand the film or whether they think it can't be immersive enough. In fact, given my experience, most younger viewers responded that this is not the case, that the film is quite real. I don't think this film is outdated or out of fashion just because times have progressed or society has changed. I don't think so.
“Ah Ying” closed, in Lisbon, the second edition of “Making Waves – Hong Kong Film Festival”. How do you feel about seeing this film shown in Portugal?
I found it interesting. I never thought that the film could be shown at this exhibition, I don't know if it was because there was a restored copy. Before this new version it was more difficult to display it. The public can see a film that shows family relationships experienced in the 80s, and I think that the film can be immersive [in the theme], when it addresses family conflicts, because everyone has a family. Watching the film, you may wonder what your relationship with your family is like. Of course, I also hope you learned more about Hong Kong. But, despite this film taking place in the 80s, it focuses a lot on family and interpersonal relationships.
Is there an episode from filming that left an impression on you?
There were several moments throughout the film, but the one that left the biggest impression on me was the last scene, in the interview, in which I was talking to a chair, but it was as if I were talking to my teacher. When I see this scene again I am always moved, because my teacher has already passed away, but all of this still makes a huge impression on me.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:42:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra: “The heroic relationships” of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/03/jorge-figueira-arquitecto-e-academico-da-universidade-de-coimbra-as-relacoes-heroicas-de-macau/</link><description>He has been writing and thinking about architecture for a long time, and Jorge Figueira, architect and academic at the University of Coimbra, has been doing so in Macau since then. After a session this week in which he highlighted the former Fai Chi Kei public housing complex, by Manuel Vicente, Jorge Figueira addresses the legacy of Nuno Portas today at the Rui Cunha Foundation
 
Participate today in the conference “Nuno Portas: from Architecture to Urbanism, from Man to City”. What legacy did this Portuguese architect leave?
Nuno Portas is someone who, at the end of the 50s, had a critical activity that was completely innovative and pioneering in the Portuguese context. Then, in the 60s, he had a more international activity, having been the first to publicize the work of Siza Vieira. It was there that he had his first contacts with Spanish and Italian architects, mainly. During those years he also wrote two books that were also unusual, such as “Architecture for Today”, in 1964, and “City as Architecture”, in 1969. They were also an extraordinary way of trying to understand what was happening in terms of international currents in architecture. But later he also had an [important] activity as an architect alongside Nuno Teotónio Pereira, namely in the work on the Church of the Sacred Heart of Jesus, in Lisbon, and in a house in Vila Viçosa. Then, on April 25, 1974, he was appointed Secretary of State for Housing and Urbanism and launched SAAL – Outpatient Services for Local Support, a completely revolutionary social housing program, in keeping with the spirit of the time. Afterwards, Nuno Portas dedicated himself more to urban planning issues and not so much to architecture. He was linked to the beginning of Expo 98. He ended up being someone who, in the last 20 years of his work, began to have more scientific and sociological concerns, and less artistic ones. It's something he had from the beginning, but later it became the center of his activity.
Did Nuno Portas have any relationship with Macau?
I think that the relationships would not be as intense compared to other architects and contexts, but we know that Nuno Portas was in Macau at the invitation of the Government for a conference, between 2001 and 2002. It is interesting because from this passage we have echoes of what happened, such as his surprise when discovering Manuel Vicente's Ellen Liang orphanage, which he did not know about. It was Manuel Vicente's first work in Macau, in the 60s, and we know that Nuno Portas was moved when visiting this work, especially the small chapel that exists in the orphanage. It's interesting because there was no direct relationship between Manuel Vicente and Nuno Portas, they are figures at very different poles, and even opposites. There is also an interesting and positive reference to the Siza plan [Vieira, Plano de Expansão da Cidade de Macau (Areia Preta e Porto Exterior, 1982), which is being built when Nuno Portas visits Macau. It is interesting that he commented on this plan because in the 60s and 70s the relationship between Nuno Portas and Siza Vieira was no longer the same, and the fact that he made complimentary references to Siza is very interesting.
He was a student of Nuno Portas. What other aspects of your career or personality can you highlight?
I also worked with him. He was a cultured man, very intelligent and with an overwhelming memory. He was someone who liked to provoke, but in a good way, to argue, to contradict. I was lucky enough to maintain a decades-long dialogue with him, and it is this personal knowledge that I will pass on. I also notice that he was a man very close to the power in Lisbon, to the parties, but always very independent. He was a personal friend of Jorge Sampaio, he was Secretary of State, but he never had a major political role. On the one hand, this is due to his independence, but on the other he was such a controversial and intelligently restless figure, that I think power was also scared of him.
This week he also spoke at the conference “Lisbon, Porto, Macau, Maputo: Heroic Collective Housing from the 60s &amp; 70s”. How do you describe Macau’s public housing projects in those years?
There are many architects I could talk about, but I focused on the work of Manuel Vicente in Macau, namely the public housing complex in Fai Chi Kei, which was demolished and later gave rise to the project by Rui Leão and Carlota Bruni. I didn't specifically talk about Portuguese or Macanese architects, we also have names like, for example, José Maneiras. Especially because Portuguese architects have always been few in Portugal, and from the 1950s there were around 150, later increasing greatly in number. But I paid [at the conference] a tribute to the Portuguese architects who built during that period, because in a complex territory and with its vicissitudes, different from those that existed in Portugal, they knew how to carry out extraordinary architectural experiments in the field of public housing. I tried to demonstrate what was happening in Lisbon, Porto, Macau and Lourenço Marques, now Maputo, in different ways. In Macau, relationships were established, which I call heroic, in the sense that they were relationships of experimental architecture, in which people had to adapt, have their own spirit. These are architectures that already have a bit of history, as 50 or 60 years have passed, but the examples we find in these cities continue to be remarkable.
What projects do you highlight from these years?
I spoke about the “Pantera Cor-de-Rosa” housing development, by Gonçalo Byrne, in Chelas, Lisbon. I showed “Cinco Fingers”, by Vítor Figueiredo, also from Lisbon, and “Bairro da Bouça”, by Siza Vieira, in Porto. I showed the Fai Chi Kei complex, by Manuel Vicente, and a project by Pancho Guedes in Mozambique. Despite being distant in time, these are architectures that remain fundamental references from a cultural and architectural point of view. There is a kind of narrative luck in being able to talk about such different places, and with such different architects, and show how they had this heroic, experimental, moving, even radical side that the architecture of that period in particular had.
Has Macau had a positive evolution with regard to the supply of public housing?
I arrived in August and have been visiting the territory in recent years, so I have been following this process a little. Macau is, obviously, an extraordinary territory and due to the coexistence of very different cultures when it comes to housing, which here has a scale and expression completely different from that of Portugal. In Portugal there is an aversion to public housing towers, it has always been something unusual and the results that are known have not been successful for various reasons. But in Macau this is exactly what we see, public housing in towers and with a very strong expression. This has to do with the characteristics of the territory and also with a certain culture in China and Hong Kong. This does not mean that everything being built in Macau is good, there are towers and buildings with less interesting solutions or that result from a certain repetition. But there is no city that only has good architecture or good public housing. The challenge is to solve the housing problem on a large scale, something that must be studied and thought about. It is beautiful and overwhelming to see that Macau is a territory that grows day after day and it is exciting to observe this from an architectural point of view as well. That's what I'm doing, working on future projects.
Analysis projects, or academic ones?
Yes, I'm a professor and researcher at the University of Coimbra and a columnist for the Público newspaper, so my job is to analyze and investigate. I've already published a lot about Macau and I want to go back to some points that I left unresolved, so to speak. I am very encouraged by everything I have seen and the people I have spoken to, and perhaps I will increase my work on the territory from an academic and research point of view.
At a time when Portugal has a chronic housing problem, with a lack of public housing, could Macau be an example?
Not directly, because of the typological issue of the housing tower. It might not be a welcome model in the Portuguese context. But without a doubt, Portugal needs to learn from other experiences and other territories and needs to find solutions. Certainly, what is happening in Hong Kong and Macau are experiences that are very interesting to know, not to replicate, but to understand that this is a global problem [the lack of housing].
Remember Nuno Portas
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will host today, starting at 6:30 pm, the conference “Nuno Portas: from architecture to urbanism, from man to city”, with Jorge Figueira. It will be time to talk about a journey that the recently deceased architect began in 1959, with a text about the new generation of the Modern Movement in Portugal. Texts followed in the 60s and 70s with “scientific approaches”, with Nuno Portas wandering between architecture and urbanism, always in a reflective way. Nuno Portas was a “multifaceted figure, best known for launching the SAAL social housing program, which is still the subject of research and an example today”, describes Jorge Figueira in a note. The speaker is linked to the Center for Social Studies and the Department of Architecture of the University of Coimbra.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 23:33:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Anabela Santiago, academic: “China is reformist and moderate”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/anabela-santiago-academica-a-china-e-reformista-e-moderada/</link><description>Anabela Santiago has just defended her doctoral thesis at the University of Aveiro that analyzes how China has positioned itself, in recent decades, as an important actor in “Global Health Governance”. Today, Beijing is looking for “alternative mechanisms” of cooperation in the “Global South” and is trying to build an alternative model to the World Health Organization
 
 
Let’s start with the concept of global health governance (GGS). Is it a more contemporary concept or one related to the post-World War II period and the founding of the World Health Organization (WHO)? Who have been the main actors in this governance until China's growth?
GGS is a concept whose prominence and relevance has grown significantly in the 21st century, largely driven by economic globalization and global interconnection. Although global health has always transcended national borders, requiring multidisciplinary approaches and international cooperation, it has only been since the 1990s that greater awareness has been made of it. Historically, GGS has been predominantly influenced by Western powers and neoliberal values. The main actors in this governance, until the rise of China, were historically marked by interventions from entities such as the WHO and non-governmental organizations, predominantly North American and European.
One of the conclusions of his doctoral thesis is that China has gradually positioned itself in this leadership. When and why did this positioning begin?
Yes, China has progressively positioned itself as a key player in the evolution of the GGS system. Although it is not possible to pinpoint an exact start date, China has evolved from a relatively isolated country to a major player in the global political, economic and technological arenas. Its growing economic and political influence also represents a change in the historical dynamics of the GGS, as in the 1960s China tried to play a role in humanitarian health assistance in neighboring countries and in Africa. The thesis highlights that China's experience can be seen as an example of what is achievable when a State chooses its own path instead of a pre-established model, aligning with the prediction of the 21st century as the “Asian Century”.
Did the years of the pandemic influence this position? In what way?
The Covid-19 pandemic has highlighted the need for global health cooperation, as well as the potential consequences of failing to prioritize global health. The thesis explores the evolution of the Health Silk Road before and after the pandemic, indicating that the years of the pandemic allowed for greater awareness of the need for instruments such as the Health Silk Road as platforms for more effective cooperation between Nations. Although not detailed in this specific section, it is implicit that the pandemic has intensified China's role in health diplomacy and health development assistance.
Looking at the internal reforms that China has carried out in the health sector, which ones do you highlight as the most important?
In the thesis, I address the reforms of China's healthcare system and highlight that the Chinese governance model is a unique combination of market-oriented economic reforms and state-led development, incorporating elements of neoliberalism and authoritarianism in political issues in general, with the healthcare sector being no different from the rest. One of China's contributions mentioned, recognized by the WHO, is its primary health care model based on the recognized good practice of “barefoot doctors”. Furthermore, the thesis analyzes the main reform policies and their progress and challenges in the period 2009-2018, which include primary healthcare reforms, hospital and pharmaceutical reform. The “Healthy China 2030” program is also an important and ambitious benchmark for China's domestic health reforms, also covering social determinants.
Is Beijing's intention to create an alternative entity to the WHO, or simply to create an alternative movement that can coexist with the WHO, in the context of its relationship with the Global South? How could this work?
The thesis suggests that China adopts a “dual approach”: while integrating into existing global structures, it simultaneously forges alternative paths, particularly through regional alliances such as the BRICS and partnerships with the Global South. This indicates an intention to create an alternative movement that can coexist with and complement the role of the WHO, rather than a direct alternative entity. China demonstrates a clear commitment to aligning the objectives of the “Belt and Road” initiative with the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals, showing its willingness to present these initiatives as complements to the cooperation mechanisms already existing in the international liberal order. President Xi Jinping's vision of a “Community of Shared Future for Humanity”, which includes the notion of “Global Health Community for All”, also points to a new perspective in the scope of international cooperation.
Masks, vaccines and Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM): what products or instruments are used by China to position itself as an increasingly global actor in GGS?
The thesis highlights that China is an indispensable provider of global public health goods, essential for the supply chain of products, such as masks and vaccines. TCM is also mentioned as one of China's great contributions to global health governance, with its treatments derived from Chinese herbs, some of which were already recognized by the WHO in 2017. Furthermore, Chinese medical assistance and medical teams sent to other regions of the globe are important instruments of Chinese health diplomacy.
In creating an alternative movement or reality to the WHO, could China be taking advantage of the lack of full representation in that same WHO, or gaps in its functioning?
The thesis does not directly address whether China is taking advantage of a lack of full representation in the WHO or gaps in its functioning. However, she emphasizes that the work aims to fill a gap in scientific knowledge regarding the health governance paradigm from a non-Western and liberal perspective, emphasizing China as an actor in the Global South. This suggests that China seeks to strengthen alternative models that can offer more personalized solutions to health challenges, different from those advocated by Western countries, positioning itself as a moderate reformist actor.
How has the European Union's (EU) foreign policy towards China affected or influenced the country's position in global health governance?
In the thesis, the fourth publication, entitled “Challenges on the European Union-China cooperation in higher education from ‘people-to-people dialogue’ perspective: The case of health-related joint projects”, explores cooperation in higher education, in particular that which includes projects related to health. It appears, therefore, that, despite strategic and economic dialogue, the deterioration of EU-China bilateral relations has intensified, with the Commission assuming a decline in enthusiasm due to “China's countermeasures to EU sanctions on human rights, economic coercion and trade measures against the single market, and China's position in the war in Ukraine”. Although challenges and tensions are recognized, cooperation in higher education, including health projects, is seen as part of a broader framework of building a strategic partnership between the EU and China. However, it is clear that there is no long tradition of health cooperation between the EU and China in higher education, and that there are few joint projects compared to the general picture. It is suggested that both the EU and China should make more efforts to align medical study curricula and promote more joint research in areas related to health, infectious diseases, among others.
In the Trump 2.0 era, and without a pandemic, what could China's role be in global health governance?
Although the thesis will be published this year, it focuses on the period leading up to and including the pandemic, where I do not directly speculate on a future scenario of “Trump 2.0” without a pandemic. However, the thesis argues that China is not just a participant but a moderate reformist force in shaping global health norms. Regardless of future political scenarios, its growing economic and political influence, strategic health diplomacy, domestic reforms and initiatives such as the Health Silk Road will continue to shape its role in global health governance. The vision of a “Global Health Community for All” also remains a guiding principle for China's efforts.
Does this power of China in the GGS occur more with bilateral or multilateral agreements?
The thesis suggests that China's power in global health governance is manifested through both bilateral and multilateral agreements, but with an increasing emphasis on certain forms of cooperation that strengthen its role in the Global South and through alternative mechanisms. Although the thesis does not explicitly quantify the predominance between bilateral and multilateral, the focus on regional alliances (BRICS) and partnerships with the Global South (which often involve bilateral agreements and group cooperation initiatives) and the Health Silk Road indicate a hybrid approach.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 23:46:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied the right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on permanence, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (even in 2011 the Municipal Council of Faro wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
The gentlemen we are talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a member of the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Motorsport | MSAR comics with special debut in Japan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/26/automobilismo-banda-desenhada-da-raem-com-estreia-especial-no-japao/</link><description>The Macau comic strip, “Heróis do Circuito” (街道), had its first international appearance in a very special way two weeks ago, at the 1000 km of Suzuka, in Japan
The classic endurance race had not been contested since 2019, and, to mark the return of this iconic race in the Land of the Rising Sun, Porsche Motorsport Asia Pacific decided to decorate the three cars it supported with the Stuttgart brand's historic colors. Among them, one of Absolute Racing's Porsche 911 GT3 R was painted yellow and black, in honor of Joest Racing's victory in the 1985 24 Hours of Le Mans, when Portuguese Domingos Piedade was Sporting Director of the German team. With the current sponsors, and not with the French clothing brand NewMan, responsible for the decoration 40 years ago, the inscription in Portuguese stood out on the rear wing of the Porsche 911 GT3 R nº 7: “Heróis do Circuito”.
For those who follow local motor sport closely, the comic strip “Heróis do Circuito” is already part of the territory’s motoring culture. Passionate about the ninth art and a self-confessed devotee of motor sports, MP Man is the “Jean Graton of Macau”. His title, often seen on cars at local Grand Prix races, has this time reached an international stage.
Regarding participation in the most prestigious endurance race for GT3 cars on the Asian continent, MP Man told HM: "Upon receiving this exciting news, I felt surprise and admiration. This recognition not only values ​​the effort and dedication of years, but also opens a door for the presence of an original Macau brand on the international motorsport stages, allowing us to show the world the unique cultural character and creativity of Macau, an honor that fills me with pride and enthusiasm.”
The international debut could not have gone better in sporting terms, as Absolute Racing's #7 Porsche 911 GT3 R, driven by Kévin Estre, Laurens Vanthoor and Patrick Pilet, crossed the line in second place overall, in a race that also scored points for the Intercontinental GT Challenge.
Bring together synergies
Interestingly, the springboard for placing the MSAR cartoon on a top car from Absolute Racing, an Asian team supported by Porsche Motorsport Asia Pacific and with several triumphs in the Macau GT Cup, was a common sponsor: a model car brand from southern China.
"We maintain a close and friendly relationship with the renowned national collector model brand Almost Real. The founder, Liu Xueshen, Mr. Sum, has always enthusiastically supported my comic book, and has now become one of the main sponsors.
With an ambitious vision, they intend to take the work across borders, exploring new horizons", explained the author, responsible for some of the illustrations on display at the Macau Grand Prix Museum. "By becoming sponsors of Absolute Racing, they integrated elements of the Heróis do Circuito brand into the racing car's paintwork, allowing the vehicle, when running on the track, to announce to the world the unique charm of the comic strip.”
For MP Man, who launched the first issue of “Heróis do Circuito” in 2018, the objective is clear: “For racing and comic book fans to pay more attention to the original creation made in Macau and recognize the effort dedicated to this project.”
Looking to the future
Presence at the Suzuka event, which brought together more than 65 thousand spectators, constituted a decisive step in the brand's internationalization.
"Now, “Heroes of the Circuit” has reached a moment of great significance. Like an eagle taking flight, he has successfully joined a team supported by Porsche, participating in an endurance race that brings together the best teams and drivers from all over Asia", says MP Man, who does not hide his ambition to go further. "If one day my brand manages to reach races like Le Mans, or even a Formula 1 Grand Prix, it will be a dream come true! (laughs) This is, without a doubt, my deepest desire. But I also know that dreams do not come true immediately; my work still has a lot to evolve and perfect. I will continue to create with humility, persevering in improving the work, seeking to offer readers ever more experiences exciting.”
Meanwhile, the fourth volume of the “Circuit Heroes” series is about to be published, opening a new chapter, always with its unique charm and captivating narratives that have won the attention and affection of the local public, increasingly establishing itself in the global universe of comics and among motor sports fans.</description><pubDate>2025-09-26 07:21:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Vernice Lao, just 15 years old, made her F4 debut in Chengdu</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/19/vernice-lao-de-apenas-15-anos-estreou-se-na-f4-em-chengdu/</link><description>In an initiative supported by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Marcus Cheong and Vernice Lao participated in the Chengdu race of the Chinese Formula 4 Championship. The two drivers from local karting competed against some of the best single-seater drivers in the region, and for young Vernice Lao, this was an absolute debut in motorsport.
At the newly built Tianfu Chengdu International Circuit, Marcus Cheong returned to the Formula 4 discipline, having already had several forays into the category, having even finished in 12th place in the 2023 Macau Grand Prix Formula 4 Race.
On this return, the Macau driver drove one of the Mygale chassis, the same as those that will be used in the FIA ​​World Cup at the Guia Circuit, at the end of the year, by the Apollo RFN Racing by Blackjack team. In the sister team Asia Racing Team, founded in Macau in 2003, and also supported by AAMC, 15-year-old Vernice Lao took her first steps in motor racing, after two days of testing in Zhuhai with the single-seater built in France.
Rodolfo Ávila, Team Manager of the team of the two drivers from the territory, highlighted "how fantastic it is to see two drivers supported by the AAMC, something that has a special meaning for me, as I also took my first steps in the single-seater competition with the support of the AAMC. Seeing these young talents from Macau following a similar path is extremely gratifying, and their participation has a very special importance for both me and the team."
Consistent results
After Friday's qualifying sessions, in Saturday's first race Marcus Cheong reached sixth place in the CFGP class and finished 12th overall. Vernice Lao ranked 6th in the Formula 4 class for young drivers, occupying 18th position overall. In the second race of the same day, Marcus Cheong repeated the result, again taking 6th place in the CFGP class and 12th place overall. Vernice Lao finished in 23rd place, also securing 6th position in the Formula 4 class.
In the first race on Sunday, Marcus Cheong improved his performance, reaching 5th place in the CFGP class and 10th place overall. In turn, Vernice Lao finished 7th in Formula 4, corresponding to 19th overall. In the final clash of the weekend, Marcus Cheong shone by taking 2nd place in the CFGP class, also obtaining an honorable 6th place in the general classification. As for Vernice Lao, she finished 13th overall, securing a consistent 6th position in the Formula 4 class.
Very positive balance
On a particularly demanding weekend, with variable track conditions, Portuguese Rodolfo Ávila highlighted the performance of the Macau drivers supported by AAMC, Marcus Cheong and Vernice Lao. "Both showed clear progress throughout the weekend and Vernice, in particular, impressed everyone with a clean and confident debut in single-seaters. Competing against such an experienced field, with so little experience in a Formula 4 car, and delivering the performance she achieved was a pleasant surprise", said the 2003 Asian Formula Renault champion.
On social media, Vernice Lao reported that this was “an incredible experience”, adding that “over the weekend we lost a lot, but we ended up achieving a satisfactory result”. The Macao SAR driver acknowledged that “there is still a long way to go” and took the opportunity to thank “the support and encouragement” from the team, the Team Manager and her teammate, in what she classified as “an unforgettable weekend with the Asia Racing Team”.
The next step for the two drivers from the territory is not yet known, but the Chinese Formula 4 Championship ends in the neighboring city of Zhuhai on the weekend of October 11th and 12th. Afterwards, these same cars from the Chinese competition will be reviewed before traveling to Macau, where they will be used in the FIA ​​World Cup.</description><pubDate>2025-09-19 00:42:07</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Entry lists presented did not disappoint</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/16/gp-macau-listas-de-inscritos-apresentadas-nao-desapontaram/</link><description>Last Monday, the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix presented the 72nd edition of the biggest sporting event in the territory. In total, there will be seven grids of GT, touring cars, single-seaters and motorcycles that will provide, between qualifying races and races, a total of eleven unpredictable battles for victory in the always charismatic and world-respected Guia Circuit
The Macao SAR will have 19 riders in total, spread across four races in the program, as it will not have riders in either the GT race, the Motorcycle Grand Prix or the Guia Race. The territory will be represented by Charles Leong Hon Chio at the Macau Grand Prix – FIA FR World Cup. The champion of this season's PRO class of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia moves on to Formula Regional, a category that has not been raced since 2020, when it was still called F3 (!) in Asia.
Tiago Rodrigues, in his third participation in the event, and Marcus Cheong, in his second, will defend the colors of the Macao SAR in the first edition of the F4 World Cup, a race that will feature seven former F4 champions or equivalent. The rest of the territory's delegation will compete in the GT Cup – Great Bay Race, with seven drivers, and in the Macau Roadsport Challenge, with nine.
We have to go back to the beginning of the 1970s to find such a low presence of Portuguese drivers in a Grand Prix. In addition to young Tiago Rodrigues, veterans of the territory Rui Valente and Jerónimo Badaraco will be present, both in the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. The universe of Lusophony is completed with the Brazilian Ethan Nobels, who will make his debut at the Guia Circuit in the F4 race.
Portugal's last representation in the race dates back to the 2022 Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, when André Pires and Sheridan Morais overcame mandatory confinement, with Morais achieving a podium, a unique feat for Portuguese motorcycling. In cars, the last participation was in 2019, when Tiago Monteiro drove a Honda Civic Type-R TCR in the Guia Race.
Interestingly, at a time when there is an increase in female participation in motorsport events worldwide, there is not a single lady among the more than one hundred and sixty drivers registered in the Grand Prix.
Mercedes smudges the paint
After two years with pelotons with two dozen GT3 cars, the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup is once again below that benchmark number. Fortunately, the sixteen cars from six different manufacturers, including the returning McLaren, will be driven by drivers with world-class credentials. Well-known names from Macau, such as Edoardo Mortara or Raffaele Marciello, joined by the new hero of Chinese motorsport, the winner of the 24 Hours of Le Mans, Ye Yifei, alleviate any disappointments. If Audi Sport Asia, at a time when the Ingolstadt brand is disinvesting in GT races, had backed down, we would have fewer cars than in the 2018 edition, where only fifteen machines lined up.
The introduction of torque sensors in this year's race – a costly decision made entirely by the FIA ​​– was at the heart of Mercedes-AMG's decision not to participate in the event. The German brand's business model involves registering cars in partnership with teams from the region at the event. In Southeast Asia, cars are constantly on the move via containerized transport, leaving little opportunity for conversion work and sensor testing, which is imperative for Mercedes-AMG. Everyone is certain that the Stuttgart brand will return to the Guia Circuit in the near future, but this year Maro Engel will not be able to defend the crown won last year.
Classics maintain their aura
With Michael Rutter's absence confirmed, there was a lot of apprehension about the entry list for the Motorcycle Grand Prix, but the presence of Davey Todd, last year's winner, and Peter Hickman will keep the race on the international radar. Twelve countries, all European, will be represented on a grid that this year will feature four newcomers, while of the four brands present, BMW and Honda make up more than 70% of the twenty entries.
Notably, no rider competes on a Kawasaki, marking the first time this decade that the company, which next year celebrates 130 years since its founding, has not had a presence in Asia's premier motorcycle road race.
At a time when Tourist racing is experiencing a less vigorous moment worldwide, the Guia Race already has twenty-four cars registered, three of which will still have to be filled by drivers to be nominated. The presence of the stars of the FIA ​​TCR World Tour, which is once again decided on the local circuit, is always synonymous with a good show on the track.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 02:48:16</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau: First names and first questions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/10/gp-macau-primeiros-nomes-e-primeiras-duvidas/</link><description>October is usually the month of preparations for the Macau Grand Prix. With the championships coming to an end all over the world, attention turns to the Macao SAR's big event, which this year will take place from the 13th to the 16th of November
 
After Marcos Cheong and Vernice Lau raced in the Chinese Formula 4 Championship race, this weekend it is Tiago Rodrigues' turn to pick up the helmet again to compete in the closing race of the Chinese competition season, on the circuit in the neighboring city of Zhuhai. The former Chinese champion of the discipline has been away from single-seater racing since participating in the Middle East Formula 4 Championship at the beginning of the year, but his experience could prove to be an asset in defending the territory's colors at the Guia Circuit.
Twenty of the Mygale M21-F4 single-seaters from the Chinese championship will be overhauled after this race at the Zhuhai International Circuit and handed over to technicians appointed by the French Automobile Sports Federation (FFSA), who will put them on the track in the first edition of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup, in Macau. This is the same model used in the French Formula 4 Championship.
Some names of the bikes
Michael Rutter's absence from the entry list for this year's Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix is ​​now a certainty. However, through the specialized press, the first names that will shape the only road race on the Asian continent are beginning to become known.
Practically confirmed are the presence of Davey Todd, winner of last year's edition, and Peter Hickman, the motorcyclist who chases Rutter's record of victories and who should be practically recovered from the injuries suffered in the accident on the Isle of Man. Both will drive the official competitive BMW M1000RR from 8TEN Racing. Rob Hodson, SMT Racing driver, has also guaranteed his presence in the Macao SAR, usually being one of the strong candidates for the Top 5 in the race.
But not only renowned names are tested. Among the debutants already confirmed is ramp driver Maurizio Bottalico. The San Marino driver, who reached the podium at the Manx Grand Prix, follows in the footsteps of other great Italian names in 21st century road racing — such as Stefano Bonetti, Luca Gottardi or Alex Polita — by taking on the most famous and feared race in the East.
According to the Road Racing News portal, there will be more newcomers to the Guia Circuit this year, such as Mitch Rees, a driver with several titles in New Zealand, Ryan Whitehall, a driver from the Isle of Wight, and the new holder of the Frohburger Dreieck lap record in the Supersport category, Paul Jordan.
Questions in the GT
Stéphane Ratel, founder and CEO of SRO Motorsports Group — the company that co-organizes the FIA ​​GT World Cup Macau Grand Prix — has been one of the most critical voices regarding the introduction of torque sensors in GT3 racing. However, the FIA ​​decided in favor of its use in the Guia Circuit World Cup, and the French businessman spoke about the matter for the first time.
"The teams competing in Macau are mostly from Asia, where torque sensors have never been used. The lack of experience could affect the sporting balance, and that's why I opposed their use", said Stéphane Ratel to the German magazine Motorsport Aktuell, adding that he does not believe this is the way forward.
Although the SRO Motorsports Group is co-organizer of the event and has a Balance of Performance (BoP) recognized worldwide, in the last two years the Macau BoP has been determined by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA's BoP was subject to a series of criticisms, with teams and drivers – particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main losers – publicly expressing their displeasure at the differences in pace. For this reason, the FIA ​​decided to introduce these expensive sensors, installed on the cars' transmission shafts, which represent the most accurate tool for measuring the power transmitted to the wheels.
“Some manufacturers supported the idea, but others, like Mercedes, were against it,” said Stéphane Ratel. "As a result, we lost some cars from the entry list. To be clear: I look at this issue pragmatically, not dogmatically. Last year in Macau, three or four manufacturers could have won without these torque sensors. In 2025 we will see if this technology is really useful", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-10-10 00:11:25</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA presents 10 teams from the FR World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/12/gp-fia-da-a-conhecer-10-equipas-da-taca-do-mundo-fr/</link><description>On Wednesday night, the International Automobile Federation (FIA), in partnership with the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix, published the official list of teams registered for this year's edition of the Macau Grand Prix – FIA FR World Cup.
Although the names of the Formula Regional (FR) drivers who will visit Macau in November have not been released, according to the official statement from the organization, based in Paris, this “carefully selected squad of ten truly international teams will bring together the best regional talents from around the world to compete in this prestigious, unique race on the iconic Guia Circuit”.
This year's edition welcomes two new major teams to the event: the Italian Trident Motorsport, which arrives in Macau after a 2025 season in which it won the FIA ​​Formula 3 Championship, with the Brazilian Rafael Câmara, and the Dutch Van Amersfoort Racing (VAR), a team that has known the Guia Circuit well since 1998 and that, in 2018, suffered a huge scare with the spectacular accident by Sophia Flörsch.
Returning to defend the coveted title in Macau will be R-ace GP, a European team that won in 2024 with Ugo Ugochukwu, a driver who will not be present this year to try to revalidate the title. The French team remains in great form, leading the current FRECA standings and finishing second in the Middle East Formula Regional Championship earlier this year.
Return of SJM Theodore
Also returning are some of the strongest contenders from last year's Macau Grand Prix and the FR scene in general, including a well-known name from the event: SJM Theodore Prema Racing. The Italian team Prema, currently in second place in the FRECA 2025 championship, is one of the most successful teams in grassroots motorsport and is once again partnering with Teddy Yip Jr. at the Macao SAR event.
Also returning are Pinnacle Motorsport, an Irish-owned team; the Australian Evans GP, which achieved fourth place in the last edition; the Japanese TOM’S Racing, one of the most prestigious in Japanese motorsport; the German PHM Racing; and the always competitive French structures Saintéloc Racing and ART Grand Prix.
On the other hand, the Dutch MP Motorsport, the Australian Kiwi Motorsport and the Japanese TGM Grand Prix left the scene. No team from China was selected, but, unlike last year, none attempted to register for the competition.
The official list of entries should only be made known in mid-October, as is tradition for the Grand Prix.
The second edition of the FIA ​​FR World Cup will take place during the week of the Macau Grand Prix, from 13 to 16 November, and will also feature, for the first time, the FIA ​​F4 World Cup, making the event one of the most prestigious global showcases for the junior single-seater categories.</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:22:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Charles Leong wins Lamborghini Super Trofeo title</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/09/09/charles-leong-conquista-titulo-lamborghini-super-trofeo/</link><description>Macau driver Charles Leong Hon Chio became the winner of the PRO class of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia last weekend, at the Sepang International Circuit, in Malaysia. This represents the Macao SAR driver's first title in Grand Tourism (GT) competitions and the first championship title achieved with SJM Theodore Racing.
Despite being ill and with two races remaining in the calendar of the competition organized by the prestigious Italian car brand, Charles Leong and the young Irishman Alex Denning always proved to be extremely fast on the Malaysian track. They won the first race of the weekend, thus achieving their sixth victory of the season, and finished second in the second race. This second place took the number of podiums achieved in 10 races to 10, extending the team's impressive run, which has never finished lower than second place.
With two races still to be contested at the Lamborghini Super Trofeo World Finals, in Misano, Italy, in November, SJM Theodore Racing will be able to focus on maintaining this impressive run of podiums, with the main objective of the season already achieved. Charles Leong and Alex Denning are tied at the top of the driver standings and are expected to complete the season side by side, sharing the same Lamborghini Huracán Super Trofeo EVO2.
Always adding
For Charles Leong, this result is the result of "incredible work by the team. We won the championship thanks to a great collective effort, without major mistakes and with total consistency. For the race, I expected a bigger group, but it was difficult to fight against my opponents with new tires. In the end, I followed my rhythm and we managed the tires to give the best car to Alex. It was a very good weekend."
After finishing in second place in the classification of this same single-brand trophy, the Macau driver adds this title to those he won at a young age in the Formula Renault Asian Championship and the Chinese Formula 4 Championship, in addition to two notable victories in the Formula 4 Macau Grand Prix.
Obviously satisfied with the results obtained by his pupils, Teddy Yip Jr., owner of SJM Theodore Racing, commented: "I want to congratulate the entire team for this achievement, the result of a collective effort throughout the season and previous years. The drivers responded in an exemplary way to the pressure. Thank you to Charles, despite being ill, and to Alex, who performed another fast and consistent stint, securing tenth ‘top-2’ in ten races.”
The Theodore Racing team and SJM have supported Charles Leong since 2021, when he achieved his second Formula 4 triumph at the Guia Circuit. In 2023, he finished very close to teammate Arvid Lindblad in the Macau Grand Prix Formula 4 race, completing a triumphant 1-2 for SJM Theodore PREMA Racing. Absent from last year's edition due to commitments at the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia in Spain, Charles Leong has not yet announced whether he will participate in this year's edition of the Macau Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-09-09 00:01:15</pubDate></item></channel></rss>