<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Japan | Member of nuclear regulator loses cell phone in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/japao-membro-do-regulador-nuclear-perde-telemovel-na-china/</link><description>Japanese authorities are investigating the loss of a professional cell phone, allegedly in China, which contained a confidential list of contacts from the Nuclear Regulation Authority, as confirmed to France-Presse by a person responsible for the organization.
The incident, now made public, occurred at Shanghai airport, on November 3, when the employee was going through security control. The absence of the device was only noticed three days later, and, according to the Japanese press, it was not possible to block it or remotely erase its data as it was already out of reach.
Although the cell phone did not contain direct access to nuclear data, according to the person in charge – who did not want to be identified – the list included names and contact details of members of the nuclear safety division of the regulatory authority – information that is not publicly accessible due to the sensitivity of the functions.
The revelation comes in a context of growing tension between Beijing and Tokyo, after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suggested in November that the country could intervene militarily in the event of Chinese aggression against Taiwan.
At the same time, the operator Tokyo Electric Power (TEPCO) is seeking final approval to reactivate the Kashiwazaki-Kariwa nuclear plant, the largest in the world, closed after the Fukushima disaster in 2011. Japan has been gradually resuming nuclear energy, with 14 reactors already reactivated, within the framework of carbon neutrality targets by 2050 and increased demand for electricity due to artificial intelligence.
The lost cellphone was reported to Japanese data protection authorities in November, according to the nuclear regulator. The case reignites concerns about information security in the nuclear energy sector at a delicate moment in Japanese energy policy.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:40:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Entertainment Zone | Government admits change of purpose</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/zona-de-espectaculos-governo-admite-mudanca-de-finalidade/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, admitted, in this Wednesday's debate in the Legislative Assembly (AL), that the Open Air Performance Zone, in Cotai, could host other types of community activities than just concerts.
In response to an oral question from deputy Chan Lai Kei, the secretary stated that, after a year of experimental use, the intention is to “expand and reinforce the functions of the venue”, with “the spaces available between concerts being used to transform the venue into 3×3 basketball courts or spaces for family sporting activities”.
The Zone will therefore be “a space open to citizens in order to increase flexibility and general benefits of use”. “Regarding the issue raised regarding the introduction of diverse events such as cultural and creative fairs, among others, the Government will maintain an open attitude in the evaluation process”, said the secretary.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:18:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn, MGM and Melco announce bonuses for workers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/wynn-mgm-e-melco-anunciam-bonus-para-trabalhadores/</link><description>Gaming concessionaires Wynn Resorts and MGM China announced a bonus equivalent to one month of work that will cover between 95 and 98 percent of workers. The information was released yesterday through press releases, after the Galaxy dealership announced a similar measure on Tuesday.
As far as Wynn Macau is concerned, the bonus will cover 98 percent of the current 11,552 eligible employees, as “recognition of the exceptional contributions of all team members over the last year”. “We are truly grateful for the efforts and contributions of our team members over the past year and are pleased to announce a special grant in recognition of their hard work,” said Linda Chen, Vice President and CEO of Wynn Macau. “This year we celebrate the important milestone of our 20th anniversary in Macau — not only an achievement for Wynn, but also a testament to the dedication of every member of our team,” he added.
General trends
In the case of MGM, the bonus will cover 95 percent of workers, as “recognition for their dedication and contributions throughout 2025”. The amount will begin to be paid from the 21st of this month.
“Reflecting on 2025, we are moving forward with a new chapter, continually optimizing our innovative products and service experiences, achieving steady progress in the development of our business – all thanks to the dedication and hard work of our team,” said Pansy Ho, president and CEO of MGM China in a statement. "Looking to the future, MGM will continue to enhance its strengths, with an unwavering focus on our guests. Guided by the philosophy of 'Originality + Innovation', we will remain dedicated to contributing to the positioning of Macau as a world-class tourism and leisure center, through the continuous introduction of more diverse tourism offerings", he stressed.
Finally, Melco Resorts also announced a bonus for “eligible workers”, but the proportion of the workforce covered was not indicated. "The discretionary bonus payment recognizes the dedication and support of our colleagues over the past year. We sincerely appreciate their loyalty and commitment to consistently exceeding guest expectations, which together helps the company maintain and enhance its leadership position in the entertainment and hospitality industry," said Lawrence Ho, group president.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:19:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Tower | Show celebrates Sino-Portuguese culture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/torre-de-macau-espectaculo-celebra-cultura-sino-portuguesa/</link><description>A new theatrical show takes the stage tomorrow to explore how 500 years of contact between Portuguese and Chinese cultures gave Macau “a unique identity”.
In the third edition of the “Macasaphis” series, the experimental theater group Frost Ice Snow Creative brings together music, theater, fashion, oral stories and stand-up comedy in the Macau Tower auditorium. The director, Sileas Ko Weng Si, told Lusa yesterday that, after a two-year break due to lack of funding, the group decided to return with the theme “Sino-Portuguese culture”.
"Sino-Portuguese culture is everywhere, but we don't even realize it anymore. People often get confused, without understanding how it influences our lives", explained Sileas Ko. The first edition of “Macasahpis”, in 2022, had already been dedicated to particular elements of the region.
“The presence of the Chinese and Portuguese languages, the historical monuments, the fact that we have the largest number of holidays in the world, both Buddhist and Catholic,” said Ko. Portuguese is one of the two official languages ​​of Macau, at least during the first 50 years of the new semi-autonomous Chinese region, according to the bilateral agreement that allowed the transition of administration in December 1999.
The 2023 edition had as guests Tuna Macaense, a musical group from the Eurasian community, made up mainly of Portuguese descendants, who play songs in the Creole dialect, Patuá. But this time the group decided to go further and celebrate how Portuguese influence is also felt among the Chinese in Macau, the show's producer, Casta Lai Chit, told Lusa.
“Maybe people still feel some shame in defining our culture and identity, because we are Chinese, but we are not the same as others”, explained Casta Lai, who has Portuguese nationality. “People are proud of Macau’s culture, but they have some shame in showing it”, lamented Sileas Ko. "Sino-Portuguese culture makes our city even more special. Without it, there would only be casinos", he added.
Cultural power
With an area of ​​just 33 square kilometers and less than 680,000 inhabitants, Macau “is a tiny fish” in the context of China, with a population of 1.4 billion, Casta Lai highlighted. “If it weren’t for Sino-Portuguese culture, Macau wouldn’t be important at all,” argued the producer.
The show includes a part in which, in a humorous way, the population of Macau is treated as “an endangered species” and not just because the city has the lowest birth rate in the world, said Sileas Ko. Casta Lai warned that "maybe after 50 years the culture will be different. If that happens, maybe people will look around and miss what was lost."</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:39:21</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM | 13 plan applications received for international companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/ipim-recebidas-13-candidaturas-a-plano-para-empresas-internacionais/</link><description>The Macau Trade and Investment Promotion Institute announced that it received 13 applications in the first two months of a program launched to attract international companies to the Macao SAR. More than 500 companies requested information about the support plan
The Macau Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM) revealed in a statement, released on Wednesday, that it had received 13 applications for the “Plan for Economic Development within the scope of Support for the Establishment of the First Store in Macau”, opened in November last year. The entity added that it is analyzing applications to grant “financial support in accordance with budgetary capacity and public interest”.
The Economic Development Plan within the scope of Support for the Establishment of the First Store in Macau provides support of up to one million patacas. To receive maximum support, companies must follow certain requirements, such as establishing themselves in NAPE, Areia Preta, Iao Hon, San Kio area, Praia do Manduco, Fai Chi Kei, Doca do Lam Mau, Bairro de Tamagnini Barbosa or Ilha Verde. Furthermore, they must have a minimum area, as well as a certain number of full-time local employees.
IPIM also highlighted that more than 500 companies requested information about the program, which was launched on November 1st. The plan lasts three years and has six application phases, the first of which runs until the end of January. At the end of November, the institute's president, Che Weng Keong, said in the Legislative Assembly that among the companies that requested more information about the plan were “brands from Portugal”.
IPIM recalled that it “took the initiative” to contact entities in mainland China, Southeast Asia and Portuguese and Spanish speaking countries.
Harvest fruits
The program, which aims to “enrich the tourist charm of Macau and boost the community economy”, was presented in Lisbon and Porto, at the beginning of October, by IPIM officials, who then also held presentations in neighboring Spain, in Madrid and Barcelona.
IPIM promised to continue publicizing the plan, including through participation in convention and exhibition events, “encouraging cooperation between Macau companies and foreign brands, including those from Portuguese-speaking countries”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:22:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Seaport forecasts 19% revenue growth in January</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/jogo-seaport-preve-crescimento-de-19-das-receitas-em-janeiro/</link><description>The basis of comparison helps, but Macau's main industry continues to expand month after month. The most recent report from Seaport Research Partners predicts that revenues will increase by 14 percent annually by March
Financial services firm Seaport Research Partners predicts 19 percent annual gaming revenue growth in January, according to the institution's most recent report. At a quarterly level, revenues can increase by around 14 percent.
“Our estimate for January points to an increase of 19 percent compared to the previous year (4 percent more compared to the previous month), with the growth rate helped by an easy comparison [compared to the 2025 value]”, can be read in the report by analyst Vitaly Umansky, cited by the GGR Asia portal. In January 2025, the game's gross revenue was 18.3 billion patacas, the lowest value of the entire year, which contributes to the highest relative growth.
Despite the low basis for comparison, the 19 percent growth in revenue at the beginning of the year is seen by Umansky as a “solid” sign for the first quarter, in which gaming revenue is expected to expand by around 14 percent. It is recalled that in the first three months of 2025, revenue reached 57.7 billion patacas.
“We estimate that the month started quite strong, possibly with revenues above 850 million patacas per day during the long weekend from January 1st to 4th”, the document states.
Weakest December
The forecast of 14 percent growth in the first quarter takes into account the fact that revenues slowed down in mid-December, which Seaport Research Partners believes is due to the fact that high rollers prefer to visit Macau to gamble between January and February.
“We anticipate gross gaming revenues to grow more than 14 percent in the first quarter and seven percent in 2026,” Umansky said. “Growth in 2026 is supported by easy comparisons in the first half of the year and the continued easing of monetary flows and visa issuance”, he highlighted.
Vitaly Umansky also said that if there is any unexpected increase in revenue in the mass market that the gaming industry's results could exceed the indicated forecast and that this increase would benefit concessionaires currently with greater capacity.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:21:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Inquiry | More than half of young people disappointed with salaries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/inquerito-mais-de-metade-dos-jovens-desapontados-com-salarios/</link><description>A survey by the General Women's Association reveals that more than half of young people think salaries are below expectations and a third admit to a lack of professional experience. In terms of training, almost half of those surveyed would like to have more proficiency in languages
The Macau General Women's Association yesterday presented a survey focused on youth employment. When looking for a job, or changing professional careers, more than 50 percent of young people surveyed indicated that salaries and benefits are below their expectations. Still on this topic, around 42 percent pointed to high competition as the main challenge, a third confessed to not having relevant professional experience. Another challenge mentioned was the mismatch between skills and the demands of the Macau job market.
The mismatch between young people's abilities and work demands, combined with the lack of opportunities to develop advanced skills and the high cost of professional certifications was identified as one of the biggest obstacles to starting a career.
When it comes to developing skills, almost half of those surveyed pointed to language training as their preferred choice, followed by what the survey authors called “interpersonal skills” (solving complex problems and negotiating skills). The other skills listed by the young people were management and leadership skills.
Lack of space
Regarding training actions, the survey by the General Women's Association reveals that almost 50 percent of young people want to access practical courses on digital content (such as Artificial Intelligence and mega-data). On the other hand, around 46 percent would like to attend internationally recognized professional certification courses.
Furthermore, more than half of young people stated that Macau's labor market is too small, with no advanced skills development projects or internationally recognized professional training plans. The time and financial cost of this type of training was highlighted as an obstacle to professional progression by more than 37 percent of respondents.
In terms of priorities in the labor market, almost 75 percent of respondents indicated that they prioritized wages, the balance between work and free time and job stability. The survey was carried out online, between October and November, among residents aged between 18 and 45, with 568 valid responses.
During the presentation of the study results, deputies Wong Kit Cheng and Loi I Weng made recommendations to address the challenges enumerated by young people. The first suggestions were policies that the Government has indicated for years as priorities, such as the construction of the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin and the adequate diversification of the economy.
The deputies also asked for an increase in support for the Training and Accreditation Exams Program for Qualified Personnel to at least 10 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:16:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Car insurance | Request for review of coverage values</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/seguro-automovel-pedida-revisao-de-valores-de-cobertura/</link><description>Without any change for 15 years, the deputy linked to the Fujian community questions the Government about the revision of the minimum insurance value, which is currently 750 thousand patacas for mopeds and 1.5 million patacas for motorcycles and cars
Representative Song Pek Kei defends the need to increase the minimum amount of civil liability insurance coverage for traffic accidents. The matter was addressed through a written interpellation, with the legislator warning that the party responsible for the accident often finds it difficult to pay compensation.
Song indicates that currently if residents opt for the cheapest insurance, the maximum amount that insurers have to cover is MOP750,000 if they drive a moped, or MOP1.5 million if the vehicle driven is a car or motorcycle. However, the legislator considers the values ​​to be inappropriate because they have remained unchanged “for 15 years”, despite social development.
The deputy linked to the Fujian community also points out that as the median income of residents is close to 20 thousand patacas and “the compensation awarded by the courts for a single traffic accident normally exceeds the minimum limit of insurance coverage” the party considered responsible finds it difficult to “provide reasonable compensation to the victim” of the accident.
For these reasons, and because the coverage amount is “inadequate to respond to social developments”, Song questions the Government about whether it will increase the minimum coverage amount to respond to “the growing demand for compensation”. The deputy also suggests the creation of a mechanism for regularly reviewing the amount to avoid problems like the current one, in which the coverage value regularly deviates from reality.
Excessive compensation?
In the interpellation, Song Pek Kei also considers that the compensation determined by the courts must be reasonable, to keep pace with social developments. “Excessively high amounts of compensation impose an unreasonable burden on the responsible parties and are not in line with the evolution of contemporary society”, he pointed out.
According to Song, the issue is the fact that court decisions regularly condemn those responsible for accidents to cover non-material damages, such as mental suffering and loss of future income. As the insurance only covers “bodily damage and partial material damage”, the deputy indicates that those sentenced to pay are regularly in difficulty paying compensation.
Furthermore, the legislator wants clarification on the possibility of insurance covering the types of compensation that are now left out.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:09:25</pubDate></item><item><title>University of Macau | Former teachers recall experiences</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/universidade-de-macau-antigos-docentes-recordam-experiencias/</link><description>The University of Macau celebrates 45 years and HM invited two former professors to recall their professional experiences at the institution. Brian Hall, from the field of psychology, found “the ideal environment” to start his career. Vera Lúcia Raposo says she “learned a lot” and saw Law as a “meeting place”
A series of events begins this Sunday to celebrate the 45 years of existence of the University of Macau (UM), including the “Open Day” which takes place at the Lakeside Theater between 11am and 5pm (see secondary text). It was in March 1981, still under the name of the University of East Asia, that UM began to take its first steps in local higher education, namely in the teaching of Law in the Portuguese language.
It was the first time that Macau had its own university, providing a higher education offering for residents, who no longer only had the opportunity to pursue studies abroad, such as Portugal, the United Kingdom, Hong Kong or Australia.
To commemorate the anniversary, HM invited two former professors of the institution, from two different academic areas, to talk about their experience at UM.
Vera Lúcia Raposo, who taught at the Faculty of Law from January 2014, remembers feeling “a shock”. "The classes were entirely in English, and I had never taught a complete course in that language, the pressure to publish in indexed journals was absolute and the evaluation system was periodic, demanding and relentless. Nothing there resembled the regime I was used to, where the simple passage of time often seemed to guarantee the natural advancement of an academic career", she said.
However, adaptation arrived and ended up following “the rules” to this day, namely at NOVA School of Law. “At the time, however, these requirements were still profoundly strange in Portugal, and they continue to be so, in many contexts, even today”, he says.
Vera Lúcia Raposo says she “learned a lot” at UM, as “the demanding scientific production goals and interdisciplinary research contributed to defining the type of academic I am today”. “I owe UM more than a professional transition, but a transformation”, he assures.
A cultural melting pot
The former professor at the UM Faculty of Law also remembers arriving in a territory that was “a space of true cultural amalgamation”, with the institution being an example of this.
"Working side by side with colleagues of different nationalities and cultures was a rare privilege. In particular, the intellectual coexistence between Chinese, Macanese and Portuguese colleagues, in the study and teaching of Macau Law, offered me an absolutely unique way of thinking about Law: less self-centered, more dialoguing, more aware of its cultural and historical contingency", highlighted Vera Lúcia Raposo.
Brian Hall, who taught at the Faculty of Social Sciences and coordinated the “Global and Community Mental Health Research Group”, highlights the possibility of doing pioneering work in the area of ​​mental health. "UM gave me the opportunity to develop unique and never-before-taught courses in Global Mental Health and Global Health. They were the first courses of their kind in Macau and at the university", recalled Brian Hall, who is now linked to New York University Shanghai.
“I was grateful to have some really great students who were interested in topics like migration, global and digital mental health, and I really enjoyed mentoring them in and out of the classroom.”
The first prizes
The academic also highlights the fact that he “regularly published research articles with undergraduate and postgraduate students, taking them to international research conferences, where they won awards”. “We were among the first at the university to achieve these excellent results and I am eternally grateful to UM for providing me with all these opportunities”, he confessed.
Brian Hall also added that he joined UM “in a period of ambitious transition and growth to become a research university”, providing “an ideal environment to launch a career”. When he was at UM, Brian Hall received, in 2020, an award for his work, the “Excellence in Advising Award” from the Center for Global Health at Johns Hopkins University, from the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health.
"The university rewarded me for my excellent research performance by granting me permission to apply for an early promotion to associate professor, which I was granted just four years after joining the university. UM served as a springboard to build a regional and international career," he said.
Book of Genesis
The need to create a university in Macau arose from the desire to develop the territory, especially taking into account the signing of the Joint Declaration between Portugal and China in 1987.
The former Governor of Macau Garcia Leandro recalled the first moments of the creation of the future university in the book “Macau in the Years of the Portuguese Revolution 1974-1979”, which reads that the initial budget was 40 million patacas for construction “on land on the island of Taipa, with a modern architectural project”.
The institution should have capacity for “a population of two thousand students in four years, at a rate of 500 per year”, with “the leadership of the various course chairs guaranteed by a dean professor with a doctorate from the University of Oxford and by several university professors from Matteo Ricci, the Chinese University of Hong Kong and also from the USA”, it is described.
The first contract to train the teaching team and pedagogical content was signed in February 1979 with the Matteo Ricci group. “I believe it was another good service provided to the population”, wrote the former Governor. In 1991, the institution changed its name to what it currently has.
According to data from the 2024 annual report, the latest available, UM has 52,146 graduated students, and in the first semester of the 2024/2025 academic year, 15,147 students attended the university, from all educational levels. Highlight is the greater number of students from abroad, 9,328, compared to 5,819 local students.
Open day in Hengqin
Despite having been formally created in March, UM begins to celebrate 45 years of existence this Sunday with an Open Day. According to a statement from the educational institution, between 11 am and 5 pm the public will be able to visit the Lakeside Theater, where the first ceremony takes place, and then other areas of the campus in Hengqin, namely the main campus and the UM Scientific and Technological Research Institute in Zhuhai, in the Youth Entrepreneurship Valley in Hengqin.
This route also includes the possibility of visiting, for the first time, the Transitional Research and Education Site at Yuxin Tower, in the Cooperation Zone. “Through a wide range of on-site activities and live online broadcasts, the event will showcase UM’s latest developments and achievements in teaching, research and community service”, highlights the same note, which recalls how UM was the first higher education institution in Macau to “extend teaching and research activities to the Guangdong-Macao Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin”.
That day there will also be “approximately 250 activities on the main campus throughout the day, including admissions lectures, academic and research activities and interactive games”.
"Visitors interested in academic subjects can attend engaging lectures on science and other disciplines, while sports enthusiasts can explore UM's sports facilities. Families can also participate in interactive games at stands, scientific experiments, workshops and knowledge challenges organized by various faculties, residences and laboratories", it is revealed. On Open Day there will also be discounts in the restaurant area.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:07:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Member of nuclear regulator loses cell phone in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/japao-membro-do-regulador-nuclear-perde-telemovel-na-china/</link><description>Japanese authorities are investigating the loss of a professional cell phone, allegedly in China, which contained a confidential list of contacts from the Nuclear Regulation Authority, as confirmed to France-Presse by a person responsible for the organization.
The incident, now made public, occurred at Shanghai airport, on November 3, when the employee was going through security control. The absence of the device was only noticed three days later, and, according to the Japanese press, it was not possible to block it or remotely erase its data as it was already out of reach.
Although the cell phone did not contain direct access to nuclear data, according to the person in charge – who did not want to be identified – the list included names and contact details of members of the nuclear safety division of the regulatory authority – information that is not publicly accessible due to the sensitivity of the functions.
The revelation comes in a context of growing tension between Beijing and Tokyo, after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suggested in November that the country could intervene militarily in the event of Chinese aggression against Taiwan.
At the same time, the operator Tokyo Electric Power (TEPCO) is seeking final approval to reactivate the Kashiwazaki-Kariwa nuclear plant, the largest in the world, closed after the Fukushima disaster in 2011. Japan has been gradually resuming nuclear energy, with 14 reactors already reactivated, within the framework of carbon neutrality targets by 2050 and increased demand for electricity due to artificial intelligence.
The lost cellphone was reported to Japanese data protection authorities in November, according to the nuclear regulator. The case reignites concerns about information security in the nuclear energy sector at a delicate moment in Japanese energy policy.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:40:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Entertainment Zone | Government admits change of purpose</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/zona-de-espectaculos-governo-admite-mudanca-de-finalidade/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, admitted, in this Wednesday's debate in the Legislative Assembly (AL), that the Open Air Performance Zone, in Cotai, could host other types of community activities than just concerts.
In response to an oral question from deputy Chan Lai Kei, the secretary stated that, after a year of experimental use, the intention is to “expand and reinforce the functions of the venue”, with “the spaces available between concerts being used to transform the venue into 3×3 basketball courts or spaces for family sporting activities”.
The Zone will therefore be “a space open to citizens in order to increase flexibility and general benefits of use”. “Regarding the issue raised regarding the introduction of diverse events such as cultural and creative fairs, among others, the Government will maintain an open attitude in the evaluation process”, said the secretary.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:18:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn, MGM and Melco announce bonuses for workers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/wynn-mgm-e-melco-anunciam-bonus-para-trabalhadores/</link><description>Gaming concessionaires Wynn Resorts and MGM China announced a bonus equivalent to one month of work that will cover between 95 and 98 percent of workers. The information was released yesterday through press releases, after the Galaxy dealership announced a similar measure on Tuesday.
As far as Wynn Macau is concerned, the bonus will cover 98 percent of the current 11,552 eligible employees, as “recognition of the exceptional contributions of all team members over the last year”. “We are truly grateful for the efforts and contributions of our team members over the past year and are pleased to announce a special grant in recognition of their hard work,” said Linda Chen, Vice President and CEO of Wynn Macau. “This year we celebrate the important milestone of our 20th anniversary in Macau — not only an achievement for Wynn, but also a testament to the dedication of every member of our team,” he added.
General trends
In the case of MGM, the bonus will cover 95 percent of workers, as “recognition for their dedication and contributions throughout 2025”. The amount will begin to be paid from the 21st of this month.
“Reflecting on 2025, we are moving forward with a new chapter, continually optimizing our innovative products and service experiences, achieving steady progress in the development of our business – all thanks to the dedication and hard work of our team,” said Pansy Ho, president and CEO of MGM China in a statement. "Looking to the future, MGM will continue to enhance its strengths, with an unwavering focus on our guests. Guided by the philosophy of 'Originality + Innovation', we will remain dedicated to contributing to the positioning of Macau as a world-class tourism and leisure center, through the continuous introduction of more diverse tourism offerings", he stressed.
Finally, Melco Resorts also announced a bonus for “eligible workers”, but the proportion of the workforce covered was not indicated. "The discretionary bonus payment recognizes the dedication and support of our colleagues over the past year. We sincerely appreciate their loyalty and commitment to consistently exceeding guest expectations, which together helps the company maintain and enhance its leadership position in the entertainment and hospitality industry," said Lawrence Ho, group president.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:19:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Tower | Show celebrates Sino-Portuguese culture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/torre-de-macau-espectaculo-celebra-cultura-sino-portuguesa/</link><description>A new theatrical show takes the stage tomorrow to explore how 500 years of contact between Portuguese and Chinese cultures gave Macau “a unique identity”.
In the third edition of the “Macasaphis” series, the experimental theater group Frost Ice Snow Creative brings together music, theater, fashion, oral stories and stand-up comedy in the Macau Tower auditorium. The director, Sileas Ko Weng Si, told Lusa yesterday that, after a two-year break due to lack of funding, the group decided to return with the theme “Sino-Portuguese culture”.
"Sino-Portuguese culture is everywhere, but we don't even realize it anymore. People often get confused, without understanding how it influences our lives", explained Sileas Ko. The first edition of “Macasahpis”, in 2022, had already been dedicated to particular elements of the region.
“The presence of the Chinese and Portuguese languages, the historical monuments, the fact that we have the largest number of holidays in the world, both Buddhist and Catholic,” said Ko. Portuguese is one of the two official languages ​​of Macau, at least during the first 50 years of the new semi-autonomous Chinese region, according to the bilateral agreement that allowed the transition of administration in December 1999.
The 2023 edition had as guests Tuna Macaense, a musical group from the Eurasian community, made up mainly of Portuguese descendants, who play songs in the Creole dialect, Patuá. But this time the group decided to go further and celebrate how Portuguese influence is also felt among the Chinese in Macau, the show's producer, Casta Lai Chit, told Lusa.
“Maybe people still feel some shame in defining our culture and identity, because we are Chinese, but we are not the same as others”, explained Casta Lai, who has Portuguese nationality. “People are proud of Macau’s culture, but they have some shame in showing it”, lamented Sileas Ko. "Sino-Portuguese culture makes our city even more special. Without it, there would only be casinos", he added.
Cultural power
With an area of ​​just 33 square kilometers and less than 680,000 inhabitants, Macau “is a tiny fish” in the context of China, with a population of 1.4 billion, Casta Lai highlighted. “If it weren’t for Sino-Portuguese culture, Macau wouldn’t be important at all,” argued the producer.
The show includes a part in which, in a humorous way, the population of Macau is treated as “an endangered species” and not just because the city has the lowest birth rate in the world, said Sileas Ko. Casta Lai warned that "maybe after 50 years the culture will be different. If that happens, maybe people will look around and miss what was lost."</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:39:21</pubDate></item><item><title>First retrospective of Portuguese artist Helena Almeida in Asia opens on the 23rd</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/primeira-retrospectiva-da-artista-portuguesa-helena-almeida-na-asia-inaugura-dia-23/</link><description>The Macau Museum of Art (MAM) will open the first retrospective of Portuguese artist Helena Almeida (1934-2018) in Asia on January 23, announced one of the exhibition's curators.
The exhibition “Helena Almeida: I'm Here – Presença and Resonance” is “one of the most comprehensive ever presented” and will be on display until April 26, Margarida Saraiva said on social media. The MAM curator stated that the retrospective will be divided into five sections, “chronologically and thematically”, including one dedicated to the first paintings and another to “the body as sculpture and the dialogue between bodies”.
Saraiva named Helena Almeida as “one of the most relevant Portuguese and European artists of her generation”, who “transformed the act of self-representation into an intense exploration of the body, space, resilience and impermanence”.
“His performative gestures — captured only through the lens of his studio — continue to challenge and expand the limits of painting, drawing and photography,” explained the curator. “This exhibition is simultaneously a tribute to Helena Almeida’s extraordinary legacy and an affirmation of the power of curatorial collaboration between cultures”, argued Saraiva.
The retrospective's main curator is Delfim Sardo, professor at the University of Coimbra and author of the book “Helena Almeida, Pés no Chão, Cabeça no Céu”, and the Chinese Song Zhen as co-curator.
Divide by two
In December, the Macau Cultural Institute indicated in a statement that the exhibition will bring together around 42 sets made up of 190 pieces by the Portuguese artist. Another part of the exhibition, “Resonância – Corpo. Objecto. Reflexão”, was opened on December 19, with pieces by six artists from Macau and mainland China, invited to interact with the work of Helena Almeida.
Born in Lisbon in 1934, Helena Almeida created, from the 1960s onwards, a multifaceted work, giving rise to a work that stood out for its self-representation, reflecting on the tension relationships between the body, space and the work. He used his body as a support and creative object, using painting, photography, engraving, installation and video. Helena Almeida studied painting at the Escola Superior de Belas-Artes in Lisbon, beginning to exhibit individually in 1967, at Galeria Buchholz.
The artist represented Portugal at the Venice Biennale on two occasions: in 1982 and 2005, and in 2004 she participated in the Sydney Biennale, with her work being exhibited in individual and collective exhibitions in national and international museums and galleries.
In 2015, he presented a traveling solo exhibition Corpus at Fundação de Serralves (2015), in Porto, in Paris (2016), in Brussels (2016) and Valencia (2017). In 2017, he also presented a solo exhibition “Work is never finished” at the Art Institute, in Chicago, in the United States.
His work is present in Portuguese and international collections such as: Berardo Collection, Lisbon; Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, Lisbon; Serralves Foundation, Porto; Hara Museum of Contemporary Art, Tokyo; Barcelona Museum of Contemporary Art; Museo Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofía, Madrid; MUDAM – Musée d’Art Moderne Grand-Duc Jean, Luxembourg; Tate Modern, London.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:25:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Zhipu AI leads round of stock market debuts worth 1,030 ME</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/hong-kong-zhipu-ai-lidera-ronda-de-estreias-em-bolsa-no-valor-de-1-030-me/</link><description>Investor interest in the technology market continues to bear fruit and leads more and more Chinese companies linked to Artificial Intelligence to enter the Hong Kong stock exchange
The Chinese artificial intelligence company Zhipu AI debuted on the Hong Kong stock exchange yesterday, on a day when two other technology companies also entered the market, collectively raising 1.2 billion dollars. Zhipu, officially called Knowledge Atlas Technology and which adopts the name Z.ai in foreign markets, registered an upward trend in the middle of the session, with a value of 11.19 percent, after having raised around 559 million dollars.
It is the first Chinese company specializing exclusively in large-scale language models to be listed on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange. According to its co-founder and executive director, Zhang Peng, the choice of this financial center is related to the company's internationalization ambitions.
Zhang said that Hong Kong and Southeast Asia will be the first markets to be explored, followed by the Middle East, Europe and the so-called “Global South”. The manager pointed to low costs as Zhipu's main attraction compared to competing models, with the aim of winning over new users.
The technology company thus joins other Chinese companies in the sector that have taken advantage of investors' interest in the growth of AI in the country. One of Zhipu's main competitors, MiniMax – also a rival to OpenAI (creator of ChatGPT) and Anthropic (developer of Claude) – is scheduled to debut on the same exchange on Friday.
Other premieres
Yesterday, graphics chip maker Shanghai Iluvatar CoreX Semiconductor, which opened with gains of 31.5 percent after raising US$473 million, and surgical robot producer Edge Medical, which rose 36.4 percent, raising around US$154 million, also debuted in Hong Kong.
Last week, Biren Technology, which specializes in AI chips, rose nearly 76 percent on its first day of trading. In December, two other companies in the sector, Moore Threads and MetaX, recorded increases of more than 100 percent on the Shanghai stock exchange.
Despite admitting that Chinese models are closing the gap compared to North Americans, Zhang Peng acknowledged that gaps still persist in areas such as research, resources and innovation. Zhipu was placed on a commercial blacklist by the United States in 2025, making it difficult for it to access North American technology.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:32:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Damn | Woman arrested for heroin trafficking</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/droga-mulher-detida-por-trafico-de-heroina/</link><description>A 43-year-old woman was arrested after being intercepted with 0.83 grams of heroin, valued at MOP1,000, while returning from Hong Kong. The case was revealed yesterday by the Judiciary Police and the investigation was based on a complaint.
According to the PJ's version, the woman is an unemployed local resident, who had made several trips between Macau and Hong Kong with the purpose of trafficking and consuming drugs.
In addition to the drugs, authorities seized syringes, packages for storing drugs and other materials for consumption. A search of the woman's house, in Coloane, also resulted in the seizure of other materials used to consume narcotics. The detainee was also tested for urine, which tested positive for drug consumption. The case was handed over to the Public Ministry (MP).
Illegal exchanges | Two cases lead to the seizure of 47,900 HK dollars
Authorities seized 47,900 Hong Kong dollars worth of gambling chips, which they believed were used in illegal money exchanges. The seizure resulted from two different cases, carried out by the Judiciary Police and the Public Security Police Corps.
The first situation involved a 40-year-old man from the Interior, caught red-handed exchanging money with a player. The latter confessed that he had previously exchanged 300 renminbi for 300 Hong Kong dollars in tokens, which led to the first arrest and seizure of 28,500,000 Hong Kong dollars, in the possession of the suspected criminal.
In turn, the first detainee claimed to have made profits from exchanging money worth 7,000 Hong Kong dollars. The second detainee, also at the casino, was also intercepted in the act. The individual is also from the Interior and, in addition to an attempt to exchange 6,000 Hong Kong dollars for 6,000 renminbis, he had 19,400,000 Hong Kong dollars in his possession.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:02:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Japanese authorities are investigating the loss of a professional cell phone, allegedly in China, which contained a confidential list of contacts from the Nuclear Regulation Authority, as confirmed to France-Presse by a person responsible for the organization.
The incident, now made public, occurred at Shanghai airport, on November 3, when the employee was going through security control. The absence of the device was only noticed three days later, and, according to the Japanese press, it was not possible to block it or remotely erase its data as it was already out of reach.
Although the cell phone did not contain direct access to nuclear data, according to the person in charge – who did not want to be identified – the list included names and contact details of members of the nuclear safety division of the regulatory authority – information that is not publicly accessible due to the sensitivity of the functions.
The revelation comes in a context of growing tension between Beijing and Tokyo, after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suggested in November that the country could intervene militarily in the event of Chinese aggression against Taiwan.
At the same time, the operator Tokyo Electric Power (TEPCO) is seeking final approval to reactivate the Kashiwazaki-Kariwa nuclear plant, the largest in the world, closed after the Fukushima disaster in 2011. Japan has been gradually resuming nuclear energy, with 14 reactors already reactivated, within the framework of carbon neutrality targets by 2050 and increased demand for electricity due to artificial intelligence.
The lost cellphone was reported to Japanese data protection authorities in November, according to the nuclear regulator. The case reignites concerns about information security in the nuclear energy sector at a delicate moment in Japanese energy policy.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Japanese authorities are investigating the loss of a professional cell phone, allegedly in China, which contained a confidential list of contacts from the Nuclear Regulation Authority, as confirmed to France-Presse by a person responsible for the organization.
The incident, now made public, occurred at Shanghai airport, on November 3, when the employee was going through security control. The absence of the device was only noticed three days later, and, according to the Japanese press, it was not possible to block it or remotely erase its data as it was already out of reach.
Although the cell phone did not contain direct access to nuclear data, according to the person in charge – who did not want to be identified – the list included names and contact details of members of the nuclear safety division of the regulatory authority – information that is not publicly accessible due to the sensitivity of the functions.
The revelation comes in a context of growing tension between Beijing and Tokyo, after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suggested in November that the country could intervene militarily in the event of Chinese aggression against Taiwan.
At the same time, the operator Tokyo Electric Power (TEPCO) is seeking final approval to reactivate the Kashiwazaki-Kariwa nuclear plant, the largest in the world, closed after the Fukushima disaster in 2011. Japan has been gradually resuming nuclear energy, with 14 reactors already reactivated, within the framework of carbon neutrality targets by 2050 and increased demand for electricity due to artificial intelligence.
The lost cellphone was reported to Japanese data protection authorities in November, according to the nuclear regulator. The case reignites concerns about information security in the nuclear energy sector at a delicate moment in Japanese energy policy.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Mo Shilong (1537-87), referring to one of the most cherished masters in the canon of painting history, known by the name Ni Yunlin zi, the «Master of the cloud forest», the painter Nizan (1306-1374), who was revealed when, in the turmoil of the violent dynastic transition, he said «no» to those closest to him, starting to live as a recluse, noted that «when ordinary people try imitate an original painting, how can they transmit its spirit to posterity?”
Later, the influential theorist Dong Qichang (1555-1636) added: «Those who study the old masters and do not introduce changes are like trapped behind a fence. By imitating models too closely you are often even further away».
And Nizan's paintings, perhaps even more than many others, in their serene austere aspect will be the most difficult to imitate because they depend intimately on the person of their author and the way in which he managed to make the «spiritual rhythm» (qiyun) flow in them. And yet many tried to reproduce the elegant and insipid (dan) appearance of those visions that were closer to their spirit than to the external visible.
Later, in another dynastic transition, from the Ming to the Qing dynasty, a painter tried to follow Nizan's path from within, in similar circumstances. He belonged to a family of seven brothers, from Shanyin (now part of Shaoxing, Zhejiang). One of the brothers, the illustrated imperial official Qi Biaojia (1603-45), would leave a unique record of the sophistication of the literati at the end of the Ming dynasty, significantly through the memory of his Yu garden, on the slope of the hill of the same name.
In the «Yu Hill Anthology», Yushan zhi, a collective work in three volumes written by him, his friends and family, travel notes, explanations of views of the garden, narratives, inquiries, dreams of personalities who interpreted their present with knowledge of the rich arts and literature of the past are kept, constituting a relevant historical archive. Which was found expressively in paintings.
Qi Zhijia (1594-c.1682), another of the brothers, in addition to being a poet, playwright, calligrapher, stamp engraver, athlete and amateur singer, had a memory of paintings, as shown in several works made in the style of great masters. If, faced with the disruption of the new foreign government, Qi Biaojia would commit suicide in his garden, as four thousand and forty-three senior officials did, according to a record from Qianlong's time, Qi Zhijia would resist through calm contemplation, accepting impermanence, as in the 1651 vertical scroll, Landscape from Nizan (ink on paper, 116 x 50.8 cm, at the Metmuseum). In him the “dragon veins”, longmo, reveal the depth of his experience of solitude and serenity, the understanding of the spirit of Winter.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Mo Shilong (1537-87), referring to one of the most cherished masters in the canon of painting history, known by the name Ni Yunlin zi, the «Master of the cloud forest», the painter Nizan (1306-1374), who was revealed when, in the turmoil of the violent dynastic transition, he said «no» to those closest to him, starting to live as a recluse, noted that «when ordinary people try imitate an original painting, how can they transmit its spirit to posterity?”
Later, the influential theorist Dong Qichang (1555-1636) added: «Those who study the old masters and do not introduce changes are like trapped behind a fence. By imitating models too closely you are often even further away».
And Nizan's paintings, perhaps even more than many others, in their serene austere aspect will be the most difficult to imitate because they depend intimately on the person of their author and the way in which he managed to make the «spiritual rhythm» (qiyun) flow in them. And yet many tried to reproduce the elegant and insipid (dan) appearance of those visions that were closer to their spirit than to the external visible.
Later, in another dynastic transition, from the Ming to the Qing dynasty, a painter tried to follow Nizan's path from within, in similar circumstances. He belonged to a family of seven brothers, from Shanyin (now part of Shaoxing, Zhejiang). One of the brothers, the illustrated imperial official Qi Biaojia (1603-45), would leave a unique record of the sophistication of the literati at the end of the Ming dynasty, significantly through the memory of his Yu garden, on the slope of the hill of the same name.
In the «Yu Hill Anthology», Yushan zhi, a collective work in three volumes written by him, his friends and family, travel notes, explanations of views of the garden, narratives, inquiries, dreams of personalities who interpreted their present with knowledge of the rich arts and literature of the past are kept, constituting a relevant historical archive. Which was found expressively in paintings.
Qi Zhijia (1594-c.1682), another of the brothers, in addition to being a poet, playwright, calligrapher, stamp engraver, athlete and amateur singer, had a memory of paintings, as shown in several works made in the style of great masters. If, faced with the disruption of the new foreign government, Qi Biaojia would commit suicide in his garden, as four thousand and forty-three senior officials did, according to a record from Qianlong's time, Qi Zhijia would resist through calm contemplation, accepting impermanence, as in the 1651 vertical scroll, Landscape from Nizan (ink on paper, 116 x 50.8 cm, at the Metmuseum). In him the “dragon veins”, longmo, reveal the depth of his experience of solitude and serenity, the understanding of the spirit of Winter.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Mo Shilong (1537-87), referring to one of the most cherished masters in the canon of painting history, known by the name Ni Yunlin zi, the «Master of the cloud forest», the painter Nizan (1306-1374), who was revealed when, in the turmoil of the violent dynastic transition, he said «no» to those closest to him, starting to live as a recluse, noted that «when ordinary people try imitate an original painting, how can they transmit its spirit to posterity?”
Later, the influential theorist Dong Qichang (1555-1636) added: «Those who study the old masters and do not introduce changes are like trapped behind a fence. By imitating models too closely you are often even further away».
And Nizan's paintings, perhaps even more than many others, in their serene austere aspect will be the most difficult to imitate because they depend intimately on the person of their author and the way in which he managed to make the «spiritual rhythm» (qiyun) flow in them. And yet many tried to reproduce the elegant and insipid (dan) appearance of those visions that were closer to their spirit than to the external visible.
Later, in another dynastic transition, from the Ming to the Qing dynasty, a painter tried to follow Nizan's path from within, in similar circumstances. He belonged to a family of seven brothers, from Shanyin (now part of Shaoxing, Zhejiang). One of the brothers, the illustrated imperial official Qi Biaojia (1603-45), would leave a unique record of the sophistication of the literati at the end of the Ming dynasty, significantly through the memory of his Yu garden, on the slope of the hill of the same name.
In the «Yu Hill Anthology», Yushan zhi, a collective work in three volumes written by him, his friends and family, travel notes, explanations of views of the garden, narratives, inquiries, dreams of personalities who interpreted their present with knowledge of the rich arts and literature of the past are kept, constituting a relevant historical archive. Which was found expressively in paintings.
Qi Zhijia (1594-c.1682), another of the brothers, in addition to being a poet, playwright, calligrapher, stamp engraver, athlete and amateur singer, had a memory of paintings, as shown in several works made in the style of great masters. If, faced with the disruption of the new foreign government, Qi Biaojia would commit suicide in his garden, as four thousand and forty-three senior officials did, according to a record from Qianlong's time, Qi Zhijia would resist through calm contemplation, accepting impermanence, as in the 1651 vertical scroll, Landscape from Nizan (ink on paper, 116 x 50.8 cm, at the Metmuseum). In him the “dragon veins”, longmo, reveal the depth of his experience of solitude and serenity, the understanding of the spirit of Winter.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Church | Pope closes 2025 with criticism of consumerism and xenophobia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/07/igreja-papa-fecha-2025-com-criticas-ao-consumismo-e-xenofobia/</link><description>Pope Leo
The speech served to close the Jubilee - a Holy Year that usually takes place every 25 years, proclaimed by the Pope as a special time of forgiveness, reconciliation and spiritual renewal -, which brought around 33 million pilgrims to Rome and included a historic transition from one American pontiff to another.
In the presence of cardinals and diplomats from all over the world, Leo
This situation had only occurred once, in 1700. Yesterday's ceremony, at the beginning of the mass celebrating the feast of the Epiphany (when the three Magi offered gifts to the newborn Jesus) ended a dizzying year of special audiences, masses and meetings that dominated Leo XIV's first months as pontiff and put his own agenda on hold.
To signal that his pontificate can now begin in earnest, the Pope summoned cardinals from around the world to the Vatican, for meetings on Wednesday and Thursday that aim to debate the governance of the Catholic Church, with its 1.4 billion faithful.
To reflect
In yesterday's homily, Leo XIV said that the jubilee year invited all Christians to reflect on the biblical teachings of welcoming strangers and resisting the “flattery and seduction of those who hold power”. “Around us, a distorted economy tries to profit from everything”, he criticized, adding that he hopes that this year it will be possible to recognize “a pilgrim in the visitor, a seeker abroad, a neighbor in the stranger and a traveling companion in someone who is different”.
The Holy Years usually include large public works projects, as was the case with the construction of the Sistine Chapel (commissioned by Pope Sixtus IV for the Jubilee of 1475) and the large Vatican garage, where popemobiles and other vehicles are parked (commissioned by John Paul II for the Jubilee of 2000).
Some works were controversial, such as the construction of Via della Conciliazione, in 1950, which leads to St. Peter's Square and which involved the demolition of an entire neighborhood. Leo XIV also announced that the next Jubilee will be in 2033, to commemorate the 2000th anniversary of what the Scriptures indicate as the death and resurrection of Jesus Christ, in 33 AD.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 02:28:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Medals | Ho Iat Seng, Kou Hoi In and Raimundo do Rosário distinguished</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/05/medalhas-ho-iat-seng-kou-hoi-in-e-raimundo-do-rosario-distinguidos/</link><description>The list of winners is marked by the award of two Medals of Honor of the Great Lotus, the highest distinction in the Macao SAR, to Ho Iat Seng and Kou Hoi In. All the individuals awarded served in the Government or in the Legislative Assembly
The former Chief Executive, Ho Iat Seng, and the former president of the Legislative Assembly, Kou Hoi In, will be awarded the Great Lotus Medal of Honor, the Macao SAR's highest distinction. The list of the Executive's distinctions for 2025 was announced on December 31st, through a statement from the Social Communication Office, and the award ceremony is scheduled for January 30th, at the Macau Cultural Center.
The main distinctions awarded by Sam Hou Fai were to former rulers, with Macanese and former Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raimundo do Rosário being awarded the Golden Lotus Medal of Honor. This distinction will also be awarded to Ho Veng On, former Commissioner of Audit, and Vong Man Chong, former director-general of the Customs Service. Medals of honor aim to distinguish individuals or entities that have contributed to the image and good name of the Macao SAR.
After the list of medals was announced, Ho Iat Seng considered the title “a profound honor”. The former Government leader also stated, in a statement, that he “has always maintained a deep affection for Macau” and that over the years he has “dedicated” himself to “serving the nation and Macau”.
The former Chief Executive praised the results of his governance and considered that they depended “not only on the dedication and hard work of the government action team and all Public Administration employees, but also on the strong support and joint efforts of the community and all residents”. “This honor is a collective victory, which demonstrates the commitment of the entire society to drive greater and better development for the Macao SAR,” he stated.
The text awarding the Great Lotus Medal of Honor to Ho Iat Seng highlights the period in which the former ruler had to deal with the Covid-19 pandemic. “During his term as the fifth Chief Executive, he united the Macao SAR Government and all social sectors, successfully overcame the severe challenges and difficulties of the Covid-19 pandemic and made every effort to promote post-pandemic economic recovery and social development”, it was stated.
In addition to being Chief Executive, Ho Iat Seng, a businessman by profession, was president of the Legislative Assembly, member of the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress and member of the Executive Council. This is the third time that Ho Iat Seng will be honored, after in 2001 having received the Medal of Industrial and Commercial Merit and in 2009 having been distinguished with the Golden Lotus Medal of Honor.
Another Lotus
Another distinguished businessman and former president of the Legislative Assembly is Kou Hoi In, notable for his activity as a member of the National People's Congress, the main legislative body of the People's Republic of China, and for more than 34 years as a deputy of the Legislative Assembly.
“In legislation work, supervision of government action and formulation of public policies, it has always defended the principles of carrying out functions in accordance with the law, in a rational and pragmatic manner, actively promoted the improvement of regimes and the construction of the rule of law and committed itself to safeguarding the rights and interests of residents and promoting social stability and long-term development”, it was considered. “During his term as President of the Legislative Assembly of Macau from 2019 to 2025, he focused his efforts on improving the efficiency of parliamentary functioning, promoting positive interaction between the Executive Branch and the Legislative Branch, and made important contributions to strengthening the construction of the Rule of Law, promoting social harmony and improving the population's well-being policies”, it was added.
After leaving the Chamber, Kou was appointed to serve as chairman of the Board of Directors of TDM, he is also vice-president of the Board of Directors and general manager of the China Special Products and Productions Company and vice-president of the Macau Commercial Association.
In the past, the previous president of AL had been awarded the Industrial and Commercial Merit Medal in 2007 and the Silver Lotus Medal of Honor in 2016.
In Portuguese
Raimundo do Rosário, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, between 2014 and 2024, is the only representative of the Macanese community in the 2025 distinctions, taking into account the distinguished individuals and associations.
In the text about the former ruler, several positions held in public and private institutions are indicated. “He joined the Civil Service in 1979 and worked until 1990 successively as a senior technician, head of department, deputy director and director of the Land, Public Works and Transport Services”, it can be read. His CV also states that he was a member of the Portuguese delegation of the Portuguese-Chinese Land Group, deputy of the Board of Directors of CAM-Sociedade of Macau International Airport and head of the Macau Economic and Commercial Delegation, in Lisbon, also having charge of the Economic and Commercial Delegations to the European Union, in Brussels and the World Trade Organization, in Geneva.
Raimundo was also a member of the Drafting Committee of the Basic Law and the Preparatory Committee for the Establishment of the Special Administrative Region of Macau, deputy and member of the Supervisory Board of Banco Comercial de Macau.
In terms of medals of honor, the Macau Banks Association will be awarded the Silver Lotus, due to its “fundamental role in promoting sector collaboration and the solid development of the industry”.
Medals of Merit
In terms of the professional merit medal this year, only one distinction appears, for Chan Iok Lin, who has been a member of the Office of the President of the Court of Final Instance since 2000, having become head in 2016. “He has always demonstrated a rigorous and dedicated attitude in carrying out his duties, possessing excellent leadership and organizational skills, as well as a high level of professionalism and a spirit of dedication”, he was justified.
In the industrial and commercial area, the distinctions went to the state-owned company Companhia de Logística Nam Kwong, from the Nam Kwong group, for its contributions to the diversification of the economy and to businesswoman Amber Li Jiaming, who is president of the HN Group and member of the 14th National Committee of the Chinese People's Political Consultative Conference (CPPCC), vice-president of the CPPCC Foreign Affairs Commission and member of the Council for the Economic Development of Macau.
At a tourist level, the only distinction was given to the House of Dancing Water Show Team, from Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment. The show was suspended during the pandemic, but returned after the end of border restrictions imposed during the years of combating Covid-19.
In terms of education, the Macau University of Science and Technology, Keang Peng School and Kao Yip School were distinguished. In culture, the distinctions went to the Chinese Opera Association of Maritime and Land Residents of Barra de Macau, deputy Lam Fat Iam and artist Chan Iu Pui, who draws caricatures for the newspaper Ou Mun.
Finally, an Altruistic Merit Medal will be awarded to the China International Emergency Medical Team (SAR) and Sports Merit medals to the MSAR Karate Team that participated in the National Games. Athlete Zhu Yuling, who defended the colors of Interior until 2024, when she moved to Macau, will also be honored. The athlete went on to represent the Macao SAR under professional staff promotion programs and won the women's singles title in the WTT of United States Smash Table Tennis, the first athlete from Macau to achieve this feat. Currently, she is a professor at Tianjin University.
Medalists
Medals of Honor
Great Lotus
Ho Iat Seng
Kou Hoi In
Golden Lotus
Raimundo Arrais do Rosário
Ho Veng On
Vong Man Chong
Silver Lotus
Macau Banks Association
Professional Merit Medals
Chan Iok Lin
Medal of Industrial and Commercial Merit
Nam Kwong Logistics Company, Limited
Li Amber Jiaming
Tourist Merit Medal
“House of Dancing Water” Show Team — Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment
Educational Merit Medal
Macau University of Science and Technology
Keang Peng School
Kao Yip School
Medal of Cultural Merit
Chinese Opera Association of Maritime and Land Residents of Barra de Macau
Lam Fat Iam
Chan Iu Pui
Altruistic Merit Medal
China International Medical Emergency Team (SAR)
Sports Merit Medal
Karate Team from the Macao SAR Sports Delegation to the 15th Edition of the National Games
Zhu Yuling
Medal of Dedication
Tai Kam Un
Community Service Medal
Macau Peng On Tung Tele-Assistance Service Center
Honorific Titles
Honorific Title of Value
Team from the Salesian Institute of the Immaculate Conception
Pui Ching Secondary School Team
Lou Hau High School Team
Macau Team at the Asian Elite Dance Competition 2024-2025
Macau secondary school women's team participating in the 2nd Asian 3×3 Basketball Championship for Secondary Schools
Macau team participating in the 2025 Bowling World Cup
Li In Iat</description><pubDate>2026-01-05 02:19:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Deputies warn of lack of trust and inequalities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/19/economia-deputados-alertam-para-falta-de-confianca-e-desigualdades/</link><description>Despite economic growth throughout this year, Chan Lai Kei and Leong Sun Iok alerted the Government to the problems in community neighborhoods and the need to distribute financial resources more equitably
Deputy Chan Lai Kei called on the Government to focus on promoting economic optimism and consumption, considering that in several neighborhoods in Macau the economic situation is worrying, despite macroeconomic growth. The matter was brought to the Legislative Assembly yesterday, an intervention before the agenda in the Plenary.
According to the deputy linked to the Fujian community, the economy is showing a “stable recovery”. Between January and September “the initial value of GDP grew 4.2 percent compared to the same period last year”. It also indicated that the unemployment rate was 2.3 percent between August and October.
However, Chan warned that “positive macroeconomic data have not completely eliminated negative indicators”, especially with regard to the lives of the population.
Citing a “recent study”, the legislator indicated that there is a weak desire to consume, because “residents’ confidence in increasing income and their satisfaction with their financial situation are still between a low and medium level”.
Chan Lai Kei explained that greater consumption abroad contributes to this wave of pessimism, but also the various closures of small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs): “In view of the stress of consumption abroad, the business environment of SMEs in areas linked to the lives of the population (such as NAPE, Iao Hon and Fai Chi Kei) continues to worsen and the risk of closure remains”, he warned. “These companies generally face the critical challenge of unstable customer sources, high costs and cross-border consumption”, he stressed.
Given the scenario outlined, the deputy asked the Executive to create a consumption incentive mechanism similar to discount vouchers, but with a permanent nature, while the “transformation phase of Macau's economic model” lasts, which “reinforces confidence in business”.
Improve distribution
Deputy Leong Sun Iok also addressed the situation of the economy and pointed out the need to better distribute resources from gambling, the main industry in the territory.
The legislator linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau praised the gaming concessionaires for the greater role they have taken in terms of investment for “urban development, tourism promotion and social security”, especially since 2023.
However, he regretted that resources are being channeled unequally: "It appears that, currently, both the revenues from the game and the gaming concessionaire companies themselves have invested a lot of resources in social development. But, in general, these resources are dispersed and lack a system and interconnection, therefore, they are unable to achieve maximum social benefit", he pointed out.
Leong thus advocated that a greater proportion of the revenue collected by the Administration from gambling be channeled to the Social Security Fund, to pay pensions for the elderly.
The deputy also called for the creation of a fund with money from concessionaires to develop the Macao SAR and to ensure that they “better” fulfill the obligations of the gaming law, such as “worker guarantees”, “support for people with disabilities or those rehabilitated”, support for SMEs and “educational, scientific research, environmental protection, cultural and sporting activities and activities of public interest”.
Leong Sun Iok also asked for a new portal with public information on concessionaires' expenses with non-gambling activities covered by the concessions' obligations and ended the intervention with a request for caution addressed to the Executive. “Society’s resources do not come easily and are the result of the joint efforts of the Government, companies, the various social sectors and the population in general”, he indicated. "The situation is not always good. I hope the Government makes good use of the resources arising from the social responsibilities of gaming companies, to improve the lives of the population", he highlighted.
Minimum Wage | Approved increase of one pataca per hour
The increase of one pataca per hour in the minimum wage, from 34 to 35 patacas, was approved yesterday in the Legislative Assembly. With the changes, starting next year, in weekly terms, the salary will go from 1,632 patacas to 1,680 patacas.
When the monthly calculations are made, the salary increases from 7,072 patacas to 7,280 patacas, an increase of 2.9 percent that will cover 4.4 percent of Macao SAR workers. Domestic workers are excluded, although the approval of the hiring quota, in the case of non-residents, is normally associated with the requirement of a salary between 3,500 and 4,000 patacas.
Budget 2026 | Deputies approve the specialty
The Legislative Assembly yesterday approved the budget for next year, which foresees an increase in gaming revenue of 3.5 percent, to 236 billion patacas. The document, which reflects the Executive's economic choices, estimates revenues of 118.8 billion patacas, while expenses are estimated at 113.5 billion patacas.
Based on these perspectives, the final balance of the regular budget should be positive at 5.3 billion patacas. However, there is a possibility that the scenario is actually better, given that the Government tends to make default estimates with regard to revenue and expenses. The budget also once again provides for exemption from paying professional tax, up to 30 percent of the annual amount, limited to 144 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>University of Macau | Former teachers recall experiences</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/universidade-de-macau-antigos-docentes-recordam-experiencias/</link><description>The University of Macau celebrates 45 years and HM invited two former professors to recall their professional experiences at the institution. Brian Hall, from the field of psychology, found “the ideal environment” to start his career. Vera Lúcia Raposo says she “learned a lot” and saw Law as a “meeting place”
A series of events begins this Sunday to celebrate the 45 years of existence of the University of Macau (UM), including the “Open Day” which takes place at the Lakeside Theater between 11am and 5pm (see secondary text). It was in March 1981, still under the name of the University of East Asia, that UM began to take its first steps in local higher education, namely in the teaching of Law in the Portuguese language.
It was the first time that Macau had its own university, providing a higher education offering for residents, who no longer only had the opportunity to pursue studies abroad, such as Portugal, the United Kingdom, Hong Kong or Australia.
To commemorate the anniversary, HM invited two former professors of the institution, from two different academic areas, to talk about their experience at UM.
Vera Lúcia Raposo, who taught at the Faculty of Law from January 2014, remembers feeling “a shock”. "The classes were entirely in English, and I had never taught a complete course in that language, the pressure to publish in indexed journals was absolute and the evaluation system was periodic, demanding and relentless. Nothing there resembled the regime I was used to, where the simple passage of time often seemed to guarantee the natural advancement of an academic career", she said.
However, adaptation arrived and ended up following “the rules” to this day, namely at NOVA School of Law. “At the time, however, these requirements were still profoundly strange in Portugal, and they continue to be so, in many contexts, even today”, he says.
Vera Lúcia Raposo says she “learned a lot” at UM, as “the demanding scientific production goals and interdisciplinary research contributed to defining the type of academic I am today”. “I owe UM more than a professional transition, but a transformation”, he assures.
A cultural melting pot
The former professor at the UM Faculty of Law also remembers arriving in a territory that was “a space of true cultural amalgamation”, with the institution being an example of this.
"Working side by side with colleagues of different nationalities and cultures was a rare privilege. In particular, the intellectual coexistence between Chinese, Macanese and Portuguese colleagues, in the study and teaching of Macau Law, offered me an absolutely unique way of thinking about Law: less self-centered, more dialoguing, more aware of its cultural and historical contingency", highlighted Vera Lúcia Raposo.
Brian Hall, who taught at the Faculty of Social Sciences and coordinated the “Global and Community Mental Health Research Group”, highlights the possibility of doing pioneering work in the area of ​​mental health. "UM gave me the opportunity to develop unique and never-before-taught courses in Global Mental Health and Global Health. They were the first courses of their kind in Macau and at the university", recalled Brian Hall, who is now linked to New York University Shanghai.
“I was grateful to have some really great students who were interested in topics like migration, global and digital mental health, and I really enjoyed mentoring them in and out of the classroom.”
The first prizes
The academic also highlights the fact that he “regularly published research articles with undergraduate and postgraduate students, taking them to international research conferences, where they won awards”. “We were among the first at the university to achieve these excellent results and I am eternally grateful to UM for providing me with all these opportunities”, he confessed.
Brian Hall also added that he joined UM “in a period of ambitious transition and growth to become a research university”, providing “an ideal environment to launch a career”. When he was at UM, Brian Hall received, in 2020, an award for his work, the “Excellence in Advising Award” from the Center for Global Health at Johns Hopkins University, from the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health.
"The university rewarded me for my excellent research performance by granting me permission to apply for an early promotion to associate professor, which I was granted just four years after joining the university. UM served as a springboard to build a regional and international career," he said.
Book of Genesis
The need to create a university in Macau arose from the desire to develop the territory, especially taking into account the signing of the Joint Declaration between Portugal and China in 1987.
The former Governor of Macau Garcia Leandro recalled the first moments of the creation of the future university in the book “Macau in the Years of the Portuguese Revolution 1974-1979”, which reads that the initial budget was 40 million patacas for construction “on land on the island of Taipa, with a modern architectural project”.
The institution should have capacity for “a population of two thousand students in four years, at a rate of 500 per year”, with “the leadership of the various course chairs guaranteed by a dean professor with a doctorate from the University of Oxford and by several university professors from Matteo Ricci, the Chinese University of Hong Kong and also from the USA”, it is described.
The first contract to train the teaching team and pedagogical content was signed in February 1979 with the Matteo Ricci group. “I believe it was another good service provided to the population”, wrote the former Governor. In 1991, the institution changed its name to what it currently has.
According to data from the 2024 annual report, the latest available, UM has 52,146 graduated students, and in the first semester of the 2024/2025 academic year, 15,147 students attended the university, from all educational levels. Highlight is the greater number of students from abroad, 9,328, compared to 5,819 local students.
Open day in Hengqin
Despite having been formally created in March, UM begins to celebrate 45 years of existence this Sunday with an Open Day. According to a statement from the educational institution, between 11 am and 5 pm the public will be able to visit the Lakeside Theater, where the first ceremony takes place, and then other areas of the campus in Hengqin, namely the main campus and the UM Scientific and Technological Research Institute in Zhuhai, in the Youth Entrepreneurship Valley in Hengqin.
This route also includes the possibility of visiting, for the first time, the Transitional Research and Education Site at Yuxin Tower, in the Cooperation Zone. “Through a wide range of on-site activities and live online broadcasts, the event will showcase UM’s latest developments and achievements in teaching, research and community service”, highlights the same note, which recalls how UM was the first higher education institution in Macau to “extend teaching and research activities to the Guangdong-Macao Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin”.
That day there will also be “approximately 250 activities on the main campus throughout the day, including admissions lectures, academic and research activities and interactive games”.
"Visitors interested in academic subjects can attend engaging lectures on science and other disciplines, while sports enthusiasts can explore UM's sports facilities. Families can also participate in interactive games at stands, scientific experiments, workshops and knowledge challenges organized by various faculties, residences and laboratories", it is revealed. On Open Day there will also be discounts in the restaurant area.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:07:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UCM | White Paper suggests methods to accelerate economic diversification</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/18/ucm-livro-branco-sugere-metodos-para-acelerar-diversificacao-economica/</link><description>The “White Paper on Scientific and Technological Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”, produced at the City University of Macau, refers to inequalities in the relationship between countries and concludes that “economic diversification has advanced at a slow pace”. Bárbara Morais, main writer of the document, explains the main conclusions of the analysis
On December 3rd, a White Paper was launched that provides a look and analysis of the way in which cooperation in scientific and technological areas between China, Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries has been taking place, outlining some criticisms, not only on this topic, but also on the economic direction that the Macao SAR is taking.
The document, entitled “White Paper on Scientific and Technological Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”, was produced by the City University of Macau (UCM) and had Bárbara Morais, a doctoral student at the institution, as main writer.
In an interview with HM, she describes that, in Macau, “economic diversification has advanced at a slower pace than desired, keeping the economy structurally dependent on gambling and tourism”.
"The central message of the White Paper is clear: Macau needs to accelerate the transition to functions with greater added value. However, the current context offers a renewed window of opportunity. With the support of the Greater Bay Area and, very specifically, the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, Macau now has new structural opportunities to recover lost momentum and reposition itself, not just as a cultural bridge, but as a true platform for innovation", he said.
Still on the territory, but in relation to Forum Macau, the “success in institutionalizing political dialogue” is mentioned, but the White Paper “points the finger at the insufficiency of execution mechanisms”. “To streamline the role of the Forum and transform it into a tool for tangible results, the White Paper advocates a paradigm shift: it is necessary to move from declarations of intent to technicality”, describes Bárbara Morais. The doctoral student suggests “the creation of specialized technical working groups, especially in the technological sphere, and the rigorous definition of performance indicators, such as the number of registered patents, startups created or joint research projects”.
“At the same time, it is suggested to establish a common agenda focused on areas of the future, such as green energy, health, the maritime economy and artificial intelligence, subject to a periodic assessment of progress”, he also said.
The place of arbitration
Taking these meager developments into account, the White Paper suggests that Macau assert itself “as a center for technological arbitration and intellectual property governance”.
HM questioned Bárbara Morais about what should be done in effective terms, taking into account the existence, for several years, of an arbitration center, and the fact that it has been a topic on the territory's political agenda for a long time. The doctoral student highlights that “in order for these ideas, debated for years, to stop being rhetoric and become reality, the Macao SAR needs to create a legal framework specialized in technological disputes aligned with the most demanding international standards”.
"It is essential to attract international experts and arbitrators through competitive incentives and establish an arbitration center that enjoys recognition both in Portuguese-speaking countries and in the Greater Bay Area. The objective is to develop mediation, certification and management services for intellectual property assets, positioning Macau as a 'safe haven', neutral and efficient, for the resolution of international technological disputes", he added.
Unequal cooperation
In global terms, and with regard to cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries (PLP), the White Paper refers to “top planning” by Beijing for cooperation in universities and scientific research. However, planning “does not translate, linearly, into equally effective execution mechanisms on the ground, nor does it guarantee homogeneous results among the nine Portuguese-speaking countries”.
Planning implies “clear guidelines, defined priorities and diplomatic instruments mobilized to guide this cooperation”, with policies such as “Made in China 2025” or the “Digital Silk Road”, which “integrate technological cooperation with the PLP into the very core of Chinese foreign policy and national innovation”, highlights the author.
However, there are “inequalities, which are perhaps the most striking feature of this relationship”, as Bárbara Morais explains. “The current scenario reveals a profound asymmetry, characterized by a ‘bicephaly’ in cooperation. (…) The main scientific capabilities, the robust technological infrastructure and the volume of effective cooperation are overwhelmingly concentrated in Portugal and Brazil”. On the contrary, “Portuguese-speaking African countries (PALOP) and Timor-Leste have a significantly lower participation”.
According to Bárbara Morais, the “disparity does not arise from a lack of political will, but rather from structural funding limitations, a shortage of qualified human resources and the fragility of local research institutions”. Thus, there is “two-speed cooperation, very asymmetrical within the Portuguese-speaking community itself”.
The White Paper highlights the “historic crossroads” in relation to cooperation between China and the PLP, which means “the urgent need to move from potential to implementation” in this matter.
"There are ambitious visions and strategic plans, but practical results remain below what is possible. To resolve this crossroads, the proposed path involves strengthening execution mechanisms, investing massively in talent and technical-scientific education, creating ecosystems of genuine collaborative innovation between China, Macau and the PLP, and, above all, having the courage to measure results and reformulate strategies based on empirical evidence, abandoning the discourse of circumstance in favor of economic and scientific pragmatism."
Gaps in Africa
Another of the conclusions of the White Paper is the “tenuity” of academic links with the African continent, which Bárbara Morais describes as a “fragile scenario”. “There is a triad of factors: the scarcity of installed scientific capacity, the chronic lack of funding and consistent mobility programs”, without forgetting “the absence of stable joint research structures”.
“To bridge this gap and create a lasting critical mass, the White Paper is not limited to diagnosis, suggesting concrete measures such as the robust reinforcement of research grants, the creation of joint doctoral programs, the implementation of collaborative laboratories and the design of academic mobility mechanisms specifically oriented to the African reality”, he adds.
The document also talks about the negative impact of “geopolitical asymmetries”, such as the “technological restrictions of the European Union and NATO on Portugal”. According to Bárbara Morais, “real and restrictive impacts” are at stake. "These limitations condition the participation of Portugal and, by extension, of other Portuguese-speaking actors that cooperate in a network with Lisbon, in high-technology projects that involve China. The impact is particularly sensitive in critical areas such as 5G telecommunications, defense, artificial intelligence and cybersecurity, creating barriers that require complex diplomatic navigation."
New strategies
The White Paper was developed at the UCM Research Institute on Portuguese-Speaking Countries, and written by Bárbara Morais with the participation of academic João Simões. The project is based on a review of academic literature on the topic and also on the results of the “Technological Cooperation Launch Seminar”, held on July 22, 2025 at UCM.
The work analyzes areas such as “strategic evolution”, “institutional mechanisms”, “technological milestones” and “structural challenges”, aiming to “provide evidence-based strategies to transform the potential of the China-PLP partnership into a concrete reality, creating a new model of technological cooperation for the Global South”, says a statement from UCM.</description><pubDate>2025-12-18 00:53:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia | Twelve killed in attack during Jewish festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/15/australia-doze-mortos-em-ataque-durante-festa-judaica/</link><description>At least twelve people died and many injured were transported to Sydney hospitals yesterday, after a shooting attack on the Australian beach of Bondi, while a Jewish celebration was taking place. “There are two people in police custody on Bondi beach”, reported the New South Wales State Police on its X account, which asks “the public to avoid the area”.
Citing police sources, the AFP news agency reports that the attack caused ten deaths. O serviço de ambulâncias de Nova Gales do Sul confirmou à televisão ABC que, pelo menos 16 pessoas foram transportadas para seis centros hospitalares da região.
Several witnesses report that it was a shooting attack carried out by an as yet undetermined number of armed people, but the authorities have not confirmed this information either. A British tourist told French news agency AFP that he saw “two gunmen dressed in black and armed with semi-automatic rifles”.
Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese has already issued a statement lamenting the “shocking and distressing scenes” coming from Bondi and confirmed the existence of injuries.
Part of the beach was the scene of a celebration of the Jewish festival of Hanukkah, which began yesterday and, although Australian authorities have not yet made any connection with the incident, the President of Israel, Isaac Herzog, denounced what he classified as a “vile terrorist attack against the Jews who were lighting the first candles” of the religious festival.
"Our heart is with them. The heart of the entire nation of Israel beats strong at this precise moment, as we pray for the recovery of the injured, we pray for them and we pray for those who lost their lives," he said in an official statement.</description><pubDate>2025-12-15 02:14:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | Government does not release data on suicides and attempts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/15/crime-governo-nao-divulga-dados-sobre-suicidios-e-tentativas/</link><description>After the Health Services, the Security department also stopped publishing data on suicides and attempts, after ten years of publication. The absence was noted in the release of crime data for the months of January to September this year, which show the increase in sexual abuse of minors to almost double
 
The Government stopped publishing data on suicide cases in Macau, as well as attempts. The absence of these numbers was noted by the newspaper Cheng Pou when it released crime data for the months of January and September this year on Friday.
The publication even questions whether “the data on suicide has become ‘the secret that cannot be said’ of the authorities, committed to building a happy Macau”, remembering that this data began to be released in 2015. Highlight is the fact that the Health Services also stopped publishing the statistics, something that was done every three months. In the case of the Security Secretariat, the data was monthly and was broken down by sex, age group and methods used.
The lack of numbers comes after Macau broke records in terms of suicide cases in 2024, registering 90 deaths, 2.27 percent more than in 2023. Compared to 2022, the increase was 12.5 percent. Of the 90 cases, 48 ​​concerned male victims and 42 female victims, aged between 12 and 76 years. The most recent data, for the first half of this year, reveals 41 deaths by suicide and 101 attempts.
In the release of crime statistics, on Friday, only one case of death by suicide appears in relation to an episode of homicide between brothers, which occurred in August this year, in the north zone. Here, the older brother jumped from the balcony, being suspected of having killed his younger brother due to financial disputes.
Break in crime
Looking at the crime panorama in general terms, there is a drop of 7.1 percent in the months under analysis, compared to the same period last year. The territory's authorities highlighted the sharp drop in computer crimes. The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, said that the drop is due to the “decreasing trend” of “crimes that attract more attention from society”, including serious violent crime, theft, robbery, fraud and computer crimes.
In the first nine months of the year, 187 violent crimes were recorded, which represents a drop of 11 percent compared to the same period in 2024 (210). Thefts, robberies and frauds fell by 7.7, 5.9 and 23.6 percent, respectively. Computer crime, which recorded 770 cases in the first nine months of 2024, showed a decline of 52.1 percent in the period under analysis, with 369 cases.
The decline in cases of fraud using telecommunications, cyber fraud and computer fraud, said Chan Tsz King, “reflects the effectiveness of the prevention and combat work carried out by the police, and the significant increase in public awareness about fraud prevention”, he said.
The Government also highlighted that crime related to illicit gambling increased by 985 percent between January and September this year, with 394 more cases compared to the same period in 2024. The increase is due to the entry into force, in October last year, of the law to combat illicit gambling crimes, which introduced “the new crime of ‘exploitation of illicit exchange for gambling’ and expanded the scope of coverage of some crimes related to illicit gambling”.
For the same reason, said the secretary, gambling-related crimes soared in the first three quarters of 2025 – 1,737 cases, 70.1 percent more than in the same period last year. In the past, the official said, fraud committed by people illegally exchanging money outside casinos “could not be identified as related to gambling”. “However, with the criminalization of ‘illegal money exchange’ and the improvement of legal provisions”, these cases “are now included in gambling crime statistics, thus increasing the number of crimes”, he indicated.
More abuse of minors
Chan Tsz King, who took office in October and presented the crime report for the first time on Friday, also referred to a 6.1 percent increase in crimes against the person, with child sexual abuse increasing by 86.7 percent, from 15 cases in the first nine months of 2024 to 28 cases in the same period this year.
The secretary explained that these are essentially “voluntary sexual acts between people of the same age”, with “transmission of photographs and pornographic images”, without forgetting cases of “less serious sexual harassment”.
“Cases involving people with family relationships were also identified, which deserves the attention of society”, said Chan Tsz King, who released data on awareness-raising actions on this problem: more than 70 activities carried out by the police, which saw the participation of more than 12,000 people, including students, guardians and teaching staff.
Drug trafficking and sale and drug consumption, in turn, registered an increase of 37.1 percent, with 13 more cases, and 72.7 percent, eight more cases, respectively. According to the secretary's presentation, the 48 cases registered in the three quarters and the respective increase are due to “the discovery of several cases of cross-border drug trafficking through the reinforcement of internal and external police cooperation”, highlighting a case that occurred in September, when 31 kilos of cannabis flower worth 31.77 million patacas were seized. Chan Tsz King said that this was “the biggest case of cannabis smuggling seized in the history of Macau”.
Between walls
In the case of the crime of rape, there was a decline in the number of rape crimes, to a total of 24 cases, 40 percent less than in the same period of the previous year.
The Secretary for Security added that “more than 70 percent of the victims were not residents of Macau”, and “the majority of these crimes occurred in hotel rooms”, while “a number of these involved pecuniary conflicts between the victims and the suspects, and it is not possible to rule out the hypothesis that some of the cases occurred in the context of a sexual transaction”.
In this context, the secretary clarified that the police authorities have been “in close communication with the hotel sector”, and “police devices and inspections in peripheral areas of hotels and casinos” have been reinforced. Between January and September, more than 160 police actions were carried out to combat prostitution, with 192 people suspected of engaging in prostitution activity being intercepted.
Furthermore, during the period in question, 17 cases of pimping or exploitation of prostitution were resolved, with the arrest of 26 suspects.
Silence as always
Questionado pela Lusa durante a conferência de imprensa sobre o primeiro caso a ser investigado em Macau no âmbito da segurança nacional, o secretário não fez comentários. “O caso (…) está a ser tratado pelas entidades judiciais e, devido ao sigilo, não seria adequado ao secretário da Segurança comentar”, completou Chan Tsz King, que era Procurador do Ministério Público quando o ex-deputado Au Kam San foi detido.
At the end of July, the territory's police announced the arrest of Au Kam San, the first under the state security defense law, which came into force in 2009, with the scope being expanded 14 years later. The accusation is not yet known and there is no information about who will defend the former deputy. With Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-15 01:25:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Entertainment Zone | Government admits change of purpose</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/zona-de-espectaculos-governo-admite-mudanca-de-finalidade/</link><description>The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, admitted, in this Wednesday's debate in the Legislative Assembly (AL), that the Open Air Performance Zone, in Cotai, could host other types of community activities than just concerts.
In response to an oral question from deputy Chan Lai Kei, the secretary stated that, after a year of experimental use, the intention is to “expand and reinforce the functions of the venue”, with “the spaces available between concerts being used to transform the venue into 3×3 basketball courts or spaces for family sporting activities”.
The Zone will therefore be “a space open to citizens in order to increase flexibility and general benefits of use”. “Regarding the issue raised regarding the introduction of diverse events such as cultural and creative fairs, among others, the Government will maintain an open attitude in the evaluation process”, said the secretary.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:18:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Chan Lai Kei warns Government of infiltration problems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/habitacao-chan-lai-kei-alerta-governo-para-problemas-de-infiltracoes/</link><description>Deputy Chan Lai Kei alerted the Government to the needs of residents who have leaks at home and are unable to contact their neighbors to resolve the problem. The matter was addressed through a written interpellation, in which the deputy indicated that there are currently 1,700 buildings in Macau that present structural aging problems.
“As both residents and buildings age, water leaks and blocked sewers caused by aging building drainage systems have become persistent problems that bother residents,” the congressman wrote.
In view of this situation, the deputy indicates that the Interservice Center for the Treatment of Water Infiltration in Public Administration Buildings received more than 1,900 requests for assistance and information between January and 12 December. “Almost 90 percent were resolved through mediation, but approximately 152 cases remained unresolved as owners failed to comply or cooperate after mediation,” he revealed. “Residents who face water infiltration problems are constantly faced with three major difficulties: obtaining access to the property, carrying out inspections and obtaining compensation”, he warned.
The legislator therefore asks the Government to promote a campaign on the obligation of property owners who refuse to cooperate with neighbors to resolve infiltrations. The deputy also asks the Executive to take “preventive” measures to deal with these problems.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:17:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Inquiry | More than half of young people disappointed with salaries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/inquerito-mais-de-metade-dos-jovens-desapontados-com-salarios/</link><description>A survey by the General Women's Association reveals that more than half of young people think salaries are below expectations and a third admit to a lack of professional experience. In terms of training, almost half of those surveyed would like to have more proficiency in languages
The Macau General Women's Association yesterday presented a survey focused on youth employment. When looking for a job, or changing professional careers, more than 50 percent of young people surveyed indicated that salaries and benefits are below their expectations. Still on this topic, around 42 percent pointed to high competition as the main challenge, a third confessed to not having relevant professional experience. Another challenge mentioned was the mismatch between skills and the demands of the Macau job market.
The mismatch between young people's abilities and work demands, combined with the lack of opportunities to develop advanced skills and the high cost of professional certifications was identified as one of the biggest obstacles to starting a career.
When it comes to developing skills, almost half of those surveyed pointed to language training as their preferred choice, followed by what the survey authors called “interpersonal skills” (solving complex problems and negotiating skills). The other skills listed by the young people were management and leadership skills.
Lack of space
Regarding training actions, the survey by the General Women's Association reveals that almost 50 percent of young people want to access practical courses on digital content (such as Artificial Intelligence and mega-data). On the other hand, around 46 percent would like to attend internationally recognized professional certification courses.
Furthermore, more than half of young people stated that Macau's labor market is too small, with no advanced skills development projects or internationally recognized professional training plans. The time and financial cost of this type of training was highlighted as an obstacle to professional progression by more than 37 percent of respondents.
In terms of priorities in the labor market, almost 75 percent of respondents indicated that they prioritized wages, the balance between work and free time and job stability. The survey was carried out online, between October and November, among residents aged between 18 and 45, with 568 valid responses.
During the presentation of the study results, deputies Wong Kit Cheng and Loi I Weng made recommendations to address the challenges enumerated by young people. The first suggestions were policies that the Government has indicated for years as priorities, such as the construction of the Deep Cooperation Zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin and the adequate diversification of the economy.
The deputies also asked for an increase in support for the Training and Accreditation Exams Program for Qualified Personnel to at least 10 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:16:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Bay | Promised alignment of social security systems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/grande-baia-prometido-alinhamento-de-sistemas-de-seguranca-social/</link><description>The governments of Guangdong and Macau reiterated their commitment to deepen cooperation in labor and social security matters, during a tour of a Macao SAR delegation to Guangzhou, Jiangmen and Zhongshan. The delegation made up of representatives from the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and the Social Security Fund participated in seminars and visited public service and professional training centers.
During the visits, Macao SAR representatives and Guangdong authorities agreed on details to implement professional internships for young people from Macau, as well as a social security data sharing mechanism between Guangdong and Macau. Reciprocal recognition of the levels of professional techniques and exams for “training qualified personnel with technical skills in the area of ​​rehabilitation due to work accidents” was also promised.
Regarding the visits themselves, the Macau delegation was at the Administrative Services Center in Jiangmen to analyze the process of social security services provided by Balcão Único to Macau residents and industrial projects set up in the city.
In Zhongshan, the delegation visited the technician training institute, “where it observed the national training base for Western confectionery and pastry, learning about the training work of the aforementioned qualified staff”, DSAL said in a statement yesterday.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:13:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Airport | Facial recognition speeds up security checks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/aeroporto-reconhecimento-facial-agiliza-controlo-de-seguranca/</link><description>The company that manages Macau International Airport announced yesterday the entry into operation of the new facial recognition system in the area of ​​security control, after a one-week trial period. The Macau International Airport Society specified that the system now allows passengers to go through security control in two minutes (without the need to open hand luggage or body searches).
Passengers over 11 years old, who have electronic travel documents, can register at check-in counters, self-service kiosks or electronic security gates. Once registered, facial recognition is associated with passport and boarding pass data, allowing you to proceed to the plane without showing physical documents or your travel ticket.
It was added that, currently, all doors connected to the boarding gates connected to bridges to the plane are "equipped with self-boarding systems for the convenience of passengers. The facial recognition system is part of the security area modernization plan at the airport which involves an investment of 43 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:11:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Car insurance | Request for review of coverage values</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/seguro-automovel-pedida-revisao-de-valores-de-cobertura/</link><description>Without any change for 15 years, the deputy linked to the Fujian community questions the Government about the revision of the minimum insurance value, which is currently 750 thousand patacas for mopeds and 1.5 million patacas for motorcycles and cars
Representative Song Pek Kei defends the need to increase the minimum amount of civil liability insurance coverage for traffic accidents. The matter was addressed through a written interpellation, with the legislator warning that the party responsible for the accident often finds it difficult to pay compensation.
Song indicates that currently if residents opt for the cheapest insurance, the maximum amount that insurers have to cover is MOP750,000 if they drive a moped, or MOP1.5 million if the vehicle driven is a car or motorcycle. However, the legislator considers the values ​​to be inappropriate because they have remained unchanged “for 15 years”, despite social development.
The deputy linked to the Fujian community also points out that as the median income of residents is close to 20 thousand patacas and “the compensation awarded by the courts for a single traffic accident normally exceeds the minimum limit of insurance coverage” the party considered responsible finds it difficult to “provide reasonable compensation to the victim” of the accident.
For these reasons, and because the coverage amount is “inadequate to respond to social developments”, Song questions the Government about whether it will increase the minimum coverage amount to respond to “the growing demand for compensation”. The deputy also suggests the creation of a mechanism for regularly reviewing the amount to avoid problems like the current one, in which the coverage value regularly deviates from reality.
Excessive compensation?
In the interpellation, Song Pek Kei also considers that the compensation determined by the courts must be reasonable, to keep pace with social developments. “Excessively high amounts of compensation impose an unreasonable burden on the responsible parties and are not in line with the evolution of contemporary society”, he pointed out.
According to Song, the issue is the fact that court decisions regularly condemn those responsible for accidents to cover non-material damages, such as mental suffering and loss of future income. As the insurance only covers “bodily damage and partial material damage”, the deputy indicates that those sentenced to pay are regularly in difficulty paying compensation.
Furthermore, the legislator wants clarification on the possibility of insurance covering the types of compensation that are now left out.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:09:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Young people | Joey Lao asks for increased allowance for first job</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/jovens-joey-lao-pede-reforco-do-subsidio-para-primeiro-emprego/</link><description>Currently, companies that hire young people for their first job can receive up to 15 thousand patacas, the deputy linked to the Jiangmen community defends the need to “keep up with the times” and make “appropriate adjustments” to the amount
Deputy Joey Lao defended strengthening support for hiring young people looking for their first job. The request was made through a written interpellation, published on the Legislative Assembly portal.
According to the legislator linked to the Jiangmen community, the current subsidy for Hiring Young People Looking for their First Job has been in force since 2004, without significant changes, which means that it no longer corresponds to the current reality. “After more than two decades in force, certain provisions of the regulation have become manifestly out of step with the demands of Macau’s economic and social development”, pointed out Joey Lao. The first problem identified by the deputy is the fact that the value of support “has remained unchanged for 21 years”.
The economist also explains that since 2004, employers who hire people with educational qualifications equivalent to secondary education receive “only” a subsidy of 12 thousand patacas. This support is delivered over six months, corresponding to an amount of 2 thousand patacas per month.
The current form of the subsidy also defines that young people hired with qualifications corresponding to higher education receive a total support of 15 thousand patacas, distributed over six monthly installments of 2,500 patacas. Given the new context of greater difficulty in finding a job for young people, which the deputy simply defines as the need to “keep up with the times”, Joey Lao wants to know if the Executive will make “appropriate adjustments to the amount of the subsidy”.
The question of age
In addition to the value of the subsidy, the deputy also asks to consider increasing the age limit for granting the subsidy by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). According to current regulations, the subsidy can only be distributed to young people under the age of 26, which in Joey Lao's view “does not cover the increasingly large group of young people [over 26 years old] looking for work”.
The deputy defends the need for changes also with the fact that in the case of the Financing Plan for Professional Careers of Young People in Macau in the Greater Bay Area, the Government sets the age limit at 35 years. With this support, the Executive finances the careers of those who move to Mainland China with an amount of 5 thousand patacas per month, which can reach 90 thousand patacas. Given the discrepancy, Joey Lao argues that the subsidy to support the hiring of young people looking for their first job should cover people aged up to 35 years.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:53:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Waiting for the light</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/a-espera-da-luz/</link><description>There are those who say that when God closes a door, he always opens a window. What if both are closed? What happens to those inside? Well, either they suffocate to death or they get bored to death.
In recent years, stores in Macau have been closing one after another. When everyone expected a window to be opened for the business to prosper, the right to open the window was given to certain contractors. Social enterprises are not commercial entities and the outcome of granting them exclusive management of commercial activities is not difficult to predict.
If the planning were viable, the operation of the Canídromo Yat Yuen in Macau and the Jockey Club in Taipa should have been handed over to community organizations a long time ago.
I recently had dinner at a hotel that once had a casino. I noticed that the hotel's parking lot was abandoned and several floors of this building, which housed several stores, are currently empty. After asking what had happened, I learned that, in addition to the closure of the satellite casino, the Chinese restaurant had also closed. Of course, this hotel is not located in any of the six historical zones defined by the SAR Government. The employees at the satellite casino received new job offers, but what happened to the staff at the Chinese restaurant, who pays attention to their future?
I am concerned that while the “diversification of 1+4 industries” is not yet mature, the drastic transformations at the core of Macau's economy will have an impact on the economic structure. Although the unemployment rate is apparently low, the reality of the employment situation deserves attention. Chief Executive Sam Hou Fai encouraged young people to leave their comfort zone and venture to the Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macao Greater Bay Area, however, the Greater Bay Area faces its own challenges. Young people from Macau who study outside the city choose to stay there and each one will have their own reasons. The SAR Government claims that it wants to attract talented foreigners to Macau, while encouraging our young people to leave the city, which seems contradictory. Former deputy Lam U Tao even expressed concern about the number of non-resident teachers in Macau, proposing the creation of a mechanism that would lead more than 100,000 non-resident workers to leave the city and “return job vacancies to local workers”. Unfortunately, although Lam passed the government assessment in the 2021 Legislative Assembly elections, he was disqualified for the 2025 elections. When will the “window to democracy” be opened so that residents can breathe fresh air?
Looking doesn't kill hunger. I recently visited the renovated Taipa Market and saw that the pedestrian traffic areas are still insufficient. Vegetable, meat and seafood vendors were waiting for customers, in stark contrast to the hustle and bustle of Gongbei Market in Zhuhai. The doors and windows of the Taipa Market were open, but the air (the clientele) was insufficient. Sellers have tried hard, but the results continue to be disappointing. Why does this happen? Is it useful to turn off lights at night and turn them on during the day?
I believe that the main people responsible for the SAR Government should leave their comfort zones. At the end of the afternoon, they should take public transport and get off at the stop in front of the Public Administration Building on Rua do Campo and experience the warm feeling of sharing the journey with other passengers. They should also try to cross the border on foot at the Portas do Cerco Border Post and the Qingmao Border Post, in the morning and late afternoon, witnessing the magnificent spectacle of “integration in the Great Bay”. With numerous advertisements saying “excellent store for rent” in various areas of Macau, how can the lights be on after they have been turned off?
The development of an urban area and the formation of a commercial area cannot be achieved simply by turning on the lights, they require collective wisdom.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:36:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela and the New World Geopolitics</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/venezuela-e-a-nova-geopolitica-mundial/</link><description>“Power reshapes the world not only through action, but through the precedents it gives to create.”  – Henry Kissinger
The United States' military intervention in Venezuela, on January 3, 2026, cannot be understood simply as a gesture of strength in a weakened country but must be read as an event that exposes the structural tension between sovereignty, responsibility and power in a world in transition. The operation, carried out with almost surgical precision, was limited to extracting Nicolás Maduro and Cilia Flores from Caracas and transporting them to New York, where they face a judicial process that quickly went beyond the criminal sphere to become a political, philosophical and legal phenomenon of global reach.
The absence of territorial occupation, provisional administration or any attempt to reorganize the Venezuelan State for now reveals a doctrine that breaks with the interventionist paradigm of the beginning of the 21st century in which the United States does not seek to rebuild countries, only to neutralize sources of threat, leaving behind the political void that inevitably forms when a regime loses its center of gravity. This void was filled by Delcy Rodríguez, whose rise is not the result of any popular mandate, but of the inertia of a state machine that, long ago, stopped functioning as a republican institution and began to operate as an instrument of survival for an exhausted political project. Its legitimacy is purely mechanical, derived from Chavismo's internal line of succession, and not from the will expressed at the polls, which in 2024 gave Edmundo González Urrutia a mandate that he never exercised.
Maduro's extraction did not dissolve the networks that supported the regime; he just removed the figure that gave them faces. Delcy inherited a corroded state, but functional enough to maintain the appearance of normality, while the underground military, economic and criminal structures continue to operate with the same logic that transformed Venezuela into a narco state. The trial in New York became a legal laboratory that challenges traditional categories of international law. The invocation of universal jurisdiction for transnational crimes committed by a head of state, albeit illegitimate, captured by military means puts into tension principles that, for decades, seemed unquestionable. Sovereign immunity, designed to protect the stability of international relations, confronts the idea that certain crimes, due to their nature, cannot be shielded by functional prerogatives.
The defense will argue that the capture violates fundamental norms, while the prosecution will maintain that the seriousness of the alleged facts justifies the exception. The court will become the stage for a dispute that goes beyond the individual destiny of the accused and touches on the very balance between sovereignty, responsibility and power. The global transmission of the process will amplify every gesture and word, converting the trial into a political event that redefines conceptual boundaries. The legal discussion inevitably refers to historical precedents that shaped the contemporary understanding of individual criminal responsibility. The trial of Eichmann, captured in Buenos Aires and taken to Jerusalem in 1961, is often cited as an example that extraterritorial capture, although controversial, does not necessarily invalidate the legitimacy of the process.
The doctrine that emerged from that case with the idea that certain crimes are so serious that they transcend borders is echoed in the current debate. However, the comparison has limits as Eichmann was a fugitive without official status, while Maduro was head of state at the time of his capture, which reactivates the discussion about functional and personal immunities. The Pinochet case, partially tried in the United Kingdom, introduced another fissure in the traditional legal edifice by admitting that crimes of torture cannot be protected by sovereign immunity. International jurisprudence has evolved since then, but remains fragmented, oscillating between the defense of sovereignty and the affirmation of an international legal order that holds individuals accountable regardless of their position. Venezuela, however, remains suspended between two periods.
The democratic opposition, although legitimized by the vote, remains far from exercising power. Edmundo González Urrutia, exiled in Spain, became a symbol of a legitimacy that exists internationally, but not in the territory he should govern. María Corina Machado, reappeared after the fall of Maduro, regained internal protagonism, but faces a structural obstacle, that the formal State is only the visible surface of a parallel system, where criminal networks, military interests and informal alliances shape political reality. The opposition has legitimacy, but does not control the territory; it has international support, but it does not have the coercive instruments that define effective power. The Venezuelan military structure, far from being dismantled by the American operation, remains fragmented and permeated by contradictory loyalties.
Maduro's extraction neutralized only the closest circle, leaving intact a hierarchy eroded by decades of politicization, corruption and involvement in illicit economies. Many senior officers maintain links with networks that operate outside the legality, while intermediate sectors seek to reposition themselves to guarantee their own survival. The absence of broader institutional intervention allowed the narco state to continue to function, now under the leadership of Delcy Rodríguez, who is trying to reorganize Chavismo without its historical leader, preserving the informal mechanisms that guarantee the continuity of power. The Venezuelan economy, devastated by years of mismanagement and hyperinflation, remains in a state of structural collapse. PDVSA, once a symbol of prosperity, operates far below its capacity, and the global fall in oil prices further reduces financial room for maneuver. Maduro's extraction did not change this reality. Without deep reforms, political transition and international trust, the economy remains paralyzed.
The criminalization of the political economy impedes any sustainable recovery, as illicit networks capture revenues, distort incentives, and block any attempt at institutional reconstruction. Venezuela has become an extreme case of a state where the formal economy is just a residual fragment of a system dominated by parallel circuits. The Portuguese community, one of the largest Portuguese-speaking diasporas outside Europe, lives in an environment of permanent uncertainty. Political instability, the lack of reforms and the continuity of criminal networks create significant risks, but also opportunities if a minimum of predictability emerges. Portugal can play a relevant role through reinforced consular protection and economic diplomacy, but any initiative will depend on the country's internal developments. At the international level, the American operation reinforced the tendency to replace multilateralism with surgical unilateral actions.
The lack of coordination with international organizations weakened traditional alliances and intensified rivalries with emerging powers, in a context in which Russia and China had responded with military demonstrations in the Caribbean and the Persian Gulf to signal that they contest the power projection of the United States and intend to preserve their influence in a hemisphere historically sensitive to external intervention. Venezuela has thus become a microcosm of the new global order; a space where strategic disputes, legal tensions and conflicts of legitimacy intersect. The country's future will depend on the interaction between internal and external factors, now profoundly changed by Delcy Rodríguez's cooperation with Washington and the increasing control of the oil sector by the Americans.
Between 2026 and 2030, four main trajectories can be outlined. The first is the consolidation under the tutelage of Delcy Rodríguez, which not only represents the continuity of Chavismo, but rather the adaptation of the regime to a new geopolitical reality. Cooperation with the United States transforms Chavismo into a partially domesticated system, where the narco state continues to operate, but within externally imposed limits. Stability becomes dependent on American tolerance, the relative discipline of the Armed Forces and the regime's ability to redistribute oil rents under implicit surveillance. It is not a sovereign stability, but a stability under guardianship, in which Caracas governs while Washington defines the perimeter of the possible.
The second trajectory is the agreed transition, now reconfigured by the centrality of oil. It is no longer just a controlled exit in exchange for personal guarantees for sectors of Chavismo, but a political-energy negotiation in which Washington accepts a gradual opening and institutional recomposition as long as it maintains decisive influence over the oil sector. Delcy becomes the bridge between the system and the transition, offering Americans energy predictability and Chavismo guarantees of partial survival. Political change would be limited but real, and would allow controlled pluralism under international supervision.
The third trajectory is the implosion of the system, now aggravated by oil cooperation itself. Shared management of the energy sector could deepen internal fissures, especially between the military, criminal networks and ideological factions that see approaching the United States as betrayal. Economic deterioration, inequality in the redistribution of income and competition for resources under external supervision can accelerate the fragmentation of the State, creating enclaves of autonomous power and multiplying armed actors. In this scenario, energy protection does not prevent implosion; amplified, by introducing new reasons for dispute and distrust.
The fourth trajectory is the possibility of a second American intervention, now more plausible precisely because oil cooperation creates an evaluation criterion. If, despite energy control, Chavismo reorganized under Delcy continues to operate as a narco state and no substantive political transformation occurs, Washington may conclude that the extraction of Maduro was insufficient. The new intervention would not necessarily imply territorial occupation, but could take surgical forms such as the neutralization of specific military actors, blocking of illicit financial networks, additional operations against security structures or even a multinational intervention legitimized by extreme humanitarian collapse. The mere existence of this hypothesis weakens the first trajectory, as Delcy's consolidation would only be sustainable in an international environment willing to tolerate the continuity of Chavismo, which is becoming increasingly less likely.
Thus, Venezuela remains in a political and institutional limbo without Maduro, but with Chavismo; with functional administration, but without legitimacy; with oil cooperation with the United States, but without full sovereignty. Maduro's extraction and oil co-management did not end the cycle; they just reshaped the battlefield. Reconstruction will require inclusive dialogue, profound reform and an international commitment to legality. Until then, the country remains suspended between the end of a regime that does not exist and the impossibility of a future that has not yet begun.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:16:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Homo Sapiens versus “Goldilocks Conditions”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/o-homo-sapiens-versus-goldilocks-conditions/</link><description>Around 13.8 billion years ago, what is known as the “big bang” occurred. From this great explosion an expanding universe emerged, which is essentially made up of dark energy, dark matter, gases, dust, planets and stars. These grouped together to form galaxies, in one of which, the Milky Way, our planet is located, fortunately very far away, around 25,800 light years, from the black hole that occupies the central area.
By happy chance, during the evolution of the universe, planet Earth, which was formed about 4.5 billion years ago, occupied an ideal position to create the conditions for life to emerge. The first signs of life are due to the existence of oxygen in the atmosphere and hydrosphere, and to the Earth orbiting around the Sun at a distance that allows it to receive radiation whose intensity can be considered neither excessive nor lacking. Thus, the first species of beings emerged that evolved, giving rise to hundreds of thousands of other species that adapted to climate variations.
The climate system has, however, undergone changes due to several factors, namely cosmic and volcanic in origin. Cosmic factors include the variation in solar activity and the Milankovitch cycles, which consist of changes in the orbit around the Sun, related to the eccentricity, obliquity and oscillation of the Earth's axis. The action of these and other factors resulted in climate changes, including those that caused the ice ages and interglacials.
The conditions favorable to the existence of life on our planet are commonly referred to, in circles related to astronomy and astrobiology, as “Goldilocks conditions”, which could be translated as “golden snail conditions”, so called by analogy with the children's story “Goldilocks and the three bears”, very popular in English-speaking countries, written by Robert Southey (1774-1843). In this story, a girl with golden curls always chose the middle ground as the best option among the possibilities that came across her throughout her mischief. For example, between three plates of porridge, one very hot, one very cold and one lukewarm, I would choose the lukewarm one, or between three beds I would prefer the one that was neither too hard nor too soft, but moderately soft. When applied to astronomy, this concept metaphorically refers to a habitable zone in the universe.
In reality, even though there may be other planets with conditions similar to those on Earth, it will not be possible, at least in the next few decades, to reach them and create the conditions so that our civilization can survive in the event of a collapse of living conditions on our planet. We must therefore take care of the Earth's climate system. Otherwise, mass extinctions of species could occur. This has already happened five times and there are those who claim that we are facing the sixth extinction, due to human activities, with special emphasis on climate change, pollution, destruction of habitats and unrestrained exploitation of natural resources.
Currently, no significant trend has been detected regarding cosmic factors that could alter these “Goldilocks conditions”. However, when it comes to human behavior, the reality is that, if we do not curb the indiscriminate use of fossil fuels, we are causing a significant increase in global warming. Humanity is not ensuring that these conditions persist, given that our planet has been warming since the beginning of the industrial era, at a rate never observed before, which causes the degradation of the various components of the climate system. And the near future does not look bright, as the country that emits the most greenhouse gases has at its head an irresponsible government that continues to ignore the warnings of institutions responsible for monitoring climate change and ensuring the sustainability of our planet. Worse than that, it has been taking measures contrary to these recommendations, such as, for example, withdrawing from the Paris Agreement, dismissing scientists from organizations that deal with the atmosphere and oceans, or cutting funding to universities where research related to climate change is carried out. Finally, a list of measures that could contribute to the deterioration of the climate system, thus posing a threat to life on our planet. The worst thing is that, as the former Secretary-General of the United Nations, Kofi Annan, stated, “there is no planet B”.
But, one might ask, «what does all this have to do with these “Goldilocks conditions”?».  In reality, the changes that the climate has undergone and which are estimated to have caused, in the last four hundred and fifty million years, some of the five mass extinctions of living beings, took place over thousands of years. It is commonly accepted by paleontologists and paleoclimatologists that the greater or lesser concentration of carbon dioxide was one of the causes of climate change that was the basis for most mass extinctions. Only one of the great extinctions, that of dinosaurs and other species of megafauna, is not directly related to climate, but rather due to the impact of an asteroid with Earth, around 66 million years ago.
The big difference between the climate changes of thousands of years ago and the changes that the climate is currently undergoing is the fact that those changes occurred slowly, over thousands of years, while the current ones have only been occurring since the beginning of the industrial revolution, that is, for around two and a half hundred years.
According to cosmologist Stephen Hawking (1942–2018), “Like Goldilocks, the development of intelligent life requires that planetary temperatures be ‘just right'”. Inspired by this statement from someone who has studied the evolution of the universe in depth, we can only contribute to ensuring that these “Goldilocks conditions” continue to be fulfilled.
Luis Queirós (1) will certainly forgive me for using the calculations contained in his book “Humanity and the Future” to highlight how recent the appearance of Homo sapiens is, in relation to the appearance of the first signs of life, between 3 billion and 4 billion years ago. Abandoning periods on a geological scale, which are difficult to grasp, and resorting to matching an intermediate value, for example 3.6 billion years, to 40 hours, Homo sapiens would have appeared only in the last fifteen seconds. Let me add that, maintaining this correspondence, the approximately 250 years since the industrial revolution correspond to 0.012 seconds. Let us hope that in the next few thousandths of a second Homo sapiens will curb the use of fossil fuels and carry out an effective energy transition, taking measures to halt and reverse global warming, ensuring that “Goldilocks conditions” continue to protect us.
(Meteorologist)
(1) Luis Queirós – author of “The World in Transition” and “Humanity and the Future”. Founder of the Marktest Group, a pioneering entity in market research in Portugal. He established the “Fundação Vox Populi” and created the blog “Transição”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:14:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Christmas isn't sexy for everyone</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/07/o-natal-nao-e-sexy-para-toda-a-gente/</link><description>I found interesting studies on how libido fluctuates among people around the holidays. There are those who have the conditions to feel a lot of sexual desire and spend the holidays in intimate moments of passion, and there are those – which I believe is the majority – feel a total disconnection with their libido. The Christmas films that, thanks to streaming platforms, proliferate by the hundreds every year, suggest that people should be more romantic and affectionate, and sex should follow this trend. The discrepancy in libido, which could point to inter-individual differences, also suggests that desire responds to the context in which we are inserted.
There is a study that shows that parties correspond to a spike in interest in sex, not only by analyzing online discussions/searches, but also by the spike in births essentially 9 months later. Sexuality somehow reacts to the symbolic aspects that parties carry, through the desire for closeness and contact.
However, this will not be the universal experience. It is also reported that, in the same Christmas context, we have people with high sexual desire, and others with low sexual desire.  Most likely the answer to the discrepancy lies in the way the festivities are viewed.
On the one hand, it is a time of deceleration, which increases the erotic potential. Research in sexual psychology repeatedly shows that lower stress states are associated with higher levels of sexual arousal and satisfaction. When the nervous system leaves “survival” mode, desire has room to reappear. It is also a time that activates feelings of nostalgia, which can increase feelings of connection and vitality — emotional states that facilitate intimacy and desire.
On the other hand, the festivities also carry dynamics, through memories and melancholy, which can be hard and heavy. Family conflicts, loneliness, anxiety, unfulfilled expectations: for many people, Christmas is not an emotional refuge but a relational minefield. And sexual desire is highly sensitive to these internal states. Psychological stress and emotional fatigue are consistently associated with decreased libido and sexual responsiveness.
A small mention can also be made of alcohol, that sexual shaper, omnipresent at parties. A drink or two can reduce inhibitions and increase subjective feelings of desire or closeness. But this effect is fragile. Larger amounts impair physiological arousal and sexual response. The result, for many people, is a short spike in desire followed by tiredness, disconnection or frustration — a common dynamic during the festive season.
All this to say that the same trigger – Christmas and its festivities – brings some people closer to their libido, and takes it away from others. Christmas, therefore, amplifies what is already within us. For those who associate this time with security, rest and emotional connection, the body responds with more erotic openness. For those who experience Christmas as stress, exposure or emotional regression, desire tends to recede.
The problem is not in libido, but in expectations. The cultural idea that Christmas should be a sexy, romantic and intimate time creates pressure that does little to help. Desire does not respond well to symbolic imperatives or emotional calendars. It responds to human conditions: rest, security, space or absence of obligation.
Accepting that Christmas can be exciting for some and completely desexualizing for others, or both at different times, is a more honest and healthy way of looking at human sexuality. Not all intimacy needs to culminate in sex. And if Christmas is devoid of desire, wait until January.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 02:26:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Tower | Show celebrates Sino-Portuguese culture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/torre-de-macau-espectaculo-celebra-cultura-sino-portuguesa/</link><description>A new theatrical show takes the stage tomorrow to explore how 500 years of contact between Portuguese and Chinese cultures gave Macau “a unique identity”.
In the third edition of the “Macasaphis” series, the experimental theater group Frost Ice Snow Creative brings together music, theater, fashion, oral stories and stand-up comedy in the Macau Tower auditorium. The director, Sileas Ko Weng Si, told Lusa yesterday that, after a two-year break due to lack of funding, the group decided to return with the theme “Sino-Portuguese culture”.
"Sino-Portuguese culture is everywhere, but we don't even realize it anymore. People often get confused, without understanding how it influences our lives", explained Sileas Ko. The first edition of “Macasahpis”, in 2022, had already been dedicated to particular elements of the region.
“The presence of the Chinese and Portuguese languages, the historical monuments, the fact that we have the largest number of holidays in the world, both Buddhist and Catholic,” said Ko. Portuguese is one of the two official languages ​​of Macau, at least during the first 50 years of the new semi-autonomous Chinese region, according to the bilateral agreement that allowed the transition of administration in December 1999.
The 2023 edition had as guests Tuna Macaense, a musical group from the Eurasian community, made up mainly of Portuguese descendants, who play songs in the Creole dialect, Patuá. But this time the group decided to go further and celebrate how Portuguese influence is also felt among the Chinese in Macau, the show's producer, Casta Lai Chit, told Lusa.
“Maybe people still feel some shame in defining our culture and identity, because we are Chinese, but we are not the same as others”, explained Casta Lai, who has Portuguese nationality. “People are proud of Macau’s culture, but they have some shame in showing it”, lamented Sileas Ko. "Sino-Portuguese culture makes our city even more special. Without it, there would only be casinos", he added.
Cultural power
With an area of ​​just 33 square kilometers and less than 680,000 inhabitants, Macau “is a tiny fish” in the context of China, with a population of 1.4 billion, Casta Lai highlighted. “If it weren’t for Sino-Portuguese culture, Macau wouldn’t be important at all,” argued the producer.
The show includes a part in which, in a humorous way, the population of Macau is treated as “an endangered species” and not just because the city has the lowest birth rate in the world, said Sileas Ko. Casta Lai warned that "maybe after 50 years the culture will be different. If that happens, maybe people will look around and miss what was lost."</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:39:21</pubDate></item><item><title>First retrospective of Portuguese artist Helena Almeida in Asia opens on the 23rd</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/primeira-retrospectiva-da-artista-portuguesa-helena-almeida-na-asia-inaugura-dia-23/</link><description>The Macau Museum of Art (MAM) will open the first retrospective of Portuguese artist Helena Almeida (1934-2018) in Asia on January 23, announced one of the exhibition's curators.
The exhibition “Helena Almeida: I'm Here – Presença and Resonance” is “one of the most comprehensive ever presented” and will be on display until April 26, Margarida Saraiva said on social media. The MAM curator stated that the retrospective will be divided into five sections, “chronologically and thematically”, including one dedicated to the first paintings and another to “the body as sculpture and the dialogue between bodies”.
Saraiva named Helena Almeida as “one of the most relevant Portuguese and European artists of her generation”, who “transformed the act of self-representation into an intense exploration of the body, space, resilience and impermanence”.
“His performative gestures — captured only through the lens of his studio — continue to challenge and expand the limits of painting, drawing and photography,” explained the curator. “This exhibition is simultaneously a tribute to Helena Almeida’s extraordinary legacy and an affirmation of the power of curatorial collaboration between cultures”, argued Saraiva.
The retrospective's main curator is Delfim Sardo, professor at the University of Coimbra and author of the book “Helena Almeida, Pés no Chão, Cabeça no Céu”, and the Chinese Song Zhen as co-curator.
Divide by two
In December, the Macau Cultural Institute indicated in a statement that the exhibition will bring together around 42 sets made up of 190 pieces by the Portuguese artist. Another part of the exhibition, “Resonância – Corpo. Objecto. Reflexão”, was opened on December 19, with pieces by six artists from Macau and mainland China, invited to interact with the work of Helena Almeida.
Born in Lisbon in 1934, Helena Almeida created, from the 1960s onwards, a multifaceted work, giving rise to a work that stood out for its self-representation, reflecting on the tension relationships between the body, space and the work. He used his body as a support and creative object, using painting, photography, engraving, installation and video. Helena Almeida studied painting at the Escola Superior de Belas-Artes in Lisbon, beginning to exhibit individually in 1967, at Galeria Buchholz.
The artist represented Portugal at the Venice Biennale on two occasions: in 1982 and 2005, and in 2004 she participated in the Sydney Biennale, with her work being exhibited in individual and collective exhibitions in national and international museums and galleries.
In 2015, he presented a traveling solo exhibition Corpus at Fundação de Serralves (2015), in Porto, in Paris (2016), in Brussels (2016) and Valencia (2017). In 2017, he also presented a solo exhibition “Work is never finished” at the Art Institute, in Chicago, in the United States.
His work is present in Portuguese and international collections such as: Berardo Collection, Lisbon; Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, Lisbon; Serralves Foundation, Porto; Hara Museum of Contemporary Art, Tokyo; Barcelona Museum of Contemporary Art; Museo Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofía, Madrid; MUDAM – Musée d’Art Moderne Grand-Duc Jean, Luxembourg; Tate Modern, London.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:25:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Boi Warehouse | Three artists present visions of Macau on display</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/armazem-do-boi-tres-artistas-apresentam-visoes-de-macau-em-exposicao/</link><description>“Land and Sea” is the new exhibition hosted by Armazém do Boi and which opens to the public tomorrow. Featuring works by David Fank, this exhibition is the result of the artist's personal experiences in the Greater Bay Area, including cities such as Macau, Zhuhai and Guangzhou. Also noteworthy are the exhibitions by Yuan Zeqiang and Fan Xianxin
A new exhibition opens tomorrow at Armazém do Boi. It is “Land and Sea”, written by David Fank, and which can be seen until February. According to a note from Armazém do Boi, the exhibition is divided into two main installations, with the themes of “Earth” and “Sea”, revealing an “exhibition space built like a room where blue and green meet, serving as the artist’s version of a ‘map'”
It is in this type of map that the artist's “personal travel experiences” through the Greater Bay Area are shown, namely in places such as Macau, Zhuhai and Guangzhou, without forgetting Beijing. The public can see “an interpretation of these diverse geographic perspectives”, in which David Fank creates “actions such as walks, photography and objects that anchor and generate this map”.
“These crystallize in his understanding of the meanings behind these spaces and, naturally, in the change of these meanings – the artist’s gaze and associations, in a sense as an ‘outsider’, thus become manifest”, he further explains.
Tomorrow, Wang Jing will give an introduction to the exhibition, starting at 4pm, with “Land and Sea” being the result of an artistic residency carried out by David Fank at Armazém do Boi, namely with the “Artistic Residency Program 3+0/1+1 (Macau / Project 2025)”.
David Fank was born in 1984, has a degree and master's degree from the Higher School of Fine Arts in Paris and also a doctorate from the Central Academy of Fine Arts in Beijing, China. He works mainly with photography, installation and sculpture.
The stone as origin
Another exhibition that can also be seen at Armazém do Boi starting tomorrow is “Seak Kam Tong”, by Yuan Zeqiang, curated by Hu Bin. This exhibition is also the result of the same artistic residency program that hosted the work of David Fank.
Here, Yuan Zeqiang establishes a relationship between art and stone, and in turn with the territory itself. “The relationship with stone begins the moment you enter Macau: under your feet, you have a mosaic stone floor”, which includes the Portuguese sidewalk, in addition to “the Temple of A-Má was built on a rocky hill, having become a place where residents and visitors turn for spiritual support”.
This exhibition presents “three-dimensional collages that reveal the dualities and truths of modern life”, where Yuan Zeqiang explores the different dimensions, perspectives and meanings of stones in a territory like Macau.
"The Portuguese sidewalk, made of fragmented stone, in Macau is a legacy of Portuguese colonial history, and this homogeneous material environment seems to reflect the clash and fusion of multiple cultures in the city. In everyday life, stone appears as a ubiquitous landscape element, something particularly evident in Macau", said Yuan Zeqiang, quoted in the same note.
Relationship with the sea
Still at Armazém do Boi, the public can see “Standing Wave Manifold”, by Fan Xianxin, curated by Sun Xiaoyu, which explores Macau's relationship with water and the way in which the territory was built with permanent mutations.
"'Sea-Mirror' is one of the many names that Macau has had throughout its history. This image refers to a state of immobilization located in a specific time and space. In this city surrounded by water, the border between water and land has been continuously reconstructed since the 19th century to the present day, and the evolution of denominations has occurred together with the changing trajectories of systems, power and identity", of the territory itself, explains a note about the exhibition.
The artist, who also completed a period of artistic residency at Armazém do Boi, analyzes Macau “from observations and travels”, trying to “understand how systems, landscapes and Feng Shui act together in shaping our concrete and detailed daily lives”.
This exhibition presents concepts such as “standing waves” and “varieties” that are not only physical, but reveal “dynamic equilibrium structures that are formed with the interference of two waves that go in opposite directions, but that constitute a method to interpret the modernization process in Macau”.
In this way, we try to understand “the complex totality that is woven by countless fragments, all of them interconnected”. Thus, “Standing Wave Manifold” focuses on the search for investigation “of a ‘mobility’ structure built from ‘movement'”, it is described.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:23:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative Macao | Exhibition “Flow”, by Alice Costa, presented today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/creative-macau-exposicao-flow-de-alice-costa-apresentada-hoje/</link><description>Creative Macau presents a new exhibition to the public today. This is “Flow”, by local artist Alice Costa (Lili), a series of works that presents “organic forms and fluid lines that capture the spontaneity of nature”. In this exhibition, the artist “employs techniques such as impasto, splashes and layers, to create textured surfaces that invite visual and tactile involvement”, reads the note released by the gallery.
Alice Costa (Lilli) is a Macau-based painter whose work explores the essence of nature through form, texture and emotion. Born in Macau to a Portuguese father and a Chinese mother, Alice Costa initially pursued a career in Law, graduating from the University of Macau in 1994 and serving as a judge at the Court of First Instance from 1997 onwards.
However, “a deep creative vocation led her to painting three years ago”, now dedicating herself completely to the abstract style of painting. Also according to Creative Macau, the artist's work “is a dialogue between the structured and the organic, translating the rhythms of the natural world, such as forests, oceans, storms and light, into non-representational forms”.
"Alice Costa's paintings are sensory experiences. They ask the viewer not to recognize, but to feel, to connect with the invisible emotions and primitive rhythms within the chaos and serenity of nature", he further explains.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:07:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM | 13 plan applications received for international companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/ipim-recebidas-13-candidaturas-a-plano-para-empresas-internacionais/</link><description>The Macau Trade and Investment Promotion Institute announced that it received 13 applications in the first two months of a program launched to attract international companies to the Macao SAR. More than 500 companies requested information about the support plan
The Macau Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM) revealed in a statement, released on Wednesday, that it had received 13 applications for the “Plan for Economic Development within the scope of Support for the Establishment of the First Store in Macau”, opened in November last year. The entity added that it is analyzing applications to grant “financial support in accordance with budgetary capacity and public interest”.
The Economic Development Plan within the scope of Support for the Establishment of the First Store in Macau provides support of up to one million patacas. To receive maximum support, companies must follow certain requirements, such as establishing themselves in NAPE, Areia Preta, Iao Hon, San Kio area, Praia do Manduco, Fai Chi Kei, Doca do Lam Mau, Bairro de Tamagnini Barbosa or Ilha Verde. Furthermore, they must have a minimum area, as well as a certain number of full-time local employees.
IPIM also highlighted that more than 500 companies requested information about the program, which was launched on November 1st. The plan lasts three years and has six application phases, the first of which runs until the end of January. At the end of November, the institute's president, Che Weng Keong, said in the Legislative Assembly that among the companies that requested more information about the plan were “brands from Portugal”.
IPIM recalled that it “took the initiative” to contact entities in mainland China, Southeast Asia and Portuguese and Spanish speaking countries.
Harvest fruits
The program, which aims to “enrich the tourist charm of Macau and boost the community economy”, was presented in Lisbon and Porto, at the beginning of October, by IPIM officials, who then also held presentations in neighboring Spain, in Madrid and Barcelona.
IPIM promised to continue publicizing the plan, including through participation in convention and exhibition events, “encouraging cooperation between Macau companies and foreign brands, including those from Portuguese-speaking countries”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:22:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Seaport forecasts 19% revenue growth in January</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/jogo-seaport-preve-crescimento-de-19-das-receitas-em-janeiro/</link><description>The basis of comparison helps, but Macau's main industry continues to expand month after month. The most recent report from Seaport Research Partners predicts that revenues will increase by 14 percent annually by March
Financial services firm Seaport Research Partners predicts 19 percent annual gaming revenue growth in January, according to the institution's most recent report. At a quarterly level, revenues can increase by around 14 percent.
“Our estimate for January points to an increase of 19 percent compared to the previous year (4 percent more compared to the previous month), with the growth rate helped by an easy comparison [compared to the 2025 value]”, can be read in the report by analyst Vitaly Umansky, cited by the GGR Asia portal. In January 2025, the game's gross revenue was 18.3 billion patacas, the lowest value of the entire year, which contributes to the highest relative growth.
Despite the low basis for comparison, the 19 percent growth in revenue at the beginning of the year is seen by Umansky as a “solid” sign for the first quarter, in which gaming revenue is expected to expand by around 14 percent. It is recalled that in the first three months of 2025, revenue reached 57.7 billion patacas.
“We estimate that the month started quite strong, possibly with revenues above 850 million patacas per day during the long weekend from January 1st to 4th”, the document states.
Weakest December
The forecast of 14 percent growth in the first quarter takes into account the fact that revenues slowed down in mid-December, which Seaport Research Partners believes is due to the fact that high rollers prefer to visit Macau to gamble between January and February.
“We anticipate gross gaming revenues to grow more than 14 percent in the first quarter and seven percent in 2026,” Umansky said. “Growth in 2026 is supported by easy comparisons in the first half of the year and the continued easing of monetary flows and visa issuance”, he highlighted.
Vitaly Umansky also said that if there is any unexpected increase in revenue in the mass market that the gaming industry's results could exceed the indicated forecast and that this increase would benefit concessionaires currently with greater capacity.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:21:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn, MGM and Melco announce bonuses for workers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/wynn-mgm-e-melco-anunciam-bonus-para-trabalhadores/</link><description>Gaming concessionaires Wynn Resorts and MGM China announced a bonus equivalent to one month of work that will cover between 95 and 98 percent of workers. The information was released yesterday through press releases, after the Galaxy dealership announced a similar measure on Tuesday.
As far as Wynn Macau is concerned, the bonus will cover 98 percent of the current 11,552 eligible employees, as “recognition of the exceptional contributions of all team members over the last year”. “We are truly grateful for the efforts and contributions of our team members over the past year and are pleased to announce a special grant in recognition of their hard work,” said Linda Chen, Vice President and CEO of Wynn Macau. “This year we celebrate the important milestone of our 20th anniversary in Macau — not only an achievement for Wynn, but also a testament to the dedication of every member of our team,” he added.
General trends
In the case of MGM, the bonus will cover 95 percent of workers, as “recognition for their dedication and contributions throughout 2025”. The amount will begin to be paid from the 21st of this month.
“Reflecting on 2025, we are moving forward with a new chapter, continually optimizing our innovative products and service experiences, achieving steady progress in the development of our business – all thanks to the dedication and hard work of our team,” said Pansy Ho, president and CEO of MGM China in a statement. "Looking to the future, MGM will continue to enhance its strengths, with an unwavering focus on our guests. Guided by the philosophy of 'Originality + Innovation', we will remain dedicated to contributing to the positioning of Macau as a world-class tourism and leisure center, through the continuous introduction of more diverse tourism offerings", he stressed.
Finally, Melco Resorts also announced a bonus for “eligible workers”, but the proportion of the workforce covered was not indicated. "The discretionary bonus payment recognizes the dedication and support of our colleagues over the past year. We sincerely appreciate their loyalty and commitment to consistently exceeding guest expectations, which together helps the company maintain and enhance its leadership position in the entertainment and hospitality industry," said Lawrence Ho, group president.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:19:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Damn | Woman arrested for heroin trafficking</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/droga-mulher-detida-por-trafico-de-heroina/</link><description>A 43-year-old woman was arrested after being intercepted with 0.83 grams of heroin, valued at MOP1,000, while returning from Hong Kong. The case was revealed yesterday by the Judiciary Police and the investigation was based on a complaint.
According to the PJ's version, the woman is an unemployed local resident, who had made several trips between Macau and Hong Kong with the purpose of trafficking and consuming drugs.
In addition to the drugs, authorities seized syringes, packages for storing drugs and other materials for consumption. A search of the woman's house, in Coloane, also resulted in the seizure of other materials used to consume narcotics. The detainee was also tested for urine, which tested positive for drug consumption. The case was handed over to the Public Ministry (MP).
Illegal exchanges | Two cases lead to the seizure of 47,900 HK dollars
Authorities seized 47,900 Hong Kong dollars worth of gambling chips, which they believed were used in illegal money exchanges. The seizure resulted from two different cases, carried out by the Judiciary Police and the Public Security Police Corps.
The first situation involved a 40-year-old man from the Interior, caught red-handed exchanging money with a player. The latter confessed that he had previously exchanged 300 renminbi for 300 Hong Kong dollars in tokens, which led to the first arrest and seizure of 28,500,000 Hong Kong dollars, in the possession of the suspected criminal.
In turn, the first detainee claimed to have made profits from exchanging money worth 7,000 Hong Kong dollars. The second detainee, also at the casino, was also intercepted in the act. The individual is also from the Interior and, in addition to an attempt to exchange 6,000 Hong Kong dollars for 6,000 renminbis, he had 19,400,000 Hong Kong dollars in his possession.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:02:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Malaysian company gives up letter factory in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/jogo-empresa-malaia-desiste-de-fabrica-de-cartas-em-macau/</link><description>Malaysian company Mega Fortris Bhd has scrapped plans to open a playing card factory in Macau due to difficulties in finding space and high rents. However, a warehouse will be established in Macau to supply local customers
Malaysian company Mega Fortris Bhd has abandoned plans to build a factory in Macau to produce playing cards. The company specializing in security seals had planned to use the funds raised through an initial public offering (IPO) to invest in the manufacturing unit in Macau, a plan that was outlined in late 2024.
At that time, Mega Fortris Bhd announced plans for two manufacturing units for printing playing cards in Macau and Malaysia, an investment of around US$24.5 million. The amount would be invested in purchasing the installation of specialized machinery and equipment. The Macau unit would be in charge of a subcontracted company, whose mission would be to find a location and adapt it for production processes, also responsible for obtaining licenses and authorizations to operate in the Macao SAR, according to the Inside Asian Gaming portal.
The decision to give up the factory in Macau was justified, in a note sent to shareholders, with the need to “reevaluate the business strategy” in the playing cards chapter.
The company indicated that it had “encountered difficulties in finding suitable industrial facilities in Macau” that would meet the size and weight requirements” needed for the production line. Furthermore, the company revealed that it had “observed an increase in rental costs in Macau, which could result in higher fees charged by the subcontractor company”, according to the GGR Asia portal.
Expected dates
The manufacturing unit in Malaysia is scheduled to begin operations in the last quarter of this year. In Macau, the group plans to set up a warehouse that provides gaming cards and sealed safety boxes to Macao SAR customers. According to the company's forecasts, the warehouse will begin operations in the second quarter of 2027.
The Macau facility will also be equipped with a tracking software system for game card lockboxes, and equipment to destroy cards after use.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:00:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Bay | New association created with a focus on AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/grande-baia-criada-nova-associacao-com-foco-na-ia/</link><description>A new association has just been created to develop the area of ​​artificial intelligence (AI) in the Greater Bay Area. According to the statutes published yesterday in the Official Gazette (BO), the Artificial Intelligence Development Association of the Greater Bay Area (Macau) aims to “promote the innovative development of AI technologies and their local application, covering key areas such as commerce, finance, scientific research, professional training and early childhood, primary and secondary education”.
Another of the entity's objectives is the “training of local technical talents and the development of the applications ecosystem, comprehensively increasing the competitiveness of Macau's smart industries”. The aim is also to “bring together forces from all sectors of society, responding actively to the national strategies of ‘a country strong in science and technology'”.
The new association also wants to “transform the development of AI into an essential engine for the adequate diversification of Macau’s economy, promoting industrial modernization, innovative transformation and sustainable development”. To achieve these ends, the aim is to “organize academic lectures, seminars, exchanges and cooperation”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:59:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Sales and prices with new drops at the beginning of December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/habitacao-vendas-e-precos-com-novas-quedas-no-inicio-de-dezembro/</link><description>The real estate market continues to crash. The average house price saw an annual reduction of 4.3 percent at the beginning of the last month of 2025, while sales fell 9.4 percent
In the first half of December, the average housing price showed an annual decline of 4.3 percent to 78,838 patacas per square meter, according to data revealed by the Financial Services Directorate (DSF).
The annual drop of 4.3 percent is due to the fact that at the beginning of December 2024 the average price per square meter was negotiated at 82,383 patacas per square meter, which represents a difference of 3,545 patacas per square meter in the space of one year.
At the beginning of the previous month, the highest prices were charged in Taipa, with the average price standing at 86,163 patacas per square meter. Despite this, there was an annual reduction of 2.9 percent, given that in the same period last year the price was 88,762 patacas per square meter.
In Coloane, housing was sold at an average price of 83,925 per square meter, a reduction of 22.7 percent compared to the same period last year, when the average price reached 102,976 patacas per square meter. Contrary to the general market trend, prices on the Macau Peninsula increased by 5 percent to 76,127 patacas per square meter, compared to 72,480 patacas per square meter in the same period last year.
At a monthly level, between the beginning of November and the beginning of December 2025, the market showed an increase in prices of around 18.9 percent, given that at the beginning of November the average housing price had been 66,315 patacas per square meter.
Fewer transactions
The annual price reduction was accompanied by a decrease in the number of transactions. In the first half of December, there was an annual drop of 9.4 percent, from 96 transactions to 87. Despite the annual reduction, on the Macau Peninsula there were 14 more sales, with 67 registered in the most recent period, when in the same period there had been 53 transactions registered.
However, in Taipa there were fewer transactions from 37 to 17, a difference of 20, and in Coloane a reduction from six to three transactions. When the comparison is made between the beginning of November and December 2025, the market showed a reduction of 31 transactions, from 118 to 87 purchases and sales.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 00:58:42</pubDate></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
At a lunch with several guests, I heard a friend, who declared herself a spiritualist, explaining the particularities of her belief, in a calm and balanced way, I would even say, without a hint of “irrationalism”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«Se se exige transparência ao político, matamo-lo; se alguém exige fidelidade ao que o outro era ou ao que diz, mata-o; se se exige uma relação mimética entre o que a multidão quer e o que diz o seu representante, mata-se a representação. Estes devem, portanto, por definição, trair, enganar, modificar, distorcer a palavra. Sem essa capacidade de dobrar a palavra e de trair, a linguagem política não existiria. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). Creio que nos fará falta para decifrar este mundo freneticamente complexo que nos coube.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Let men refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish, because of it the tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the pride of the countries will be destroyed.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were restricted, or if it merely lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the position of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, in a different way, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse like a shadow
[misshapen
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piela than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Member of nuclear regulator loses cell phone in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/japao-membro-do-regulador-nuclear-perde-telemovel-na-china/</link><description>Japanese authorities are investigating the loss of a professional cell phone, allegedly in China, which contained a confidential list of contacts from the Nuclear Regulation Authority, as confirmed to France-Presse by a person responsible for the organization.
The incident, now made public, occurred at Shanghai airport, on November 3, when the employee was going through security control. The absence of the device was only noticed three days later, and, according to the Japanese press, it was not possible to block it or remotely erase its data as it was already out of reach.
Although the cell phone did not contain direct access to nuclear data, according to the person in charge – who did not want to be identified – the list included names and contact details of members of the nuclear safety division of the regulatory authority – information that is not publicly accessible due to the sensitivity of the functions.
The revelation comes in a context of growing tension between Beijing and Tokyo, after Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi suggested in November that the country could intervene militarily in the event of Chinese aggression against Taiwan.
At the same time, the operator Tokyo Electric Power (TEPCO) is seeking final approval to reactivate the Kashiwazaki-Kariwa nuclear plant, the largest in the world, closed after the Fukushima disaster in 2011. Japan has been gradually resuming nuclear energy, with 14 reactors already reactivated, within the framework of carbon neutrality targets by 2050 and increased demand for electricity due to artificial intelligence.
The lost cellphone was reported to Japanese data protection authorities in November, according to the nuclear regulator. The case reignites concerns about information security in the nuclear energy sector at a delicate moment in Japanese energy policy.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:40:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Zhipu AI leads round of stock market debuts worth 1,030 ME</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/hong-kong-zhipu-ai-lidera-ronda-de-estreias-em-bolsa-no-valor-de-1-030-me/</link><description>Investor interest in the technology market continues to bear fruit and leads more and more Chinese companies linked to Artificial Intelligence to enter the Hong Kong stock exchange
The Chinese artificial intelligence company Zhipu AI debuted on the Hong Kong stock exchange yesterday, on a day when two other technology companies also entered the market, collectively raising 1.2 billion dollars. Zhipu, officially called Knowledge Atlas Technology and which adopts the name Z.ai in foreign markets, registered an upward trend in the middle of the session, with a value of 11.19 percent, after having raised around 559 million dollars.
It is the first Chinese company specializing exclusively in large-scale language models to be listed on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange. According to its co-founder and executive director, Zhang Peng, the choice of this financial center is related to the company's internationalization ambitions.
Zhang said that Hong Kong and Southeast Asia will be the first markets to be explored, followed by the Middle East, Europe and the so-called “Global South”. The manager pointed to low costs as Zhipu's main attraction compared to competing models, with the aim of winning over new users.
The technology company thus joins other Chinese companies in the sector that have taken advantage of investors' interest in the growth of AI in the country. One of Zhipu's main competitors, MiniMax – also a rival to OpenAI (creator of ChatGPT) and Anthropic (developer of Claude) – is scheduled to debut on the same exchange on Friday.
Other premieres
Yesterday, graphics chip maker Shanghai Iluvatar CoreX Semiconductor, which opened with gains of 31.5 percent after raising US$473 million, and surgical robot producer Edge Medical, which rose 36.4 percent, raising around US$154 million, also debuted in Hong Kong.
Last week, Biren Technology, which specializes in AI chips, rose nearly 76 percent on its first day of trading. In December, two other companies in the sector, Moore Threads and MetaX, recorded increases of more than 100 percent on the Shanghai stock exchange.
Despite admitting that Chinese models are closing the gap compared to North Americans, Zhang Peng acknowledged that gaps still persist in areas such as research, resources and innovation. Zhipu was placed on a commercial blacklist by the United States in 2025, making it difficult for it to access North American technology.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:32:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cambodia liquidates bank of tycoon leader of fraud network</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/camboja-liquida-banco-de-magnata-lider-de-rede-de-burlas/</link><description>Cambodia announced yesterday the immediate liquidation of Prince Bank, owned by Chinese tycoon Chen Zhi, detained this week and extradited to China, where he is being investigated for leading a transnational fraud and human trafficking network.
In a resolution published by the National Bank of Cambodia, the entity was prevented from accepting deposits and granting loans, one day after Phnom Penh confirmed Chen's arrest and handover to Beijing. The settlement will be supervised by the company Morisonkak MKA, which will guarantee the withdrawal of deposits by customers and the continuation of payment of ongoing credits.
Prince Bank was one of more than 100 companies in the Prince Group conglomerate, founded by Chen Zhi, which over the past decade has expanded into areas such as tourism, technology, logistics, food and finance. Several of these companies have been identified by Washington as fronts for online fraud schemes and human trafficking networks in Southeast Asia.
The Cambodian Interior Ministry said Chen, 37, was detained on Tuesday “as part of cooperation to combat transnational crime and at the request of Chinese authorities.” The operation also included the capture of Chinese citizens Xu Ji Liang and Shao Ji Hui, who were also extradited.
Joint investigation
Phnom Penh revealed that Chen was stripped of Cambodian nationality in December, by royal decree, months after ensuring that the businessman had obtained it legally. The arrest, according to the statement, was the result of “months of joint investigation” with China.
Last October, the US Department of Justice charged Chen with financial crimes linked to forced labor. US authorities allege that the businessman led an “industrial-scale” online fraud operation, involving hundreds of victims held under duress in prison-like facilities in Cambodia. US courts confiscated $15 billion in bitcoin from the group, in the largest seizure of cryptocurrencies in its history.
Last year, Cambodia's interior ministry spokesman stated that Chen was not in the country and that neither he nor his company faced local charges. The change in position has now been interpreted as a sign of greater alignment with Beijing in combating financial crime and cross-border fraud networks.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:30:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Beijing condemns interception of ship linked to Russia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/eua-pequim-condena-intercepcao-de-navio-ligado-a-russia/</link><description>Beijing yesterday denounced the seizure by the United States of an oil tanker sailing under the Russian flag in international waters, classifying the action as “arbitrary” and a violation of international law. Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning stated that the detention of ships from other countries on the high seas “seriously contravenes international law” and the principles of the United Nations Charter.
The statements come after the US Coast Guard intercepted the tanker Marinera – formerly known as Bella 1 – in the North Atlantic, accusing it of violating the sanctions regime imposed by Washington. According to the United States, the ship was trying to access Venezuelan waters to load crude oil.
Moscow has already described the operation as an “illegal interception” and demanded “humane and dignified” treatment for the crew. Beijing also reiterated its opposition to the unilateral sanctions imposed by Washington without the support of the United Nations, considering that they “lack a legal basis”.
In response to news about a possible worsening of US sanctions against Russia – with warnings aimed at companies from countries such as China, India or Brazil – Mao Ning stressed that economic, commercial and energy cooperation between Beijing and Moscow is “normal” and “does not target third parties”, and therefore “should not be interfered with”.
The seizure of the Marinera comes as part of growing US pressure on oil exports from Russia and Venezuela. Washington recently announced new measures to confiscate ships linked to the Venezuelan oil trade and indefinitely control the associated revenues.
According to North American media outlets, the Marinera was part of the so-called “ghost fleet” used to circumvent Western sanctions, which has fueled diplomatic friction between Washington, Moscow and now also Beijing.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:27:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Greenland | China calls for respect for the UN Charter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/gronelandia-china-apela-ao-respeito-pela-carta-da-onu/</link><description>Beijing defended yesterday that relations between countries must respect the principles of the United Nations Charter, following statements by the United States about possible military action to take control of Greenland.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said at a press conference that Beijing's position has been consistent in defending that relations between States should be managed in accordance with the objectives and principles of the UN Charter, without commenting further on the case.
The topic arose after Washington once again suggested the possibility of using military means in its strategy to acquire or influence control of Greenland, an issue that has generated opposition from European countries and the Danish government itself, which claim that the territory can only decide its future sovereignly.
Mao's statements occur in a context of international tension amplified by the recent US military operation in Venezuela, in which US forces captured the Venezuelan leader, Nicolás Maduro, and which sparked debate about the legality of the use of force and respect for the sovereignty of States.
China has intensified calls for respect for international law and state sovereignty following US external actions, stressing that any control of sovereign territory by another country must respect the norms and principles enshrined in the United Nations Charter.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:21:06</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Beijing announces new measure against Japan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/comercio-pequim-anuncia-nova-medida-contra-o-japao/</link><description>China yesterday worsened trade tensions with Japan by announcing an anti-dumping investigation into imports of a chemical gas used in the production of semiconductors, after imposing restrictions on the export of dual-use products.
The Chinese Ministry of Commerce justified the measure based on a complaint from the domestic industry, which alleged a 31 percent drop in the prices of Japanese imports of dichloro silane between 2022 and 2024. “The ‘dumping’ of products imported from Japan has harmed the production and operations of our national industry,” the statement reads.
The decision comes after Beijing banned on Tuesday the export to Japan of goods considered dual-use – with possible civil and military purposes. Relations between the two countries have deteriorated in recent weeks, after the new Japanese Prime Minister, Sanae Takaichi, suggested that the Japanese Armed Forces could intervene if China took action against Taiwan.
Tensions rose further on Tuesday when Japanese lawmaker Hei Seki – previously sanctioned by Beijing for “spreading falsehoods” about Taiwan – visited the island and declared Taiwan an independent country. “I came to Taiwan to demonstrate this and tell the world that Taiwan is an independent country,” he said, according to Taiwan’s official news agency, CNA.
Asked about these statements, the spokeswoman for the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Mao Ning, replied: “Hateful words from an insignificant villain do not deserve comment.”
The director for Asia and Oceania Affairs at the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Masaaki Kanai, called on China to lift trade restrictions and classified as “unacceptable” any measure aimed exclusively at Japan and outside international practices. Tokyo, however, has not yet announced retaliation.
Rare Trumps
However, speculation is growing that China may impose restrictions on the export of rare earths to Japan, similar to what it already did with the United States in the context of the trade war between the two countries. China has most of the world's production of heavy rare earths, essential for the production of heat-resistant magnets used in the defense and electric vehicle industries.
Although the ministry did not mention new restrictions in this sector, the official China Daily newspaper cited anonymous sources according to which Beijing is considering limiting exports of certain rare metals to Japan – information not independently confirmed.
While relations with Japan worsen, China has sought to strengthen ties with South Korea. South Korean President Lee Jae Myung concluded yesterday a four-day visit to China – his first since taking office in June – during which he met with his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, and oversaw the signing of agreements in the areas of technology, trade, transport and environmental protection.
During the visit, 24 export contracts were signed, worth a total of US$44 million, according to the South Korean Ministry of Commerce and Industry. The Chinese press also noted that, during the New Year holiday, South Korea overtook Japan as the main destination for international flights from mainland China.
Beijing has advised against traveling to Japan, claiming that statements by Japanese authorities about Taiwan pose “significant risks” to the safety of Chinese citizens in the country.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:17:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela | Global Times warns of “serious erosion” of international order</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/venezuela-global-times-adverte-para-grave-erosao-da-ordem-internacional/</link><description>An editorial in a Chinese Communist Party newspaper warned yesterday that the United States military operation, which resulted in the capture of the Venezuelan president, represents a serious erosion of the international order established after World War II.
The Global Times denounces the “subversion of fundamental principles of international law”, including sovereign equality, non-interference in the internal affairs of States and the prohibition of the use of force, by allowing “certain countries to unilaterally decide who is guilty, who should be punished and in what way”.
“If such practices are tolerated, international law will be reduced to a selectively applied tool, and the collective security mechanism established by the United Nations Charter will be emptied,” reads the editorial. The newspaper emphasizes that the detention and transfer of a serving head of state, without a clear warrant from the United Nations, is not only a violation of a country's sovereignty, but a direct attack on the predictability and authority of international law.
“What is at stake is not just the security of Venezuela, but the future of the international legal order”, writes the English-language newspaper, recalling that several representatives expressed similar concerns at a meeting of the UN Security Council.
The Global Times considers that the imposition of force over multilateral rules represents a return to the Hobbesian “state of nature”, where the strong dictate the rules. “The overwhelming majority of countries do not wish to return to an international jungle governed by the law of the strongest”, he states.
Story factory
The publication also criticizes what it classifies as “fabricated narratives” by Washington to justify the operation, stating that replacing legal norms with arbitrary political judgments only generates global instability and weakens the multilateral system.
Beijing has openly spoken out against the capture of Venezuelan President Nicolás Maduro. Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said this week that the US “arbitrarily trampled on the sovereignty, security and legitimate rights and interests of Venezuela”, calling for the immediate release of Maduro and his wife.
Against bullying
The Chinese Government yesterday considered the alleged United States demand that Venezuela break off economic relations with Beijing as an act of intimidation as a condition for exploring and selling its oil.
Questioned at a press conference about the information provided by the North American television channel ABC News, Mao Ning declared that Venezuela “is a sovereign country and enjoys full and permanent sovereignty over its natural resources and all economic activities in its territory”. According to ABC News, the Administration of US President Donald Trump demanded that Venezuelan interim president Delcy Rodríguez end ties with China, Russia, Iran and Cuba as a precondition for restarting the production and sale of crude oil.
Mao described the alleged pressure as a “brazen use of force” and stated that the attempt to condition access to Venezuelan energy resources to a “United States first” logic constitutes a “typical case of intimidation” that “seriously violates international law, seriously infringes on Venezuela’s sovereignty” and “harms the rights of the Venezuelan people.” Mao reiterated that Beijing defends economic cooperation between sovereign states and highlighted that China “has always developed exchanges and cooperation with other countries based on mutual respect, equality and reciprocal benefit”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:12:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Beijing accuses William Lai of “sabotaging peace”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/taiwan-pequim-acusa-william-lai-de-sabotar-a-paz/</link><description>China yesterday accused Taiwanese leader William Lai of “sabotaging peace” after his New Year's speech, in which he warned of increased pressure from Beijing and called for strengthening the island's defense.
The reaction came from the Taiwan Affairs Office of the Chinese State Council, whose spokesman, Chen Binhua, classified the message as “full of lies, hostility and malice” and accused Lai of repeating “separatist fallacies” about Taiwan’s independence and “inciting confrontation between the two sides of the strait”.
According to Beijing, Lai resorted to the rhetoric of “democracy versus authoritarianism” to “confuse fellow Taiwanese and deceive international public opinion”, demonstrating an “incorrigible” stance in support of the island’s independence. Chen Binhua went further to describe Lai as a “destabilizer of peace”, “creator of crises” and “instigator of war”, arguing that the Taiwanese leader has “deliberately intensified tensions” since taking office and promotes a strategy of “preparing for war with the aim of achieving independence”.
“The failure of Taiwan’s independence is inevitable”, reads the statement, which reiterates that “Taiwan is part of China” and calls on the island’s population to “firmly oppose separatism and external interference”.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:10:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Secretary cancels visit to the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/hong-kong-secretario-cancela-visita-aos-eua/</link><description>Hong Kong's Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry, Sun Dong, canceled, without any explanation, a visit to the United States, four hours after the trip was announced. In a statement released at 12:00 on Tuesday, the government of the Chinese region said that Sun would participate in the Consumer Electronics Show (CES), one of the largest technology and consumer electronics fairs in the world, which is taking place in Las Vegas.
The secretary would lead the largest delegation ever from Hong Kong to the CES, made up of 61 companies, the statement highlighted. The trip would include a visit to the city of San Francisco, where Sun would visit and “also exchange experiences with local technology companies and a university in the Silicon Valley region”.
However, in another statement, published at 4:20 pm, with just one sentence, the Government announced that Sun had canceled his visit to the United States. The secretary's office told Hong Kong media that the Government is constantly carrying out “dynamic assessments” on the desirability of international travel.
“After an assessment, it was decided to cancel the trip,” said a spokesperson for the office. The Government highlighted that the business delegation will participate in the Las Vegas fair, led by directors from the Hong Kong Trade Promotion Council.
The cancellation of Sun Dong's visit came on the same day that China accused the United States of placing its domestic legislation above international law, in reaction to the detention of the President of Venezuela, Nicolás Maduro, during a US military operation.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:09:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Sofia Ferreira da Silva, author of a study on opera in the Mao years: “Silk Road was the biggest influence”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/07/sofia-ferreira-da-silva-autora-de-um-estudo-sobre-opera-nos-anos-de-mao-rota-da-seda-foi-a-maior-influencia/</link><description>In “Singing the Revolution: The Role of Songs and Opera in the Spread of Communism in Mao Zedong's China”, Sofia Ferreira da Silva analyzes the way in which songs and opera spread political ideals, leaving marks on the country's cultural panorama. The analysis came from the doctoral thesis in Artistic Studies, defended by the author at Universidade Nova de Lisboa
What was the musical environment like in the country before Mao Zedong came to power?
China was, and continues to be, a territory with a huge variety of practices at regional, local and ethnic levels. We can speak of four main types: music of a more erudite nature, symbolized by court music (yayue) and guqin music, more centered on Confucian ideals and with ritual functions and self-cultivation of individual morals; folk music, with vocal and instrumental genres varying according to region and ethnicity; Taoist, Buddhist and other religious music; and traditional opera, such as Kunqu and Peking, Sichuan and Canton operas, combining singing, declamation, stylized movements and martial arts. The biggest influence on Chinese music was, perhaps, the Silk Road, as a good part of the musical instruments that are now considered “Chinese”, such as the erhu, the pipa, the suona and the sanxian, have their origins in foreign instruments brought to Chinese territory, and which were gradually adapted and incorporated into their music. On the other hand, some narrative and operatic genres evolved from the adaptation and combination of counterparts from the territories crossed by this route. If it weren't for the Silk Road, traditional Chinese music would be radically different.
What other influences are there?
The other big influence is Western music. This, despite having entered the country in the 16th and 17th centuries, was felt with greater intensity from the middle of the 19th century and throughout the 20th century. The growing foreign presence and influence led to the systematic introduction of Western notation, academic training along European lines and Western classical and popular music genres, which would be assimilated in varying ways by Chinese composers, such as Ma Sicong, Li Jinhui or Xian Xinghai, combining them or not with traditional music motifs.
In the thesis, he talks about two major changes in the Mao years, with the creation of the so-called “model shows (yangbanxi)” and the revolutionary Peking operas. How did these formats help to reshape the music scene at the time?
The model shows, which include Peking operas and revolutionary songs, played an important role in reforming the Maoist musical landscape, implying changes not only in musical styles, but also in the social function of music. Production became entirely subordinated to the political project of the Chinese Communist Party (PCC), resulting in the mandatory membership of artists and designated artistic associations, and the suppression, through criticism in the media, of musical elements or genres considered “feudal”, “bourgeois” or “superstitious”. In opposition, and following successive political movements and campaigns, other formats were promoted, more in line with the regime's ideals.
How, in concrete terms?
In the case of the “yangbanxi”, from the Cultural Revolution, the fact that they were called “model” implied that all new creations must strictly follow the aesthetic precepts established through them, especially the rules of the “basic task”, with the construction of revolutionary heroic figures as the ultimate aim of artistic creation. There were also the “Three Prominences”, with the attribution of greater or lesser prominence to a certain character depending on their degree of positivity or negativity, their function in the plot. These rules guided not only the narrative structure and the role of the characters, but also aspects such as the integration between music and gestures, the construction of costumes and sets, and the harmony between traditional and Western musical elements. This codification would aim, to this extent, to guarantee the ideological and aesthetic uniformity essential to the creation of a controlled, functional and politically effective musical culture within the framework of the objectives of the revolution.
What are the main political messages conveyed through these two types of shows?
The first big idea is the almost religious loyalty to Mao Zedong and the unconditional observance of his ideas. It is his thought that inspires and guides the actions of the heroes and heroic characters, the second most important category of characters in revolutionary operas, and leads them to the successful completion of the mission assigned to them or to heroic sacrifice in favor of the communist cause. The second is the class struggle as the driving force of history. We have, on the one hand, the oppressive, capitalist, imperialist and feudal class as the villain, and on the other the working people, exploited and oppressed by the former, suffering the greatest storms at their hands. The conflicts and difficult situations faced by the heroes or other positive characters, such as the death of family members, imprisonment or slavery, were always the direct expression of this struggle, and their resolution would only come from the revolutionary stance and the assumption of an active role in the construction of socialism.
And the third idea present in the shows?
This is collectivism, as a true revolutionary places the interests of the Party and the People above any individual dream or desire. No matter how prominent his role, the hero needs popular support to complete his mission: his aspirations are the aspirations of the people, and it is in solidarity between all that difficulties are overcome and the much-desired socialist harmony is achieved. Personal achievement only has value if it serves the collective cause, and individual sacrifice is glorified when it contributes to common progress. Operas promote, to this extent, a worldview where individual identity dissolves into the identity of the revolutionary collective, and where the active participation of the masses is not only desirable, but necessary.
These were years of so-called cultural Maoism, as mentioned in the thesis. How is it characterized?
Cultural Maoism presents points of contact regarding the subordination of art to politics, the valorization of the daily lives of the masses as the raw material for creation and the defense of its widespread popularization. However, it is distinguished by its emphasis on the proletarianization of the artist himself, who should abandon his position as a distant intellectual and become an active member of the working people, learning through practice and inserting himself in their daily struggles.
What are the main influences of this movement?
In addition to the Marxist-Leninist matrix, cultural Maoism would be marked by Confucian influences, giving art an ethical and formative function, as in Confucius, Mencius or Xunzi, art shaped character. However, in the Maoist context, this molding was channeled towards the construction of socialist consciousness and the eradication of traces of the bourgeois mentality. One of the central principles of this policy was the “mass line”, a kind of circular cultural dynamic in which popular ideas and expressions were collected and systematized by the Party, before being returned to the people in a clearer and more politically oriented way. Another aspect to consider is the appreciation of native and foreign cultural heritage, condensed in the maxim “use the past to serve the present, use the foreign to serve China”.
In what way?
To create new artistic works, Mao recommended the initial study of Western works, considered “scientific” and technically superior, before selectively incorporating elements of Chinese tradition. In both cases, the value of artistic forms lay in their social and political function, not in their preservation as heritage. In this context, the PCC leader proposed two criteria for artistic evaluation: the political, which required the promotion of national unity and the rejection of ideas contrary to the Party; and the artistic, which presupposed technical and aesthetic rigor following an abstract notion of “scientific criteria of art” at the service of the masses. This double requirement replaced, in Maoism, the Confucian distinction between moral quality and aesthetic quality.
In these years, what were the biggest influences on songwriting?
The composition of songs was greatly influenced by two great musical traditions: the native, with the use of regional melodies and motifs and those of the various ethnic minorities that make up the territory; and the Western, in which I include the Soviet musical tradition, most visible in marches and so-called “art songs”, which could be understood as a type of revolutionary ‘lieder’ or with highly politicized content. The influence of each of them was more or less visible depending on the political situation of the territory.
How did the years of “cultural Maoism” change the country’s musical landscape?
Some aspects of the production of Cultural Revolution operas, such as the introduction of the Western orchestra and the use of techniques from Western music, the incorporation of more realistic scenarios and the melodramatic nature of the stories influenced and continue to influence the production of new Beijing operas, especially those with contemporary or historical themes relating to the 20th century. XX. Over the last 30 years, operas with historical themes have also been produced with some of these elements, especially in terms of music and settings, such as “Cao Cao and Yang Xiu”. Some remnants of this period can also be seen in the interpretation of traditional operas, especially in the presentation of arias or excerpts on television programs. I see countless performances that combine, just like in the revolutionary repertoire, arrangements with a Western orchestra and realistic scenarios, with extensive use of new technologies. However, what I consider to be the greatest remnant of revolutionary operas will, perhaps, be a greater artistic audacity on the part of the creators of new operas. It is an issue that deserves further study by the academy, but, from my observations as a spectator, I notice a greater openness to the incorporation of elements from other arts, such as dance and theater, and a greater complexity in the characters, especially those considered negative, less antagonistic, with more nuances when it comes to motivations for acting in a certain way. It is obvious that the psychological suffering inflicted by these operas on an entire generation of Chinese people is undeniable and cannot, under any circumstances, be forgotten; however, model operas boosted the creative impetus of composers and librettists, in line with the evolutionary process, of fusion with other arts, of Peking Opera over the centuries.</description><pubDate>2026-01-07 01:10:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Alfredo Gomes Dias, historian, on Rocha Vieira: “A historical figure, whether he wanted to or not”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/20/alfredo-gomes-dias-historiador-sobre-rocha-vieira-uma-figura-historica-quer-quisesse-ou-nao/</link><description>Launched on Thursday in Porto, with the seal of War and Peace, “Macau: The Last Transition – Vasco Rocha Vieira (1991–1999)” is the result of 20 years of work by historian Alfredo Gomes Dias. The work contains personal testimonies from Rocha Vieira and documented details of the last Portuguese Administration of Macau
Another book has just been released about Rocha Vieira and the last Portuguese administration of Macau. Tell me about the beginning of this project.
This project is more or less 20 years old, and began when I met Rocha Vieira, in 2005, to write a text for the book “Governadores de Macau” [published by Livros do Oriente in 2013]. In the midst of this, I discovered that there was a personal document fund of General Rocha Vieira, while governor. As a historian, I was excited by the idea. I offered to do a project with him, which we called a “report”. All the documents were at his home, in Lagoa, where he was from. They were then deposited in a space provided by Mafra City Council and between 2007 and 2013 I worked on this documentation. It was lonely and long work, because I had to organize 1,700 boxes of documentation and combine it with my work as a teacher. Rocha Vieira kept postponing the project, saying no, but in 2016 he told me to move forward with the “report”, the book. I finished the first version in 2021. It is a committed book, in the sense that it aims to give General Rocha Vieira's vision of what his Government was like. This is not an academic work.
He had complete access to the personal file.
He gave me the green light to consult all the documentation, I had no restrictions. Rocha Vieira told me one story or another in detail, gave me guidelines and revealed to me his concerns during his government. He told me some positions he had and then the different paths they took, and the entire book is built around the many conversations I had with the general, in which I also use documentation. We have a vision of everything that happened between 1991 and 1999 and the governor's actions in the different dimensions of the Administration, at an economic, social and political level, in relations with China and Lisbon, with Hong Kong, and then everything related to the work related to the transformation of the territory, such as the birth of Cotai and the major works that were carried out. There is also talk about the transition phase and the major themes, such as the entry of Chinese troops into Macau, the ceremony and how it was organized. Today we live in an immediate world, and at today's speed it's always strange to say that this book took 20 years to make.
Can we say that this is the first time that we have such a complete testimony of Rocha Vieira's vision of his Government?
The edited biography [Vasco Rocha Vieira – Todos os Portos a que Aguei] already gives many ideas about his concerns. What I ended up doing was not focusing so much on the general's entire life, but only on the years of the Government and developing as much as possible many of the issues that Pedro Vieira raised in this biography.
What subjects are then further developed in this new work?
I describe very well all the processes linked to Macau's transition, such as the issue of laws and localization, the need to translate them into Chinese. This was a gigantic job. Then I discuss the construction of major works, the birth of Cotai. All of this based on the original plans and plans designed for Cotai, where the beginning of the idea for this area is known. Any historian who, in the future, wants to study the transition process must necessarily go through this book. I don't want to say that what's there is definitive, because it never is. But it is important to have this basis and testimony, which is enriched and substantiated by documentation.
I imagine that the controversies of the Rocha Vieira Government are also in the book. The quarrel with Jorge Sampaio, the creation of the Fundação Oriente in Portugal. What is Rocha Vieira’s testimony about these two moments?
He always maintained the same speech compared to what he had already said publicly. There is a specific chapter on Fundação Oriente, where, with the support of documentation, an attempt is made to explain the process and why Rocha Vieira, when he arrived in Macau, felt the need to solve a problem that had been dragging on and which was important to overcome. It describes how he managed to resolve it, as it was an issue that was making dialogue with the Chinese authorities difficult. It explains how Rocha Vieira interacted with the different Governments of the [Portuguese] Republic and the different Presidents, the positions he took in order to guarantee what was his responsibility. While he was at the head of the Government, Rocha Vieira always tried to assert his views, and one of the interesting things is that I had access to copies of minutes of meetings of the State Council, in which Rocha Vieira presented his vision on the situation in Macau. It's an interesting contribution. But he explains that the way he spoke with President Mário Soares was completely different from the way he spoke with Jorge Sampaio. The institutional relationship changed, the way of attending a meeting was also different. This is explained, but without going into the personal side of the dispute.
Did Rocha Vieira leave Macau with a feeling of accomplishment?
I think he left Macau very convinced, and the entire transfer ceremony ends up giving us this image that Portugal left in the best possible way. We also have to think that we are talking about two completely different countries, and that one of them is giant. And that, despite this difference, it was possible to maintain an almost equal dialogue between two States to resolve, in the best way, a specific issue that was Macau. What surprised me most about Rocha Vieira's vision was that he changed the centrality of his vision to Macau.
In what sense?
In general, the Portuguese and the authorities spoke of Macau thinking about guaranteeing the transition process without jeopardizing Portugal's interests. And General Rocha Vieira reverses the terms of the issue, that is, to guarantee Macau's interests, with the idea that guaranteeing Macau's interests would be the same as guaranteeing Portugal's interests. It looks like the same thing, but it's not. This vision, for me, was surprising.
Why?
Because it went against what was the most common discourse among the authorities and people responsible for the Portuguese administration [of Macau]. This central idea ends up changing the way he organizes his Government, how he acts and the type of actions he triggers. They all had to do with this deep conviction, that, in the remaining years, a great development of Macau would be guaranteed, the affirmation of Portuguese culture, supporting institutions, or even with the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM), whose solution ended up not being the one he proposed. It turned out to be a minimalist option.
What, specifically, was Rocha Vieira’s position?
It was to ensure that the old Macau High School was the EPM, which would give the school a completely different dimension compared to [the current location]. It has nothing to do with it. He didn't just want a Portuguese school, but also a space where it was possible to develop cultural activities, create a cultural hub in Macau linked to Portugal, and with a much more dignified option than what was, later, the option of the Ministry of Education, in the figure of Marçal Grilo, who chose [the location] of the old Commercial School. Therefore, the focus has always been to guarantee and develop Macau's interests, its autonomy, and the airport issue was fundamental to guarantee Macau's autonomy. It was also intended that Macau would adhere to international agreements regarding respect for human rights. The idea was that, by managing to guarantee Macau's interests, thinking of the territory as part of China's second system, and that if we invested a lot in Macau, we would, naturally, be defending Portuguese interests and leaving a great legacy.
What was the most complex dossier for Rocha Vieira?
I think he had great regrets regarding the Ministry of Education's option for Portuguese schools. From the conversations I had with him [that's what it seemed to me]. Then there were the security issues, with the sects, which ended up being resolved. The years 1997 and 1998 were very critical moments in Macau, but as it always had good relations with the Chinese authorities, this led to China realizing the situation, starting to collaborate more with the Portuguese authorities in Macau, in order to control the problem.
About Cotai, how did the idea come about?
It arises in the context of the airport works, when it is realized that it would be relatively easy to mobilize the land that was associated with the airport works, taking advantage of that moment to make a connection and create, essentially, a second urban center in Macau. Cotai's initial plans had to do with urban space, green and industrial spaces. The entire plan was designed to bring together different areas, social spaces, such as schools or health, as if Cotai were a mini-city, so to speak, in the territory.
But who actually had the idea?
It was an idea from Rocha Vieira's Executive, developed with secretaries. The idea came from him, when he was faced with the issue of the works, and was then developed with the team. He was always concerned about developing things with the team, also ensuring continuity with what had been done before. When he talked to me, he was careful to say: “this didn't start with me”, or that this or that secretary had been fundamental for a certain job. He never wanted to take credit that wasn't his, and this is also a great recognition from previous governors.
Therefore, Cotai was not supposed to have so much area dedicated to the game.
From what I analyzed in the documents, there was no idea of ​​giving up such a large space for entertainment, with casinos. I think the initial vision for Cotai was a little more balanced, with housing, schools, health centers, green spaces. It was supposed to be a new urban space that would be created with all the services necessary to function, it wasn't just supposed to be games.
The moments in which Rocha Vieira clutches the flag to his chest, moved, will go down in history. Did he remember those moments with him?
Yes, but despite the historical dimension of his role, Rocha Vieira was not exactly aware of the historical role he was playing. He was there with a clear mission and objectives, without really thinking about the role he could have in the future. Once, when we were having lunch, I told him that we could put our work into perspective, but that he was going to become a historical figure in the history of Portugal, whether he wanted to or not. And the funny thing is that he looked at me with a face like he had never thought of that, with a very surprised look. In fact, it is unthinkable to take away his status as the last Portuguese governor in Macau in hundreds of years of history. On top of that, he was there for a long period [9 years], when most governors were there for three or four years.</description><pubDate>2025-12-20 04:01:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Christian Montag, UM Institute for Collaborative Innovation: “AI cannot imitate the human touch”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/17/christian-montag-instituto-de-inovacao-colaborativa-da-um-a-ia-nao-consegue-imitar-o-toque-humano/</link><description>Can artificial intelligence help combat loneliness? The issue was analyzed in a study by the University of Macau, led by academic Christian Montag. The director of the Institute for Collaborative Innovation emphasizes that AI tools “are not long-term solutions” on a psychological level
How can artificial intelligence (AI) help overcome feelings of loneliness, if social networks cannot achieve this goal?
The “needs and gratifications theory” states that technology can only be successful if its use satisfies human needs, such as, for example, the need for social interaction. With AI companions, whether as stand-alone products or integrated into social media platforms, we have reached a new level, because human beings start talking to an artificial person and not with another human person, as happens on social media. Specific problems arise with these new AI companions, in that there are overly pleasant and charming AI systems that do not challenge a person's biased views of the world. Furthermore, many people around the world have become overly dependent on these products, using them without critical reflection.
One of the conclusions of your study is that AI cannot, on its own, resolve feelings of loneliness. What steps in the investigation were followed to reach this conclusion?
There are well-conducted studies that show that interactions with AI companions can actually reduce feelings of loneliness. We do not doubt these results nor deny the potential that can arise from these interactions between humans and AI, as long as such systems are designed safely and when a human is not available. That said, we believe that these interactions between humans and AI do not represent a long-term solution.
Why?
This is due to the absence of social contact and the real presence of another human being when turning to AI companions based on large-scale language models, especially in moments of desperation. We have reviewed a vast literature that demonstrates that we need to take our evolutionary heritage seriously, with the real need for other human beings, particularly in the age of AI. Our perspective is based on many years of research in the area of ​​affective neuroscience. Still, it is clearly necessary to develop more new empirical studies that directly address interactions with AI and support this vision.
We run the risk of AI causing profound cognitive changes in people. To what extent? Can we change as human beings, especially when it comes to our need for others?
The same discussion arose with the appearance of smartphones. It is important to note that this oldest discussion has not yet been resolved: what happens or happened to our cognitive abilities when we began to permanently outsource the learning of telephone numbers, the guidance from A to B, among other tasks, to a machine? Recent research from MIT [Massachusetts Institute of Technology] suggests that the brain is less activated when using ChatGPT for writing tasks, compared to writing without such support. To me, this is not surprising and should not lead to moral panics. We have other more urgent problems, such as when real difficulties arise when inequalities in society increase, this is because some people use AI and others do not invest in this area.
What are the concrete impacts?
Some people may soon become very, very productive, while those who are not educated to use AI properly will not be able to keep up. Interestingly, we have observed in recent research that people with a deep learning style are more willing to engage with AI to become more productive. As for the question of whether we have changed in relation to our need for others, I highly doubt that, as these evolutionary impulses are genetically anchored in our species and we cannot simply eliminate them. Social needs are an essential part of what it means to be human.
Could these cognitive changes, if they occur, be more significant in young people than in adults, for example?
Interesting question. We know, from some studies on attitudes towards AI, that younger users tend to have more positive views about AI and, therefore, are more likely to adopt it in their daily lives. However, we are currently observing something quite problematic, such as the fact that AI is often eliminating jobs for young people just leaving university. Thus, AI appears to make it more difficult to enter the job market after obtaining a university degree. In other words, a lack of work experience makes things difficult for many young people. In the end, this could also lead to young people's perception of AI becoming more negative soon.
How should governments legislate or adopt policies to promote healthy acceptance and use of AI in society and schools?
We see very different approaches around the world to respond to the AI ​​revolution. I am German and, in Europe, we are seeing strong regulatory efforts with the so-called Artificial Intelligence Regulation (Artificial Intelligence Act). Personally, I am not convinced that the current European regulatory scheme is well planned, as I think it is too strict and, in some points, uses legally undefined terms, although I applaud the aim of promoting reliable AI and trying to reduce harm. I think the current regulation of AI in the European Union could go too far and end up harming the European economy by stifling much-needed innovation. But there are real dangers associated with AI and some regulation is needed.
What dangers?
I'm talking, for example, about the unregulated fusion between biotechnology and AI that could result in harm if people start to “create” new viruses in their backyards. I find Singapore's approach based on lifelong learning as a response to the AI ​​revolution very interesting. The Singapore Government offers its citizens the possibility of obtaining an academic degree in AI from the age of 40, with financial support from the State itself. What I like about this approach is that we need to remind people that it is also their responsibility to acquire new skills throughout their lives. This mentality must be instilled from an early age in schools.
In what areas of our lives can large-scale language models (LLMs) do more good than harm?
There are many routine and repetitive tasks where AI will be really useful to humans. However, we know from scientific literature that humans experience what is called “algorithm aversion”: in some areas of our lives, people do not like AI playing a role. For example, when we talk about couples therapy, people clearly prefer to talk to a human being than an AI system. Perhaps the closer we come to our evolutionary heritage in terms of caring for each other, the more the role of AI must be carefully monitored and reflected upon if we want it to have a place there. Personally, I wouldn't want to see my child being taken care of in kindergarten by an AI-powered robot.
How should psychology adapt to AI, given the growing number of people using it for this purpose?
There are different perspectives on this topic. Firstly, not everyone knows that psychology is a discipline that relies heavily on data. Therefore, psychology students are trained to become excellent data scientists. In this context, it is logical that our discipline adopts AI as a data analysis tool. However, I think it speaks to how psychologists view the increasing use of AI in human relationships. As with many things, this is complex. If AI enables better human communication, such as improving hearing aids for people with hearing problems, that is very welcome. If AI replaces human relationships, from my perspective it will cause problems. As we exposed in our most recent work, AI cannot currently successfully imitate human social touch or the real presence of another person.
At the Center for Cognitive and Brain Science at the University of Macau, what are the main projects developed in this area?
We have unique research opportunities at the University of Macau to study interactions between humans and AI, using neuroscientific techniques. I hope we can publish very interesting discoveries in the near future.
Humanity still lives here
Recently published in the scientific journal “Trends and Cognitive Sciences”, the article “Can AI really help solve the loneliness epidemic?” [Can AI Really Help Solve the Loneliness Epidemic?] counts Christian Montag, associate director of the Institute for Collaborative Innovation at the University of Macau (UM) as lead author, followed by academics Michiel Spapé, associate professor at the Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences at UM, and Benjamin Becker, professor at the Department of Psychology at the University of Hong Kong, as co-authors.
According to a press release released by UM regarding this investigation, one of the main conclusions is that AI “will probably not be a long-term solution to human loneliness”. Quoted in this note, Christian Montag stated that “if a person is lonely, they long for the physical presence of someone close to them”, and this “is very difficult to imitate with the available chatbots”.
"The major language models operate primarily through text communication. Clearly, this is not enough to provide lonely people with the best cure for loneliness: direct in-person support," he stated. According to the World Health Organization, “loneliness affects one in six people worldwide”, having been “identified as a global public health concern”.
Despite the sign, the study points to a positive side of this universe, noting that “AI technology has significant potential to support human beings in moments of psychological crisis, especially when human intervention is not available”. However, “the researchers argue that the technology must be made safer before it can be used in this context”, emphasizing “the importance of remembering our evolutionary heritage and the need for genuine interpersonal connections”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 01:04:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Luís Bernardino, academic: “We need to define a defense cooperation strategy” for the CPLP</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/25/luis-bernardino-academico-precisamos-definir-uma-estrategia-de-cooperacao-defesa-para-a-cplp/</link><description>The book “25 Years of Defense Cooperation at CPLP” was released in 2023 in digital format and, two years later, reached the printed version. Luís Bernardino, co-author linked to the Universidade Autónoma de Lisboa, highlights positive developments since the creation of the Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries, despite inaction and controversies with Equatorial Guinea
“25 Years of Defense Cooperation in the CPLP [Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries]” was released as an e-book and is now available in print. Why edit this book?
This book talks about the 25 years of cooperation in the CPLP defense area and is written by me, together with a colleague from Brazil, Camila Rizzi. It results from a research project developed at the CPLP Strategic Analysis Center, based in Mozambique. It has the CPLP defense component and makes strategic reflection on this topic. Due to the fact that 25 years of cooperation have passed in this area, we wanted to carry out an evaluation and the book so that it would remain in the history of the organization. In 2023, there were no financial conditions to publish the book on paper as we wanted, and it was now launched on November 18th, in Maputo.
There is criticism regarding the effective action of the CPLP. Do you consider that this organism has grown sustainably?
The assessment I make is in the area of ​​defense. When the CPLP was created, cooperation in the area of ​​defense was not included in the initial six areas. This area only emerged in 1998. The CPLP was born with six main areas – culture, language, political-diplomatic concentration – and currently has 26 areas of cooperation, which is proof that it has grown in a sustained manner. Obviously, with ups and downs, situations have become easier over these almost 30 years. But what stands out in this book, in the area of ​​defense, is that there was a very consolidated and participated growth. In these 25 years, a lot of interesting things have been done and the evaluation is positive.
And the future?
We need to define a defense cooperation strategy and what we want for the CPLP in this area over the next 25 years. This is the challenge we face, of greater activity and initiative, so that cooperation and defense can be strategic in what is cooperation within States. So that it can be more visible and effectively allow for growth, participation and development, or even greater commitment, in regional contexts.
But looking at the past, present and future, what has the dynamic been like in the defense area?
The book shows a certain dynamic of substantial constitutional growth in the first phase. Then there were very interesting developments, with some protocols and cooperation at the level of the Armed Forces, but there is still a lot to do, namely looking at the area of ​​defense cooperation as a strategic area.
The global geopolitical system appears to be changing very quickly, following a multipolar path. Should the CPLP have another role in this context, with actors such as China, Russia or the United States?
The CPLP is not a multilateral instrument, it is not an organization of that level. We have to place the CPLP at the level of the Commonwealth, for example, of organizations at a cultural, linguistic level, of partnership between countries, of concern for development. What I usually say is that the CPLP is a good diplomatic communication instrument, a soft power in areas related to conflict management and prevention. Let us not expect there to be armed forces, or an army, from the CPLP. This body is one of dialogue and cooperation. What we do, in terms of defense, is exactly that, create partnerships so that there are mechanisms for responding to disasters, to provide training capacity for the armed forces. There are even those who ask the question: why did the CPLP not intervene in Cabo Delgado, in Mozambique, on the issue of terrorism?
And why?
Because the CPLP is not a hard power mechanism, it has no capacity, doctrine, logistics, mandate or viability to be used in combat operations. And CPLP Member States are very aware that we are a very good mechanism for cooperation, partnership and development, with contributions to culture and language. Therefore, the CPLP will not intervene in the conflict between Russia and Ukraine, because that is not its area, nor does it have mechanisms for this dynamic.
Is the existence of the CPLP justified?
I think so, obviously, because, as I said, the CPLP is a very good instrument in terms of cooperation, the dissemination of the Portuguese language, of history. The fact is that we have around 350 million people who speak Portuguese. We have 30 countries that are associated observers, such as Ukraine, Chile, and Portuguese culture is represented in this organization. Each country has what it wants from the CPLP and gives it the importance it thinks it should give, and this depends on the foreign policy of each State. But I think the CPLP makes a lot of sense in the world we live in, and does so as a multilateral representative of language, culture, cooperation between Portuguese-speaking states, and those that ultimately have some affinity [with the Portuguese-speaking world]. The Macau issue is very specific to this organization.
Macau has the role of a commercial platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, and China has an agenda for Lusophony.
Before 1999 Macau had its own status within the CPLP, as it was administered by Portuguese. There was a Joint Declaration that allowed Macau, not being a Member State, to have, in a certain way, a protocol [with the CPLP]. When it became a Macao SAR, things changed and it lost that connection status, and Macau is not a member of the CPLP, and obviously cannot be. Neither does China, and it cannot be. Therefore, there is an associated observer status here that arises for countries, international and regional organizations, and even territorial entities with their own administration, which is also not quite the case in Macau. The territory is in limbo, between having a very strong history linked to Lusofonia, and having an administration very linked to China, which gives it, in my perspective, two dynamics.
In what sense?
Macau is a fundamental element in the connection between the CPLP countries and China. For all reasons, but due to the issue of language, history, and its representation, it is a fundamental actor in this cooperation. Macau must effectively be seen as a partner and as a gateway for China to Portuguese-speaking countries. This is what, in a way, is already happening, and this is what the CPLP will be paying attention to, in this relationship in which Macau has a special status. Whether we like it or not, it has an impact. Macau is an attractive factor in facilitating relations between China and Angola, Portugal or Brazil.
Does Equatorial Guinea's stay in the CPLP raise questions of credibility?
I agree with you. In these 30 years, it has been one of the main difficult moments in creating consensus. I remember that Equatorial Guinea was admitted in 2014, but there was already a process in the previous analysis phase. There was always an extension, year after year, and it was difficult to reach a consensus within the CPLP countries. In 2014, there was a summit in Timor-Leste and, through the action of Brazil and Angola, there was, in a way, a lot of pressure for Equatorial Guinea to join. But there are two principles, for better and for worse, that justify Equatorial Guinea's presence in the CPLP.
What are…
The first argument is that, in fact, Equatorial Guinea has Portuguese as its official language in its Constitution, despite us knowing that the Portuguese language, for example, covers four or five percent of society as a whole, and I am already being quite generous. But there is a commitment from the Equatorial Guinea authorities to develop Portuguese as a working language and there is a historical connection to Portuguese culture and Lusophony. Another criterion is the promise that, in the next constitutional review, a commitment will be made to abolish the death penalty. As for Portuguese, it's something that takes generations, it's not done from one year to the next. Not even in the next 10 or 15 years will we have Portuguese perfectly implemented. There is some shyness, a commitment, in a way. As for the death penalty, the fact is that, it seems, some change has been achieved. There has never been a death penalty action again [since accession]. And there is hope that, in the next constitutional review, this fact will be abolished from the Constitution and that it may, effectively, cease to exist. As a member of the CPLP, these changes will be easier and more visible and, in the future, Equatorial Guinea can effectively assume CPLP status taking these premises into account. I don't know if it will happen, I leave here a reluctance, and this is a challenging moment for the CPLP itself. Work needs to be done from within, so that Equatorial Guinea can be at the same level as other countries, especially in these two areas.
What is certain is that there remains a certain lack of transparency regarding what is happening in the country.
We are aware that Equatorial Guinea has major problems with issues of democratic legitimacy and elections. There are a series of situations that we recognize are not perfectly adequate given the status of CPLP countries. I think there is hope that things can change, an attempt to create space for Portuguese to grow within Equatorial Guinea, and also a commitment to greater openness and participation. What is a fact is that Equatorial Guinea has participated in CPLP meetings, and I have participated in some. In international situations we have to be pragmatic, and we hope that, just because Equatorial Guinea is in the CPLP, this can help Guinea itself to develop some mechanical gestures.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied the right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on permanence, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (even in 2011 the Municipal Council of Faro wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
The gentlemen we are talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a member of the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Nuno Borges advances to the quarter-finals after beating Marin Cilic</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/08/hong-kong-nuno-borges-segue-para-os-quartos-de-final-apos-bater-marin-cilic/</link><description>Portuguese number one Nuno Borges qualified yesterday for the quarter-finals of the Hong Kong Open in tennis after beating Croatian Marin Cilic in two partials.
The first half was more balanced, with the player from Maia, 47th in the ATP rankings, being the first to break the serve of the 37-year-old veteran, number 70 in the world. The winner of the US Open in 2014 still responded in kind, but Borges once again broke the Bosnian veteran's game to win the first partial 7-5.
O português entrou melhor no segundo ‘set’, vencendo os três primeiros jogos, vantagem que manteve para fechar o parcial em 6-3 e vencer a partida ao fim de apenas 47 minutos. Nos quartos de final, Borges vai defrontar o vencedor do encontro entre o terceiro cabeça de série do torneio e 16.º mundo, o russo de 28 anos Andrey Rublev, e o chinês de 26 anos Wu Yibing, o número 179 do mundo, que veio da qualificação.
Borges is the eighth seed in the tournament in the Chinese region, which also serves as preparation for the Australian Open – one of the four Grand Slams, the main tournaments in world tennis – which starts on January 12th.
In the 2025 season, the maiato beat, for the first time in his career, a top 10 player, world number eight, Norwegian Casper Ruud, in the second round of Roland Garros, in May. Borges also reached the fourth round at the Australian Open, in January 2025, and at the United States Open, in August, and was also the first Portuguese to reach the round of 16 of the Masters 1,000 in Shanghai, China, in October.</description><pubDate>2026-01-08 01:19:09</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Date and two competitions confirmed</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/12/gp-data-e-duas-competicoes-confirmadas/</link><description>The final meeting of the 2025 FIA World Motor Sport Council took place last Wednesday, during FIA General Assembly Week, in Tashkent, Uzbekistan. The session was attended by delegates from the various National Sports Authorities (ASNs), from which important decisions were taken, some of which concern Macau
The date of the 73rd Macau Grand Prix has been officially revealed, confirming that the Macao SAR's biggest annual sporting event will take place from 19 to 22 November next year. The international federation also took the opportunity to announce that the date and location of the ninth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup, which has been contested at the Guia Circuit since its creation, as part of the Grand Prix program, have been approved by the GT Commission. The same entity did not reveal the guidelines for next year's race, which in this year's edition only featured sixteen competitors, but this is the first time it has confirmed it so early.
For its part, the Touring Car Commission confirmed the calendar for the next season of the Kumho TCR World Tour, which will once again end at the Guia Circuit, as in previous years. China's strong presence on the calendar stands out: the Macau and Zhuzhou races are joined by an absolute debut, the new Chengdu Tianfu International Circuit. With eight events – one in Mexico and three in Europe, including the visit to the Vila Real International Circuit -, Asia gains new importance with a total of four rounds.
Quatro dos eventos de 2026 do Kumho TCR World Tour manterão o formato tradicional de duas corridas, incluindo Macau, enquanto os restantes quatro – México, Espanha (Valência), Coreia do Sul (Inje) e China (Chengdu) – adoptarão o formato de três corridas por fim-de-semana, introduzido no ano passado, atingindo um total de vinte corridas na temporada.
O Conselho Mundial do Desporto Motorizado da FIA não se pronunciou publicamente sobre a continuidade, ou não, das Taças do Mundo de Fórmula Regional (FR) e Fórmula 4 no programa do Grande Prémio de Macau, ainda que o projecto desta última, que envolve igualmente o promotor chinês Mintime e a Fédération Française du Sport Automobile (FFSA), tenha sido concebido para três anos.
Also bet on karting
The World Council also approved the regulations that support the expansion of Karting under the supervision of the FIA, at a time when the next phase of implementation of the “Global Karting Plan” begins, which, next year, will integrate new “Arrive &amp; Drive” championships, included in one of the most extensive calendars ever.
Following the auspicious start of the FIA ​​“Arrive &amp; Drive” Karting World Cup, held in Malaysia last month, the innovative format will be expanded with new continental championships, bringing these accessible and affordable events closer to communities around the world. The 2026 calendar, already approved, will feature a European Championship and an Asia-Pacific Championship, each consisting of three rounds, the winners of which will secure a place on the 2026 FIA “Arrive &amp; Drive” Karting World Cup grid, to be contested at the end of the season.
The Coloane Kart Track, still one of the most modern in Southeast Asia, will be part of this first edition of the “Arrive &amp; Drive” Asia-Pacific Championship, hosting the inaugural race on the weekend of June 20th and 21st. The calendar of this low-cost competition also includes two other stages: one in Zhuzhou, in Hunan Province, and another in Madras, India.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 01:19:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Coloane | Kartódromo hosts the Champions of the Future Academy Program</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/coloane-kartodromo-recebe-o-champions-of-the-future-academy-program/</link><description>The Coloane Kartdrome will start the year at high speed, hosting from the 16th to the 18th of January the first edition in the territory of the new Champions of the Future Academy Program competition, organized and promoted by the Swiss company RGMMC Group
The Champions of the Future Academy Program is an international Arrive and Drive karting competition designed to develop the next generation of motorsport talent. According to the promoter, the event is aligned “with FIA sporting standards and combines elite competition with comprehensive training for drivers, offering young people the experience and international visibility necessary to launch professional careers, while keeping costs under control”.
With three competitive categories — Mini, OK-N Junior and OK-N Senior — the concept aims to bring together emerging talents from around the world to compete in world-class events. According to the organization, this event in Macau “aims to expand the Champions of the Future Academy Program to national series”, reinforcing the presence of the concept outside its main calendar.
In addition to the event in Macao, RGMMC, founded in 2004, also has a non-championship event planned in the United Arab Emirates in February. The regular championship consists of six stages, taking place between February and December, with visits to Spain, Greece, Italy, Oman and the United Arab Emirates. The same entity also promotes a series along the same lines in the United Kingdom.
The Champions of the Future Academy Program Macau, which has the support of the General Automobile Association of Macau-China (AAMC) and the MSAR Sports Institute, will take place over three competitive days, with two final races that determine the classification of the event winner for each category. The paddock will open to teams on Thursday, followed by a full day of free practice on Friday, while timed training and racing will take place on Saturday and Sunday.
Equal for everyone
Each category admits a maximum of 24 competitors, a limit that remains the same in all events. The Mini Group 3 category, aimed at drivers between 9 and 12 years old, will use Parolin chassis and TM engines, with a registration cost of approximately 32,750 patacas. The OK-N Junior categories, for ages between 12 and 14, and OK-N Senior, for ages 14 and 17, will compete with Kart Republic chassis and IAME engines, with the registration fee being around MOP42,125 per weekend.
As the name Arrive &amp; Drive indicates, these values ​​include the kart and its engine, space in the tent, necessary tools, tires — supplied in all classes by LeCont Pneumatici —, fuel, lubricants and all associated logistics. This way, drivers can focus exclusively on driving and, thanks to mechanical equality, competitive and lively races can be expected at one of the best kart tracks in Southeast Asia.
In 2026, the Coloane Kartódromo will have a particularly busy calendar. In addition to the karting and motorcycling competitions organized by the AAMC, the route designed by architect Carlos Couto will host the Chinese Karting Championship, on the 11th and 12th of April, the IAME Series Asia, on the weekend of the 23rd and 24th of May, and the Macau International Karting Grand Prix, scheduled for the period between the 11th and 14th of December.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:34:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Davis Cup | Tiago Pereira makes his national team debut with China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2026/01/09/taca-davis-tiago-pereira-estreia-se-pela-seleccao-com-a-china/</link><description>Tiago Pereira is the new addition to the national tennis team for the Davis Cup match with China, on February 6th and 7th, which also includes Nuno Borges, Francisco Cabral, Jaime Faria and Henrique Rocha, it was announced yesterday. “Tiago Pereira has been improving a lot and, in recent months, he has obtained good results not only in singles but also in doubles, which makes him an option for both variants”, said captain Rui Machado about the debutant.
In addition to the 21-year-old Algarvian, ranked 265th in the world rankings, Rui Machado's bet was on Nuno Borges (45th) and Francisco Cabral (20th), the best Portuguese tennis players today in singles and doubles, respectively, in addition to Henrique Rocha (157th) and Jaime Faria (151st).
Portugal has not competed at home since September 2022, then against Brazil, and the visiting condition has been favorable, but Rui Machado is confident in the group he will take to China.
“We are aware that it will be a very difficult tie against a team with experienced players, with a lot of potential and who have already proven that they can play at a very high level”, he considered, without knowing his counterpart Di Wu's chosen ones. Portugal will visit China in the play-off of Group I of the Davis Cup in tennis, in which they will try to avoid relegation to Group II, where they have not been since 2015.</description><pubDate>2026-01-09 02:28:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau | Rosa Mota in second place in the minimarathon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/09/macau-rosa-mota-em-segundo-lugar-na-minimaratona/</link><description>The Portuguese Rosa Mota came second on Sunday in the Macau mini-marathon, a 4.5-kilometer race that is part of the International Marathon in the Chinese region. The 67-year-old former Olympic champion finished the race in 17 minutes and 10 seconds, 54 seconds more than the first, local athlete Kin I Chao.
In February, the Portuguese woman was discharged from hospital, following a planned surgical intervention, after overcoming a “serious problem”, a “dissecting aortic aneurysm”. Rosa Mota, born in Porto, was Olympic marathon champion at the Seoul Olympic Games in 1988, after having won bronze in Los Angeles in 1984. Her achievements also include three European titles (1982, 1986 and 1990) and one world title (1987).
She is still the national marathon record holder, with a time of 02.23.29 hours, a mark achieved in Chicago in 1985. In recent years, Rosa Mota had reappeared at the highest level and won several veteran races, having set in Barcelona, ​​in 2024, the world half-marathon record (1:24.27 hours), for the 65 to 69 age group.
Also last year, the Portuguese won the Macau mini-marathon, repeating the triumphs in 2018, 2019 and 2023. This year, the organization invited several athletes, nominated by the Association of Portuguese Language Olympic Committees (ACOLOP), from Portugal, Angola, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Mozambique, São Tomé and Príncipe, Sri Lanka and the state of Goa (India).
Lusophony highlighted
Lusophones were in the spotlight in the half-marathon, with Cape Verdean Samuel Freire, from Sporting Clube de Portugal, finishing third in the men's race, behind winner Martin Ndungu and David Kipkorir Rono, both Kenyans.
In fourth place came the Portuguese Fábio Oliveira, 30th in the marathon of the first edition of the European Road Championships, in April, and part of the Portugal team that finished in fourth place. Soon after came the young Mozambican Pinto Victor Jequecene, aged 22, while Angolan David Jundo Elias finished in seventh place.
In the women's race, Angolan Lúcia Kawele Capingala came in third place, behind the winner, Kenyan Lucy Ndambuki, and Chinese Na Zhao. Already off the podium, in fourth position, finished the young Portuguese Joana Ferreira, who won the silver medal in the under-23 race of the national athletics championships in 10 thousand meters, in May.
Mozambican Domingas Ernesto Checane came in sixth place. Around 12 thousand participants signed up for the three races of the Macau International Marathon, with the title of the premier race going to Kenyan Victor Kipchirchir and Ethiopian Senay Mastewal Birhanu.
In addition to his triumph, Kipchirchir broke the Macau marathon record, finishing in two hours, nine minutes and 27 seconds, 34 seconds less than the previous record, set in 2017 by Ethiopian Felix Kiptoo Kirwa.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 03:18:38</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Unanimity regarding “Super Pole” in GT</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/05/gp-unanimidade-quanto-a-super-pole-nos-gt/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) should continue to focus on the “Super Pole” system for the ninth FIA GT World Cup, if this race is once again included in the program of the 73rd Macau Grand Prix next year
For the first time, in last November's edition, the ten fastest in Qualifying 1 had 20 minutes to prepare for the first “Super Pole” in the history of the FIA ​​GT World Cup, in which, in reverse order of times, each driver entered the track alone for one out lap, two timed laps and one return lap, with one-minute intervals between competitors and the possibility of using a new set of tires. The best time obtained between the two timed laps determined Qualification 2 “Super Pole”, which defined the starting grid for the Classified Race.
Following the success of this initiative, the international federation intends to continue applying it in the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup, having even produced a promotional video to confirm this. Lutz Leif Linden, President of the GT Commission and the FIA ​​Constructors' Commission, admits that this is something “very exciting for the spectators as well as the drivers”.
Present in Macau during the Grand Prix, the influential Stéphane Ratel, CEO of SRO Motorsports Group, co-organizer of the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup, also agrees with the measure, highlighting that it represents "an additional challenge and one that works. At SRO we do this on a global level. In the biggest events, like the 24 Hours of Spa, we have a 'Super Pole', and it is something we like."
Riders and brands agree
Drivers and brands were equally impressed with this first experience on the territory's streets. “Macau is already special and I think that, with this format, we had something even more special”, recalled Antonio Fuoco, the driver who gave Ferrari its first in Macau since 1995.
Ferdinando Cannizzo, head of Ferrari's Competizioni GT, reinforces the idea, highlighting the technical advantage when the challenge comes down to the driver and the circuit, without external interference. “Without cars, without traffic, you can really focus on your strengths and try to maximize the car’s performance”, said the Cavallino Rampante brand representative.
This qualification system, an important moment of the weekend given the difficulty of overtaking on the Guia Circuit, also adds an element of uncertainty and elevates the spectacle. Stefan Gugger, responsible for the development of Lamborghini's competition cars, said that, in his opinion, "it's an improvement for our fans. We can really see the performance of the driver and the car, which also represents a good challenge for the team."
Porsche, one of the brands that most advocated the mandatory introduction of expensive torque sensors in this race, was also one of the main drivers of the “Super Pole”. “I believe the new format is a real step forward,” said Thomas Laudenbach, Vice President of Porsche Motorsport. "It allows the drivers to have clean laps. It's a great step in the right direction, maybe with some tuning, but overall for me it's positive. I hope they maintain this format because it's fantastic."
Meanwhile, the date of the 2026 edition of the Macau Grand Prix is ​​expected to be confirmed next week, during the FIA ​​World Council, which will take place before the FIA ​​awards ceremony for 2025, in the city of Tashkent, Uzbekistan.</description><pubDate>2025-12-05 01:52:45</pubDate></item></channel></rss>