<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>MNE Iranian says that first Israelites and now USA "have exploded diplomacy"</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/mne-iraniano-diz-que-primeiro-israelitas-e-agora-eua-fizeram-explodir-a-diplomacia/</link><description>The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the United States and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran.
"We were negotiating (about the Iranian nuclear program) with the United States when Israel decided to explode this diplomacy," said Abbas Araghchi, through platform X and then in statements in Istanbul, adding that when they were in dialogue with European Union countries -referring to Geneva negotiations this week -"the United States decided, in turn, to reverse this diplomatic."
“What conclusions can you draw from this?” Araqchi replied to the appeals made yesterday by the head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, and British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer.
The EU high representative for Foreign Affairs, Kaja Kallas, called for “all parts” to take a “backwards”, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb ”after bombing, last morning, from the US against the major nuclear facilities of Iran.
The British Prime Minister, in turn, called for the will "return to the negotiation table", stressing that "stability in the region is a priority." In the answer lasts to these appeals to return to the negotiating table, the head of Iranian diplomacy also maintained: "How could they go back to something he never abandoned, let alone destroyed?"
To attack
US President Donald Trump confirmed at dawn that the United States Armed Forces attacked three nuclear centers in Iran, including Ford, joining Israel directly to wage the country's nuclear program.
"We have completed our successful attack on the three nuclear facilities in Iran, including Fordo, Natanz and Esfahan," Trump said in a social media post. The war began at dawn on June 13, with Israel to launch a vast military offensive against the Persian country, allegedly to prevent the advance of the Iranian nuclear program for military purposes.
The attacks decimated Iran's military and nuclear infrastructures, which has responded with missile vacancies on major Israeli cities, including Tel Aviv and Jerusalem, as well as several military facilities throughout the country.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:44:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Casinos | Suggested new projects to attract tourists to Zape</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/casinos-satelite-sugeridos-novos-projectos-para-atrair-turistas-ao-zape/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) suggested, in a meeting with representatives of the Zape hotel sector, that this zone can integrate more intellectual property projects and initiatives, such as large facilities or dolls, to attract tourists.
This meeting took place on Friday and had as context the discussion of measures to deal with the satellite casinos closure by the end of the year. According to a note, STD also wants to promote “the extent of the economic benefits of concerts, the proper use of spaces for the accomplishment of activities and the optimization of the zone environment, among others”, and the exploration of “new sources of visitors” was suggested.
Entrepreneurs were also advised to launch “complementary tourist products or accommodation promotions”. Representatives of the hotel and tourist sectors “have generally agreed with preliminary measures defined by the government,” the same note describes. Zape has over 20 hotels of different types and categories.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:12:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Auto Silos Management | Accepts 9 of 12 proposals delivered</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/gestao-de-auto-silos-aceites-9-de-12-propostas-entregues/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) accepted, this Friday, 9 of 12 proposals submitted to public tender organized to manage several public parking parks, namely the self-solo of the building of the services for traffic issues, the self-solo building, the self-solo of the Taipa Marítimo da Taipa terminal SELF-SILO of the Lake Building and the Public Parking of the Residence for the elderly of Avenida do Nordeste.
According to a statement from DSAT, proposals for quarterly base returns between 1.088 million patacas and 2.038 million patacas, and the three societies were excluded because they volunteered from the competition, is explained.
The management deadline for management is six years and covers 2188 parking places for light cars and 1858 for motorcycles and mopeds. DSAT explains that the concessionaire will be responsible “not only for the daily management and exploitation of self-siles, but also for the optimization of the electronic payment system and without contact of auto-subsidia, the reinforcement of safety surveillance systems” and “implementation of ecological and energetically efficient equipment, and the improvement of existing facilities”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:19:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Accepts Submissions for 2nd Short Festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/aceites-submissoes-para-2o-festival-de-curtas-metragens/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) and Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG) accept resident film submissions for the “2nd International Festival of Macao Shorts of Galaxy Entertainment Group”, namely for the “Macao Shorts” category.
According to a press release, it is intended, with this initiative, to “encourage local film production talents to build a base of local short films and expand opportunities for exchange and international collaboration”.
Submissions should be made by July 21, and the “Macao Award” and “Special Jury Prize” winners can receive a trophy and monetary prize of up to 45,000 patacas.
The second edition of this festival takes place in September in the Galaxy theaters, the Galaxy auditorium of the International Convention Center and the Andaz Hotel at Galaxy Macao, as well as at Cinemateca Paixão.
"A large event program will be presented, including an opening and projected ceremony, the" prominent director "section and lectures given by experts, movie themed workshops, an industry forum, as well as a closing and awarding ceremony and a red treadmill event."
By parts
The festival includes a total of five categories, and in addition to the “Macao Shorts”, the public will be able to watch films integrated in the sections “New Voices of the Horizon”, “Highlight Director”, “Vision of East Asia” and “Special Sessions”. The same note reports that “experienced filmmakers” were invited to join the jury. In the case of “Macao Shorts”, the choice will be made by the International Advisory Committee of the “International Macao Short Festival of Macao”.
The event regulation and registration forms can be discharged on the Electronic Page of the Cultural Institute or Macao's Cultural and Creative Industries. Candidates may deliver the duly completed registration form, along with the necessary materials in person in the building of the Cultural Institute.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:36:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Water | Miriam Grupo carboys with high levels of bacteria</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/agua-garrafoes-de-miriam-grupo-com-niveis-elevados-de-bacterias/</link><description>It is the third case, since the beginning of the year, of waters distributed in Macau without complying with quality standards. The carboys were provided to public services, such as health services. In reaction to the case, Miriam Group accuses “some customers” of purposely contaminating the carboys used
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has announced that several water carboys supplied to public services of the brand Sun spoiled in quality tests, presenting high levels of coliform bacteria and pseudomonas aeruginosa bacteria. Coliform are a type of bacteria, such as E.Coli, which inhabit the gut of mammals, while pseudomonas aeruginosa bacteria can be found in waters and soils and can lead to severe infections in the lungs, skin or urinary tract.
The problem with water Sun, from Miriam Group Limited, was identified in lots produced on May 7 and 21 this year, and communicated on Friday. However, the information provided by AMI and SS did not reveal the time when the problems were detected by the entities.
Since the beginning of the year, this has been the third brand of Macao Águas de Macau to have quality and safety problems. The first case took place on 9 March with the Iceblue brand, from the Oi Kou Pou factory. More recently, also in May, authorities have detected problems with water from the Ieong IAT Tat brand.
Water Sun will have been provided to local public services, including health services (SS). However, it was denied that the contaminated water had entered the retail, hospitals or schools. "The two lots of distilled water did not enter the retail market, being mainly supplied to government services and commercial societies. The lots were not supplied to schools or hospitals," was reported by SS.
After disclosure of the information, the SS announced the cancellation of the water supply of that brand: “After verification, the lots concerned were not provided to health services. However, for safety reasons, health services stopped using the potable waters of that brand, and began to use the bottled waters of another qualified brand, in order to ensure the supply of drinking water”, was justified. The statement does not identify whether there is a new water supplier or if the watermark of Miriam Grupo Limitada has been changed.
Attack of “some customers”
Upon detection of this case, AMI reported that it requested the group to “apply prevention measures, namely the collection of the distilled water lots, as well as implementing the cleaning and disinfection of the water production line”.
Miriam Grupo Limitada also responded to the case by indicating that since June 1, which had issued a warning to warn of the collection of contaminated lots and that since May 30 the water production has been suspended for cleaning and applying the necessary rectifications. The same information indicated that compared to the plot of 7 May were collected 196 of the 367 carboys of water produced and compared to the lot of 21 May were collected 121 of the 432 carboys of distributed water. "Under the witness and organization of the AMI, the plots of abnormal water carboys were eliminated. Between May 30 and June 1, an independent cleaning company also cleaned the factory and production equipment. About 9,000 water carboys in May were eliminated," was released by the group.
In the statement, the group also complained of media coverage, and denied that the lot of May 7 had presented positive results of coliform bacteria contamination, not denied contamination with pseudomonas aeruginosa bacteria.
Miriam Grupo Limitada also accused some customers of contaminating the used carboys, which are later returned, to harm the company.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Visitors | Second best start up to May</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/visitantes-segundo-melhor-arranque-de-sempre-ate-maio/</link><description>Between January and May, 16.3 million visitors were received, the second best record of visitors. However, the number is still below what happened before the pandemic and the policy of isolation
 
Macau received 16.3 million visitors in the first five months of this year, the second highest amount ever for a year start, was announced on Friday. According to official data, the number of tourists who passed by Macau was only surpassed between January and May 2019 -before the COVID -19 pandemic -during a period when nearly 17.2 million visitors.
However, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), almost 59 percent of visitors arrived on organized excursions and spent less than one day in the city.
In 2024, the central government released a series of measures to support Macau, such as the increase in the tax exemption limit of goods for personal use acquired by visitors from China.
At the same time, the Chinese authorities widened 10 other cities in China the list of places with “individual visas” to visit Hong Kong and Macau. Also, since January 1 that residents of the neighboring city of Zhuhai can visit Macau once a week and stay up to seven days.
As a result, the overwhelming majority (90.7 percent) of tourists who arrived in Macao in the first two months of the year came from interior or Hong Kong, while only 1.14 million were international visitors.
On January 17, Macao's director of tourism services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, said he hoped Macau could receive between 38 and 39 million visitors this year. In August, the leader pointed to more than three million international visitors in 2025.
More without visas
The territory authorities announced on Monday that Saudi Arabia national citizens, Qatar, Kuwait, Barizer and Oman are dismissed from a visa to enter Macao from July 16.
The measure comes at a time when the Macao government wants to attract more international visitors and after the territory's authorities and tour operators visited in February Saudi Arabia and Dubai to promote cooperation.
Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor, excluding in the casinos, fell 13.2 percent in the first quarter of the year, compared to the same period of 2024.
In early May, the direction of statistics and census services in the region pointed to the “change of visitors' consumption pattern” as one of the main reasons for the fall of 1.3 percent of Macau's economy between January and March.
It was the first time that the territory's gross domestic product has shrunk in homologous terms since the end of 2022, when the region began to raise restrictions due to Covid-19 pandemic.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Elections | After 35 years, Kou Hoi In is in the process of leaving al</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/eleicoes-apos-35-anos-kou-hoi-in-esta-em-vias-de-deixar-a-al/</link><description>In addition to Kou Hou in, they may still be out of exit Chui Sa Cheong and Vong Hin Fai. In the opposite direction, they enter the lists of the indirect suffrage Kevin Ho, Vong Hou Piu and Wong Chon. IAU TENG PIO AND SI KA LON ALSO join the indirect suffrage
 
The current President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, is out of the lists of the elections for indirect suffrage and should be left out of Hemiciclo for the first time since 1991. Kou maintenance in Parliament now depends on a possible appointment by Sam Hou Fai, chief executive.
In recent years, the entrepreneur has always been elected by the list of Macau business interests, but is not on the list of candidates, such as Wang Sai, who had been elected deputy for the first time in 2021.
In the opposite direction, Edmund Ho's businessman and nephew, Kevin Ho starts to join the list, which practically guarantees him the election. For this list it also enters Si Ka Lon, deputy since 2013, elected by direct suffrage on the lists of the Fujian community, linked to businessman Chan Meng Kam. This time, if Ka Lon applies to Al through the indirect suffrage. Kevin Ho and Si Ka Lon are also deputies by Macau to the National People's Assembly.
Regarding 2021, the union of Macau business interests maintains in the lists José Chui Sai Peng, businessman, and IP Sio Kai, vice president of the Banco da China Macao branch. These two candidates, as well as Kevin Ho and Si Ka Lon, have the election confirmed, given that in the industrial, commercial and financial sectors there is only one list for four places. The only obstacle to the election would be a lead to the candidacies of the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) or the State Security Defense Commission.
During the delivery of the list, Chui Sai Peng, cousin of former Chief Executive Fernando Chui Sai On, said, quoted by the newspaper or Mun, that the purpose of the list is to contribute to improving the business environment in Macao, and reinforcing the development of the economy.
More changes
The expected changes at the Legislative Assembly are not for the industrial, commercial and financial sectors, also in the professional sector there are changes, Chui Sai Cheong, Al, Vong Hin Fai, President of the Macao Lawyers Association, and Chan Iek Lap are out of the Macao Professional Interests list.
The doctor had revealed in February last year that he was leaving. However, in relation to Chui Sai Cheong and Vong Hin Fai there was no such indication. However, these deputies may be appointed by the Chief Executive. Vong Hin Fai and Chan Iek Lap will be replaced by Vong Hou Piu, Accountant and Wong Chon, doctor.
The list is now led Iau Teng Pio, lawyer and academic, who was so far in the Legislative Assembly by appointment of the Chief Executive. Speaking cited by the newspaper or Mun, Iau Teng Pio stated that the list in an objective "to develop the primacy of the law" and "achieve common progress in industry."</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:03:18</pubDate></item><item><title>PATANE MARKET | CE hears complaints from traders</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/mercado-do-patane-ce-ouve-queixas-de-comerciantes/</link><description>The chief executive visited several neighborhoods of Macau, including Fai Chi Kei, Ilha Verde and the Canidroma Zone. In the Patane market, Sam Hou Fai heard complaints of bad business and promised to find solutions together with society. In addition, it revealed that the possibility of connecting Qingmao is being studied to Fai Chi Kei through the light meter
 
The chief executive made a journey through the Macau Peninsula on Saturday, visiting several neighborhoods accompanied by secretaries of his executive. Sam Hou Fai went to the Patane market, the Ilha Verde neighborhood and the Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, “to find out about the business exploration environment, as well as visited the former Yat Yuen canhydrome” to learn about the construction work of the Sports Park.
In the Patane Municipal Market, the government leader hear traders who complained about the lack of customers and weak sales. “We are living very difficult times. We can only earn 200 or 300 patacas a day, although market income is low, we can't cover expenses. If you can not solve [the problem], how can we solve?” Asked a trader from a fresh product sales board. Sam Hou Fai pointed to cooperation. “Let's work together to solve the problem,” replied the ruler.
The saleswoman returned to the cargo and argued that online consumer habits razed the traditional trade. "Now residents do not shop in stores. After the pandemic, they only do online shopping," warned residents. "We can't close the internet, this is impossible," he replied between laughs Sam Hou Fai, commenting that "things have changed a lot." “Let's work together to try to solve the problems,” insisted the chief executive.
The banking merchant next to the answer to how the businesses went to the same scenario. "The business is still difficult, it is true. The lives of residents are becoming increasingly difficult. We hope that with their leadership, the market environment can be optimized," he said. Sam Hou Fai replied that this was also his desire.
Reinforcement of supports
The chief executive also visited the Patane Food Center, where he spoke to residents and tourists. Sam Hou Fai encouraged traders to "constantly implement news to explore characteristics that attract more visitors."
After passing through Patane, the entourage led by the chief executive went to Ilha Verde, Fai Chi Kei and surroundings, accompanied by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP. Some traders have asked Sam Hou Fai a new round of consumption prize to improve business.
The Chief Executive also took the opportunity to visit the “Sanrio Character Dream Garden”, and the FEELING HOUSE OF THE PARTY OF THE ROUND OF EDUCATION AND Youth Development Services, where it interacted with students.
Regarding the “Dream Garden”, Tai Kin IP said that in about 80 days, the initiative “managed to divert more than 240,000 visitors to the social neighborhood”.
Finally, Sam Hou Fai visited the land of the former Yat Yuen Caniderom where the construction of a sports park is planned and was known the situation of the work, listening to a presentation of the secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam. The chief executive said that the “public contest of works for the first zone is scheduled to soon”.
Regarding the traffic of the adjacent zones, Sam Hou Fai revealed that the works for the eastern line of the Light Metro that connects the northern part of the city to the Taipa result at a good pace. The ruler revealed that his executive "is studying the possibility of extending the line of the slight meter from the Qingmao border post to the Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, as well as the future sports park."</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 02:51:33</pubDate></item><item><title>History | The MA-chan escape to the colonial and macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/historia-a-fuga-dos-ma-chan-para-o-portugal-colonial-e-para-macau/</link><description>The MA-chan family is from Mozambique with Chinese roots, sought its new path in the then colonial Portugal and since 1976 that set roots in Macao. José Manuel Machon, resident in the territory since he was 13, told Lusa the very peculiar trajectory of his family, which reflects many of the family directions taken in the years of war and the end of the Portuguese colonial empire
 
The MA-chan, the Mozambican family with roots in China, fled twice to communism and twice resumed in colonial Portugal. In 1976, they landed in Macao, where Mozambique's memory had erased with the departure of the Landins, African troops that parked in the territory for decades since 1912.
According to a report by Luís Andrade de Sá published in Macau magazine in 1992, and quoted by the blog "Chronicles Macanese", the Landins were in Macao "for about five decades", and "the Chinese never used to their conviviality, suspiciously who had the huge blacks who played a horrible drumsticks while returning the ostensiva. ferocity ”. The term Landim became a reference “to identify all indigenous battalions that passed by Macau”, is described in the same report.
Massá Ma-chan went in 1963 to the Namphlam, northern Mozambique Conservatory to register the fifth son, but once again denied this Chinese, with roots in Guangzhou, the transmission of the nickname to descent. José Manuel was the same as his brothers: the nickname Machon, corruption of MA-chan.
The identity of José Manuel Machon, embryoly marked by this bureaucratic detail imposed by the then Portuguese Mozambique, is not only a reflection of the colonial past of Portugal, but from the beginnings of Sino-Mozambican relations.
“I don't have great confusion, I tried to adapt to life,” he tells Lusa in Macau, where he has lived since he was 13. The grandfather-also MA-chan-was the one who defined that this story began in Africa, leaving China looking for better life, in the starter of the twentieth century, and settling in Nampula, alongside Sharing, a Macua woman, Mozambican ethnic group.
Massá, the son -and father of José Manuel -was sent to Guangzhou at 14, to receive formal education there. When he returns to Mozambique, he is a married man with a bullet mark near his left shoulder.
In China, he faced the Japanese in World War II and married a Chinese, which he met on the day of marriage, until, on the threshold of the civil war, which would victory to Mao Zedong's communists, fled. He dedicated himself to Nampula to the cucumber of the cucumber-the 'Magojojo'-and the tubar bit, which he exported to Hong Kong.
The Great Return
However, unable to adapt, the woman returned to Macao with her four children, where she died. Massá returned to marry, this time with a Mozambican - José Manuel came first, Carla later.
When the Frelimo flag raised on the mast in Mozambique on June 25, 1975, the MA-chan-headed Macao, with a brief passage in Portugal, where they inhabited a pension paid by the then IARN.
“We are nothing returned, because we have not returned anywhere, we are refugees,” says Carla Machon, residing in Portugal.
“When my father heard again about communism, he fled,” says his brother, José Manuel. While speaking, bowling balls pack on the floor and travel the track to a new crash. The noise in the center of Bowling Future Bright does not seem to bother this big man, 61, fluent in Cantonese and Portuguese and president of Macao Bowling Club. “This is what keeps me stable. Instead of going to the glasses, I come here,” he notes.
For Joseph, independence "it was an open openness, an opening to the world." It doesn't even talk about political reasons, but how important it was to cross half a world until you arrived in Macau.
A new life
In this page turn, the MA-chan/maachon family came to find, in 1976, a city with little civil presence abroad. José and Carla do not remember other Mozambicans, who began to arrive after independence, many from Portugal.
Mong-Há's fortress is an old witness to Mozambique's presence in Macau. Then the Landins, Mozambican soldiers at the service of the Colonial Army were quartered, recalls journalist João Guedes, a scholar in the history of Macao. It is this historical circumstance that baptized the hill of Mong-há of “Mountain of Black Ghosts”.
These troops, with the “greatest warrior instinct”, in the expression of Emperor Gungunhana, remained in Macao half a century, until around the 1960s. They were responsible, for example, by the storage of the siege gates, border of the territory with China and recurring incident place.
“They passed by and faded as if they had never been,” resumes Guedes, indicating that there was no material heritage attesting this military presence. Not far from Mong-Há, but at the Riquexó restaurant, troops are still there, eternalized in photos hanging on the walls.
This serves African chicken, macanese dish, whose origin is still today the target of debate. Two theories: It was created by the Portuguese chief Américo Ângelo, inspired by a trip to Mozambique. Another version realizes that, seeing the African soldiers missing roasted chicken, Americo made the dish.
And the memory of macau-moca-mandamous relationships is not complete without evoking the trafficking in leaf. If, on the one hand, it is known that the Portuguese took slaves from the African colonies by settling in the doors of China, in reverse, were also sent via Macao, Chinese to work in Mozambique, often in slavery conditions.
The sons were part of a migratory movement from the late nineteenth century, “to develop the Mozambican colony,” explains the professor at Joaquim Chissano University in Maputo, Fatima Papelo, who investigates Sino-Mozambican cooperation. The first group, he says, was sent in 1858 and "consisted of 30 men."
More than a century later, in the struggle for Mozambican independence, Beijing supported the Liberation Front of Mozambique (Frelimo) and is one of the first countries to recognize the new sovereign state. In Macao, the reinforcement of the ties was later paid, with the transition from the territory of Portugal to China in 1999.
But for José Manuel, Mozambique was always present. The last time it went, tells, visited and cleaned the family campaign, "there at Machamba". "It's a Chinese custom," he explained.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 02:46:38</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE Iranian says that first Israelites and now USA "have exploded diplomacy"</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/mne-iraniano-diz-que-primeiro-israelitas-e-agora-eua-fizeram-explodir-a-diplomacia/</link><description>The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the United States and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran.
"We were negotiating (about the Iranian nuclear program) with the United States when Israel decided to explode this diplomacy," said Abbas Araghchi, through platform X and then in statements in Istanbul, adding that when they were in dialogue with European Union countries -referring to Geneva negotiations this week -"the United States decided, in turn, to reverse this diplomatic."
“What conclusions can you draw from this?” Araqchi replied to the appeals made yesterday by the head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, and British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer.
The EU high representative for Foreign Affairs, Kaja Kallas, called for “all parts” to take a “backwards”, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb ”after bombing, last morning, from the US against the major nuclear facilities of Iran.
The British Prime Minister, in turn, called for the will "return to the negotiation table", stressing that "stability in the region is a priority." In the answer lasts to these appeals to return to the negotiating table, the head of Iranian diplomacy also maintained: "How could they go back to something he never abandoned, let alone destroyed?"
To attack
US President Donald Trump confirmed at dawn that the United States Armed Forces attacked three nuclear centers in Iran, including Ford, joining Israel directly to wage the country's nuclear program.
"We have completed our successful attack on the three nuclear facilities in Iran, including Fordo, Natanz and Esfahan," Trump said in a social media post. The war began at dawn on June 13, with Israel to launch a vast military offensive against the Persian country, allegedly to prevent the advance of the Iranian nuclear program for military purposes.
The attacks decimated Iran's military and nuclear infrastructures, which has responded with missile vacancies on major Israeli cities, including Tel Aviv and Jerusalem, as well as several military facilities throughout the country.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:44:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Casinos | Suggested new projects to attract tourists to Zape</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/casinos-satelite-sugeridos-novos-projectos-para-atrair-turistas-ao-zape/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) suggested, in a meeting with representatives of the Zape hotel sector, that this zone can integrate more intellectual property projects and initiatives, such as large facilities or dolls, to attract tourists.
This meeting took place on Friday and had as context the discussion of measures to deal with the satellite casinos closure by the end of the year. According to a note, STD also wants to promote “the extent of the economic benefits of concerts, the proper use of spaces for the accomplishment of activities and the optimization of the zone environment, among others”, and the exploration of “new sources of visitors” was suggested.
Entrepreneurs were also advised to launch “complementary tourist products or accommodation promotions”. Representatives of the hotel and tourist sectors “have generally agreed with preliminary measures defined by the government,” the same note describes. Zape has over 20 hotels of different types and categories.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:12:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Auto Silos Management | Accepts 9 of 12 proposals delivered</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/gestao-de-auto-silos-aceites-9-de-12-propostas-entregues/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) accepted, this Friday, 9 of 12 proposals submitted to public tender organized to manage several public parking parks, namely the self-solo of the building of the services for traffic issues, the self-solo building, the self-solo of the Taipa Marítimo da Taipa terminal SELF-SILO of the Lake Building and the Public Parking of the Residence for the elderly of Avenida do Nordeste.
According to a statement from DSAT, proposals for quarterly base returns between 1.088 million patacas and 2.038 million patacas, and the three societies were excluded because they volunteered from the competition, is explained.
The management deadline for management is six years and covers 2188 parking places for light cars and 1858 for motorcycles and mopeds. DSAT explains that the concessionaire will be responsible “not only for the daily management and exploitation of self-siles, but also for the optimization of the electronic payment system and without contact of auto-subsidia, the reinforcement of safety surveillance systems” and “implementation of ecological and energetically efficient equipment, and the improvement of existing facilities”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:19:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Accepts Submissions for 2nd Short Festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/aceites-submissoes-para-2o-festival-de-curtas-metragens/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) and Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG) accept resident film submissions for the “2nd International Festival of Macao Shorts of Galaxy Entertainment Group”, namely for the “Macao Shorts” category.
According to a press release, it is intended, with this initiative, to “encourage local film production talents to build a base of local short films and expand opportunities for exchange and international collaboration”.
Submissions should be made by July 21, and the “Macao Award” and “Special Jury Prize” winners can receive a trophy and monetary prize of up to 45,000 patacas.
The second edition of this festival takes place in September in the Galaxy theaters, the Galaxy auditorium of the International Convention Center and the Andaz Hotel at Galaxy Macao, as well as at Cinemateca Paixão.
"A large event program will be presented, including an opening and projected ceremony, the" prominent director "section and lectures given by experts, movie themed workshops, an industry forum, as well as a closing and awarding ceremony and a red treadmill event."
By parts
The festival includes a total of five categories, and in addition to the “Macao Shorts”, the public will be able to watch films integrated in the sections “New Voices of the Horizon”, “Highlight Director”, “Vision of East Asia” and “Special Sessions”. The same note reports that “experienced filmmakers” were invited to join the jury. In the case of “Macao Shorts”, the choice will be made by the International Advisory Committee of the “International Macao Short Festival of Macao”.
The event regulation and registration forms can be discharged on the Electronic Page of the Cultural Institute or Macao's Cultural and Creative Industries. Candidates may deliver the duly completed registration form, along with the necessary materials in person in the building of the Cultural Institute.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:36:21</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Debate around the ICC Arbitral Tribunal takes place today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/frc-debate-em-torno-do-tribunal-arbitral-da-icc-decorre-hoje/</link><description>Integrated in the “reflections on the afternoon” cycle, today's conversation at the Rui Cunha Foundation revolves around the Arbitral Tribunal of the International Chamber of Commerce and the connection to the local legal community, with four interveners: Winnie Wat, Ana Coimbra Trigo, Mariana Esteves and Fatima Dermawan
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts today, from 6.30 pm, the “Arbitral Court of the ICC: linking to the legal community of Macao”, dedicated to discussing the International Court of Arbitration, as “world leader arbitral institution” and its connection to local reality.
According to a press release, “since 1923 [which this entity] has helped to resolve disputes in international commercial and investment disputes”, and the Court administers “arbitration exercising judicial supervision of arbitral procedures, ensuring the proper application of the 2021 arbitration rules and assisting the parties and referees”.
“These efforts are supported by the Court Secretariat, consisting of more than 100 lawyers and employees, operating in offices in Paris, New York, Sao Paulo, Singapore, Abu Dhabi and Hong Kong,” he says, and today's panel “aims to present to the Macao legal community the operation of the ICC International Arbitration Court [International Trade Chamber] to explain the role of the secretariat and the court in their arbitration services and ADR.
The debate also aims to present “an overview of the legal framework of arbitration in Macao and its latest developments”, and it serves the interest of “companies, internal and external lawyers, government officials, judges, teachers and students who are interested in learning about ICC or participating in ICC arbitration in the future, such as lawyers, experts or referees”.
The voices of reason
In these “reflections on the afternoon” participate Winnie Wat, deputy counselor of the Secretariat of the International Arbitration Chamber of Trade. He is accredited as a member of the Chartered Institute of Arbitators (FCIB) since 2021 and mediator of the Litigation Resolution Center (CEDR).
Also noteworthy is the participation of Ana Coimbra Trigo, senior associate in the area of ​​dispute resolution of the Portuguese Law Firm PLMJ Law Firm.
With 10 years of experience, he regularly participates as a lawyer and secretary of the Court in international and national arbitration and related legal proceedings, as well as other civil and commercial disputes, including postfusions and acquisitions, telecommunications, energy, aviation and real estate.
In addition, he is a member of the ICC International Arbitration Court for Macao and University Teacher.
Mariana Afonso Esteves, another of the speakers, has been a C&amp;C Advogados &amp; Notary senior lawyer since 2009. Its areas of action have encompassed litigation and dispute resolution, mediation and arbitration, game law, insurance, family law, as well as administrative and public law.
Fátima Dermawan is an assistant legal advisor at Game Operator Sands China, where he supervises the company's Litigation Department. Fatima has a degree in Law from the Faculty of Law of the New University of Lisbon and Master from the Harvard Law School, exercising law in Portugal since 2013, in Macao since 2016 and in the state of New York since 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:33:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Rainfall | Floods leave tens of thousands of displaced</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/chuvas-inundacoes-deixam-dezenas-de-milhares-de-desalojados/</link><description>The intense rains that have plagued various southern and downtown China regions since the beginning of last week have affected at least 300,000 people and forced tens of thousands of residents, especially in Guangdong province.
In the village of Huaiji, one of the most affected zones, the rains caused flooding of up to three meters deep, leaving half of the local roads.
Images released on state television show muddy and neighbors and volunteers streets working in their cleaning. The situation is also critical in other provinces of the center and eastern of the country, such as Hunan, where the Lishui River has registered its largest flood since 1998.
In the village of Longshan, four people remain missing after being trapped in a flooded underground garage. In the neighboring province of Hubei, the authorities have removed hundreds of people in municipalities such as Hefeng and Laifeng.
In the latter, a day care center was completely flooded and it was necessary to transport 500 children in rafts, said The Paper newspaper. The Ministry of Water Resources sent technical teams to high -risk zones and asked local governments to reinforce surveillance and preventive evacuation of vulnerable areas.
Local experts have warned in recent years that climate change may increase the frequency of extreme weather phenomena in the Asian country.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:28:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Inflation slowed to 0.19% in May</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/economia-inflacao-desacelerou-para-019-em-maio/</link><description>Inflation in Macao slowed in May, was announced on Friday, but the region escaped the fall in consumer prices, something that took place for the fourth consecutive month in the interior of China.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) in Macau rose 0.19 percent in May, in homologous terms, slower than the amount recorded in April (0.23 percent), according to official data released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
Although the CPI has dropped 0.05 percent compared to April, the territory escaped for the third consecutive month of deflation (annual fall in consumer prices).
Deflation reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly severe, as a drop in the price of assets, as awarded to credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
China, by far Macao's largest commercial partner, has been in consecutive months in deflation after the IPC has retreated 0.1 percent in May, the same amount recorded in April and March.
According to Macao DSEC data, the deceleration of inflation in May is due to the cost of meals acquired away from home, which rose only 1.39 percent, while the expenditures on apartment mortgages increased only 0.42 percent.
The housing price index fell 11.7 percent last year, notwithstanding Macau's monetary authority approved three interest rates in the last three months of 2024. Despite the increase in the number of visitors, the region registered a 2.5 percent drop in the price of clothing and footwear.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:14:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the United States and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran.
"We were negotiating (about the Iranian nuclear program) with the United States when Israel decided to explode this diplomacy," said Abbas Araghchi, through platform X and then in statements in Istanbul, adding that when they were in dialogue with European Union countries -referring to Geneva negotiations this week -"the United States decided, in turn, to reverse this diplomatic."
“What conclusions can you draw from this?” Araqchi replied to the appeals made yesterday by the head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, and British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer.
The EU high representative for Foreign Affairs, Kaja Kallas, called for “all parts” to take a “backwards”, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb ”after bombing, last morning, from the US against the major nuclear facilities of Iran.
The British Prime Minister, in turn, called for the will "return to the negotiation table", stressing that "stability in the region is a priority." In the answer lasts to these appeals to return to the negotiating table, the head of Iranian diplomacy also maintained: "How could they go back to something he never abandoned, let alone destroyed?"
To attack
US President Donald Trump confirmed at dawn that the United States Armed Forces attacked three nuclear centers in Iran, including Ford, joining Israel directly to wage the country's nuclear program.
"We have completed our successful attack on the three nuclear facilities in Iran, including Fordo, Natanz and Esfahan," Trump said in a social media post. The war began at dawn on June 13, with Israel to launch a vast military offensive against the Persian country, allegedly to prevent the advance of the Iranian nuclear program for military purposes.
The attacks decimated Iran's military and nuclear infrastructures, which has responded with missile vacancies on major Israeli cities, including Tel Aviv and Jerusalem, as well as several military facilities throughout the country.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the United States and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran.
"We were negotiating (about the Iranian nuclear program) with the United States when Israel decided to explode this diplomacy," said Abbas Araghchi, through platform X and then in statements in Istanbul, adding that when they were in dialogue with European Union countries -referring to Geneva negotiations this week -"the United States decided, in turn, to reverse this diplomatic."
“What conclusions can you draw from this?” Araqchi replied to the appeals made yesterday by the head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, and British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer.
The EU high representative for Foreign Affairs, Kaja Kallas, called for “all parts” to take a “backwards”, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb ”after bombing, last morning, from the US against the major nuclear facilities of Iran.
The British Prime Minister, in turn, called for the will "return to the negotiation table", stressing that "stability in the region is a priority." In the answer lasts to these appeals to return to the negotiating table, the head of Iranian diplomacy also maintained: "How could they go back to something he never abandoned, let alone destroyed?"
To attack
US President Donald Trump confirmed at dawn that the United States Armed Forces attacked three nuclear centers in Iran, including Ford, joining Israel directly to wage the country's nuclear program.
"We have completed our successful attack on the three nuclear facilities in Iran, including Fordo, Natanz and Esfahan," Trump said in a social media post. The war began at dawn on June 13, with Israel to launch a vast military offensive against the Persian country, allegedly to prevent the advance of the Iranian nuclear program for military purposes.
The attacks decimated Iran's military and nuclear infrastructures, which has responded with missile vacancies on major Israeli cities, including Tel Aviv and Jerusalem, as well as several military facilities throughout the country.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the United States and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran.
"We were negotiating (about the Iranian nuclear program) with the United States when Israel decided to explode this diplomacy," said Abbas Araghchi, through platform X and then in statements in Istanbul, adding that when they were in dialogue with European Union countries -referring to Geneva negotiations this week -"the United States decided, in turn, to reverse this diplomatic."
“What conclusions can you draw from this?” Araqchi replied to the appeals made yesterday by the head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, and British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer.
The EU high representative for Foreign Affairs, Kaja Kallas, called for “all parts” to take a “backwards”, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb ”after bombing, last morning, from the US against the major nuclear facilities of Iran.
The British Prime Minister, in turn, called for the will "return to the negotiation table", stressing that "stability in the region is a priority." In the answer lasts to these appeals to return to the negotiating table, the head of Iranian diplomacy also maintained: "How could they go back to something he never abandoned, let alone destroyed?"
To attack
US President Donald Trump confirmed at dawn that the United States Armed Forces attacked three nuclear centers in Iran, including Ford, joining Israel directly to wage the country's nuclear program.
"We have completed our successful attack on the three nuclear facilities in Iran, including Fordo, Natanz and Esfahan," Trump said in a social media post. The war began at dawn on June 13, with Israel to launch a vast military offensive against the Persian country, allegedly to prevent the advance of the Iranian nuclear program for military purposes.
The attacks decimated Iran's military and nuclear infrastructures, which has responded with missile vacancies on major Israeli cities, including Tel Aviv and Jerusalem, as well as several military facilities throughout the country.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Assistant researcher and coordinator of the CCCM Educational Service
June 2025
Much has been written about Luís Vaz de Camões in his fifth centenary, celebrated over the past two years, given the question mark, subscribing to the exact date of his birth, 1524, 1525 or always Renaiscent? It is in the perpetual movement of its eternal Renaissance that this article fits, this time in the search for biography recreated from contemporary poets, read swimming and created in the twentieth and twentieth centuries, which were passed, passed or just stayed overnight in dreams in Macao. Some of them identified with the national poet, others dialogued, distanced themselves or simply silenced him.
Dialogues
Among those who dialogue with Camões, is Cecilia Jorge1, who in the work dedicated to writer João Aguiar, with the preface by Professor Vera Borges, meditates and recreates the identity of Macaense, presenting the valuable perspective of the daughter of the earth, in which it seeks to provide a realistic look at what is “being macanese”, deconstructing myths. Already the Portuguese ancestor is presented in its less romanticized version, in the poem “mestizaje”, such as “Corsican, Reinol, Adventurer”, in the wake of the cultural tradition of Fernão Mendes Pinto. Therefore, it is natural that Camões arise not in the solar space of praise and more of dialogue, in the shadow of the demystification of a very expensive idea to a certain macanese and Portuguese intellectuality, that of “Lusitanity”, which dates back to the epic poem Os Lusíadas and their wonderful heroes to contrace it with illustrious divines of the Greco-Latin world. In “Making Read…” (without forgetting the reticence), says the poetic self in the last block of the poem:
Lusitanity clay feet
loose candle caravels
ripping
on the return to the homeland
(Jorge, 2021, 33)
Still it is the figure of Camões who gives strength to the poem, even with a “lusitanity of clay feet”, for, in a possible reading, while the caravels (or ships) remain in the sea, there is a destination to fulfill, with “flesh and bone” feet, or rather, with full feet; The problematic space seems to arise when the return that removes the adventurers from their predestined maritime adventure.
The Camonian ideas are discussed, perhaps, to the best defend.
António Duarte Mil-Homens2 will be a Portuguese poet, this time in open dialogue with Camões in his work poemography, in the poem, untitled, started by the verse “There is a cave”:
There is a cave
In my chest
And it's not Camões.
Stanzas of suffering,
Karma from other lives,
Eco docts poems,
Involves Darkeys.
Praying many coming,
Tear of many trips,
Headquarters of the same source,
Failure of other passions.
(MIL-HOMENS, 2019, 16)
There is a clear existential identification of the Poetic Mil-Homens self with the 16th century poet, although the cave is not the same, because they are not the same meat, however, identical the poetic space in which they live, one and the other, fed by a constant movement between here and there, in which they imagine both to stop drinking to the inspiring source and feeder.
Myths and images
Camões is an inexhaustible source of myths, not only for his existential path, but also for the poetic epic around which he developed, from his death to our day, a national image that contributed to the creation of a collective imagination and a Portuguese philosophy around national heroes, the Lusitans and the Lusitanity. The illustrious descendants of Lusitanians are a people of adventurers and poets, all people linked to the sea, where they will seek their greatest inspiration. Thus we are presented and seen by the descendants lenses, which extend from Portugal to the East, naturally passing through Brazil. Read the verses of Ricardo Portugal's “TAPROBAN BLues” in passages, with which many Portuguese instinctively identify, sympathize or, even when they distance, are not able to remain indifferent:
Round World The Father's Name
That sounds to Camões, short and thick
(…)
Every sailor seeks the port,
Every poet is a sailor.
Portuguese Ocean Sea
that the port opens by the crests
from another written sea,
badly sacred by the thread of poetry,
text of other texts, a country,
Dead Sea without Bible.
All Portuguese is poorly born,
The whole poet is Portuguese.
(Portugal, 2004, 55)
The romantic appeal of the sea is stronger in these verses that cross sailors and poets, connecting the sea indissolibly to Portugal, “Portuguese the Ocean Sea”, as another larger poet, Fernando Pessoa4, had already told him in “Portuguese Sea”, shed in salt, so much tear from Portugal:
O Salgado Sea, how much of your salt
They are tears of Portugal!
For crossing you, how many mothers cried,
How many children in vain prayed!
How many brides were getting married
So you were ours, O sea!
(PERSON, 1986, 86)
Of course, “it was worth it, even for the myths it has been cherishing on this Portuguese soul, recreated literary to the present.
The sea of ​​poets, or perhaps the sea inspired by the national poet, but also that of love spirits, where once again Camões appears in a place. This will be brought here by António Manuel Couto Viana5 in the book to the distant China navigated… In the long drama in verse “Camões and Dinamene, argument for a ballet”, in which the sad wreck of Camões and his love story with “Dinamene” 6 is narrated. Couto Viana Nothing Nething, not even the poetic verses of the national poet, which introduces into the "poetic argument." To retain the explicit reference to Os Lusíadas, which imbr while in the plot, in order to explain that the beloved of Camões passed away, but fate had other accounts for him:
The poet will finish the corner.
If it does not end, Portugal is mute.
And God wants this homeland to be
The word of the world. And the Lusíadas
They are the source and root of that word.
(VIANA, 1991,84)
Certain images can be discussed by some intellectuals, but will be forever linked to Macao, such as Camões has been in the territory, being closely related to a homonymous garden, in which it appears a bust of yours and the first, second and third resorts of Canto I of the Lusíadas recorded in the pedestal.
António Bondoso7 in the work in Macau Porsa (1999) dedicates the poem “Garden of Camões”, contributing, with so many other poets, including those cited in this text, to consolidate the connection of the cultural image of the national poet to Macau, in a poem of accurate simplicity:
In the garden there are flowers
and stones with history.
And the shadow of the poet's bust
cut in the slab
weather
eternalizes centuries of words!
(Bondeoso, 1999, 41)
Camões in China and, specifically, his stone address in Macao are still sung by José Augusto Seabra in “Da Gruta”, José Valle de Figueiredo “in the Cave of Camões”, or Josué da Silva8 in “Camões to the Sad orient”, this brings the last stanza:
Finally here I find insignated rod
in this cave so sad and so dark,
Trying in her hauir all the passion
that forces this cold stone,
SEE HEAR THE HEART OF A HEART
that made Portugal, the soul of poetry.
(Kelen and Han, 2009, 305)
Myths and dialogues, separately, or myths and dialogues included, the truth is that even today the Portuguese, wandering and migrants, with more or less built-in Portuguese, drags sadness, sharing it with Camões, some well counterfeit, due to the hope of better and greatest destination, the one that can only be found in the “soul of poetry”, with Josué Silva with the Portuguese language ” Person/Bernardo Soares.
This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors ”https://www.ccccm.gov.pt
Bibliographic references
Bondeosa, Antonio. 1999. In Macau by chance. Macao: Author's edition with the sponsorship of the Office of the Assistant Secretary for Communication, Tourism and Culture and Foundation for the Cooperation and Development of Macao.
JORGE, Cecilia.  2021. Poems for Macau. (2nd.). Macau: Books from the East.
Kelen, kit, Lili Han. 2009. PORTUGUESE POETS OF MACAU. PORTUGUESE POETS OF MACAU. Macau: ASM-Association of Stories in Macau.
MIL-HOMENS, António Duarte. 2019. Poemography of Macau. Macao: Cultural Institute of the Special Administrative Region of Macau.
PERSON, FERNANDO. “Portuguese Sea”, in Message. Blog Mar Portuguese - Fernando Pessoa. International Organization Nova Acropolis, Brazil. https://nova-acropole.org.br/blog/mar-portugues-ferando-pessoa/
PERSON, FERNANDO. 1986. Message. Jin Guo Ping translation. Macau: Macao Cultural Institute.
Portugal, Ricardo. 2004. Porto Alegre: Ameop - Love the Poem Editora.
VIANA, António Manuel Couto. 1991. Until the distant China sailed… Macau: Macao Cultural Institute.
Additional Information:
Cecilia Jorge is a native of Macau, from an illustrious Macanese family. Came to Portugal to attend Germanic Philology at the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon in the 70s of the twentieth century. From 1973, it is dedicated to journalism. In the 1980s, he developed cultural activity through the Macao Cultural Institute and the direction of Chinese affairs services. In 1990, he started to develop editorial activity, founding with Rogério Beltrão Coelho, Consort, the East Books Publishing House. In his work, he has deepened, under various angles, the cultural identity of Macaense, attentive to the influences of Portuguese and Chinese cultural matrices, as witnessing wants the works published in magazines, for example, the magazine Macau, both the books that have been legally as author, where it addresses themes related to Maca society and culture. From his poetic work, the work poems to Macau stands out.
António Duarte Mil-Homens was born in Lisbon on October 9, 1049. Photographer since 1974, he has been professionalized in 1984. Since 1989 photography workshops and has been participating in about half a hundred exhibitions, individual and collective, photography and art. It is also distinguished in poetic activity, both in collections and in individual works, of these refers to life or death of an announced hope (2010), Universália (2019) and Poemography of Macau (2019).
Ricardo Portugal was born in 1962 in Porto Alegre, on February 28. He has a degree in Letters from the Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, being a diplomat. He was a teacher of Brazilian literature and Portuguese language, as well as, in Porto Alegre, organizer of cultural activities in the area of ​​literature, at the Municipal Secretariat of Culture. Participated in various poetry dissemination activities, such as recitals, shows, publication in periodicals and poetry anthologies. Here stands out passages, individual poetic text published in 2004.
Fernando Pessoa was born in Lisbon on June 13, 1888, lived in South Africa, having attended the University of Cape. Then he distinguished himself as a student, having been awarded the “Queen Victoria Memorial Prize”. In 1905, he returned to Portugal not to leave the country again, where he remains painful and lonely as foreign correspondent, office employee and translator, collaborating sporadically in newspapers. Of his vast poetic, homonymous and heteronymous work, he only made the message published in life.
António Manuel Couto Viana was born in 1923 in Viana do Castelo. He was a poet, playwright, essayist, memoralist and author of children's literature. He was also actor, director and theatrical businessman, having directed the Gerifalto Theater Company and the National Theater Company. He also dedicated himself to the experimental theater, having been an actor, set designer and director of the Salitre Study Theater. In addition to 40 titles from various literary genres, 25 works in poetry, translated into Spanish, English and Chinese, from which are distinguished here “in the East of the East” and “Even the distant China navigated…”
Dinamene can be a handy way to refer to a Chinese name "Dina Mei", which may be translated as "Dina Girl."
António Bondoso was born in Moimenta da Beira in 1950. He walked through the space of the old Portuguese colonies. First was in S. Tomé, where he grew up, studied and married. Then he professionalized on the radio and also fulfilled military service, which led him to Nova Lisbon, in Angola. Returning to Portugal in October 1974, he continued to be linked to radio, first at the national station in Lisbon, then at the Northern Regional Emitter, in Porto. He devoted much of his attention to the training area, having participated in the Porto Journalists Training Center and in the founding of the Porto Journalists School. He went to Macao in 1994, having been chief of writing at the Macao TDM (Teledifusion), where he held a 31 series programs (Macau - The East of History) to mark the transfer of the Portuguese administration from Macao to the RPC in 1999. It has more than twelve titles published here in poetry in Macau Porso (1999).
Josué da Silva was born in 1930. He was a journalist, having started his career in the Diário de Lourenço Marques in 1955 in Mozambique. He then collaborated with several Portuguese newspapers such as the century, weekly current, Jornal do Fundão, among others. As a writer, he was a collaborator of the newspaper Arts and Letters and the Literary Supplements of the Diário de Lisboa and The Capital. His first poetic experience dates from 1963, mountain notebooks. He has resided in Macau since 1990, having published, among other works, the soap opera Amor Oriente, in 1993.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Lu Dongbin, the Immortal, waited sitting in a Handan inn, the city of Hebei at Hanshan's term, the reddish purple mountain. He had a porcelain pillow and expected, he would know later, to demonstrate the possibilities offered in the finitude of the flow of the days.
Unknowingly, he came to a luminous encounter, Lu Sheng was immersed in obscure thoughts raised by repeated setting of fortune, but would come with the accuracy of the road that would place him face to face with the immortal patient. Having a brief exchange of words, Lu Sheng realized that the lovely man, who was in front of him with the robes of a daoist priest, was available to listen to his complaints. And the disappointed traveler told how he had narrowly disapproved of the Jinshi exam that would allow him a quiet life in the service of the Empire and now even admitting to imagine a future.
Depois de o escutar, Lu Dongbin estendeu-lhe a almofada que trazia e disse-lhe para descansar um momento enquanto uma reconfortante papa de sorgo amarelo cozia ao lume. Soon the traveler fell asleep. And he dreamed the most comforting dream: that passed the imperial exam, knew the most beautiful and intelligent wife, who would give him many children, with whom he would live many years in a well paid and quiet imperial post. Suddenly but awakened from the dream that seemed to have lasted a lifetime. Asking the Master of theist how long he had slept, he replied that the sorghum Pope had not yet bought it yet.
The ancient account in which an immortal allows a mortal to live, in fact, another life for a short time to show him the illusory and transitory character of ambitions for himself to deduce another path, would be resumed in 1601 by playwright Tang Xianzu (1550-1616). But it was well known as one of Handan's many proverbs, reduced to four short characters: 黄粱美梦 Huangliang Meimeng, "a good dream, yellow sorghum."
Huang Ding (c.1650-1730), a changzhou painter, made a series of paintings "in the way of" augustes painters of the past such as Wang Meng, Dong Yuan or even Nizan's unmistakable style landscapes (vertical roller, ink on paper, 92.7 x 35.1 cm, at the Minneapolis Art Institute) as wanting to embrace under his tiz. Long history of painting made for a wide time.
At that time a small album was circulated with notes of the influential Dong Qichang, but which is attributed to Wang Shimin (1592-1680) entitled Xiaozhong Xianda, "Revelation of Large Things In Small", which contained, in a small format, recreations of works by great masters. Can you see something too big can be done in a small shape, but a lifetime in a short time? Because what travels is the Spirit, Lu Dongbin made him in less than an hour, the time it takes to cook the yellow sorghum.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Elections | “Soldier of Mao” claims innocent and says he was six days unable to take a shower</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/18/eleicoes-soldado-de-mao-afirma-se-inocente-e-diz-que-esteve-seis-dias-sem-conseguir-tomar-banho/</link><description>Accused of electoral corruption and having an illegal Mahjong business, Wong Wai Man yesterday returned to the load to cry out his innocence. The president of the Iron and Steel Shipowners Association says he was “provoked” to climb to the roof where he was a few hours, and was six days without being able to bathe or change clothes
 
The panorama of the legislative elections for the hemicycle already boils. In addition to these elections with the smallest number of candidate lists since the creation of the MSAR, the controversy is installed with the almost candidate Wong Wai Man, who tried to submit his candidacy without success.
Also known as the “Soldier of Mao” and “Captain of Macao”, and after being accused of electoral corruption and having an illegal Mahjong business, behold, Wong Wai Man returned to the cargo to explain: refuses the accusations that he is targeted, says he was persecuted by the authorities and refers to “torture” the way he was treated when his detention.
The president of the Iron and Steel Association was on Monday, several hours on a roof of a house made with a metal plate in the mud, having been rescued by the Fire Department. A solution that says it was “provoked” after being detained by the Judiciary Police (PJ), referred to the Public Prosecution Service and receiving the Commissioner's Call against Corruption (CCAC), which accuses him of having the illegal business.
Wong Wai Man explained that, shortly after leaving the CCAC Office in the Nape area, he was intercepted by an employee of this body that alleged the lack of signature in some documents. However, not satisfied with the situation, Wong Wai Man picked up a taxi towards the mud, eventually taking refuge on the roof. "I had no other option, CCAC wanted to chase me to death. So I was on the roof," he explained.
Regarding accusations of electoral corruption, man says he is poor and is unable to commit such illegalities. Regarding Mahjong's alleged illegal business, Wong Wai Man stressed that the Association's headquarters in fact has Mahjong tables, but only for the enjoyment of the partners.
Regarding the use of money in these games, Wong Wai Man said there was always a sign to say that it was forbidden to be bets on money and that there was, at the association's headquarters, a box for donations, but that was intended for voluntary support of the members to help the association's operation.
This is because, according to this, besides being president is also the only one to support all expenses of the Association of Iron and Steel shipowners, namely those related to income, water and light, considering that since 2014 that the entity has not received subsidies.
One thing is certain: the association's headquarters will close doors tomorrow due to the end of the lease. Wong Wai Man says that for now, he will not look for a new address for the association because, for now, he has a more pressing subject: looking for a place to live. Wong Wai Man made the association's headquarters to his home.
Life lesson
Despite having missed the opportunity to submit a list and be a candidate for elections for the Legislative Assembly by Via Direct, Wong Wai Man argued that the most important thing was to participate in the whole process and learn new things. The "captain of Macao" also said that he is dedicated to society of heart and not by selfishness. Your ideal is to do things justly for society, since it argues that traditional associations do not defend the people.
Wong Wai Man also told journalists a personal episode to justify their participation in social and public causes. "In 2007 my wife was pregnant and the hospitals convinced her to end her pregnancy because the baby's survival rate would be 50 percent, due to the fact that a fetal anomaly was detected after the exams. I insisted and the government eventually paid the operation worth 70 thousand patacas. So I want to make my contribution to repay a favor" to heaven "," he said.
Six days without bathing
According to the All About Macau newspaper, Wong Wai Man reported that he was still six days without bathing and sleeping, having remained a week missing until he performed with CCAC this Monday. Before he did, he said he was a total of six days detained, which for himself was “torture”, and that in total was all this time without bathing, sleeping or changing clothes. On Sunday, you will have been able to go home.
"Last night [Tuesday] I finally managed to sleep well and bathe. I was six days without being able to bathe or change my clothes," he explained. The climb to the roof of the house in the mud was also a form of protest by the way it was treated, he said.
The detention took place at dawn last Wednesday, the 11th, between 3 am and 4 am, with the argument that Wong Wai Man would maintain an illegal Mahjong business. It was then that he was detained for 48 hours in a squad in the mud, and was then transferred to the Public Prosecution Service (MP) to continue to make statements.
After this process, he was notified to present himself with CCAC, having signed the requested documents. He was then arrested again for another 48 hours and transferred again to the MP. When, already on the street, he was again informed that he would have to return to CCAC to sign more documents, decided to escape and take refuge on the roof.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 23:46:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Breast Cancer | Research of one does “revolutionary discovery”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/18/cancro-da-mama-investigacao-da-um-faz-descoberta-revolucionaria/</link><description>A study by a team led by two professors at the University of Macao seeks answers to combat breast cancer. Academics concluded that cancer cells spread mainly through the lymphatic system, not by the bloodstream
 
“The lymphatic system is the main route for breast cancer dissemination and metastasis, revealed by tracking unique cell lineage” is a scientific article that seeks to increase knowledge that allows you to find solutions to the disease. The work was developed by a research team led by the full professor Chuxia Deng and assistant professor Miao Kai at the University of Macao Faculty of Health Sciences (one) and, according to a note from UM, is a “revolutionary discovery in the study of cancer metastases”.
Thus, and for the first time, “a qualitative and quantitative analysis of breast cancer metastases was made, and was applied by scientists“ a barcode system based on an unique cell lineage tracking approach ”called Celltag.
With this method, results were obtained that reveal that "cancer cells spread mainly through the lymphatic system, not by the bloodstream." In addition, he points out one, “research also found that interaction between tumor cells and the tumor microenvironment (TME) determines the metastatic potential of cancer cells”, ie whether or not they may easily reproduce.
In this sense, “the study systematically demonstrates the roads of tumor metastases and opens new ways for the development of cancer treatment strategies”, is described.
The article was published in the magazine “Molecular Cancer” and is the result of an investigation by a vast team, consisting of Kai Miao, Aíping Zhang, Xiaodan Yang, Yipeng Zhang, Anqi Lin, Lijian Wang, Xin Zhang, Heng Sun, Jun Xu, Yuzhao Feng, Fangyuan Shao, Sen Guo, Zhihui Weng, Peng Luo, Xiaoling Xu and Ch -xia Deng.
Highlight for the collaboration of scientists from other higher education institutions in the region, such as Aiping Zhang, Hong Kong-Shenzhen Hospital University, and Jingyao Zhang and Shuai Gao, linked to China Agricultural University in Beijing. In turn, Dong Wang and Xiao-Yang Zhao are linked to Southern Medical University's School of Basic Medical Sciences in Guangzhou.
Microenvironment is an important factor
One explains, in the same statement, that the study in question “provides empirical evidence for the route preference in cancer metastasis”, demonstrating that tumor cells are “pre-programmed” with “intrinsic information that determines their metastatic potential”, and these cells “adapt dynamically their genetic expression based on the target organs”.
Thus, "these findings establish the foundations for the development of therapies directed to lymphatic metastasis, such as the inhibition of cytokine signaling or the interruption of communication between tumor and stroma to suppress metastasis."
In the investigation, the “single cell RNA sequencing technology” was used, which allowed the team to “discover that genetically identical tumor cells exhibit profiles of specific genetic expression of the organ”, so the microenvironment proves to be “fundamental in the formation of tumor cell behavior”.
"For example, pulmonary metastatic cells positively regulate oxidative stress -related genes, while hepatic metastatic cells activate metabolic regulatory pathways," is referred to.
The danger of metastases
One points out that, in cancer diseases, metastases are the main cause of death. However, to date, "the mechanisms that govern the selection of the route" of these same metastases remained "obscure."
“Using Celltag technology, the research team traced the spread of breast cancer cells on mice models,” discovered that “less than 3 percent of cancer cells spread throughout the bloodstream, while more than 80 percent metasta through the lymphatic system for distant organs such as lungs and liver”.
Thus, "more in-depth analysis has shown that lymph spread cells have distinct genetic expression patterns and communicate closely with stromal cells, such as endothelial fibroblasts and cells in the microenvironment, forming an adaptive" seed-solo "mechanism."
Looking at the study, the authors explain that cancer metastasis “is a process in which the tumor cells of the primary tumor invade the basal membrane of the blood or lymphatic vessels (intravasation), travel the blood or lymphatic system and colonize distant organs and tissues to continue their development”. Several studies point to the fact that metastases are responsible for 70 to 90 percent of cancer -related mortality, and “the dissemination of tumor cells in the vasculature and lymphatic vessels occurs simultaneously in the vast majority of cancers”.
Blood roads
In the discussion of the results, the study authors say that, in general terms, “tumor cells metastatize mainly through blood circulation and lymphatic system”, and until the publication of this work had been performed “numerous studies to distinguish the role of both systems in the various phases of cancer metastasis”, without knowing “which way’ for metastasis ”.
It is referred to in the article, citing other studies that “cancer cells enter the bloodstream through intravasation to become CTCs [Circulating Tumor Cells-Tumor Cells in circulation], having revealed highly correlated with the survival results of breast cancer patients”.
The authors also explain that “the lymphatic system is considered critical for metastasis”, as “melanoma cells with lymphatic experience were more resistant to iron and more metastases”, and in cases of “cancer tumor resection, cancer cells can further spread the lymph nodes for blood vessels and form tumors and forming tumors. metastatic in the lungs ”.
To date, “although metastatic dissemination was viable by both ways, the relative importance of each process for a certain type of cancer and the target organ was unknown due to the lack of adequate quantitative tools”, something to which this study, using the celltag system, intended to respond.
Thus, “we demonstrate that most lung and liver metastatic cells can be detected in the lymphatic system rather than CTCs [circulation tumor cells] derived from the blood, indicating that lymphatic vessels can be the favorite way for tumor cell metastasis, at least in breast cancer”.
The authors promise not to stop here in the discovery of the course made by the metastasis of carcinogenic cells, having already performed "preliminary tests" with some cells in order to find out the possibility of "drastic" reduction of tumor cells disseminated by lymphatic. "We will continue to work on this to deepen the lymphatic dissemination mechanism and explore therapeutic interruptions in our future efforts," he is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-06-18 02:57:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | CUPPA Coffee manager calls for support to Portuguese companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/17/comercio-gestor-do-cuppa-coffee-pede-apoio-a-empresas-portuguesas/</link><description>The story of Cuppa Coffee dates back to 2008 when it was hard to find a space in Macau to drink good coffee. The location in the old mud brought fame to the project, but the space ended up closing doors and moving to Studio City. João Incarnation, who manages coffee, speaks of the news and the importance of supporting Lusophone matrix projects
 
It all started in the mind of Portuguese Cristiana Figueiredo, at a time when for a Portuguese or passionate about coffee living in Macau it was hard to find a space to enjoy this drink accompanied by bakery or pastry products, in good Portuguese way.
Cristiana Figueiredo said, in an interview with the Macao Commerce and Investment Promotion Institute (Ipim), which led her to invest in this type of business. "In Europe, people have a habit to go to coffee and to work for work. When I came to Macau for over 20 years, I realized that the Portuguese coffee culture is not popular in Macao, so I was born the idea of ​​opening a coffee in Macao, hoping to promote the food and culture of Portuguese coffee."
Since 2008, Cuppa Coffee, associated with the initial project of the businesswoman, Nata Bakery, founded in 2007 and focused on bakery and pastry products, has become one of the favorite spaces of the Portuguese, foreign and even resident of the territory. However, the direction of the economic environment, with greater difficulties in paying lace, has dictated some transformations to the project, which now ends doors to the entrance of Taipa Velha and also with Lakes Nam Van, to be only in the Studio City venture in Cotai. The closure in the lakes Nam Van took place in January.
At HM, João Incarnation, director and shareholder of the company that generates Cuppa Coffee, explains that, in fact, the change to the Cotai was decided for a long time. "I often say that there was no change to Studio City, because this was a plan that already existed and that came regardless of the taipa store closure. We would always open this space regardless of whether we continue, or not, with the store in the mud, whose closure was due to a failed negotiation regarding space income."
Segundo João Encarnação, que hoje gere a empresa com Nicole Massa Helm, ambos consideraram que “na situação económica actual não havia condições para continuar naquele espaço, que é relativamente grande e tinha os seus custos”.
“Precisávamos de fazer alguma contenção se queríamos que o negócio continuasse a funcionar, porque a alternativa é sempre fechar completamente. Não desistimos da ideia de abrir qualquer coisa na Taipa e de estarmos um pouco mais próximos dos nossos clientes regulares e mais fiéis, pelo que continuamos com esse propósito de abrir outro estabelecimento na Taipa que possa servir os clientes que lá vivem. Portanto, não há propriamente uma deslocação para o Studio City”, adiantou João Incarnation.
The director and shareholder understands that this change always causes some nostalgia. “We pity it to have closed it. It cost us, we really have a lot of pity,” he confessed. "It was a decision that could have been made longer, at least a year, but we still tried to keep the establishment there, but we were not possible. We will see what the future reserves us."
Despite these changes, Cuppa Coffee can be considered a successful case. "It worked there for many years and it worked well. This is a business that has to have certain conditions to work because, as we know, it has a lot of movement, but with little performance regarding each client. It is a business that needs many customers to support themselves, and for many years, at the level of rent values ​​and everything else, suppliers, for example, was much cheaper and things worked better," he recalls.
The location in Taipa Velha gave Cuppa Coffee “a very large recognition and clientele”, despite the growing difficulties. "As prices were increasing, we also needed to increase our prices, but never in proportion to the increase in expenses. There was a time when we could not continue," he assumed.
What the future reserves
João Incarnation ensures that what customers have always sought in this space will continue in Studio City: good coffee and pastry products, with the presence of Portugal. "We always try to introduce new products. We created a new, coffee and coconut -based drink, which is excellent. We also introduced the" Nata Bomb ", a Milkshake Beat Concept flavored Nata, a true bomb," he described.
There are also “traditional Portuguese products that did not exist before, such as bay bread”, as well as the donuts with different flavors, “to complete the offer we have”. "Our offer is already so varied that, even without introducing more products, it is sufficient to satisfy the values ​​of Portuguese customers and others as well."
John Incarnation also said that the change of establishment to Studio City was born from an invitation. “We don't know how to run yet, it's a bet that we are making right now”, and the goal is always to go back to street coffee. "The concept of having a neighborhood store or on the street is something that interests us a lot and we are already seeing other possibilities," he added.
"I don't have enough data to at this moment tell you that the change to Studio City is a winning bet. It's different, just like the concept, and we will have another type of customers beyond the usual."
A “Heart” project
Looking back, John Incarnation says that, for example, major problems have never been registered with human resources. "To this day we do not feel the big problem with lack of labor, it has never been something that has greatly affected us. Nowadays it is not as easy as it used to have quotas [for non-resident workers], as there are enough places that need placement. It is able to be easier, at this time, to get more local workers than before," he said, confirming that lace remain to be the big problem for such business.
“Cuppa Coffee is a project of the heart and during the pandemic I realized that I was going to close. I also realized that there was a series of closures, almost simultaneously, from other Portuguese establishments. Talk to my partner, who has a lot of experience in this area, and told him that I liked to try to keep Cuppa Coffee open. Possible to continue exactly the same concept and the same quality as it had been having with Cristiana, who did an excellent work in the creation and growth of Cuppa Coffee. ”
Overcoming the pandemic years, and at a time when Macau faces a break in local consumption, João Incarnation says that "it fulfills a bit to the Portuguese community to make the possible to support the effort we do so that everything is still open."
“I am not just about Cuppa Coffee, but also from wheat d'old, butter, Portuguese restaurants and Lord Stow, which is not a typical Portuguese business is based on Portuguese culture. All of these businesses have to be fed and supported. For our part, we must maintain quality, but the Portuguese community has to take advantage of what exists and support the Portuguese business.”
Despite the breach of consumption by the places, João Incarnation says that a balance with the consumption of tourists is guaranteed. "We feel a little [Break of consumption], but we can counterbalance with the offers we do and that satisfy the taste of local Chinese and visitors. But of course [consumer breakage] has, of course, impact on business, not just the Portuguese, and this is in the city. But I think there is still some critical mass to keep Portuguese business open," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 00:32:25</pubDate></item><item><title>History | The MA-chan escape to the colonial and macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/historia-a-fuga-dos-ma-chan-para-o-portugal-colonial-e-para-macau/</link><description>The MA-chan family is from Mozambique with Chinese roots, sought its new path in the then colonial Portugal and since 1976 that set roots in Macao. José Manuel Machon, resident in the territory since he was 13, told Lusa the very peculiar trajectory of his family, which reflects many of the family directions taken in the years of war and the end of the Portuguese colonial empire
 
The MA-chan, the Mozambican family with roots in China, fled twice to communism and twice resumed in colonial Portugal. In 1976, they landed in Macao, where Mozambique's memory had erased with the departure of the Landins, African troops that parked in the territory for decades since 1912.
According to a report by Luís Andrade de Sá published in Macau magazine in 1992, and quoted by the blog "Chronicles Macanese", the Landins were in Macao "for about five decades", and "the Chinese never used to their conviviality, suspiciously who had the huge blacks who played a horrible drumsticks while returning the ostensiva. ferocity ”. The term Landim became a reference “to identify all indigenous battalions that passed by Macau”, is described in the same report.
Massá Ma-chan went in 1963 to the Namphlam, northern Mozambique Conservatory to register the fifth son, but once again denied this Chinese, with roots in Guangzhou, the transmission of the nickname to descent. José Manuel was the same as his brothers: the nickname Machon, corruption of MA-chan.
The identity of José Manuel Machon, embryoly marked by this bureaucratic detail imposed by the then Portuguese Mozambique, is not only a reflection of the colonial past of Portugal, but from the beginnings of Sino-Mozambican relations.
“I don't have great confusion, I tried to adapt to life,” he tells Lusa in Macau, where he has lived since he was 13. The grandfather-also MA-chan-was the one who defined that this story began in Africa, leaving China looking for better life, in the starter of the twentieth century, and settling in Nampula, alongside Sharing, a Macua woman, Mozambican ethnic group.
Massá, the son -and father of José Manuel -was sent to Guangzhou at 14, to receive formal education there. When he returns to Mozambique, he is a married man with a bullet mark near his left shoulder.
In China, he faced the Japanese in World War II and married a Chinese, which he met on the day of marriage, until, on the threshold of the civil war, which would victory to Mao Zedong's communists, fled. He dedicated himself to Nampula to the cucumber of the cucumber-the 'Magojojo'-and the tubar bit, which he exported to Hong Kong.
The Great Return
However, unable to adapt, the woman returned to Macao with her four children, where she died. Massá returned to marry, this time with a Mozambican - José Manuel came first, Carla later.
When the Frelimo flag raised on the mast in Mozambique on June 25, 1975, the MA-chan-headed Macao, with a brief passage in Portugal, where they inhabited a pension paid by the then IARN.
“We are nothing returned, because we have not returned anywhere, we are refugees,” says Carla Machon, residing in Portugal.
“When my father heard again about communism, he fled,” says his brother, José Manuel. While speaking, bowling balls pack on the floor and travel the track to a new crash. The noise in the center of Bowling Future Bright does not seem to bother this big man, 61, fluent in Cantonese and Portuguese and president of Macao Bowling Club. “This is what keeps me stable. Instead of going to the glasses, I come here,” he notes.
For Joseph, independence "it was an open openness, an opening to the world." It doesn't even talk about political reasons, but how important it was to cross half a world until you arrived in Macau.
A new life
In this page turn, the MA-chan/maachon family came to find, in 1976, a city with little civil presence abroad. José and Carla do not remember other Mozambicans, who began to arrive after independence, many from Portugal.
Mong-Há's fortress is an old witness to Mozambique's presence in Macau. Then the Landins, Mozambican soldiers at the service of the Colonial Army were quartered, recalls journalist João Guedes, a scholar in the history of Macao. It is this historical circumstance that baptized the hill of Mong-há of “Mountain of Black Ghosts”.
These troops, with the “greatest warrior instinct”, in the expression of Emperor Gungunhana, remained in Macao half a century, until around the 1960s. They were responsible, for example, by the storage of the siege gates, border of the territory with China and recurring incident place.
“They passed by and faded as if they had never been,” resumes Guedes, indicating that there was no material heritage attesting this military presence. Not far from Mong-Há, but at the Riquexó restaurant, troops are still there, eternalized in photos hanging on the walls.
This serves African chicken, macanese dish, whose origin is still today the target of debate. Two theories: It was created by the Portuguese chief Américo Ângelo, inspired by a trip to Mozambique. Another version realizes that, seeing the African soldiers missing roasted chicken, Americo made the dish.
And the memory of macau-moca-mandamous relationships is not complete without evoking the trafficking in leaf. If, on the one hand, it is known that the Portuguese took slaves from the African colonies by settling in the doors of China, in reverse, were also sent via Macao, Chinese to work in Mozambique, often in slavery conditions.
The sons were part of a migratory movement from the late nineteenth century, “to develop the Mozambican colony,” explains the professor at Joaquim Chissano University in Maputo, Fatima Papelo, who investigates Sino-Mozambican cooperation. The first group, he says, was sent in 1858 and "consisted of 30 men."
More than a century later, in the struggle for Mozambican independence, Beijing supported the Liberation Front of Mozambique (Frelimo) and is one of the first countries to recognize the new sovereign state. In Macao, the reinforcement of the ties was later paid, with the transition from the territory of Portugal to China in 1999.
But for José Manuel, Mozambique was always present. The last time it went, tells, visited and cleaned the family campaign, "there at Machamba". "It's a Chinese custom," he explained.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 02:46:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Entrepreneurship | Event for local companies wants to capture “angel investors”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/16/empreendedorismo-evento-para-empresas-locais-quer-captar-investidores-anjo/</link><description>Macau today hosts an event designed to capture the so -called “angel investors” for local entrepreneurship projects. Macao Angel Investor Network takes place at “The Macao Young Entrepreneur Incubation Center” and aims to support emerging business projects or simply startups that are taking the first steps
 
It's called “Macau Angel Investor Network”, anything like “Angel Investor Network in Macao” and aims to bring residents closer who want to be successful entrepreneurs and create their own business in an economy that wants to diverse. The event is scheduled for today at Hengqin Development Center, at 517 Avenida da Praia Grande, Nam Tung commercial building, between 11h and 12h30, and has several personalities linked to the local economy, but not only. They are Raphael Chan, Deputy Director of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Paulo Andrez, Emeritus President of the “European Business Angel Network” and also figures such as Emanuel Soares, Legal Consultant, U Man Fai, angel investor for the Great Bay and Founder/founder of “Esenia Fund” and even Ung Choi Kun, former deputy to the Legislative Assembly and president of Kun Cheong Holding Ltd and also an “angel investor”. The event is developed by the Association for Entrepreneurship and Innovation for Macao, China and Portuguese-speaking countries, which is linked Marco Duarte Rizzolio, being co-organized by the Macao Sino-Buspone Platform Association for sustainable development.
To HM, this explained the main objectives that are behind this initiative. "We want to connect an angel investors to startups and small and medium enterprises (SMEs), fostering the entrepreneurial ecosystem and promoting the economic diversification of Macao." In turn, Alvin Fong, also linked to the organization of this event and president of Direch International, argued that it is intended to “create a platform that brings together knowledge about angel investments, helping in the diversification of Macao's economy”.
According to Rizzolio, "Investors Angel, who invest capital in emerging companies, are fundamental to support startups in early stages where financing possibilities are more scarce in the traditional financial sector."
“In addition,” he said, the contact network that now runs on Praia Grande Avenue “seeks to bring investors closer to Portuguese -speaking and China countries, creating mutual access to the best projects developed in these regions and reinforcing Macao as a strategic link between the East and the West”.
For Alvin Fong, this is the "opportune moment" for the holding of such an event, given that "the world is going through many changes and new opportunities are emerging."
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, in Macao have already occurred in previous events in an attempt to capture angel investments, "but this is the first time it is intended to create a" Business Angels "network in Macao with Chinese investors and Portuguese -speaking countries."
"The conditions to hold this event now arise from various factors, such as the rapid growth of innovation and technology, the greater digitization and the use of software in business, the need to diversify the local economy, the growing focus on the great bay as a pole of innovation," he said.
At issue, there are also factors such as “the joint effort of public and private entities in creating an environment favorable to entrepreneurship”, something that has been greatly enhanced by the pandemic years, defended, having brought Macao and the authorities “a new understanding of the importance of supporting local and regional businesses, making this moment particularly strategic”.
Who is who
For today's session were invited “Successful Entrepreneurs and Entrepreneurs, some of whom are leaders in their areas”, and their “experience and intelligence add a lot to this event,” said Alvin Fong.
Already Marco Duarte Rizzolio, stressed that will be present "people interested in technology and innovation, including some angel investors, representatives of risk capital funds, renowned entrepreneurs and specialists in innovation and business development."
Today's session is an “opportunity to obtain valuable knowledge and expand the network of contacts”, and Marco Duarte Rizzo highlights personalities such as Paulo Andrez, “recognized international expert in entrepreneurship, innovation and angel investment”, or Ung Choi Kun, “prominent figure in Macao in real estate and education sectors, and also an angel investor in several companies”.
Asked about the main areas in which this initiative is focused on, Rizzolio adds that the event is focused on “startups and SMEs that act on sectors such as technology, intelligent tourism, green economy, health, digital education, logistics or finance”, because they are “sectors with high growth potential and that are aligned in local needs”, namely in the “1+” economic diversification strategy or “1+4” strategy global trends ”.
"We want to identify innovative companies that can thrive not only in Macau, but also in the big bay and in international markets," added this official who is also linked to the organization of the startup and entrepreneurship contest, the "929 Challenge".
Right moment
For Alvin Fong, Macao currently presents potentialities for the connection of business projects to the cities of the Great Bay, all located in Guangdong Province.
"Macau has a lot of freedom and flexibility to experience new ideas. In addition, we have received many tourists from around the world. Being one of GBA's eleven cities, Macau is, in fact, an excellent platform," he said. In turn, Marco Duarte Rizzolio speaks of “unique characteristics” of the territory, “like their position as a bridge between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, a stable regulatory environment and tax and financial incentives that can attract investors and startups”.
There is also “the increase in the focus on the diversification of the economy beyond the game sector”, verifying “a fertile ground for innovation and new business”.
"In a global scenario of low interest rates, capital markets with some geopolitical friction, investment in technology has presented multiple incomparable from other assets. In this context, the creation of more financial incentives and the strengthening of startup support programs are crucial steps," said the event co-creator.
Great competition
Despite the potential, the challenges persist, given that “Macao does not have many advantages beyond the game sector,” there is “intense competition in the big bay,” warned Alvin Fong.
For Marco Duarte Rizzolio "Challenges are significant," because "the transition from an economy so dependent on the game sector to a more diverse model takes time and requires coordinated efforts."
It is also necessary to take into account the opportunities that arise with the integration of MSar on Hengqin Island, said Rizzolio, who recalls, however, “the challenges related to competitiveness and regulatory adaptation”.
"In addition, housing and commercial remodeling requires balance between economic growth and the preservation of local social fabric. It is essential to create policies that encourage entrepreneurship and investment, minimizing the negative impacts of these transformations," he said.
Asked whether the authorities have been enough to capture angel investors, both argue that there is more work to do. "This is a good start, but more can be done in the future," said Alvin Fong.
Already Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said that "the Government of MSAR has made important efforts", as well as mentioning "several times the need to create a" Business Angels "network."
“Macau has supported many initiatives that aim to stimulate investment. It is true that the creation of more financial incentives and the strengthening of startup support programs are crucial steps. It is also necessary to promote Macau more actively as an attractive destination for investors, highlighting its competitive advantages on the international scene. This event is an example of good collaboration between the public and private sector to stimulate ecosystem,” said Rizzolio.
Also noteworthy is that today's close connection with 369, an entity that aims to become “an international hub of science and technology in Macau, giving new generations a greater stage of exploration” of opportunities, ”said Alvin Fong, president of this entity. Marco Duarte Rizzolio stressed that we are facing “an incubator of the Macao ecosystem that has organized several events”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>June 10 | Alexandre Leitão highlights the end of the waiting lists at the Consulate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/11/10-de-junho-alexandre-leitao-destaca-fim-das-listas-de-espera-no-consulado/</link><description>Yesterday was held at the consular residence in Bela Vista, the usual celebration ceremony of June 10-Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese Communities. Alexandre Leitão, Consul, highlighted the end of the waiting lists in the consulate and the modernization of some services, noting that Portugal is ready to promote stronger economic ties with the MSAR
 
After years when renewing the citizen card or passport could be a small major problem for Portuguese citizens to reside in the MSAR, since this subject seems to be solved. Alexandre Leitão, Portuguese consul-general in Macao and Hong Kong, proved yesterday to be a satisfied man to talk about the last achievements achieved in the operation of the Portuguese Consulate-General in Macau and Hong Kong, this regards the June 10th, Portugal, Camões and Portuguese Communities celebrations.
"After two years of intense concentration in the normalization of consular services, we eliminated waiting lists in the field of issuing citizen cards and passports," he said.
According to Alexandre Leitão, "users have returned access to 90 percent of services without prior appointment, we introduced electronic payment, we drastically reduce response and referral times after the admission of processes, and reorganize human resources and procedures."
The consul did not forget the consulate's team, "which is constituted, almost in full, by macanese who have positively reacted to the successive challenges that have been presented to them," also noting that "in 15 months were issued or renewed 55,000 citizen cards and passports, which also demonstrates the size of the Portuguese community of Macau and Hong Kong."
Portugal with value
Thus, the official said he could “safely say that the essential, from the strictly consular point of view, is done”, but intends to bet on the “deepening of Portugal's diplomatic, economic and cultural relations with the special administrative regions” of Macau and Hong Kong.
Addressing the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, Alexandre Leitão recalled that the ruler “has defended the acceleration of the opening and diversification of the economy” and that from this point of view Portugal has a privileged role to fulfill.
"Portugal has the same purpose, which makes us, once again, bridged in a common purpose: to grow and diversify our economies, internationalizing them for the benefit of our peoples. Portuguese companies are prepared to take advantage of the" most open and inclusive posture to intensify international ties and increase global projection and attractiveness and the renowned Macao as an international metropolis "," Since, they are aware of the contribution of Portuguese companies and workers to the growth and quality of Macao economy services ”.
The consul was still clear in saying Sam Hou Fai that "he can count on the Portuguese community to actively participate in the ambitious design of economic diversification of MSAR."
Alexandre Leitão did not forget the last major Chinese investment in Portugal, namely in Sines, by Calb - China Aviation Lithium Battery, being “the largest of the decade”, which “demonstrates the confidence of the large Chinese and the world's quality and capacity of Portugal as an investment destination”.
Camões, the Great
Given that there are numerous celebrations of the 500th anniversary of the birth of Luís Vaz de Camões, Sam Hou Fai brought the Portuguese poet to his speech at yesterday's ceremony in Bela Vista. “The strong and deep historical ties between Portugal and Macau are already known to all, and are reflected on this day, because today is also celebrating the largest Portuguese poet who lived a few years in Macao and was part of the first moments of this historical meeting of two peoples.”
"It is never too much to remember that it is because of this centenary meeting of cultures, in this" outdoor window "of China, that the" uniqueness "of Macao arises as" the only place in the world whose official languages ​​", as expressly underlined by President XI Jinping," said the chief executive.
Sam Hou Fai has not yet forgotten the “commitment and commitment of the Government of MSA in the concentration of efforts to build a higher level opening platform”, as well as the “reinforcement of bilateral opening with Lusophony and promoting comprehensive mutual benefits cooperation that enriches and further widen the role and functions of Macao as a sino-illusion platform”.
The chief executive's words also referred to the defense “Macao's multicultural characteristics” and promoting “development in all strands, seeking to continually ensure and improve the well-being of all residents of Macao, including Portuguese communities in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-11 02:30:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Casinos | Government says that closing impact will be controlled</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/casinos-satelite-governo-diz-que-impacto-de-encerramento-sera-controlado/</link><description>It is official: the 11 satellite casinos will even end the doors until December 31 this year, and Melco and the Macao Game Society have already announced the restructuring plans. Regarding the affected workers, the government presents numbers lower than those already mentioned by deputies and associations: 5,600. An impact on SMEs is still expected, but without a major consequence for banks
 
After much speculation, here is finally the authorities and operators have announced what will actually happen to the 11 satellite casinos operated in the territory. They all will close, and the Macau Game Society (SJM) Resorts and Melco have already defined the plans for what follows [see secondary text], which includes acquisitions of L'ARC and Bridge 16, as well as the transfer of workers and game machines.
The executive presented yesterday, at a press conference, numbers of workers affected with the closing of the satellite casinos below those already referred to by sector associations. It will, after all, will be 5,600 and no more than ten thousand as some deputies said to these entities, and from this cake, 4,800 workers were directly hired by the operators of the game, so if the satellite casino, they can be integrated into their paintings. The rest, 800, were contracted directly by the satellite casinos themselves. There are still 400 non -resident workers (TNR) involved in this process. With regard to Mocha Clubs, 300 local workers and 50 TNR.
Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, said that "the data were collected by different means", but that the government calculations "are official". "As the other means came to this data, I don't know," he added.
Asked about the support of these 800 workers, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, explained that "the owners of the satellite casinos have the responsibility to ensure the work relationship of these people."
"In the case of the 4,800 hired by the dealers, such as Croupiers or Treasury Employees, they can return to work in these dealers' casinos. In relation to 800, the concessionaires have guaranteed the government that if they have employment problems they can absorb them and provide adequate jobs on the properties of the dealers," he said.
Representative Song Pek Kei even talked about the possibility of about 15,000 unemployed, while Nick Law, in a plenary intervention, said that among the satellite casinos and associated stores, there were "13,500 workers", representing "4.6 percent of the total macao work force".
POSSIBILITY OF CONVERSION
Regarding small and medium-sized companies (SMEs) located in the neighborhoods that will no longer have these satellite casinos, namely in areas such as the Inner Port, Zape, Nape or Fishermen's Dock, the government predicts some impact but controlled. There are, in total, 320 stores that operate in the vicinity with 800 workers, and “about 400 workers will have another employment situation according to the reconversion of stores,” said Secretary Tai Kin IP.
Essentially, and after the government's surveys, half of the 320 stores "will be affected directly by the satellite casinos closure, such as the pledge houses, mobile phones, restaurants and jewelery." However, Tai Kin IP pointed out that there will be others that will not have a great impact on depending on sales to residents.
Above all, the ruler pointed out that this scenario may even constitute an opportunity. "It will be a challenge and an opportunity for the reconversion of stores. Traditional stores that have a close relationship with satellite casinos customers have to reconvert.
Highlight that Hospitality Consultant Savills referred in March that the satellite casinos closure would devalue the hotels in 60 percent and cause more non-compliance with the SMEs, with bank credit obligations valued between 25 and 39 billion.
Tai Kin IP devalued this scenario. “From the knowledge we have, the loans granted to satellite casinos involve less than 1 percent of all bank loan activity, and we find that the risks are very limited to the operation of banks. In terms of risk supervision indicators in the financial industry, such as capital flow and others, banks' behavior will be safe and stable.”
Regarding the SMEs, Tai Kin IP said that the monetary and currency of Macao is “closely monitoring the situation with the banks to mitigate the recovery of customers”, and the secretary in advance that in April, “ten billion patacas were injected to loans to the SMEs, attenuating their pressures”.
Asked about the timing of these measures, André Cheong said it is the right time. "It all depends on the dealerships' decisions and we now officially receive the decision. This is a problem that has to do with several casinos and a considerable number of workers, and we did not want that only at the end of the year they knew about their situation. With six months to finish the transition period we understand that this is the indicated phase to advertise," he said.
No impact on recipes
Given the budgetary revision for this year with 12 billion Patacas in the forecast of game revenues, André Cheong assured that the satellite casinos closure will not have a major impact on the overview of revenues.
"We made the budgetary review with less 12 billion patacas due to lack of consumption. We believe that the closure of satellite casinos does not have great impact on the game's recipes," he said.
The secretary also stressed that, regarding the intention of SJM Resorts to purchase the enterprises Ponte 16 and L'ARC, the concessionaire "has to complete this acquisition procedure until December 31, and if they cannot buy these satellite casinos [who operate in the projects] have to end."</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 23:32:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Satellite Casinos | Suggested new projects to attract tourists to Zape</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/casinos-satelite-sugeridos-novos-projectos-para-atrair-turistas-ao-zape/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) suggested, in a meeting with representatives of the Zape hotel sector, that this zone can integrate more intellectual property projects and initiatives, such as large facilities or dolls, to attract tourists.
This meeting took place on Friday and had as context the discussion of measures to deal with the satellite casinos closure by the end of the year. According to a note, STD also wants to promote “the extent of the economic benefits of concerts, the proper use of spaces for the accomplishment of activities and the optimization of the zone environment, among others”, and the exploration of “new sources of visitors” was suggested.
Entrepreneurs were also advised to launch “complementary tourist products or accommodation promotions”. Representatives of the hotel and tourist sectors “have generally agreed with preliminary measures defined by the government,” the same note describes. Zape has over 20 hotels of different types and categories.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:12:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | Ella Law and Leong Sun Iok lead the list of workers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/eleicoes-ella-lei-e-leong-sun-iok-lideram-lista-dos-operarios/</link><description>Representative Ella Lei Cheng I and Deputy Leong Sun IOK are the Union's heads for development, a candidacy linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom), in the upcoming direct elections for the Legis' Assembly.
The names were presented on Friday and include in the third place Cheng Ka Man, which given the small number of lists could join the Legislative Assembly. The list of 12 names is also made up of Wu Hang San, Chan Ka Keng, Kuong Chi Fong, Chio Lan Ieng, Leong Meng Ian, Lao Ka Chong, Chan Hon Sam, Chan Chio I and Un hi Mou.
The publication of the list also shows that Chan U, current deputy of Faom, should leave the hemiciclo, as he is not on the list of indirect suffrage, was not part of the list of direct suffrage. The possibility of law staying in the hemiciclo now goes through a possible appointment of the chief executive.
In statements cited by the newspaper or Mun, Ella Law has promised that the list will continue to hear the opinions of the population and that it will transmit faithfully and true the aspirations of the population to the government, to guarantee the rights and interests of residents.
As part of the political project, the head and deputy since 2014 has defended the diversification of the economy, but stated that it has to promote the improvement of the well-being of the population and the creation of jobs for residents.
Ella Lei also left the hope that the list can contribute to improving the health, education system and developing support for the elderly population.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:07:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | Song Pek Kei leads Fujian community list</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/eleicoes-song-pek-kei-lidera-lista-da-comunidade-de-fujian/</link><description>Deputy Song Pek Kei will be the head of the Macao United Citizens Association, linked to the Fujian community and businessman Chan Meng Kam. The information was released on Friday, with the name of the 12 candidates.
The main change against 2021 is the departure of Si Ka Lon, which although this will be maintained as a deputy, with the election of indirect suffrage practically guaranteed.
Second on the list comes Nick Leong Wong, currently deputy, followed by Chan Lai Kei and Loi Si Weng. The list of 10 candidates also includes NG Hong Kei, Xu Zhiwei, Tong Ho Laam, Chan Ian Ian, Wang Guanxun and Winny NG.
At the time of the list delivery, Song Pek Kei said the list has been serving society for 20 years and is committed to continuing the mission. The deputy also pointed out that the list will seek to serve the population, based on the reality of the facts, and deal with various aspects of society to build a better macao for the population.
In terms of intervention areas in the Legislative Assembly, Song promised to focus six main points: national security, economic diversification, living conditions, employment security, administrative efficiency and urban renewal. Song also stated that he has a young list, with the average ages around 33.
Chan Meng Kam and Ung Choi Koi, entrepreneurs and former deputy elected by this list, were present at the time of the names of the list. The Macao United Citizens Association was the big winner of the elections in 2021, with a total of 26,599 votes, in the one that was the least participated election since the establishment of the MSAR.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:05:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | After 35 years, Kou Hoi In is in the process of leaving al</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/eleicoes-apos-35-anos-kou-hoi-in-esta-em-vias-de-deixar-a-al/</link><description>In addition to Kou Hou in, they may still be out of exit Chui Sa Cheong and Vong Hin Fai. In the opposite direction, they enter the lists of the indirect suffrage Kevin Ho, Vong Hou Piu and Wong Chon. IAU TENG PIO AND SI KA LON ALSO join the indirect suffrage
 
The current President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, is out of the lists of the elections for indirect suffrage and should be left out of Hemiciclo for the first time since 1991. Kou maintenance in Parliament now depends on a possible appointment by Sam Hou Fai, chief executive.
In recent years, the entrepreneur has always been elected by the list of Macau business interests, but is not on the list of candidates, such as Wang Sai, who had been elected deputy for the first time in 2021.
In the opposite direction, Edmund Ho's businessman and nephew, Kevin Ho starts to join the list, which practically guarantees him the election. For this list it also enters Si Ka Lon, deputy since 2013, elected by direct suffrage on the lists of the Fujian community, linked to businessman Chan Meng Kam. This time, if Ka Lon applies to Al through the indirect suffrage. Kevin Ho and Si Ka Lon are also deputies by Macau to the National People's Assembly.
Regarding 2021, the union of Macau business interests maintains in the lists José Chui Sai Peng, businessman, and IP Sio Kai, vice president of the Banco da China Macao branch. These two candidates, as well as Kevin Ho and Si Ka Lon, have the election confirmed, given that in the industrial, commercial and financial sectors there is only one list for four places. The only obstacle to the election would be a lead to the candidacies of the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) or the State Security Defense Commission.
During the delivery of the list, Chui Sai Peng, cousin of former Chief Executive Fernando Chui Sai On, said, quoted by the newspaper or Mun, that the purpose of the list is to contribute to improving the business environment in Macao, and reinforcing the development of the economy.
More changes
The expected changes at the Legislative Assembly are not for the industrial, commercial and financial sectors, also in the professional sector there are changes, Chui Sai Cheong, Al, Vong Hin Fai, President of the Macao Lawyers Association, and Chan Iek Lap are out of the Macao Professional Interests list.
The doctor had revealed in February last year that he was leaving. However, in relation to Chui Sai Cheong and Vong Hin Fai there was no such indication. However, these deputies may be appointed by the Chief Executive. Vong Hin Fai and Chan Iek Lap will be replaced by Vong Hou Piu, Accountant and Wong Chon, doctor.
The list is now led Iau Teng Pio, lawyer and academic, who was so far in the Legislative Assembly by appointment of the Chief Executive. Speaking cited by the newspaper or Mun, Iau Teng Pio stated that the list in an objective "to develop the primacy of the law" and "achieve common progress in industry."</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:03:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Visit | Sam Hou Fai in the Great Bay</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/visita-sam-hou-fai-na-grande-baia/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai, head of the Executive of MSAR, has been holding from yesterday and until tomorrow, an official visit to six cities in the Great Bay, namely Shenzhen, Huizhou, Dongguan, Canton, Zhaoqing and Foshan.
According to an official statement, this visit "comes in the head of the Chief Executive, last April, to the three cities of the Great Bay, namely Zhuhai, Zhongshan and Jiangmen", and in this stay the ruler will have meetings "with the leaders of the six cities" in order to "change ideas in a deepened way on the continuous boost's development, the reinforcement of benefits with cooperation with benefits. mutual, among other themes ”.
The travel program also includes "visits to developments under development and their companies in the areas of technological innovation, energy resources, among others, in order to know the development situation of the important industries of those cities." During the absence of Sam Hou Fai, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, acts interimly the functions of Chief Executive.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 02:54:23</pubDate></item><item><title>PATANE MARKET | CE hears complaints from traders</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/mercado-do-patane-ce-ouve-queixas-de-comerciantes/</link><description>The chief executive visited several neighborhoods of Macau, including Fai Chi Kei, Ilha Verde and the Canidroma Zone. In the Patane market, Sam Hou Fai heard complaints of bad business and promised to find solutions together with society. In addition, it revealed that the possibility of connecting Qingmao is being studied to Fai Chi Kei through the light meter
 
The chief executive made a journey through the Macau Peninsula on Saturday, visiting several neighborhoods accompanied by secretaries of his executive. Sam Hou Fai went to the Patane market, the Ilha Verde neighborhood and the Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, “to find out about the business exploration environment, as well as visited the former Yat Yuen canhydrome” to learn about the construction work of the Sports Park.
In the Patane Municipal Market, the government leader hear traders who complained about the lack of customers and weak sales. “We are living very difficult times. We can only earn 200 or 300 patacas a day, although market income is low, we can't cover expenses. If you can not solve [the problem], how can we solve?” Asked a merchant from a fresh product sales board. Sam Hou Fai pointed to cooperation. “Let's work together to solve the problem,” replied the ruler.
The saleswoman returned to the cargo and argued that online consumer habits razed the traditional trade. "Now residents do not shop in stores. After the pandemic, they only do online shopping," warned residents. "We can't close the internet, this is impossible," he replied between laughs Sam Hou Fai, commenting that "things have changed a lot." “Let's work together to try to solve the problems,” insisted the chief executive.
The banking merchant next to the answer to how the businesses went to the same scenario. "The business is still difficult, it is true. The lives of residents are becoming increasingly difficult. We hope that with their leadership, the market environment can be optimized," he said. Sam Hou Fai replied that this was also his desire.
Reinforcement of supports
The chief executive also visited the Patane Food Center, where he spoke to residents and tourists. Sam Hou Fai encouraged traders to "constantly implement news to explore characteristics that attract more visitors."
After passing through Patane, the entourage led by the chief executive went to Ilha Verde, Fai Chi Kei and surroundings, accompanied by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP. Some traders have asked Sam Hou Fai a new round of consumption prize to improve business.
The Chief Executive also took the opportunity to visit the “Sanrio Character Dream Garden”, and the Feliz of Love Pavilion for the Homeland of the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services, where he interacted with students.
Regarding the “Garden of Dreams”, Tai Kin IP said that in about 80 days, the initiative “managed to divert more than 240 thousand visitors to the social neighborhood”.
Finally, Sam Hou Fai visited the land of the former Yat Yuen Caniderom where the construction of a sports park is planned and was known the situation of the work, listening to a presentation of the secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam. The chief executive said that the “public contest of works for the first zone is scheduled to soon”.
Regarding the traffic of the adjacent zones, Sam Hou Fai revealed that the works for the eastern line of the Light Metro that connects the northern part of the city to the Taipa result at a good pace. The ruler revealed that his executive "is studying the possibility of extending the line of the slight meter from the Qingmao border post to the Fai Chi Kei neighborhood, as well as the future sports park."</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 02:51:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Government admits to increase cautions paid by travel agencies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/governo-admite-aumentar-caucoes-pagas-pelas-agencias-de-viagem/</link><description>Helena de Senna Fernandes, director of the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), said yesterday at the Legislative Assembly (AL) that there may be an increase in the value of the security to be presented by travel agencies in the scope of the licensing of the activity. The guarantee was given in the debate on the vote, in the specialty, of the new law of activity of travel agencies and the profession of tourist guide, approved yesterday in Hemiciclo.
"We have the model of security and liability insurance, which is equal to the interior of China. We will consider whether or not it is necessary to raise the amount of the deposit and perhaps there will be a slight adjustment, but I think it will not be a very large increase," said Helena de Senna Fernandes.
This information arose about the intervention of Deputy José Pereira Coutinho, who suggested a change to the model composed of the payment of security and liability insurance associated with trips that are not paid by the travelers, and which is treated under the licensing process of agencies.
“In Hong Kong there is a compensation fund, and in Portugal there is the Travel and Tourism Guarantee Fund. For years we use the model of security and liability insurance, there is a way to change it?” Asked the deputy. According to the Portuguese Tourism Portal, this fund “responds jointly and severally liable for the payment of the credits of travelers arising from the breach of services contracted to travel agencies”.
Helena de Senna Fernandes explained that, in the case of Hong Kong, the fund is supported with a percentage of the commissions charged on the excursions, and in both territories, "in terms of the number of tourists, it is very different."
No permanent licenses
Another of the points addressed by the deputies, it concerns the fact that the agencies have to renew their license annually. Coutinho suggested a permanent license, but the government understands that it is up to the companies to decide according to the market panorama.
"The sector is always changing, and with regard to agencies there are some that have more or less activity. We have to know what their situation is like, so we put a period of one year for license renewal," he explained.
Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, stated that “it has to do with its will” the continuity, or not, of the business by the agencies. "We have electronic services for license renewal, which greatly makes your life much easier, but agencies have to express their willingness to renew," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 07:07:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Neonazis would kill the President of the Republic, António Costa and Gouveia and Melo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/neonazis-iam-matar-o-presidente-da-republica-antonio-costa-e-gouveia-e-melo/</link><description>Guessed. The increase in violent actions of neo -Nazi groups in Portugal and the continuous discourse of incitement to hatred on social networks is to worry populations and judicial authorities to make a bomb of amazement and informative concern. The judicial police had been controlling since 2020 certain neo -Nazis groups and last week owned several elements of a group that had over 900 elements. The detainees are suspected of integrating the so -called Lusitanian Armillary Movement (evil), which already has an armed militia.
After searches of surprise from certain properties suspected of belonging to this neo-Nazi group, several weapons were found, some of 3D system war, as well as Soqueiras, large knives, Nazi propaganda, and very serious documentation that indicates that the group was preparing to kill President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, former Prime Minister António Costa and presidential candidate Almirante Gouveia and Melo and Melo and Assembly of the Republic with armed violence. Eight members of the Neonazi Group have already been arrested including a PSP head that operated at the Lisbon Municipal Police and several PSP agents and GNR military, who belonged to the group and raised young people to the group. Among the many members of the group is the father of the arrival deputy, Rita Matias. The facts are very serious. Constitutional law itself is concerned because we talk about crime and terrorism, not a simple political position.
Secret Services and Judicial Police have already detected 11 neo -Nazi organizations in Portugal. None of this appears by chance. On social networks, namely in the Telegram network, there is a discourse of hatred and xenophobia by the Elements of the arrival and neonazis, which has given strength to which most radical movements of the far right can lead to acts of violence essentially against African and Asian immigrants. This time, the Judicial Police already have very serious elements of terrorist actions that were planned soon. Neo -Nazism is a sad reality in Portugal that is coming to plans of high criminal violence. And nothing happens by chance. When we watched the radical, xenophobic and racist politician André Ventura to instill in public opinion a speech against Gypsy communities and immigrants, obviously that neonazis feel that this discourse is favorable to terrorist action.
On the 10th of Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities, the illustrious and nationally and internationally awarded writer Lídia Jorge, as coordinator of the ceremonies, gave a speech of great depth and realism regarding our history of centuries, as the President of the Republic must have given his best discourse of his two mandates, having pointed out that we are all clear against discrimination, in a clear reference against discrimination, in a clear reference that we are all clear against discrimination, in a clear reference against discrimination that we are all Portuguese defend against immigrants.
And what happened next? André Ventura came to public with absolutely offensive statements to Lídia Jorge and Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, and not only. The Leader of the arrival stated that "Lídia Jorge and the President of the Republic betrayed the name of Portugal". What's more, "José Luís Carneiro gives pity when he appears on television. I feel like going there and telling the man:" Listen, friend. The country has not been the same as 40 or 30 years ago. " What's more, "if the constitutional revision does not advance shows me that the prime minister is hostage, he is kidnapped, is stuck with the same interests and to the same collusion that the PS has always been."
Now, who calls traitor to the President of the Republic is not reflecting a speech of hatred before those who hear it? Isn't it instilling forces to more radical groups? When Ventura says that the country today is not like 40 or 30 years ago, of course not, today we have at least 11 terrorist neo -Nazi organizations, of which elements of PSP, GNR and relatives of deputies of the André Ventura party are part. Crimes of incitement to hatred and violence have increased more than 200 percent in the last five years.
The situation regarding these neo -Nazi groups is severe. Democrats are worried. The list that the Judiciary Police seized where individualities to kill is not small. Only the intention to propose to kill personalities that have been given to their country, including freedom on April 25, 1974, is already very serious. And why do we speak in freedom? Because in the referred list are also part of Captains of April.
Judicial authorities can no longer be contemplated by such organizations and serious statements given by certain politicians who only aim to increase their will to the neo -Nazis to get out of the den, as in many violent cases they have done so. The trendy justice reform also has to include the building of special prisons where fascists can be placed convicted of criminal or terrorist activity.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:43:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/rezar-por-macau/</link><description>In 2007 Pope Benedict XVI established the tradition of praying for the Catholic Church of China on May 24. On June 24, the day is celebrated when the residents of Macao repelled, in 1622, the Dutch invaders and all those who love the city should also pray for it, as in Macao there were too many unpleasant incidents lately.
Bishop Stephen Lee Bun-Ssang of the Diocese of Macau wrote a pastoral letter to be read during Pentecost Sunday, which this year was celebrated on June 8, where he declared, “recently, there were several suicides and several suicide attempts in Macao. According to health services, 18 suicides were recorded in the first trimester of 2025, which evidences the urgent need for Taking measures to solve the problem. These tragedies not only bring deep pain to family members, but they also shake us all. lonely ».
Unfortunately, in early May, other suicides were even more registered. The fact that they were not publicly disclosed does not mean that the tragedies did not happen. Ultimately, we release ourselves from the current depressing social atmosphere is the most effective path and, for that, we need to pray!
The administrative measure that requires a person to live in Macau at least during 183 to benefit from the pecuniary reimbursement plan for economic development for the year 2025 also affected some residents who are outside the city, especially those living in Hong Kong, a city that is part of the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay. I noticed that there are in fact several opinions regarding the necessary conditions to benefit from this plan. The requirement of 183 days of permanence is not a problem in itself; The fundamental question lies in the calendar of its implementation. Last year, before the term of his mandate, former Ho Iat Seng Chief Executive announced that the pecuniary reimbursement plan for economic development for the year 2025 would not be changed, which citizens faced as good news. However, when the plan was implemented this year, the condition that determines the need to have remained in Macao in 2024, at least for 183 days, was added, which deprived some residents living outside the possibility of achieving this goal.
If this measure had only had an effect from 2026, I believe it would have been less controversial and that the disagreements it caused among the residents would have been reduced. For some people, the amount of 10,000 patacas may seem insignificant, but for the very needy, especially the elders, no longer entitled to receive this value can be quite devastating. If the social atmosphere were a little more harmonious, there would be less tragedies. For this to happen, we need to pray!
There are still a lot for which we have to pray. In 2022, the Legislative Assembly changed the “legal regime for the exploration of casino fortune or unlucky games”, which had a negative impact on the situation of the “satellite casinos” so most will close by the end of the year. I wonder what will be of the 4,800 employees of the game companies that work in the "satellite casinos". The doubt is and if they can maintain their current level of income or if their lives will be affected. The future of the 800 who worked on the "satellite casinos" but were not employees of the game companies, and the staff of the stores located around the satellite casinos also raises concern and it is not known if they will have any guarantee of subsistence. On the 17th, some journalists were prevented from entering the Legislative Assembly and covering the work session, an unusual event for members of the press. The subsistence of Macao residents and the maintenance of press freedom is equally important, so we pray for them!
On June 24, 1622, the residents of Macao, who fought with all their strength to repel the Dutch forces, will certainly have prayed during the resistance!</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 07:05:46</pubDate></item><item><title>The door of the stars (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/19/a-porta-das-estrelas-ii/</link><description>“The Increase of Artificial Intelligence Mega Sites Or Mega Cities Will Increase The Earth's Temperature By 2 ° BECAUSE of the Need for the Energy Input for Function. If's True Thes We Have Already Gone Beyond The Danger Point.”
George Lowells
However, to understand the viability of the operation and its impacts, it is necessary to proceed to two consideration orders. From the financial point of view, some doubts begin to arise. At this time, Softbank and OpenAi appear to be willing to invest nominel millions of dollars each in the project, with the support of Oracle's seven billion dollars and many others from MGX.
In total, we are talking about fifty -two billion dollars, that is, just over half of what was announced. Altman and Masa can't do much more. OpenAi's business model, which basically foresees reinvesting everything, prevents ChatgPT's mother company from having huge liquidity reserves to invest in the project. Likewise, according to the September 2024 balance, Softbank's cash flow ascends to the 'only twenty -five billion dollars, insufficient to reach the fixed quota. These problems exist, but they are somehow solutionable.
Firstly, the new joint venture legitimized by the president will have no problem resorting to credit. And in any case, the door to new investments by a limited number of partners remains open, especially at a time when Trump promised to strive to stimulate them, simplifying the bureaucratic process and getting rid of Biden's regulations. But the most problematic issue concerns the internal balances of the American technological world and the way the president intends to regulate, obviously informally, the relations between the great actors of the sector. The star door seems, in fact, to have been made as OpenAi. Altman's goal a few months ago was to ensure simpler and more immediate access to the data, computing capacity and the physical infrastructure needed to train their AI models.
Stargate responds to all these problems, as OpenAi can now count on Oracle's cloud (not just Microsoft), investments in joint venture computing capacity and the colossal data centers that will be built. As an anonymous source told Financial Times. 'Stargate's intention is not to provide data centers to the world.
Everything revolves around OpenAi. In addition, still at hardware level, ARM's presence at Joint Venture signals Masa's desire to offer the company that specializes in chips, of which it is the main investor, an ecosystem in which it grows. At the moment, ARM is mainly concerned with the chip design, but the masa plan is to integrate it with the Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company (TSMC) with which it has excellent relationships to create an alternative to Nvidia. To do this, obviously, it takes a lot of money. At the moment, Sofbank does not have this money but Stargate also fits that, especially if the project picks up and Nvidia has trouble delivering the necessary graphics boards.
The ties between Masa and Altman are narrow, because they both share the same problem in AI's value chain, that is, the 'bottleneck' consisting of Jensen Huang's company and its essentially monopolistic position. And the two Stargate stars have excellent arguments to convince Donald Trump of the need to invest in a company that can compete with Nvidia, as in 2024 Jensen did business with China worth about 10 billion dollars.
It's not just business. But despite the Chinese warning, Trump's choice to rely on Masa and Altman by offering them obvious industrial advantages is not politically neutral. However, it has a logic that we can understand if we widen our gaze and try to understand how the president is distributing burdens and honors within the American technological world. Premise, as pointed out by Trump in his inauguration speech, the two sectors who will receive more attention from the technological policy of their administration are space and AI.
And, observing the president's first movements, he immediately jumps in sight that no actor dealing with spatial issues has received a role in Stargate. Musk, who developed an AI model called Explainable Artificial Intelligence (Xai), was left out. Even bezos that with Amazon Web Services (AWS) which is one of the main suppliers of this service was not considered. The same goes for those with social networks and therefore is able to influence public opinion. For Elon, it is worth what was said earlier, while Zuckerberg is more encouraged to turn the goal into a super app like Wechat, obviously without content moderation.
Paypal Mafia will continue to traffic IA with regard to defense -related issues, but will remain out of Stargate's dynamics although it remains potentially to invest in OpenAi, as Peter Thiel did through its Founders Fund in 2023. Trump's goal is, in short, evident. Assign to each technological actor one or more niches, but prevents a dominant figure from exerting too many strategic sectors (AI, social networks, space).
(Continues)</description><pubDate>2025-06-19 00:18:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Michael Hui (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/17/michael-hui-ii/</link><description>Last week, we analyzed the determining factors in the success of Michael Koon-Man's films (許冠文). Michael has been a film star of the last 50 years. Since 1977. A person who dedicates 50 years to a career has demonstrated dedication, enthusiasm and recognition for his profession.
Michael also understands the difference between the thinking of the oldest generation and the latest generation and used this knowledge to entertain audiences. The dialogue about love in the “Talk Show 2005 ″ is an example of this. Today, we will continue to explore the factors of the success of Michael Koon-Man movies.
After the delivery ceremony of his doctorate Honoris Causa, Michael agreed to give an interview. He pointed out that he had studied sociology at the university, which allowed him to understand more deeply the influence films have on viewers. Good movies are a good influence and this is the social responsibility of cinema. Movies have to have a beneficial influence on society. As a film industry worker believes that films are not only used to benefit him financially but also to favor society. How could he do not do well?
If a person wants to succeed in their profession, it is indispensable to have vision. Michael sets the example of a meal to illustrate the current Hong Kong film market. If a restaurant serves a great meal, people in the city good will spend their money to taste it; Similarly, they spend their money to watch a good movie, and the latter, "The Last Dance," is certainly a good example. But if the movie has a vulgar brake, audiences won't spend your money to see it.
How do you make a good movie? One of the keys to success is the discovery of new topics. It is necessary to have the courage to choose to address a subject that has never been addressed and transform it into the argument of a movie. The theme of "The Last Dance" is a funeral. A mother who lost her son believes he can be resurrected and hires a funeral agent to wrap his body and hide it on Morgue. This behavior leads people to think that this mother is crazy in pain for the loss of her child, but also shows audiences that she is violating Chinese traditions; who argue that people must be buried in peace.
At another point in the film, the funeral agent who chairs the ceremony distributes to family members and friends present, dolls made similar to the deceased and miniatures of the sports cars of his choice, to relieve the heavy atmosphere of the funeral. Few films to date have addressed this theme, which makes it a novelty.
The protagonist "Hello Man" (Hello 文) of "The Last Dance" is an annoying character, but Michael said bluntly that the character makes people miss the previous generation, especially the figure of the traditional Chinese "father". Hello Man is a Taoist (道教傳人) and taught his son all the Taoist practices and rituals (道家) that must be performed in a funeral. His son disguised his reluctance to follow his father's footsteps and become a Taoist monk (道士), but because his son (Hello Man's grandson) wanted to attend a Catholic school, was baptized and became Catholic. After that, he left Hello Man, who had been paralyzed due to a stroke in Hong Kong and emigrated to Australia with his family, asking his sister to take account of his father alone. In the film, Hello Man represents the ancient generation that valued children more than daughters and does not accept religions from outside China. This is a mindset that the new generation does not accept. The film's argument illustrates the conflict between two generations simply and easy to understand, thus gaining the recognition of all and meeting the various sensitivities of the audiences.
Hearings can only be attracted to prestigious films and in which they recognize themselves. Only hong Kong successful movies have the opportunity to reach the international market and only then can the world see the cinema that is made in Hong Kong.
Next week, we will continue to analyze the elements that determined the success of Michael Koon-Man's movies.

Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-06-17 01:26:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Accepts Submissions for 2nd Short Festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/aceites-submissoes-para-2o-festival-de-curtas-metragens/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) and Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG) accept resident film submissions for the “2nd International Festival of Macao Shorts of Galaxy Entertainment Group”, namely for the “Macao Shorts” category.
According to a press release, it is intended, with this initiative, to “encourage local film production talents to build a base of local short films and expand opportunities for exchange and international collaboration”.
Submissions should be made by July 21, and the “Macao Award” and “Special Jury Prize” winners can receive a trophy and monetary prize of up to 45,000 patacas.
The second edition of this festival takes place in September in the Galaxy theaters, the Galaxy auditorium of the International Convention Center and the Andaz Hotel at Galaxy Macau, as well as at Cinemateca Paixão.
"A large event program will be presented, including an opening and projected ceremony, the" prominent director "section and lectures given by experts, movie themed workshops, an industry forum, as well as a closing and awarding ceremony and a red treadmill event."
By parts
The festival includes a total of five categories, and in addition to the “Macao Shorts”, the public will be able to watch films integrated in the sections “New Voices of the Horizon”, “Highlight Director”, “Vision of East Asia” and “Special Sessions”. The same note reports that “experienced filmmakers” were invited to join the jury. In the case of “Macao Shorts”, the choice will be made by the International Advisory Committee of the “International Macao Short Festival of Macao”.
The event regulation and registration forms can be discharged on the Electronic Page of the Cultural Institute or Macao's Cultural and Creative Industries. Candidates may deliver the duly completed registration form, along with the necessary materials in person in the building of the Cultural Institute.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:36:21</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Debate around the ICC Arbitral Tribunal takes place today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/frc-debate-em-torno-do-tribunal-arbitral-da-icc-decorre-hoje/</link><description>Integrated in the “reflections on the afternoon” cycle, today's conversation at the Rui Cunha Foundation revolves around the Arbitral Tribunal of the International Chamber of Commerce and the connection to the local legal community, with four interveners: Winnie Wat, Ana Coimbra Trigo, Mariana Esteves and Fatima Dermawan
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts today, from 6.30 pm, the “Arbitral Tribunal of the ICC Court: connecting to the legal community of Macao”, dedicated to discussing the International Court of Arbitration, as “world leader arbitral institution” and its connection to local reality.
According to a press release, “since 1923 [which this entity] has helped to resolve disputes in international commercial and investment disputes”, and the Court administers “arbitration exercising judicial supervision of arbitral procedures, ensuring the proper application of the 2021 arbitration rules and assisting the parties and referees”.
“These efforts are supported by the Court Secretariat, consisting of more than 100 lawyers and employees, operating in offices in Paris, New York, Sao Paulo, Singapore, Abu Dhabi and Hong Kong,” he says, and today's panel “aims to present to the Macao legal community the operation of the ICC International Arbitration Court [International Trade Chamber] to explain the role of the secretariat and the court in their arbitration services and ADR.
The debate also aims to present “an overview of the legal framework of arbitration in Macao and its latest developments”, and it serves the interest of “companies, internal and external lawyers, government officials, judges, teachers and students who are interested in learning about the ICC or participating in ICC arbitrations in the future, such as lawyers, experts or referees”.
The voices of reason
In these “reflections on the afternoon” participate Winnie Wat, deputy counselor of the Secretariat of the International Arbitration Chamber of Trade. He is accredited as a member of the Chartered Institute of Arbitators (FCIB) since 2021 and mediator of the Litigation Resolution Center (CEDR).
Also noteworthy is the participation of Ana Coimbra Trigo, senior associate in the area of ​​dispute resolution of the Portuguese Law Firm PLMJ Law Firm.
With 10 years of experience, he regularly participates as a lawyer and secretary of the Court in international and national arbitration and related legal proceedings, as well as other civil and commercial disputes, including postfusions and acquisitions, telecommunications, energy, aviation and real estate.
In addition, he is a member of the ICC International Arbitration Court for Macao and University Teacher.
Mariana Afonso Esteves, another of the speakers, has been a C&amp;C Advogados &amp; Notary senior lawyer since 2009. Its areas of action have encompassed litigation and dispute resolution, mediation and arbitration, game law, insurance, family law, as well as administrative and public law.
Fátima Dermawan is an assistant legal advisor at Game Operator Sands China, where he supervises the company's Litigation Department. Fatima has a degree in Law from the Faculty of Law of the New University of Lisbon and Master from the Harvard Law School, exercising law in Portugal since 2013, in Macao since 2016 and in the state of New York since 2020.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:33:49</pubDate></item><item><title>June 10 | New Film Show this weekend</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/10-de-junho-nova-mostra-de-cinema-este-fim-de-semana/</link><description>Still about the celebrations of June 10-Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities, Casa Garden hosts, from today, a Portuguese film cycle that includes the short film “Ice Merchants”, named for the Oscars. But there are also feature films to see, in a total of five sessions
 
Another year, another movie round. This is how summer is approaching and celebrates June 10 - Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese Communities. This time, the seventh edition of the “Portuguese Cinema Show in Macau” brings short and long films, in a diversity that has accustomed the local audience. The intention is to bring quality and award-winning films, standing out on this year's poster the short of animation “Ice Merchants”, which took the stage of the Oscars.
Organized by the Oriente Foundation, Portugal Film-Portuguese International Film Agency and the Indielisboa Festival-International Film Festival, among other entities, the show features a total of five sessions that perform throughout this weekend, ending on Sunday. The curatorship of the festival is in charge of Margarida Moz, director of Portugal Film.
According to a statement, what is intended with this show is “not only to show Portuguese films around the world, but also to make known the proper language of national cinematography and their agents”, including directors, actors, technical teams and producers. ”It is thus proposing to“ include the participation of creative agents in this show ”, is mentioned.
Today starts at 7 pm with Leonardo Mouramateus's movie “Greice”. It is a 1h10-minute movie that had a “strong international presence” last year and also this year, having premiered at the International Film Festival Rotterdam. "Greice" was screened at important film festivals such as Kino Pavasaris, Filmadrid and Transilvania Iff.
In Portugal, the film won the “Best Realization Award” at the Indielisboa Festival (2024), and in the Cinema-Curitiba International Festival (2024, Brazil) won three main awards, including “Best Film Film”.
Ice sellers
Tomorrow starts at Casa Garden at 5 pm with a special session, displaying the short film “Ice Merchants”, by João Gonzalez, which was selected for the 95th edition of the gym awards, ie the Oscars, namely for the “Best Animation Short Film” category, becoming the only Portuguese film to ever be named for this important initiative of world cinema.
This is followed by Carolina Rosendo's “A Solo”, a 16-minute movie made last year regarding the graduation of the director at the Lisbon School of Theater and Cinema. Carolina Rosendo's project won some international awards and was appointed by the Portuguese Cinema Academy for the “Sophia Student Prize” this year.
Also noteworthy is the display of “Atom &amp; Void”, by Gonçalo Almeida. This fiction short of fiction, just nine minutes long, debuted at Fantastic Fest (2024) in the US, where he won an “honorable mention” of the jury. In Europe, its debut took place at Sitges International Fantastic Film Festival of Catalonia (2024), one of the largest and most important fantastic film festivals in the world.
In Portugal, it was recently appointed by the Portuguese Academy of Cinema for the Sophia (2025) prizes in the category of “Fiction Short Film”.
Sensations and other stories
The poster of this film show is also made with “Percees”, by Alexandra Ramires and Laura Gonçalves, who explores the genres of animation and documentary, in just 12 minutes. This film was pre-selected for the 97th edition of this year's Oscars, but did not reach the list of five finalists. However, “perceive” already has 18 international awards in the curriculum, as well as 130 selections in the most prestigious international film festivals.
Casa Garden also welcomes “my sensations are all I have to offer”, by Isadora Neves Marques, who is currently in Hong Kong working in her first feature film. This film premiered at the Cannes Film Festival at “Semaine de la Critique” last year, and has since traveled to other prestigious international festivals.
Still on Saturday, and after all these performances, the day ends with the last movie, aired from 19h. This is “We are in the air”, by Diogo Costa Amarante. The film premiered at the International Film Festival Rotterdam (2024) and has since traveled Brazil and the main festivals in Europe, where it was awarded. It was recently appointed by the Portuguese Academy of Cinema for the Sophia Prize for Best Main Actress (2025), due to the “magnificent” interpretation of the protagonist, Sandra Faleiro.
Sunday cinema
The last day of this shows at 5 pm with the exhibition of the documentary “A Savana e A Mountain”, by Paulo Carneiro. The film debuted at the Cannes Film Festival at “Quinzaine des Cinéastes” in 2024, and has since traveled mainly through Latin America, but also through Europe and Asia. From 19h, it is displayed “Always”, by Luciana Fina, also a documentary. The premiere was made at the 81st Internazionale D'Ar Arte Cinematographic show La Biennale di Venezia last year and is now being selected for festivals in Europe and Latin America.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 07:04:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature | Giorgio Sinedino wins 18th edition of Special Book Award of China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/19/literatura-giorgio-sinedino-vence-18a-edicao-do-special-book-award-of-china/</link><description>Giorgio Sinedino, a translator and synologist in Macau, won the 18th edition of the Special Book Award of China, one of the “most important China awards offered to foreigners in the field of publications,” says the central government connection office on the MSAR. This award has been awarded 20 years ago
 
The winner of the 18th Special Book Award of China is already known. This is Giorgio Sinedino, a synologist and translator, who was an advisor to the former Chief of Executive, Chui Sai On. Author of a vast translation work of poetry and Chinese culture, Giorgio Sinedino is a professor at the Portuguese Department of Macao. In addition, he is also a member of the Executive Council of the International Confucian Association and Member of the World Synologists Council.
According to a statement issued by the Central Government's liaison office, this is “China's most important prize offered to foreigners in the field of publications”, and in 20 years, 219 translators, editors and authors from 63 countries were highlighted.
The prize awarded to Giorgio Sinedino, by “his important contributions”, was handed over to the target on Tuesday in Beijing. At the ceremony, the translator highlighted “the impressions of his trajectory in the exchange between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries”, reiterating “the commitment to continuing such work”.
The same note tells that Giorgio Sinedino, "in the various institutions he went through, has consistently endeavored in the dissemination of traditional Chinese culture, promoting the knowledge and understanding of this legacy abroad," and foster “dialogue and exchange of experiences between China and other civilizations”.
The place of experience
The same note reports the vast curriculum that Giorgio Sinedino presents in the area of ​​translation and research of Chinese classics, as since 2012, he began to publish in Brazil commented editions of writings such as “The Analects”, “Dao de Jing de Lazi with the Glossas of the Lord on the banks of the river” and “The Immortal of Southern China - a cultural reading of Zhuangzi”.
"The Analects" were the "first edition commented on Portuguese to be translated directly from the archaic Chinese", and "for over ten years, it remained the only one of the genre available on the market in a western language." In addition, it is considered “a new translation classic”, having already sold 200 thousand copies.
Last year, the three works referred to here won new editions in China, having been added to the “Understanding to China” collection by the “Editions in Foreign Languages” Public publisher.
In the same note, it is also said that these books "stated as remarkable achievements in the field of cultural exchanges between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, gathering important gaps in the field of the publication of Chinese classics in the Lusophone world."
The “unique merits” of the award -winning, conquered “in the translation of old classic works”, and the organizers of the prize do not forget the fact that Giorgio Sinedino have come to “seek new directions, expanded their specialties to also include the modern literature of China”.
Lu Xun's work
The connecting office also highlights Giorgio Sinedino's new work published this month in Brazil, dedicated to Lu Xun's poetry, which is entitled “Scream de Lu Xun - dramatized translation and critical studies by Giorgio Sinedino” and has the seal of Publishing 34.
The work resulted from “four years of research and experimentation”, and was supported by the China Ministry of Education, the Lu Xun Museum of Beijing, the Lu Xun Research Foundation and the World Culture, as well as the Feng Zikai Foundation.
It is noteworthy that “the final text was calibrated to correspond to the profile of Portuguese-speaking readers”, and in the translation process Giorgio Sinedino “followed certain standards of the literature of this language and combined the reading habits and stylistic preferences of his audience, producing a faithful recreation of Lu Xun's classic”.
This "dramatization" required the use, by the award -winning author, of "a new method of literary translation, in which the usual conventions of translation be broken." Thus, there was the “reinforcement of the original text depending on the impact of dramatic situations and the tension of characterizations”, attributing “a new vitality to the already canonized stories of that great Chinese writer”. In this context, “Sinedino expressed his confidence that his new work will provide a new reading experience for the Lusophone aficionados of Chinese literature,” he said.
Giorgio Sinedino has also been highlighted in the editions in Macao, having launched, in 2022, at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the book “Confucius-The Founder of Tradition”, an initiative of the Center for Chinese-Portuguese Bilingual Teaching and Training of the University of Macao (UM).</description><pubDate>2025-06-19 00:16:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Auto Silos Management | Accepts 9 of 12 proposals delivered</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/gestao-de-auto-silos-aceites-9-de-12-propostas-entregues/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) accepted, this Friday, 9 of 12 proposals submitted to public tender organized to manage several public parking parks, namely the self-solo of the building of the services for traffic issues, the self-solo building, the self-solo of the Taipa Marítimo da Taipa terminal SELF-SILO of the Lake Building and the Public Parking of the Residence for the elderly of Avenida do Nordeste.
According to a statement from DSAT, proposals for quarterly base returns between 1.088 million patacas and 2.038 million patacas, and the three societies were excluded because they volunteered from the competition, is explained.
The management deadline for management is six years and covers 2188 parking places for light cars and 1858 for motorcycles and mopeds. DSAT explains that the concessionaire will be responsible “not only for the daily management and exploitation of self-siles, but also for the optimization of the electronic payment system and without contact of auto-subsidia, the reinforcement of safety surveillance systems” and “implementation of ecological and energetically efficient equipment, and the improvement of existing facilities”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:19:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Water | Miriam Grupo carboys with high levels of bacteria</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/agua-garrafoes-de-miriam-grupo-com-niveis-elevados-de-bacterias/</link><description>It is the third case, since the beginning of the year, of waters distributed in Macau without complying with quality standards. The carboys were provided to public services, such as health services. In reaction to the case, Miriam Group accuses “some customers” of purposely contaminating the carboys used
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has announced that several water carboys supplied to public services of the brand Sun spoiled in quality tests, presenting high levels of coliform bacteria and pseudomonas aeruginosa bacteria. Coliform are a type of bacteria, such as E.Coli, which inhabit the gut of mammals, while pseudomonas aeruginosa bacteria can be found in waters and soils and can lead to severe infections in the lungs, skin or urinary tract.
The problem with water Sun, from Miriam Grupo Limited, was identified in lots produced on May 7 and 21 this year, and communicated on Friday. However, the information provided by AMI and SS did not reveal the time when the problems were detected by the entities.
Since the beginning of the year, this has been the third brand of Macao Águas de Macau to have quality and safety problems. The first case took place on 9 March with the Iceblue brand, from the Oi Kou Pou factory. More recently, also in May, authorities have detected problems with water from the Ieong IAT Tat brand.
Water Sun will have been provided to local public services, including health services (SS). However, it was denied that the contaminated water had entered the retail, hospitals or schools. "The two lots of distilled water did not enter the retail market, being mainly supplied to government services and commercial societies. The lots were not supplied to schools or hospitals," was reported by SS.
After disclosure of the information, the SS announced the cancellation of the water supply of that brand: “After verification, the lots concerned were not provided to health services. However, for safety reasons, health services stopped using the potable waters of that brand, and began to use the bottled waters of another qualified brand, in order to ensure the supply of drinking water”, was justified. The statement does not identify if there is a new water supplier or if the watermark of Miriam Grupo Limitada has been changed.
Attack of “some customers”
Upon detection of this case, AMI reported that it requested the group to “apply prevention measures, namely the collection of the distilled water lots, as well as implementing the cleaning and disinfection of the production line”.
Miriam Grupo Limitada also responded to the case by indicating that since June 1, which had issued a warning to warn of the collection of contaminated lots and that since May 30 the water production has been suspended for cleaning and applying the necessary rectifications. The same information indicated that compared to the plot of 7 May were collected 196 of the 367 carboys of water produced and compared to the lot of 21 May were collected 121 of the 432 carboys of distributed water. "Under the witness and organization of the AMI, the plots of abnormal water carboys were eliminated. Between May 30 and June 1, an independent cleaning company also cleaned the factory and production equipment. About 9,000 water carboys in May were eliminated," was released by the group.
In the statement, the group also complained of media coverage, and denied that the plot of May 7 had presented positive results of coliform bacteria contamination, not denied contamination with pseudomonas aeruginosa bacteria.
Miriam Grupo Limitada also accused some customers of contaminating the used carboys, which are later returned, to harm the company.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Economy | Inflation slowed to 0.19% in May</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/economia-inflacao-desacelerou-para-019-em-maio/</link><description>Inflation in Macao slowed in May, was announced on Friday, but the region escaped the fall in consumer prices, something that took place for the fourth consecutive month in the interior of China.
The Consumer Price Index (IPC) in Macau rose 0.19 percent in May, in homologous terms, slower than the amount recorded in April (0.23 percent), according to official data released by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
Although the CPI has dropped 0.05 percent compared to April, the territory escaped for the third consecutive month of deflation (annual fall in consumer prices).
Deflation reflects weakness in domestic consumption and investment and is particularly severe, as a drop in the price of assets, as awarded to credit, generates an imbalance between the value of loans and bank guarantees.
China, by far Macao's largest commercial partner, has been in consecutive months in deflation after the IPC has retreated 0.1 percent in May, the same amount recorded in April and March.
According to Macao DSEC data, the deceleration of inflation in May is due to the cost of meals acquired away from home, which rose only 1.39 percent, while the expenditures on apartment mortgages increased only 0.42 percent.
The housing price index fell 11.7 percent last year, notwithstanding Macau's monetary authority approved three interest rates in the last three months of 2024. Despite the increase in the number of visitors, the region registered a 2.5 percent drop in the price of clothing and footwear.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:14:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors | Second best start up to May</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/visitantes-segundo-melhor-arranque-de-sempre-ate-maio/</link><description>Between January and May, 16.3 million visitors were received, the second best record of visitors. However, the number is still below what happened before the pandemic and the policy of isolation
 
Macau received 16.3 million visitors in the first five months of this year, the second highest amount ever for a year start, was announced on Friday. According to official data, the number of tourists who passed by Macau was only surpassed between January and May 2019 -before the COVID -19 pandemic -during a period when nearly 17.2 million visitors.
However, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), almost 59 percent of visitors arrived on organized excursions and spent less than one day in the city.
In 2024, the central government released a series of measures to support Macau, such as increasing the tax exemption limit of goods for personal use acquired by visitors from China.
At the same time, Chinese authorities widened 10 other cities in China the list of places with “individual visas” to visit Hong Kong and Macau. Also, since January 1 that residents of the neighboring city of Zhuhai can visit Macau once a week and stay up to seven days.
As a result, the overwhelming majority (90.7 percent) of tourists who arrived in Macao in the first two months of the year came from interior or Hong Kong, while only 1.14 million were international visitors.
On January 17, Macao's director of tourism services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, said he hoped Macau could receive between 38 and 39 million visitors this year. In August, the leader pointed to more than three million international visitors in 2025.
More without visas
The territory authorities announced on Monday that Saudi Arabia national citizens, Qatar, Kuwait, Barram and Oman are dismissed from a visa to enter Macao from July 16.
The measure comes at a time when the Macao government wants to attract more international visitors and after the territory's authorities and tour operators visited in February Saudi Arabia and Dubai to promote cooperation.
Despite the increase in the number of tourists, the average consumption of each visitor, excluding in the casinos, fell 13.2 percent in the first quarter of the year, compared to the same period of 2024.
In early May, the direction of statistics and census services in the region pointed to the “change of visitors' consumption pattern” as one of the main reasons for the fall of 1.3 percent of Macau's economy between January and March.
It was the first time that the territory's gross domestic product has shrunk in homologous terms since the end of 2022, when the region began to raise restrictions due to Covid-19 pandemic.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Industrial and financial weakness is obstacle to the Mozambican presence in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/fraqueza-industrial-e-financeira-e-entrave-a-presenca-mocambicana-em-macau/</link><description>Experts consider that Mozambican bet in Macau is kept conditioned by the lack of industry and financial resources, and that new partnerships, including the new Chinese regional project, can project Mozambique in the territory.
By visiting the Macao Forum Product Exhibition Center last year, the Academic Fatima Papolo, which studies Sino-Mozambican relations, has realized the existence of few Mozambique products on site, where articles from various Portuguese-speaking countries are exposed.
"There are many more Brazilian products, but it is, to some extent, a reflection of the Mozambican economic structure. I believe that, through the Macao Forum, we can also think about how to transform this economic structure positively and that will result in the existence of more Mozambican products to be sold in Macao," he said now to Lusa.
Official data from the Macau government support the perception of the Joaquim Chissano University Academic in Maputo: the territory imported from Mozambique last year of goods worth about 12 million patacas. In the case of Brazil, the value exceeded a billion million patacas.
In this sense, paper refers to the need to create “more events” that put agents of the Macao and Mozambique trade “to discuss and explore possibilities for deepening these relationships”.
"It is also necessary to put other individuals linked to industry, because only a developed industry can check out products that will be changed. Mozambique still needs to work hard on this development of the industry and this is how it will turn their products into manufactured, put them in the Macao market and, perhaps, from all over China," he says.
Forum is “differential”
Created in 2003, the Macao Forum constitutes "a differential" in the relationship between Mozambique and China, says papers, but "there has been a long time that has not yet been done." "It is important to look like a space of exchanges. In this case, investments should come to Mozambique, but Mozambican investments should also go to Macau. This second sense needs to be worked," he says.
Although China was one of the first countries to recognize Mozambique as a sovereign state, on the day it declared independence on June 25, 1975, the “fortification of ties” with Macau, then under Portuguese administration, will only take place after 1999.
"From the moment the Chinese government begins to take control over the territory, then there is already this possibility that Mozambique also cooperates with Macau. So, this relationship begins to become much more alive, much more present," he says.
Historian Wu Zhiliang considers the creation of the Macao Forum “a recognition” of the role of the territory as a bridge between China and Lusophone partners.
Assuming that the region “has a lot to do to fulfill this mission well”, also president of the Macau Foundation refers to Lusa that the Forum should “expand its action, as well as the promotion of economic and commercial exchange, to the areas of teaching, culture and scientific research”.
Bet on the bay
An opportunity for Mozambique in the region constitutes, according to Fatima Papalo, the Great Bay, a project that Maputo should “enjoy and explore”.
“I see a space in which Mozambique can promote their potential, can also seek services that will allow their economic development in various areas, from energy, industry, transportation, communication, because there is a lot of technological development in the area of ​​transport, to public policy formulation,” he proposes. And the Portuguese language, he says, will be “always advantage”: “It is necessary that Mozambique realizes this special place that has and makes good use of it, in the positive sense”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 02:49:22</pubDate></item><item><title>STD | Warns to avoid travel to Israel and Iran</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/dst-alerta-para-evitar-viagens-a-israel-e-ao-irao/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) has issued a warning note yesterday for residents to avoid traveling to Israel or will take into account the latest war and political events, noting that "they should not travel to these two countries and those who find themselves in those countries should abandon the territories as soon as possible, ensuring their personal safety."
In addition, STD says it is "following the situation in Israel and Iran, warning the residents of Macao to be aware of the security situation."
Until yesterday, no request for information or assistance for the open line of STD had not yet been received. The same note indicates that there are no Macao mobile phones in Iran, taking into account the data provided by Macao's telecommunications operators.
Since Friday, Israel and Iran have been bombarding each other, leading some embassies to temporarily end their presence in Iran. The attacks began in Israel with targets designated in various parts of Iran, contributing to worse the tensions that were already living in the midfielder thanks to Israelo-Palestinian conflict. Last days attacks have killed more than 200 people, most of them in Iran.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 07:08:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Customs | Seized more than 20 thousand fake labubu</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/alfandega-apreendidos-mais-de-20-mil-labubu-falsos/</link><description>The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge Border Customs, on the side of Zhuhai, detected three cases of violation of property rights, seizing 20,599 Peluches Labubu, the popular Pop Mart toys.
According to the Xinhua state agency, the seized cocks came in three trucks that tried to cross the border to leave China in different periods of the day.
The agency cites the brand owner, which confirmed the counterfeit of products and the use of the brand without permission. It should be noted that the Gongbei shopping center, adjacent to the border post with the doors of the siege, is full of clothing stores counterfeit with fake brands of internationally known brands.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 06:45:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad for us, in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed with scholastic rigor stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those waiting for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of it, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “I never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstandings, if they are fortunately fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered a war, the best animals will be beheaded. superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as António Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter My Dear Friend: You are a pure, excellent, and very noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
Mas atrás dos meus passos soam passos do tamanho do infinito
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE Iranian says that first Israelites and now USA "have exploded diplomacy"</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/mne-iraniano-diz-que-primeiro-israelitas-e-agora-eua-fizeram-explodir-a-diplomacia/</link><description>The Iranian Minister of Foreign Affairs reacted to the European Union and London appeals to return to the dialogue by stating that the United States and Israel "decided to explode" diplomacy by bombing Iran.
"We were negotiating (about the Iranian nuclear program) with the United States when Israel decided to explode this diplomacy," said Abbas Araghi, through platform X and then in statements in Istanbul, adding that when they were in dialogue with European Union countries -referring to Geneva negotiations this week -"the United States decided to reverse this diplomat."
“What conclusions can you draw from this?” Araqchi replied to the appeals made yesterday by the head of European diplomacy, Kaja Kallas, and British Prime Minister Keir Stmerer.
The EU high representative for Foreign Affairs, Kaja Kallas, called for “all parts” to take a “backwards”, return to the negotiating table and avoid a new climb ”after bombing, last morning, from the US against the major nuclear facilities of Iran.
The British Prime Minister, in turn, called for the will "return to the negotiation table", stressing that "stability in the region is a priority." In the answer lasts to these appeals to return to the negotiating table, the head of Iranian diplomacy also maintained: "How could they go back to something he never abandoned, let alone destroyed?"
To attack
US President Donald Trump confirmed at dawn that the United States Armed Forces attacked three nuclear centers in Iran, including Ford, joining Israel directly to wage the country's nuclear program.
"We have completed our successful attack on the three nuclear facilities in Iran, including Fordo, Natanz and Esfahan," Trump said in a social media post. The war began at dawn on June 13, with Israel to launch a vast military offensive against the Persian country, allegedly to prevent the advance of the Iranian nuclear program for military purposes.
The attacks decimated Iran's military and nuclear infrastructures, which has responded with missile vacancies on major Israeli cities, including Tel Aviv and Jerusalem, as well as several military facilities throughout the country.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:44:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Rainfall | Floods leave tens of thousands of displaced</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/chuvas-inundacoes-deixam-dezenas-de-milhares-de-desalojados/</link><description>The intense rains that have plagued various southern and downtown China regions since the beginning of last week have affected at least 300,000 people and forced tens of thousands of residents, especially in Guangdong province.
In the village of Huaiji, one of the most affected areas, the rains caused flooding of up to three meters deep, leaving half of the local roads.
Images released on state television show muddy and neighbors and volunteers streets working in their cleaning. The situation is also critical in other provinces of the center and eastern of the country, such as Hunan, where the Lishui River has registered its largest flood since 1998.
In the village of Longshan, four people remain missing after being trapped in a flooded underground garage. In the neighboring province of Hubei, the authorities have removed hundreds of people in municipalities such as Hefeng and Laifeng.
In the latter, a day care center was completely flooded and it was necessary to transport 500 children in rafts, said The Paper newspaper. The Ministry of Water Resources sent technical teams to high -risk zones and asked local governments to reinforce surveillance and preventive evacuation of vulnerable areas.
Local experts have warned in recent years that climate change may increase the frequency of extreme weather phenomena in the Asian country.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:28:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visit | China and New Zealand bet on cooperation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/visita-china-e-nova-zelandia-apostam-na-cooperacao/</link><description>Despite the recent difference around the Cook Islands, the two countries reaffirm their commitment to deepen the historical bilateral relations
 
Chinese President Xi Jinping and New Zealand Prime Minister Christopher Luxon highlighted the solidity of bilateral relations Friday and bet on deepening cooperation, despite the differences in the approach between Beijing and the Cook Islands.
During the meeting, held at the Great Palace of the People, next to Tiananmen Square, XI pointed out that China and New Zealand "have been going hand in hand" a half -century, in a relationship that "was at the forefront" of Beijing's bonds with developed countries.
The Chinese leader said that both parties should “deepen economic and commercial cooperation”, explore new spaces in areas such as technological innovation and the fight against climate change, and “adequately manage differences”, preserving the principle of “mutual respect” and “pursuit of consensus”.
Xi also noted that the two nations "have no historical conflicts or fundamental interests in dispute", which, he added, "must facilitate a constructive and stable relationship."
According to CCTV state television, Luxon reiterated that his country "maintains a commitment to the policy of" one China "and expressed its intention to" reinforce high level dialogue ", while defending the expansion of cooperation in sectors such as agriculture, dairy and tourism.
"The world is going through a period of uncertainty, and China is expected to play a relevant role," said the New Zealand Prime Minister, who was willing to collaborate with Beijing in the defense of the Multilateral Trade System and the preparation of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation Forum (APEC) that China will welcome by 2026.
Views
The visit occurs in a context of diplomatic tensions between New Zealand and the Cook Islands, after signing an agreement between the South Pacific and China, which led Wellington to freeze part of his help to development.
Beijing rejected Wellington's criticism and stressed that his cooperation with the Cook Islands "is not directed against third parties, nor should it be interfered or restricted by third parties."
China has argued that its agreements with the archipelago are based on “equality and mutual respect” and aim to “boost economic development and improve living conditions” in these territories of the Pacific.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:25:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia | Putin says Nato rearmament is not a threat</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/russia-putin-diz-que-rearmamento-da-nato-nao-e-uma-ameaca/</link><description>Russian President Vladimir Putin said yesterday that NATO rearmament does not represent a threat to the country, ensuring that Moscow has the “defense capabilities” necessary to face the transatlantic alliance.
"We do not consider any rearmament of the NATO as a threat to the Russian Federation, because we are self-sufficient in security," Putin said during a round table with representatives of international news agencies, on the sidelines of the St. Petersburg International Economic Forum. The Russian head of state added that the country is "constantly improving its armed forces and defense capabilities."
At a time when the NATO prepares a new summit next week in The Hague (Netherlands), and encourages members to increase their investment in defense, Putin considered that an eventual budget reinforcement up to 5 percent of GDP would represent “specific challenges” to Moscow, but said that this financial effort “makes no sense” to the alliance countries themselves.
"We will respond to all the threats that arise. There is no doubt," he said. Putin referred to the offensive launched against Ukraine in 2022 as part of a broader confrontation with NATO, which he considers to represent a “existential” threat to the Russian borders.
In the board of future peace negotiations, the Russian leader expressed interest in discussing European security architecture, namely US President Donald Trump.
Kiev, however, seeks safety guarantees from NATO as a condition for a possible agreement to end the war. Two cycles of negotiations between Russians and Ukrainians took place in Istanbul, but did not result in concrete advances.
Putin also stated that Russian forces continue to advance “every day” in front of combat, facing a Ukrainian army in numerical inferiority and operational difficulties. On the ground, the Russian forces maintain daily attacks on Ukrainian cities and villages.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 07:10:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Earthquake with a magnitude of 6.1 sacode island of Hokkaido</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/japao-sismo-com-magnitude-de-61-sacode-ilha-de-hokkaido/</link><description>A 6.1 magnitude earthquake yesterday reached the eastern coast of the Japanese island of Hokkaido in the north of the archipelago, without a tsunami alert or damage has been recorded.
The earthquake occurred at 8:08 places with epicenter at an depth unspecified in the waters off the coast of the Nemuro Peninsula, according to the Japan Meteorological Agency (JMA).
The earthquake in the city of Kushiro reached level 4 on the 7 -level Japanese seismic scale, which focuses on the measurement of surface shaking and the destructive potential of the earthquake, and was felt less intense in other zones of Hokkaido and parts of Honshu's main island in the northeast of the country.
JMA warned that the earthquake could cause some tide changes in the area, but added that there is no reason to worry about potential damage. Local authorities have not been informed of any earthquake -related incidents.
Japan is located in the so-called fire ring, one of the world's most active seismic zones, and suffers land with relative frequency, so its infrastructures are specially designed to resist tremors.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 06:58:49</pubDate></item><item><title>More than 200 victims of the fall of Boeing 787 in India identified</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/identificadas-mais-de-200-vitimas-da-queda-do-boeing-787-na-india/</link><description>Indian authorities announced Wednesday that they identified the bodies of more than 200 victims of flight 171 from Air India, which fired on June 12 in Ahmedabad, northwestern India. According to the clinical director of the city's Civil Hospital, Rakesh Joshi, until Wednesday, 208 victims of the accident were identified.
The fall of the Boeing 787, shortly after being peeled to Gatwick airport in London, killed at least 279 people, according to the last official balance, making it the worst air disaster in the world since 2014.
The plane, with 242 people on board, drew himself in an Ahmedabad residential zone on June 12, a minute after take-off at 13:39. According to the Indian civil aviation authority, this long -haul plane carried 230 passengers - 169 Indians, 53 British, seven Portuguese and one Canadian - and 12 crew members.
Only one passenger, sitting next to an emergency exit on the front of the plane, miraculously survived the accident. On land, at least 38 people died, according to the latest balance.
In investigation
Civil aviation investigators in charge of the inquiry recovered the two black boxes of the plane, which record conversations on the cockpit and the technical parameters of the flight. According to the first conclusions, the pilot issued an emergency appeal (Mayday) shortly after taking off.
Widespread video images after the catastrophe show the plane without being able to gain altitude and then pour heavily on the ground in an orange fireball.
The Indian Civil Aviation Authority ordered an inspection of the other 33 Boeing 787 at the service in the Air India fleet “by precaution”. These inspections did not show "any major problem," the civil aviation authority said on Tuesday night.
"The devices and maintenance systems were considered in accordance with the safety standards in force," he said. Air India announced Wednesday in a statement that will perform “Reinforced Safety Controls in the Boeing 787 fleet” and cancel some flights.
"Geopolitical tensions in the Middle East, the mandatory gathering night in the air spaces of many European and East Asian countries, the ongoing reinforced safety inspections, as well as the necessary cautious approach adopted by the technical staff and the Air Pilots, led to the increase in the number of canceled flights," the airline said in the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 06:57:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Israel | Chinese citizens begin to leave the country</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/israel-cidadaos-chineses-comecam-a-sair-do-pais/</link><description>The China Embassy in Israel began registering Chinese citizens resident in that country wishing to be withdrawn for Egypt in a process that will start today, the diplomatic mission yesterday announced in a statement.
According to the note, “a situation cannot be ruled out, following the escalation of attacks between Israel and Iran over the past week, which is why the embassy will provide support to citizens who choose to abandon Israelite territory.
Evacuation will be done by land through organized groups, carried in bus to the Taba border post, on the border between Israel and Egypt.
China Jiakun Foreign Ministry spokesman revealed on Wednesday that some Chinese citizens have been successfully transferred since Israel, without further details. According to official data, about 1,200 Chinese citizens in Israel currently reside.
In parallel, China also started the withdrawal of its nationals in Iran, where the Chinese community is around 4,000 people. By Wednesday, 791 Chinese citizens had already been transferred to safe areas in neighboring countries, such as Azerbaijan and Turquemenistan, and more than a thousand were “in the process of evacuation,” said Guo.
Beijing expressed this week his "deep concern" with the aggravation of the conflict between Tehran and Telavive, appealing to the adoption of "immediate measures to calm tensions", while reiterating that "strength cannot bring lasting peace."</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 06:54:41</pubDate></item><item><title>International Law | Wang Yi condemns Israel in conversation with Egypt and Oman</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/direito-internacional-wang-yi-condena-israel-em-conversa-com-egipto-e-oma/</link><description>Chinese diplomacy head Wang Yi yesterday sentenced Israel for "ignoring international law" and provoking "an abrupt climbing of tensions in the Middle East," during a telephone conversation with Egyptian and Oman's counterparts.
In conversation with Egyptian diplomacy head, Badr Ablatatty, Wang appealed to consensus and joint actions by the international community, "especially among countries in the region," according to a statement from the Chinese Foreign Ministry.
Chinese minister reiterated the appeal to a ceasefire and the reduction of tensions between Israel and Iran, and said that China is willing to work with eggyte to improve communication and coordination with multilateral organisms-such as the United Nations-and to make the efforts to promote peace and reconciliation.
In a similar tone, Wang Yi told Oman's counterpart, Sayyid Badr Bin Hamad Bin Hamood Albusaidi, who Israel violated "The Sovereignty and Security of Iran."
Chinese diplomacy head also expressed Beijing's support to the joint statement issued by 21 Arab countries, including Oman, and expressed confidence in which these nations remain united and persist in their efforts to bring the parties involved in the dialogue.
Beijing, a partner near Tehorão, reiterated that "strength cannot bring lasting peace" and has assured that "it will continue to maintain communication with the relevant parts, promoting peace and dialogue."</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 06:53:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Medium-Earient | China warns “risk of uncontrollable”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/20/medio-oriente-china-adverte-para-risco-de-descontrolo/</link><description>Beijing continues to appeal to the end of hostilities between Israel and Iran, while the United States hesitate whether or not to intervene directly in the conflict
 
China warned yesterday that "the situation in the Middle East is tense and delicate, and runs the risk of uncontrollably," asking for "responsible attitude" to the United States at a time of strong tensions between Iran and Israel.
"The conflict has been a week for a week, caused great damage to peoples from both countries and severely affected the peace and stability of the region and the world," said Guo Jiakun, spokesman for the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs at a press conference in Beijing.
Guo stressed that the aggravation of the conflict "will not bring winners" and reiterated China's opposition to "any violation of the United Nations Charter's purposes and principles and any attack on sovereignty, safety and territorial integrity of other countries," as well as "to the use or threat of use of force in international relations."
In a veiled message to Washington, the spokesman said that "the international community, especially the large influential countries, should maintain a fair position and a responsible attitude, in order to create favorable conditions for a ceasefire and the return to dialogue and negotiations" to prevent "the regional situation fall into an abyss and even greater disasters".
Flavor of the wind
On Wednesday, Trump left open the possibility of US military intervention against Iran. "It may be that. It may not do so. I mean, no one knows what I'm going to do," said the Republican.
Trump added that Teuão still wants to negotiate a nuclear agreement with the United States and that, he said, Iran will even have proposed to send a delegation to the White House to resume conversations - something the Iranian government has denied.
The US President also suggested that the beginning of Israelite attacks against Iran's nuclear and military facilities occurred after the deadline imposed by Washington to Tehran to complete a new nuclear pact.</description><pubDate>2025-06-20 06:50:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the appropriate place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
What other projects are in this book?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Yes. The idea of ​​publication, with Barcelona's Actar Books, has to do with putting the work, and more than that, its message, which is very specific to Macau and our way of working in the international and architects community, and this goes a lot through the Biennial. It was also in Europe that a consensus was built on the level of descriptions [in architecture] for a few centuries, and where there is a discussion, national and international, around the issues of the profession. We want our work to be present, either through the book and through acting Books, in this international community, to be part of the world.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through the space narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and see as soon as I was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, directed to teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
What do you talk about is economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | Jaguar that won in Macau in 1984 returned to the tracks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/gp-jaguar-que-venceu-em-macau-em-1984-regressou-as-pistas/</link><description>The more than seventy years of history of the Macau Grand Prix are people, machines and great moments. We were in 1984, when Tom Walkinshaw won Jaguar's only victory in the guide race. After years away from the audience, for the affected man, this same car returned to the tracks at the hands of an enthusiast of the MSAR MOTOR EVENT
 
Richard Meins, an English maritime transport entrepreneur who lived many years in Hong Kong, who participated on several occasions at the Macao Grand Prix, led this Jaguar XJs of Group A in the Historic Touring Car Challenge race, a competition for classics during the Donington Historic Festival. This “Big Cat”, Chassis No. 5 and one of the four original XJs still existing, is practically as it was in 1984, but given the limitations of tobacco advertising, today boasts the colors used in the European Tourism Championship, instead of the iconic black and gold decoration of John Player Special (JPS) that marked the ticket through the guide circuit.
Interestingly, this return to the clues, from a car that has been still in New Zealand and Japan, was scheduled for the Algarve International Race Track, but the Historic Touring Car Challenge canceled its race in early April in Portimão. So it was in lands of his majesty that Richard Meins made his first race with the British car.
“The car won in Macao in 1984, so I'm a big fan of this model,” Ricard Meins told the English magazine Motorsport News. “I still have the photographs I took this weekend in Macao,” said this avid classic competition car collector who, besides driving, supported several riders at the Macao Grand Prix.
In Donington Park, Richard Meins shared the imposing Jaguar XJS, equipped with a 5.3 -liter V12 engine with Jack Tetley, and ended in sixth place, winning in his class. Richard Meins had only guided the car once or twice, but plans to participate in more historic touring car challenge rounds with XJS 1984. “Let's try to put it on track more often now,” Ricard Meins said, who revealed that he was a stake in the Silverstone Festival in August with this very rare and striking copy of the 1980s tourism cars history.
Premiere of an iconic decoration
In the summer of 1984, Tom Walkinshaw accepted the challenge of the Portuguese organization of the Grand Prix to travel later this year to Macau. With the European title in his pocket, the English driver and team boss was accompanied by one of his usual riders, German Hans Heyer. The guide race was a BMW fiefdom and the controversial English wanted to put an end to the Bavarian domain in the race. To this end, it had the precious support of JPS, which was relaunching the brand, decorating its cars with the famous black and gold colors that would later be eternalized in Ayrton Senna's Lotus. At the time, the guide race took place three weeks before 1000 km from Bathurst, another important race on the worldwide calendar of tourist racing, and so TWR made a "two in one."
The 100 -mile race on the streets of Macau would not have much history, such as the cars built in the Kidlington workshops against the competition headed by the two BMW 635i Schnitzer officers, guided by Hans Stuck and Dieter Quester, and painted by rival Marlboro. Tom Walkinshaw ended first and Hans Heyer and m second.
At the end of the race, quoted by the Portuguese newspaper Autosport, Tom Walkinshaw said: “The circuit is fantastic. Tight, but with many curves, climbs and descents, which made the race become difficult. But I like difficult things and, for me, the race was great from beginning to end.
The Jaguar were again invited by the Macao Grand Prix committee to run in 1985, but Tom Walkinshaw had other plans for his cars. Fortunately, thanks to Richard Meins we will continue to see this beautiful car on the tracks.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MOTOR EMBALISM | Project for new track in Zhuhai emerges</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/30/automobilismo-surge-projecto-para-nova-pista-em-zhuhai/</link><description>With a very black cloud to turn to the future of the Zhuhai International Circuit, there is a potential good news for the great bay of motoring: a project for a new permanent circuit in the Chinese city adjacent to the MSAR.
According to Hong Kong's Ta Kung Pao newspaper, Guangdong's provincial government recently published the document “Measures to promote high quality tourism and accelerate the construction of a strong tourist province”, which proposes, for the first time, the creation of an “industrial circle of culture and tourism of the Great Bay”, offering political support to the integrated development of culture and tourism in the region. With this, the first industrial and tourist complex of motorized sports in the Great Bay may emerge.
The project of the Zhuhai Chaoyue international circuit was recently presented at the Zhuhai Ocean Spring Resort, located in Doumen, not far from the city's airport, with an initial investment of 250 million Renminbis.
According to the first information, the project of this circuit provides for welcoming evidence such as Formula 3 and foster collaborative development between motorized sports sectors, cultural events and exhibition industry. The plan includes the holding of several international tests per year and foresees collaboration with Hong Kong and Macau to connect cities such as Jiangmen and Zhongshan, promoting “Multiple stops” and boosting the innovative development of “Event Economics + Cultural Tourism”.
According to Zhou Jian, China Travel Service (Zhuhai) Executive Director General Ocean Spring Resort Co., the FIA ​​grade certification-will also include a karting track, drift track and an interior space of 2,400 m² for exhibitions and events related to the automobile sector. With more than 50 international events projected annually, the goal is to become a "super IP" that joins running, leisure and tourism under the same concept.
The first phase of the Zhuhai Chaoyue International Circuit project will include international certification professionals, as well as support facilities. This project aims not only to fill “a gap in the high -end motorized sports sector in Zhuhai, but will also promote the modernization of the Great Bay's cultural, sports and tourist industries by conducting international racing and themed cultural events linked to motorsport.”
Uncertainties in the air
Last summer, the company Malay LBS Bina Group BHD announced that it sold its participation in the Zhuhai International Circuit (ZIC) - the first permanent circuit built in the interior of China - by 124.7 million ringits (about 214.15 million patacas). In a statement to Bursa Malaysia Securities BHD, the group reported that their subsidiary, Dragon Hill Corporation Ltd, sold all his participation in Lamdeal Investments Ltd (Lil) to Huafa Urban Operation (HK) Ltd, a well -known real estate operator. Lil Detinha 60 percent of Zhuhai International Circuit Limited (ZICL), circuit operator.
Raised in 1996 in order to receive the first major prize of Formula 1 China - something that never materialized - the ZIC was still the initial engine of motor racing in the country and a reference in Asian motorsport. Since its opening, it has welcomed several international evidence, such as the FIA ​​GT, A1 GP or the Intercontinental Le Mans Series. In recent years, track administration has chosen to organize its own events, abdicating the most costly international evidence.
Despite having received, in the past, auto competitions from MSAR, ZIC has been losing protagonism in local motorized sport, due to high prices, limited availability and reducing sports activity in favor of the most profitable commercial activities. The future of the circuit remains uncertain: it is only known that lease agreements between resident teams and the circuit have been frozen and are not being renewed. The track approval will also be about to expire, requiring a new certification to continue to receive competitions in the future.
However, on the weekend of June 14 and 15, the still only circuit of Zhuhai will host the third race of the Formula 4 China Championship season.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 01:53:33</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA AFINA REGIONAL Formula Rules</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/23/gp-fia-afina-regras-da-formula-regional/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) took advantage of the holding of the Extraordinary General Assemblies and its annual conference to publish the Macao Grand Prix Regulation - FIA Regional Formula Cup of 2025. There are not many changes compared to 2024, but the changes introduced aim to browse gaps in the first edition of this macau.
The twelve red flags during last year's qualification session called for the level of pilots at the Guide Circuit, which was the premiere of the FIA ​​regional formula in Macau regional formula. This happened after the controversial decision of the FIA ​​to consider that Formula 3 was no longer adequate to the Macao Citadino layout.
Unsurprisingly, the sports regulation is now clear that, to compete in the FIA ​​regional formula world, “all pilots must have participated at least 3 competitions with a monolugar that has been projected and/or built to achieve a weight/power ratio of more than 3.0 kg/hp.”
Emanuele Pirro, a former F1 pilot, winner of the Guide Race and president of the FIA ​​monoligai committee, said during the weekend of the 71st edition that, in the future, the FIA ​​will be more demanding about track discipline. Thus, from now on, “any pilot who, in the opinion of sports commissioners, is solely responsible for the display of a red flag during the qualification training session, will not be able to continue to participate in this session and its best time back can be annulled.” The new regulation also states that “if a qualification training session is interrupted with less than four minutes remaining, it will not be restarted.”
On the other hand, the FIA ​​maintains the limit in the participation of more experienced pilots, except only “pilots who participated in a maximum of 3 FI F2 Championship competitions of 2025.” This measure goes a little against the spirit and history of the Great Prize, which has always gathered pilots from higher categories in its main race. In fact, this was a fervent question between Macao and the International Federation on two previous occasions.
In 1985, Alfredo César Torres, then responsible for Portuguese motorsport, convinced Jean-Marie Balestre, against his will, to allow the participation of F1 pilots in the F3 Intercontinental Cup in the name of the economic viability of the race. In 2016, the controversy returned with the veto da FIA to the participation of Nelsinho Piquet, a decision badly received by the teams and then coordinator Barry Bland, which would eventually abandon the co-organization of the race a year later.
Bet on continuity
In sports terms, registrations for this second edition of the FIA ​​regional formula Cup will remain open until July 30. The grill may include a maximum of 27 Tatuus regional formula monologues, all equipped with Alfa Romeo engines built by the Italian Autotechnic. Pirelli will once again be the official tire supplier.
The identities of the invited teams have not yet been revealed, but some news is expected in this field compared to 2024. To avoid any behind -the -scenes disputes, it has already been defined that “the position on the boxes for the teams that participate in the Macao Grand Prix will be based on the ranking of the previous year” and, in turn, “the position in the roadway for new teams will be attributed based on the order of application.”
Equal awards and more restricted advertising
The values ​​of monetary awards remain unchanged this year, with a total of US $ 68,500 to distribute, the equivalent of just over 550,000 patacas at the current exchange rate. The race winner will receive $ 12,000, an amount that is still far from covering the costs of participation in this nature.
On the other hand, the sports regulation introduces two new prohibitions on advertising into the monoligales. In addition to the existing prohibition of advertising to fortune or bad luck, tobacco or pornography, also the promotion of electronic cigarettes and alcoholic beverages - a measure that follows the legislation in force in the territory.
The 72nd Macao Grand Prix, the largest international sports event of the MSA, will take place between November 13 and 16, 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-06-23 03:31:16</pubDate></item><item><title>FIA | Conference helped perceive future of motorsport</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/13/fia-conferencia-ajudou-a-perceber-futuro-do-automobilismo/</link><description>For the first time in its history, in 2025, Macau welcomed the Extraordinary General Assemblies and Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). Organized in partnership with the Macau-China General Association (AAMC), the FIA-affiliated sports territory, and Galaxy Entertainment Group, this event brought together more than five dozen FIA senior delegates from 147 countries in the field.
 
In the Galaxy International Convention Center, to this day, the future of motoring and mobility worldwide is discussed. However, some details about the future of sport in the territory have already been revealed between the lines. Focused on obtaining information about the growth of motorsport and promoting safe, sustainable and accessible mobility to everyone in the Asia Pacific region, the FIA ​​conference opening session highlighted the importance of communication and collaboration, as well as the region's ability to innovate and create solutions that respond to specific questions it faces.
Roberto Carlos Osório, president of the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), said the association has a strong tradition in motor racing and that following FIA's guidelines is being able to grow rapidly competition at the base level in the region.
“We organized the first GT Macau Cup in 2008,” said the AAMC leader. "Currently, we also have the GT Cup - Great Bay Race for GT4 cars. In addition, in 2008, we created Road Sport Challenge," he explained. “And today, in 2025, we are proud to announce that we have 68 tourism cars in the region to compete in the qualification race to enter the 72nd Macao Grand Prix.”
In a year when AAMC celebrates 30 years of existence - was born as Macao Automobile Club - we also learned that the association's bet for the future will be in the basic disciplines of motor sport. Roberto Carlos Osorio also revealed a curious fact: Macau has 135 pilots with sports license from the territory.
“This growth was achieved following FIA's guidelines to promote grassroots motorsport and create accessible races for riders in the region,” added the manager of the territory. “With the interest of pilots, teams and promoters in developing state-of-the-art activities in Macau, we will focus even more on base competitions and affordable races, not only to support tourism, but also to make Macau in a Karting international center of international events, where champions can be selected for F4 and, later, for regional formula.”
Confirmed GP program
The Macao Grand Prix Organizing Committee (COGPM) held a press conference on June 8 at the Macao Grand Prix Museum to confirm the 72nd Macao Grand Program races, which will take place from November 13 to 16 this year.
As last year, there will be seven races in total, respectively, the Macao Grand Prix - FR da Fia World Cup, the GT Macau Cup - GT da Fia World Cup, the Macau Guide Race - Kumho Fia tcr World Tour Event of Macau, the Formula 4 Formula 4 World Cup, the 57th Macao Motor Motor Prize, GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4) and Macao Roadsport Challenge. For the first time, the guide circuit receives four different cups under the FIA ​​seal on the same weekend.
Other news
Between meetings and communications, other information was revealed about the November edition of the Macao Grand Prix. The FIA ​​World Council approved in Macao that the winner of the first Formula 4 World Cup of the FIA ​​will receive two points for the super license. We have also noticed that Pirelli will equip all the monologes that participate in both the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup and the FIA ​​regional formula World Formula Cup. In turn, the supply of tires and fuel to the FIA ​​GT World Cup remains in the contest phase.
Registration for the Formula 4 World Cup will be open until July 30. The final selection of 20 pilots will be confirmed by the FIA ​​through an official invitation letter, taking into account the current classification of the pilots in the respective championships.
In the case of the FIA ​​Regional Formula World Cup, registrations will also remain open until July 30, and the grill will be able to host a maximum of 27 Tatuus regional formula -equipped with alpha Romeo engines built by the autotechnic. As with Formula 4, participation will be by invitation, with priority assigned to pilots who have reached the best positions in the five regional formula championships of 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-06-13 18:43:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao's historicals get a GP clearance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/20/historicos-de-macau-conseguem-apuramento-para-gp/</link><description>The Guangdong International Circuit welcomed, last weekend, the second and decisive double journey of Macao - Macau Road Sport Challenge cars, proof of finding for the most important motor racing of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. In a journey with few celebration reasons for the colors of the sinters, the veterans Jerónimo Badaraco and Rui Valente managed to ensure the qualification.
With a list of 68 subscribers, the grill was divided into two groups, A and B, with all the pilots competing with Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) models. This year, with only one race scheduled for the Grand Prix Program - due to the inclusion of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup - the number of riders was reduced to 36, which placed a supplementary pressure for both missing races. To complicate, the rain came, changing the turns to teams and riders.
In Group A, where Rui Valente faced a complicated weekend on the track around Zhaoqing, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão failed to qualify, in a series dominated by Hong Kong pilots. In Saturday's race, the podium consisted of Wong Chuck Pan, Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping. On Sunday, these three repeated the feat, but with a new order: Lo Pak Yu, Chan Ka Ping and Wong Chuck Pan.
In difficult atmospheric conditions on Saturday, Rui Valente ended only 25th, due to an error in tuning, improving to 15th on Sunday, with the track dry. A penalty after the second race fired him to the 27th place. Still, the 7th place obtained on the first round was enough to secure a place in the Macao Grand Prix.
On the contrary, Maximiano Mannão, behind the wheel of a Toyota with the colors of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended on 26th and 14th, a result below the finding, but it turns out to be positive given that it was Jove Pilot's debut in these wanderings. Célio Alves Dias, with difficulties in his car since the first race, was 24th and 28th, far from the usual level of this experienced Macaense pilot.
Badaraco with final sprint '
On a weekend, where the lively races were broadcast on live streaming in Group B, Hong Kong riders stood out again. On Sunday, Adrian Chung won, with Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin completing the podium. In the second confrontation, Cheang Kin Sang reached a deserved victory, followed again by Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin.
Jerónimo Badaraco came to this challenging weekend without the assured clearance. A modest qualification and 11th Saturday place maintained the open outcome. However, a solid race on Sunday and an excellent 4th place assured veteran Macanese the much desired place on the grid of the Macao Grand Prix, along with countrymen Cheng Kin San, Leong Keng Hei, Lou Check In and Carson Tang.
Also outside the big prize was Dionísio Albino Pereira, who finished 23rd in Saturday's race, but closed the time more forcefully, by cutting the line of goal in 13th place in the second race.
At the end of the races, competitors provisionally calculated had an extra technical verification, being forced to open engines and gearbox, to verify the legality of these two decisive organs of their vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-05-20 01:57:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Council of Motorsport approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and a MSAR test enthusiast, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The growth and development potential in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into detail, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula cup last year, says that “this big step will undoubtedly benefit local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item></channel></rss>