<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Gaza | Xi calls for the Strip to be under Palestinian control</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/gaza-xi-defende-que-faixa-fique-sob-controlo-palestiniano/</link><description>The Chinese President called for the reconstruction of the Gaza Strip to be carried out under the principle of “Palestinians govern Palestine” and urged the international community to promote a “comprehensive and lasting ceasefire”.
Xi Jinping stated that the Palestinian issue “affects international equity and justice” and constitutes “a test of the effectiveness of the global governance system”, said the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs. In a message sent to a UN meeting on Tuesday, the Chinese leader argued that the international community must “take responsibility, correct historical injustices and defend justice”.
On the occasion of the International Day of Solidarity with the Palestinian People, Xi stressed that any post-war structure must respect “the will of the Palestinian people” and take into account the legitimate concerns of countries in the region. The Chinese leader insisted that efforts must “be anchored in the two-state solution” to achieve a “comprehensive, fair and lasting” political agreement.
The Chinese President said that the immediate priority is to improve the humanitarian situation and alleviate the suffering of civilians in Gaza, and reiterated that Beijing, as a permanent member of the Security Council, “will continue to support the just cause of the Palestinian people to restore their legitimate national rights”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:09:18</pubDate></item><item><title>DSPA | Renewed Director Service Committee</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/dspa-comissao-de-servico-de-director-renovada/</link><description>Ip Kuong Lam's service commission as director of Environmental Protection Services has been renewed for a period of one year, according to an order published yesterday in the Official Gazette.
As happens in these situations, the order indicates that the appointee has “appropriate experience and professional capacity to carry out his duties”. Ip Kuong Lam has a bachelor's degree and a master's degree in Environmental Engineering. He entered the public service in 2001, and served as senior technician at the Environment Council, head of the Environmental Pollution Control Department at DSPA and deputy director of DSPA, between 2014 and 2024, when he was promoted to his current position.
IH | Iam Lei Leng's mandate renewed
The mandate of the president of the Housing Institute (IH), Iam Lei Leng, was renewed for a period of one year, according to an order published yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Iam was first appointed to these roles in 2023, during Raimundo do Rosário's period as Secretary for Transport and Public Works.
The renewal of the mandate was justified by the fact that Iam had “appropriate experience and professional capacity to carry out his duties”. Before being appointed president of IH, Iam Lei Leng headed the Department of Studies at the Housing Institute since March 2015.
The current president joined IH, as a technician, in April 1999, remaining in the position for around a year. Between June 2002 and January 2006, he became a senior technician. After completing this mission, he became head of Legal Affairs at the Housing Institute, where he remained until 2015.
Commerce | António Lei dismissed as managing director
António Lei Chi Wai was dismissed from the position of managing director of the Board of Directors of the Macau World Trade Center, according to information released yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Lei will be replaced by Ao Weng Tong, currently a member of the Consumer Council and who will hold both roles.
The decision by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, was published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, but came into force on November 19th. The order does not make it clear whether António Lei Chi Wai will continue to serve as president of the Executive Committee of the Macau World Trade Center. Currently, António Lei has an annual salary of 1.2 million patacas, for both roles, which if divided over 12 months represents a salary of 100 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:28:55</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Satellite casinos’ | Kam Pek closes doors in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/casinos-satelite-kam-pek-fecha-portas-em-macau/</link><description>Macau gaming concessionaire SJM Resorts announced yesterday that the Kam Pek Paradise 'satellite casino', with almost 600 employees, will close on December 1st. SJM said that Kam Pek Parasise “will officially cease operations at 23:59 (Monday, December 1st), thus becoming the seventh ‘satellite casino’ in the region to close its doors.
In a statement, SJM, founded by gaming tycoon Stanley Ho Hung Sun (1921-2020), highlighted that all local employees directly hired by the company have guaranteed employment. SJM explained that staff with resident status in Macau will be “transferred to other company casinos to perform gaming-related functions, according to operational needs”.
Local employees who were not hired directly by SJM Resorts “are invited to apply for related vacancies” within the group, “with priority for hiring” and with conditions equal to those they had. Also yesterday, the Macau Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ) assured that it will “strictly supervise, on site, the closure procedures” of Kam Pek Paradise.
With regard to the 584 casino employees, the DICJ assured, in a press release, that it will maintain communication with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, to ensure compliance with the guarantees given by the SJM, namely “the relocation of all aforementioned workers”. SJM highlighted that “all tables and gaming machines currently operating on site will be transferred to other company casinos”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:11:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Edgar Martins wins Grand Prize Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/edgar-martins-vence-grande-premio-sovereign-portuguese-art-prize-2025/</link><description>Photographer Edgar Martins won the Grand Prize of the Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025, worth 25 thousand euros, for the work “Anton’s Hand is Made of Guilt”, inspired by the disappearance of a friend during wartime. The announcement was made this Tuesday, the day of the opening of the finalists' exhibition, at the Sociedade Nacional de Belas Artes, in Lisbon, during a press visit, led by Howard Bilton, founder and president of the Sovereign Art Foundation (SAF).
This is the fourth edition of this annual award, which is awarded by the SAF Association, the Portuguese branch of the Sovereign Art Foundation, created in 2003 in Hong Kong to promote, support and recognize contemporary art and encourage artistic production, as well as financing programs for disadvantaged children in Portugal.
The winning work, which is also present in the collection of the Museu de Arte Contemporânea Armando Martins (MACAM), is a chromogenic proof, mounted in aluminum and framed, which is part of the series “Anton’s hand is made of Guilt. No muscle of Bone. He has a Gung-ho Finger and a Grief-stricken Thumb” (2023).
Edgar Martins' work explores themes such as war, incarceration, migration, urbanism and technology, with this project, in particular, focusing on the death and disappearance of a friend, photojournalist Anton Hammerl, during the Libyan war in 2011.
Central questions
The work is articulated around a central question: how to narrate a story without witnesses, evidence or traces, and in the absence of the photographic referent itself”, states the catalog information about the work, adding that “more than a tribute, this work portrays a complex story, distorted by absences, which talks about the difficulties of documenting, witnessing and imagining war”.
"While I don't tend to categorize my work as photography in the traditional sense of the term, it is, in virtually every way, photographic. And photography, historically, has not been particularly successful when it is forced to compete with other mediums. So I received this news with surprise and excitement in equal measure. It is, of course, a huge honor to receive such a prestigious award. And what's more, a privilege to know that this financial support will directly contribute to the Sovereign Art Foundation's solidarity program, making me feel part of of something much greater than this isolated artistic feat”, declared the winner, quoted in a statement.
For the president of the jury, David Elliott, it has not been an easy task to find a winner, with the “variety, depth and subtlety of the finalist works”.
"The cruelly savage ironies that confront us in every daily news report are part of the theme of Edgar Martins' winning work. Rooted in both the present and the recent past, it was triggered by the still unexplained disappearance and death of his friend, photojournalist Anton Hammerl, during the Libyan War in 2011. It remains a crime without witnesses or any other evidence, a void that Martins has addressed in other works, as well as in the winning work 'Anton's Hand is Made of Guilt. In Muscle or Bone. He has a Gung-ho Finger and a Grief-stricken Thumb'”, said the president of the jury, quoted by the organization.
In female
This year, for the first time, the Women's Prize was created, created in partnership with the Sassy Women Society, worth two thousand euros, which distinguishes the finalist with the highest score, with the choice going to the artist Alice Marcelino, for the work “Black Skin White Algorithm”.
The 30 finalist works will be on display until December 13th, the date on which the Public Vote prize will be awarded, which can be done in person or online, also worth two thousand euros.
The 30 finalist works that will be on display were chosen by an international jury made up of seven experts – Adelaide Ginga, Armando Cabral, David Eliott, Francisco Trêpa (who won the grand prize in 2024), João Paulo Queiroz, Maura Marvão and Tim Marlow OBE – from around 200 artists proposed by a panel of independent arts professionals, including Portuguese critics, curators and academics.
All finalist works are available for purchase and profits will be divided equally between the artists and SAF's expressive arts programs for disadvantaged children in Portugal.
The Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize is an annual award that celebrates the work of contemporary artists living in Portugal and its diaspora, offering international recognition and financially supporting artists, whilst also raising funds for disadvantaged children in Portugal through the sale of finalist works.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:54:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | At least 13 people died in a fire</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/hong-kong-pelo-menos-13-pessoas-morreram-num-incendio/</link><description>The images of the fire that spread through the apartment blocks with capacity for 2,000 people suggest a major tragedy
At least 12 people died yesterday in a fire that spread to several buildings in a Hong Kong housing complex, according to the Chinese press, highlighting that there were people trapped in the apartments. According to the South China Morning Post portal, 12 people, including a firefighter, died and at least 16 others were seriously injured in the fire that devastated the Tai Po neighborhood.
The other 11 fatalities were eight women and three men, according to sources cited by the media outlet. The flames consumed bamboo scaffolding in all eight buildings in the social neighborhood, leaving several other residents trapped inside the apartments, according to the Chinese news portal.
The director of the local fire department, Andy Yeung, told reporters that one firefighter was among the dead and another had to receive medical treatment for heat exhaustion.
According to the Associated Press (AP) news agency, videos from the scene showed at least five buildings close to each other in flames, with smoke coming out of many apartment windows, as night fell. Firefighters fought the flames by throwing water from the ladders of the corporation's trucks.
The violent fire released a column of flames and dense smoke as it spread through the bamboo scaffolding and protective screens installed around the buildings, located in the Tai Po district. Records show the housing complex is made up of eight buildings with almost 2,000 apartments.
Hong Kong police said they had received several reports of people trapped in fire-stricken buildings, but did not provide details.
Maximum level
The fire was reported in the middle of the afternoon and, after dark, authorities raised it to alert level 5, the highest level of severity, according to the fire department.
Tai Po district authorities opened temporary shelters for people left homeless by the fire. Tai Po is a suburban area in the New Territories, in the northern part of Hong Kong and close to the border with the city of Shenzhen in mainland China.
Bamboo scaffolding is common in Hong Kong in building construction and renovation projects, although the Government announced earlier this year that it would begin phasing it out of public projects due to safety concerns.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:56:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Cambodia | Money laundering suspicions in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/camboja-suspeitas-de-lavagem-de-dinheiro-em-macau/</link><description>Companies linked to the Prince Holding group and Chen Zhi, accused of cybercrime, human trafficking and money laundering, conducted business in Macau and Hong Kong. One of the companies was Companhia de Vinho Pou Long, which operated in the Macao SAR and even organized a gala dinner for the elderly in 2020
Octopus tentacles from a dismantled scam center in Cambodia may have reached Macau and Hong Kong. An investigation by the HK01 portal revealed that companies related to billionaire Chen Zhi's criminal empire operated in the special administrative regions.
The 37-year-old Chinese businessman is seen as the “brain behind a criminal empire” and is at the center of the largest cryptocurrency seizure in history, with around $14 billion in bitcoins confiscated by the United States Treasury Department. The schemes allegedly operated in industrial complexes in Cambodia, where foreign workers were forced to commit online fraud under armed surveillance.
According to the Hong Kong publication, in the Prince Holding business universe, chaired by the Fujian businessman, there are companies that had business in Macau selling alcoholic beverages through a network of companies that had as a common denominator a businessman also active in Hong Kong: Qiu Yong. The businessman, who appears on the list of 146 companies and people sanctioned by the United States due to the alleged commission of the crimes mentioned above, holds passports from Cambodia and Saint Lucia, a small island in the Caribbean, and was the main shareholder of eight companies based in Hong Kong, two of which have already been dissolved.
One of the companies based and operating in the neighboring region was the Wine Mini Store Digital Economy Industry Company, led together with Ng Sang Lei, a Macau resident and Macao SAR passport holder.
A web in the delta
The Wine Mini Store had a commercial address in Tsim Sha Tsui in the same place where several companies were headquartered that fugitive billionaire Chen Zhi controlled indirectly through offshore companies in the British Virgin Islands and companies in Hong Kong.
Among the companies created and dissolved is the Pou Long Wine Company, based in Tsim Sha Tsui, which was fully owned by Ng Sang Lei before the commercial registration was annulled in October this year. According to reports in Macau in the past, the Pou Long Wine Company launched a series of activities, including a gala dinner for the elderly, in January 2020, which was attended by Qiu Yong.
In February 2020, during the outbreak of Covid-19 in Wuhan, the Pou Long Wine Company donated 1.5 million patacas and 60,000 masks to the provincial authorities.
In relation to the Macau resident, HM found references to Ng Sang Lei in the Official Gazette, when she was authorized by the Macau Monetary Authority to practice as an insurance intermediary in the Macao SAR in June 2019. Less than 10 months later, the resident was the target of an infringement procedure.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:50:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Sports Garden | Zone 1 works awarded for 1.34 billion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/jardim-desportivo-obras-da-zona-1-adjudicadas-por-134-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The Public Works Services Department (DSOP) announced the award of the work to the consortium made up of Grupo Construção Omas Limitada, Companhia de Engenharia de Túneis Shanghai S.A., and China Zhong Ji Indústria e Instabilidade (Macau) Lda.
The construction of Zone 1 of the future Sports Garden for Citizens, on the former Canídromo site, was awarded 1.34 billion patacas, according to information released by the Public Works Services Department (DSOP).
The work was awarded to the consortium made up of Grupo Construção Omas Limitada, Companhia de Engenharia de Túneis Shanghai S.A., and China Zhong Ji Indústria e Instacção (Macau) Lda. This consortium presented the cheapest new proposal, among the 17 accepted in the public tender.
Regarding the period of work, the consortium committed to completing the works in 964 days, the second fastest period. This period was also presented by eight other proposals.
The competition jury rejected the proposal from the consortium Companhia de Construção e Engenharia Rock-One, Limitada, Rock-One Imobiliária Empresa Limitada and Rock-One Desenvolvimento Empresa Limitada, which presented the lowest price, of 1.27 billion patacas, as well as the shortest deadline, for a total of 913 days.
Work plan
The Sports Garden covers an area of ​​40,425 square meters and will be divided into four pavilions, in addition to including an outdoor athletics track and a basement.
The first pavilion with four floors includes two swimming pools, one of which is for children, a basketball court, and a running track and cycle path. In the second pavilion, with six floors, a skate park, tennis courts, climbing area, volleyball and badminton courts will be built.
Regarding the third pavilion, the project envisages a seven-story building to house a five-a-side football field, a two-story multipurpose room, a multipurpose activity room and spaces for outdoor activities. Finally, the fourth pavilion is designed for children, and according to the project, it envisages the construction of an outdoor activity area, a children's playground and classrooms and reading rooms.
In the basement, there will be a public parking lot with 69 spaces for cars and 166 spaces for motorcycles. There will be another parking lot, to be built in the second phase, with 415 parking spaces for light vehicles and 425 for motorcycles.
The works are divided into Zone 1 and Zone 2. Work in Zone 1 will start first and includes the demolition of existing structures on the land and the construction of the pavilions, excluding the one dedicated to children, the basement and the smaller car park.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:42:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Finance | Reserve with biggest increase until September since the pandemic</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/financas-reserva-com-maior-subida-ate-setembro-desde-a-pandemia/</link><description>In nine months, the value of reserve assets increased by 42.5 billion patacas, exceeding last year's figure. Macau's financial reserve is at its highest level since April 2021, with a value of 658.8 billion patacas
The financial reserve had the best first nine months of the year since 2019, before the start of the covid-19 pandemic, it was announced yesterday. According to a balance sheet published in the Official Bulletin by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM), the value of assets rose by 42.5 billion patacas in the first nine months.
Official data show that this is the best start to the year since the first nine months of 2019, a period in which the reserve appreciated by 64.7 billion patacas.
According to AMCM, the reserve has already appreciated more than in 2024, the year in which assets rose by 35.7 billion patacas, the highest annual value since the pandemic. Last year recorded the highest increase since 2019, when the value of Macau's financial reserve rose by 70.6 billion patacas.
In September alone, the reserve gained 5.49 billion patacas, reaching 658.7 billion patacas, the highest value in more than four years.
Macau's financial reserve is at the highest level since recorded in April 2021, at 658.8 billion patacas. Still, it remains below the historical record of 663.6 billion patacas, reached at the end of February 2021, despite the territory being in the midst of a pandemic at the time.
The inside of the melon
The value of the extraordinary reserve at the end of September this year was 456.5 billion patacas and the basic reserve, equivalent to 150 percent of Macau's public budget, was 167.3 billion patacas. Subcontracted investments represent the largest share of Macau's financial reserve, 281.3 billion patacas, which also includes deposits and current accounts worth 265.4 billion patacas and even credit securities worth 109.4 billion patacas.
In 2024, investments yielded almost 31 billion patacas to the financial reserve, corresponding to a profitability rate of 5.3 percent, said AMCM, at the end of February.
The territory's initial budget for 2025 predicted a 7 percent increase in total expenditure, to 109.4 billion patacas. But the Legislative Assembly (AL) approved in July a proposal presented by the Government for a new budget, which includes an extra increase of 2.86 billion patacas in expenses.
On Tuesday, the AL also unanimously gave the green light to the budget for 2026, which foresees public expenditure of 113.5 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:26:33</pubDate></item><item><title>National security | Government will create risk alert system</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/seguranca-nacional-governo-vai-criar-sistema-de-alerta-para-riscos/</link><description>Guardianship debates continue on the report on the Lines of Government Action for 2026. Yesterday the Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, guaranteed that in 2026 a risk alert system for national security will be created
The Macau Government promised to create, in 2026, a risk warning system for national security and warned of “acts of interference and destruction” by “external forces”.
The Secretary for Security set the goal for next year to implement “a system of monitoring and warning indicators of risks related to the defense of national security”. Chan Tsz King, who until December 2024 served as commissioner against Corruption, spoke during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for 2026, in the Legislative Assembly (AL). The former prosecutor promised to “remain highly vigilant in the face of the new and complex panorama” of international security and warned of “multiple factors of uncertainty that could compromise the security of the State”.
Prevention matters
Macau will “strictly prevent acts of interference and destruction [by] external forces”, guaranteed Chan, highlighting the importance of guaranteeing security in “major events”.
Between the 9th and 21st of November, the regions of Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong hosted the 15th edition of the National Games. On November 18, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, said that Macau received 2,480 people in delegations to the National Games. More than two million tourists passed through the city during the event.
During yesterday's LAG debate, MP Lam Lon Wai defended the creation of “standardized security guidelines and procedures” for large events, including concerts. Chan Tsz King, who took office on October 16, promised to study Lam Lon Wai's suggestion, but stressed that authorities already have “specific [security] plans for different types of activity”.
The secretary said that this year, the police “effectively prevented and investigated crimes against national security, deterring and combating anti-China and disruptive Macau individuals.”
On July 31, local police authorities announced the arrest of former deputy and pro-democracy activist Au Kam San, a Portuguese citizen, in the first case under the region's national security law, which came into force in 2009 and whose scope was expanded in 2023.
Last Thursday, the head of the European Union (EU) Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau wrote on social media that he had met with Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Anton Tai Kin Ip. “I also expressed concern about political issues,” added Briton Harvey Rouse. But the EU representation declined to reveal whether the case of Au Kam San was mentioned at the meeting.
Smuggling | Secretary highlights stability
The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, stressed that the security situation in the territory is stable. “Between January and October 2025, the crime rate in Macau decreased compared to the same period in 2024”, he said, highlighting “the decreasing trend” in crimes such as “serious violence, theft, theft and computer fraud”, so “security in general remains stable and good”.
However, Chan Tsz King highlighted the occurrence of several cases of smuggling, and in the first ten months of the year alone, 108 people “of school age” were intercepted, “seven times more than the same period” last year. The secretary also spoke of the occurrence, this year, of 126 cases of smuggling detected by the Customs Services.
"We have established a communication mechanism with schools to reinforce compliance with the law. We will resort to a cooperation mechanism with the three parties [Hong Kong, Macau and Guangdong] to combat smuggling."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Gaza | Xi calls for the Strip to be under Palestinian control</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/gaza-xi-defende-que-faixa-fique-sob-controlo-palestiniano/</link><description>The Chinese President called for the reconstruction of the Gaza Strip to be carried out under the principle of “Palestinians govern Palestine” and urged the international community to promote a “comprehensive and lasting ceasefire”.
Xi Jinping stated that the Palestinian issue “affects international equity and justice” and constitutes “a test of the effectiveness of the global governance system”, said the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs. In a message sent to a UN meeting on Tuesday, the Chinese leader argued that the international community must “take responsibility, correct historical injustices and defend justice”.
On the occasion of the International Day of Solidarity with the Palestinian People, Xi stressed that any post-war structure must respect “the will of the Palestinian people” and take into account the legitimate concerns of countries in the region. The Chinese leader insisted that efforts must “be anchored in the two-state solution” to achieve a “comprehensive, fair and lasting” political agreement.
The Chinese President said that the immediate priority is to improve the humanitarian situation and alleviate the suffering of civilians in Gaza, and reiterated that Beijing, as a permanent member of the Security Council, “will continue to support the just cause of the Palestinian people to restore their legitimate national rights”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:09:18</pubDate></item><item><title>DSPA | Renewed Director Service Committee</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/dspa-comissao-de-servico-de-director-renovada/</link><description>Ip Kuong Lam's service commission as director of Environmental Protection Services has been renewed for a period of one year, according to an order published yesterday in the Official Gazette.
As happens in these situations, the order indicates that the appointee has “appropriate experience and professional capacity to carry out his duties”. Ip Kuong Lam has a bachelor's degree and a master's degree in Environmental Engineering. He entered the public service in 2001, and served as senior technician at the Environment Council, head of the Environmental Pollution Control Department at DSPA and deputy director of DSPA, between 2014 and 2024, when he was promoted to his current position.
IH | Iam Lei Leng's mandate renewed
The mandate of the president of the Housing Institute (IH), Iam Lei Leng, was renewed for a period of one year, according to an order published yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Iam was first appointed to these roles in 2023, during Raimundo do Rosário's period as Secretary for Transport and Public Works.
The renewal of the mandate was justified by the fact that Iam had “appropriate experience and professional capacity to carry out his duties”. Before being appointed president of IH, Iam Lei Leng headed the Department of Studies at the Housing Institute since March 2015.
The current president joined IH, as a technician, in April 1999, remaining in the position for around a year. Between June 2002 and January 2006, he became a senior technician. After completing this mission, he became head of Legal Affairs at the Housing Institute, where he remained until 2015.
Commerce | António Lei dismissed as managing director
António Lei Chi Wai was dismissed from the position of managing director of the Board of Directors of the Macau World Trade Center, according to information released yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Lei will be replaced by Ao Weng Tong, currently a member of the Consumer Council and who will hold both roles.
The decision by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, was published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, but came into force on November 19th. The order does not make it clear whether António Lei Chi Wai will continue to serve as president of the Executive Committee of the Macau World Trade Center. Currently, António Lei has an annual salary of 1.2 million patacas, for both roles, which if divided over 12 months represents a salary of 100 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:28:55</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Satellite casinos’ | Kam Pek closes doors in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/casinos-satelite-kam-pek-fecha-portas-em-macau/</link><description>Macau gaming concessionaire SJM Resorts announced yesterday that the Kam Pek Paradise 'satellite casino', with almost 600 employees, will close on December 1st. SJM said that Kam Pek Parasise “will officially cease operations at 23:59 (Monday, December 1st), thus becoming the seventh ‘satellite casino’ in the region to close its doors.
In a statement, SJM, founded by gaming tycoon Stanley Ho Hung Sun (1921-2020), highlighted that all local employees directly hired by the company have guaranteed employment. SJM explained that staff with resident status in Macau will be “transferred to other company casinos to perform gaming-related functions, according to operational needs”.
Local employees who were not hired directly by SJM Resorts “are invited to apply for related vacancies” within the group, “with priority for hiring” and with conditions equal to those they had. Also yesterday, the Macau Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ) assured that it will “strictly supervise, on site, the closure procedures” of Kam Pek Paradise.
With regard to the 584 casino employees, the DICJ assured, in a press release, that it will maintain communication with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, to ensure compliance with the guarantees given by the SJM, namely “the relocation of all aforementioned workers”. SJM highlighted that “all tables and gaming machines currently operating on site will be transferred to other company casinos”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:11:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Edgar Martins wins Grand Prize Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/edgar-martins-vence-grande-premio-sovereign-portuguese-art-prize-2025/</link><description>Photographer Edgar Martins won the Grand Prize of the Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025, worth 25 thousand euros, for the work “Anton’s Hand is Made of Guilt”, inspired by the disappearance of a friend during wartime. The announcement was made this Tuesday, the day of the opening of the finalists' exhibition, at the Sociedade Nacional de Belas Artes, in Lisbon, during a press visit, led by Howard Bilton, founder and president of the Sovereign Art Foundation (SAF).
This is the fourth edition of this annual award, which is awarded by the SAF Association, the Portuguese branch of the Sovereign Art Foundation, created in 2003 in Hong Kong to promote, support and recognize contemporary art and encourage artistic production, as well as financing programs for disadvantaged children in Portugal.
The winning work, which is also present in the collection of the Museu de Arte Contemporânea Armando Martins (MACAM), is a chromogenic proof, mounted in aluminum and framed, which is part of the series “Anton’s hand is made of Guilt. No muscle of Bone. He has a Gung-ho Finger and a Grief-stricken Thumb” (2023).
Edgar Martins' work explores themes such as war, incarceration, migration, urbanism and technology, with this project, in particular, focusing on the death and disappearance of a friend, photojournalist Anton Hammerl, during the Libyan war in 2011.
Central questions
The work is articulated around a central question: how to narrate a story without witnesses, evidence or traces, and in the absence of the photographic referent itself”, states the catalog information about the work, adding that “more than a tribute, this work portrays a complex story, distorted by absences, which talks about the difficulties of documenting, witnessing and imagining war”.
"While I don't tend to categorize my work as photography in the traditional sense of the term, it is, in virtually every way, photographic. And photography, historically, has not been particularly successful when it is forced to compete with other mediums. So I received this news with surprise and excitement in equal measure. It is, of course, a huge honor to receive such a prestigious award. And what's more, a privilege to know that this financial support will directly contribute to the Sovereign Art Foundation's solidarity program, making me feel part of of something much greater than this isolated artistic feat”, declared the winner, quoted in a statement.
For the president of the jury, David Elliott, it has not been an easy task to find a winner, with the “variety, depth and subtlety of the finalist works”.
"The cruelly savage ironies that confront us in every daily news report are part of the theme of Edgar Martins' winning work. Rooted in both the present and the recent past, it was triggered by the still unexplained disappearance and death of his friend, photojournalist Anton Hammerl, during the Libyan War in 2011. It remains a crime without witnesses or any other evidence, a void that Martins has addressed in other works, as well as in the winning work 'Anton's Hand is Made of Guilt. In Muscle or Bone. He has a Gung-ho Finger and a Grief-stricken Thumb'”, said the president of the jury, quoted by the organization.
In female
This year, for the first time, the Women's Prize was created, created in partnership with the Sassy Women Society, worth two thousand euros, which distinguishes the finalist with the highest score, with the choice going to the artist Alice Marcelino, for the work “Black Skin White Algorithm”.
The 30 finalist works will be on display until December 13th, the date on which the Public Vote prize will be awarded, which can be done in person or online, also worth two thousand euros.
The 30 finalist works that will be on display were chosen by an international jury made up of seven experts – Adelaide Ginga, Armando Cabral, David Eliott, Francisco Trêpa (who won the grand prize in 2024), João Paulo Queiroz, Maura Marvão and Tim Marlow OBE – from around 200 artists proposed by a panel of independent arts professionals, including Portuguese critics, curators and academics.
All finalist works are available for purchase and profits will be divided equally between the artists and SAF's expressive arts programs for disadvantaged children in Portugal.
The Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize is an annual award that celebrates the work of contemporary artists living in Portugal and its diaspora, offering international recognition and financially supporting artists, whilst also raising funds for disadvantaged children in Portugal through the sale of finalist works.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:54:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature | José Cordeiro, former teacher in Macau, launches book of chronicles</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/literatura-jose-cordeiro-ex-docente-em-macau-lanca-livro-de-cronicas/</link><description>It is with the approval of the Writing Workshop that José Cordeiro, who was a physical education teacher in Macau for several years, makes his literary debut. After many chronicles written on the social network Facebook, the encouragement of friends and readers led him to edit “Ao Invés, Pois Claro”, where there is not even a lack of text about what it means to be Macanese
“Ao Invés, Pois Claro” is the title of the first book by José Cordeiro, former resident of Macau and former physical education teacher in the territory. With the approval of Oficina da Escrita, the book has just been published in Portugal and is the result of a series of publications, on different topics, published on the social network Facebook.
According to the description of the work, it is not only a “collection of chronicles”, but also “an invitation to freedom of thought, the exploration of doubt and knowledge”, the “celebration of diversity of opinions” that is carried out with a “relaxed approach”.
"I don't have any specific guidelines for writing a chronicle, it depends on the mood of the moment. It's not something doctrinal, it doesn't intend to influence anything. It's a personal pleasure I have, playing with words", he told HM. Although José Cordeiro has always made physical activity his profession, the truth is that the connection to letters has always existed.
"I've always liked playing with words. I only started writing more systematically recently. I selected some chronicles, like a literary kitchen, where you make soup and a lot of it ends up going to waste", he exemplified. The themes are diverse and “cover religion, politics, friendship, everything and nothing”.
One of the chronicles refers to Macau and being Macanese, a community issue that José Cordeiro knows well. In “State of siege or state of mind”, Cordeiro talks about the existence of the community and says that today, 25 years later, Macanese live “both things”. “It could be a state of siege, because they are limited to a community, which is Portuguese in Chinese territory, and a state of mind, because many people don't live in Macau, but feel Macanese living abroad”, he stressed.
“Ao Invés, Pois Claro” is a name that was born from the author’s desire to be “a little contrary”. "They say I'm stubborn, and so it seems to me [so]. I don't comment on the comments they make on my chronicles, and when I launch a chronicle it stops being mine at that moment, it becomes those who interpret it", he said.
The power of social networks
José Cordeiro believes that “a good way for a person to discipline their reasoning is to write” and writing “is a way of disciplining my intervention in the contacts I make with people”. It's "having a clear idea and, as a first principle, expressing it. It was in a wave of fun that I started doing things, writing. There were people who liked the texts and suggested that I publish them."
"I say it's an album because, for me, it's something else. It's when you take a theme and carry it through to the end", highlighted José Cordeiro, who confesses that social networks "have allowed everything", even giving voice to new authors.
"Sometimes I feel uncomfortable with what is done [on social media], but I am responsible for myself and what I do. I have no intention of indoctrinating or wanting to take anyone wherever. I am a simple citizen who likes to play in my literary kitchen, as I usually call it", he said. José Cordeiro is still preparing a launch session for the work, but it is already for sale on several online platforms.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:53:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul | Bill presented to reduce US taxes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/seul-apresentado-projecto-de-lei-para-reduzir-taxas-dos-eua/</link><description>The ruling party in South Korea yesterday presented a bill to support South Korean investment commitments in the United States in exchange for reduced US tariffs.
The bill provides for the creation of a special fund to finance the promised investment of 350 billion dollars to the United States, in exchange for the reduction of Washington's customs tariffs on vehicles and vehicle parts, among others, from 25 percent to 15 percent.
Of the total amount, 150 billion dollars will be allocated to the North American naval sector, while the remaining 200 billion dollars will be invested, in annual tranches of up to 20 billion dollars, in various strategic US sectors.
Although the legislative proposal will still be analyzed by the South Korean parliament, with the mere presentation of the document the tariff reduction will apply with retroactive effect to November 1st, in line with the bilateral memorandum of understanding signed in the middle of this month.
The South Korean Ministry of Commerce sent a letter to the United States Secretary of Commerce, Howard Lutnick, informing that the proposed law to implement the memorandum of understanding has already been presented to the South Korean National Assembly and requesting that the retroactive reduction be applied accordingly.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:05:04</pubDate></item><item><title>TUI | Reduced sentence for man who tried to kill ex-wife</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/tui-reduzida-pena-a-homem-que-tentou-matar-ex-mulher/</link><description>The Court of Final Instance (TUI) decided to reduce the prison sentence from 11 years and six months to eight years for a man convicted of attempted murder of his ex-wife, as “aggravating circumstances” had not been proven. The man was thus convicted of the attempted crime of simple homicide, in its attempted form, and decreed in the first instance by the Base Judicial Court (TJB), and not the crime of qualified homicide, also in its attempted form.
The TUI understood that the man “only decided to attack B [his ex-wife] after having questioned her and realized that she would not pay the compensation” demanded by him. “Although it appears that the idea of ​​killing B [the woman] came to him since 2017, it was just a thought he had in his mind, and in the period from 2017 to April 2023, no action was taken to implement the idea of ​​killing”, it reads.
The judges also considered, according to the ruling released yesterday, that “it is not clear that A [the accused man] acted coldly when attacking B [the woman]”, which is why the appeal presented by the man was upheld, considering the “excessive severity of the sentence determined” in the second instance.
The case dates back to 2017, and the woman was already a victim of domestic violence during the relationship. The man “held a grudge” against the woman “for having reported his acts of domestic violence and other family disputes, giving him the idea of ​​killing her”.
After the divorce, the man understood that his ex-wife had only obtained the Resident Identity Card (BIR) thanks to the marriage, so “he should pay her an amount as compensation”.
The time of the crime
The crime then began to enter into the plans of this man, who since April 2023 “kept a metal hammer in the box of his motorcycle”. On June 26 of that year, he stopped his motorcycle near his ex-wife's residence and “wandered around waiting for her”, then approached her and “demanded payment of the aforementioned compensation”.
The woman ignored the man and walked away, and that was when the man “removed the metal hammer from the box of his motorcycle, ran after [her] and hit her in the head with the hammer”, and she “consequently fell to the ground”. The ruling describes that, “despite her fall, [the man] continued to hit the victim in the head with the hammer a total of five times, only stopping when he noticed that [the woman] was lying on the floor with decreased consciousness”.
In the first instance, on July 31, 2024, the TJB convicted the man of committing a crime of attempted homicide and a crime of detention and use of a prohibited weapon, which, in legal terms, resulted in a sentence of eight years. Both the man and the Public Prosecutor's Office appealed to the second instance, which increased the sentence to 11 years and six months for the crime of attempted qualified homicide, crime of detention and use of a prohibited weapon. On February 14 of this year, the TUI accepted the convict's appeal and sent the case again to the Court of Second Instance (TSI), which repeated the trial and maintained the sentence of 11 years and six months in prison, but the man did not accept the decision and requested a new appeal, claiming that the TSI “did not fulfill its obligation to carry out a new trial, incurring an error in interpreting and applying the law”, determining “an excessively severe penalty”. The attacker has now managed to see his sentence reduced.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:08:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yi (508-555), Emperor Yuan of Liang (552-555), had a scroll of paintings made documenting, through the portraits of the respective ambassadors, the number of vassal states that in the four directions were tributaries of his kingdom. Thus showing how diverse the faces and clothing of those who lived beyond the borders were.
With the passage of time and unforeseen events caused by the movements of the imperial courts, this scroll would have become damaged, but during the brief Southern Tang dynasty (937-976) its third and last emperor Li Yu (r. 961-976), who cultivated the arts of the brush while neglecting the government of the kingdom, ordered that a copy be made, in ink only. The use of copying as a method would allow the continuity over time of ideas and perceptions, countering the fragility – of the limits of the deterioration of the supports and of the authors' own lives.
The court painter in Jiankang (present-day Nanjing, Jiangsu) chosen to make this Copy of foreign guests entering the court of Emperor Yuan of Liang (Liang Yuandi fanke ruchao tu, at the National Palace Museum, in Taipei) are attributed two other paintings that allude in different ways to circulation and crossing boundaries. In the vertical scroll in ink and color on silk attributed to him, Pond of lotuses and water birds, at the Tokyo National Museum, the natural cycle of the lotus flower is depicted, from the bud to the flower to the withering of the leaves and flowers. In another vertical scroll called Night Hunter returning home on a snowy night (ink and color on silk, 114 x 61 cm, at the Frankfurt Museum of Applied Art, Angewandte Kunst, Frankfurt) we see the figure of a man with an angry appearance, to express powerful, in exquisite clothes to say that he is noble, with an unusual weapon, a trident, from which hang two dead animals that could be two ermines. He comes walking in the snow under a cliff accompanied by a dog whose collar looks like a necklace. In fact, these figures may be telling another story.
Gu Deqian is said to have portrayed in this painting the recognizable figure of popular religion and Daoism called Erlang Shen, the «Divinity of the second boy» with his blue immortal's robes, a caregiver and trustworthy protector, with his sanchaji trident or sanjian liangren qiang, a «three-pronged double-bladed spear» that Manchu shamans used to defeat evil spirits who wanted to cross the border of the other World. Those, like stoats (mustela erminea), were seen as wanderers capable of stealing and replacing people's souls. Erlang shen can be seen in several representations, as here, accompanied by the black dog xiaotian quan, the “howling celestial dog”. The snow will melt but there will be no floods because Erlang shen will not allow it, in the cold of the night the fearsome hunter is after all a figure of stillness.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yi (508-555), Emperor Yuan of Liang (552-555), had a scroll of paintings made documenting, through the portraits of the respective ambassadors, the number of vassal states that in the four directions were tributaries of his kingdom. Thus showing how diverse the faces and clothing of those who lived beyond the borders were.
With the passage of time and unforeseen events caused by the movements of the imperial courts, this scroll would have become damaged, but during the brief Southern Tang dynasty (937-976) its third and last emperor Li Yu (r. 961-976), who cultivated the arts of the brush while neglecting the government of the kingdom, ordered that a copy be made, in ink only. The use of copying as a method would allow the continuity over time of ideas and perceptions, countering the fragility – of the limits of the deterioration of the supports and of the authors' own lives.
The court painter in Jiankang (present-day Nanjing, Jiangsu) chosen to make this Copy of foreign guests entering the court of Emperor Yuan of Liang (Liang Yuandi fanke ruchao tu, at the National Palace Museum, in Taipei) are attributed two other paintings that allude in different ways to circulation and crossing boundaries. In the vertical scroll in ink and color on silk attributed to him, Pond of lotuses and water birds, at the Tokyo National Museum, the natural cycle of the lotus flower is depicted, from the bud to the flower to the withering of the leaves and flowers. In another vertical scroll called Night Hunter returning home on a snowy night (ink and color on silk, 114 x 61 cm, at the Frankfurt Museum of Applied Art, Angewandte Kunst, Frankfurt) we see the figure of a man with an angry appearance, to express powerful, in exquisite clothes to say that he is noble, with an unusual weapon, a trident, from which hang two dead animals that could be two ermines. He comes walking in the snow under a cliff accompanied by a dog whose collar looks like a necklace. In fact, these figures may be telling another story.
Gu Deqian is said to have portrayed in this painting the recognizable figure of popular religion and Daoism called Erlang Shen, the «Divinity of the second boy» with his blue immortal's robes, a caregiver and trustworthy protector, with his sanchaji trident or sanjian liangren qiang, a «three-pronged double-bladed spear» that Manchu shamans used to defeat evil spirits who wanted to cross the border of the other World. Those, like stoats (mustela erminea), were seen as wanderers capable of stealing and replacing people's souls. Erlang shen can be seen in several representations, as here, accompanied by the black dog xiaotian quan, the “howling celestial dog”. The snow will melt but there will be no floods because Erlang shen will not allow it, in the cold of the night the fearsome hunter is after all a figure of stillness.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>Macau gaming concessionaire SJM Resorts announced yesterday that the Kam Pek Paradise 'satellite casino', with almost 600 employees, will close on December 1st. SJM said that Kam Pek Parasise “will officially cease operations at 23:59 (Monday, December 1st), thus becoming the seventh ‘satellite casino’ in the region to close its doors.
In a statement, SJM, founded by gaming tycoon Stanley Ho Hung Sun (1921-2020), highlighted that all local employees directly hired by the company have guaranteed employment. SJM explained that staff with resident status in Macau will be “transferred to other company casinos to perform gaming-related functions, according to operational needs”.
Local employees who were not hired directly by SJM Resorts “are invited to apply for related vacancies” within the group, “with priority for hiring” and with conditions equal to those they had. Also yesterday, the Macau Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ) assured that it will “strictly supervise, on site, the closure procedures” of Kam Pek Paradise.
With regard to the 584 casino employees, the DICJ assured, in a press release, that it will maintain communication with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, to ensure compliance with the guarantees given by the SJM, namely “the relocation of all aforementioned workers”. SJM highlighted that “all tables and gaming machines currently operating on site will be transferred to other company casinos”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>José Simões Morais</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/jose-sm/</link><description>In Macau, most commercial establishments have the image of Kuan Tai (Guan Di in Mandarin), who appears with a strong body, red face, long black beard and dressed as a military officer, holding a spear in his right hand.
As a person, he is known as Guan Yu and is related to the fall of the Han dynasty and the struggles to establish the Shu kingdom, in the period that preceded the Three Kingdoms. With the name Chang Sheng (长生), he was born in Xiezhou (today Yuncheng, Shanxi province), on the 24th day of the sixth lunar month in the 60s of the 2nd century.
As an episode from his youth, it is said that one day a nobleman forcibly wanted to possess a girl and Guan Yu, outraged, killed him. Pursued by the authorities, he had to flee and according to legend, in order not to be recognized, Guanyin (known in Macau as Kun Iam) changed the color of his face to red.
Another story says that a rural owner with a lot of power, in order to force everyone to buy water from him, polluted the other sources in the region. Saturated with such infamy, Guan Yu one day killed him and had to flee the city. During this flight, to cross the border (guan), he took the name Guan Yu.
In the late Eastern Han dynasty (25-220), the decadent court in Luoyang was dominated by eunuchs and generals. Guan Yu was wandering as a street vendor in Zhuo Municipality (now Hebei Province) when he met Liu Bei and Zhang Fei. The three swore an oath in the Peach Garden to become brothers in arms, with Guan Yu and Zhang Fei vowing to help Liu Bei, linked to the royal house of Han, in his armed uprising to establish the Shu-Han kingdom.
At that time there were two other different factions that divided the country and thus in the North, the Wei army led by Cao Cao dominated, in the East and South the Wu forces and in the West, the Shu. There were constant battles between them.
Guan Yu, an avid reader of the Classic “Spring-Autumn Annals” (Chunqiu jing) who always accompanied him, had commanded the Shu garrison in Jingzhou for 10 years. In the year 219/220, while engaged in a battle outside the wall against the Wei forces, he was caught in a surprise attack by the Wu army, which was more or less allied with the Shu. The Wu conquered the city and killed Guan Yu, cutting off his head and, as a proof of friendship, handing it over to Cao Cao. Halfway there they learned that the Wei had made a peace agreement with the Shu and so the head was abandoned near Luoyang.
The process of his deification was long. Although he was only God of War during the Ming period, when in 1578 Emperor Wan Li gave him the title of Emperor Guan (Guan Di), already in the Sui dynasty he had a temple dedicated to him in the place where he was buried, with the titles being given by all the following dynasties.
During his life, Guan Yu had the position of Military Officer (Hou). In the Song dynasty he took the place of King (Wang). Due to his loyalty, honesty, piety, benevolence, sense of justice and courage, he became very popular due to the book San Guo Yan Yi, written at the beginning of the Ming dynasty. In this dynasty he was promoted to Emperor (Di) and then, in 1614, to Sage (Sheng) or Military Saint (Wu Di). As a Being so perfect, all professions want him as their patron and thus he is venerated as the God of War, Literature, Wealth and patron of Martial Arts.
In Macau, Guan Di is known as Kuan Tai and the Sam Kai Wui Kun temple, located on Rua Sul of the S. Domingos market, is dedicated to him. There, the image of the God is entirely golden, with no objects in his hands and is accompanied on his left by Chau Chong and on the other side by Kuan Peng. His birthday falls on the 24th of the sixth lunar month, although no festivities are officially held in his honor.
灶神 Zao Shen – the god of the Stove
The god of the Stove, known in Macau as Tchôu-Sân (in Mandarin Zao Shen), is the most important of the domestic deities and twice a month (during the New Moon and the Full Moon) he received offerings, despite his birthday only being celebrated on the third day of the eighth Moon. However, the most important ceremonies performed to this god are those that occur before the week-long journey, when the god leaves home and goes to Heaven to perform the annual report to the Jade Emperor about the family of the residence where he is placed. And that is why this god, also known as the god of the Kitchen, as for simplification he came to be called the god of the Kitchen Chimney, has great power over the lives of the people who form the household. It is in the last week of the lunar year that he ascends to Heaven to meet with the Jade Emperor, where he reports to him the events that took place in the room in his charge, returning on the first day of the year, where he is placed again in the kitchen, behind the stove.
On the eve of the trip, on the twenty-third day of the last lunar month, the inhabitants of the house offer sacrifices to this deity, filling him with sweets so that he only tells good things to the Jade Emperor.
In a ceremony performed only by men, the god of Stove leaves transported on a horse and to make the journey easy and pleasant, one of the male beings in the house takes a candle and burns the image of the god so that it can more easily ascend through smoke to Heaven.
Before being named by the Jade Emperor as God of the Stove, or of the Kitchen, he was a husband who, having spent all his money gambling and selling his wife, years later, while begging on the streets, arrived at his former wife's house. She, recognizing him and taking pity on him, takes him to the kitchen where she gives him something to eat. But her current husband arrives and so she doesn't see him, she hides him in the fireplace. When the maid lights the fire, so as not to compromise the charitable woman, she stays there. The Jade Emperor, seeing his sacrifice, named him the god of the Stove, also known as the god of the Kitchen, or the god of the Home.
There are other versions of both how the man lost the money and how his ex-wife supported him. She, without being recognized by her ex-husband, gave him some cakes and placed a coin in each one. The man, on the way, met another beggar, who, upon seeing the bag with cakes, asked him for one. He discovered the coin in the middle of the cake and, realizing that the other didn't know about the filling, proposed keeping them all, which he managed in exchange for a small amount. When he later found out what he had done, realizing his bad luck, he decided to commit suicide. The Jade Emperor, seeing his kindness, named him god of the Kitchen.
The celebration of this deity's journey to Heaven began in summer, but during the Han dynasty it moved to winter and during the Ming dynasty it was celebrated by the people on the 24th, with sacrifices taking place the day before. Zao Shen is represented in an image containing only his figure, or associated with his consort, or even just characters, which is placed on the first day of the lunar year in the kitchen behind the stove.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yi (508-555), Emperor Yuan of Liang (552-555), had a scroll of paintings made documenting, through the portraits of the respective ambassadors, the number of vassal states that in the four directions were tributaries of his kingdom. Thus showing how diverse the faces and clothing of those who lived beyond the borders were.
With the passage of time and unforeseen events caused by the movements of the imperial courts, this scroll would have become damaged, but during the brief Southern Tang dynasty (937-976) its third and last emperor Li Yu (r. 961-976), who cultivated the arts of the brush while neglecting the government of the kingdom, ordered that a copy be made, in ink only. The use of copying as a method would allow the continuity over time of ideas and perceptions, countering the fragility – of the limits of the deterioration of the supports and of the authors' own lives.
The court painter in Jiankang (present-day Nanjing, Jiangsu) chosen to make this Copy of foreign guests entering the court of Emperor Yuan of Liang (Liang Yuandi fanke ruchao tu, at the National Palace Museum, in Taipei) are attributed two other paintings that allude in different ways to circulation and crossing boundaries. In the vertical scroll in ink and color on silk attributed to him, Pond of lotuses and water birds, at the Tokyo National Museum, the natural cycle of the lotus flower is depicted, from the bud to the flower to the withering of the leaves and flowers. In another vertical scroll called Night Hunter returning home on a snowy night (ink and color on silk, 114 x 61 cm, at the Frankfurt Museum of Applied Art, Angewandte Kunst, Frankfurt) we see the figure of a man with an angry appearance, to express powerful, in exquisite clothes to say that he is noble, with an unusual weapon, a trident, from which hang two dead animals that could be two ermines. He comes walking in the snow under a cliff accompanied by a dog whose collar looks like a necklace. In fact, these figures may be telling another story.
Gu Deqian is said to have portrayed in this painting the recognizable figure of popular religion and Daoism called Erlang Shen, the «Divinity of the second boy» with his blue immortal's robes, a caregiver and trustworthy protector, with his sanchaji trident or sanjian liangren qiang, a «three-pronged double-bladed spear» that Manchu shamans used to defeat evil spirits who wanted to cross the border of the other World. Those, like stoats (mustela erminea), were seen as wanderers capable of stealing and replacing people's souls. Erlang shen can be seen in several representations, as here, accompanied by the black dog xiaotian quan, the “howling celestial dog”. The snow will melt but there will be no floods because Erlang shen will not allow it, in the cold of the night the fearsome hunter is after all a figure of stillness.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>November 25th | Manuel Geraldes remembers “moment of betrayal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/25-de-novembro-manuel-geraldes-recorda-momento-de-traicao/</link><description>Portugal marked the 50th anniversary of November 25, 1975 yesterday with a military parade and a solemn session in the Assembly of the Republic, amidst controversies and political readings from right to left. Manuel Geraldes, a former soldier based in Macau, remembers the moment he was arrested at RTP
For Manuel Geraldes, if happiness had a date it would be April 25, 1974, along with the day his daughter was born. But it was in connection with the 50th anniversary of November 25, 1975, an attempted coup d'état and one of the stages of the revolutionary process that began with the overthrow of the dictatorship in Portugal on April 25, 1974, that we spoke with the former soldier.
Based in Macau since the 1980s, Manuel Geraldes was arrested at RTP on November 25, 1975, but, as one of the youngest captains of April, he was involved in the revolution since its beginning, starting with the so-called captains' movement in 1973.
To HM, he remembers the 25th of November as “a very sad moment, of betrayal by comrades, revolt, a horrible moment, especially compared to one of the happiest days of my life, together with the birth of my daughter, which was the 25th of April”, taking into account the military plans planned for that day, which took a different turn. Manuel Geraldes worked at RTP when the station was controlled by one of the military factions that carried out the 25th of November. Control of RTP, at the Lumiar studios in Lisbon, included the intervention of figures such as Manuel Duran Clemente, then linked to the military extreme left of the 5th Division.
"When we talk about the 25th of November we have to talk about a day of betrayal. Those who were betrayed were the soldiers who remained faithful to their ideas of the 25th of April and who swore to comply with it, and which we were fulfilling. There was a group of soldiers who, forgetting their condition, and I'm talking more about permanent staff officers, made that day of shame for any self-respecting officer."
Manuel Geraldes had been at RTP for about a year and was “caught in that trap”. I went to meet my comrades at the television news management office and it was there that we were caught by Captain Duran Clemente”, he tells HM.
“I can talk about those who were closest to me, and who were at RTP that day”, he began by saying. "Those who were on the 25th of April and arrested me, as they arrested six other officers, all of them 'dangerous fascists, reactionaries'. Also arrested that day was a man who was a great revolutionary, and who, still as a student at the military academy, studying at Técnico, committed the noble gesture of leaving the armed forces of the fascist regime to emigrate to northern Europe. The 'powerful' Marques, who had been in the Beja coup, and who was arrested, and managed to go into exile in Brazil. Captain Canavilhas, a ‘dangerous’ man who had been on the 25th of April and who was there providing a service to the Republic at RTP as an electrical engineer.”
Duran Clemente appeared at RTP's facilities to control broadcasts, prohibit the dissemination of information from the Presidency of the Republic, since Costa Gomes was President at the time, and let messages from rebels linked to a faction of the movement pass through. The station's board of directors was detained for several hours. His live images are known on RTP, reading a statement, when he was suddenly interrupted and replaced in the broadcast by the film “The Man from the Diner’s Club”. This is because the winning faction of the 25 de Novembro movement had taken control of events from the RTP studios in Porto.
Speaking to the newspaper Público, Duran Clemente also speaks of November 25th as “a betrayal of April 25th, in the way it has been interpreted and was interpreted, to the extent that it interrupted the natural course of a revolution that is never a natural path”.
Duran Clemente also speaks, in the same interview, of the “fantasy story of a civil war” that many believe was about to happen in Portugal on that date. He also says “he did not commit any crime”.
For Manuel Geraldes, these moments of detention “were indescribable, unbelievable, forgettable”. When he left the RTP studios, Manuel Geraldes went home to his wife, “trying to rest and try to forget the enormous sadness that was that scene”, with “the soldiers he had commanded on April 25, 1974, observing that absurd arrest that Duran Clemente made of us”.
The culmination of tensions
The 25th of November was an attempted coup d'état in which military personnel linked to the extreme left took several strategic points, especially in Lisbon, which led the country to enter a state of siege. But the moderates won and the country entered a calmer phase, especially after the new Constitution of 1976. It was a culmination of the so-called “Hot Summer”, or the months of the PREC – Revolutionary Period in Progress, marked by nationalizations of banks and companies, the Agrarian Reform process, organization of workers committees, attacks on the headquarters of the Portuguese Communist Party and various actions connoted with both the extreme left and the far right.
Manuel Geraldes recalls that “the situation was complex and was not exactly what we had imagined” with the 25th of April. “We had designed other scenarios than that, but with great camaraderie.” Even so, the former soldier highlights the “stability and credibility” that Portugal gained after November 25, 1975. However, he does not agree with the fact that the Portuguese authorities are currently celebrating this date.
"There is definitely a political component and, for me, it makes absolutely no sense. We shouldn't forget the past to correct any mistakes that were made, but celebrating a sad day makes no sense at all. We must remember."
Regarding the important and decisive figures in resolving the 25th of November, Manuel Geraldes highlights “general Costa Gomes, who experienced such vast violence, Sousa e Castro and others who had consensus and managed to bring the vast majority of the armed forces to reason”. Mário Soares, as leader of the Socialist Party, “also had [importance]” to stop the movement, especially because “he had positions close to the so-called ‘Group of Nine’, the moderate members of the Coordinating Commission of the Armed Forces Movement”.
Manuel Geraldes also remembers a day when the factions were ruled by “military against military”, and when “the homeland was put at risk”, in a scenario “very, very close to civil war”.  Yesterday morning, a military ceremony took place promoted by the Armed Forces, at Praça do Comércio, in Lisbon, presided over by the President of the Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa. There was also a formal session in the Assembly of the Republic.
Vasco Lourenço: “A coup d’état was not on the ground”
In addition to the official ceremonies of the 25th of November 1975, there have been several exhibitions, lectures and conferences that celebrate all stages of the revolution of the 25th of April 1974. One of them took place on Tuesday, the seminar “25th of November – 50 years later”, at the Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, where one of the central figures of the 25th of November and the entire April revolution, Vasco Lourenço, remembered the day.
"It is clear that, after all this time, we cannot say that a coup d'état was on the ground. But I challenge anyone who is capable of saying that, at that time, given what was happening, we did not look at it as if a coup d'état were actually taking place."
After several military movements, in which the paratrooper forces retreated, the episodes of November 25th resulted in three deaths, all military personnel, “at the beginning of November 27th”, recalled Vasco Lourenço.
The role of women
Another figure who participated in the debate was doctor Isabel do Carmo, who at the time of November 25th was linked to the COPCON group – Continent Operational Command, led by the now deceased Otelo Saraiva de Carvalho.
Isabel do Carmo argued that “what happened after the 25th of April was the existence of a space of people, organizations and political protagonists, in which there were clearly two trends”, marked by “those who wanted to lead a revolutionary movement to de facto socialism, and those who wanted a liberal democracy with an economy regulated by a market”.
"The 25th of April was, and for many people of my generation, the best times of my life. I hear many people say this, particularly women, who until then were discreet. What happened after [the 25th of April] were the public sessions, freedom of the press, the total change in the environment in schools, there was a great transformation in the country", concluded Isabel do Carmo.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:15:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Timorese women victims of sexual violence during the war demand an end to discrimination</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/mulheres-timorenses-vitimas-de-violencia-sexual-da-guerra-exigem-fim-da-discriminacao/</link><description>Reporting by Domingos Freitas, from the Lusa agency
The Pirilampo association, which represents women victims of sexual violence between 1974 and 1999, demands that the Timorese State supports them, after years of discrimination by society and their families.
"We continue to fight alone because we were victims in the past, not of our own free will. We have suffered the consequences of this country's politics since 1974, because we wanted self-determination. Because of these political decisions, we, women, were the target of many sexual violations", Maria Isabel da Silva, president of Pirilampo, told Lusa, as part of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence and Indonesian occupation.
Maria Isabel da Silva accused the Timorese State of not having granted them recognition that could help them recover their courage and dignity.
"We created Pirilampo because we know that we are not minor survivors. We are survivors of sexual violence that occurred during the war, between 1974 and 1999. We want to recover dignity, because many face stigma in their communities and even within their own families", explained Maria Isabel da Silva.
The president of Pirilampo explained that the organization's mission is to support women survivors of sexual violence through social, legal and economic assistance so that they become strong and independent citizens. The association also defends the rights of victims and survivors who remain without a voice, so that they can obtain recognition and attention from the State or Government.
Maria Isabel da Silva clarified that Pirilampo's vision is to contribute to ensuring that Timorese society never again allows anyone to be a victim of serious human rights violations, especially sexual violence, including harassment, abuse, rape or forced marriage.
The president of Pirilampo also regretted that cultural aspects discriminate against women who became pregnant or had children by unidentified men. "Sometimes they are considered prostitutes, remnants of the Indonesian military. These are insults that have been directed at us for a long time," he said.
With support from the Chega Ba Ita Association (ACBIT) and Asia Justice and Rights (AJAR), several victims participated in various activities and, on October 22, 2022, these organizations helped them create the Klibur Survivor Feto Firefly 1974-1999, to alleviate the suffering and difficulties faced.
Pirilampo has already registered 455 women survivors of sexual violence, of which 87 gave birth to children resulting from these violations. To this day, those children, often called “war children”, face a very difficult life, due to discrimination by their families, society and, above all, in the public administration.
"They call them children of unknown fathers, children of bush men, of militia. This greatly affects their self-esteem and many refuse to go to school", warned the president. Maria Isabel Silva explains that many of these young people are also unable to obtain basic documents, such as baptism certificates from the Church or State documents. They live in remote areas, depend on agriculture and do not have adequate access to health and education.
The president called on the Government to pay attention and recognize these people like any other citizen, so that their children can also live in freedom and equality. "We are alive. We don't ask for anything, we don't ask for money. The money from the State is not enough to pay for our dignity. We lost our bodies, we carry pain and trauma. We just want to recover our complete being. We don't ask for money", said an emotional Maria Isabel Silva.
There is still discrimination
Fernanda Guterres and Maria Gusmão were born after their mothers were raped by Indonesian soldiers during the occupation of Timor-Leste, and to this day they continue to face discrimination in their country. The two carry the stigma of being “war children”, a name given to people who were born to women who were raped between 1974 and 1999, during the conflict between various Timorese factions and during the Indonesian occupation.
"I don't feel free, because I continue to face discrimination from society. Colleagues say words to me that hurt me, and I myself am afraid of making friends because of the harsh words they say to me", Fernanda Guterres, who works at the non-governmental organization ACBIT, which supports, with Asia Justice and Rights (AJAR), the "children of war" and women victims of sexual violence during the occupation to overcome the difficulties and traumas that marked their lives, told Lusa.
“I only feel a little freedom when I participate in oratory sessions or in training given by the sisters, which encourage young people to face reality”, he highlighted. The report by the Commission for Reception, Truth and Reconciliation (CAVR), released 20 years ago, and which collected testimonies from hundreds of victims of sexual violence, states that the majority was committed by the Indonesian occupation forces.
"We are Children of War because our mothers were forced and impregnated by other men during the occupation. Otherwise, the invaders would have killed the entire family. To save their own lives, many Timorese women suffered sexual violence", explained Fernanda Guterres. As a consequence of this forced rape, “war children” continue to be targets of insults and stigma. “You have no father”, “you are the son of the enemy” or “son of a militia”, are some of the insults that those women continue to hear.
When she was little, Fernanda Guterres' mother told her that her father was alive, but she never met him. She later discovered that it didn't exist, but her mother never explicitly admitted it. "I asked about my mother and father many times. My mother always said 'your father is there', and said not to believe if someone said otherwise. But I never met him. In the end, I realized that I didn't have a father", he said.
Fernanda Guterres also remembers, with sadness, the attempts of sexual violence by members of the community, solely due to her mother's past. "The family and also some neighbors tried to abuse me. When I was an adult, I stopped keeping quiet and asked my family to face anyone who tried to harm me", said the 28-year-old.
Today, Fernanda has her own family, with three children, and said she has found a partner who fully supports her. "I met my husband thanks to God's plan. He knew about my mother's past and his whole family knew too, but they never discriminated against me. They always welcomed me. My husband supports me, gives me courage. The past is behind us. Now we look to the future and our children. That's what gives me strength", she stated.
"We live a simple life. We don't have formal jobs, but we always maintain respect and mutual understanding. When a problem arises at home, we talk and look for a solution together", he said. Fernanda Guterres managed to obtain documents from the Church or State, thanks to the support of people who helped her regularize everything.
Maria Gusmão also acknowledged that her mother was a victim of sexual violence by Indonesian soldiers. "When I was little, in primary school and pre-secondary school, I suffered discrimination due to the conflict my mother faced. They said I was the daughter of the militia, the daughter of the enemy. I heard this with my own ears", said the young woman from Covalima.
He also remembers that some members of his community even banned children from playing with him. Later, at university and even within his family, he continued to face discrimination. Despite this, Maria Robinson appealed to other young women not to lose their will to fight, nor their hope, even in the face of discrimination, highlighting that the State must dignify women who have been victims of sexual violence and also their children.
Maria Robinson was able to obtain documents because her stepfather agreed to put her name on the birth certificates. When asked about her feeling of freedom, she replied that she just feels “a little free”, highlighting that she still faces discrimination, stigma and injustice today. “From the family, to society, to the community and even to our own State”, said the 25-year-old. Maria Robinson recently completed her degree at the University of Peace (UNPAZ) and also works at the non-governmental organization ACBIT.
On November 28, Timor-Leste marks 50 years since the unilateral declaration of independence and Indonesian occupation, on December 7, 1975. The restoration of independence took place on May 20, 2002, after a referendum for self-determination was held on August 30, 1999.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 20:06:22</pubDate></item><item><title>LAG | Government restricts the use of “Western” devices because they represent a “risk”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/lag-governo-restringe-uso-de-aparelhos-ocidentais-por-representarem-um-risco/</link><description>The Government is betting on Chinese electronic devices, to avoid risks associated with equipment coming from countries with a “hostile stance” towards China. Wong Sio Chak revealed that all public servants, including Portuguese, will take an oath of loyalty to China and Macao by the end of the year
The Government revealed on Friday that the Public Administration is giving priority to Chinese electronic devices, because those coming from Western countries “with a hostile stance towards China” represent “a risk”.
“Instructions have already been issued by the DSAFP [Directorate of Administration and Public Function Services], especially for critical infrastructures,” said the Macau Secretary for Administration and Justice. “We considered, as a priority, the use of devices from our country” in RAM’s government services and departments, highlighted Wong Sio Chak.
The leader admitted to the Legislative Assembly that “there is a risk” in the supply of electronic telecommunications devices. “It is a very sensitive issue and one in which there is also a fragility”, said Wong, pointing the finger at “Western countries, especially some with a hostile stance towards China”.
However, the secretary highlighted, during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action for 2026 in the area of ​​Administration and Justice, that the limitations only apply to the public administration of Macau. "We have an open market and we will not restrict the private sector to use foreign devices. Entities and the private sector have the freedom to choose these devices", explained Wong.
On October 19, the Central Government accused the United States of carrying out a cyber-attack against the National Time Service Center (NTSC), responsible for maintaining the accuracy of the country's official time.
The Chinese Ministry of State Security said the “systematic and long-planned” attack began in 2022, through a vulnerability in the SMS (short message) service of a “foreign brand” of mobile phones. The vulnerability made it possible to “covertly attack and gain control of the cell phones of several NTSC employees and steal confidential data stored on them”, said the ministry.
Faithful and loyal
Another highlight of Wong Sio Chak's presentation was the oath of loyalty to China and the Macao SAR that all public servants, including those of Portuguese nationality, will have to take by the end of the year. The oath is part of a review of the statutes of management and leadership staff and Public Administration workers, which came into force on 1 November.
The two revised laws determine that workers already in office have 90 days to take the oath, with refusal automatically implying the annulment of the appointment to the position or dismissal. But the Secretary for Administration and Justice said he believes the process will be completed sooner and that “all public service workers will take the oath by the end of this year”.
Wong Sio Chak, who took office on October 16, defended during the presentation of the Governing Action Lines for 2026 that the review “improved the management and accountability regime of management and leadership staff”. On November 1st, 264 directors of public entities and services took an oath in a ceremony, declaring that “they will dedicate themselves with all loyalty to the Macau Special Administrative Region [SAR] of the People's Republic of China”.
In a speech given during the ceremony, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, asked civil service leaders to “firmly safeguard the full governance power of the Chinese Central Government”.
In December 2024, the Legislative Assembly approved, unanimously and without any debate, the law that provides that public servants in Macau can be dismissed if they carry out “acts contrary” to their oath. A month earlier, when presenting the proposal, the then Executive Council spokesman, André Cheong, warned that public servants could be fired due to private conversations or comments published on social media.
The oath will be mandatory for all public officials, including Portuguese ones, but it can be taken in Portuguese, one of Macau's two official languages, along with Chinese.
According to the most recent Public Administration Human Resources Report, in 2023 the region had 34,311 public employees. The document does not mention how many have Portuguese nationality, only mentioning that 257 were born in Portugal. The two proposals also oblige public servants to take the oath in a “sincere and solemn” manner. The sincerity of the oath will be assessed by the hierarchical superior and any dismissal may be appealed to the courts.
Every head
The Government wants to launch, at the beginning of 2026, negotiations with Portugal on an agreement for the reciprocal recognition of civil and commercial judgments.
Macau's Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, said that he intends to “strengthen judicial cooperation abroad and further expand legal exchange”.
According to the LAG report, Macau wants, from the first quarter of 2026, to start negotiating an “agreement on the reciprocal confirmation and enforcement of judicial decisions in civil and commercial matters” with Portugal. However, the document does not mention any date for the conclusion of negotiations and the eventual signing of a final agreement.
Macau and Portugal signed an agreement in 2019 regarding the surrender of fugitive offenders, whose criminal legality was called into question by the Portuguese Bar Association. The protocol is not in force, as it was not voted on in the Assembly of the Republic.
The Macau LAG report also reveals plans to conclude, by the end of 2026, three agreements with Angola for the transfer of convicted people, the delivery of fugitive offenders and mutual legal assistance in criminal cases. These three agreements with Angola have been mentioned in the Macau LAG since November 2023, and that report pointed to the end of 2024 as a target for concluding the negotiations.
Angola and mainland China signed an extradition treaty in 2006, which was only approved by the Angolan Parliament in 2011, and was ratified by the Government of Luanda two years later.
During the discussion in the Angolan Parliament, the then Angolan deputy minister of Justice, João Monteiro, defended the importance of the agreement due to the large migratory movement between the two countries. At the time, authorities estimated that close to 50,000 Chinese lived in Angola, working mainly in construction, in reconstruction projects financed largely by loans granted by China.
João Monteiro guaranteed that the two States agreed that extradition requests cannot include crimes of a political or military nature.
Macau Simplex
Wong Sio Chak reiterated to the deputies an old promise from the Administration and Justice department: administrative simplification. The government priority will aim to speed up processes and licenses, for example, for commercial establishments. In response to a question from Deputy Si Ka Lon, the Secretary for Administration and Justice said that, “as long as there are no major works”, a food and beverage establishment can obtain a license to operate in two days, upon presentation of all the required documents. The government official stressed that behind the flexibility of the administration machine are the concepts of “simplifying, decentralizing and optimizing”.
Get to work
The Secretary for Administration and Justice stated in the Legislative Assembly that the Government will continue efforts to implement the quota system for Public Service workers and reorganize some careers, eliminating those that are outdated and promoting mobility. Wong Sio Chak highlighted that since the launch of the quota management system in the Administration, in 2020, the number of public servants has increased, and that before changing the rules for progression or access between careers in the administrative machinery, the Government will listen to workers.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 04:52:12</pubDate></item><item><title>East Timor | April Revolution left “difficult memories”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/timor-leste-revolucao-de-abril-deixou-memorias-dificeis/</link><description>Marisa Ramos Gonçalves, researcher at the University of Coimbra, addresses, in a study, the experiences of the Timorese during the period of the 25th of April
Marisa Ramos Gonçalves, a researcher at the Center for Social Sciences at the University of Coimbra, considered that the April revolution in Timor-Leste left “difficult memories” and that reconciliation is fundamental for “national cohesion”.
“When we talk about the 25th of April in Timor, we know that we are talking about difficult memories that have left marks to this day due to the internal conflict and the violation of human rights during the occupation”, Marisa Ramos Gonçalves, who is currently carrying out a study on that period in the country, told Lusa.
Marisa Ramos Gonçalves is also a member of the International Advisory Board of the National Chega Center (in Timor-Leste), which, among other activities, documents the history of the conflict in Timor-Leste between 1974 and 1999.
The researcher explained to Lusa that the objective is to understand the other side of the story “based on the experiences of the Timorese of the 25th of April and this period of transition, which gives rise to a proclamation of independence, but which is very short compared to the occupation”.
“This collective memory of the Timorese is inseparable, both from the internal conflict and from the human tragedy that is the Indonesian invasion and occupation”, highlighted Marisa Ramos Gonçalves.
The unilateral proclamation of Timor-Leste's independence, on November 28, 1975, came after a period marked by clashes between the East Timorese and already under the shadow of the possibility of occupation of the territory by Indonesia, which came to fruition on December 7, 1975. Asked about reconciliation between East Timorese, the researcher said that the “issue has been on the table”.
"It is necessary to achieve reconciliation between Timorese who were on opposite sides during the civil conflict with different options for the future of Timor. At the time, UDT wanted an association with Portugal for a few more years before independence, Fretilin wanted immediate independence, and Apodeti, which wanted integration into Indonesia and they are all Timorese", he stated.
According to Marisa Gonçalves, the National Chega Center wants “this to start being on the table, because it has not been easy until now for Timorese who suffered torture or were persecuted during the period of internal conflict to speak openly”.
"But we are already beginning to see this possibility when talking about violence and torture, which existed for a very short period in 1975, but which left strong marks. There is also a reconciliation at the level of political leadership that is yet to be achieved and I think this is also complicated. It is a reconciliation of the entire society", stated Marisa Ramos Gonçalves.
Larger opening
Considering reconciliation between Timorese people as fundamental for social cohesion, the researcher highlights, on the other hand, that the new generations formed in the Indonesian period and the younger ones “are completely prepared for this reconciliation”.
“They are not so tied to previous conflicts and they really want to reconcile and, therefore, I think they are already looking at that future, they already think that all people are part of the Timorese Nation, including the Timorese who are in West Timor”, where there is a community of around 80,000 people, he highlighted.
"It is also important that the older generation reconciles, especially because it is still a generation, the so-called generation of 75, that continues in power. It would also be interesting for them to take the initiative to get closer", he added.
Regarding the study she is carrying out, Marisa Ramos Gonçalves said that there is a lack of historical research in Timor-Leste and that it is good to understand the expectations that people had not only in relation to the 25th of April, but also in relation to the political transition.
“It means knowing the narratives, the experiences, the memories of Timorese people of various geographic origins, professional occupations and party affiliations about the same historical moment”, he explained, highlighting that reconciliation is also achieved through the writing of history.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:00:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Decolonization in Timor-Leste left deep traumas in the Portuguese military, argues researcher</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/23/descolonizacao-em-timor-leste-deixou-traumas-profundos-nos-militares-portugueses-defende-investigadora/</link><description>The researcher at the Institute of Contemporary History at Universidade Nova Zélia Pereira stated that the decolonization process in Timor-Leste left deep traumas in the Portuguese military, leading many to silence during the period of Indonesian occupation.
“The decolonization process in Timor, in addition to the trauma of the Indonesian invasion for the Timorese themselves, left profound traumas for the Portuguese military, personal and psychological traumas, consequences for their professional careers, most of them ended up abandoning military life, because they were successively passed over for promotions,” the researcher told Lusa.
“Lemos Pires, when he was promoted to general, there was an internal campaign against him,” he said. General Mário Lemos Pires was the last governor of Portuguese Timor (between November 8, 1974 and November 27, 1975).
Zélia Pereira is coordinating, together with Pedro Aires de Oliveira, professor of History at the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences at Universidade Nova, the reissue of the report prepared by the commission for the analysis and clarification of the decolonization process of Timor-Leste, created by former President Ramalho Eanes, which will include declassified testimonies from military and civilian personnel heard in 1975 and 1976.
The project is being financed by the Foundation for Science and Technology, with the support of the commission for the celebration of the 50th anniversary of the 25th of April, as part of a competition for exploratory projects.
"It is such a huge trauma that throughout the entire period of Indonesian occupation, apart from Lemos Pires, no other soldier wanted to speak. After the referendum, some memoirs began to be published and only now more recently have they started to agree to do some interviews", explained the researcher.
According to Zélia Pereira, the testimonies given in 1976, with the “very fresh memory” and the “very vivid trauma” will allow access to a very “detailed, very interesting” set of information. The researcher also hopes that these testimonies will help the Timorese to “better understand a period that was very traumatic for them”.
“We need to understand the following, even today books continue to be published, articles that replicate all the accusations made in 1975. In doctoral and master's theses, because they are based on books published in the 70s, 80s, 2000s, up until the present and which still today are based on ideas and assumptions, which are not all 100% wrong, but which need to have other interpretations”, he highlighted.
History, said Zélia Pereira, is about placing several contexts under analysis simultaneously, because no one owns the truth. “What we want is for this to open up other perspectives, other research perspectives, and heal hurts, reconcile people with their past, regardless of whether they made decisions that didn’t turn out to be the right ones,” he added.
Timor-Leste became independent from Portugal on November 28, 1975, but nine days later, on December 7, it was occupied by Indonesia.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 18:47:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Venezuela | Maduro declares that country will never be defeated</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/05/venezuela-maduro-declara-que-pais-jamais-sera-derrotado/</link><description>The President of Venezuela declared yesterday that the country will never be defeated and that the Venezuelan people will respond to what he considered to be a psychological war orchestrated by the United States.
Speaking to the official Venezuelan television station VTV, Nicolás Maduro stated that the authorities and people of Venezuela will respond with work and achievements to the “psychological war”, referring to the North American Administration as “media scoundrels” from Miami. “How do you say ‘imbecile’ in English?” asked Maduro, warning those “who want to do harm” will never be able to defeat Venezuela.
Washington has intensified military operations off Venezuela in recent days, reiterating accusations against Maduro that he promotes drug trafficking.
The North American head of state, Donald Trump, also authorized new attacks against vessels, allegedly belonging to drug trafficking networks, near the Venezuelan coast. Maduro added that Venezuelan security forces have seized 63 tons of drugs since the beginning of the year.
On the other hand, the Venezuelan leader also denounced the attempt to enter Venezuela by two planes linked to drug trafficking. In the same speech, Maduro declared that Venezuela and Russia are making progress in military cooperation, which he described as peaceful and fruitful.
Daily contact
Asked about contacts between Caracas and Moscow in the context of “threats” from the United States, Maduro stated that the government maintains daily communication with Russian President Vladimir Putin on “several developing issues”, including military matters.
On Sunday, the Russian Presidency admitted having maintained contacts with Venezuela regarding a possible request for help from Maduro to Putin. At the same time, the People's Republic of China stated that there is normal cooperation between Beijing and Caracas.
The North American newspaper Washington Post reported that the Venezuelan President asked Russia, China and Iran for help to defend the country from pressure from the United States. For Beijing, this is cooperation between sovereign states and is not directed against third parties.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said at a press conference that China supports strengthening international cooperation to combat “transnational crime” and opposes the use or threat of such force in international relations.</description><pubDate>2025-11-05 00:37:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Pop Mart, fabricante de Labubu, cai 10,8% em Hong Kong entre dúvidas sobre crescimento</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/24/pop-mart-fabricante-de-labubu-cai-108-em-hong-kong-entre-duvidas-sobre-crescimento/</link><description>Shares in Pop Mart, the Chinese company responsible for the global phenomenon of Labubu figures, sank 10.8% this Thursday, the biggest drop since April, in a new episode of volatility that contrasts with the good sales results released the day before.
The devaluation reflects investors' growing caution regarding the possibility of a slowdown in the company's growth, after several quarters driven by the popularity of its collectible products.
On Wednesday, Pop Mart shares rose 4.23% on the Hong Kong stock exchange, despite the negative tone of the market, following the announcement that revenue in the third quarter increased between 245% and 250%, driven by Labubu's virality on social media and the company's international expansion.
According to data provided by the company, domestic sales grew 190%, while international sales soared 370%, highlighted by increases of 175% in the Asia-Pacific region, more than 740% in Europe and almost 1,270% in the United States. The strong drop recorded today is largely attributed to profit taking, after appreciation of more than 186% since the beginning of the year, and uncertainty about the sustainability of the current growth rate.
The stock fell 8.1% on Tuesday, its worst performance since April, weighed down by fears of a slowdown in sales after months of euphoria. The preliminary release of results helped to temporarily dispel these concerns, but the absence of an official date for the presentation of the accounts maintains uncertainty regarding the company's future evolution. Executive chairman and founder Wang Ning expressed confidence in the long-term resilience of the Labubu character, arguing that cultural icons continue to generate revenue even after peak popularity.
According to the Bloomberg agency, the explosion in demand forced the company itself to revise its internal goals upwards. If at the beginning of 2024 Pop Mart predicted a turnover of 2,800 million dollars (around 2,400 million euros), in August Wang raised this target to 4,200 million dollars (3,600 million euros), pointing to the brand's global momentum as a key factor.
Founded in Beijing in 2010, Pop Mart has established itself as one of the main Asian references in the toy and collectible figures sector, combining exclusive design, limited editions and collaborations with international brands, artists and franchises.
Its business model is based on so-called “surprise boxes”, which encourage repeat purchases and have created a community of fans willing to pay high premiums for rare pieces. Among its main lines is Labubu, a monster with pointy ears and a mischievous smile inspired by Norse mythology, created by Hong Kong artist Lung Ka-sing in 2015 and integrated into the company's portfolio in 2019.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>DSPA | Renewed Director Service Committee</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/dspa-comissao-de-servico-de-director-renovada/</link><description>Ip Kuong Lam's service commission as director of Environmental Protection Services has been renewed for a period of one year, according to an order published yesterday in the Official Gazette.
As happens in these situations, the order indicates that the appointee has “appropriate experience and professional capacity to carry out his duties”. Ip Kuong Lam has a bachelor's degree and a master's degree in Environmental Engineering. He entered the public service in 2001, and served as senior technician at the Environment Council, head of the Environmental Pollution Control Department at DSPA and deputy director of DSPA, between 2014 and 2024, when he was promoted to his current position.
IH | Iam Lei Leng's term renewed
The mandate of the president of the Housing Institute (IH), Iam Lei Leng, was renewed for a period of one year, according to an order published yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Iam was first appointed to these roles in 2023, during Raimundo do Rosário's period as Secretary for Transport and Public Works.
The renewal of the mandate was justified by the fact that Iam had “appropriate experience and professional capacity to carry out his duties”. Before being appointed president of IH, Iam Lei Leng headed the Department of Studies at the Housing Institute since March 2015.
The current president joined IH, as a technician, in April 1999, remaining in the position for around a year. Between June 2002 and January 2006, he became a senior technician. After completing this mission, he became head of Legal Affairs at the Housing Institute, where he remained until 2015.
Commerce | António Lei dismissed as managing director
António Lei Chi Wai was dismissed from the position of managing director of the Board of Directors of the Macau World Trade Center, according to information released yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Lei will be replaced by Ao Weng Tong, currently a member of the Consumer Council and who will hold both roles.
The decision by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, was published yesterday in the Official Bulletin, but came into force on November 19th. The order does not make it clear whether António Lei Chi Wai will continue to serve as president of the Executive Committee of the Macau World Trade Center. Currently, António Lei has an annual salary of 1.2 million patacas, for both roles, which if divided over 12 months represents a salary of 100 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:28:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Finance | Reserve with biggest increase until September since the pandemic</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/financas-reserva-com-maior-subida-ate-setembro-desde-a-pandemia/</link><description>In nine months, the value of reserve assets increased by 42.5 billion patacas, exceeding last year's figure. Macau's financial reserve is at its highest level since April 2021, with a value of 658.8 billion patacas
The financial reserve had the best first nine months of the year since 2019, before the start of the covid-19 pandemic, it was announced yesterday. According to a balance sheet published in the Official Bulletin by the Macau Monetary Authority (AMCM), the value of assets rose by 42.5 billion patacas in the first nine months.
Official data show that this is the best start to the year since the first nine months of 2019, a period in which the reserve appreciated by 64.7 billion patacas.
According to AMCM, the reserve has already appreciated more than in 2024, the year in which assets rose by 35.7 billion patacas, the highest annual value since the pandemic. Last year recorded the highest increase since 2019, when the value of Macau's financial reserve rose by 70.6 billion patacas.
In September alone, the reserve gained 5.49 billion patacas, reaching 658.7 billion patacas, the highest value in more than four years.
Macau's financial reserve is at the highest level since recorded in April 2021, at 658.8 billion patacas. Still, it remains below the historical record of 663.6 billion patacas, reached at the end of February 2021, despite the territory being in the midst of a pandemic at the time.
The inside of the melon
The value of the extraordinary reserve at the end of September this year was 456.5 billion patacas and the basic reserve, equivalent to 150 percent of Macau's public budget, was 167.3 billion patacas. Subcontracted investments represent the largest share of Macau's financial reserve, 281.3 billion patacas, which also includes deposits and current accounts worth 265.4 billion patacas and even credit securities worth 109.4 billion patacas.
In 2024, investments yielded almost 31 billion patacas to the financial reserve, corresponding to a profitability rate of 5.3 percent, said AMCM, at the end of February.
The territory's initial budget for 2025 predicted a 7 percent increase in total expenditure, to 109.4 billion patacas. But the Legislative Assembly (AL) approved in July a proposal presented by the Government for a new budget, which includes an extra increase of 2.86 billion patacas in expenses.
On Tuesday, the AL also unanimously gave the green light to the budget for 2026, which foresees public expenditure of 113.5 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:26:33</pubDate></item><item><title>National security | Government will create risk alert system</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/seguranca-nacional-governo-vai-criar-sistema-de-alerta-para-riscos/</link><description>Guardianship debates continue on the report on the Lines of Government Action for 2026. Yesterday the Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, guaranteed that in 2026 a risk alert system for national security will be created
The Macau Government promised to create, in 2026, a risk warning system for national security and warned of “acts of interference and destruction” by “external forces”.
The Secretary for Security set the goal for next year to implement “a system of monitoring and warning indicators of risks related to the defense of national security”. Chan Tsz King, who until December 2024 served as commissioner against Corruption, spoke during the presentation of the Lines of Government Action (LAG) for 2026, in the Legislative Assembly (AL). The former prosecutor promised to “remain highly vigilant in the face of the new and complex panorama” of international security and warned of “multiple factors of uncertainty that could compromise the security of the State”.
Prevention matters
Macau will “strictly prevent acts of interference and destruction [by] external forces”, guaranteed Chan, highlighting the importance of guaranteeing security in “major events”.
Between the 9th and 21st of November, the regions of Macau, Hong Kong and Guangdong hosted the 15th edition of the National Games. On November 18, the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, said that Macau received 2,480 people in delegations to the National Games. More than two million tourists passed through the city during the event.
During yesterday's LAG debate, MP Lam Lon Wai defended the creation of “standardized security guidelines and procedures” for large events, including concerts. Chan Tsz King, who took office on October 16, promised to study Lam Lon Wai's suggestion, but stressed that authorities already have “specific [security] plans for different types of activity”.
The secretary said that this year, the police “effectively prevented and investigated crimes against national security, deterring and combating anti-China and disruptive Macau individuals.”
On July 31, local police authorities announced the arrest of former deputy and pro-democracy activist Au Kam San, a Portuguese citizen, in the first case under the region's national security law, which came into force in 2009 and whose scope was expanded in 2023.
Last Thursday, the head of the European Union (EU) Delegation in Hong Kong and Macau wrote on social media that he had met with Macau's Secretary for Economy and Finance, Anton Tai Kin Ip. “I also expressed concern about political issues,” added Briton Harvey Rouse. But the EU representation declined to reveal whether the case of Au Kam San was mentioned at the meeting.
Smuggling | Secretary highlights stability
The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, stressed that the security situation in the territory is stable. “Between January and October 2025, the crime rate in Macau decreased compared to the same period in 2024”, he said, highlighting “the decreasing trend” in crimes such as “serious violence, theft, theft and computer fraud”, so “security in general remains stable and good”.
However, Chan Tsz King highlighted the occurrence of several cases of smuggling, and in the first ten months of the year alone, 108 people “of school age” were intercepted, “seven times more than the same period” last year. The secretary also spoke of the occurrence, this year, of 126 cases of smuggling detected by the Customs Services.
"We have established a communication mechanism with schools to reinforce compliance with the law. We will resort to a cooperation mechanism with the three parties [Hong Kong, Macau and Guangdong] to combat smuggling."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Video surveillance helped police solve more than 38 thousand cases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/videovigilancia-ajudou-policia-a-resolver-mais-de-38-mil-casos/</link><description>Video surveillance cameras have helped solve more than 38 thousand cases since they began to be installed on the city's streets. “From 2016 until now we have been able to solve 38 thousand cases through” the network of surveillance cameras, the general commander of the Unitary Police Services (SPU) of Macau, Leong Man Cheong, told deputies yesterday.
During the first five phases of the Macau City Video Surveillance System, known as ‘Eyes in the Sky’, more than 1,920 cameras were installed throughout the region. In 2023, the SPU said that the system had helped investigate cases of homicide, drug trafficking, robbery, theft, arson, possession of a prohibited weapon, offenses against physical integrity and fraud.
Leong Man Cheong revealed that the sixth phase of 'Eyes in the Sky' will include the installation of an additional 800 video surveillance cameras by the end of 2027, including 120 on a new artificial island, known as zone A. "We have already installed ten cameras in several public housing buildings, which have come into operation. In addition, surveillance cameras have been installed on the main roads," added the commander.
Leong stressed that the installation of the remaining cameras “must follow the technical progress of construction” and urbanization of zone A. The official was speaking at the Legislative Assembly during the debate on the Lines of Government Action for 2026, presented by the Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King.
The missing solution
In the same debate, Chan pointed to new technologies, including artificial intelligence, as the solution to dealing with “the lack of personnel” in the territory's security forces. “Within two to three years, several workers will reach retirement age, so we will then see that the problem will be more serious”, warned the secretary.
But Chan stressed that “all leaders” in Macau have to “face certain limitations” due to “the Government’s general policy” for hiring public servants. “We have to be pragmatic, realistic and we also have to take into account the use of new technologies to overcome this gap”, defended the former prosecutor.
Despite the limitations, Chan assured that he will not give up on the fight against illegal work and revealed that security forces have detected, “so far this year”, 76 cases involving 173 people. An increase compared to the same period in 2024, in which the police registered 63 cases involving 117 people, with the majority of illegal workers coming from Mainland China, Hong Kong and Southeast Asia.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:19:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Public consultation on new money laundering law in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/consulta-publica-sobre-nova-lei-de-branqueamento-de-capitais-em-2026/</link><description>The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, assured that the public consultation will be launched in the coming months to review the law to combat terrorism and money laundering. “We will improve the diplomas related to money laundering, and next year launch the respective legislation and carry out public consultation, so that the future proposed law has everyone's consent”, stressed the secretary.
It should be noted that the measure is included in the LAG report, released last week. The document reads that the changes to the 2006 law, relating to the prevention and repression of the crime of money laundering, and to the administrative regulation, also from that year, which legislates measures of a preventive nature against the crimes of money laundering and terrorist financing, aim to “respond to the latest changes introduced to international standards for combating money laundering and trends in this crime”.
Make accounts easier
One of the deputies who spoke about the need to improve this legislation was Ip Sio Kai. "Many times, those holding positions in companies face problems in setting up companies taking into account the diplomas in force, and this has been an impediment and deterrent factor. When an account is opened it has to be verified several times. Singapore is a financial center and also has a gambling sector, why is it so easy there to open accounts and set up companies compared to Macau? When it comes to financial security, there is no clear limit on the demands, one cannot demand too much in terms of requirements, and people don’t know how to proceed”, he defended.
Even so, the deputy, linked to the financial area, praised the activity of the Financial Information Office. "The results have been good and we have even received praise. But can the authorities define and present different requirements in relation to risks of different levels? I agree that a legislative review should be carried out to increase the requirements."</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:18:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Song Pek Kei wants more support</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/comercio-song-pek-kei-quer-mais-apoios/</link><description>Deputy Song Pek Kei yesterday called on the Government to promote the extension of the Consumer Grand Prix to support the local market. The position was taken in an intervention before the agenda, in the Plenary of the Legislative Assembly.
In his intervention, Song began by outlining a scenario of difficulties in local commerce: “Due to the multiple impacts resulting from the consumption drain, the internet economy and the change in consumption, Macau's community economy is no longer as prosperous as before”, he pointed out. “The business space for physical stores is increasingly narrow, the pressure on exploitation is increasing, the opportunities to make money are fewer, the companies that can survive are in a very difficult situation, and many companies even choose to close their businesses because they suffer considerable losses, so there are many unoccupied stores in Macau”, he described.
In this difficult environment, Song called for more measures to support residents' consumption to promote Macau's domestic economy. “The Macao SAR Government should, if financial conditions allow, study the launch of new consumption subsidy plans […] in order to increase subsidy plans and specific benefits for electronic products, household appliances, meals, etc., with the aim of continuing to stimulate the community economy, stabilizing confidence in social development”, he appealed.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:26:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Pereira Coutinho calls for greater investment in the face of regional competition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/jogo-pereira-coutinho-pede-maior-aposta-face-a-concorrencia-regional/</link><description>Despite economic diversification efforts, José Pereira Coutinho alerted authorities to the development of the gaming sector, so that the industry is not overtaken by regional competition. The warning from the deputy linked to the Macau Public Service Workers Association (ATFPM) was left in an intervention at the Legislative Assembly.
"Due to the excessive dependence on a single industry, the Government of Macau has continued to work on economic diversification with the aim of creating and increasing other revenues from different economic activities to cover the constant annual increase in public expenditure. But this work has not been easy", said Coutinho. “The Macao SAR’s public revenues continue to come disproportionately from the gaming industry, representing around 86.2 percent of the total collected between January and July 2025”, he pointed out.
Therefore, the legislator warns that it will not be difficult to find alternative sources of income, so it is necessary not to forget the care to be taken with the gaming industry. “The Government of Macau must make an effort to implement policies that increase the competitiveness of the gaming industry in the face of high competition from adjacent regions that operate under much more advantageous conditions, both in terms of taxation and the payment of commissions”, he stressed.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:24:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Germany's Strategic Awakening (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/o-despertar-estrategico-da-alemanha-ii/</link><description>“The claim that a state’s security interest necessarily coincides with that of its citizens appears downright absurd.”
Ole Nymoen
If the draconian dictates of the Morgenthau Plan proposed by the United States in 1944 to demilitarize and deindustrialize Germany after World War II, transforming it into an agrarian country and incapable of starting new conflicts remained a dead letter, it was only because, in those same months, awareness of a fundamental conflict in Europe with the Soviet Union began to mature in the United States. As the weeks went by, the priority stopped being the neutralization of Germany and became preventing Moscow from absorbing it into its sphere of influence. In the interpretation of several American officials at the time, before reaching the Atlantic, the Red Army would have to seize the industrial capabilities of the Rhineland and the Ruhr region, the historic heart of German industry, with emphasis on the coal, steel, chemical, energy and logistics sectors.
Hence the need to rebuild a West German state and direct its economic, human and technological potential against Soviet expansionism. Summarized in a 1949 CIA document, the United States' objective became “the permanent control of German power”. Eighty years later, the contours have changed, not the substance. Today, for Washington, the challenge of the century is called China, and the costs of defending the Old Continent must fall on the Europeans. France and the United Kingdom's financial room for maneuver is limited, also due to their expensive nuclear arsenals. And, from the point of view of the Poles, Balts and Scandinavians, Russia is an existential threat, to be contained and eroded by all means. Everything points in a single direction, which is German rearmament. According to this logic, it will be up to Germany to ensure the critical mass of economic resources and conventional forces that the remaining Western partners cannot or do not want to mobilize.
Naturally, an essential assumption of this bet is that Berlin does not act on its own, building a sphere of influence or pursuing strictly national interests. Only then can it be understood that the Federal Republic, whose legal system theoretically prohibits even the sending of weapons to areas of armed conflict, is currently debating whether to place troops on the ground in Ukraine. In recent years, the Germans have broken several long-standing taboos, such as the debt brake, but this would be, for obvious reasons, the most clamorous. Thus, in August, at the end of the Washington summit, Merz stressed that Germany has a “fundamental interest” in cooperating to offer guarantees to Kiev, with the image of the chancellor in the role of a sinister Uncle Sam, accompanied by the caption that “Merz wants to send you to Ukraine? Not us!” To this day, this is not only an unpopular perspective according to a recent poll, as 51 percent of Germans are against it and only 36 percent are in favor, but it is also technically impractical.
Despite the significant increase in military expenditure, the number of personnel in the German Armed Forces continues to decline and age. The objective of 203,000 units by 2031 seems out of reach, a goal that the strategic community of Berlin-Mitte, the most central and historic district of Berlin, considered the political, cultural and tourist heart of the German capital, considers totally insufficient to meet current German security needs. In the last three years, the approximately 180 thousand employees have decreased slightly. It is difficult to imagine that the military service reform recently approved by the federal government could represent the solution, as recruitment, for now, will continue to be voluntary. We are not, therefore, faced with a linear process. But it is worth remembering that, no matter how much legions of experts strive every day to present German rearmament as the panacea for all the ills of the West, it continues to be a high-risk bet.
Above all because the European strategic context is radically different from the one that, in the post-war period, led Washington to allow itself to be convinced by London and Paris not to abandon Europe. At the time, it was French leaders, particularly figures like Robert Schuman and Jean Monnet, who firmly argued that any withdrawal of American troops would have “disastrous consequences” for the national security of the victors. And in the United States there was full awareness that the rapprochement between France and Germany was a fundamental condition for giving solidity to the Western bloc. As Secretary of State Dean Acheson, who played a central role in formulating American foreign policy during the early years of the Cold War, stated in 1949, “Only France can take the decisive lead in the integration of Germany in Western Europe… if it is to avoid Russian or German or perhaps Russian-German domination in Europe.”
Having all due consideration for the pro-European rhetoric, without the security guarantees of the United States there would not have been any Franco-German axis, the true engine of European integration. The proof is there for all to see and is it a coincidence that the partial American disengagement with the continent coincides today with a crisis in relations between Germany and France? Washington seems increasingly distant. Old wounds resurface, never fully healed. In particular, the origin of tensions between the two banks of the Rhine lies in an opposing perception of German rearmament. Paris fears that the Federal Republic could transform into an assertive power unrelated to any control. Berlin, for its part, suspects that the French intend to use German funds to further their expensive ambitions. This is a structural fracture, impossible to completely bridge, regardless of the good will of Merz and Macron.
(Continues)</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:07:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Attachment Theory and the new “Astrology”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/a-teoria-da-vinculacao-e-a-nova-astrologia/</link><description>Attachment theory, for decades confined to academic articles and psychology offices, entered popular culture. From one moment to the next, we find people describing themselves as “anxious”, “avoidant” or “disorganized” with the same ease with which they declare their astrological sign. Clinical language entered common sense, attachment styles came to life in memes and reels on TikTok, and intimacy began to be talked about like someone reading an astral chart. I'm like this, you're like this.
There is something irresistible about this trend. In times of uncertainty, the promise of a clear explanation for our emotional patterns has a quasi-therapeutic effect. Typification offers a vocabulary: we can finally express, in a few words, why we feel too attached to one relationship or too disconnected from another. And for many, there is genuine relief in recognizing that certain behaviors—the urgency of a response, the impulse to disappear—are not random but learned strategies for surviving emotionally.
However, as this theory became mainstream, it also gained a more complicated side. The speed of social media has simplified complex concepts until they almost lost nuance. What was supposed to be a lens became a label; what could help to understand, began to imprison. And this is where the frustration arises: the feeling that attachment theory has been transformed into a kind of emotional determinism.
It's common to hear statements like “I'm avoidant, that's how I am”, or “he'll never be able to give me what I need, because he's anxious”. Each of them reveals, at the same time, a desire for understanding and a certain resignation. Typification, when used as a sentence, gives comfort but takes away agency: it facilitates explanations, but impoverishes the complexity of human experience. Even more serious, it can serve to excuse behavior or to pathologize the other.
However, attachment theory, when applied sensitively—especially in couples therapy—becomes a revealing tool. Instead of reducing the person to their standard, it allows us to look at what that standard tries to protect. It shows that our reactions in adult life are echoes of our first experiences of care; They are not destinations, but paths that we can deviate from, if we understand them.
Let's think about the case, so common in therapy, of the couple in which one partner seeks contact and the other withdraws. On the surface, it seems incompatible. But, when the two begin to explore their own history, it is discovered that what today manifests itself as “anxiety” or “avoidance” was born from very different contexts.
There are those who grew up in an environment where care was inconsistent: sometimes present, sometimes absent. These people learn to be vigilant, to interpret any silence as rejection. In adult relationships, they get closer when they are afraid of losing. Others grew up in families where autonomy was the only safe way to exist. They learned not to depend, not to ask not to take risks. In a relationship, they move away when intimacy intensifies — not because they don't feel it, but because feeling too much has always been dangerous.
When these two worlds meet, they form a painful cycle: the more one party seeks connection, the more the other withdraws; and the more the latter retracts, the more the former intensifies the search. And this is precisely where typing becomes useful: illuminating patterns. In therapy, when a partner can say “I'm not staying away because I don't care, but because I'm overwhelmed,” something changes. And when the other person is able to recognize “I don't want to pressure you; I just need to feel that you're still here”, a new space of vulnerability opens up.
The attachment theory thus makes it possible to transform misunderstandings into bridges. It gives language to silences, context to reactions, humanity to disagreements. It shows that no one is anxious “just because”, nor essentially avoidant: we are all the result of complex stories, shaped by what life has taught us about love.
The problem, therefore, is not in the theory, but in the way pop culture simplifies it. When we reduce attachment styles to caricatures we miss the opportunity to see the emotional richness behind these strategies. And, perhaps most importantly, we forget that attachment is malleable.
In the end, perhaps we should look at this trend in the same spirit with which we read a good horoscope: a mix of curiosity, lightness and critical sense. Attachment theory can be a valuable map, as long as we don't confuse the map with the territory. Words and definitions are only worth it if they give us freedom.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 02:00:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Pre-prepared food (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/25/comida-pre-preparadaii/</link><description>Last week, we looked at the recent online controversy surrounding pre-prepared food. Mainland China had issued a “Notice on Strengthening Food Safety Supervision of Pre-Prepared Food and Promoting High-Quality Development of Industry.” The Notice explains what “pre-prepared food” is and states that food that is prepared in the central kitchens of restaurant chains in accordance with food safety laws and regulations, and then distributed through their branches, is therefore not considered pre-prepared food.
Although there are different definitions of pre-prepared food, for most consumers, as long as the food is not cooked in the restaurant, and if it contains ingredients that have signs of having been industrially processed, whether they are ready meals or semi-finished products, they are considered “pre-prepared food”. In other words, “if they are not freshly cooked, they are pre-prepared” is the widespread perception.
Pre-prepared meals are ubiquitous in modern restaurant chains. The standardized taste ensures that consumers have the same experience regardless of which group restaurant they visit. This procedure encourages consumer loyalty to the brand. Restaurants do not gain or lose customers because of the quality of the chef. Pre-prepared food reduces the number of staff required, reducing payroll costs and increasing restaurant efficiency. We have a society where people order take-away every day; restaurants need to time food preparation and couriers need to time delivery times. If food preparation is not fast enough, restaurants cannot survive the competition. To ensure efficient food preparation, restaurants inevitably need to use pre-prepared food. Driven by restaurant needs, the demand for pre-prepared food has increased exponentially. Studies indicate that this market in mainland China will reach 1,072 billion dollars in 2026, with the potential to develop into the next market valued at billions of dollars. Therefore, it is essential to establish national food safety standards in the country.
Restaurants' focus on serving food quickly leads consumers to view pre-prepared food as “fast food”. Therefore, they may not be willing to pay high prices for this type of food. Furthermore, customers expect to feel the “wok hei” (the smoky aroma imparted by a hot wok during meal preparation) and enjoy “freshly made” cuisine when they come to the restaurant. If food is prepared in the chain's central kitchen with pre-packaged ingredients, customers will experience a “psychological gap” that causes a series of issues. For example, is the food I am eating past its expiration date? Does it contain preservatives? Are these preservatives harmful to health? Does it affect the taste of food? If flavor and freshness are affected, should the price be lowered? These questions easily give rise to doubts. If consumers are forced to pay high prices for pre-prepared food, they may feel cheated and come into conflict with the restaurant.
This controversy made society realize that if consumers “eat happily and calmly” they will return, which will be advantageous for customers and the restaurant. Perhaps it could be considered indicating on the menu whether the dish is “freshly made”, whether it comes from the “central kitchen of the restaurant chain” or whether it is “pre-prepared”, thus giving the consumer the possibility of choice. One such restaurant chain in mainland China, “Lao Xiang Ji,” uses this method by indicating whether meals are “made in the restaurant,” “semi-prepared,” or “reheated pre-prepared food.” This method satisfies customers, freeing them from misunderstandings and concerns about pre-prepared food and food safety. Lao Xiang Ji's approach imposed itself on industrialization, thus managing to retain customers.
Furthermore, restaurants must understand that a transparent and honest environment better informs consumers, which increases their trust in restaurants. Consumer trust is the foundation of all brands. Consumers are both participants and drivers of the food industry. This controversy will help the food industry develop in a more standardized and healthy direction.
To support this development, mainland China needs to implement national standards for the safety of pre-prepared meals as soon as possible and establish a strict quality control and tracing mechanism, which will be more beneficial to society.
According to Macau Law No. 5/2013, the “Food Safety Law”, pre-prepared meals must be packaged securely and their ingredients must be labeled, but restaurants are not required to indicate whether or not their dishes use pre-prepared ingredients. This controversy demonstrates that consumers are concerned about restaurants serving pre-prepared meals. Given the current tendency for Macau residents to go shopping to mainland China, in order to survive, the restaurant industry needs to improve to attract more tourists. Perhaps Macau restaurants could consider explaining to customers that if they use locally pre-prepared food, they are serving typical dishes, “Made in Macau.” If they use pre-prepared foods sourced from mainland China and processed in their kitchens, they may identify them as “Made in mainland China + Processed in Macau” as a marketing slogan. In this way, operational costs can be reduced and the perception of the value of what is “Made in Macau” can be increased. After all, our tourism industry depends on tourists, and selling typically local products to tourists is the key to the city's business survival.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences of the Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 04:00:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Presidents for all tastes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/presidentes-para-todos-os-gostos/</link><description>The electoral campaign for candidates for President of the Republic is on the road. The suitors for the Belém palace are more than many and for all tastes. On January 18th of next year, the Portuguese people are, once again, called to go to the polls to vote for whoever intends to be the new President of Portugal. There are candidates from the extreme right to the extreme left. The vote is secret, but most people already have an idea who they will vote for. One thing is certain: the Portuguese want to continue living in democracy and do not accept xenophobic, racist and neo-Nazi theories. Polls are worth what they are worth. They usually make mistakes in the final result. However, certain television channels have done everything to influence the vote in a certain direction.
Today, I leave you with what we think of each of the candidates.
André Ventura – A candidate anti-current political system, who has defended hatred for immigrants, who advocates a change in nationality laws and even in the Constitution of the Republic itself. It is clear that he is only running to try to maintain his electoral base for future legislative elections, despite the fact that his Chega Party has been losing followers. In the television debates he has participated in, he only knows how to shout and present the same arguments that he has announced since he founded the party. It is not even possible that he will be able to participate in a possible second round of the presidential elections.
Marques Mendes – The former television commentator and PSD leader decided to run because his partner Luís Montenegro assured him that he would have the support of the PSD/CDS Democratic Alliance, which currently governs the country. Marques Mendes presents himself as a faction candidate. Without a doubt, supporters of the Montenegro government will vote for him. However, not all PSD activists support this candidacy. For these activists, Marques Mendes is Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa number two, with less knowledge of constitutional legislation. The polls created for his appreciation have already presented him as being ahead of voting intentions. We sincerely do not believe that the people will choose a President who would just go to Belém to defend all of Montenegro's proposals.
Almirante Gouveia e Melo – A candidate who immediately received, upon announcing his candidacy, overwhelming popular support for having been a man of seriousness and organization when the Covid-19 virus pandemic hit. Some once again support a military man for the Presidency of Portugal. Others are radically against the election of a military officer. They say he has no political experience and cannot explain what political area he is in. How can a citizen who becomes an admiral not know politics? How is it that you have not followed the vicissitudes of politics in the 50 years of democracy? Impossible. Gouveia e Melo knows perfectly well what support he has and what ideas he has to be a different President. The problem is that their political opponents know that Gouveia e Melo knows too much, for example, who received “gloves” in the acquisition of the high-tech submarines Arpão and Tridente, and there was no investigation by the Public Ministry when the German participants in the deal were arrested. His opponents want to remove him at all costs, as Gouveia e Melo knows all the ins and outs of those who want to remove him. He is one of the strong candidates to win the elections, in the first or second round.
António José Seguro – An experienced candidate in politics and academic life where he has maintained extensive contact with young people. He was general secretary of the Socialist Party and after the “war” with António Costa he hibernated. After 10 years, he returns bringing with him his seriousness, his political knowledge of the Portuguese reality and his serenity in analyzing national problems. The Socialist Party, or a part of it, was forced to announce that it supported this candidate. Seguro thanked him for the support, but emphasized his independence. Safe since he announced his candidacy for President, he has gradually risen in the voting intentions of the Portuguese, especially among a moderate “centrão” that includes social democrats and socialists. You may be surprised and go on to a second round.
Cotrim Figueiredo – A candidate who was leader of the Liberal Initiative, a party that is more similar to Chega than to the PSD. Cotrim could be a surprise, especially when it comes to voting among young people and women. Personally, he is a cordial person, knowledgeable about political dossiers, with experience in the corridors of the European Parliament and who presents himself as a defender of modern and reformist liberalism. It may surprise in the percentage of votes, but we don't believe it will be enough to contest a second round. The mobilization around Cotrim is being active and influential. Its result will depend greatly on the criticisms it announces against Chega, otherwise, social democratic activists unhappy with Marques Mendes will not support him and may opt to vote for Seguro.
António Filipe – This candidate is a Gentleman. Serious, deputy of the Assembly of the Republic for many years, knowledgeable about the Constitution from the first to the last paragraph, affable and popular. He does not deny his communist roots, but he often disagreed with the guidelines of the Central Committee of his party, the PCP. He is a candidate who has traveled the entire country and who sits in cafes listening to people's complaints. He has achieved a support base larger than that of his own party. We have already heard socialists saying that they will vote for his candidacy. António Filipe is cultured, an excellent commentator, a friend of the unprotected and could obtain a surprising result, despite the polls commissioned by the AD placing him as having no electoral significance. Maybe they are wrong.
Catarina Martins – The candidate supported by the Bloco de Esquerda should have remained in the insignificance that has been registered in her party, which month after month has seen voters flee to Livre. Catarina has no chance of obtaining a good result, because the crisis raging in the Bloc does nothing to help her win over voters. She knows what she's talking about, she points out errors in Montenegro's governance, she defends the poverty-stricken pensioners, but there is no machine in her candidacy that could promote her to a credible candidate capable of achieving a good result.
We will not comment on the candidate of Livre and other pretenders to the “throne” of Belém due to the fact that they have no chance of being elected. In our humble opinion, the elections will be disputed between Gouveia e Melo and Marques Mendes or António José Seguro. And in a second round, if Seguro is present, the entire left will be able to coexist with Álvaro Cunhal's thesis of covering his eyes and putting the cross on Seguro.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:39:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Edgar Martins wins Grand Prize Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/edgar-martins-vence-grande-premio-sovereign-portuguese-art-prize-2025/</link><description>Photographer Edgar Martins won the Grand Prize of the Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize 2025, worth 25 thousand euros, for the work “Anton’s Hand is Made of Guilt”, inspired by the disappearance of a friend during wartime. The announcement was made this Tuesday, the day of the opening of the finalists' exhibition, at the Sociedade Nacional de Belas Artes, in Lisbon, during a press visit, led by Howard Bilton, founder and president of the Sovereign Art Foundation (SAF).
This is the fourth edition of this annual award, which is awarded by the SAF Association, the Portuguese branch of the Sovereign Art Foundation, created in 2003 in Hong Kong to promote, support and recognize contemporary art and encourage artistic production, as well as financing programs for disadvantaged children in Portugal.
The winning work, which is also present in the collection of the Museu de Arte Contemporânea Armando Martins (MACAM), is a chromogenic proof, mounted in aluminum and framed, which is part of the series “Anton’s hand is made of Guilt. No muscle of Bone. He has a Gung-ho Finger and a Grief-stricken Thumb” (2023).
Edgar Martins' work explores themes such as war, incarceration, migration, urbanism and technology, with this project, in particular, focusing on the death and disappearance of a friend, photojournalist Anton Hammerl, during the Libyan war in 2011.
Central questions
The work is articulated around a central question: how to narrate a story without witnesses, evidence or traces, and in the absence of the photographic referent itself”, states the catalog information about the work, adding that “more than a tribute, this work portrays a complex story, distorted by absences, which talks about the difficulties of documenting, witnessing and imagining war”.
"While I don't tend to categorize my work as photography in the traditional sense of the term, it is, in virtually every way, photographic. And photography, historically, has not been particularly successful when it is forced to compete with other mediums. So I received this news with surprise and excitement in equal measure. It is, of course, a huge honor to receive such a prestigious award. And what's more, a privilege to know that this financial support will directly contribute to the Sovereign Art Foundation's solidarity program, making me feel part of of something much greater than this isolated artistic feat”, declared the winner, quoted in a statement.
For the president of the jury, David Elliott, it has not been an easy task to find a winner, with the “variety, depth and subtlety of the finalist works”.
"The cruelly savage ironies that confront us in every daily news report are part of the theme of Edgar Martins' winning work. Rooted in both the present and the recent past, it was triggered by the still unexplained disappearance and death of his friend, photojournalist Anton Hammerl, during the Libyan War in 2011. It remains a crime without witnesses or any other evidence, a void that Martins has addressed in other works, as well as in the winning work 'Anton's Hand is Made of Guilt. In Muscle or Bone. He has a Gung-ho Finger and a Grief-stricken Thumb'”, said the president of the jury, quoted by the organization.
In female
This year, for the first time, the Women's Prize was created, created in partnership with the Sassy Women Society, worth two thousand euros, which distinguishes the finalist with the highest score, with the choice going to the artist Alice Marcelino, for the work “Black Skin White Algorithm”.
As 30 obras finalistas vão estar expostas até ao dia 13 de Dezembro, data em que será atribuído o prémio do Voto Público, que pode ser feito presencialmente ou ‘online’, também no valor de dois mil euros.
The 30 finalist works that will be on display were chosen by an international jury made up of seven experts – Adelaide Ginga, Armando Cabral, David Eliott, Francisco Trêpa (who won the grand prize in 2024), João Paulo Queiroz, Maura Marvão and Tim Marlow OBE – from around 200 artists proposed by a panel of independent arts professionals, including Portuguese critics, curators and academics.
All finalist works are available for purchase and profits will be divided equally between the artists and SAF's expressive arts programs for disadvantaged children in Portugal.
The Sovereign Portuguese Art Prize is an annual award that celebrates the work of contemporary artists living in Portugal and its diaspora, offering international recognition and financially supporting artists, whilst also raising funds for disadvantaged children in Portugal through the sale of finalist works.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:54:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature | José Cordeiro, former teacher in Macau, launches book of chronicles</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/literatura-jose-cordeiro-ex-docente-em-macau-lanca-livro-de-cronicas/</link><description>It is with the approval of the Writing Workshop that José Cordeiro, who was a physical education teacher in Macau for several years, makes his literary debut. After many chronicles written on the social network Facebook, the encouragement of friends and readers led him to edit “Ao Invés, Pois Claro”, where there is not even a lack of text about what it means to be Macanese
“Ao Invés, Pois Claro” is the title of the first book by José Cordeiro, former resident of Macau and former physical education teacher in the territory. With the approval of Oficina da Escrita, the book has just been published in Portugal and is the result of a series of publications, on different topics, published on the social network Facebook.
According to the description of the work, it is not only a “collection of chronicles”, but also “an invitation to freedom of thought, the exploration of doubt and knowledge”, the “celebration of diversity of opinions” that is carried out with a “relaxed approach”.
"I don't have any specific guidelines for writing a chronicle, it depends on the mood of the moment. It's not something doctrinal, it doesn't intend to influence anything. It's a personal pleasure I have, playing with words", he told HM. Although José Cordeiro has always made physical activity his profession, the truth is that the connection to letters has always existed.
"I've always liked playing with words. I only started writing more systematically recently. I selected some chronicles, like a literary kitchen, where you make soup and a lot of it ends up going to waste", he exemplified. The themes are diverse and “cover religion, politics, friendship, everything and nothing”.
One of the chronicles refers to Macau and being Macanese, a community issue that José Cordeiro knows well. In “State of siege or state of mind”, Cordeiro talks about the existence of the community and says that today, 25 years later, Macanese live “both things”. “It could be a state of siege, because they are limited to a community, which is Portuguese in Chinese territory, and a state of mind, because many people don't live in Macau, but feel Macanese living abroad”, he stressed.
“Ao Invés, Pois Claro” is a name that was born from the author’s desire to be “a little contrary”. "They say I'm stubborn, and so it seems to me [so]. I don't comment on the comments they make on my chronicles, and when I launch a chronicle it stops being mine at that moment, it becomes those who interpret it", he said.
The power of social networks
José Cordeiro believes that “a good way for a person to discipline their reasoning is to write” and writing “is a way of disciplining my intervention in the contacts I make with people”. It's "having a clear idea and, as a first principle, expressing it. It was in a wave of fun that I started doing things, writing. There were people who liked the texts and suggested that I publish them".
"I say it's an album because, for me, it's something else. It's when you take a theme and carry it through to the end", highlighted José Cordeiro, who confesses that social networks "have allowed everything", even giving voice to new authors.
"Sometimes I feel uncomfortable with what is done [on social media], but I am responsible for myself and what I do. I have no intention of indoctrinating or wanting to take anyone wherever. I am a simple citizen who likes to play in my literary kitchen, as I usually call it", he said. José Cordeiro is still preparing a launch session for the work, but it is already for sale on several online platforms.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:53:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Jazz | Thai drummer Hong in concert on Saturday at FRC</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/jazz-baterista-tailandes-hong-em-concerto-no-sabado-na-frc/</link><description>Thai jazz drummer Chanutr Techatana-nan, better known as Hong, will perform at the Fundação Rui Cunha gallery on Saturday night. The musician will be accompanied on stage by members of the Macau Jazz Promotion Association. Entry is free
The rhythmic engine of one of the most renowned jazz quartets on the Asian scene, The Asian All-Stars Power Quartet, will perform live at Fundação Rui Cunha (FRC) next Saturday, starting at 9pm. Anyone who passes by the FRC gallery will be able to watch the performance of Thai drummer Chanutr Techatana-nan, better known as Hong, accompanied by members of the Macau Jazz Promotion Association performing jazz classics and some original songs.
The musician is described by the organizers of the event, in charge of the FRC and the Macau Jazz Promotion Association, as “a prominent figure in the Asian jazz scene, celebrated for his innovative drumming style that combines a groovy swing with intricate polyrhythmic embellishments”.
In addition to praise for his performances and stage presence, Hong is a dedicated music teacher, a vocation he applies as an instructor and coordinator of the jazz studies program at Silpakorn University, in Thailand. With a career marked by collaboration with renowned musicians and participation in prestigious festivals around the world, “Hong is one of the influential figures in the musical genre, both as a performer and as an educator”.
With the help of friends
Born in Bangkok in 1978, Hong performed a little everywhere where jazz rhythms sound in Thailand. In 2002, his virtuosity was recognized with the “best drummer” award at the Thailand Drum Competition, an event organized in cooperation with the Percussive Arts Society.
One of his facets as a music educator received greater acclaim with the release of the DVD “Over the Barline”, which received an avalanche of positive reviews.  However, Hong's association with Singaporean pianist Jeremy Monteiro, also known as the “King of Swing”, would end up taking the Thai to perform all over the world, both with The Asian All-Stars Power Quartet and in the Organamix trio.
In the quartet, Monteiro and Hong are accompanied by Hong Kong jazz guitarist Eugene Pao, and Filipino saxophonist Tots Tolentino.
On Friday, starting at 6:30 pm, the FRC gallery will once again present “Uma Noite de Piano”, in a session “open to young talent” with a performance by Anson Lai. The event is co-organized by FRC and Elite – Association for Creativity and Musical Culture and has free entry.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:59:25</pubDate></item><item><title>IIM | Visit to historic neighborhoods scheduled for December 6th</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/25/iim-visita-aos-bairros-historicos-marcada-para-6-de-dezembro/</link><description>The International Institute of Macau (IIM) will carry out two guided community visits to the historic neighborhoods of Macau, on December 6th. The tours, entitled “Macaense Neighborhoods: Roots of a Multicultural City”, will last around an hour and a half, with the first session scheduled for 2:30 pm and the second starting at 3 pm.
The tours will start at Largo do Lilau, passing through Rua Central, Largo de Santo Agostinho, Rua da Felicidade, and end at the Dimensões M space, on Rua do Barão, close to the Seminário de São José, “where there will be a gathering and a drink”, indicates the IIM.  The IIM initiative has the support of the Macau Foundation, and will be organized in partnership with the Association of Macau Heritage Ambassadors, and in collaboration with the Association of Young Macanese and Language Exchange and Culture Promotion.
The visits were designed in conjunction with the twentieth anniversary of the inscription of the Historic Center of Macau on the World Heritage List and interested parties can now register on the social networks of the IIM and the Association of Macau Heritage Ambassadors.
The event is free and will have a participation limit of 50 people for two separate sessions (25 people in each session). The IIM states that the objective of the initiative is to provide the public, especially younger people, with knowledge about the experiences and stories of historic neighborhoods, as well as their cultural identity.</description><pubDate>2025-11-25 01:31:22</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Satellite casinos’ | Kam Pek closes doors in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/casinos-satelite-kam-pek-fecha-portas-em-macau/</link><description>Macau gaming concessionaire SJM Resorts announced yesterday that the Kam Pek Paradise 'satellite casino', with almost 600 employees, will close on December 1st. SJM said that Kam Pek Parasise “will officially cease operations at 23:59 (Monday, December 1st), thus becoming the seventh ‘satellite casino’ in the region to close its doors.
In a statement, SJM, founded by gaming tycoon Stanley Ho Hung Sun (1921-2020), highlighted that all local employees directly hired by the company have guaranteed employment. SJM explained that staff with resident status in Macau will be “transferred to other company casinos to perform gaming-related functions, according to operational needs”.
Local employees who were not hired directly by SJM Resorts “are invited to apply for related vacancies” within the group, “with priority for hiring” and with conditions equal to those they had. Also yesterday, the Macau Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department (DICJ) assured that it will “strictly supervise, on site, the closure procedures” of Kam Pek Paradise.
With regard to the 584 casino employees, the DICJ assured, in a press release, that it will maintain communication with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, to ensure compliance with the guarantees given by the SJM, namely “the relocation of all aforementioned workers”. SJM highlighted that “all tables and gaming machines currently operating on site will be transferred to other company casinos”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:11:45</pubDate></item><item><title>TUI | Reduced sentence for man who tried to kill ex-wife</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/tui-reduzida-pena-a-homem-que-tentou-matar-ex-mulher/</link><description>The Court of Final Instance (TUI) decided to reduce the prison sentence from 11 years and six months to eight years for a man convicted of attempted murder of his ex-wife, as “aggravating circumstances” had not been proven. The man was thus convicted of the attempted crime of simple homicide, in its attempted form, and decreed in the first instance by the Base Judicial Court (TJB), and not the crime of qualified homicide, also in its attempted form.
The TUI understood that the man “only decided to attack B [his ex-wife] after having questioned her and realized that she would not pay the compensation” demanded by him. “Although it appears that the idea of ​​killing B [the woman] came to him since 2017, it was just a thought he had in his mind, and in the period from 2017 to April 2023, no action was taken to implement the idea of ​​killing”, it reads.
The judges also considered, according to the ruling released yesterday, that “it is not clear that A [the accused man] acted coldly when attacking B [the woman]”, which is why the appeal presented by the man was upheld, considering the “excessive severity of the sentence determined” in the second instance.
The case dates back to 2017, and the woman was already a victim of domestic violence during the relationship. The man “held a grudge” against the woman “for having reported his acts of domestic violence and other family disputes, giving him the idea of ​​killing her”.
After the divorce, the man understood that his ex-wife had only obtained the Resident Identity Card (BIR) thanks to the marriage, so “he should pay her an amount as compensation”.
The time of the crime
The crime then began to enter into the plans of this man, who since April 2023 “kept a metal hammer in the box of his motorcycle”. On June 26 of that year, he stopped his motorcycle near his ex-wife's residence and “wandered around waiting for her”, then approached her and “demanded payment of the aforementioned compensation”.
The woman ignored the man and walked away, and that was when the man “removed the metal hammer from the box of his motorcycle, ran after [her] and hit her in the head with the hammer”, and she “consequently fell to the ground”. The ruling describes that, “despite her fall, [the man] continued to hit the victim in the head with the hammer a total of five times, only stopping when he noticed that [the woman] was lying on the floor with decreased consciousness”.
In the first instance, on July 31, 2024, the TJB convicted the man of committing a crime of attempted homicide and a crime of detention and use of a prohibited weapon, which, in legal terms, resulted in a sentence of eight years. Both the man and the Public Prosecutor's Office appealed to the second instance, which increased the sentence to 11 years and six months for the crime of attempted qualified homicide, crime of detention and use of a prohibited weapon. On February 14 of this year, the TUI accepted the convict's appeal and sent the case again to the Court of Second Instance (TSI), which repeated the trial and maintained the sentence of 11 years and six months in prison, but the man did not accept the decision and requested a new appeal, claiming that the TSI “did not fulfill its obligation to carry out a new trial, incurring an error in interpreting and applying the law”, determining “an excessively severe penalty”. The attacker has now managed to see his sentence reduced.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:08:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Government signs agreement with Chinese mapping application</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/turismo-governo-firma-acordo-com-aplicacao-chinesa-de-mapas/</link><description>The Tourism Services Bureau (DST) and Gaode, a Chinese digital maps, navigation and location company, signed a strategic cooperation agreement that culminated yesterday in the launch of the “Smart Travel to Macau with One Click” platform.
The function that can be used on the Mapa Gaode mobile phone application provides DST information, such as “festive events, real situations of points of tourist interest, traffic navigation and entertainment itineraries”, including information on food, accommodation, travel, entertainment.
The application also has a “sharing function, encouraging users to exchange practical tips and travel strategies”. Furthermore, this year, Gaode classified Macau as the first priority city of “Super destinations abroad”.
The platform dedicated to Macau has a list of street establishments, “reflecting the degree of popularity of traders from different sectors”, while also suggesting points of interest in community neighborhoods.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:51:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Cambodia | Money laundering suspicions in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/camboja-suspeitas-de-lavagem-de-dinheiro-em-macau/</link><description>Companies linked to the Prince Holding group and Chen Zhi, accused of cybercrime, human trafficking and money laundering, conducted business in Macau and Hong Kong. One of the companies was Companhia de Vinho Pou Long, which operated in the Macao SAR and even organized a gala dinner for the elderly in 2020
Octopus tentacles from a dismantled scam center in Cambodia may have reached Macau and Hong Kong. An investigation by the HK01 portal revealed that companies related to billionaire Chen Zhi's criminal empire operated in the special administrative regions.
The 37-year-old Chinese businessman is seen as the “brain behind a criminal empire” and is at the center of the largest cryptocurrency seizure in history, with around $14 billion in bitcoins confiscated by the United States Treasury Department. The schemes allegedly operated in industrial complexes in Cambodia, where foreign workers were forced to commit online fraud under armed surveillance.
According to the Hong Kong publication, in the Prince Holding business universe, chaired by the Fujian businessman, there are companies that had business in Macau selling alcoholic beverages through a network of companies that had as a common denominator a businessman also active in Hong Kong: Qiu Yong. The businessman, who appears on the list of 146 companies and people sanctioned by the United States due to the alleged commission of the crimes mentioned above, holds passports from Cambodia and Saint Lucia, a small island in the Caribbean, and was the main shareholder of eight companies based in Hong Kong, two of which have already been dissolved.
One of the companies based and operating in the neighboring region was the Wine Mini Store Digital Economy Industry Company, led together with Ng Sang Lei, a Macau resident and Macao SAR passport holder.
A web in the delta
The Wine Mini Store had a commercial address in Tsim Sha Tsui in the same place where several companies were headquartered that fugitive billionaire Chen Zhi controlled indirectly through offshore companies in the British Virgin Islands and companies in Hong Kong.
Among the companies created and dissolved is the Pou Long Wine Company, based in Tsim Sha Tsui, which was fully owned by Ng Sang Lei before the commercial registration was annulled in October this year. According to reports in Macau in the past, the Pou Long Wine Company launched a series of activities, including a gala dinner for the elderly, in January 2020, which was attended by Qiu Yong.
In February 2020, during the outbreak of Covid-19 in Wuhan, the Pou Long Wine Company donated 1.5 million patacas and 60,000 masks to the provincial authorities.
In relation to the Macau resident, HM found references to Ng Sang Lei in the Official Gazette, when she was authorized by the Macau Monetary Authority to practice as an insurance intermediary in the Macao SAR in June 2019. Less than 10 months later, the resident was the target of an infringement procedure.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:50:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibitions | More events but less money</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/exposicoes-mais-eventos-mas-menos-dinheiro/</link><description>Between January and September, 1,331 conventions and exhibitions were held in Macau, an increase of 25.7 percent year on year, or 272 events. The numbers were released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
However, despite there being more events, the sector's profits were lower than in 2024. Revenue generated by convention and exhibition events was 3.72 billion patacas, which represented a reduction of 9.4 percent compared to the same period last year, when revenues reached 4.10 billion patacas.
DSEC explained the reduction in annual revenue “mainly due to the drop in the number of visitors in general from abroad who came to the exhibitions”. The drop was most pronounced between January and June, with the third quarter being the exception.
Compared to the third quarter, 385 convention and exhibition events were held, a year-on-year increase of 10.3 percent, and the number of participants and visitors was 567,000, up 8.2 percent year-on-year. Revenues were 2.02 billion patacas, an annual increase of 9.8 percent, given that in the third quarter of 2024 revenues did not exceed 1.84 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:49:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Retail | Turnover down 5.4 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/retalho-volume-de-negocios-com-quebra-de-54-por-cento/</link><description>Between January and September, retail trade turnover showed an annual reduction of 5.4 percent to 50.56 billion patacas. The data was released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). Among the reductions, the turnover of motor vehicle fuels and leather goods fell by 11.6 percent and 11.1 percent, respectively. On the opposite side, pharmacy turnover rose 7.8 percent.
At the same time, the average sales volume index of retail establishments registered a year-on-year drop of 7.5 percent. The average sales volume index for watches and jewelry fell 19.6 percent, while that for pharmacies grew 8.2 percent.
In relation to the fourth quarter of the year, DSEC indicates that 46.8 percent of retailers anticipate the stabilization of sales volume in annual terms, while 43.5 percent foresee a decrease, that is, they expect the situation to get even worse. However, 9.7 percent of businesspeople were optimistic and expected improvements.
Despite the drop and the lack of optimism, when the analysis is made only taking into account the third quarter of this year, retail trade turnover grew 2.2 percent year-on-year, to 16.96 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:48:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Room prices in luxury hotels fell 1.8%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/118153/</link><description>On average, the price of rooms in five-star hotels in October registered an annual drop of 1.8 percent to around 1,572 patacas, in the month of Golden Week. In the first 10 months of this year, the decrease reached almost 5 percent
The average price of a room in a five-star hotel last October was around 1,572 patacas, a figure that represented an annual drop of 1.8 percent. In the same month, which included the Golden Week holidays, the average occupancy rate remained at 94.2 percent, similar to that seen in 2024.
The data was provided by the GGR Asia portal, based on the Macau Hotel Association's monthly survey, which collects information from 48 hotel units, 27 of which are five-star. According to the association's accounts, average room prices in five-star hotels have recorded consecutive annual drops in the last 16 months.
Remember that the five-star segment dominates the city's hotel market. According to the latest official data, for the month of September, the total number of rooms in five-star hotels represented almost 60 percent of the approximately 44 thousand rooms available in Macau. The proportion is more significant considering that Government statistics include establishments below three stars.
Glass almost full
If in October the average price of a night in a five-star hotel room was 1,572 patacas, in the first 10 months of 2025 the average price is almost 60 patacas lower than the monthly figure, totaling 1,513 patacas, which represents an annual decrease of 4.8 percent. However, between January and the end of October, the occupancy rate of five-star hotels rose 2.3 percent year on year, to an average of 94.4 percent.
Taking into account all hotels in Macau, regardless of the number of stars, in the first 10 months of 2025, the average occupancy rate reached 93.6 percent, 2.1 percent more compared to the same period in the past. The average price of a night fell 3.2 percent to around 1,352 patacas.
Macau received 3.47 million visitors in October, 10.8 percent more than in the same period in 2024 and the highest figure ever for the month under analysis since the Government began compiling monthly data in 1998, still during the Portuguese administration.
Between the 1st and 8th of October alone, the holiday period, 1.14 million tourists entered Macau. Despite record arrivals in October, with the increase in day-trippers or tourists opting for accommodation outside Macau, the number of overnight stays grew by just 1.7 percent.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
At a lunch with several guests, I heard a friend, who declared herself a spiritualist, explaining the particularities of her belief, in a calm and balanced way, I would even say, without a hint of “irrationalism”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«If transparency is demanded from politicians, we kill them; if anyone demands fidelity to what the other was or what he says, kill him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, representation is killed. These must therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to bend the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). I believe we will be needed to decipher this frantically complex world that has fallen to us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Let men refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish, because of it the tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the pride of the countries will be destroyed.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were restricted, or if it merely lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, in a different way, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse like a shadow
[misshapen
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piela than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Xi calls for the Strip to be under Palestinian control</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/gaza-xi-defende-que-faixa-fique-sob-controlo-palestiniano/</link><description>The Chinese President called for the reconstruction of the Gaza Strip to be carried out under the principle of “Palestinians govern Palestine” and urged the international community to promote a “comprehensive and lasting ceasefire”.
Xi Jinping stated that the Palestinian issue “affects international equity and justice” and constitutes “a test of the effectiveness of the global governance system”, said the Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs. In a message sent to a UN meeting on Tuesday, the Chinese leader argued that the international community must “take responsibility, correct historical injustices and defend justice”.
On the occasion of the International Day of Solidarity with the Palestinian People, Xi stressed that any post-war structure must respect “the will of the Palestinian people” and take into account the legitimate concerns of countries in the region. The Chinese leader insisted that efforts must “be anchored in the two-state solution” to achieve a “comprehensive, fair and lasting” political agreement.
The Chinese President said that the immediate priority is to improve the humanitarian situation and alleviate the suffering of civilians in Gaza, and reiterated that Beijing, as a permanent member of the Security Council, “will continue to support the just cause of the Palestinian people to restore their legitimate national rights”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:09:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul | Bill presented to reduce US taxes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/seul-apresentado-projecto-de-lei-para-reduzir-taxas-dos-eua/</link><description>The ruling party in South Korea yesterday presented a bill to support South Korean investment commitments in the United States in exchange for reduced US tariffs.
The bill provides for the creation of a special fund to finance the promised investment of 350 billion dollars to the United States, in exchange for the reduction of Washington's customs tariffs on vehicles and vehicle parts, among others, from 25 percent to 15 percent.
Of the total amount, 150 billion dollars will be allocated to the North American naval sector, while the remaining 200 billion dollars will be invested, in annual tranches of up to 20 billion dollars, in various strategic US sectors.
Although the legislative proposal will still be analyzed by the South Korean parliament, with the mere presentation of the document the tariff reduction will apply with retroactive effect to November 1st, in line with the bilateral memorandum of understanding signed in the middle of this month.
The South Korean Ministry of Commerce sent a letter to the United States Secretary of Commerce, Howard Lutnick, informing that the proposed law to implement the memorandum of understanding has already been presented to the South Korean National Assembly and requesting that the retroactive reduction be applied accordingly.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 02:05:04</pubDate></item><item><title>China says it will crush interference in Taiwan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/china-diz-que-esmagara-ingerencias-em-taiwan/</link><description>China yesterday again accused Japan of increasing regional tension with the announced deployment of missiles on islands near Taiwan, warning that it will “crush” any attempt at external interference in what it considers an internal matter.
The spokesman for the Taiwan Affairs Office of the State Council (Chinese Executive), Peng Qing'en, classified Tokyo's decision as an “extremely dangerous provocation” and accused Japan of “creating tension and fueling military confrontation” in an area just 110 kilometers from Taiwan.
"We have the firm will, determination and ability to safeguard China's sovereignty and territorial integrity and crush any attempt at external interference," Peng said at a press conference in Beijing. The spokesman accused Tokyo of violating the spirit of the country's pacifist Constitution and moving towards “military expansion”, driven by “right-wing forces seeking to free themselves from post-war restrictions”.
Peng recalled that the Potsdam Declaration (1945) prohibited Japanese rearmament, stressing that this development “aroused the concern of the international community”.
The concrete date for the deployment of this anti-missile system on a chain of islands near Taiwan, capable of intercepting aerial threats at an altitude of around 50 kilometers, has not yet been decided, but it corresponds to 14 new surface-to-air anti-missile units that the Japanese Government plans to install by 2031 to triple the protection systems in an area of ​​special strategic interest.
China's reaction comes at a time of maximum diplomatic tension between Beijing and Tokyo, following recent statements by the new Japanese Prime Minister, Sanae Takaichi, who declared that a Chinese attack against Taiwan could justify the intervention of the Japanese Self-Defense Forces.
China demanded the retraction of the head of the Japanese Government, summoned the Japanese ambassador and issued official warnings advising Chinese citizens against traveling to Japan, which caused hundreds of thousands of flight cancellations and affected the Japanese tourist and cultural sector.
Tokyo, in turn, argued that the deployment of surface-to-air missiles on the islands of the Nansei archipelago is exclusively for defense purposes and is part of the security strategy adopted in 2022, in the midst of Tokyo's historic shift towards rearmament.
The Japanese Ministry of Defense reported this week the incursion of a Chinese drone between the island of Yonaguni and Taiwan, which justified the sending of fighter jets.
No progress
Diplomatic tension remains, despite recent appeals from US President Donald Trump to both Chinese leader Xi Jinping and Takaichi.
During a telephone conversation with Trump, Xi insisted that Taiwan's "return" to China constitutes an "important part" of the post-World War II international order, while Tokyo insists that its position has not changed and that any dispute over the island, self-governed since 1949, must be resolved peacefully.
Tokyo and Beijing have held high-level bilateral meetings looking for ways to de-escalate the current tension, without clear signs of progress, according to analysts.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:58:53</pubDate></item><item><title>HK commercial real estate investment triples in third quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/investimento-no-imobiliario-comercial-em-hk-triplica-no-terceiro-trimestre/</link><description>Capital raising in Hong Kong's commercial real estate sector recorded a historic increase in the third quarter of 2025, with a year-on-year increase of 231 percent, according to data from Morgan Stanley Capital International (MSCI). Trading volume reached US$4.9 billion, placing the city as the second fastest growing market in the Asia-Pacific region, behind only Malaysia.
According to the data services provider, which compiles operations valued at more than 10 million dollars, this is the largest quarterly amount since 2019, reflecting a progressive recovery in the financial enclave's real estate sector, which has been hit hard in recent years.
The report details that capital was concentrated in offices, data centers, commercial spaces, hotels and senior housing. MSCI highlighted that the main operations in Hong Kong covered both corporate and technology assets, driven by a gradual improvement in investment flows from mainland China.
This 'boom' comes after years of asset depreciation and financial restrictions, accentuated by the rise in interest rates, which reached highs not seen since 2007. However, the recent decision by the Hong Kong Monetary Authority to reduce the reference interest rate by a quarter of a point, to 4.25 percent, eased credit burdens and supported investment activity.
Good numbers
Between January and September, real estate investment in the territory accumulated US$6.2 billion, an annual increase of 39 percent, according to calculations by Morgan Stanley published yesterday in the South China Morning Post newspaper. Since the beginning of the monetary easing cycle, in September last year, several important operations have been concluded.
In July, Mike Cai Wensheng, co-founder of Chinese app Meitu, a popular photo editing and digital retouching platform, acquired land for redevelopment in the Causeway Bay district for HK$750 million, the company's second purchase in three months.
In turn, Alibaba Group and its associate Ant Group spent 7.2 billion Hong Kong dollars in October to purchase several floors of a project promoted by Mandarin Oriental International, on the site of the former Excelsior hotel. The deal constituted the city's largest real estate transaction since 2021.
However, the office market remains active. This week, the sale of a unit on the 35th floor of the Bank of America Tower, in the Central district, was recorded for 27.31 million Hong Kong dollars, while the 52nd floor of The Center was transferred to Prosperous Global Investment for 565.29 million Hong Kong dollars.
“Global expectations are more optimistic than at the beginning of the year”, said Benjamin Chow, head of private asset research for Asia at MSCI, quoted by the Hong Kong daily. "Incomes are once again positive and activity is recovering in most major markets. Everything indicates that 2025 will end with a favorable balance", he highlighted.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:57:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | At least 13 people died in a fire</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/27/hong-kong-pelo-menos-13-pessoas-morreram-num-incendio/</link><description>The images of the fire that spread through the apartment blocks with capacity for 2,000 people suggest a major tragedy
At least 12 people died yesterday in a fire that spread to several buildings in a Hong Kong housing complex, according to the Chinese press, highlighting that there were people trapped in the apartments. According to the South China Morning Post portal, 12 people, including a firefighter, died and at least 16 others were seriously injured in the fire that devastated the Tai Po neighborhood.
The other 11 fatalities were eight women and three men, according to sources cited by the media outlet. The flames consumed bamboo scaffolding in all eight buildings in the social neighborhood, leaving several other residents trapped inside the apartments, according to the Chinese news portal.
The director of the local fire department, Andy Yeung, told reporters that one firefighter was among the dead and another had to receive medical treatment for heat exhaustion.
According to the Associated Press (AP) news agency, videos from the scene showed at least five buildings close to each other in flames, with smoke coming out of many apartment windows, as night fell. Firefighters fought the flames by throwing water from the ladders of the corporation's trucks.
The violent fire released a column of flames and dense smoke as it spread through the bamboo scaffolding and protective screens installed around the buildings, located in the Tai Po district. Records show the housing complex is made up of eight buildings with almost 2,000 apartments.
Hong Kong police said they had received several reports of people trapped in fire-stricken buildings, but did not provide details.
Maximum level
The fire was reported in the middle of the afternoon and, after dark, authorities raised it to alert level 5, the highest level of severity, according to the fire department.
Tai Po district authorities opened temporary shelters for people left homeless by the fire. Tai Po is a suburban area in the New Territories, in the northern part of Hong Kong and close to the border with the city of Shenzhen in mainland China.
Bamboo scaffolding is common in Hong Kong in building construction and renovation projects, although the Government announced earlier this year that it would begin phasing it out of public projects due to safety concerns.</description><pubDate>2025-11-27 01:56:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Japan sends military planes to nearby island after detecting Chinese drone</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/taiwan-japao-envia-avioes-militares-para-ilha-proxima-apos-detectar-drone-chines/</link><description>Japan yesterday sent military planes to Yonaguni, the Japanese island closest to Taiwan, following the detection of a Chinese drone, as tension between Beijing and Tokyo has been rising in recent weeks.
“We confirm that a suspected Chinese drone flew over the airspace between the island of Yonaguni and Taiwan on Monday,” the Japanese Ministry of Defense declared yesterday on the social network X. The Air Force “sent aircraft” in response to this incident, the Japanese Ministry added.
On Monday, China strongly criticized statements made the previous day by Japanese Defense Minister Shinjiro Koizumi. The Japanese minister, who was visiting Yonaguni, stated that the plan to install medium-range surface-to-air missiles on that island was “on schedule”.
“Japan's sending of offensive weapons to the southwestern islands, close to Taiwan, deliberately aims to create regional tension and provoke a military confrontation,” said Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning at a press conference.
Yesterday, Koizumi told journalists that the missiles “are not intended to attack other countries (…) and clearly do not contribute to increasing tension in the region”. Tension between China and Japan has increased since Japanese Prime Minister Sanae Takaichi declared on November 7 that armed operations against Taiwan could justify Japanese military intervention to defend the island.
China, which claims Taiwan as part of its territory, considered these statements a provocation. Yonaguni has been home to a Japan Self-Defense Forces base since 2016, despite initial objections from locals. Tokyo announced its intention to deploy medium-range surface-to-air missiles on the island to defend against missile and aircraft attacks.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 02:04:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong bans imports from Santarém due to bird flu</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/hong-kong-proibe-importacoes-de-santarem-devido-a-gripe-aviaria/</link><description>The Hong Kong region yesterday banned the import of poultry meat and derivatives, including eggs, from the Santarém district, following the detection of cases of bird flu.
The Hong Kong Center for Food Safety (CFS) stressed that the decision was taken “to protect public health”, following notifications from the World Organization for Animal Health (WOAH). According to official data cited in a CFS statement, the semi-autonomous Chinese territory did not import poultry meat or derivatives from Portugal in the first nine months of 2025.
The CFS said it has already contacted the Portuguese authorities and that it will “closely” monitor the situation and the information issued by WOAH. “Appropriate measures will be taken in response to the developing situation,” he added. The CFS also banned yesterday, for the same reason, the import of poultry meat and poultry products from some regions of Poland, Italy, Belgium, Ireland and the United Kingdom.
On November 18, Hong Kong had already banned the import of poultry meat and derivatives, including eggs, from the Porto district, following the detection of cases of bird flu. A similar measure was taken the following day by the neighboring Chinese region of Macau.
Confirmed disease
On Monday, the Portuguese Directorate-General for Food and Veterinary Affairs (DGAV) confirmed an outbreak of avian influenza in a domestic chicken and duck farm, in the district of Santarém.
According to information published by DGAV, the total number of outbreaks detected this year rose to 39. DGAV has been warning that the risk of spreading bird flu is, at the moment, high in Portugal and has called for the adoption of safety measures.
Poultry in establishments located in high-risk areas, including domestic poultry houses and captive birds, must be in captivity, in accordance with the rules determined by DGAV.
In protection and surveillance zones, the movement of birds, the restocking of game birds, fairs, markets and exhibitions, the movement of fresh meat and eggs for incubation and for human consumption, as well as the movement of animal by-products are prohibited.
The DGAV specified that all infringements of these rules will be punished. On November 11, DGAV warned in a notice that avian influenza causes “very high mortality, especially in poultry”.
This has “an important impact (…) on poultry production, as it constitutes a reason for suspending the sale of live birds and their products in the affected areas and may be a reason for preventing the export of birds and products”, he added. Transmission of the H5N1 virus to humans occurs rarely, with sporadic cases having been reported around the world. However, when it occurs, the infection can lead to a serious clinical condition.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:56:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong wants to ban two exile organizations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/hong-kong-quer-banir-duas-organizacoes-de-exilados/</link><description>Hong Kong Security Secretary Chris Tang Ping-keung said yesterday that he wants to ban two organizations created abroad by exiles from the semi-autonomous Chinese region, which he accused of separatism.
On Monday, the territory's government announced that it was considering banning the organization Hong Kong Parliament (Hong Kong Parliament), created in Canada, and the Hong Kong Democratic Independence Union (HKDIU), established in Taiwan.
In a statement, the Hong Kong executive said it had sent written notices to the two organizations, allowing them to present allegations before a possible ban. Yesterday, at a press conference, Chris Tang confirmed that the two groups have a week to respond to the allegations, but hinted that the decision has already been made.
“I analyzed the relevant evidence and believe that the ban is a necessary measure to safeguard national security”, highlighted the leader. "The objective of these two organizations is to divide the country and subvert the power of the State. They promote the so-called autonomy, that is, the independence of Hong Kong, and what they describe as the constitution of Hong Kong", said the secretary.
“In fact, this undermines the basic system of our national Constitution and also harms the power of Hong Kong and our country,” assured Tang, quoted by the local press. The leader advised Hong Kong residents not to participate in the activities of the two organizations and recalled that, according to the national security law approved in March 2024, they risk a prison sentence of up to 14 years.
Crimes and arrests
Tang recalled that the city's courts have already issued arrest warrants for 19 members of the Hong Kong Parliament organization and that a collaborator of the group was sentenced to 12 months in prison. On November 13, a court found 19-year-old Lan Fei guilty of the crime of sedition for appearing in two videos, published in April and May, that promoted the election for the Hong Kong Parliament organization.
Four members of the Democratic Union for the Independence of Hong Kong have already been detained – including a 16-year-old – and are awaiting trial, while another member is wanted for calling for a boycott of the elections for the local parliament on December 7th.
In 2018, the Hong Kong government banned the Hong Kong National Party, a pro-independence movement, in an unprecedented decision since the transfer of sovereignty from the former British colony in 1997. John Lee Ka-chiu, the then Secretary for Security and current leader of the Government, justified the ban at the time with the protection of national security, public safety, public order and the freedom and rights of citizens.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:54:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomacy | Xi defended the importance of Taiwan's return to China with Trump</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/26/diplomacia-xi-defendeu-junto-de-trump-a-importancia-do-regresso-de-taiwan-a-china/</link><description>In a telephone conversation between the two presidents, Xi Jinping emphasized the importance of maintaining the good relations achieved after the meeting in Busan and took the opportunity to once again emphasize that Taiwan's return to China is an important part of the international order.
Chinese President Xi Jinping defended with his North American counterpart the importance of the territory of Taiwan returning to China, which admits retaking it by force, the Chinese news agency Xinhua reported on Monday.
In a telephone conversation between the two, the Chinese President told Donald Trump that the two countries must “maintain the dynamics of their relations” after the October meeting in South Korea and “underlined that Taiwan's return to China is an important part of the post-war international order”, according to Xinhua.
Xi also stressed that Beijing and Washington have already “fought side by side against fascism and militarism” and that they now “should jointly safeguard the victorious results of World War II”, according to the Chinese agency.
Trump and Xi met for the first time since 2019 in October, in Busan, South Korea, and held talks that were closely watched, in the midst of a trade war between the two countries. The battle between the world's two biggest economies, covering everything from rare earths to soybeans to customs duties, has roiled markets and disrupted supply chains for months.
Xi also told Trump that the “successful” Busan meeting helped “produce momentum in the steady movement of the gigantic ship of Sino-US relations,” according to news agency France Presse (AFP). “Since the Busan meeting, Sino-US relations have remained stable and continued to improve, which has been warmly welcomed by the two countries and the international community,” Xi added.
Japanese threats
Also on Monday, China warned Japan that the project to install missiles near Taiwan is an “extremely dangerous” development, following statements by Japanese Prime Minister, Sanae Takaichi, about the nationalist island.
“Japan’s deployment of offensive weapons on the southwestern islands neighboring Taiwan is deliberately aimed at creating regional tensions and provoking a military confrontation,” said Chinese diplomatic spokeswoman Mao Ning in Beijing. Mao was reacting to statements by Japanese Defense Minister Shinjiro Koizumi, who said on Sunday that the objective of placing surface-to-air missiles on Yonaguni, the Japanese island closest to Taiwan, was “on track”.
The governments of Beijing and Tokyo have been involved in a climate of tension since Takaichi stated on November 7 that armed operations against Taiwan could justify Japanese military intervention to defend the island. Beijing, which claims Taiwan as part of China's territory, sees Takaichi's words as a provocation.
Visit in April
North American President Donald Trump announced on Monday a visit to Beijing in April, which will be reciprocated with a trip by his counterpart to the United States at the end of next year. Donald Trump made the announcement a few hours after speaking with Xi by phone, at which time, as he indicated, both discussed issues such as the conflict in Ukraine, the fight against the opioid fentanyl and the soy trade.
The phone call took place almost a month after the two met in the South Korean city of Busan. Chinese officials confirmed the phone call, without mentioning the two leaders' state visits, reporting that topics discussed included Ukraine, trade and Taiwan. After the conversation, the White House leader considered, in a message on his Truth Social network, the relationship with Beijing as “extremely strong”, but made no reference to the sensitive issue of Taiwan.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 01:52:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Luís Bernardino, academic: “We need to define a defense cooperation strategy” for the CPLP</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/25/luis-bernardino-academico-precisamos-definir-uma-estrategia-de-cooperacao-defesa-para-a-cplp/</link><description>The book “25 Years of Defense Cooperation at CPLP” was released in 2023 in digital format and, two years later, reached the printed version. Luís Bernardino, co-author linked to the Universidade Autónoma de Lisboa, highlights positive developments since the creation of the Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries, despite inaction and controversies with Equatorial Guinea
“25 Years of Defense Cooperation in the CPLP [Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries]” was released as an e-book and is now available in print. Why edit this book?
This book talks about the 25 years of cooperation in the CPLP defense area and is written by me, together with a colleague from Brazil, Camila Rizzi. It results from a research project developed at the CPLP Strategic Analysis Center, based in Mozambique. It has the CPLP defense component and makes strategic reflection on this topic. Due to the fact that 25 years of cooperation have passed in this area, we wanted to carry out an evaluation and the book so that it would remain in the history of the organization. In 2023, there were no financial conditions to publish the book on paper as we wanted, and it was now launched on November 18th, in Maputo.
There is criticism regarding the effective action of the CPLP. Do you consider that this organism has grown sustainably?
The assessment I make is in the area of ​​defense. When the CPLP was created, cooperation in the area of ​​defense was not included in the initial six areas. This area only emerged in 1998. The CPLP was born with six main areas – culture, language, political-diplomatic concentration – and currently has 26 areas of cooperation, which is proof that it has grown in a sustained manner. Obviously, with ups and downs, situations have become easier over these almost 30 years. But what stands out in this book, in the area of ​​defense, is that there was a very consolidated and participated growth. In these 25 years, a lot of interesting things have been done and the evaluation is positive.
And the future?
We need to define a defense cooperation strategy and what we want for the CPLP in this area over the next 25 years. This is the challenge we face, of greater activity and initiative, so that cooperation and defense can be strategic in what is cooperation within States. So that it can be more visible and effectively allow for growth, participation and development, or even greater commitment, in regional contexts.
But looking at the past, present and future, what has the dynamic been like in the defense area?
The book shows a certain dynamic of substantial constitutional growth in the first phase. Then there were very interesting developments, with some protocols and cooperation at the level of the Armed Forces, but there is still a lot to do, namely looking at the area of ​​defense cooperation as a strategic area.
The global geopolitical system appears to be changing very quickly, following a multipolar path. Should the CPLP have another role in this context, with actors such as China, Russia or the United States?
The CPLP is not a multilateral instrument, it is not an organization of that level. We have to place the CPLP at the level of the Commonwealth, for example, of organizations at a cultural, linguistic level, of partnership between countries, of concern for development. What I usually say is that the CPLP is a good diplomatic communication instrument, a soft power in areas related to conflict management and prevention. Let us not expect there to be armed forces, or an army, from the CPLP. This body is one of dialogue and cooperation. What we do, in terms of defense, is exactly that, create partnerships so that there are mechanisms for responding to disasters, to provide training capacity for the armed forces. There are even those who ask the question: why did the CPLP not intervene in Cabo Delgado, in Mozambique, on the issue of terrorism?
And why?
Because the CPLP is not a hard power mechanism, it has no capacity, doctrine, logistics, mandate or viability to be used in combat operations. And CPLP Member States are very aware that we are a very good mechanism for cooperation, partnership and development, with contributions to culture and language. Therefore, the CPLP will not intervene in the conflict between Russia and Ukraine, because that is not its area, nor does it have mechanisms for this dynamic.
Is the existence of the CPLP justified?
I think so, obviously, because, as I said, the CPLP is a very good instrument in terms of cooperation, the dissemination of the Portuguese language, of history. The fact is that we have around 350 million people who speak Portuguese. We have 30 countries that are associated observers, such as Ukraine, Chile, and Portuguese culture is represented in this organization. Each country has what it wants from the CPLP and gives it the importance it thinks it should give, and this depends on the foreign policy of each State. But I think the CPLP makes a lot of sense in the world we live in, and does so as a multilateral representative of language, culture, cooperation between Portuguese-speaking states, and those that ultimately have some affinity [with the Portuguese-speaking world]. The Macau issue is very specific to this organization.
Macau has the role of a commercial platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, and China has an agenda for Lusophony.
Before 1999 Macau had its own status within the CPLP, as it was administered by Portuguese. There was a Joint Declaration that allowed Macau, not being a Member State, to have, in a certain way, a protocol [with the CPLP]. When it became a Macao SAR, things changed and it lost that connection status, and Macau is not a member of the CPLP, and obviously cannot be. Neither does China, and it cannot be. Therefore, there is an associated observer status here that arises for countries, international and regional organizations, and even territorial entities with their own administration, which is also not quite the case in Macau. The territory is in limbo, between having a very strong history linked to Lusofonia, and having an administration very linked to China, which gives it, in my perspective, two dynamics.
In what sense?
Macau is a fundamental element in the connection between the CPLP countries and China. For all reasons, but due to the issue of language, history, and its representation, it is a fundamental actor in this cooperation. Macau must effectively be seen as a partner and as a gateway for China to Portuguese-speaking countries. This is what, in a way, is already happening, and this is what the CPLP will be paying attention to, in this relationship in which Macau has a special status. Whether we like it or not, it has an impact. Macau is an attractive factor in facilitating relations between China and Angola, Portugal or Brazil.
Does Equatorial Guinea's stay in the CPLP raise questions of credibility?
I agree with you. In these 30 years, it has been one of the main difficult moments in creating consensus. I remember that Equatorial Guinea was admitted in 2014, but there was already a process in the previous analysis phase. There was always an extension, year after year, and it was difficult to reach a consensus within the CPLP countries. In 2014, there was a summit in Timor-Leste and, through the action of Brazil and Angola, there was, in a way, a lot of pressure for Equatorial Guinea to join. But there are two principles, for better and for worse, that justify Equatorial Guinea's presence in the CPLP.
What are…
The first argument is that, in fact, Equatorial Guinea has Portuguese as its official language in its Constitution, despite us knowing that the Portuguese language, for example, covers four or five percent of society as a whole, and I am already being quite generous. But there is a commitment from the Equatorial Guinea authorities to develop Portuguese as a working language and there is a historical connection to Portuguese culture and Lusophony. Another criterion is the promise that, in the next constitutional review, a commitment will be made to abolish the death penalty. As for Portuguese, it's something that takes generations, it's not done from one year to the next. Not even in the next 10 or 15 years will we have Portuguese perfectly implemented. There is some shyness, a commitment, in a way. As for the death penalty, the fact is that, it seems, some change has been achieved. There has never been a death penalty action again [since accession]. And there is hope that, in the next constitutional review, this fact will be abolished from the Constitution and that it may, effectively, cease to exist. As a member of the CPLP, these changes will be easier and more visible and, in the future, Equatorial Guinea can effectively assume CPLP status taking these premises into account. I don't know if it will happen, I leave here a reluctance, and this is a challenging moment for the CPLP itself. Work needs to be done from within, so that Equatorial Guinea can be at the same level as other countries, especially in these two areas.
What is certain is that there remains a certain lack of transparency regarding what is happening in the country.
We are aware that Equatorial Guinea has major problems with issues of democratic legitimacy and elections. There are a series of situations that we recognize are not perfectly adequate given the status of CPLP countries. I think there is hope that things can change, an attempt to create space for Portuguese to grow within Equatorial Guinea, and also a commitment to greater openness and participation. What is a fact is that Equatorial Guinea has participated in CPLP meetings, and I have participated in some. In international situations we have to be pragmatic, and we hope that, just because Equatorial Guinea is in the CPLP, this can help Guinea itself to develop some mechanical gestures.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timor-Leste / Independence – Mari Alkatiri: Proclamation was anticipated by the Indonesian military presence</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/timor-leste-independencia-mari-alkatiri-proclamacao-foi-antecipada-pela-presenca-militar-indonesia/</link><description>Interview by Isabel Marisa Serafim, from the Lusa agency
The leader of the Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin), Mari Alkatiri, said that the unilateral proclamation of independence was scheduled for December 1, 1975, but was brought forward because Indonesian troops were already in the territory.
“It was initially scheduled for December 1st,” said Mari Alkatiri, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, which is marked on Friday, and of the Indonesian occupation, nine days later, on December 7th.
In November, Mari Alkatiri went on a “safari” through several African countries, mainly the Portuguese-speaking African Countries (PALOP), which involved participating in the declaration of Angola’s independence on November 11, 1975.
"After this 'tour', this African 'safari', I returned to the country. At the time I was in Maputo to prepare my return and I received a call from Nicolau Lobato not to return, because we needed to have someone outside the country", he recalled, highlighting that he did not follow the order from the then vice-president of Fretilin.
“So I returned to Dili on the 22nd or 23rd of November and the central committee and military political committee were meeting at the current headquarters of the National Police of Timor-Leste, which was the provisional headquarters of Fretilin, and the proclamation for December 1st was being discussed”, he explained. On November 28, Mari Alkatiri, then 25 years old, recalled that Nicolau Lobato came to her house and said that it was necessary to proclaim independence that day.
"We both left in his car for Lahane where Xavier do Amaral [former president of Fretilin] was and we conveyed this to Xavier Amaral, who clearly said to wait another three or four days. We said there was no time to wait and we decided to make the proclamation that day in the afternoon", he said.
"Fortunately, not only was the Constitution ready, but also the flag was ready. It was my mother who sewed the flag. There were minimum conditions for the proclamation of independence", stated the current secretary general of Fretilin, who also wrote the text of the proclamation.
“When I start talking about these days it’s not just memory, I actively participated in the unilateral proclamation of independence, although people try to cut out my photo, politics, but the truth is that there is only one person still alive who actively participated in the proclamation 50 years ago, that’s me”, he highlighted.
In the first Timorese Government, led by Nicolau Lobato and which only lasted nine days, Mari Alkatiri was appointed Minister of State for Political Affairs. Nocolau Lobato led the fight against the Indonesian occupation and was assassinated in December 1978. The restoration of independence took place on May 20, 2002, after a referendum for self-determination on August 30, 1999 and 24 years of resistance against Indonesia.
A question of egos
Mari Alkatiri also stated, in the same interview, that “egos” are preventing Timor-Leste from overcoming the challenges and that a more democratic, inclusive and comprehensive leadership culture is needed.
"If we managed it at the time, with all the difficulties, with all the challenges to overcome, at almost the speed of light, why can't we today? That's the question, the question of the cause. When the cause unites, the journey can go on, with many setbacks here and there, but we will succeed and we will win", said Mari Alkatiri in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, which marks this Friday.
Asked about the reason for no union, the leader of the Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin) ​​said it was “egos”.
“I am following the budget debate, when we continue to think in a 'cantin' way about State matters, we are not going anywhere”, criticized the former East Timorese Prime Minister, whose party chose to abstain in the final global vote on the State Budget.
Regarding criticism of the current government's options, Mari Alkatiri said she did not know if there was ever an option. "I don't see a strategy. There are some successes here and there, tries here and there, but there is no strategy, but there is a lot of support for strategic planning, strategic investment, but I don't see it", he stated.
“There is a need for a much more democratic, much more inclusive, very comprehensive leadership culture, with a sense of mission and vision for the future”, highlighted the secretary general of Fretilin. The party leader also warned not to wait for the “bomb to explode”.
“The delay bomb is there, the time bomb is there, I hope we don’t have to, after that, apologize for the truth, after the bomb goes off”, he highlighted. Asked if the “bomb” is dissatisfaction, the former prime minister said: “complete”.
"A country that after 24 years of restoring independence, with the means it had to work, why did it fail? Lack of sense of inclusion. We are building a State, we talk about the Democratic Rule of Law, is that true? Or oligarchic", he asked.
The new generations
Still in relation to young people, who represent the majority of the approximately 1.4 million inhabitants of Timor-Leste, Mari Alkatiri said that they feel lost. "Young people are naturally more generous when they are more considered, or more rebellious, when they are revolted. There are two facets here in youth, one of generosity when they embrace a cause, the other is a much more violent reaction of confrontation", he said.
Pointing out that more than 70% of the population is under 35 years old, Mari Alkatiri warned that those “two generations have already been sacrificed” due to “poor quality” education and “increasingly worse health” and “no prospects”. “Now, we all say that oil money will run out, I see that for the Government, the alternative to oil is oil”, he said.
In September, the capital of the Timor-Leste Petroleum Fund was US$18.95 billion (€16.4 billion). “We kept dreaming about Sunrise and as I usually say while we dream about Sunrise, we will have the ‘sunset’, because there is no politics, there are no plans, there are no programs”, he added.
Mari Alkatiri was referring to the Greater Sunrise gas field, located 150 kilometers from Timor-Leste and 450 kilometers from Darwin, whose project has been mired in an impasse, with Dili defending the construction of a gas pipeline to the south of the country, and Woodside, the consortium's second largest partner, leaning towards a connection to the existing unit in Darwin.
The consortium is made up of the Timorese company Timor Gap (56.56%), the operator Woodside Energy (33.44%) and Osaca Gás (10.00%). The Government of Timor-Leste announced on Saturday the signing of a cooperation agreement with the Australian Woodside Energy for studies to process and export gas to the country.
Missing discussions
The secretary general of the Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin), Mari Alkatiri, defended the need for “all together” to discuss what failed in the last 24 years, after the restoration of independence in May 2002.
"There is a lot of talk about new paradigms and the old paradigm, we are ready to sit down together to discuss the old paradigm, why did it fail? No", said the former Timorese prime minister, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, which marks this Friday.
For Mari Alkatiri, everyone contributed with “their positive part, with their negative part”, but it is necessary to understand the failures in “individual terms”, in “collective terms” and there be “responsibility”. Asked by Lusa about the reasons why there is no such discussion, the leader of the Timorese opposition replied that a “leader who cannot sit at the table is not a leader”.
"The leader must know that there is a time to sit at the table. I made proposals. When I returned in 2018, I said 'my vote is so that the people can win', I didn't say for Fretilin to win. The message was clear, it was time for us all to think together. I ran the campaign saying Fretilin wins, Xanana wins", stated Mari Alkatiri.
The Fretilin leader said the response has been “revenge, hate”. "In such a way that to take revenge on me, it affects hundreds of people, families. If it's me, come and talk to me, you don't have to harm others, but this is a specific issue", he stated, referring to the Timorese Prime Minister, XAnana Gusmão. The fundamental issue, continued Maria Alkatiri, is “to have a sense of mission, a vision of the future and to have a common cause”.
"What is crucial is knowing all the money that was spent, what was done. A balance of collective and individual performance. When we were waging war, we knew what we wanted, to restore independence, 24 years after the restoration of independence we don't know where we are going", lamented the leader.
Mari Alkatiri also said he was “very concerned” about the report by the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC), which warned on September 11 of the proliferation of criminal networks in Oecussi, a Timorese enclave on the Indonesian side of the island of Timor, highlighting that recent investigations show contamination of the region.
"It is already being absorbed by the mafia cartel, who are coming here in all their strength. We have closed kiosks and we think we are fighting the mafia. I am very worried," he said. For the future, Mari Alkatiri stated that he will continue to fight, but to “create critical mass”.
"My fight now is not the concern with electoral cycles, but how I can actually create a true critical mass in Timor-Leste. Let's end blindness, many of our academic intellectuals get pregnant through their ears, but they don't get pregnant", he highlighted.
The Fretilin leader also told everyone in his generation that it is time to put “egos” aside and start “thinking together”, highlighting that they have another five years to do so. “The next term of governance must be the product of understanding if we really want this country to move forward”, stated Mari Alkatiri, highlighting that the Timorese people deserve “much more and much better” than what has been given to date.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 17:33:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Independence | Ramos-Horta: It is “thanks to Xanana” that Timor-Leste is here</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/23/independencia-ramos-horta-e-gracas-ao-xanana-que-timor-leste-esta-aqui/</link><description>The Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, highlighted, in an interview with Lusa, the journey of the current prime minister and former leader of the residence, highlighting that it is “thanks to Xanana [Gusmão]” that Timor-Leste is here today.
“Xanana survived and with an impressive willpower, which few human beings can have, reorganizes the resistance, new attacks against the Indonesians”, said Ramos-Horta, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the declaration of independence, on November 28, 1975, remembering the attacks that the prime minister was the target of.
The Timorese leader lost men and suffered setbacks, but organized the clandestine network and resistance in the occupied cities. Xanana Gusmão was elected leader of the resistance and commander-in-chief of the Armed Forces for the National Liberation of Timor-Leste (FALINTL) in 1981, having launched the National Unity Policy, developed the Clandestine Front and established the National Council of Maubere Resistance, later named the National Council of Timorese Resistance.
"We reached the referendum in 1999 thanks to Xanana, not thanks to anyone else, obviously, the church got involved, because Xanana had the lucidity to talk to D. Martinho da Costa Lopes, abandon Marxism-Leninism. Thanks to Xanana that we are here today", stated the head of state.
Martinho da Costa Lopes was one of the most important figures in the Catholic Church in East Timor during the Indonesian occupation and played a central role in defending the human rights of the Timorese.
José Ramos-Horta also regretted that they now say that Xanana Gusmão is no longer the great man he was during the fight. "I say: gentlemen, now he was also the one who won the maritime border for us. I don't know who would win", he said, referring to the negotiation of maritime borders with Australia, concluded in 2018 and led by the current Prime Minister.
The President also highlighted that Xanana Gusmão was the one who took the historic decision to diversify from the Petroleum Fund in 2009, which “brought 11 billion dollars in return to Timor” and carried out the reconciliation, without persecution or judgment from anyone.
José Ramos-Horta also highlighted that it is Xanana Gusmão who “continues to have the technical competence” to discuss maritime borders with Indonesia, whose negotiation process began this year, as well as to resolve the Greater Sunrise issue, with the agreement expected to be signed at the beginning of next year.
"He wants to resolve all these issues before leaving power. He does not want to leave these very complex dossiers to the new generation", added the President.
Ideas and defenses
José Ramos-Horta stated that he was not in favor of the unilateral declaration of independence, on November 28, 1975, considering that it was made “hastily” given the imminent occupation by Indonesia.
"I was not in favor of the unilateral declaration of independence, I was, but it wasn't on November 28th. More preparation time was needed, because when you make a unilateral declaration of independence without any preparations, the result was what it was. There was no one. No one reacted", said Ramos-Horta, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary.
On November 28, 1975, the current head of state recalls a ceremony without the presence of a “single global personality” and a dark night. "The unilateral declaration of independence was made hastily for reasons determined by the circumstances of the time. The fall of Atabae [municipio de Bobonaro]", said Ramos-Horta.
"The base fell with a large onslaught of regular Indonesian forces, already deep inside Timor-Leste. First Batugadé fell, that was in October, Balibó and Maliana fell, in October and Atabai, fell in the early twenties of November. Soon after, Fretilin declared unilateral independence", explained the President.
The occupation by Indonesia took place on December 7, 1975. “Indonesian forces were already in the national territory before December 7 and the decision in Jakarta had been made in 1974 either Timor-Leste integrates into Indonesia peacefully through some pseudo-democratic act, or Timor-Leste would pass to Indonesian domination by force”, said the Timorese head of state.
The invasion is supported by the United States, Australia and some countries in the Association of Southeast Asian Nations (ASEAN).
"Obviously, in that context of 1975, the United States would not support Portugal on the issue of Timor-Leste. On the issue of Timor-Leste, Indonesia weighed more, especially in the post-Vietnam war context, in which the United States was discredited and fled. For the United States and for the countries in the region, the communist threat was real and Timor-Leste was isolated, abandoned", highlighted the Nobel Peace Prize winner.
The liberation of Timor-Leste took place on August 30, 1999, when the referendum for self-determination took place, which gave victory to independence, which would eventually take place on May 20, 2002, after a transitional administration by the United Nations.
“Twenty-four years later the country is freed against all the prophets of defeat, all those who preached realism to us, to me, some said atrocious unrealism, others said a lost cause, we heard a lot, including in Portugal”, added Ramos-Horta, highlighting that Timor-Leste managed to prevail.
Defense of the constitutional amendment
José Ramos-Horta defended, in the same interview, a constitutional amendment to adopt the presidential system in the country, because there is a need for “clear authority” and “without duality” and ruled out a re-candidacy for the position.
"I believe that we should make a constitutional amendment and move to the presidential system. The President is the executive, the so-called semi-presidentialism is over", said José Ramos-Horta, in an interview with Lusa as part of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, on November 28, 1975.
Currently, Timor-Leste has a semi-presidential system with a parliamentary bias, with the Government emanating from parliament. According to the head of state, the system chosen in the Constitution, drawn up in 2001 and 2002, “has not been bad at all”, but it has been seen that instead of “instead of being a balancing factor”, it can be a “factor of instability”.
Ramos-Horta exemplified what happened in the eighth Government, after the coalition led by Xanana Gusmão won the legislative elections with an absolute majority. “Xanana is invited to form a Government, they presented the list of rulers and President Lu Olo decides to veto, he did not want to inaugurate nine members”, said the Nobel Peace Prize winner.
"It is necessary to have a clear authority and without this duality, to share power with the President. It doesn't work. It works well in Portugal", highlighted Ramos-Horta. For the Timorese President, “there is no reason” for Timor-Leste to have adopted that model, because “balance is the parliament, the judiciary”.
"These three bodies are the constitution of the State. I think everyone will agree", he said. José Ramos-Horta considered that “it is time”, after around 25 years of the current Constitution, to make “some amendments” and move to the presidential system.
"For me, Xanana Gusmão should continue. We reach 2027, my term ends, new elections in 2028. Between the period of 2027, in which I leave, and 2028, we actively work on a constitutional amendment so that the 2028 election is already based on the new Constitution, that is what I defend", he explained.
When asked by Lusa whether he did not intend to run for a new term, the President stated that he was not “at least motivated”. “I, in 2027, will go to the ceremony of transition of the portfolio to the new President at midnight on May 19, 2027 and I won't even attend the ceremony on the 20th. I'm already in AeroDili on my way to Singapore”, he stated.
Problems of the new generation
In the same conversation, José Ramos-Horta also highlighted some of the country's current problems, namely the fact that the generation after 1975 has not yet found a leader with national affirmation. He highlighted that since 2002, members of this generation have held seats in the Government and parliament.
"The new generation has been there since 2002. The problem is that the new generation has not yet found a single person to assert themselves as a national leader. They have not yet appeared. That is the problem. They are in the Government, in the courts, in parliament, all new generations", said the President in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence.
José Ramos-Horta also questioned who is the leader of the new generation that “has a national dimension”. “There is none, not one, because in a democracy you have to win over the electorate”, he said, highlighting that a party is created and that party competes in the elections.
The head of state highlighted, however, that today Timor-Leste already has 210 doctorates and 1,700 masters, graduated from “good universities” and “there are people who know”. Timorese civil society has accused the current Timorese leadership, which continues to focus on figures from the resistance era, of creating obstacles to the emergence of new leaders with the capacity to respond to contemporary challenges.
Asked whether, after 50 years of the unilateral declaration of independence, the Timorese are reconciled, Ramos-Horta stated that among the “factions of [19]75 more than reconciled”. "Some have even died, the majority have died. There is no problem at all. When I see some brilliant being saying 'they are still the divisions of 75', you don't know that the majority have already died, only if they are the souls in the cemetery", said José Ramos-Horta.
According to the President, the divisions result from the democratic struggle. “I find it ridiculous, interesting, sometimes frustrating when I hear that the Timorese are divided,” said the President.
"Very well, let's all unite like it is done in North Korea, or rather, single party, single candidate, it is already known who wins the elections in North Korea, so there is not much headache, everything is simple, 97% votes for Kim Jong-un, then they do the recount and after all it was not 97%, but it was 101%. It's an option, then we are all united", joked Ramos-Horta.
But, he added, the Timorese chose democracy. "A democracy that is praised today and survives the wave of setbacks against democracy in Asia, Latin America, Africa and Europe. We are doing very well with democracy", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-11-23 18:59:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuca Roseta, fado singer: “Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/10/06/cuca-roseta-fadista-o-fado-e-um-samba-poesia-cantado-vindo-do-coracao/</link><description>During the pandemic, she sang for the Macau public through a video concert, but now, the fado singer gives her heart and soul to a concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra, part of the lineup for the Macau International Music Festival, next Saturday, 11th. In an interview with HM, Cuca Roseta talks about the show's lineup, her 15-year career and the truth found in her compositions.
Performs in Macau on October 11th with the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM). Tell me a little about what we can expect from this show.
Yes, we are finally going to Macau. It will be the first time because we previously did a video concert for Macau during the pandemic, and we were unable to be there physically. We now work with OCM, which is very good, and I am happy with this partnership, for being able to unite, in some way, two cultures. We are a little anxious about that fact.
The concert will have songs such as “Meu”, “Preto e Branco”, “Canção do Mar”, “Não Sei de Onde” and “Finalmente”. What does this alignment bring us?
We already had arrangements made for orchestra by Marinho de Freitas, which are extraordinary arrangements, and which will be adapted to the traditional OCM instruments. These songs are practically all written by me, lyrics and music, and tell different stories, some that I have lived myself or stories that, in some way, I have experienced someone living very closely. They are original fados. “Canção do Mar” is very old and became known in the voices of Dulce Pontes and Amália Rodrigues, and has a new arrangement. We thought it would look beautiful with OCM. Of course, there are songs that we always sing and that never leave the repertoire, linked to traditional phases of my career. There are some songs that people like and request, but we bring a completely different repertoire to what we presented at the time [in Macau, with the video concert], which was very well received. It was a concert that went very well, even though it was via video, and we received wonderful messages.
This year he released the album “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu”, which has an exclusively Brazilian repertoire, with several names in Brazilian music, such as Seu Jorge or Zeca Pagodinho. Why explore this universe, mixing it with the language of Fado?
Yes, but this year I will also release a French album with Amália Rodrigues' agent, who invited me. But “Até a Fé Se Esqueceu” came from an invitation from a great Brazilian producer to record old sambas, which have a lot to do with Fado. Even though it's a Brazilian album, all sambas, it's my saddest album of all, the most melancholic. That's why we went looking for this root of samba to find great poets and great composers that Brazil has, and who have this weight that Fado also has.
As?
Fado has a lot to do with words and composition, in fact, Fado is samba-poetry sung from the heart, because there has to be this truth in the interpretation, the idea of ​​truth coming from life's experiences, in transforming the story it tells. This melancholy is in the veins of Portuguese blood and is mixed with art and music. This invitation wanted to put a fado singer to sing seriously and with the weight that Fado brings, and be able to interpret the great poets and sambas. The album [Até a Fé Se Esqueceu] has very old sambas, one of them from 1937. It is, therefore, a very strong and even very beautiful album, with great poems and composers, such as Tom Jobim, Vinicius de Morais, and wonderful partnerships with Seu Jorge and Zeca Pagodinho, who came to Fado. It's an album that made me really proud.

Therefore, it is possible to marry Fado with the joy of samba, which also has a melancholic side, right? Like the melancholy of our Fado.
In fact, when we hear the word samba we think of joy, but in fact the basis of samba is not joy. There is that phrase by Vinicius de Morais, “To make a samba beautifully you need a bit of sadness, otherwise you won’t make a samba”. So that's where the beauty of this work lies, which goes to the roots of samba and shows that there aren't that many differences between the melancholy at the root of samba and the melancholy of Fado. It's a nostalgic and melancholic album, it doesn't bring that joy. It can bring hope, and we can say that some themes bring with them this hope, which we find in Brazilian culture and drums. Because they literally put their sadness on the skirt wheel and on the drums, right? They transform sadness into dance and music, but in this work we don't see that type of samba.
Cuca also has a previous album, “Cabo Verde Nha Cretcheu”, so it can be said that she has explored, in her career, the different Portuguese-speaking sounds, going beyond Fado, mixing sounds?
This album didn't come from my will, and I think [it's a sign] that life takes me, deep down. This album was born from a tour I took across the nine islands of Cape Verde with a live recording of the mornas I sang on each island, as I sang the traditional mornas of each island. Between one island and another there are very different moraines. What I did was, after my Fado concerts, I sang two mornas and then we compiled all the songs in Creole in celebration of the fact that I was the first international artist to do the nine islands in a row. But I was also in Goa and did my concert in Concanim. I find it easy and enjoy learning the traditional songs of the countries where I am going to sing. I already sang in Moscow and learned a Russian song; I learned the songs of Goa, and in Georgia, in Tblisi, I also learned a song. It's a treat I make when I travel around the world taking Fado. But morna is wonderful and there really are similarities between this musical genre, and I wanted to bring this encounter between Fado and morna to Cape Verdeans, and this album came about, which is beautiful.
Once it goes to Macau, can we expect a song in Cantonese, or Mandarin?
Yes. By chance, I had already spoken to my manager to contact someone in this regard, so that we could discover a traditional song that I could learn.
Last year, he celebrated 15 years of career. How do you review your career, which began with the albums “Cuca Roseta” and “Raiz”?
In fact, it was great to celebrate 15 years at MEO Arena [the concert hall in Lisbon], and be able to revisit all the albums since the first. “Raiz” opened up something that is rarer, which is the fado singer composing and writing her lyrics. This was a record that went wonderfully well and, from then on, it was good, because in this search for the truth that Fado has, being able to compose and write your own lyrics always means giving a little more of yourself. Each person composes and writes in their own way, and when they can do it, it is always a bit like the lines on the palm of their hand, that is, it is something unique. In this search that people make to follow standards to achieve success, I believe that success exists when we are not afraid to follow our voice and our instinct, what comes from our heart, tell our stories and sing our melodies without fear. In this way we end up becoming unique. Although it is not usual in Fado for a fado singer to compose and write, it was nice to see that my songs became important to many fans. Sometimes I have great composers and poets [to collaborate with me], but I think [writing and composing] brings out this side of the person being more truthful. My poems can never be compared to those of the great poets I have sung, but I think people feel that I am more in my own skin. In a way, this touches and moves them. Celebrating 15 years of career was the closing of a cycle and the beginning of another, and it was great to return to the “roots”, and realize that that was where the “gunpowder” lay, in the sense of not being afraid of ourselves.</description><pubDate>2025-10-06 05:24:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied the right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on permanence, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (even in 2011 the Municipal Council of Faro wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
The gentlemen we are talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn how to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a member of the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Roadsport | Badaraco took the podium on his birthday, but ended up penalized</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/roadsport-badaraco-subiu-ao-podio-em-dia-de-aniversario-mas-acabou-penalizado/</link><description>On his birthday, Badaraco recovered from 17th to reach second place on the podium. Hours after the party, the bad news arrived, with a penalty relegating him to 15th. Rui Valente was placed off the track, after recovering several positions
On his birthday, Jerónimo Badaraco climbed to second place on the podium of the Roadsport Challenge race, after starting from 17th. However, the worst came later, when the top three, all local drivers, were penalized and relegated in the general classification, for overtaking other cars that had lost their way before the starting line, after the safety car had left.
The Macanese driver had a setback when he was relegated to 15th, after an almost perfect race: “It was very unfair and I think the stewards don't know what they are doing”, said Jerónimo. "I think the decision was not transparent. After the safety car came out, several drivers hit the barriers... of course we thought they weren't going to continue in the race after those crashes and we had to overtake them", he explained. “And even if we had stopped or slowed down in the face of these drivers' missteps, we would have created a much more dangerous situation for everyone, because the cars behind us would have been surprised by our braking, meaning there would have been more accidents”, he explained.
Even so, the Macanese assured HM that the penalty would not ruin his day: “I will continue to enjoy the day, I went up to the podium, drank the champagne, took the photos… More cup, less cup, I will continue to celebrate”, he guaranteed with a laugh.
Hours before, Badaraco had already explained that reaching the podium in Guia “is a different feeling” that justifies “80 percent” his choice to drive 26 years ago.
The driver was also satisfied with the race, considering that no one can take away the merit of what he achieved on the track, as he rose from 17th to 2nd: "Before the race I thought a lot about how I was going to approach the start, to recover positions, and I was confident of a good result. The most important thing was not to have given up, after qualifying, and not to have stopped believing that it was possible to reach the podium", explained the Macanese driver. “I know that the Guia Circuit always has a lot of changes throughout the race, there are a lot of safety cars and yellow flags, and I knew I had the experience, and also the calm, to be able to take advantage of the opportunities”, he highlighted.
“They ruined my race”
In turn, Rui Valente gave up and appeared disappointed, due to what he considered to be an excess on the part of the driver who tried to overtake him on the inside, on the curve leading to the São Francisco road. "I don't know what was going through the driver's head who tried to overtake me. I can't understand how he saw a space that simply didn't exist!", said Valente. "I was put out of the race. When I tried to make the turn, he touched me and that was it, my rear end was damaged and I had to go back to the pits to retire", he reported.
When the crash occurred that ended the race, Valente was circulating in the top 10, even after a less successful start, following the exit of the first Safety Car. Despite this aspect, the Macanese came to believe that it was possible to achieve a result in the top five: “I had a good pace, I was confident and I think I would achieve a result in the top five... It's the races...”, he lamented.
The Macanese also took stock of a “complicated” weekend in which he was also involved in another accident during the free practice session. "To be honest, it wasn't one of the weekends I had the most fun in Macau. I had that first touch, which conditioned my qualifying. In the race I actually did well, gaining positions, but they put me off the track...", he highlighted.
At 64 years old, Rui Valente now admits that he may be left out of the next edition of the Grand Prix: “With such a difficult qualifying model for Macau and then with races with so many accidents, I will consider what to do in the future”, he confessed. “I don't want to sit still, I want to stay active and involved in different activities, so if I find an activity that occupies me and makes me feel good, maybe I'll stay out of racing next year”, he said.
Results
1st Leung Tsz Wa Toyota GR86 40m09s237
2nd Adrian Chung Toyota GR86 at 0.148
3rd  Tsang Pak Yin Toyota GR86 a 0.407
(…)
15th Jerónimo Badaraco Toyota GR86 at 29,061
High and Low
High
Jerónimo Badaraco's performance, recovering several positions, shows the importance that experience has on the circuit
Low
The safety car was on the track for too many laps, which greatly reduced the race time</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 05:00:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Prix Shorts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/curtas-do-grande-premio/</link><description>Spectators | More than 110 thousand passed through the stands
Over the four days of the Macau Grand Prix, more than 110 thousand people passed through the stands of the Guia Circuit, an increase compared to last year, which was marked by the passage of a typhoon. According to official figures, the good weather helped and on Thursday there were more than 15 thousand spectators, on Friday around 28 thousand and on Saturday 35 thousand. Yesterday, on the day of the main races, the number of spectators was over 32 thousand.
Tobacco | Harmony Racing fined
Driver Ye Yifei's Harmony Racing team was fined 500 euros after one of its members was caught smoking in the garage. According to the stewards' sanction, the team member was smoking when he was approached by those responsible. When he was caught, he immediately put out his cigarette, inside a glass, containing five other butts.
Great Bay | Lu Wenlong has become superior
Lu Wenlong (Lotus Emira) was the winner of the GT Cup-Greater Bay Race, finishing ahead of Han Lichao (Toyota GR Supra GT4 Evo2) and Liu Kai Shun (Lotus Emira). The experienced Leong Ian Veng (BMW M4 GT4) was the best driver in Macau, finishing in fourth place, very close to the podium. In what he admitted was a farewell to Guia, Darryl O’Young (Mercedes AMG GT4 EVO), who competed in the GT Cup for several years, did nothing more than withdraw. The Hong Kong driver crashed the Mercedes when he went head-on at the entrance to the San Francisco climb.
Organization | Satisfactory event
The coordinator of the Organizing Committee considered that the event ran satisfactorily and that it contributed, together with the National Games, to creating a festive atmosphere in Macau. Lei Si Leng highlighted the value of the seven races in the program for the Grand Prix, which he said was wonderful.
When asked about a possible return of Formula 3, the official stated that the organization will continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​to choose the races that best suit Macau. At the same time, he left the guarantee that the plan involves continuing to receive drivers of training age and that they are expected to establish themselves as the future of motorsport.</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 04:56:12</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA will continue to invest in Formula Regional in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/gp-fia-vai-continuar-a-apostar-na-formula-regional-em-macau/</link><description>The fact that the FIA ​​switched from Formula 3 to Formula Regional (FR) continues to be a recurring theme when the topic is the Macau Grand Prix. Although the show's premier race did not disappoint in this year's edition, somewhat erasing the bad image left last year, there is still a widespread feeling that the international federation deprived the Grand Prix of its favorite race.
At the end of the 72nd edition, the Coordinator of the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix, Lei Si Leng, when questioned again by the local press about a possible return of Formula 3, stated that the organization will continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​to choose the races that best suit Macau. At the same time, the director of the Macau Sports Institute left the guarantee that the plan involves continuing to receive drivers of training age and who assert themselves as the future of motorsport.
“We have been communicating closely with the FIA ​​to find out which races can be held in Macau and the FIA ​​has selected the best drivers to come and compete here”, he said, adding that he hopes “that the best drivers can come to Macau and that we continue to collaborate with the FIA ​​to organize the most suitable races for Macau”.
On the FIA ​​side, there is the conviction that FR is the discipline that best adapts to the characteristics of the Guia Circuit, a layout that remains practically unchanged after seven decades of existence. The discontent that still exists is considered natural. “Motor sport is traditional, and I don't remember any change that was well received at the beginning, even good changes” admitted Emanuele Pirro, the current president of the FIA ​​Single Seater Commission, in conversation with journalists in Macau.
The former Italian driver, a connoisseur of the Guia Circuit and winner of the Guia Race with BMW, took advantage of his time in the Macao SAR to remember that “if we look at the history of Macau, it started with Formula 2, or Formula Pacific, and then moved on to Formula 3. In 1984, a journalist could have asked: 'why don't we race in Formula 2 anymore?' I think it's inevitable. Everything has a price. For us to have the privilege of having a circuit that has remained unchanged since Throughout its history, the price to pay is to use cars that continue to be reasonably safe. And I think Formula Regional offers a good balance in terms of speed.”
In a rare interview with the specialized magazine INSIDE, the former coordinator of the Grand Prix, José Manuel Costa Antunes, warned against letting the level of the race drop. "Today, with the transition to Formula Regional and Formula 4, which is not a problem, they are just different cars, we see more inexperienced drivers", said the man who was at the helm of the event for the longest time, touching on a sensitive topic: "Some people can simply buy a seat. That is worrying. As fans, we want real races, not red flags. We owe it to the history of the Grand Prix to recover that selection process, to ensure that only the best compete here."
Numbers support the decision
Looking at the time sheets, it can be concluded that the records for the main FR race were around 2m16s, around ten seconds slower than the times recorded in the last year of the FIA F3 single-seaters, in 2023. In historical terms, these times place the FR cars on a level similar to that of the Formula 3 cars of the late 1990s. However, from a safety point of view, the speeds reached in the “Sprint” for Curva Lisboa continues to be the main concern since Sophia Flörsch’s accident in 2018. With the suction cone, speeds above 290 km/h were common in 2023 with the Dallara F3, but the change to FR cars reduced these values to around 260 km/h.
In 2026, the new Formula Regional car, the Tatuus T-326, is expected to arrive in Macau, which is equipped with a three-cylinder, 1.6-liter Toyota ATM163T engine, prepared by Autotecnica Motori, which is more powerful and efficient. The chassis was designed according to the latest FIA specifications, in order to provide improvements in terms of performance, safety and aerodynamics, facilitating overtaking and promoting more lively racing. However, although lap times are expected to drop again, top speeds will probably not be dramatically higher.
It should be noted that the change to FR was not motivated solely by security concerns. When the FIA ​​granted Formula One Management (FOM) the commercial and promotional rights for Formula 3, the territory's race became a non-championship race of an international competition, limited to the participation of the same teams that competed in the championship. This change was received unfavorably by the promoter himself, as he never played a truly intervening role within the Grand Prix. Furthermore, holding the race in Macau, in November, involved particularly demanding logistics, with a negative impact on the planning and execution of pre-season tests.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:37:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorsport | GP will continue on the TCR World Tour in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/19/automobilismo-gp-continuara-no-tcr-world-tour-em-2026/</link><description>The Macau Grand Prix will once again form part of the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour calendar next season and, once again, as the season-ending event of a competition that will increase its presence in Asia in 2026
Marcelo Lotti, president of the WSC Group, confirmed to the press, during the weekend of the 72nd Macau Grand Prix, that next year's calendar should include a race in South Korea – home country of the tire brand and championship sponsor, Kumho, as well as Hyundai, the brand with the most cars on the starting grids of the world competition -, a second race in the People's Republic of China and the traditional end-of-season round at the Guia Circuit.
To increase the presence on the Asian continent, without affecting the teams' budgets, Australia will be left out of the calendar. The championship promoter will also not move forward with the possibility of organizing a second race on the American continent, with a visit to Mexico being a certainty. Already on the “old continent”, the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour will maintain its three events, with the Portuguese city circuit of Vila Real hosting one of these events in July.
For Marcello Lotti, “the Macau Grand Prix is ​​our equivalent to Monaco”, and for the Italian businessman, “all championships need an event like this”. Despite the smaller number of entrants that this year's event gathered in the territory, “leaving Macau is obviously out of the question”.
The 2026 Kumho FIA TCR World Tour season calendar is expected to be revealed to the public on December 13, when the FIA ​​World Council meets in Tashkent, Republic of Uzbekistan, at the same time as the FIA's annual awards ceremony.
Number questions
The list of participants for the Guia Race Macau – Kumho FIA TCR World Tour Event of Macau had only seventeen of the twenty-four cars initially registered. This would have been one of the smallest starting grids ever for the highly popular Guia Race, whose first edition took place in 1972. In part, this number below expectations was due to the absence, for unknown reasons, of teams and drivers from TCR China, one of the strongest national tourism championships in the world.
Meanwhile, Marcello Lotti said during the Grand Prix weekend that TCR is preparing to welcome a new brand to the championship. However, this announcement, scheduled for next Friday, is not expected to have an impact on the starting grids of the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour, as it will be a car group that already has a presence in the championship and will replace one of its brands with another. The Italian businessman also said he was in negotiations with a second brand.
Asia's influence on today's biggest Touring Car championship is not just limited to the Koreans from Kumho and Hyundai, as the competition also features the Chinese brand Link &amp; Co, at an official level, and the Japanese counterpart Honda. At a time when electric cars, SUVs and city cars are the focus of big brands, Asian manufacturers are still among the few that invest in cars, with fuel engines, with dimensions suitable for Touring events.</description><pubDate>2025-11-19 01:34:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau GT Cup | Fuoco avenges the 2024 disaster and wins without a problem</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/taca-gt-macau-fuoco-vinga-desastre-de-2024-e-vence-sem-espinhas/</link><description>The Italian driver finally managed to take the Ferrari to the highest place on the podium, and overtook Raffaele Marciello, the driver he collided with last year at Curva do Lisboa, when he was leading, and which earned him a retirement.
Antonio Fuoco (Ferrari 296 GT3) was the winner of the Macau GT Cup, a race that he dominated from the beginning to the end. The Italian thus avenged last year's retirement, after being forced to retire, when he was leading, after a contact with Raffaele Marciello (BMW M4 GT3), at Curva do Lisboa.
"I think it's very special to win in Macau, especially after what happened last year. But this is part of racing, and the main thing was to come back this year, and manage to do everything well", said Fuoco. "The team did everything for us to come back and win (…) I tried to make a strong start, and push hard in the last corner to open up an advantage over the rest. I pushed a lot and at a certain point I was losing control of the car in the Mandarin Curve, but everything went well", he said.
Fuoco also praised the new qualifying format, with a second session only for the best qualified: “it was a lot of fun, I think it was a good change”, he considered.
In second place was Raffaele Marciello, who had won last year, but who in this edition never showed the pace to threaten Ferrari's dominance. However, the Swiss was once again involved in collisions, this time with Alessio Picariello (Porsche 911 GT3 R), who ended up in the barriers.
“I tried to recover at the beginning and I almost managed (…) but the Ferraris had a good start and it was a difficult race”, said the driver. “The car was very difficult to drive, so at a certain point I had to realize that the important thing was to reach the end”, he added.
Porsche with different fortunes
Porsche also secured a presence on the podium, through German Laurin Heinrich (Porsche 911 GT3 R). “I knew that starting from eighth place on the grid it would be very difficult to recover, but I think I benefited when I lost a position in the qualifying race, because that way I was on the most favorable side of the starting grid”, he reported.
Heinrich also acknowledged that he did not have the pace to achieve more than the lowest place on the podium. "I tried to put pressure on Raffaele Marciello, but I felt there was no progress for him, so I knew I could only do better if he made a big mistake, which he didn't. The race went like this also to make sure there was no pressure from behind", he pointed out.
Heinrich also regretted the touch on teammate Ayhancan Guven, which caused the Turk to be left out of the race: "On the one hand I'm happy with the podium, but I'm also sad about what happened. I think my colleague had a good pace and deserved more", he lamented.
High and Low
High
On a track where it is not always easy to complete laps, the new qualifying model brings more excitement to the race
Low
Edoardo Mortara knows the Guia circuit like few others, however, the Italian's race was marked by the Lamborghini's lack of pace, driver errors and bad luck
Classification
1st Antonio Fuoco  Ferrari 296 GT3 27m29s598
2nd Raffaele Marciello BMW M4 GT3 at 3,960
3rd Laurin Heinrich Porsche 911 GT3 R a 4,609
Ye Yifei popularity phenomenon
Ye Yifei (Ferrari 296 GT3) returned to Macau, in the year in which he became the first Chinese driver to win the 24 Hours of Le Mans, the greatest achievement so far in motorsport in the Middle Kingdom. Despite racing in Macau with an Italian license, the Chinese driver was welcomed as a national hero and was one of the most sought after drivers in the paddock to take photographs and sign autographs. The driver even dreamed of victory, after starting from second place on the starting grid, but a less successful start meant he did not go beyond fifth place in the end. Nothing that would affect his popularity, given that after the race he continued to be the most sought after among fans.</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 04:54:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorcycles | Todd crowned King of Guia after driving recital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/motas-todd-coroado-o-rei-da-guia-depois-de-recital-de-conducao/</link><description>After a year in which he was declared the winner without a race, Davey Todd showed that he is currently the fastest driver on the Guia Circuit, dominating throughout the weekend. In the end, he regretted not having set a new circuit record
Davey Todd (BMW M1000RR) was the winner of the 57th edition of the Macau Motorcycle Grand Prix, on a weekend in which he did not give his competition any chance. After being declared the winner of last year's edition, without there being a race due to rain, the Englishman returned and removed all doubts about the fact that he is currently the fastest driver in the category.
“It was a fantastic result,” said Todd, moments after the victory. "I knew I had a good pace, that I was strong, but that Peter was also going to be fast in the race. Fortunately, I managed to push from the start, gain a significant advantage in the first few laps, and in the end I just had to manage", he explained.
As happened last year, rain once again interfered with the organization's plans and qualifying, which was originally scheduled for Friday morning, was moved to Saturday, right before the main race.
Todd secured pole position and during the race he never let go of that place again, building a considerable advantage lap by lap, enough to cross the finish line in a wheelie.
However, the winner regretted not having taken advantage of Saturday's high pace to set a new circuit record. "I think I'm disappointed with the fact that I was close to breaking the circuit record, but, during the race, I didn't know what time I was running. I was very close, so I could have beaten that record", he lamented. “But we are here to win the race, it is not to break records, so the most important thing has been achieved”, he stressed.
In recovery
In second place was four-time Macau winner Peter Hickman (BMW M1000RR), who had to deal with gear problems on the first lap. Recovering from a major accident, the Englishman started from third and took advantage of Erno Kostamo's (BMW M1000RR) mistake, who went ahead at Curva do Lisboa, taking the middle spot on the podium.
In the end, Hickman acknowledged that he had a good pace, but was far from ideal shape: "I need to work more on my body, to gain endurance. At this point, I have the necessary strength, but I get tired quickly. I'll have to work in the winter", acknowledged Hickman.
The driver also admitted that he was scared in the first laps by Erno Kostamo's driving. “To be honest I was a little scared with the way Erno was running, because he started with a really strong pace, but he was also making big mistakes,” revealed Hickman. "Luckily he didn't fall, because if he fell I would have fallen with him. This also allowed him to gain some advantage at the beginning", he acknowledged. “Then, when he went ahead at Curva do Lisboa, I managed to have a free track, and I managed to do my race”, he indicated.
Happy running
Mistakes aside, the Finn was one of the great entertainers of the race. He started from second place, lost position at the beginning and until the Hotel Lisboa curve, still on the first lap, he managed to regain it.
Then, due to the error, he dropped to fifth place and in just over a lap he rose to third. Therefore, despite the incidents, Kostamo said he was happy with the result: "In three laps I pushed the pace a lot. It's true that I made a big mistake at Curva do Lisboa, when I missed the braking point, which was crazy", he reported. “But I’m happy with the result and for having set the fastest lap of the race,” he said.
Classification
1st  Davey Todd BMW M1000RR 29m07s289
2nd Peter Hickman BMW M1000RR at 10,021
3rd Erno Kostamo BMW M1000RR at 24,706
High and Low
High
Peter Hickman's performance shows that the pilot is recovering after the serious accident he suffered
Low
The cancellation of the qualifying session on Friday morning once again reduced track time for the Motorcycle Grand Prix</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 04:52:35</pubDate></item></channel></rss>