<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Tokyo | Japanese newspaper correspondent killed in Gaza</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/toquio-correspondente-de-jornal-japones-morto-em-gaza/</link><description>A Palestinian correspondent from the Japanese newspaper The Asahi Shimbun was killed in the Gaza Strip, apparently by an Israeli attack. According to the newspaper, Mohammed Mansour, 29, died in the city of Khan Youis, in southern Gaza, on Monday. It is believed to have been killed by an attack by an Israelite missile.
The newspaper initially told NHK that Mansour died with his wife and son still a baby, but then corrected the explanation, citing information that his wife and son were being treated in a hospital.
Mansour, a native of Gaza, began working for The Asahi Shimbun in 2023. The young journalist worked at Rafah and Khan Youis, sending reports and photos about the evolution of the situation in Gaza. The newspaper issued a statement expressing the inevitable feeling of deep sadness and anger at his death.
The publication emphasized that attacks on civilians, including journalists, can never be tolerated under any circumstances. Meanwhile, the Qatar-based Al Jazeera satellite TV station, said on Monday that one of its reporters was killed in another Israeli air strike in northern Gaza.
Gaza authorities say the number of journalists killed in the territory has reached 208 since the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:52</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ | Government wants young people to celebrate victory in the war against Japan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/dsedj-governo-quer-jovens-a-celebrar-vitoria-na-guerra-contra-o-japao/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) wants to see the young people of Macao celebrating the “80th anniversary of the victory of the Chinese people's resistance against Japanese aggression and world victory against fascism” and, therefore, will fund various activities in schools.
The revelation was made by the vice president of the Youth Council, and director of DSEDJ, Kong Chi Meng, at the meeting that took place on Tuesday. The goal is to lead "young people and students to better understand the history of the resistance war and increase the feeling of belonging to the nation and love of the country."
According to the official statement of the meeting, financing fits the program for young people “looking for red roots” and has as recipients the local schools and associations.
The representatives of DSEDJ also framed the financing of activities in the “implementation of patriotic education with young people and students in different aspects and forms” in the “continuous enrichment of the work content of patriotic education” and the “comprehensive dissemination of the social fundamental value of love for the homeland and Macao through attractive means”.
At the meeting, the Secretary for Social and Culture Affairs and President of the Youth Council was also present, LAM, which warned the Youth Council that “patriotic education work must be developed more deepened, more detailed and more appropriate” in the future and that the hengqin cooperation zone should be used as a “exchange platform between young people from Macau and the interior”. Lam also linked that Xi Jinping pays close attention to the formation of Macao young people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:26:01</pubDate></item><item><title>HISTORICAL BUILDINGS | Support applications open on Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/edificios-historicos-candidaturas-a-apoio-abrem-na-segunda-feira/</link><description>The first round of applications to the “Financial Support Plan for the Benefit of Historical Buildings”, awarded by the Culture Development Fund (FDC), will take place between May 30.
The measure aims to increase the “motivation of the owners” to make regular reparations for their own initiative “and reinforce the safeguarding of classified and private buildings and cultural interest”. The purpose of the FDC is to finance “regular structural inspections or tests, external repair of classified and private buildings and cultural interest”
Support is attributed through a subsidy, "being the amount financed by 50 to 80 percent of the expected expenses, up to 2 million patacas, with the maximum period of financial support of 12 months."
Applications for the second phase of the Financial Support Plan will take place between September 15 and November 14.
Applications can only be submitted if they are to finance works that have not yet been started, and must be presented by the owner, or prosecutor of the property. If there is more than one owner, the application can be submitted by any of the owners.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:34:27</pubDate></item><item><title>AFA | Autumn Hall prolonged because of Hong Kong's Art Basel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/afa-salao-de-outono-prolongado-por-causa-da-art-basel-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The 15th edition of the Fall Salon, an annual event organized by AFA - Art for All Society, which brings together works by several local artists, will be more time on display in order to coincide with Art Basel de Hong Kong. Thus, the public can see, until next Monday, 30, various works of artists such as Ung Vai Meng or Carlos Marreiros, among others
 
It takes place in the region neighboring Art Basel de Hong Kong, one of the largest art fairs in the world, and for Macau not to lose the rhythm of the art, AFA - Art for All Society, has decided to extend the deadlines for the fall of the fall lounge, which this year celebrates the 15th edition this year. Originally the autumn hall would close this Tuesday, 25.
The extension of the autumn hall, patent at Parisian venture in Cotai, thus allows “offering a unique opportunity to international art enthusiasts visiting Hong Kong for the dynamic art scene that is flourishing in Macao,” says a statement. This year's edition "offers an attractive juxtaposition of art and commerce, echoing the spirit of the original 'Salon d'Amaro" created in the early twentieth century in France. "
More than 200 works of 116 artists are available, "selected from an unprecedented number of candidates," including "a diversified range of artistic media, from traditional Chinese painting and oil painting to state -of -the -art digital art, 3D modeling and video installations."
Thus, “art lovers from around the world are invited to explore the various creative expressions that flourish in Macao,” reads the same note.
Generational mixture
In the autumn hall the public will have the opportunity to see the usual names of the local artistic landscape, but also work of new talents, in a mix of creativity and vision of what art can be.
One of the participating artists is a Chi iam, master in Fine Arts at the Nanjing Institute of Art and a member of the Culture Circle of Macao Culture, in partnership with Carlos Marreiros, Mio Pang FEI, already deceased, and other local artists. UN Chi iam was also a editor of art and designer at the Cultural Institute, as well as teaching Chinese painting at the Macao Visual Arts Academy and the former Polytechnic Institute of Macao.
Another name present in the autumn hall is Lok Hei, born in Macao and featuring “extensive experience in advertising design and exhibition planning”. Lok Hei, who participates in this edition of the Autumn Hall with drawings, is also linked to various associations, being, for example, vice president of the Macao Cultural Development Promotion Association.
One of the highlights of the Fall Salon is the presence of the works of Macanese architect Carlos Marreiros, author of various architectural projects in Macau and a major promoter of local culture. In 2019 he won the “Identity Award” awarded by the Macao International Institute. Vítor Hugo Marreiros, his brother and designer, also shows his works in this show. A usual name of local design, after several years to collaborate with the Cultural Institute, Vítor Marreiros has been conducting several exhibitions throughout his career, creating, every year, the June 10 poster of the Casa de Portugal in Macao. It holds a “professional merit medal” awarded by the government in the final phase of Portuguese administration in 1999.
Guilherme Ung Vai Meng, former president of the local cultural institute and local artist, also participates in this fall hall with a painting of his own. Born in Macao, study at the reputed Ar.CO, in Lisbon, in 1991, having been a master's degree at the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts. He was the first director of the Macao Art Museum.
Another present artist is still Chan Hin Io, who presents to the public his photographic work. For over 20 years, it has been photography, especially conceptual, aspect that has revealed in various exhibitions. Since 2009 he has published more than ten photography books, having exposed in places such as the Belém Cultural Center in Lisbon, or the Macao Art Museum, among others.
Tong Chong, a new generation artist, graduated from the previous Macao Polytechnic Institute in Visual Arts, and made a master's degree in sculpture at the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts. “Its work explores contemporary social cultural, its relationship between human development and the natural world, the essence of human nature and the role of humanity within the current environmental landscape,” describes the same note.
Joey Ho is another well -present name in the local panorama of the arts, both as a curator. “Joey Ho is one of the few artists who actively works with a great diversity of means. His unique approach, mixing artistic and literary sensitivities with a style that varies between tradition and contemporary formats, allows him to reinterpret the classic works of arts and literature, extending his humanistic values,” he reads.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:36:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Attack | Aggressor in psychological evaluation at the hospital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/ataque-agressor-em-avaliacao-psicologica-no-hospital/</link><description>The man who attacked two people with a knife in a store in Travessa dos Anjos is indicted of the commission of attempted murder and severe offense to physical integrity. The information was revealed yesterday by the Judiciary Police, at a press conference, and cited by the newspaper or Mun.
The 41-year-old suspect is a resident of Macao and is currently at the Conde São Januário Hospital Center, where he will be evaluated, as he is suspected of suffering from mental problems.
According to the authorities, the man, unemployed and without a fixed residence, was inside and entered Macao at 1:30 pm on Tuesday, through Qingmao border. It was seen the wandering for several areas of the city, until it arrived at Rua do Campo, where at first it attacked a passerby with a Chapada, for no reason.
Once the first attack, the man moved to a supermarket and bought a knife to peel fruit, with a blade about nine centimeters.
Unimportant
With the knife, the man entered the telecommunications store at Travessa dos Anjos, where four employees, three men and one woman were.
Inside the store, without making him an anticipation, the man soon attacked one of the employees, who was struck in one of his arms. Another of the employees tried to prevent the attack, and was hit with a cut on the back of the neck that lasted for 18 centimeters to the back. Given the uncontrolled attack, the men eventually hid in a collection, which did not prevent the attacker from trying to persecute them. It was at this time that it dropped the knife.
Without the white weapon, he turned to the maid who tried to drag out the store. The woman asked people who passed on the street, unsuccessfully, while stores employees contacted the authorities.
When public security police officers arrived at the scene, they managed to control the man and, minutes later, to deliver him to the Judiciary Police. Employees told authorities that the attack began for no reason and that there was no discussion.
The employee with neck and back injuries, who even lost consciousness, was sewn with 100 points. However, the vital organs have not been hit, so a quiet recovery is expected, with no danger of life.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:55:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club | Cats adopted with health problems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/jockey-club-gatos-adoptados-com-problemas-de-saude/</link><description>Among the 22 adopted cats living in the Macao Jockey Club, a outbreak of feline panleukopenia was detected, which led to the deaths of at least two animals. After the information was made public, the company of Macau Jockey Club announced the distribution of a support of 5,000 patacas to adopters
 
Among the 22 cats available for adoption by Macau Jockey Club and the animal animal protective society, at least eight were infected with feline panleucopenia and two died. The information was released by anima.
According to the association, eight felines were diagnosed with parvovirus infections, which is regarded as highly contagious and dangerous. Among these eight, two died and six are, or were in serious condition, needing to receive expensive medical treatments.
Detection of a surge of the disease in the cats that were in the Jockey Club is not a surprise, since on the day of adoptions there were three cats, of the 25 initially available, which were diagnosed with the disease. For this reason, only 22 cats were adopted during the campaign.
Anima also reported that among these 22 cats only two had no health problems. However, there were other cases where felines had severe bronchitis, tooth fall, despite being only one year, and other respiratory system infections.
“We deeply regret the heavy financial burden caused to adopters or the pain and suffering of adopted cats and kittens who died due to the virus,” was indicated. "We promise to continue to communicate actively with the Jockey Club of Macao to get compensation for the medical expenses incurred by adopters," he was added.
In addition to the adoption cats promoted by Macau Jockey Club and anima, Mary Jean Reimer, actress, lawyer and activist for the animal rights of Hong Kong, also revealed that one of the Jockey Club cats who adopted positive tested for feline panleukopenia.
Positive response
When it issued the first statement, anima still did not confirm that the treatments of sick cats would be paid by Macau Jockey Club. Initially, it was feared that they would have to be the adopters to pay the costs.
However, yesterday, almost 24 hours after the first publication reporting the problems, the company's administration agreed to distribute 5,000 patacas support for each cat adopted.
Macau Jockey Club was involved in a new controversy with cats, when in the middle of this month, tried to send about 100 felines to the interior to an unknown destination that was never revealed. The sending of cats was approved by the Institute for municipal affairs, which in a statement even promised to ensure animal health conditions for transport to Zhuhai.
However, several local animal protection associations have mobilized to prevent this outcome. In addition to the adoption promotion campaign, associations also received several of the cats.
The animals were raised as bravery at Macau Jockey Club, where they had as their function hunting rats, as the use of space by horses prevented the use of chemicals. However, as they had not been sterilized, the cats reproduced until they were about 100. Now it is also known that they had developed several diseases.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:32:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Payments | Institutions teach the elderly how to use mobile phones</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/pagamentos-instituicoes-ensinam-idosos-a-usar-telemoveis/</link><description>An inquiry has revealed that more than three quarters of respondents over 60 do not know how to make electronic payments. In this sense, the government is encouraging social institutions to organize courses and lectures to teach the elderly how to use mobile applications. In addition, the CTT released discounts for the elderly in the purchase of mobile phones
 
Last year, the General Association of Respectful Elderly of Macao carried out an inquiry into the use of mobile phones by people over 60. Although more than 90 percent answered that he used mobile phone, 76.8 percent admitted not knowing how to make electronic payments and 18.6 percent of respondents stated that mobile data packages and mobile phones are expensive, minimizing their use.
The statistics were presented by Deputy Leong Hong Sai, in a written interplies, in which he concludes that “the consciousness of the elderly about the use of intelligent technologies” is weak. In response, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Hon Wai, listed a series of measures designed to appeal the elders with technological knowledge.
In order to “foster computer generalization”, IAS has encouraged social institutions “teaching the elderly how to use computer equipment, including smartphones, through recreational courses, workshops, courses or lectures”. Hon Wai highlighted the usefulness of using applications such as “Single Account”, “Bus Location” and “Macao Health Data Platform”.
In addition, the president of IAS said that, to “demonstrate the affection for the elderly, CTT have been encouraging mobile telecommunications service operators to launch specially designed benefits for this age group”. Plans offer "unlimited data at restricted speed and allow the purchase of mobile phones at promotional prices."
Warn
The president of IAS also recalled that the older population can also enroll in courses of the Program for Development and Continuous Improvement for mobile phone applications and safe use of the internet.
Hon Wai also stressed the effort to prevent the older population from being a victim of burlas. In addition to raising awareness in social institutions that offer services to the elderly, police authorities last year, 126 “Anti-Burial Lectures”, in which more than 8,300 people participated.
Alongside this, last year, “the Judiciary Police went to Chinese restaurants, recreational, markets and vendin areas” to sensitize the elderly to be aware of burla schemes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:28:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Mountain Island | Complaints of obstacles to integration</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/ilha-da-montanha-queixas-de-obstaculos-a-integracao/</link><description>Long lines to cross the border, insufficient health services, non -recognized addresses and letters that never reach the destination. These are some of the problems of Macao residents in Hengqin, that Deputy Nick Lei expects the government to be able to resolve
 
Deputy Nick Lei states that there are many obstacles to ensure the integration of Macao residents in Hengqin, and asks authorities to take new measures to improve the situation.
Heard by the Citizen Journal, the deputy linked to the Fujian community indicated as one of the main obstacles the lack of conditions to cross the border, which makes those who live in Hengqin, but work or study in Macau has to often face long lines, especially during holidays or in the edge hours.
As a solution to this issue, the deputy proposes that Macao authorities coordinate with the hengqin customs to install automatic border calculations or inspection channels only for Macao residents, in order to increase the speed of border passage.
Regarding the identified problems, Nick Law also points out that the Health Center of the new Macao neighborhood of Hengqin, which began operating in November last year, has no regular blood harvesting service. Another of the identified flaws is the fact that some drugs available in Macao are not in Hengqin. Health services in the neighborhood for residents of Macau are thus considered insufficient. Law even reveals that there were residents who had to come to Macau to receive the necessary health treatments as they were not available in Hengqin.
Bureaucratic problems
In the list of complaints that appears in the statements made to the Citizen Journal, Nick Lei states that several residents find difficulties when they have to declare the address on Mountain Island with public services or financial institutions of Macao.
According to the deputy, it is often that Hungqin addresses are not accepted in local institutions as a resident recognized in Macao. Another frequent situation happens when the home on mountain island is recognized, but correspondence never reaches the destination. Law thus asks the authorities to ask the post office on the other side of the border to find a way to overcome this obstacle.
On the other hand, law regretted that the measure of the interior authorities so that the macao enrolled cars authorized to circulate in Hengqin could circulate throughout the Canton province has not yet come out of paper, although announced.
Nick Law understands that integration is a process that takes its time, but argues that these aspects should be improved quickly to attract more residents from Macau to Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:22:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial Parks | Company with profits of 10 million patacas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/parques-industriais-empresa-com-lucros-de-10-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>Despite the company's operational profits for the development of Macau's industrial parks worsened with 2023, capital interest gains allowed to improve results by about 7 percent
 
Last year, the Society for the Development of Macao Industrial Parks reached 10.01 million Patacas. The information was made available by the company in the Portal of the Directorate of Supervision and Management of Public Assets.
The 2024 profits represent an increase of 7.37 percent compared to 2023, when the gains of the company detained by the Government of MSA had been 9.33 million patacas.
Increased profits marks a reversal of the reduction trend compared to the period between 2022 and 2023, when a break of 71.8 percent of 33 million patacas from profits to 9.33 million patacas. However, at that time, the company explained that the 2022 profits had originated in extraordinary revenues about 31.8 million patacas, explained with “contract transfers”.
In the year 2024, the main revenues of the company for the development of the industrial parks of Macao were due to the lease of the spaces in Concordia Park, in Coloane, and Transfronho Industrial Park Zhuhai-Macau, built on Verde Island. Last year the incomes surrendered to the company 18.18 million patacas, while the previous year the amount had been 18.15 million patacas.
However, the big difference for increased profits was due to revenues from capital interest rates from 5.96 million patacas by 2023 to 7.30 million in 2024.
More expenses
Interest generated by the company contributed to disguise the wear and tear of operational profits, ie the difference between the company's gains with the main activity, the lease of spaces, and the operating expenses. As a result, operational profits went from 4.56 million patacas to 4.03 million patacas.
This “wear” was mainly due to the increase in total expenses with members of the administration and workers, as the weight rose from 5.80 million patacas to 6.05 million patacas.
In 2024, the company maintained the number of workers, which totaled 10 employees, but salary costs, which exclude payment of members of the administration, rose from 3.85 million patacas to 4.14 million patacas. The payment of members of the Administration increased from 1.36 million patacas to 1.43 million patacas.
Last year, Lo Ioi Weng was replaced as chairman of the company's board by Chan Hon Sang, which has foreseen an annual compensation of 1.29 million Patacas.
The Society for the Development of the Macao Industrial Parks has as its shareholders the MSAR and the Institute of Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM), which delivered 1.09 million PATACA in dividends, the same value as in 2023.
Bet on diversification
The Society for the Development of Macao Industrial Parks was created in 1993 with the aim of attracting investment and industries to Concórdia Park in Coloane.
In 2003, the company was responsible for the exploitation of the Zhuhai-Macau Transfronho Industrial Park, built on Verde Island, a space created with the aim of diversifying the industry of the territory. The company aims to develop and manage land that were reserved for industrial development and related activities, according to the company's portal.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:21:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Tokyo | Japanese newspaper correspondent killed in Gaza</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/toquio-correspondente-de-jornal-japones-morto-em-gaza/</link><description>A Palestinian correspondent from the Japanese newspaper The Asahi Shimbun was killed in the Gaza Strip, apparently by an Israeli attack. According to the newspaper, Mohammed Mansour, 29, died in the city of Khan Youis, in southern Gaza, on Monday. It is believed to have been killed by an attack by an Israelite missile.
The newspaper initially told NHK that Mansour died with his wife and son still a baby, but then corrected the explanation, citing information that his wife and son were being treated in a hospital.
Mansour, a native of Gaza, began working for The Asahi Shimbun in 2023. The young journalist worked at Rafah and Khan Youis, sending reports and photos about the evolution of the situation in Gaza. The newspaper issued a statement expressing the inevitable feeling of deep sadness and anger at his death.
The publication emphasized that attacks on civilians, including journalists, can never be tolerated under any circumstances. Meanwhile, the Qatar-based Al Jazeera satellite TV station, said on Monday that one of its reporters was killed in another Israeli air strike in northern Gaza.
Gaza authorities say the number of journalists killed in the territory has reached 208 since the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:52</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ | Government wants young people to celebrate victory in the war against Japan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/dsedj-governo-quer-jovens-a-celebrar-vitoria-na-guerra-contra-o-japao/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) wants to see the young people of Macao celebrating the “80th anniversary of the victory of the Chinese people's resistance against Japanese aggression and world victory against fascism” and, therefore, will fund various activities in schools.
The revelation was made by the vice president of the Youth Council, and director of DSEDJ, Kong Chi Meng, at the meeting that took place on Tuesday. The goal is to lead "young people and students to better understand the history of the resistance war and increase the feeling of belonging to the nation and love of the country."
According to the official statement of the meeting, financing fits the program for young people “looking for red roots” and has as recipients the local schools and associations.
The representatives of DSEDJ also framed the financing of activities in the “implementation of patriotic education with young people and students in different aspects and forms” in the “continuous enrichment of the work content of patriotic education” and the “comprehensive dissemination of the social fundamental value of love for the homeland and Macao through attractive means”.
At the meeting, the Secretary for Social and Culture Affairs and President of the Youth Council was also present, LAM, which warned the Youth Council that “patriotic education work must be developed more deepened, more detailed and more appropriate” in the future and that the hengqin cooperation zone should be used as a “exchange platform between young people from Macau and the interior”. Lam also linked that Xi Jinping pays close attention to the formation of Macao young people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:26:01</pubDate></item><item><title>HISTORICAL BUILDINGS | Support applications open on Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/edificios-historicos-candidaturas-a-apoio-abrem-na-segunda-feira/</link><description>The first round of applications to the “Financial Support Plan for the Benefit of Historical Buildings”, awarded by the Culture Development Fund (FDC), will take place between May 30.
The measure aims to increase the “motivation of the owners” to make regular reparations for their own initiative “and reinforce the safeguarding of classified and private buildings and cultural interest”. The purpose of the FDC is to finance “regular structural inspections or tests, external repair of classified and private buildings and cultural interest”
Support is attributed through a subsidy, "being the amount financed by 50 to 80 percent of the expected expenses, up to 2 million patacas, with the maximum period of financial support of 12 months."
Applications for the second phase of the Financial Support Plan will take place between September 15 and November 14.
Applications can only be submitted if they are to finance works that have not yet been started, and must be presented by the owner, or prosecutor of the property. If there is more than one owner, the application can be submitted by any of the owners.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:34:27</pubDate></item><item><title>AFA | Autumn Hall prolonged because of Hong Kong's Art Basel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/afa-salao-de-outono-prolongado-por-causa-da-art-basel-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The 15th edition of the Fall Salon, an annual event organized by AFA - Art for All Society, which brings together works by several local artists, will be more time on display in order to coincide with Art Basel de Hong Kong. Thus, the public can see, until next Monday, 30, various works of artists such as Ung Vai Meng or Carlos Marreiros, among others
 
It takes place in the region neighboring Art Basel de Hong Kong, one of the largest art fairs in the world, and for Macau not to lose the rhythm of the art, AFA - Art for All Society, has decided to extend the deadlines for the fall of the fall lounge, which this year celebrates the 15th edition this year. Originally the autumn hall would close this Tuesday, 25.
The extension of the autumn hall, patent at Parisian venture in Cotai, thus allows “offering a unique opportunity to international art enthusiasts visiting Hong Kong for the dynamic art scene that is flourishing in Macao,” says a statement. This year's edition "offers an attractive juxtaposition of art and commerce, echoing the spirit of the original 'Salon d'Amaro" created in the early twentieth century in France. "
More than 200 works of 116 artists are available, "selected from an unprecedented number of candidates," including "a diversified range of artistic media, from traditional Chinese painting and oil painting to state -of -the -art digital art, 3D modeling and video installations."
Thus, “art lovers from around the world are invited to explore the various creative expressions that flourish in Macao,” reads the same note.
Generational mixture
In the autumn hall the public will have the opportunity to see the usual names of the local artistic landscape, but also work of new talents, in a mix of creativity and vision of what art can be.
One of the participating artists is a Chi iam, master in Fine Arts at the Nanjing Institute of Art and a member of the Culture Circle of Macao Culture, in partnership with Carlos Marreiros, Mio Pang FEI, already deceased, and other local artists. UN Chi iam was also a editor of art and designer at the Cultural Institute, as well as teaching Chinese painting at the Macao Visual Arts Academy and the former Polytechnic Institute of Macao.
Another name present in the autumn hall is Lok Hei, born in Macao and featuring “extensive experience in advertising design and exhibition planning”. Lok Hei, who participates in this edition of the Autumn Hall with drawings, is also linked to various associations, being, for example, vice president of the Macao Cultural Development Promotion Association.
One of the highlights of the Fall Salon is the presence of the works of Macanese architect Carlos Marreiros, author of various architectural projects in Macau and a major promoter of local culture. In 2019 he won the “Identity Award” awarded by the Macao International Institute. Vítor Hugo Marreiros, his brother and designer, also shows his works in this show. A usual name of local design, after several years to collaborate with the Cultural Institute, Vítor Marreiros has been conducting several exhibitions throughout his career, creating, every year, the June 10 poster of the Casa de Portugal in Macao. It holds a “professional merit medal” awarded by the government in the final phase of Portuguese administration in 1999.
Guilherme Ung Vai Meng, former president of the local cultural institute and local artist, also participates in this fall hall with a painting of his own. Born in Macao, study at the reputed Ar.CO, in Lisbon, in 1991, having been a master's degree at the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts. He was the first director of the Macao Art Museum.
Another present artist is still Chan Hin Io, who presents to the public his photographic work. For over 20 years, it has been photography, especially conceptual, aspect that has revealed in various exhibitions. Since 2009 he has published more than ten photography books, having exposed in places such as the Belém Cultural Center in Lisbon, or the Macao Art Museum, among others.
Tong Chong, a new generation artist, graduated from the previous Macao Polytechnic Institute in Visual Arts, and made a master's degree in sculpture at the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts. “Its work explores contemporary social cultural, its relationship between human development and the natural world, the essence of human nature and the role of humanity within the current environmental landscape,” describes the same note.
Joey Ho is another well -present name in the local panorama of the arts, both as a curator. “Joey Ho is one of the few artists who actively works with a great diversity of means. His unique approach, mixing artistic and literary sensitivities with a style that varies between tradition and contemporary formats, allows him to reinterpret the classic works of arts and literature, extending his humanistic values,” he reads.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:36:41</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM | Macau welcomed Portuguese wines proof</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/mgm-macau-acolheu-prova-de-vinhos-portugueses/</link><description>MGM Macau was the stage on Tuesday of a Portuguese wine tasting event, which presented more than 100 wines from 13 producers to more than 200 sector professionals and consumers from all over the Great Bay. The “Wines of Portugal Macau 2025 Grand Tasting” was organized by the wines of Portugal, the national body promotion body.
The day was also marked by a masterclass conducted by the educator of the wine of Portugal, Sofia Salvador, in which more than 50 people participated. Also present were Portuguese winemakers Jorge Seródio Borges, from Wine &amp; Soul, in Douro, and Simon Baptista Cardoso, Quinta de Valbom and Herdade dos Grous, in Alentejo.
The representative of the wines of Portugal stressed the importance of the territory for the projection of the Portuguese industry, where he occupies the third place in value and volume, after Australia and France. "We have been present in Macau for many years and, currently, we also see Macao as an excellent showcase for Portuguese wine, especially for the Chinese tourists of the continent," said Sofia Salvador.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:31:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Thai Prime Minister survives the motion of distrust</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/primeira-ministra-tailandesa-sobrevive-a-mocao-de-desconfianca/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Thailand, Paetongtarn Shinawatra, survived yesterday to a motion of distrust in Parliament, which questioned the management of the economy and the links to the former leader and father, Thaksin Shinawatra, convicted of corruption.
Paetongtarn, 38, who took office in August, was supported by 319 deputies, against 161, who voted against it, totaling 500 members of the Chamber of Representatives, the Baixa do Parliament
As planned, the leader was supported by the 11 parties of the government coalition, led by Puea Thai (Thai people), a platform linked to the Shinawatra clan. The motion was presented Monday by the Popular Party, in opposition, heir to the Avanzar party, dissolved last August by a controversial court decision.
During the two sessions preceding the vote, the debate turned around the poor performance of the Thai economy and the alleged influence of Thaksin, who ruled the country between 2021 and 2006, the year that was removed from power by a military coup.
Paetongtarn, a first-minister candidate for PUEA Thai in the May 2023 elections, reached the power in August 2024, after the then leader Srettha Thavisin, also from PEA Thai, was deprived by order of the Constitutional Court after appointing minister a corruption-convicted leader.
Do what I say
Thaksin, Thailand's most influential and polarizing politician in the last 20 years, has returned to the country after spending almost 15 years in exile the same day Srettha has taken office.
The former leader was arrested on arrival at Bangkok, accused of corruption, but did not pass a night in prison, having been transferred on the same day to a hospital, where he was six months old, and then placed in house arrest until his release, days after his daughter had risen to power.
Thaksin, 75, claims to be taken from politics, but occasionally admitted to advice to the current leader and was seen to preside over meetings with other prominent Thai political leaders. The Reform Party Advance won the May 2023 elections, but failed to rule due to a Senate veto, then composed of representatives linked to the extinct military council.
The party was eventually dissolved by the Constitutional Court, following an electoral promise to alter the laws that protect the Thai Royal House of criticism. PEA Thai, which initially allied with Advance, eventually agreed with a coalition government in which parties are associated with the military, once enemies of the Shinawatras.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:49:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Consulate | Citizen registers in -person vote after complaint</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/consulado-cidadao-regista-voto-presencial-apos-reclamacao/</link><description>After unable to change the form of participation in the upcoming Portuguese legislative elections, vote for correspondence for face -to -face vote, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, Marcelino Marques filed a complaint to the National Election Commission, which eventually gave him reason and allows the face -to -face vote.
In an email sent to the newsrooms, the Portuguese citizen indicates that he went to the consulate on March 19, after seeing at the media that the registration of face-to-face vote could be made until March 20. His claim was rejected due to alleged “administrative impediments” and was told “the system was already blocked in Portugal”.
It should be noted that news about the deadline to request the registration of the face -to -face vote came from a publication of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macao and Hong Kong on March 18. The publication was eventually deleted the same day.
Marcelino Marques also has known “many citizens resident in Macau” to whom the same claim was refused.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:30:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A Palestinian correspondent from the Japanese newspaper The Asahi Shimbun was killed in the Gaza Strip, apparently by an Israeli attack. According to the newspaper, Mohammed Mansour, 29, died in the city of Khan Youis, in southern Gaza, on Monday. It is believed to have been killed by an attack by an Israelite missile.
The newspaper initially told NHK that Mansour died with his wife and son still a baby, but then corrected the explanation, citing information that his wife and son were being treated in a hospital.
Mansour, a native of Gaza, began working for The Asahi Shimbun in 2023. The young journalist worked at Rafah and Khan Youis, sending reports and photos about the evolution of the situation in Gaza. The newspaper issued a statement expressing the inevitable feeling of deep sadness and anger at his death.
The publication emphasized that attacks on civilians, including journalists, can never be tolerated under any circumstances. Meanwhile, the Qatar-based Al Jazeera satellite TV station, said on Monday that one of its reporters was killed in another Israeli air strike in northern Gaza.
Gaza authorities say the number of journalists killed in the territory has reached 208 since the conflict.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Houcong (1507-67), Emperor Jiajing devoting a lot of his time to his own person, discovered the state's affairs, delegating them in the corrupt Yan Song (1480-1567) who, among other infamies, would have a recognized righteous man who denounced him in a memorial sent to the monarch where his resignation proposed.
This is called this poet literate and painter Yang Jisheng (1516-1555). The animadversion he felt in the face of injustice, risking his life to tell the truth, did not allow him to falter. Late on the night of December 2, 1553, feeling grateful for so many things that life had given him, in a conversation with his wife, Mrs. Zhang, who installed him to avoid the conflict given the impossibility of counteracting Yan Song's power, he replied that this was the way he had to pay all the assets he had received, as he recalled in a chronological biography (Nianpu).
And yet, like many celebrated literati, he had also suffered exile on the distant margins of the Empire. It was in the course of one of these days in 1551 that, moved by the beauty of a landscape, made the painting traveling along the roller coaster (vertical roll, paint on paper, 147.5 x 39.5 cm, sold on Sotheby's) where he reveals his scholarship in the art of painting the literati in which the painted figure tends to the abstraction and the accompanying poem.
In front of the mountain, whose name can be translated as "the heavenly beauty," he writes:
«The Tianhua Mountain is not too far west of the provincial city walls,/ which chases admire these climbing blue-peeled blue clutches and rocks of a red-red!/ Towers and pavilions settle to the mutant shapes of the descent and climbed the mountain,/ shadows of flags and shamelies up and down the trees. shining against the vision of the clean sky,/ clouds entering; One could catch one with the sleeve.
Yang Jisheng made in this painting a literate traveling in a river on a vessel that is suddenly alerted by the boatman who with a staff points to houses nested on the mountain. As on an album page that signed Jiaoshan, "Pepper Mountain" (PAPER, 27 x 35 cm ink, sold in the auctioneer Nagel) represented a home hung on top of a mountain, would say the figuration of its search for a place in the world, which would after all to refuse it.
In the night that preceded his execution he wrote a famous pair of verses, in a practice known as Juemingshi, "poem of a cut life", which seeks to make a brief reflection on the meaning of his own life: "Iron Shoulders, to carry the length and the way,/ the pungent hand to writing ingeniously."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Houcong (1507-67), Emperor Jiajing devoting a lot of his time to his own person, discovered the state's affairs, delegating them in the corrupt Yan Song (1480-1567) who, among other infamies, would have a recognized righteous man who denounced him in a memorial sent to the monarch where his resignation proposed.
This is called this poet literate and painter Yang Jisheng (1516-1555). The animadversion he felt in the face of injustice, risking his life to tell the truth, did not allow him to falter. Late on the night of December 2, 1553, feeling grateful for so many things that life had given him, in a conversation with his wife, Mrs. Zhang, who installed him to avoid the conflict given the impossibility of counteracting Yan Song's power, he replied that this was the way he had to pay all the assets he had received, as he recalled in a chronological biography (Nianpu).
And yet, like many celebrated literati, he had also suffered exile on the distant margins of the Empire. It was in the course of one of these days in 1551 that, moved by the beauty of a landscape, made the painting traveling along the roller coaster (vertical roll, paint on paper, 147.5 x 39.5 cm, sold on Sotheby's) where he reveals his scholarship in the art of painting the literati in which the painted figure tends to the abstraction and the accompanying poem.
In front of the mountain, whose name can be translated as "the heavenly beauty," he writes:
«The Tianhua Mountain is not too far west of the provincial city walls,/ which chases admire these climbing blue-peeled blue clutches and rocks of a red-red!/ Towers and pavilions settle to the mutant shapes of the descent and climbed the mountain,/ shadows of flags and shamelies up and down the trees. shining against the vision of the clean sky,/ clouds entering; One could catch one with the sleeve.
Yang Jisheng made in this painting a literate traveling in a river on a vessel that is suddenly alerted by the boatman who with a staff points to houses nested on the mountain. As on an album page that signed Jiaoshan, "Pepper Mountain" (PAPER, 27 x 35 cm ink, sold in the auctioneer Nagel) represented a home hung on top of a mountain, would say the figuration of its search for a place in the world, which would after all to refuse it.
In the night that preceded his execution he wrote a famous pair of verses, in a practice known as Juemingshi, "poem of a cut life", which seeks to make a brief reflection on the meaning of his own life: "Iron Shoulders, to carry the length and the way,/ the pungent hand to writing ingeniously."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhu Houcong (1507-67), Emperor Jiajing devoting a lot of his time to his own person, discovered the state's affairs, delegating them in the corrupt Yan Song (1480-1567) who, among other infamies, would have a recognized righteous man who denounced him in a memorial sent to the monarch where his resignation proposed.
This is called this poet literate and painter Yang Jisheng (1516-1555). The animadversion he felt in the face of injustice, risking his life to tell the truth, did not allow him to falter. Late on the night of December 2, 1553, feeling grateful for so many things that life had given him, in a conversation with his wife, Mrs. Zhang, who installed him to avoid the conflict given the impossibility of counteracting Yan Song's power, he replied that this was the way he had to pay all the assets he had received, as he recalled in a chronological biography (Nianpu).
And yet, like many celebrated literati, he had also suffered exile on the distant margins of the Empire. It was in the course of one of these days in 1551 that, moved by the beauty of a landscape, made the painting traveling along the roller coaster (vertical roll, paint on paper, 147.5 x 39.5 cm, sold on Sotheby's) where he reveals his scholarship in the art of painting the literati in which the painted figure tends to the abstraction and the accompanying poem.
In front of the mountain, whose name can be translated as "the heavenly beauty," he writes:
«The Tianhua Mountain is not too far west of the provincial city walls,/ which chases admire these climbing blue-peeled blue clutches and rocks of a red-red!/ Towers and pavilions settle to the mutant shapes of the descent and climbed the mountain,/ shadows of flags and shamelies up and down the trees. shining against the vision of the clean sky,/ clouds entering; One could catch one with the sleeve.
Yang Jisheng made in this painting a literate traveling in a river on a vessel that is suddenly alerted by the boatman who with a staff points to houses nested on the mountain. As on an album page that signed Jiaoshan, "Pepper Mountain" (PAPER, 27 x 35 cm ink, sold in the auctioneer Nagel) represented a home hung on top of a mountain, would say the figuration of its search for a place in the world, which would after all to refuse it.
In the night that preceded his execution he wrote a famous pair of verses, in a practice known as Juemingshi, "poem of a cut life", which seeks to make a brief reflection on the meaning of his own life: "Iron Shoulders, to carry the length and the way,/ the pungent hand to writing ingeniously."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>A Palestinian correspondent from the Japanese newspaper The Asahi Shimbun was killed in the Gaza Strip, apparently by an Israeli attack. According to the newspaper, Mohammed Mansour, 29, died in the city of Khan Youis, in southern Gaza, on Monday. It is believed to have been killed by an attack by an Israelite missile.
The newspaper initially told NHK that Mansour died with his wife and son still a baby, but then corrected the explanation, citing information that his wife and son were being treated in a hospital.
Mansour, a native of Gaza, began working for The Asahi Shimbun in 2023. The young journalist worked at Rafah and Khan Youis, sending reports and photos about the evolution of the situation in Gaza. The newspaper issued a statement expressing the inevitable feeling of deep sadness and anger at his death.
The publication emphasized that attacks on civilians, including journalists, can never be tolerated under any circumstances. Meanwhile, the Qatar-based Al Jazeera satellite TV station, said on Monday that one of its reporters was killed in another Israeli air strike in northern Gaza.
Gaza authorities say the number of journalists killed in the territory has reached 208 since the conflict.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>BOAO FORUM | Ia, globalization and sustainability in discussion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/forum-boao-ia-globalizacao-e-sustentabilidade-em-discussao/</link><description>Another edition of the Boao Forum began in Haião, where topics such as artificial intelligence, globalization, current economic issues and sustainable development will be discussed. The head of the Executive of Masters departs today for the event, whose theme is “Asia in the world in transformation: towards a shared future”
 
Posters to announce another edition of the Boao Forum can be seen everywhere in Haião, the Chinese island that hosts the International Forum promoted by Beijing to discuss, with other countries, issues of economic, commercial and cooperation at various levels.
The MSAR will be represented by an official delegation led by Sam Hou Fai, chief executive, who will be on the island between today and tomorrow. Liu Xianfa, commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the People's Republic of China in the MSAR, continues to join the delegation of MSAR as a guest advisor.
The official delegation of the MSAR is also composed by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, and the chief executive chief of the cabinet, Chan Kak. During the absence of Sam Hou Fai, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, will interim the functions of Chief Executive.
The Boa Goveal Forum for Asia 2025 ends on Friday and has as its theme “Asia in the world in transformation: Towards a shared future” [Asia in the Changing World: Tows a Shared Future], and, according to a statement released by the chief executive's office, focuses on four essential areas, one of them “rebuilding confidence and promoting cooperation in a rapid transformation world”.
Objectives are followed by "encouraging growth and rebalanced globalization for inclusive development" or "modeling the future and rapidly implementing the objectives of sustainable development to respond more effectively to global challenges." In turn, the fourth objective concerns a very current area: Artificial Intelligence (AI).
It is thus intended to “explore potentialities and intensify AI's application and governance for development motivated by innovation”.
According to the People's Daily Journal, this year are expected for more than two thousand participants from 60 countries and regions, being held 50 forums, or discussion groups, around the above objectives. 1,140 journalists are expected to coverage the event.
The forecasts of a forum
The main conferences of the Boao Forum include discussions about the Chinese and World Economy, namely in "High-Level dialogue: China's reform and economic predictions" and "construction of an open world economy: challenges and solutions." Following is “Improvement of the construction of digital capacity &amp; conforming the gap between digital”, as well as “unlock the great potential of regional free trade agreements”.
Among the remaining panels are also conversations about the potential of AI in "AI: how to ensure a balance between application and governance." Countries will also address the issue of global governance in the relationship with the United Nations (UN), in "high-level dialogue: global governance after the UN summit of the future."
But the discussion forums start with some predictions made in the report released in the context of the Boao Forum, entitled "Asian Economic Outlook and Integration Progress". One of the forecasts is that the Gross Domestic Product (GDP) of the Asian continent should grow 4.5 percent this year, reported Xinhua. "Despite growing global economic uncertainty, Asia remains a key growth engine for the world economy," the report says.
In addition, in terms of parity of purchasing power, the Asia GDP ratio, within the world total, is expected to increase from a registration of 48.1 percent last year to 48.6 percent this year. In turn, the report describes that the general situation of employment and wages “is improving in Asia”, with an unemployment rate of 4.39 percent for this year, less than the global rate of 4.96 percent.
The Asian Economic Outlook and Integration Progress also highlights foreign investments in Asia, describing that China and Asean-Association of Southeast Asia nations "are the most appealing economies in Asia." In addition, it refers that the dependence on the internal and external foreign direct and external investment of Asian economies in the region itself reached 49.15 percent by 2023.
From the point of view of the bidirectional dependence of IDE in Asia, China continued to be the most dependent economy of the Asian IDE flows, followed by Indonesia, with its dependence rates over 80 percent and 75 percent, respectively.
The report also pointed out that China remains the center of global production value chains, and since 2017, global trade in intermediate goods has been more dependent on China than in North America.
In 2023, China's global dependence on intermediate goods was 16 percent compared to 15 percent to North America. The commercial friction caused by the United States in 2018 did not raise their position in the global value chains of the transforming industry, the report added.
Thus, the advance of Asia is also described in the level of emerging green technologies, since this is "driven by strong industrial capabilities and political support." Thus, the continent seems to be positioning itself "as a potential leader in advanced materials related to batteries or production of biodegradable plastics."
China, Japan, and the Republic of Korea dominate the Lithium Battery Battery Technology Global Supply Chain, a factor considered crucial for the electrification of transport, the report underlines. However, China is at the forefront of the expanding green hydrogen industry in Asia, being the region responsible for almost 70 percent of the worldwide capacity of hydrogen electrolisters, also reveals the same report.
An ecological island
According to an Xinhua report, Haião Island, which welcomes the Boao Forum, is “a pioneer in development with low carbon emissions”, namely the use of photovoltaic energy.
"On Dongyu Island, in Hainan province, southern China, the almost null carbon emissions demonstration zone is redefining harmony between humanity and nature-remodeling modern life through the integration of cutting-edge technology with sustainable development," he describes.
But there are more technological news, such as the use of "a simple QR code that unlocks a coffee carbon emissions experience, and where a robotic arm prepares coffee using clean energy." There is also the bet on recycling, as "an advanced recycling cube separates the materials, converting them into" carbon points ", which can be changed to ecological awards."
The area that welcomes the Boao Forum has a total area of ​​190 hectares, where a bet on “three key strategies” was made, namely the “renewal of ecological buildings, use of renewable energy and ecological transport”. The renewal of the zone for more sustainable bets will have begun in 2022, being proof of “how technological innovation and urban renewal can shape a future with low carbon emissions, paving the way for sustainable development, particularly in the tropical regions of the world,” says Xinhua.
Also according to the same report, "one of the main strengths of the area lies in energy production capacity", currently producing "about 32 million kWh of green electricity, almost double its search for 17 million kWh". In turn, "surplus energy is introduced into the network, contributing to an annual savings of 7 720 tons of negative carbon resources," he said to Xinhua Ouyang Qinglun, deputy director of the Cosco Shipping Boao Co. Department of Engineering.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>History | Lara Reis, Professor of Macao High School, remembered in Lisbon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/historia-lara-reis-professor-do-liceu-de-macau-recordado-em-lisboa/</link><description>The former teacher of the Macao High School Fernando Lara Reis was remembered in the “Spring Conferences”, from the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center, by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira. A native of Leiria, Lara Reis fought in the 1st World War and lived on Avenida da República, in the villa that today houses the Macau Red Cross house
 
Fernando Lara Reis was born in 1892 and died in 1950. Throughout a life filled with historical events and testimonies, the natural man of Leiria was a military man and a teacher at Macao High School, eventually making the territory his home.
Lara Reis's life was recently remembered at the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) by historian Celina Veiga de Oliveira, herself to her former teacher in the territory.
At the session, the historian, who won the 2024 Macao International Institute Identity Award (IIM), recalled the “teacher, meritorious, driving of the arts”, and owner of “unusual knowledge”.
“He was a native of Leiria and lived in Macao until his death. He attended Leiria High School, the Military College, then joined the Army School. In World War I was in Elvas, and then left to Angola in 1915 when he faced the German threat over Portuguese colonies in Africa. Observer-Aviator. ”
Lara Reis was never a pilot as she wanted, having dedicated much of her life to teaching and Macao. “In 1919, Lara Reis went to Macao High School. He took a long circum-gap trip, leaving Portugal from Lisbon, going to the United States of America, crossed the entire territory and then went to Japan, down to Hong Kong and even Macau. He was a teacher in Macao, drawing, handicrafts and gymnastics until the end of his life,” said Celina Veiga de Oliveira.
The historian took to the session some written testimonies left by other Macao figures who wrote about Lara Reis, namely Monsignor Manuel Teixeira in the book “Macao Lyceu”. He said he never found "no teacher who had served the High School with greater dedication."
“He was a rigorous methodical teacher, whose military formation was certainly not oblivious to these characteristics. What was truly standing out was his artistic vein, because Lara Reis was always concerned with ascertaining the aesthetic meaning of the students and opening their mental horizons. This at the time when Macau was a small town. that he organized and also exhibitions by Portuguese and foreign artists he sponsored, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira also highlighted the words left by the writer Henrique de Senna Fernandes in an interview on "one of the greatest qualities of Lara Reis", which "besides rigor and discipline, was the consideration by the students, not distinguishing rich from the poor."
Professor Lara Reis was "a party prosecutor who served to obtain tuition fees for needy students," and "he is due to the initiative of the creation of the High School Association, of which he was the first president." This association organized in the former canhydrome “sports parties of the end of the year when students performed the most difficult exercises”.
Work done in Macau
The historian also highlighted “another aspect of dedication to territory” by Lara Reis. The Leiriense "participated in the First World War and this led him to interest all those who were incorporated into this conflict, having founded the League of the Great War fighters and had built in the cemetery of St. Miguel Archangel the monument where the bodies of combatants rest."
Moreover, "another facet of his personality was a taste for travel, because he had no family and thus left for the world." "I visited museums, art schools and photographed everything I saw, having created a estate with 32 volumes that is now a heritage of Leiria."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira did not forget the old “Sol Pente” villa, located in the middle-leaf zone, namely the Avenida da República, which was the house of Lara Reis, later donated to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao to “an anti-cancer clinic that was the first institution of the genre in the Portuguese colonial space”. Today this villa serves as a house to the Red Cross of Macao, and on its walls you can find a stone with the following message: “In this building legacy by the Rotary Fernando Reis to the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao, it was installed at the initiative of the Rotary Club of Macao the first anti-cancer fighting center on April 15, 1951.”
“Change of Ares”
When Fernando Lara Reis goes to Macao, political times are troubled, with the political agitation to be lived in China after the fall of the Empire and the Republican Revolution of 1911.
"In the 1920s the nationalist shock waves lived in the Canton, which sometimes haunted the Portuguese enclave quiet, but never moved with everyday life. The Portuguese administration guaranteed a standard appearance, and the parties at Christmas, Chinese New Year, the religious festivities of the Catholic community and the Chinese population were habitual."
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recalled that in the late 1920s, Lara Reis decided to transfer to Goa, a trip that would only accentuate her belonging to Macau.
“In the late 1920s, he felt he was time to change his air and asked to be transferred to the Afonso de Albuquerque High School in Pangim, and was there between 1941 and 1945, taking the opportunity to know India, and met the whole country. Instead, with a graceful and already sick license, choosing Macau to be his last address, ”he recalled.
Celina Veiga de Oliveira recordou também as palavras de Orlando Cardoso, que no artigo “Macau e o Oriente na vida de Lara Reis” falou do homem que se deslumbrou com Macau “a partir do momento em que, às 8 horas da noite de 23 de Outubro de 1919, avistou pela primeira vez o Farol da Guia, um pouco antes de se instalar no ‘New Macao Hotel’ e sorver de sentidos atentos os sons, os cheiros e as luzes desta porta of an immeasurable and fantastic Asia that he would describe to exhaustion. ”
These Lara Reis testimonies are “in a remarkable set of travel books that lay virtually unexplored in all their research potentialities on the shelves of the Leiria District Archive”, and were investigated by Orlando Cardoso himself.
In the same article, this one refers to a text from the newspaper “News of Macau” of January 17, 1950, about Lara Kings: “The Auster and Worsen Teacher; the tenacious and thorough tourist; the military who fought and consecrated the memory of those who fell in the field of struggle; the honest and firm friend; the lovely and humorous companion; social celibate that, despite this, did not disdain any opportunity to undo its gallants, always kind and inconsequential to any palm with a face that in the goto ”.
Given the few studies that exist about Lara Reis and the estate he left, Celina Veiga de Oliveira left a suggestion: "May the CCCM get the detailed index of the Leiria Archive, so that the research is possible for any interested researchers."</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 00:57:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Public Hiring | New regime “is on the good way,” says lawyer</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/contratacao-publica-novo-regime-esta-no-bom-caminho-diz-advogado/</link><description>Marco Caldeira, a lawyer and auxiliary teacher at the University of Lisbon Faculty of Law, argues that the proposed public hiring law, under analysis in the specialty in Hemiciclo, is “on the good way” regarding the attempt to “promote transparency and competition and bet on digitization”. The theme was discussed last week at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
 
The proposal of public hiring, currently under analysis in the specialty in the First Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly (AL), was one of the topics addressed in the “Spring Conferences”, at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) last week. The author of the lecture, the lawyer and teacher Marco Caldeira, made praise for the diploma for his attempt to reform and innovation in many respects.
"Although not perfect, the bill under discussion is justified by the need to update legislation that was approved four decades ago. It is a proposal that seems to point in the good way, with an effort to codify the regime, promote transparency and competition and bet on digitization," said the professor at the University of Lisbon Law School (FDUL) to HM.
In addition, Marco Caldeira understands that the diploma, and the content proposed by the government, aims to "follow what are good practices adopted in Europe and the West in general."
"It is also very commendable that the proposal was prepared following a serious and participated procedure of public consultation, which gave the opportunity to economic operators and contracting entities to identify deficiencies in current legislation and make suggestions," added Marco Caldeira.
At the CCCM session, the FDUL professor also pointed out that the concern [demonstrated, in the diploma] with the competition and transparency of the procedures ”, as well as“ the focus on training in the use of databases, as well as the focus on centralization ”.
The teacher also understood that, in this bill, the Portuguese regime "can help, because the practice followed in Portugal, and legislative evolutions, have useful teachings that, with proper adaptations, can be transposed to Macao."
Positive points
In the presentation at CCCM, Marco Caldeira highlighted several positive aspects of the current law proposal, namely “the express determination of inapplicability to certain contracts”, or the fact that “fundamental principles of public hiring” are established.
It is also required with the new law “qualifications to candidates and competitors” of public tenders, and there is also “the clarification and standardization of the types of public hiring procedures”.
Thus, a “centralized hiring regime” is created, as well as regulating “award criteria” in competitions, and the creation of an exclusive website for the public hiring area is also foreseen.
Marco Caldeira also drew attention to the real need of this diploma, as public hiring was legislated with various diplomas, including two decrees of 1984 and 1985, which established, respectively, the expenditure regime with works and service acquisitions, and the process of acquisition of goods and services. Such diplomas were “undone of reality” of Macao, even though the 1984 decree was reviewed in 2021, the teacher considered.
Marco Caldeira also considered that the process of reviewing this diploma has been “lengthy”, as the public consultation took place between November 6, 2018 and January 4, 2019, and a later report was prepared, but the truth is that the proposal has been under analysis since December 2023, having been voted generally on January 11 last year.
What has to change
In the same session, the causal and university professor also highlighted the points already addressed by the first Standing Commission of AL regarding the necessary changes to legislate in the area of ​​public hiring. It was imposed “expressly consecrating fundamental legal principles, such as economy, efficiency and effectiveness, as well as publicity and transparency”, and there is also “a lack of regulation of public hiring policies”.
There was also the “need to promote transparency in public hiring procedures” and ensure “greater protection of loyal competition”. There was also “lack of rigorous and explicit regulation on the composition and operation of the proposals evaluation committees” submitted to a public tender, and there is “lack of explicit demands on the qualifications and capabilities of candidates and competitors in hiring procedures”.
Other gaps point to “insufficient regulation and transparency in the evaluation and adjudication procedures”, or “lack of explicit regulation on proposals presentation with an abnormally low price”. It was still necessary to “improve the sanctioning and inspection regime”, as well as bet on “regulation that promotes the development of electronic hiring”.
Says the executive
Looking at the justification of the law proposal, submitted by the Executive to AL, it is read that one of the great reasons for his presentation was even the legislative dispersion that was verified and the misfit over the current reality.
"The nuclear part of these diplomas was prepared in the mid-1980s, and has been in force for over 30 years. A significant part of the provisions of other legal diplomas already has an obvious divergence regarding the needs of Macao's current socioeconomic development, the efficiency of public administration management and the reinforcement of transparency and supervision," he reads.
According to the executive, "given that public hiring involves the use of the public purse, it is essential to review these regimes in order to meet the needs of the society of our day." Thus, in this law proposal, “the process and regime of expenses and acquisitions of goods and services” are regulated, with some provisions of a 1999 law, as “the provisions related to the public works contract regime have a high degree of specialization and are still effective”.
It is intended, with the new law of public hiring, to “guarantee justice, impartiality in the evaluation of proposals”, defining “expressly aid criteria and rigorously determining the rules of conduct of workers and members of the opening and evaluation of proposals” subjected to contest, so that “excerpt their functions impartially and entirely”.
Thus, it is foreseen that “contracting entities must adequately publicize the informative elements related to public hiring procedures”. They are “those related to the public tender, the clarifications provided, the rectification of documents, the extension of the deadline for the presentation of proposals, the causes for non -adjudication, the decision to annul the procedure and the award decision”.
In order to guarantee loyal competition, the government wants to ensure that all entities interested in participating in a competition have “the broader access” to all procedures, prohibiting “all acts, agreements or practices that can prevent, false or restrict competition”. Moreover, there is the “principle of impartiality”, which determines that “the program of procedures, book of charges or other documents, made by the contracting party, cannot contain any clause designed to favor or harm a particular interested party”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 02:18:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Apomac | Jorge Fão regrets lack of people to manage association</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/apomac-jorge-fao-lamenta-falta-de-pessoas-para-gerir-associacao/</link><description>APOMAC - Macao's retirees, retired and pensioners association goes to elections tomorrow with a unique list. Francisco Mannão competes again for president, Jorge Fão for the General Assembly and Daniel Mendonça to the Fiscal Council. Mannão suggests the creation of a “satellite city” only for the elderly and calls for pensions update
 
Increasing the elderly pensions would be "gold on blue." In the meantime, Francisco Mannão continues to fight for this and other flags designed to improve the lives of older residents, again leading the candidate list for the management of Apomac - Macao's retirees, retirees and pensioners association, which take place tomorrow.
The list is unique and the faces have little or nothing difference from previous years: Jorge Fão continues to lead the General Assembly, while Daniel Mendonça competes for the Fiscal Council. There is only one new name in the position of Member of the Fiscal Council.
"It is very difficult to find people available to do this volunteer work. Jorge and I would like to find someone who could replace us, because we are for a long time in this association. We are elderly, but we have energy. As long as we have strength on the legs to walk, we are walking and trying to do our best by Apomac," Francisco Mannhão told HM.
Jorge Fão highlights the fact that Apomac has been about to celebrate 25 years since the foundation, noting that there is, in fact, a leadership problem that if not solved can culminate in the disappearance of the association. "We are not seeing the emergence of another list of younger and younger people, so that we offer our services for another term and so on, as far as possible. There is a leading problem at Apomac and in other associations. The Apomac issue is more serious, because we have been standing for 24 years, we will celebrate in May."
Satellite city and pensions
In a list that will lead the association by 2028, the motto is “we are elderly but energetic”, reads in the action program.
At the first point, it is indicated that the team's objective is "to monitor the government's policy and the Macau Foundation, with a view to adjusting the needs of our action program throughout this three -year term." In addition, they intend to "provide the necessary support to members so that they can enjoy the benefits awarded by the Government of MSAR and other official entities."
One of the requests on the list to the government led by Sam Hou Fai is the increase in pensions, which is currently 3,740 patacas. It would be for the association would be the update to four thousand monthly patacas.
"It would be good for the government of MSar to pay the pension monthly to the elderly, the pecuniary compensation and the old age, instead of having to wait every three months to receive the pension for the elderly, seven months to receive the pecuniary compensation and ten months to receive old age. Hm.
Another idea left by Francisco Mannão is from the construction of a satellite city only for elderly dwellings, in what would be a larger project against residence for the elderly already built by the executive, in the area of ​​sand black.
"I liked the Government of MSA to build a satellite city for the elderly. I worry a lot because there are many living alone, and with the construction of this satellite city they no longer have problems of loneliness, and could live with each other, and can provide services common to all. The construction of high buildings is good, but for the elderly it is not that good," he defended.
Still, Mannão assures that being elderly in Macau is much easier than in Hong Kong. “Nowadays, in Macau, the elderly live quite well, because there are many social support attributed to this group of people.
Sufficient resources
Asked about the essential points to make Apomac a larger association, Francisco Mannhão says that “they have enough”, but lames the closure of the clinic where they were provided to the elderly health care.
"Of course we had the plan to be able to develop our headquarters more, but due to the lack of the allowance we had to end our clinic. In this context, we had a program to develop this area that had to be abandoned, and that would benefit our associates. We tried to organize more lectures about health, because the senior group needs to know more about disease and health affairs, something that can generate great concerns."
In political terms, Francisco Mannhão, who was even a candidate for deputy to the Legislative Assembly, says that Apomac is an advocate of the principle of “one country, two systems”, thought by Beijing to the regions of Macau and Hong Kong. "We agree with the national policy of 'a country, two systems', so that Macau can be a paradise for us. So far we have been quite well in Macau, we have no problems, but we would like this principle to continue."
A lot of bureaucracy
One of the services provided by Apomac goes through bureaucratic support to the elderly in communication with the General Retirement Caixa (CGA), in the case of former civil servants who receive the reform of Portugal, or the Macao Pension Fund.
"The communication with CGA has improved a little, but the bureaucratic part is still very difficult to deal with on the part of our associates. Not long ago one of our associates has waited more than three years for an amount of an amount that was improperly charged," said Francisco Mannão.
Jorge Fão, in turn, stressed that Apomac is also popular with non -partners, including from the Chinese community, to treat various issues, such as requests for subsidies or funeral -related paperwork.
Still looking at the Action program, Apomac's list also aims to “organize more sightseeing tours to mainland China, making known its culture and success of the country”, as well as the promotion of “more coexistence, so that members join periodically”. Much sought after by the dining service, since in Apomac some dishes of macanese gastronomy can be eaten, the list wants to "improve the management of the canteen whenever possible."
Asked if many elderly from Macau want to pass the renovation in China one day, at a time when regional integration is increasingly a reality, Francisco Mannão admits yes, although many “prefer to stay in the territory, as they have their life rooted here, being used to the uses and customs of Macao”. "The Government of MSA has been doing a lot of work so that they can join the great bay," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Aviation | Maria José de Freitas regrets removal of panels from the airport</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/20/aviacao-maria-jose-de-freitas-lamenta-retirada-de-paineis-do-aeroporto/</link><description>The first attempts to establish in Macao airlines in the early twentieth century were approached by historian Célia Reis in the “Spring Conferences” of the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center. The architect Maria José de Freitas regretted the removal of panels from Macao International Airport that told this same story
 
Between the departure of the plane and the entrance to Macao International Airport (AIM) was a corridor that told the history of civil and military aviation from the territory of the early twentieth century. The project of this area of ​​the airport is by the studio of architect Maria José de Freitas, which regrets the removal of the panels and historical information that were installed in 2013.
The architect left this idea in an intervention after the presentation of historian Célia Reis about the history of civil and military aviation in Macao on Monday, on the occasion of the “Spring Conferences” that take place at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in Lisbon.
“We decided to tell the story of Aviation in Macao in this corridor, with a great extent, although at the time there was little documentation about it. I discovered some information in a work by Luís Andrade de Sá. We collected texts and images and put it all on the walls of this corridor, and that was there for a while.”
"With a new direction [at AIM], I was asked how I could prove that all these events had happened. I had documentation in Portuguese, but I had nothing in Chinese and English, and at a time when I moved to Portugal on vacation, I saw, when I returned to Macau, who had removed all the information and images from this corridor. This story is unfortunate," he added.
The architect added that she would like the history of the early days of Aviation in Macao to be told in these same walls. "It would be important to realize where there is more information, so that they realize the history of aviation in Macao, which was a pioneer. There was, for example, an aviation hangar near the mud houses, and there are a series of references linked to the history of this land that should be made visible at the airport, in the rooms, for example. This story should be told and things should be placed in the right place," he said.
Ricou plans
Célia Reis, historian and teacher, is developing an investigation project around the early days of aviation in Macao and this was the theme that led to the “spring conferences” on Monday, with the session “Aviation and Air Navigation in Macao in the 1920s-a process of colonial innovation”.
Célia Reis spoke of a time when aviation began to be important to China for security reasons, and also begins to be thought to Macau. In this process, there is a personality whose name is important, a Hong Kong -born Frenchman: Charles William Ricou, a engineering and aviation pilot. From November 1919 the possibility of “establishing an air career between Macao, Hong Kong, Shanghai, Philippines, Java, India” began to equate, from November 1919, the possibility of Macaoi, Shanghai, Java, India, "contacting local government entities to obtain facilities and agreements.
Célia Reis explained that Ricou intended to form two airlines, the “Far East Aviation Company”, with “a much wider connection, reaching Manila”, and another to connect Macau, Hong Kong and Cantão, named “Macau Aerial Transport Company”.
This company "was constituted in Hong Kong, with a capital of $ 50,000, and had as founding partners personalities from Macau, such as Humberto de Avelar, Rodrigues dos Santos, Francisco Nolasco and Francisco da Silva". The historian also said in the presentation that the idea "was to complete the rest of the capital necessary with low value actions so that they could be bought by all [the inhabitants] in Macao."
"There is even the appeal of the company's board of directors for the Macanese to subscribe to capital, showing that the company was extremely important for the inhabitants of Macao, highlighting its patriotic value, of solidarity with progress," he added.
"Several voices demonstrated at that time that the company's commercial success, at first, could be little or none, although it was thought that the company could have some profits, having the ability to transport the air mail. However, this transportation capacity would be extremely limited, as the number of mail objects to transport from Macau was 24 letters a day," said Célia Reis.
At the time it was thought that Macau would be a pioneer, because "it would be the first territory to the East to have an aviation company", something that would "bring more visitors and increase trade." The Government of Macao, then led by Governor Correia da Silva, "gives in to the company's appeals, granting various facilities, such as the permission to build a provisional hangar on public ground that was vacant or from sea access infrastructure." In addition, “exemption from payment of the fuel storage tax” was allowed.
Thus, Macao even had hydroavião and 21 American airmen hired by the company. "It was considered that it was the largest load of air material exported by the United States of America (USA), all brought to Macao." Then the company tries to organize itself, "even asking for space on Taipa Island, designed to have definitive hangars, although provisional concessions have existed." In this context, he recalled the historian, "there were subsidies, a contract for the transportation of postal bags", to "allow a development of air navigation."
Impasses to the end
In May 1920, a new worldwide aviation convention emerged, to which Portugal adheres, which causes the “Macau Aerial Transport Company” to be nationalized. The project comes to advance, but quickly retreats.
“The airline therefore accesses the condition of obtaining a subsidy, and having four aircraft available for military service in Macau, if necessary. The issue of defense was always present. There was then some disagreement between the conditions required by the company and those that the governor understood were necessary. In addition, the government of Macao needed the Lisbon authorization for the operation of the airline. Advance, and this one begins to negotiate with the company. But voices begin to emerge in Lisbon that will make things change. ”
This is the idea that the US would be showing hidden interests through the establishment of the company. "[In Lisbon] it is fear that this is the found form of an American aviation company to settle in Macao, Portuguese territory, by different ways."
First, Lisbon forbids, retreating in the negotiations, and the next governor, Rodrigo Rodrigues, "is not in accordance with the company, understanding that it will not be viable," which leads to the entire project and dialogue to be suspended.
Célia Reis also pointed out that "the government of Correia da Silva has undergone several difficulties in these years, in terms of security", having occurred "very serious incidents in the relationship between Portugal and China".
“For this reason, the governor considered that having airplanes was extremely important because, at this moment, China was also resorting to aviation. The authorities of Portugal, however, considered that the planes of Macao would be of no importance, comparing with the set of aircraft that would have China or even Japan. When permission for the constitution of the airline in Macao, Lisbon understands that the territory could have in a worrying situation and planes could have functions with planes Military, even if there were few, ”explained the historian. The project would fall, however, by land.</description><pubDate>2025-03-20 01:43:40</pubDate></item><item><title>The garden of Almerindo in Timor-Leste can be watered from Portugal or England</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/a-horta-de-almerindo-em-timor-leste-pode-ser-regada-de-portugal-ou-inglaterra/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
"It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It's the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden," he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth formation center,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:19:38</pubDate></item><item><title>IC | Launched book on the historical roots of Rua das Estlagês</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/ic-lancado-livro-sobre-as-raizes-historicas-da-rua-das-estalagens/</link><description>“In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Street of Estalagins” is the name of the work Bilingual, launched in digital format, which tells the story of this historic street of Macao, revealing the business that survived the passage of time. Production was in charge of the Macao Artists Society, with the support of the Cultural Institute and Sands China
 
The history serpes through the stalage street since the end of the nineteenth century. The narrow artery has always been the scene of an intense social and commercial rebolement and it was where Sun Yat-Sen, considered the father of modern China and the Republican Revolution, opened pharmacies and drugstores, especially from 1893. Over the years, Rua das Estalagem, in Porto, was a living example of commerce, and the Portuguese governors were progressively expanding the street, composed of the street Chinese -style buildings and temples, such as the Temple of the Bazaar and Goddess Temple NOVA WO.
All these pieces of history are now counting on the digital publication “In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Rua das Estlagês”, a work produced by the Society of Macao Artists and authored by Siguo Chen in Shirley Lule's texts and illustrations. Those responsible for the edition are the Cultural Institute (IC) and the game operator Sands China.
According to a press release of Sands China, the book, in Chinese and English, intends to “highlight the fascinating past of the historic Macau Street and the beauty of its legacy”, containing interviews with street -related figures, whether merchants or residents. Thus, it is intended to bring “residents and visitors to rediscover the preciousness of the centenary stores and the cultural heritage of the street through legendary stories” so that they can “widen their understanding of the transformation of the neighborhood and its inhabitants”.
The content of the book results from “close conversations with representatives of associations, business entities and residents of the neighborhood,” having dozens of oral stories that can easily be lost if not recorded. This work is not closed in the digital world, having been printed to appear in the public libraries of Macao and schools, in order to “promote the meaning of cultural heritage and enhance mutual ties among the people of Macao”, intending to be “a valuable community resource to deepen the understanding and appreciation of Macao and the street”.
200 years of history
One of the highlights given in the book is to the textile sector that has always predominated on Rua das Estlagenas. In the chapter entitled "Two Centuries of Prosperity: Spinning A Legacy in the Textiles Trade" [two centuries of prosperity: the construction of a legacy in the textile trade], it is read that "Street of Estlagins has always been a center for the textile industry." In the years when the textile sector had a larger presence in the territory, between the 70's and 90's, "Rua housed more than 20 stores with factory products, including three spaces from the Veng On Farm Store." “Around 30 businesses related to these stores, such as tailors, clothing stores, western products and funeral ornament stores, which brought a reputation to the street,” he reads. In Rua das Estlagenas “Tissue trade is over 200 years old,” says the same text.
Other chapters of the book speak of the presence of the republican revolutionary in Macao in “The Starting Point of Sun Yat-Sen’s Story” [The Starting Point of the story of Sun Yat-Sen] or stories of street-linked personalities and their commerce.
In the conclusion of the work, it refers that after the transition, the street "faced new challenges: the global financial crisis, the SARS epidemic, the COVID-19, and the uncertainty of the economy, leaving the need for renewal again."
"In the past, the business has flourished, by themselves, thanks to hard work and resilience. But nowadays the community joins with a shared vision, actively planning [the development of the street] with the support of the Macao government and the integrated resort companies. With these efforts, there is a sense of hope that the street of the stalage will briefly recover its old vitality, being ready for a new era."
Institutional view
IC President Deland Leong Wai Man pointed out that the book results from the “weighted effort to widen the discussion around preservation and revitalization [of the street],” according to the same press release. "Street renewal is expected to inspire more people to learn about the historic neighborhoods of Macao and participate in their preservation, combining ideas and resources to ensure that the city's culture and history continue to prosper during generations," he said.
In turn, Wilfred Wong, CEO of Sands China, argued that "Street of Estalagues is a microcosm of Macao itself, a place where a rich story meets a modern future."
"The walls of their alleys witnessed the transformation of Macao, and their stories and people deserve to be remembered, as they are precious sources of Macao's cultural heritage. Our effort to publish the book was possible thanks to the collaboration of our local team to conduct interviews with owners of historical stores, create illustrations and take pictures, among other works," he said.
New facades
It is recalled that this publication arises after the Government was announced by the Sands performance at the Rua das Estalagens Revitalization Plan, namely with the “Entrepreneurs Recruitment Program for Rua das Estlagês”, launched in April last year.
The game operator explains that the seven businesses selected for the initiative “have been opening through phases, bringing energy to the zone along with other new businesses, providing a platform for young ambitious entrepreneurs to realize their dreams”.
In addition, the game operator intends to revitalize stores' façades “with drawings that enhance their characteristics, resonating the history of the street and the city”. For this initiative, Sands has also collaborated with the Macao Artist Society, and the drawings will be created by two young local artists, Chek On Law and Sit Kat Kit.
"The aim is that, with a collective effort like this, the community can rediscover the history of the street and learn about its past stories and stores through the visual interpretations of these local artists from Macao and their perceptions of the territory," he reads.
Siguo Chen, the book's author, is a veteran journalist with a career of over 60 years who has been deeply linked to the media area in Macau and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 01:50:15</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ | Government wants young people to celebrate victory in the war against Japan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/dsedj-governo-quer-jovens-a-celebrar-vitoria-na-guerra-contra-o-japao/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) wants to see the young people of Macao celebrating the “80th anniversary of the victory of the Chinese people's resistance against Japanese aggression and world victory against fascism” and, therefore, will fund various activities in schools.
The revelation was made by the vice president of the Youth Council, and director of DSEDJ, Kong Chi Meng, at the meeting that took place on Tuesday. The goal is to lead "young people and students to better understand the history of the resistance war and increase the feeling of belonging to the nation and love of the country."
According to the official statement of the meeting, financing fits the program for young people “looking for red roots” and has as recipients the local schools and associations.
The representatives of DSEDJ also framed the financing of activities in the “implementation of patriotic education with young people and students in different aspects and forms” in the “continuous enrichment of the work content of patriotic education” and the “comprehensive dissemination of the social fundamental value of love for the homeland and Macao through attractive means”.
At the meeting, the Secretary for Social and Culture Affairs and President of the Youth Council was also present, LAM, which warned the Youth Council that “patriotic education work must be developed more deepened, more detailed and more appropriate” in the future and that the hengqin cooperation zone should be used as a “exchange platform between young people from Macau and the interior”. Lam also linked that Xi Jinping pays close attention to the formation of Macao young people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:26:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Mountain Island | Complaints of obstacles to integration</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/ilha-da-montanha-queixas-de-obstaculos-a-integracao/</link><description>Long lines to cross the border, insufficient health services, non -recognized addresses and letters that never reach the destination. These are some of the problems of Macao residents in Hengqin, that Deputy Nick Lei expects the government to be able to resolve
 
Deputy Nick Lei states that there are many obstacles to ensure the integration of Macao residents in Hengqin, and asks authorities to take new measures to improve the situation.
Heard by the Citizen Journal, the deputy linked to the Fujian community indicated as one of the main obstacles the lack of conditions to cross the border, which makes those who live in Hengqin, but work or study in Macau has to often face long lines, especially during holidays or in the edge hours.
As a solution to this issue, the deputy proposes that Macao authorities coordinate with the hengqin customs to install automatic border calculations or inspection channels only for Macao residents, in order to increase the speed of border passage.
Regarding the identified problems, Nick Law also points out that the Health Center of the new Macao neighborhood of Hengqin, which began operating in November last year, has no regular blood harvesting service. Another of the identified flaws is the fact that some drugs available in Macao are not in Hengqin. Health services in the neighborhood for residents of Macau are thus considered insufficient. Law even reveals that there were residents who had to come to Macau to receive the necessary health treatments as they were not available in Hengqin.
Bureaucratic problems
In the list of complaints that appears in the statements made to the Citizen Journal, Nick Lei states that several residents find difficulties when they have to declare the address on Mountain Island with public services or financial institutions of Macao.
According to the deputy, it is often that Hungqin addresses are not accepted in local institutions as a resident recognized in Macao. Another frequent situation happens when the home on mountain island is recognized, but correspondence never reaches the destination. Law thus asks the authorities to ask the post office on the other side of the border to find a way to overcome this obstacle.
On the other hand, law regretted that the measure of the interior authorities so that the macao enrolled cars authorized to circulate in Hengqin could circulate throughout the Canton province has not yet come out of paper, although announced.
Nick Law understands that integration is a process that takes its time, but argues that these aspects should be improved quickly to attract more residents from Macau to Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:22:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial Parks | Company with profits of 10 million patacas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/parques-industriais-empresa-com-lucros-de-10-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>Despite the company's operational profits for the development of Macau's industrial parks worsened with 2023, capital interest gains allowed to improve results by about 7 percent
 
Last year, the Society for the Development of Macao Industrial Parks reached 10.01 million Patacas. The information was made available by the company in the Portal of the Directorate of Supervision and Management of Public Assets.
The 2024 profits represent an increase of 7.37 percent compared to 2023, when the gains of the company detained by the Government of MSA had been 9.33 million patacas.
Increased profits marks a reversal of the reduction trend compared to the period between 2022 and 2023, when a break of 71.8 percent of 33 million patacas from profits to 9.33 million patacas. However, at that time, the company explained that the 2022 profits had originated in extraordinary revenues about 31.8 million patacas, explained with “contract transfers”.
In the year 2024, the main revenues of the company for the development of the industrial parks of Macao were due to the lease of the spaces in Concordia Park, in Coloane, and Transfronho Industrial Park Zhuhai-Macau, built on Verde Island. Last year the incomes surrendered to the company 18.18 million patacas, while the previous year the amount had been 18.15 million patacas.
However, the big difference for increased profits was due to revenues from capital interest rates from 5.96 million patacas by 2023 to 7.30 million in 2024.
More expenses
Interest generated by the company contributed to disguise the wear and tear of operational profits, ie the difference between the company's gains with the main activity, the lease of spaces, and the operating expenses. As a result, operational profits went from 4.56 million patacas to 4.03 million patacas.
This “wear” was mainly due to the increase in total expenses with members of the administration and workers, as the weight rose from 5.80 million patacas to 6.05 million patacas.
In 2024, the company maintained the number of workers, which totaled 10 employees, but salary costs, which exclude payment of members of the administration, rose from 3.85 million patacas to 4.14 million patacas. The payment of members of the Administration increased from 1.36 million patacas to 1.43 million patacas.
Last year, Lo Ioi Weng was replaced as chairman of the company's board by Chan Hon Sang, which has foreseen an annual compensation of 1.29 million Patacas.
The Society for the Development of the Macao Industrial Parks has as its shareholders the MSAR and the Institute of Commerce and Investment Promotion (IPIM), which delivered 1.09 million PATACA in dividends, the same value as in 2023.
Bet on diversification
The Society for the Development of Macao Industrial Parks was created in 1993 with the aim of attracting investment and industries to Concórdia Park in Coloane.
In 2003, the company was responsible for the exploitation of the Zhuhai-Macau Transfronho Industrial Park, built on Verde Island, a space created with the aim of diversifying the industry of the territory. The company aims to develop and manage land that were reserved for industrial development and related activities, according to the company's portal.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:21:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial Reserve | Year starts with gains of 5.3 billion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/reserva-financeira-ano-arranca-com-ganhos-de-53-mil-milhoes/</link><description>Macau's financial reserve began 2025 on the rise, with the value of assets increasing 5.3 billion patacas in January, was announced yesterday. The reserve value was 621.5 billion patacas in late January, according to data published in the official bulletin. Still, the value remains away from the record of 663.6 billion patacas reached in February 2021, in the middle of the pandemic.
According to data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the reserve had recorded by 2024 the best year since the COVID-19 pandemic after earning 35.7 billion patacas. This was the highest annual increase since 2019, when the value of the reserve increased by 70.6 billion patacas.
The value of the extraordinary reserve at the end of January was 452 billion Patacas and the basic reserve, equivalent to 150 percent of the Macao Public Budget, was 164.2 billion Patacas.
The territory budget for 2025 foresees a 7 percent increase in total expenses to 109.4 billion patacas.
The Macao Financial Reserve is mostly consisting of deposits and current accounts worth 248.1 billion, credit securities of 119.3 billion patacas and up to 247.6 billion in subcontractors.
In 2024, investments surrendered to the financial reserve nearly 31 billion patacas, corresponding to a 5.3 percent profitability rate, AMCM said in late February.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:17:34</pubDate></item><item><title>TDM | Sam Hou Fai replaces Neto Valente in the Fiscal Council</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/tdm-sam-hou-fai-substitui-neto-valente-no-conselho-fiscal/</link><description>Lawyer Jorge Neto Valente was replaced as President of the TDM Fiscal Council - Macao Teledifusion, by decision of the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai.
The decision was revealed yesterday in the official bulletin. Macanese António Dias Alado was chosen for president of the Fiscal Council, reveals the same document. Jorge Neto Valente was the only one of the members of the Fiscal Council to be replaced, given that the mandates of Lam Bun Jong and Iong Weng Ian were renewed for a year.
According to the information available on the SUPERVISION SERVICE and PUBLIC SERVICE SERVICE page, Jorge Neto Valente had an annual remuneration for the functions of 140,400 patacas, while the remaining members had 102,960 patacas each.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:16:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Security | Fired instruments filmed to touch themselves</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/seguranca-despedidos-instruendos-filmados-a-tocarem-se/</link><description>Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, decided to say goodbye to the three instructs of the Macao Security Forces (ESFSM) Higher School involved in a video in play with the private parts. The application of the penalty, within the scope of a disciplinary proceeding, was revealed through the Secretary's Office Portal.
The case built in September 2023, when a video was shared on social networks, which became
Viral, in which two instructs emerged in games that involved their intimate parts.
Following the disclosure of the images, a disciplinary process was filed to decide the future of the three involved.
“In early September 2023, a short film circulated on the Internet with two men to commit indecent behaviors. After preliminary investigation, it was confirmed that both are instructing to receive training at the Macao Higher School of Security Forces,” was reported at the opening of the survey.
In the course of the investigation, in the first phase, it was announced that the three instructs were "eliminated by moral misconduct, in the assessment of the" Personal Merit "module." However, more recently, the application of a most serious dismissal penalty has been confirmed.
"The Macao Security Forces Higher School has already completed disciplinary proceedings, and the penalty of extinction of the public employment bond was applied to the three instructions, by order of the Secretary for Security," was nominated. According to the general rules, the instructs may appeal the decision to the MSAR courts in order to avoid the decision made.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:34:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Sam hu fai bet on Heilongjiang to diversify economy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/cooperacao-sam-hou-fai-aposta-em-heilongjiang-para-diversificar-economia/</link><description>During a meeting between the Chief Executive and the representatives of Heilongjiang were signed several memos in areas such as Industry, Chinese Medicine, Education or Commerce
 
The chief executive expects Macao to be able to use Heilongjiang's industrial base to diversify the local economy. The hope was left during a meeting, at the closed door, between Sam Hou Fai and Xu Qin, secretary of the Provincial Committee of Heilongjiang of the Communist Party of China and president of the Permanent Committee of the Provincial Popular Assembly, which took place on Monday.
According to the official version, Sam Hou Fai pointed out that “Heilongjiang has a solid industrial base, with rich ecological resources” and argued that both parties should use “different advantages in resources and industries” to reinforce cooperation, and contribute to the diversification of Macau's economy.
As he has argued in meetings with interior representatives, the Chief Executive also indicated that there is a perspective of “broad” cooperation, in the level of “economy, trade, science, technology, education, cultural and sports” to “inject a new dynamic in promoting the development of the proper diversification of the Macao economy”.
The Chief Executive also pointed out that the Government of MSAR will fulfill “the spirit of the important speeches of President XI Jinping”, which is “persisting in the principle of a country, two systems”, fully play the role of Macao as a link between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, actively articulates with major national strategies, such as the initiative ‘a track, a route’ and the construction of the great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau ”.
Protocol signature
The meeting also served to sign different protocols, whose reach were not revealed in the statement that made the report of the meeting.
The signed protocols were the “Memorandum of Tourism Cooperation between the Department of Culture and Tourism of the Province of Heilongjiang and the Directorate of MSAR Tourism Services”, the “Memorandum of Cooperation between the Heilongjiang Province Department and the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of the MSAR”, the “Memorandum of Cooperation between the Department of Education of the Province of Heilongjiang and Directorate of MSAR Youth Education and Youth Development Services ”.
The “Strategic Cooperation Agreement in the area of ​​traditional Chinese medicine between MSAR health services and the Management of Traditional Chinese Medicine of the Province of Heilongjiang”, the “Exchange and Cooperation Agreement in the Sports Area between Heilongjiang Province and the Institute of Sports of Masters”, “Memorandum of Cooperation, Steel deepening of the exchange and development of youth between the Heilongjiang Youth Federation and the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services of MSAR ”, and the“ Cooperation Agreement on the Construction of Heilongjiang Medicines Certification and Product Innovation 'between the University of Macao and the Academy of Traditional Chinese Medicine of the Province Heilongjiang ”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:31:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence in Macao Culinary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/inteligencia-artificial-na-culinaria-de-macau-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the March 20 edition)
As the food industry adapts to new technologies, bosses take on new roles as curators of experiences rather than mere producers. The combination of human creativity with AI capabilities can lead to unparalleled gastronomic offers.
The impact of AI on consumer behavior cannot be ignored. The emergence of mobile applications that use AI algorithms to predict gastronomic preferences can change the way residents and tourists experience food in Macao. Food delivery services, such as FoodPanda and Uber Eats that do not yet operate in Macao, use AI to suggest restaurants based on users' habits and preferences.
This personalization increases customer satisfaction by presenting options that closely align with individual tastes. In addition, food sustainability is another critical area to which AI can contribute positively.
In Macao, like in other regions, there is increasing sensitization for the environmental impact of food production and waste. AI can optimize supply chain logistics, predict demand and reduce excesses, leading to more sustainable practices. For example, algorithms can analyze seasonal trends to suggest menus that align with available ingredients, reducing waste and ensuring that customers receive fresh offers.
Collaboration between food brands and AI development companies is also becoming predominant. Partnerships may arise with the aim of creating innovative culinary products that capitalize on AI data and knowledge.
For example, collaborations between chefs and technology companies can result in products designed specifically for Macanese cuisine, combining traditional recipes with AI -generated recommendations for the purchase and use of ingredients. The future of AI in the gastronomic landscape of Macau is promising. With continuous advances in automatic learning and data analysis, we can expect even greater AI integration into kitchens. For example, kitchen robots that may replicate the accuracy of human heads may become common.
These robots will be able to improve techniques such as cooking and precise emphasis, improving the consistency of food production. In addition, virtual reality and AI can join to revolutionize gastronomic experiences in Macao.
Imagine that customers can participate in virtual cooking classes guided by top chiefs, learning how to prepare traditional dishes while exploring the integration of Ia in real time. These experiences would promote culinary education, maintaining the essence of heritage. In the light of such advances, the ethical considerations surrounding AI in the culinary arts should also be carefully analyzed.
The question of the displacement of jobs due to automation is a pressing concern. As AI assumes tasks traditionally performed by humans, bosses and kitchen staff can see their functions evolve.
The formation and improvement of competences will become fundamental to ensure that cooking professionals can prosper in an IMI environments. Educational institutions in Macao must respond to this need, incorporating culinary technology courses in their curricula. This initiative will prepare aspiring bosses not only to dominate traditional cooking techniques, but also to understand the role of AI in modern kitchen.
By combining the traditional teaching of culinary arts with technology, the next generation of bosses can enjoy the best of both worlds. The use of AI in Macau cuisine means an important turning point in the way food is prepared, served and experienced.
By improving operational efficiency and customizing gastronomic experiences, AI brings a new era of culinary possibilities. Influential heads like André Chiang are leading the process, demonstrating how technology can coexist with tradition. However, the authenticity of Macanese cuisine should be preserved as we adopt these innovations.
By addressing this weighted integration, Macau can remain a vibrant gastronomic center, balancing the richness of his heritage with the exciting possibilities of the digital age.
The interaction between AI and traditional macao cuisine is a reflection of broader trends in the culinary arts globally. The trip of mixing the AI ​​with Macau's cultural heritage is just starting, but has a vast potential to shape the future of food. Resistance to embrace it can mean stagnation, while opening to innovation can lead to a prosperous and dynamic culinary scenario in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:53:47</pubDate></item><item><title>LIMITS OF WORK</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/limites-do-trabalho/</link><description>On March 17, the Hong Kong Census and Statistics Department released data showing that approximately 12,900 people worked on digital food delivery platforms and other goods over the past year.
52,5 por cento destes trabalhadores têm entre 15 e 39 anos, mais de metade tem menos de 40 e 24,2 por cento mais de 50 anos. 64.7 percent of respondents stated that this work is their main source of income, 61 percent receives less than $ 5,000 from Hong Kong (HKD) per month and 37.1 percent earns more than 15,000 hkd a month.
53.9 percent work less than 44 hours a week, 24.9 percent over 44 hours per week and 21.2 percent of these workers claim not to have a fixed time. 68.6 por cento trabalham apenas para uma plataforma de entregas a cada dia.
91.3 percent of respondents say they have started working in this business because it is easy to enter, having a flexible working method and having great control over methods and procedures. 98.2 percent claim to have more maneuver field to balance work with personal life. 45 percent are attracted to this work due to salary.
Other data previously issued by the Hong Kong government show that the average salary of these workers was 22,000 USD between October and December 2024. By comparison, only 37.1 percent earn more than 15,000 USD, showing that they usually receive wages below average.
Office employees in Hong Kong usually work from 9am to 6pm during the week and another four hours on Saturdays, which means a total of 49 hours of weekly work. Excluding the break from an hour for lunch from Monday to Friday, exactly 44 hours. Since 53.9 percent of distributors work less than 44 hours per week, it is reasonable that their salaries will be lower than the market average.
98.2 percent of people who make deliveries say they do this service by giving them more room to balance their work with family life. This demonstrates that the new generation pay more attention to the balance between work and personal life, a different phenomenon from the “tele-work” that emerged during the epidemic. The “tele-work” means working from home because it is difficult to evaluate the limit between work and family life.  As people working on delivery platforms can control their working hours, the problem of defining the border between work and leisure is very small.
The three main limits that define the exercise of labor functions are psychological, temporal and physical. Psychological boundaries are rules created by individuals who determine specific thoughts, behaviors and emotions, which means that one should have a rational attitude when working and an emotional attitude when one is in family. Time limits mean defining working hours, turning off duties outside this time, and dedicating this extra labor time to home and family. The physical limit is defined by the workplace. When you go to the office you will work, when you leave the work ended. The statistical data of delivery platforms show that people choose to collaborate with them mainly because they have more room to control their hours and work model. This phenomenon indicates that the new generation values ​​the existence of boundaries to work time and, in terms of psychological limits, seeks to have more control over their work.
In the post-epicide era, it is given greater importance to the balance between professional and family career. Limits theory helps companies understand and better manage work and family boundaries, thus achieving better balance and allowing workers' quality of life to improve.
In Hong Kong, delivery platform distributors earn less. Although it has a better notion of the limits of work and a happier family life, material goods that can give to the family are limited. These workers need to achieve balance between family life and material goods. From a business point of view, giving workers more space and flexibility, as well as broader borders, will help recruit a new generation of employees.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:26:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mata Minor, in the prison “committed suicide”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/24/mata-menor-na-prisao-suicidou-se/</link><description>Family or passionate crime is increasing every year. Authorities have no hands to measure to investigate the causes of crimes, and in most cases investigators are perceived. There are people who kill or have their mates kill, allegedly, for love.
It is a transverse reality to all age groups and all social strata, which happens throughout the year. The passion crime happens by jealousy, revenge, a sense of possession brought to the extreme, or simply because the relationship has ended and cannot be lived without the presence of the other person - most of these passionate crimes are imputable being rare cases of unconsciousness due to pathological causes.
Those who decide to punish this way their companions or former companions always find a reason that legitimizes the death of the other. The murderer often happens, suicide next. The latest data point to an increase in marital homicide in Portugal in the last ten years. Worst of all is when passionate crime inserts the death of young children. There are psychologists who have not yet arranged full explanation that justifies how a father can kill a minor child.
Our arrests are full of criminals, but in prisons there is a very special "statute" for the prisoners who have killed their mate or a child, as they will know later. This internal status is a justice for those who, even having committed another kind of crime, does not accept or admit to killing a child. The arrests of our country have been dozens of times in the various media. Or because they have more prisoners, without hygiene conditions, without food with the minimum of quality, with little recess, with the postponement of medical support, finally, a gap panoply that places Portugal on the tail of countries that do not fulfill human rights rules. The Portuguese prisons are a world apart, where it happens a little and even escapes so scandalous that they are international news. We recently had that Jewish Valley Escape, where five of the biggest detained criminals managed to escape while a vigilante ate a cream pastel…
By the way, with us a prison guard resides with us and one day I invited him to have a coffee. By chance, I drank the coffee but he drank six beers. All good. The conversation demonstrates well what is happening in the underworld of prisons.
So you now had an increase. Wasn't it bad?
Ah!… Do you think the increase in salary was something that solves the difficult life we ​​have? Don't even think.
And the risk allowance?
Look, I haven't received anything yet and from what I heard there in the prison of Monsanto, the risk allowance is a bullshit…
Tell me one thing: How was it possible that those dangerous criminals had managed to escape from the Jewish valley? And why weren't they in Monsanto?
Well, first I never realized how the worst of them was in my Monsanto prison and was transferred to Jewish Valley, where I had friends… Surely there was a lot of money…
To whom?
Well, that now I can't tell you, but the Lord certainly imagines that those who are in prison are not saints ... and that escape was very well prepared with the mobster support from abroad.
But, you prison guards are the reputation for being corrupt. To take the drug, to introduce mobile phones and other lethal objects…
Not quite. We cannot take a dry branch through the tree. Of course, I have colleagues who make good money from what they just said, but not all. And about the mobile phones and drugs, I can tell you that we have already caught women of prisoners who were visiting and had all this inside the vagina…
A mobile phone?
Exactly! Nothing special for some…
Another thing, do you run or not danger to life, or have a "agreement" with prisoners' heads?
We risk life if we make black life to prisoners. There are many who do not play in service, there are many who control the drug business through coded abroad messages, there are even mobsters who control life within arrests in all aspects and even control abroad activity. I give you an example: in prisons there is a certain “statute” among prisoners. These heads of the prisoners admit nothing to those who go to prison for killing the woman or a small son… Then we couldn't do anything, even if we put the children who killed their children… They arrange the way when the bath time treats them.
Do they take a beating?
Batcher? A lot and not only. They sticking them with a stick by the tail inside, oblige them to oral sex and whenever they can kill them…
And the news is not given to the family and the public?
Of course, the information is given. But always the same way.
As?
That the prisoner committed suicide ...
- And you, prison guards, silents…
Obviously. Do you have no family either? Are you realizing me?
Absolutely. I would like to ask him something else: there is a lot of homosexuality in prisons. Do you allow?
It is not a matter of allowing. This happens during the bath, in the cells with more than one inmate, in the work in the countryside and even in the libraries, especially oral sex.
Do you see any solution so that life in prisons can have more quality and more human rights?
I don't see. From now on it will always be worse because new arrests are not built, such as in the Nordic countries.
I thank this meeting and I can inform you that our conversation will be read in Macau, but be rested that your name does not exist. Thanks. I was pleased to know him better.</description><pubDate>2025-03-24 03:21:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Let us be practical</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/sejamos-praticos/</link><description>The annual plenary session of the National Popular Congress and the National Committee of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference, held in Beijing, has recently ended. One of the main concerns of Macau representatives was the “Integration of Macao and Hengqin”. I transcribe an excerpt from a conversation I heard as I had breakfast, "Are you going to buy an apartment in Hengqin?" "No, if I wanted a house, I bought it in Zhuhai, because it gets closer to Macau."
Living in Hengqin certainly has its advantages. Many students from China who study at Macao universities live in Hengqin and catch the bus to the mud every day. There are also many residents and newly arrived people living in Hengqin for reasons related to work or children's school.
But even if they come to live in Hengqin, which has an area of ​​106.46 square kilometers, 100,000 people, or even more than 200,000, is still not much. At the time when the housing fractions of the “new neighborhood of Macau” were for sale, there were many restrictions, which were being raised over time on the grounds of “development policy changes with development”. But deep down, they are "policies that give in to reality." In fact, whether it is politics or economics, the practical sense is imposed.
I am not opposed to the improvement of the legal framework aimed at the “integration of Macao and Hengqin,” as it is necessary to clarify the difference between “in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin” and “New Zone of Hengqin”. If we think about the efforts that are being developed for the “integration of Macao and Hengqin,” we will see that Macau has played a more active role than Guangdong Province. In the case of Macao, I suggest that hengqin circulation of all types of vehicles from the city is allowed. However, how can Hengqin attract residents of Macao to live there and contribute to their development if there is not even a public parking park for Macao vehicles at the Hengqin border post?
If there are those who ask that the “Macao vehicle circulation policy in Guangdong province” has already made it difficult to survive companies in the North Zone of Macao, then if these vehicles are allowed to circulate in Hengqin, will this not even have negative consequences for Macao's economy? In my opinion, the introduction of reforms in the commercial sector is just a way to get out of your current situation. It is a priority to end the monopoly of the commercial sector, to open the economy to different markets, to develop and use the unoccupied land as much as possible, while reducing the negative impact of “road works” on companies and store owners.
For example, the Jockey Club of Macao has been closed since last year and the clues have been covered with grass. However, the Macao government has not announced any development plan for the site, thus being wasted valuable resources. Perhaps the Macao government can be inspired by the operational management of Hong Kong's “Kai Tak Sports Park”.
As for this subject, the Macao Executive can grant one of six resort and leisure companies integrated the Jockey Club's land development and management rights for a given period of time, which can somehow help create a new commercial zone that attracts the consumption of more tourists.
It would also be important to create political incentives and/or flexibility of restrictions on companies to attract traders to settle in the old neighborhoods and community neighborhoods throughout the city. If we look at the “reordering of the amendment street and four other streets of the parish of Santo António” that took place a few years ago, and compare the agitated environment that existed before and after reordering, it becomes evident that the “ideas” that come out of those who “are sitting in their offices” have to be put to the test to be effective. We impose on reality only usually results in disaster.
The “Integration of Hengqin and Macau” is an ambitious venture that the homeland has entrusted to Macao. Before Hengqin is officially under the jurisdiction of Macao, the most important thing is to preserve and develop Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 17:17:18</pubDate></item><item><title>AFA | Autumn Hall prolonged because of Hong Kong's Art Basel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/afa-salao-de-outono-prolongado-por-causa-da-art-basel-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The 15th edition of the Fall Salon, an annual event organized by AFA - Art for All Society, which brings together works by several local artists, will be more time on display in order to coincide with Art Basel de Hong Kong. Thus, the public can see, until next Monday, 30, various works of artists such as Ung Vai Meng or Carlos Marreiros, among others
 
It takes place in the region neighboring Art Basel de Hong Kong, one of the largest art fairs in the world, and for Macau not to lose the rhythm of the art, AFA - Art for All Society, has decided to extend the deadlines for the fall of the fall lounge, which this year celebrates the 15th edition this year. Originally the autumn hall would close this Tuesday, 25.
The extension of the autumn hall, patent at Parisian venture in Cotai, thus allows “offering a unique opportunity to international art enthusiasts visiting Hong Kong for the dynamic art scene that is flourishing in Macao,” says a statement. This year's edition "offers an attractive juxtaposition of art and commerce, echoing the spirit of the original 'Salon d'Amaro" created in the early twentieth century in France. "
More than 200 works of 116 artists are available, "selected from an unprecedented number of candidates," including "a diversified range of artistic media, from traditional Chinese painting and oil painting to state -of -the -art digital art, 3D modeling and video installations."
Thus, “art lovers from around the world are invited to explore the various creative expressions that flourish in Macao,” reads the same note.
Generational mixture
In the autumn hall the public will have the opportunity to see the usual names of the local artistic landscape, but also work of new talents, in a mix of creativity and vision of what art can be.
One of the participating artists is a Chi iam, master in Fine Arts at the Nanjing Institute of Art and a member of the Culture Circle of Macao Culture, in partnership with Carlos Marreiros, Mio Pang FEI, already deceased, and other local artists. UN Chi iam was also a editor of art and designer at the Cultural Institute, as well as teaching Chinese painting at the Macao Visual Arts Academy and the former Polytechnic Institute of Macao.
Another name present in the autumn hall is Lok Hei, born in Macao and featuring “extensive experience in advertising design and exhibition planning”. Lok Hei, who participates in this edition of the Autumn Hall with drawings, is also linked to various associations, being, for example, vice president of the Macao Cultural Development Promotion Association.
One of the highlights of the Fall Salon is the presence of the works of Macanese architect Carlos Marreiros, author of various architectural projects in Macau and a major promoter of local culture. In 2019 he won the “Identity Award” awarded by the Macao International Institute. Vítor Hugo Marreiros, his brother and designer, also shows his works in this show. A usual name of local design, after several years to collaborate with the Cultural Institute, Vítor Marreiros has been conducting several exhibitions throughout his career, creating, every year, the June 10 poster of the Casa de Portugal in Macao. It holds a “professional merit medal” awarded by the government in the final phase of Portuguese administration in 1999.
Guilherme Ung Vai Meng, former president of the local cultural institute and local artist, also participates in this fall hall with a painting of his own. Born in Macao, study at the reputed Ar.CO, in Lisbon, in 1991, having been a master's degree at the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts. He was the first director of the Macao Art Museum.
Another present artist is still Chan Hin Io, who presents to the public his photographic work. For over 20 years, it has been photography, especially conceptual, aspect that has revealed in various exhibitions. Since 2009 he has published more than ten photography books, having exposed in places such as the Belém Cultural Center in Lisbon, or the Macao Art Museum, among others.
Tong Chong, a new generation artist, graduated from the previous Macao Polytechnic Institute in Visual Arts, and made a master's degree in sculpture at the Guangzhou Academy of Fine Arts. “Its work explores contemporary social cultural, its relationship between human development and the natural world, the essence of human nature and the role of humanity within the current environmental landscape,” describes the same note.
Joey Ho is another well -present name in the local panorama of the arts, both as a curator. “Joey Ho is one of the few artists who actively works with a great diversity of means. His unique approach, mixing artistic and literary sensitivities with a style that varies between tradition and contemporary formats, allows him to reinterpret the classic works of arts and literature, extending his humanistic values,” he reads.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:36:41</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM | Macau welcomed Portuguese wines proof</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/mgm-macau-acolheu-prova-de-vinhos-portugueses/</link><description>MGM Macau was the stage on Tuesday of a Portuguese wine tasting event, which presented more than 100 wines from 13 producers to more than 200 sector professionals and consumers from all over the Great Bay. The “Wines of Portugal Macau 2025 Grand Tasting” was organized by the wines of Portugal, the national body promotion body.
The day was also marked by a masterclass conducted by the educator of the wine of Portugal, Sofia Salvador, in which more than 50 people participated. Also present were Portuguese winemakers Jorge Seródio Borges, from Wine &amp; Soul, in Douro, and Simon Baptista Cardoso, Quinta de Valbom and Herdade dos Grous, in Alentejo.
The representative of the wines of Portugal stressed the importance of the territory for the projection of the Portuguese industry, where he occupies the third place in value and volume, after Australia and France. "We have been present in Macau for many years and, currently, we also see Macao as an excellent showcase for Portuguese wine, especially for the Chinese tourists of the continent," said Sofia Salvador.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:31:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Entrepreneurship | USJ DELIVERS AWARDS THIS SATURDAY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/empreendedorismo-usj-entrega-premios-este-sabado/</link><description>The University of St. Joseph (USJ) will be the stage for the delivery of the Deignan awards to responsible entrepreneurship [Deignan Award for Responsible Entrepreneurship], an initiative organized by WOFOO Social Enterprises, Ricci Institute of Macao and USJ itself.
The objective is to “encourage ethical business practices and involve companies in their efforts to create sustainable business models guided by the principles of justice, solidarity and responsibility,” says USJ in a note, where it is added that the prize delivered on Saturday “recognizes top business leaders who exhibit exemplary practices that contribute positively to the common good of society”.
The awards will take place between 2:30 pm and 5:30 pm, which is the second edition of the initiative, which is made according to Alfred Deignan's “Mission and Commitment” in the areas of “Education, Promotion of Values ​​and Ethical Business Practices”.
The deignan prize focuses on the SMEs operating in the intercultural centers of Hong Kong and Macau, selecting those that prove to be “more successful and qualified” and “demonstrate a credible history of specific achievements in the field of sustainability and the implementation of ethical practices based on the most up to date research on companies and business ethics”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:58:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Letters Route | From Mongolia to the old Portuguese colonies: the exhibitions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/rota-das-letras-da-mongolia-as-antigas-colonias-portuguesas-as-exposicoes/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival features three photography exhibitions, two of them patents until April, which feature a diversity of themes and creative styles. João Miguel Barros collaborated in the curatorship of all of them: “Nomadic Time: An Introduction”, by Jessie Rao; “The wind blows on the prairie,” by Wang Zhengping; and “New Independences”, with images of photojournalist Alfredo Cunha. Here's a trip through three distinct worlds
 
If you photograph is counting, or transmitting speechlessly, there is then the bet of the Literary Festival Rota das Letras to present three distinct exhibitions, ranging from the distant scenarios of Mongolia to the ancient Portuguese colonies in Africa. João Miguel Barros, healer, also a photographer, helped curate them all, and at HM reveals some of the details of each project.
In the case of “The wind blows on the prairie”, with work by Wang Zhengping, the curated was done in partnership with Risong. Available until April 28 at the TAP Seac Gallery, this was, “by far, the most challenging exhibition in curatorial terms,” he confessed.
“I had to start from a set of about 300 files with images and choose the main narrative. I chose to focus the exhibition on the Mongolian horses project, which is what fascinates me the most, giving it more space, and completed it with the other project of the communities,” said João Miguel Barros, explaining that “it could have been the other way around, because he [Wang Zhengping] has two very well developed components over the time decades of work".
In addition, the curator had to create "a dialogue between the size of the images and its placement in the gallery space, creating groups with its own identity." "I was very happy with the end result and I think I was able to surprise the artist, who confessed to me not waiting for this result," he said.
Wang Zhengping is, besides photographer, ethnographer, being currently known as one of China's great contemporary photographers, especially for its artistic aspect. It began to obtain international recognition from 2015, being considered one of the top ten pioneers of Asian photography in the ranking of the Pixel photographic magazine. It has a work very focused on the horses that live in the Mongolia steppes, in the autonomous region of Mongolia Interior, a region that has marked its work a lot.

Decolonization
For a completely different creative and themed field, João Miguel Barros organized “New Independences”, with images of photojournalist Alfredo Cunha, which can be seen in the former municipal slaughterhouse until Sunday.
"Alfredo Cunha's show is an appetite for the big breath exhibition that is being built from root to come to Macau next year," he said.
With the theme of Portuguese decolonization, which started after April 25, 1974, “new independence” focuses on Portuguese-speaking African countries, which lived more intensely this process of decolonization. However, the curator wanted to remove him "the institutional and political burden," selecting "hundreds of images sent by Alfredo to me from a more personal and humanist criterion."
The curator then decided to group these images into five sets, entitled "places", "people", "to weapons", "arrivals and matches" and "rituals". “The images are very significant and reveal the great talent of one of the great names of Portuguese April 25 photography,” added João Miguel Barros.
Alfredo Cunha began working in photography in 1970, having entered the newspapers the following year, starting at Amadora News. Since then he has collaborated with the most important Portuguese newspapers, such as the already missing century; The public or the Jornal de Notícias, having also been editor of the photography section.
He was an official photographer of the Presidents of the Republic Ramalho Eanes and Mário Soares, receiving the Commendation of the Order of Infante D. Henrique in 1996. His work on the Revolution of Cloves, on April 25, 1974, and Portuguese decolonization, are among their best known photographic works.
Nomadas in the hostel
The third show integrated into the Rota das Letras Literary Festival is “Nomada Time: An Introduction”, inaugurated this Monday at SCM Hostel and which is evident until April 10th.
“I brought Jessie [Rao] to Macau in the context of this festival because it is a disciple of Wang Zhengping and the fact that its project is also about Mongolia. The work that is exposed, which is all color, unlike Wang's show, which is totally black and white, shows a different and more experiential view of communities and people,” he explained.
Although Jessie Rao is not a native of Mongolia, the truth is that she eventually captured something from the region's culture, demonstrating, in the curator's view, "a huge talent." "This project [nomada time] obtained the excellence award, which is the main prize, in Pingyao International Photography Festival last year. It captures the human side of people with a unique density, and its photographs are beautiful," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:57:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Attack | Aggressor in psychological evaluation at the hospital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/ataque-agressor-em-avaliacao-psicologica-no-hospital/</link><description>The man who attacked two people with a knife in a store in Travessa dos Anjos is indicted of the commission of attempted murder and severe offense to physical integrity. The information was revealed yesterday by the Judiciary Police, at a press conference, and cited by the newspaper or Mun.
The 41-year-old suspect is a resident of Macao and is currently at the Conde São Januário Hospital Center, where he will be evaluated, as he is suspected of suffering from mental problems.
According to the authorities, the man, unemployed and without a fixed residence, was inside and entered Macao at 1:30 pm on Tuesday, through Qingmao border. It was seen the wandering for several areas of the city, until it arrived at Rua do Campo, where at first it attacked a passerby with a Chapada, for no reason.
Once the first attack, the man moved to a supermarket and bought a knife to peel fruit, with a blade about nine centimeters.
Unimportant
With the knife, the man entered the telecommunications store at Travessa dos Anjos, where four employees, three men and one woman were.
Inside the store, without making him an anticipation, the man soon attacked one of the employees, who was struck in one of his arms. Another of the employees tried to prevent the attack, and was hit with a cut on the back of the neck that lasted for 18 centimeters to the back. Given the uncontrolled attack, the men eventually hid in a collection, which did not prevent the attacker from trying to persecute them. It was at this time that it dropped the knife.
Without the white weapon, he turned to the maid who tried to drag out the store. The woman asked people who passed on the street, unsuccessfully, while stores employees contacted the authorities.
When public security police officers arrived at the scene, they managed to control the man and, minutes later, to deliver him to the Judiciary Police. Employees told authorities that the attack began for no reason and that there was no discussion.
The employee with neck and back injuries, who even lost consciousness, was sewn with 100 points. However, the vital organs have not been hit, so a quiet recovery is expected, with no danger of life.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:55:23</pubDate></item><item><title>HISTORICAL BUILDINGS | Support applications open on Monday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/edificios-historicos-candidaturas-a-apoio-abrem-na-segunda-feira/</link><description>The first round of applications to the “Financial Support Plan for the Benefit of Historical Buildings”, awarded by the Culture Development Fund (FDC), will take place between May 30.
The measure aims to increase the “motivation of the owners” to make regular reparations for their own initiative “and reinforce the safeguarding of classified and private buildings and cultural interest”. The purpose of the FDC is to finance “regular structural inspections or tests, external repair of classified and private buildings and cultural interest”
Support is attributed through a subsidy, "being the amount financed by 50 to 80 percent of the expected expenses, up to 2 million patacas, with the maximum period of financial support of 12 months."
Applications for the second phase of the Financial Support Plan will take place between September 15 and November 14.
Applications can only be submitted if they are to finance works that have not yet been started, and must be presented by the owner, or prosecutor of the property. If there is more than one owner, the application can be submitted by any of the owners.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:34:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club | Cats adopted with health problems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/jockey-club-gatos-adoptados-com-problemas-de-saude/</link><description>Among the 22 adopted cats living in the Macao Jockey Club, a outbreak of feline panleukopenia was detected, which led to the deaths of at least two animals. After the information was made public, the company of Macau Jockey Club announced the distribution of a support of 5,000 patacas to adopters
 
Among the 22 cats available for adoption by Macau Jockey Club and the animal animal protective society, at least eight were infected with feline panleucopenia and two died. The information was released by anima.
According to the association, eight felines were diagnosed with parvovirus infections, which is regarded as highly contagious and dangerous. Among these eight, two died and six are, or were in serious condition, needing to receive expensive medical treatments.
Detection of a surge of the disease in the cats that were in the Jockey Club is not a surprise, since on the day of adoptions there were three cats, of the 25 initially available, which were diagnosed with the disease. For this reason, only 22 cats were adopted during the campaign.
Anima also reported that among these 22 cats only two had no health problems. However, there were other cases where felines had severe bronchitis, tooth fall, despite being only one year, and other respiratory system infections.
“We deeply regret the heavy financial burden caused to adopters or the pain and suffering of adopted cats and kittens who died due to the virus,” was indicated. "We promise to continue to communicate actively with the Jockey Club of Macao to get compensation for the medical expenses incurred by adopters," he was added.
In addition to the adoption cats promoted by Macau Jockey Club and anima, Mary Jean Reimer, actress, lawyer and activist for the animal rights of Hong Kong, also revealed that one of the Jockey Club cats who adopted positive tested for feline panleukopenia.
Positive response
When it issued the first statement, anima still did not confirm that the treatments of sick cats would be paid by Macau Jockey Club. Initially, it was feared that they would have to be the adopters to pay the costs.
However, yesterday, almost 24 hours after the first publication reporting the problems, the company's administration agreed to distribute 5,000 patacas support for each cat adopted.
Macau Jockey Club was involved in a new controversy with cats, when in the middle of this month, tried to send about 100 felines to the interior to an unknown destination that was never revealed. The sending of cats was approved by the Institute for municipal affairs, which in a statement even promised to ensure animal health conditions for transport to Zhuhai.
However, several local animal protection associations have mobilized to prevent this outcome. In addition to the adoption promotion campaign, associations also received several of the cats.
The animals were raised as bravery at Macau Jockey Club, where they had as their function hunting rats, as the use of space by horses prevented the use of chemicals. However, as they had not been sterilized, the cats reproduced until they were about 100. Now it is also known that they had developed several diseases.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:32:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Consulate | Citizen registers in -person vote after complaint</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/consulado-cidadao-regista-voto-presencial-apos-reclamacao/</link><description>After unable to change the form of participation in the upcoming Portuguese legislative elections, vote for correspondence for face -to -face vote, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, Marcelino Marques filed a complaint to the National Election Commission, which eventually gave him reason and allows the face -to -face vote.
In an email sent to the newsrooms, the Portuguese citizen indicates that he went to the consulate on March 19, after seeing at the media that the registration of face-to-face vote could be made until March 20. His claim was rejected due to alleged “administrative impediments” and was told “the system was already blocked in Portugal”.
It should be noted that news about the deadline to request the registration of the face -to -face vote came from a publication of the Consulate General of Portugal in Macao and Hong Kong on March 18. The publication was eventually deleted the same day.
Marcelino Marques also has known “many citizens resident in Macau” to whom the same claim was refused.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:30:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Payments | Institutions teach the elderly how to use mobile phones</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/pagamentos-instituicoes-ensinam-idosos-a-usar-telemoveis/</link><description>An inquiry has revealed that more than three quarters of respondents over 60 do not know how to make electronic payments. In this sense, the government is encouraging social institutions to organize courses and lectures to teach the elderly how to use mobile applications. In addition, the CTT released discounts for the elderly in the purchase of mobile phones
 
Last year, the General Association of Respectful Elderly of Macao carried out an inquiry into the use of mobile phones by people over 60. Although more than 90 percent answered that he used mobile phone, 76.8 percent admitted not knowing how to make electronic payments and 18.6 percent of respondents stated that mobile data packages and mobile phones are expensive, minimizing their use.
The statistics were presented by Deputy Leong Hong Sai, in a written interplies, in which he concludes that “the consciousness of the elderly about the use of intelligent technologies” is weak. In response, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Hon Wai, listed a series of measures designed to appeal the elders with technological knowledge.
In order to “foster computer generalization”, IAS has encouraged social institutions “teaching the elderly how to use computer equipment, including smartphones, through recreational courses, workshops, courses or lectures”. Hon Wai highlighted the usefulness of using applications such as “Single Account”, “Bus Location” and “Macao Health Data Platform”.
In addition, the president of IAS said that, to “demonstrate the affection for the elderly, CTT have been encouraging mobile telecommunications service operators to launch specially designed benefits for this age group”. Plans offer "unlimited data at restricted speed and allow the purchase of mobile phones at promotional prices."
Warn
The president of IAS also recalled that the older population can also enroll in courses of the Program for Development and Continuous Improvement for mobile phone applications and safe use of the internet.
Hon Wai also stressed the effort to prevent the older population from being a victim of burlas. In addition to raising awareness in social institutions that offer services to the elderly, police authorities last year, 126 “Anti-Burial Lectures”, in which more than 8,300 people participated.
Alongside this, last year, “the Judiciary Police went to Chinese restaurants, recreational, markets and vendin areas” to sensitize the elderly to be aware of burla schemes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:28:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade Balance | Deficit with annual reduction</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/balanca-comercial-defice-com-reducao-anual/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) reveal that in January and February this year the trade balance deficit registered a slight reduction of 1.33 billion patacas, and the total amount of 17.51 ​​billion of deficit was registered. Last year, in the same same period, the trade balance deficit was 18.84 billion.
These data, which are accounted for through imports and exports, are explained by the amount exported in goods in the amount of 2.38 billion patacas, an increase of 13.8 percent; While imports were 19.88 billion of patacas, less five percent. In February alone, goods were exported in the amount of 1.125 billion Patacas, importing 9.13 billion of products of products, which represents an increase of 29.7 percent and 5.5 percent, respectively, compared to February 2024. Thus, the February Balance deficit of this year was 7.88 billion Patacas, says DSEC.
Analyzing exports by countries or destination territories, exported goods for Hong Kong, 1.84 billion patacas and to the European Union, 40 million patacas, from January to February this year increased 24.2 and 2.3 percent, respectively, compared to the same period last year.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:23:51</pubDate></item><item><title>MIECF | Lusofonia companies look for business in renewable energy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/miecf-empresas-da-lusofonia-procuram-negocios-nas-energias-renovaveis/</link><description>A set of 26 companies from Portugal, Brazil and Timor-Leste will be present in Macao at the Forum and International Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation (MIECF), which runs from March 27 to 29, the organizers said yesterday.
Lusophony exhibitors “will expose products related to new energies, waste management, wastewater treatment and environmental hygiene,” said the president of the Institute for the promotion of commerce and investment, Vincent U SENG.
The event, which has been organized since 2008, aims to address topics such as carbonic neutrality, green and ecological mobility, and has activities such as the “Green Forum”, green exhibition, contact bags and a “green day of the public”. “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for Construction of Beautiful Cities”, is this year's theme, which will be exposed in an area of ​​12,000 square meters, according to the organizers.
This year, “we will also organize business visits to Hengqin and Zhuhai for representatives of Portuguese -speaking countries, and thus expand the influence of our platform to new international green business opportunities,” said U.
José Carlos Pimenta Machado, president of the Portuguese Environment Agency, will participate in the event with a lecture dedicated to the theme “Green Transformation and Development”, scheduled for the third day of the event.
According to the organizers, more than 60 international exhibitors participate in this year's Miece, 17 percent than last year, and will be visited by a number of foreign professional buyers also higher than last year, around 23 percent.
The event is organized by the Executive of the Macao Special Administrative Region, with the support of a dozen neighboring Chinese provinces and the Beijing Government.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 01:02:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Tokyo | Japanese newspaper correspondent killed in Gaza</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/toquio-correspondente-de-jornal-japones-morto-em-gaza/</link><description>A Palestinian correspondent from the Japanese newspaper The Asahi Shimbun was killed in the Gaza Strip, apparently by an Israeli attack. According to the newspaper, Mohammed Mansour, 29, died in the city of Khan Youis, in southern Gaza, on Monday. It is believed to have been killed by an attack by an Israelite missile.
The newspaper initially told NHK that Mansour died with his wife and son still a baby, but then corrected the explanation, citing information that his wife and son were being treated in a hospital.
Mansour, a native of Gaza, began working for The Asahi Shimbun in 2023. The young journalist worked at Rafah and Khan Youis, sending reports and photos about the evolution of the situation in Gaza. The newspaper issued a statement expressing the inevitable feeling of deep sadness and anger at his death.
The publication emphasized that attacks on civilians, including journalists, can never be tolerated under any circumstances. Meanwhile, the Qatar-based Al Jazeera satellite TV station, said on Monday that one of its reporters was killed in another Israeli air strike in northern Gaza.
Gaza authorities say the number of journalists killed in the territory has reached 208 since the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:50:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Thai Prime Minister survives the motion of distrust</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/primeira-ministra-tailandesa-sobrevive-a-mocao-de-desconfianca/</link><description>The Prime Minister of Thailand, Paetongtarn Shinawatra, survived yesterday to a motion of distrust in Parliament, which questioned the management of the economy and the links to the former leader and father, Thaksin Shinawatra, convicted of corruption.
Paetongtarn, 38, who took office in August, was supported by 319 deputies, against 161, who voted against it, totaling 500 members of the Chamber of Representatives, the Baixa do Parliament
As planned, the leader was supported by the 11 parties of the government coalition, led by Puea Thai (Thai people), a platform linked to the Shinawatra clan. The motion was presented Monday by the Popular Party, in opposition, heir to the Avanzar party, dissolved last August by a controversial court decision.
During the two sessions preceding the vote, the debate turned around the poor performance of the Thai economy and the alleged influence of Thaksin, who ruled the country between 2021 and 2006, the year that was removed from power by a military coup.
Paetongtarn, a first-minister candidate for PUEA Thai in the May 2023 elections, reached the power in August 2024, after the then leader Srettha Thavisin, also from PEA Thai, was deprived by order of the Constitutional Court after appointing minister a corruption-convicted leader.
Do what I say
Thaksin, Thailand's most influential and polarizing politician in the last 20 years, has returned to the country after spending almost 15 years in exile the same day Srettha has taken office.
The former leader was arrested on arrival at Bangkok, accused of corruption, but did not pass a night in prison, having been transferred on the same day to a hospital, where he was six months old, and then placed in house arrest until his release, days after his daughter had risen to power.
Thaksin, 75, claims to be taken from politics, but occasionally admitted to advice to the current leader and was seen to preside over meetings with other prominent Thai political leaders. The Reform Party Advance won the May 2023 elections, but failed to govern due to a Senate veto, then composed of representatives linked to the extinct military council.
The party was eventually dissolved by the Constitutional Court, following an electoral promise to alter the laws that protect the Thai Royal House of criticism. PEA Thai, which initially allied with Advance, eventually agreed with a coalition government in which parties are associated with the military, once enemies of the Shinawatras.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:49:42</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea | Forest Fires have already made 24 dead</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/coreia-do-sul-fogos-florestais-ja-fizeram-24-mortos/</link><description>The fireworks that triggered last Friday are sowing the chaos through the Asian country. In addition to destroying temples, houses and factories, the flames have already caused death to at least 24 people
 
The wind fires caused by the wind, which are among the worst in the history of South Korea, caused the death of 24 people, destroyed more than 200 structures and forced the evacuation of 27,000 people, according to the last balance.
The death toll included a pilot who died after a helicopter dropped during efforts to contain forest fires in the city of Uiseong in the Southeast, one of the hardest areas, according to the authorities.
The aircraft had no other crew. According to the National Fire Agency, at least 26 other people suffered varying degrees of injuries.
An old Buddhist temple, houses, factories and vehicles are among the structures destroyed in forest fires. South Korea's acting president Han Duck-Soo said the forest fires that began last Friday are causing worse damage than many other previous forest fires.
"The damage is increasing. We fear having forest fires damage we have never had before, so we have to concentrate all our capabilities to erase the fires by the end of this week," said Han. According to the official, about 4,650 firefighters, soldiers and other employees are on the ground, with the help of about 130 helicopters.
Missing heritage
The biggest fires occurred in Andong, in the counties of neighbors of Uiseong and Sancheong and in the city of Ulsan, according to the South Korean Ministry of Interior.
The Uiseong fire destroyed almost half of more than 30 structures in Gounsa, a temple that was originally built in the seventh century.
Korea Forest Service has raised forest fire alert to the highest level across the country on Tuesday, requiring local governments to designate more workers to respond to emergencies, increase the entrance restrictions to forest and parks and recommend that military units suspend royal exercises. Government authorities suspect that human error caused several fires.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:48:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Rangel highlights the importance of Chinese investment for the economy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/rangel-destaca-importancia-do-investimento-chines-para-a-economia/</link><description>Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel highlighted yesterday the “important role” of Chinese investment in the Portuguese economy, during a meeting with Chinese counterparts Wang Yi, according to a statement issued by the Chinese authorities.
The head of Portuguese diplomacy has invited “more Chinese companies to invest and prosper in Portugal” and indicated that Lisbon “is willing to reinforce cooperation with China in the domains of economics and commerce, energy, health, finance, infrastructure and ecological transformation”.
Rangel stated that Portugal and China “have a long history of interaction” and that relations between the two countries “have been developing well,” reads the note widespread by the Chinese Foreign Ministry.
Beijing and Lisbon “gave an example to the world” by solving the issue of Macao peacefully, he added. Quoted in the same statement, Wang Yi highlighted the “good tradition of respect and mutual support” between the two countries.
"Portugal is one of the countries of the European Union that receives the most Chinese investment" per capita "," said the chief of Chinese diplomacy, who appealed to "widening cooperation in the domains of investment in projects, ecological transformation, digital economy, innovation and research, information and communication."
Wang highlighted the role that Macau can play "like a bridge to promote the relationship between the two countries to achieve greater development."
The Chinese diplomat expressed his "support for Europe in maintaining his strategic autonomy" and the hope "that Portugal play an active role in" healthy development of relations between China and Europe. "
The two ministers “discussed issues of common interest, such as the 'crisis' in Ukraine,” according to the Chinese Foreign Ministry's statement, which no longer gave details.
Weight -investor
China has become, in the last decade, the fourth largest foreign direct investor in Portugal. Chinese, state and private companies have a global position evaluated at 11.2 billion euros in the Portuguese economy, according to Banco de Portugal. Investments cover the areas of energy, bank, safe or health.
In 2018, the two countries signed a memorandum of understanding of the “Track and Route” initiative, a mega project of infrastructure launched by Beijing that aims to expand its global influence through the construction of ports, railways or self-destined.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:46:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple donates almost 4 me to Chinese University to train programmers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/apple-doa-quase-4-me-a-universidade-chinesa-para-formar-programadores/</link><description>The American technology company Apple will donate 30 million Yuan to the Chinese university of Zhejiang, announced its executive president, Tim Cook, on a visit to Hangzhou, headquarters of technological giants Deepseek and Alibaba.
The city, located in eastern China, is considered a technological epicenter of the country, at a time when the artificial intelligence sector (IA) is having a new boom in the region.
The initiative is part of the Apple Mobile App Incubation Fund, a fund created to support the formation of entrepreneurial programmers and encourage the development of mobile applications in the iOS ecosystem.
Through this program, participants will receive technical training, mentoring and access to investors and experts from the sector.
"We believe that programming is a powerful tool that allows us to create, communicate and solve problems in totally new ways. We have the honor of deepening our collaboration from a decade with the University of Zhejiang to enable the next generation of programmers," said Cook.
According to Apple, the company has allocated 50 million Yuan to the university in the last ten years.
The mobile innovation contest, supported by Apple a decade ago, attracted more than 30,000 applications from nearly 1000 universities from “Greater China”.
In recent years, specific students have been added to students without prior program track and recent entrepreneurs (“Launch Track), simultaneously widening their reach to less developed regions in the country.
"We will work together with Apple to create a new generation of talents with integrity in terms of knowledge, skills, character and values," said Ren Shabo, secretary of the Communist Party of China (CPC) at Zhejiang University.
Commitment and investment
Cook's visit to Hangzhou is part of his current tour of China, where he has reiterated Apple's commitment to the local market.
On Monday, in Beijing, he met Chinese Minister Wang Wenta, whom he reaffirmed plans to increase investment in investigation, supply chain and social responsibility in the country.
Cook made at least three trips to China last year to show his commitment to further increase the investment in the country and "take advantage of the opportunities offered by its opening."
In one of these visits he said he gives his Chinese partners "great value", without whom the manufacturer "could not do what he does," and on another trip opened the largest Apple store in Asia, located in the eastern megalopolis of Xangai. Greater China is Apple's third largest market after America and Europe.
However, iPhone sales have decreased in the region, partly due to increasing competition from local brands such as Huawei and the lack of AI functionality in the latest Californian company.
According to The Wall Street Journal, Apple has been in conversations with several Chinese AI companies about a possible partnership to implement Apple Intelligence in China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:42:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Government accuses Taiwan of “delivering the TSMC tray” to the United States</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/governo-acusa-taiwan-de-entregar-a-tsmc-de-bandeja-aos-estados-unidos/</link><description>China yesterday accused Taiwan authorities of “delivering tray” to Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company (TSMC), the world's largest semiconductor manufacturer to the United States, where the company announced major investment and expansion plans.
The Council of State's Office spokesman for the Taiwan affairs, Chen Binhua, lamented that "TSMC has become a piece of juicy meat on the cutting board, ready to be undone in pieces," according to state television CCTV.
According to Chen, TSMC is becoming "an American company," which, according to him, is a sign that the Progressive Democratic Party (DPP) in Taiwan power, "only has in mind party selfishness and is not concerned with the well-being of the Taiwan compatriots or the interests of the industrial sector."
The spokesman warned that the DPP "will move forward" on the "Taiwan's Sale and Destruction" and that the industrial sector and the people of the territory "will not only lose jobs, but also opportunities for future development." The spokesman accused Taiwan leader William Lai of "selling Taiwan" and "abuse of power."
TSMC controls about 90 percent of the worldwide market for advanced semiconductors, essential for US companies such as Nvidia and Apple, and for technologies such as Artificial Intelligence.
Rain
TSMC CEO C.C. Wei announced earlier this month, from the White House, an investment of $ 100 billion in the US, which some analysts played as a gesture of goodwill to US President Donald Trump.
The investment is intended to build three new factories, two advanced chips packaging facilities and a research and development center.
These $ 100 billion join the investment of TSMC's $ 65 billion in Phoenix, Arizona, where there is a factory that started operating in late 2024 and plans to open two more factories in the coming years.
Although TSMC defended these investments from a purely commercial perspective, the Taiwan government is looking for an approach to Trump, which threatened to impose rates up to 100 percent on Taiwanese chips and repeatedly accused the island of “usurping” the semiconductor industry in the United States.
According to Taiwan's leader, TSMC's global expansion reinforces its leadership and the competitiveness of the Taiwan semiconductor industry.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:39:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Space | Beijing wants the launching platform of electromagnetic rockets by 2028</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/27/espaco-pequim-quer-plataforma-de-lancamento-de-foguetoes-electromagneticos-ate-2028/</link><description>The ambitious Chinese spatial expansion plan seeks to reduce expenses and promote access to the increasingly frequent space
 
China plans to develop the world's first electromagnetic rocket launch platform by 2028, in a project that seeks to reduce costs and increase the frequency of access to space.
The system, developed by the private company Galactic Energy in collaboration with state research institutes, the Ziyang Municipal Government and China Aerospace Science and Industry Corporation (Casic), will use superconducting imons to accelerate rockets at supersonic speeds before ignition, in a structure similar to a maggev, but vertically oriented train.
According to its creators, this technology would double the load capacity, significantly reduce operating costs and facilitate more frequent releases with less maintenance, the Hong Kong South China Morning Post post on Tuesday.
The long-term objective is to make rocket launches as frequent, predictable and efficient as daily high-speed train trips, integrating them into a regularly used technological infrastructure.
However, experts warned that there are still technical obstacles, such as flight accuracy and thermal resistance during the initial climb.
The verification platform is being built by Casic and the Ziyang government. In September 2023, a magnetic levitation test using high temperature superconductors reached a speed of 234 kilometers per hour on a 380 meter track, as part of the project's initial technical checks.
For exploiting
Founded in 2018, Galactic Energy conducted 18 successful releases of its Ceres-1 rocket, with a total of 77 satellites placed in orbit. The most recent, on March 21, placed six meteorological satellites in a heliosyncron orbit.
The company is also working on the development of CERES-2, with a payload capacity up to 3.5 tons compared to the 400 kilograms of the previous model. In September 2023, however, one of its releases failed due to “abnormal flight performance”, according to the company.
A few days earlier, Galactic Energy had become the first Chinese private company to make a successful sea release.
Chinese scientists have already begun to investigate similar systems to the lunar environment, with the aim of transporting materials such as the helium-3 of the terrestrial satellite surface using electromagnetic catapults, thus eliminating the need for large amounts of fuel.
Although the plan is still in a preliminary phase, the initiative is part of the Chinese government strategy to consolidate its commercial aerospace industry.
China has invested strongly in its space program in recent years, reaching Marcos such as the landing of the Chang'e 4 probe on the hidden side of the moon, the arrival in Mars and the construction of the Tiangong space station, which will operate for about ten years.</description><pubDate>2025-03-27 03:38:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Apple | China tells Tim Cook that he expects more investment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/apple-china-diz-a-tim-cook-que-espera-mais-investimento/</link><description>China Minister Wang Wenta said yesterday expects Apple to “expand his investment” and “integrate deeply in the Chinese market” at a meeting with the company's chairman Tim Cook.
"China remains firm in its commitment to expand its opening to the world, provide equitable conditions to foreign-funded companies and support the equitable participation of its products in our consumer promotion policies," Wang said at the meeting, according to a ministry statement.
The minister stated that the Chinese economy demonstrates “strong resilience and vitality” and is “fertile ground for development driven by innovation”, despite the context of slowing down in the country, which seeks to recover foreign investment in falling and facing the commercial war began by US President Donald Trump.
"Commercial wars do not produce winners and protectionism offers no way out. Dissociation and disorders in supply chains will only harm the interests of all parties," he said, adding that the imposition of fees by the United States "created uncertainty to the global economy."
However, "China is willing to work with the United States to create a more stable political environment for companies through fair dialogue," he said.
Cook, who is in Beijing to participate in the Annual Development Forum, organized by the Asian country as a dialogue platform between senior executive leaders, multinational and academic leaders, has ensured that Apple will continue to increase its investments in China.
"We will continue to increase our investments in sectors such as supply, research and development and social responsibility chains in China, with the aim of supporting the country's high quality development," he said, according to the statement.
The same note also stressed that the company is willing to play an active role in promoting a “stable and healthy development” of economic and commercial relations between China and the United States.
Lacking intelligence
Sales in China from the company's mobile phones fell 18 percent in the last quarter of 2024 and were behind local companies, according to the Counterpoint Research research company.
Apple has the “big China” - a term that encompasses mainland China, Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan - as its third largest market, after the Americas and Europe. However, China is the only one of its main markets where sales are falling.
One of the reasons that may be behind the popularity of the company's devices is that Chinese consumers are not receiving the latest iPhone Artificial Intelligence Services (AI). However, local Huawei, Honor and OPPO devices offer this pioneering technology in their devices.
According to The Wall Street Journal, Apple has been in conversations with several Chinese AI companies about a possible partnership to deploy Apple Intelligence in China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 01:00:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Visit | Rangel underlines “very positive” state of the relationship with Beijing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/26/visita-rangel-sublinha-estado-muito-positivo-da-relacao-com-pequim/</link><description>Portuguese Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel stressed yesterday to Lusa, in Beijing, the “very positive” state of the relationship with China, devaluing the absence of visits in the last five years.
"There is a very positive state in relationships. The fact that there was this hiatus did not slow the interest that both countries have in their bilateral relationship," he said after meeting with Chinese counterparts Wang Yi.
The Portuguese minister yesterday began a four -day visit to the Asian country, which ends up more than five years without Portuguese high -level visits to Beijing, at a time of reconfiguration of the international order.</description><pubDate>2025-03-26 00:55:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Vera Lúcia Raposo, jurist and teacher: “It was propagated today as a virus”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/vera-lucia-raposo-jurista-e-docente-ia-propaga-se-hoje-como-um-virus/</link><description>Vera Lúcia Raposo presented on Wednesday at the University of Macao the new regulatory framework of the European Union for Artificial Intelligence, in a session promoted by the Institute of European Studies of Macao. The former Macao University officer argues that China is gaining the race in an area that has never been so present in our lives
 
 
Spoke on Wednesday of “Ai Act” approved by the European Union (EU). Specifically, what are the main points of this document?
This is the Artificial Intelligence Regulation (IA) published last year in the EU official newspaper. It is a European law, but it is also, so far, the most detailed legal regime about the products surrounding AI.
Is it difficult to legislate on the AI ​​at this preliminary phase?
Maybe we will never stop being at this stage. Notice, AI did not come up with ChatgPT or anything that looks like. Since the middle of the last century, and even before, but especially since Alan Turing's 'Paper' that Ia exists, first in the laboratory, girded with a group of researchers. Then it began to be released into the world and to be part of our lives, but never as now. We are currently in a kind of pandemic, where AI propagates in our existence as a virus, but not a bad virus, because I understand that the AI ​​often propagates with positive effects. Of course, although it is not a completely new thing, it is a very mysterious reality for us jurists. The problem begins that we can't even get a definition mostly accepted by experts of what AI is. First of all, we don't know what it is, because it is a moving entity that constantly changes. What we thought was ten years ago, today it will be an algorithm.
In the areas of private life defense, or personal data, for example, or copyright, what does European legislation tell us in concrete terms?
The AI ​​regulation [of the EU] is part of what we call “Data Package” [Data Package], it is inserted in the group of regulations that concern product security. But this is understood in very comprehensive terms, not only security as we are used to thinking about it, as something that calls into question physical integrity, but covers environmental issues, respect for fundamental values ​​and technology rights and data protection. It is true that the regulation has these practical aspirations and realization in some standards, but the idea is to develop with other existing regulations on data protection and intellectual property, and that does not conflict with them.
We currently have ChatgPT on the American side, and DeepSeek on the Chinese side. Do you think China positions itself as a leader in the AI ​​area?
China is found to be a colossus in the digital world. The way the world has been evolving has differentiated. 100 years ago we had war conflicts, and today we have wars where we continue to kill people, but we also have commercial wars and these technological wars. And I say that more than a war is a race to reach the new invention. The old blocks of countries have different strategies. For example, in the case of the United States of America (USA), this strategy has changed a lot with the presidency of Trump, but was always more liberal and "Laissez-Faire". This has also been the form of US action, but with Trump is more in the line of "Vale Tudo", what matters is to arrive first. There is a great promotion of technological companies, as you see with the great support they gave to Trump's presidential campaign. Then we have China, with a state policy, which is not so much in the hands of the private. There is a great focus on technological advancement, but it is visible that the country is already in a position that will hardly be achieved by others. Europe is not exactly well positioned.

Why?
Europe has made the decision that the best way to develop technological progress and foster innovation is through hyper-regulation. There is no centimeter that is not regulated or not being regulated by the EU. Of course, it may have some advantages, and the aspirations can be in the face of controlled and sustainable development, and respect our fundamental rights and the rule of law. But I have some doubts. First, that this is achieved, because the protection of fundamental rights does not go through this hyper-regulation either. Then it seems to me that we are doing this at the expense of a value that seems to me, which is innovation. This idea comes, by the way, in the report of Mario Draghi, who warned the EU to the ability to mortgage future generations because we are leaving innovation behind. I don't see that any of these three technological models [US, China and EU] be particularly fruitful because they have benefits and disadvantages. We have an interesting model, which is the British.
In what sense?
The United Kingdom maintains the legal framework it inherited from the EU, and has not yet changed it. The United Kingdom will not adopt AI regulation [Europe's Ai Act], because it is no longer part of the EU, it seems that it will not create such a regulatory framework, but have an approach that is having a very generic picture that fixes the main points and limits, but then there will be a sectoral regulation. This regulation, which is still being created, is to establish the 'guidelines' for each area of ​​activity, so that there is autonomy in each sector and always respecting the particularities of each. In theory, it is more interesting, but everything is at first and I have not seen cases applied in practice.
How do you comment on the use of AI in the legal and judicial area?
Using sources that are not desirable to do our work was not something that came with ChatgPT. Speaking of something I know well, such as academic theses or scientific papers, it is not unprecedented that some less scrupulous authors quote sources in which they have never put their eyes, and then quote the wrong way, or quote sources that do not exist. There are situations in which unafable sources are cited, such as blogs, or papers that have not been subject to the peer review system. This is not new. We have the chatgpt beside it helps a lot and the temptation is great. I don't think it's the end of the world. Literacy was fundamental to the academy and any citizen. We all have to understand the benefits of Generative AI and risks as well. Research on Wikipedia pages can also generate errors. It is impossible to tell students not to use chatgPT, because this ban would be hollow. I can't know how people do their job. There may be situations of scientific dishonesty and situations where information is not true, but if someone tells me who wrote something with ChatgPT support, I have no problem with that. I have if the person is considered to be the author's author. ChatgPT works a lot as a Google search, it's not completely new. But I have to realize that the information that ChatgPT gives me has to be very analyzed and again investigated. ChatgPT can only give me clues where I can go, and then it can be useful and make us think. It is a source like any other, but it is not very credible. Chatgpt never deals with things in detail, for example.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 16:42:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby Hui, President of the Macao Autism Association: “Autism differs from person to person”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/ruby-hui-presidente-da-associacao-de-autismo-de-macau-autismo-difere-de-pessoa-para-pessoa/</link><description>Created in 2012, the Macao Autism Association continues to fight for more care for children and young people with this development disturbance. But the association's president, Ruby Hui, warns of the need for more incisive policies for adolescents and their specific needs, especially in access to employment
 
 
What balance does the work done by the association in recent years?
My work is above all to establish a connection with all the entities and resources made available by the government and also the game industry, as the authorities have started to [the context of the new game concession contracts] that develop more social support activities. Therefore, we have gathered all these resources to organize recreational activities for children and youth. In addition, we organize therapy sessions for our members. Usually, we request financial support from private companies and the government, covering 30 to 50 percent of these expenses.
The support of the game sector is therefore quite important.
Yes, but it has not really been a great support. For example, the government covers part of our monthly expenses, about 40,000 patacas. But this amount comes only to hire two full -time employees and one part -time employee. They are the ones who organize all activities, deal with the bureaucratic part, which includes the presentation of many reports to the government, because we ask for subsidies for almost half of our expenses.
Therefore, do you consider that they need more support from the executive to be able to hire more professionals?
Yes, it would be ideal. Associations like ours are getting bigger and the children we support are growing. I would say that 60 percent of our members are 11 or more, and about 20 percent are even larger, over 14 years old. We have to think about their future and the needs of therapy and treatment for adolescents, as it is not only small kids who need therapies such as speech or occupational therapy. They are young people who are still in high school and need to acquire different types of social skills, boys need to know how to deal with girls and vice versa. Then, when they become adults, they need to know how to deal with bosses in jobs. There are many valences to explore, but at this moment I would say that the supports are not enough.
Are schools not yet prepared to receive these students, for example?
Autism may be different from person to person. Students with autism, but who have better learning skills, are in normal schools. But parents tell me that there are not enough teachers with certain skills to deal with and teach these children. There are teachers who still have a very traditional mindset to treat these young people, who often have to deal with alone with bullying, for example. I would say that there are many children and young people with autism with psychological problems because of the school.
When it speaks of the traditional mindset, what does this mean in concrete?
In the case of my son, for example, he is obliged to always be sitting at school, but often likes to move and get up from his chair. From the point of view of parents who have children with this problem, there would be no problem, as long as it did not bother others, but for teachers it cannot be, and complain. They say things of the genre: "He will beat the table, he will move the painting, makes a lot of noise." Every day I receive complaints from parents to connect with the school, and for small situations like this.
What are the main difficulties or challenges that Macao families face when they deal with an autistic child?
In my case, my family is middle -class, and financially we are fine. But when my son was younger needed to do therapy and it was very expensive. Now these therapies cost even more. At the time my son was in primary education, 600 to 700 patacas was paid for each therapy session, but there are days a father told me that the sessions now cost about 1000 patacas per class, which is very expensive. Families of lower social classes cannot afford. Therefore, this support is one of the great objectives of our association, raising money so that we can provide explanations, therapy sessions or other type of support. All so that our members can attend classes with 50 percent discount, where the association pays half the amount.
When the association was created, what were its main objectives?
In 2012 autism was not a very spoken theme. Therefore, we joined [some parents and families] and we started to ask for support from the government and try to draw attention to the subject. We got some things because the government now gives more support to these young people, at least for those under 12. The problem we feel is that these young people are growing and adolescents need other types of supports that do not exist.
What is necessary to change in mindsets and society in relation to autism?
In Macao there are not many companies willing to hire young people with autism. Situation that is not seen in Hong Kong, where there are several hiring programs with social companies. Macau needs to follow this path.
One day in Rio
World Autism Consciousness Day is celebrated on April 2 and, in this context, the Macao Autism Association joined Sands China for a series of activities with children and parents, which took place last March 10th. Through the program “Sands Care”, the game operator provided a visit to the exhibition “Coastal Fantasia”, with the figure of “King Lobster”, a creation of Philip Colbert artist ” A boat trip through the Delta of the Pearl River.
In total, 70 people participated. Quoted by a game operator statement, Ruby Hoi said the tour "allowed children to enjoy the maximum of the trip." "Thank you for all the support provided to people with autism in Macau, and I hope that all sectors of society can continue to support the development of these people and promote their inclusion in society," he said.
For the game operator, this type of events can help “reinforce the cohesion of families dealing with autism, but also promote the awareness of society and support for the community of people with autism fostering a more inclusive and supportive social environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul French, writer: Looking for Wallis Simpson in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/paul-french-escritor-a-procura-de-wallis-simpson-na-china/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival, which starts on Friday, will feature the presence of writer Paul French, who launched last year a new biographical book, "Her Lotus Year", which describes Wallis Simpson's experience in China before being a Duchess of Windsor. The British author will also talk about “Destination Macau”, a nostalgic and almost cinematic account of the city's history
 
How did you come to the history of Wallis Simpson's life experience in China?
I lived in Shanghai for many years and many visitors knew that Wallis Simpson had spent time in the city. Rumors ran on what he had done, and visitors always wanted to know if the rumors were true, such as the idea that she had learned esoteric sexual techniques or had posed naked for photographs. It was also said that he had belonged to a group of opium smuggling, or a group of bets that combined horses races. For me, as an author and expert in foreign experiences in Shanghai in the first half of the twentieth century, none of this made sense. So I thought this was the ideal time to really find out what Wallis had done in China. The fact that she was in the country in 1924 and 1925, two of the most fascinating years in the history of modern China, helped a lot.
How do you describe the life of the duchess in the country during that specific political period?
China was in total chaos when she was there, because Puyi, the last emperor, had been expelled from the forbidden city and occurred the biggest strikes ever in Hong Kong history. In addition, political fractions were recorded in Guangzhou, warlords of war in Shanghai and northern China. These were also the most wet years that there is a record in China, with crop production breaks and the occurrence of tiphoid and cholera fever outbreaks. He fired the number of bandits and pirates. Then, in March 1925, Sun Yat-Sen, leader of the Republican Revolution of 1911, died without leaving an obvious successor. Wallis came across all this, as he was retained on the island of Shamian, Guangzhou, while the city struggled; In Shanghai, he saw corpses to be brought to the city from the battles of the warlords; He saw victims of typhus and anger in Tianjin; and troops of the warlords threatening Beijing. But he was also largely in a foreign protective bubble that protected her from foreign soldiers and her white skin. He could delight in China's culture and aesthetics, while around him the whole country threatened to explode.
How was the personality of Wallis Simpson, a controversial figure in the context of the marriage to the Duke of Windsor?
It is very important not to confuse Wallis of 1924 with the later Wallis, from the long years of exile and controversy as Duchess of Windsor. In 1924 Wallis was only 28 years old, fleeing from a physically abusive husband (her first husband, Win Spencer, an American Navy commander) and was not yet particularly sophisticated or cosmopolitan. These were characteristics that would learn in China, mingling in the “colonies” [concessions] international foreign and bohemiums of Shanghai and Beijing. In fact, it was in Beijing that it first mixed with ambassadors, high -level Chinese politicians, high -ranking military officers and a stretch, and from them learned everything from playing Bridge and enjoying Jade to how to behave in high society. Obviously, this was useful a decade later when he met the Prince of Wales in England. Admittedly, the posterior Wallis, the Duchess, is a more difficult figure to like. Perhaps she and the Duke have made some bad political decisions and made some friendships, perhaps Wallis became a little bitter for not being accepted by the British royal family. But the truth is that in 1924 she was young, free of a bad husband and was in one of the most fascinating countries in the world.
What can readers perceive this figure and about China of that time, with "Her Lotus Year"?
China in 1925 was on the brink of potential explosion, as the whole country could have fallen into total chaos, dividing into the size of Portugal managed by warlords with private armies, or a resurgent Qing Dynasty supported by Japan in the North [China], the South and, of course, the foreign powers-England, America, France and Japan-who had Chinese lands like colonies. Ultimately, this did not happen, but no one knew this in 1925. Wallis herself oscillated between feeling incredibly comfortable and happy in what was her "year of lotus," as he described him, quoting Homer's Sopoifers who never want to return home; and feel terrified of the violence of the warlords or those who were against foreigners.
What are the biggest challenges, as a writer, in the process of researching the history of Wallis?
Wallis probably became the most photographed and spoken woman in history, more than Marilyn Monroe, more than Queen Isabel II. But in 1924 she was not famous at all. So it left a very difficult trail to follow. He wrote his memories, but these were "disinfected." A big problem was also the rumors that the British government and secret services circulated in 1936 in an attempt to destroy the idea of ​​a marriage between King Eduardo VIII and Wallis. The attempt failed because he abdicated the throne and they married, but these sexual rumors and insinuations, many of them racist and misogynists, have remained to this day, and they continue to be regularly recycled in the British and American Tabloid Press. I found the real Wallis a much more friendly character than I expected, and I hope readers will feel that too.
Is invited to another edition of Rota das Letras. How do you feel for being part of the festival?
I love to be part of the Macao Literary Festival. Although he had spoken before in Macao, namely in the Portuguese bookstore and other places, he had never participated in the festival. I look forward to being able to talk about Wallis Simpson and also about my new collection of rehearsals about Macau, entitled "Destination Macau". Some stories of Macao that have pleased me over the years, some of them presented with a more English look, as it were, may be interested and will be new to the local public.
Book | “Destination Macau”, the city between “The Imaginary and the Real”
Paul French has just launched the third volume of the “Destination” collection, which had editions of Shanghai or Beijing, and is now dedicated to telling stories of the ancient macao, a “place as imaginary as real”, as described the synopsis of the work. The work of the British author presents "The Macao by artists George Chinnery and George Smirnoff, the writers Deolinda da Conceição and Maurice Dekobra, to the fantasies of" Pulp Fiction "and febrile dreams of Josef Von Sternberg and Jean Delannoy."
There is still no shortage of Paul French, stories around historical figures such as Pedro José Lobo and Ian Fleming, author and creator of James Bond. Macao of the time of World War II, those who “came to Macao in search of gold, and those who sought war refuge” is described, not forgetting “the combatants looking for a secret passage through the 'neutral' macao”.
Paul French unveil mysteries or tells forgotten stories to many, such as the idea that Japan had tried to buy Macau in 1934 or the person who sailed with the Macau pirates queen, Lai Choi San. There are, in all, 18 stories “true of fascinating people who lived or visited Macau in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Augusto Nogueira, President of Artm: “Macau is ahead of Hong Kong”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/augusto-nogueira-presidente-da-artm-macau-esta-a-frente-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Macao toxicode dependent rehabilitation association is 25 years old this year. Augusto Nogueira makes a positive balance of the fourth century that began with a small therapeutic community and reached international recognition. The Association's president argues that, in prevention, Macau is at the head of Hong Kong and that the use of synthetic drugs is not yet problematic in the territory
 
 
What balance does the work developed by ArtM in these 25 years?
We do the balance very positive, because we started with a small area and a small therapeutic community. Nowadays we have a community with a capacity of 60 people, much more than the 15 we had at the time. We have developed several programs, namely the syringe distribution, which is a success, because it has led to a reduction and almost suppression of HIV contagion by people who inject drugs. For nine years there is the program and we have zero cases of infection. We developed support for social integration and follow -up after treatment, with “After Care”. We do preventive work in schools with the “Be Cool” program. We have the project “Hold on To Hope”, betting on vocational education, through coffee and the art gallery. It is a project that is well achieved and that turns out to be turned to tourism. We have visits from international entities and various non-governmental organizations, and the United Nations themselves. The most positive for us is to know how many people are recovered and who are well today. Unfortunately, we could not recover all people, but in each relapse there is always the possibility of the person coming again to do treatment.
How many people have recovered in 25 years?
We couldn't get this notion. We maintain contact with many people, but others have already left Macau, followed their lives. We have some contacts in the first two years after treatment, but then life goes on. People also want to go on a lifetime with no connection with the artm, sometimes marry and new companions don't know about their previous life and want to keep some confidentiality. But sometimes we meet. The other day they paid me a water without me knowing (laughs). These are small gestures that give us satisfaction to continue and make us believe that recovery is always possible.
What are the big challenges to maintain the ArtM project in terms of space and financing?
In terms of space and places for treatment we are well. The facilities are ten years old, there are maintenance problems, but this is more related to the panorama of construction in Macao. We need a space for the After Care, because what we have currently rented and is deteriorated. We are talking to the Institute of Social Action (IAS) to have a new space. With regard to the back, all our departments have financing, but we obviously seek support for our activities otherwise.
Regarding the authorities' posture regarding consumption and treatment, do you understand that it is still conservative in relation to other countries and regions?
This question is a little ambiguous. In terms of treatment and strategy in combating consumption, I think Macau is very ahead of Hong Kong, for example. In Macao, we have therapeutic community, we work on prevention and treatment, as well as our syringes and methadone distribution program. We have a range of treatments available to those in need. In the area of ​​prevention, the government has given a lot of support. The IAS has been quite open in strategies to combat consumption and prevention. In Hong Kong, for example, there is no syringe distribution program. Macao is from the few regions of Southeast Asia that has a government -supported syringes distribution program. But there could be another different interpretation of the law, with a differentiation between what is trafficking and their own consumption. For example, at this time if the person has a higher amount than that stipulated is soon considered trafficking, without proof. We think that in this case there should be a differentiation. It is then up to the police to investigate whether the quantities found are for consumption or trafficking. There should be an opening to give people more opportunities to be referred for treatment instead of going to prison. But lately, there have not been as many cases as that.
How do you describe the current consumer profile in Macau?
There is a large reduction in heroin consumption, and the few people who did so consume it today, or sleep. At this time the highest consumption is metabetamin, cannabis and some ketamine residues. As for the new synthetic drugs, there have been some records, but so far nothing alarming. But of course we have to be alert, we have to continue to do a good prevention job so that people are aware of the problems related to drug use. Regarding trafficking, we know that before the pandemic there was much cocaine trafficking to Macao, and after Covid-19 this situation almost ceased to happen. A good dissuasive work has been done and has to continue to be done so that there is less traffic to pass through Macau. It does not mean that there are no situations currently, but we are not in such a chaotic situation as that.
Speaking of synthetic drugs and their consumption, which according to the latest United Nations report has reached a worrying situation around the world. What is your comment to the scenario described in the annual report of the International Narcotics Control Board?
It is evident that the use of this type of drugs has been increasing over the years. Synthetic drugs are a real problem in the United States of America, for example, with fentanyl consumption, and Asia in some countries. It is a global problem because consumption and production are easy. Some of these drugs are made with other chemicals and many other products that are not well known to the origin and that can cause many overdoses. The UN suggests combating the production of ingredients that are used to produce these drugs, continue to reinforce the investigation to catch traffickers. But there are points of this report that it is necessary to follow, for many countries, which is the struggle between ideologies.
In what sense?
There is a struggle between those who argue that harm reduction is sufficient to combat all these problems that are arising, and that it is the solution to everything. Then we have those who think that harm reduction is not missing. In the artm we consider that there has to be a balance, because prevention is something important that cannot stop. What happened in Portugal, for example, when they liberalized the drug and failed to prevent and support treatment, [it was not good], and today Portugal is again in a slightly chaotic situation at consumption and trafficking. This means that prevention can never cease to exist. There should be quality treatments, with supervision of entities. The speed of access to treatment has to exist, and it can not be like in some countries where people have been waiting for a vacancy or permission to enter, as non -governmental organizations do not let the person enter until they receive the subsidy for each bed and patient. In these months a lot can happen. Damage reduction should be seen as a continuity for recovery, with rooms for consumption with medical and technical support, or syringe management programs. There is another problem, especially in Europe, which is heroin consumers, when they reach a more advanced age, already have many health problems and need sites to be, of a certain dignity. We have been wasting a lot of time with these ideological wars, and some of them exist for the sake of power, to influence the liberalization of drugs, and this is quite harmful. People's rights end when it begins to harm the rights of all other people, there must be a balance. As the report also says, there is a lack of medicines for some countries in Africa.

Art
To commemorate the 25th anniversary, the artm inaugurated on Friday the “Exhibition of the 25th Anniversary of Artm”, which is evident in the Hold on To Hope Gallery until the 23rd of this month. In the cultural space in the village of Nossa Senhora in Ká-Hó, which is part of the Occupational Therapy Program for the Arts users, you can see an art show done by these, with 45 works of ceramic, painting and wooden works. According to a press release of the association, the exhibition “celebrates resilience, creativity and healing”. “Throughout the last quarter of century, the artm has been a symbol of hope for individuals on its journey of recovery of dependence. This exhibition presents the extraordinary works of art created by our residents,” he is also read.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Iame Asia finals of Karting back in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/finais-da-iame-asia-de-karting-voltam-em-dezembro/</link><description>The Macao Karting International Award will receive again, from December 11 to 14, the Iame Asian finals. Like last year, the coloane karting race will give invitations to the very coveted world end of Iame in 2026.
Organized by the Institute of Sport, Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Otk Kart Asia and Iame Asia, the 2024 event brought back the international spirit to one of the largest competitions of the sport on the Asian continent. Coloane's karting received several races and different categories of Iame Series Asia, recovering the international prestige of an event that has been the scene of the Cik-Fia World Championship events.
Pilots from the interior of China, Singapore, Philippines, Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Japan, India, Sri Lanka, Australia, New Zealand, Sweden, Italy, France, Austria, the United States of America, Brazil, Hong Kong, and, of course, Macao, filled the track from the mashes in 2024 for four days of intense Competition, something that has not been seen for several years.
After the success of the previous edition, the formula is repeated this year. Singapore's organization again chooses Coloane's karting for its biggest event of the season, confirming the presence of the usual categories: Cadet, Junior, Senior and Master.
Thank you Macau!
The Iame (Italian American Motor Engineering) is one of the world's leading engine manufacturers for Karting. Founded in 1968 by Bruno Grana, the company is headquartered in Italy and is one of the references in Karting Internacional, having bet strongly in the Asian market in recent years. The presence in Macau is part of this strategy of growth and expansion.
The announcement of the return to the territory was made on social networks: “After an incredible debut in 2024, we are back with the Macao International International Award and the Iame Asia final for another epic confrontation! The city of emotions at high speed and legendary races will be the stage for the best pilots in Asia and the world!
Satisfied with the reception in 2024, Iame Asia organizers took the opportunity to leave a "huge thanks to AAMC and the Macao government for their continuous support and confidence to make it possible!"
In addition to the Macao test, the 2025 calendar of Iame Series Asia includes three events in Malaysia and three events in Thailand. However, for the first time, last weekend of March, the Iame Asia Cup will be held at the International Shanghai Circuit Karting.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 01:04:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to GIC | Local tests return to Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/regresso-ao-gic-provas-locais-voltam-a-zhaoqing/</link><description>The dates for the Macao of Tourism Car Championship (MTCs in the English acronym) were made known on the past Friday by the General Automóvel Association of Macau-China (AAMC) through a newsletter. The competition for local pilots and decides to find out the Macao Grand Prix in November will again return to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC).
After a year when the MTCS headed to the Zhuzhou International Circuit in Hunan province, AAMC listened to most of the territory pilots and chose to make these important races closer to the main interveners' house - the pilots. In recent years, the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing has been the preferred stage for the realization of these races, due to the proximity and the fact that it serves as an operational basis to most teams.
The first of the two events scheduled for the 2025 MTCS is scheduled from 18 to 20 April, while the second round is scheduled from 16 to 18 May. The AAMC newsletter says that "all riders must go through a selection process before they can participate in the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix - Macau Touring Car Challenge."
Registration, for the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), are open until March 29 and after the end of the registration period, "all applications will be subject to AAMC approval, which reserves the final right to accept or reject any registration."
The technical regulation was also published, as was officially confirmed the use of tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, which belongs to the Chinese conglomerate Sinochem, as had already happened on the last edition of the Macao Grand Prix.
Confirmation of the Great Bay
AAMC also confirmed the two findings for the GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4), which will be concomitant with the new Chinese Championship Sro GT Cup. The first race will be played from March 21 to 23, at the International Circuit of Shanghai, in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix. Zhuhai International. Also here Pirelli will be the only tire supplier.
These two tests will be determined for the big holiday party on the guide circuit, and it is defined that only 28 cars will be accepted on the starting grid in the mashed race. The 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix runs from November 13 to 16.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 04:17:32</pubDate></item><item><title>FIRST RALENT PROOF FOR THE MACAU GP took place in Shanghai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/25/primeira-prova-de-apuramento-para-o-gp-macau-decorreu-em-xangai/</link><description>The first determination test for the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix took place last weekend at the International Shanghai Circuit. Integrated in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix Program, Chen Weian and Lichao Han won the two races that will serve to select competitors entitled to participate this year in the GT - Great Bay Cup -
 
The GT Cup-Great Bay Race joined the newly created SRO GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macao Grand Prix. Thirty-three cars, six of them driven by Macau pilots, signed up for this debut-a record number of participants in a GT4 category in Asia category.
According to the organizer's statement, Sro Motorsports Group, “the total number of cars and the variety of builders have even exceeded the organizers' expectations for a championship that only began to be discussed in late November 2024. Since then, the Sro Asia team and their partner AAMC (Macau-China General Automobile Association) have worked tirelessly to make the series a reality before their debut.”
The event started in a troubled way. Due to a customs problem that affected several cars, more than a dozen competitors was unable to participate in the free training session on Friday. Fortunately, for this group of pilots, among which were included the drivers of the Kevin Leong Ian Veng, Kim Hou Lao and Un Hou IP, the cars arrived at the circuit in time for Saturday's qualification.
Animated races and decision in Zhuhai
With three dozen cars, from ten different brands, on track, all with very balanced tasks, was attended by two animated races in the imposing Shanghai track. In the first 12 -lap race, the two Lotus Emi GT4 Officials, by Daniel Lu and Luo Kailuo, who departed from the first line of the grill, were overcome on track by the Chen Weian Audi R8 LMS GT4. In the second match of the weekend, Lichao Han, behind the wheel of the same Toyota GR GT4 who beat the GT Cup - Great Bay Race in 2024, triumphed ahead of Chen Weian and Lotus de Liu Kai Shun.
Macao pilots had no easy life on a track where they had little or no experience. The most rewarded of all, Kelvin Leong, abandoned in the second round of the first race, while Miguel Law, in Audi R8 LMS GT4, was the best of the riders of MSAR, ending in 19th place. In Sunday's race, Leong took his BMW M4 GT4 F82 to 11th place.
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, at the end of the season, on the streets of Macau. The places will be attributed based on the classification after the second round of the championship, scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit, in a date yet to be announced.</description><pubDate>2025-03-25 01:20:30</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Fia introduces costly measure to GT world cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/21/gp-macau-fia-introduz-medida-onerosa-para-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) announced on Tuesday afternoon a technical measure for the GT3 cars participating in the GT World Cup of the Macao Grand Prix, which will certainly have an impact on a race that is the event's headlord
 
To improve the Balance of Performance (BOP) - the method that balances the progress between all cars in the GT3 category - the FIA ​​decided to force the use of torque sensors, like what you already do in their championships, such as resistance worlds (WEC) and Rally Raid or Formula E. Torque sensors offer a very high precision in power measurement, allowing FIA ensures that the power of each car does not exceed the values ​​assigned by BOP and that external factors, such as atmospheric conditions, do not influence performance.
Although Sro Motorsports Group is co-organizer of this race, and having a bop recognized worldwide, in the last two years, the Macao Bop has been provided by the FIA ​​itself. Last year, the FIA ​​BOP was worth a series of criticisms, with teams and pilots-particularly from Audi, Porsche and Lamborghini, the main impaired-to publicly express their natural discontent with the difference in progress.
These sensors are installed in car transmission veins and represent the most effective tool for measuring wheel power, being individually attributed by the BOP process to each car model that participates in the world's most prestigious “sprint” race for GT3 class machines. According to FIA, the decision to make torque sensors mandatory after consultations with the brands involved in the GT3 technical working group.
Costs will shoot
For a race that has several private teams, this measure will be expensive, as these sensors exceed half a million patacas per car, and the teams need to have another same spare reserve system. This, given that most teams that participate in the MSar test do not use torque sensors in their cars in any competition, and cannot amortize the brutal investment.
"From the experience I had in Qatar, it is noted that there is a difference between several builders in the way it generates this technology. An extra support team is needed to monitor and maximize performance without exceeding the stipulated limits," he told HM Duarte Alves, the experienced track engineer in the territory who was with the official Ford team in the first WEC season in the Arab country.
"A good example is the difficulty and time needed for a builder who enters as a newcomer. An illustrative case is Mercedes-AMG, which is facing growth pains while developing its own systems," said Duarte Alves. “In more flat circuits, the management of these systems is simpler. In places like Macau, where 'torque peaks' will always be frequent, it will be a real challenge for the engineers of these systems!”
Confident
Immune to all this, the FIA ​​chooses a speech directed to builders, forgetting that most of the starting grid is made up of private competitors.
Lutz Leif Linden, chairman of the FIA ​​GT commission, said the institution that represents “made this decision in consultation with the builders”, adding that, to the international federation, “this means even more justice and improved control of BOP values, which is particularly important in such a prestigious and media event, in such a demanding circuit, where the long -speed straight lines contrast with tight curves and narrow ”.
Fabrice Van Ertvede, FIA speed technical manager, stressed the idea that "our goal, as a regulatory entity, is to ensure total equity for all participants." The implementation of torque sensors “is an extremely effective tool for achieving this goal, allowing us to align very different cars in parameters such as pure power, but also at full speed, a crucial factor in a circuit like the guide circuit.”
Despite the difficulties that Mercedes-AMG encountered with this system last month, Fabrice Van Ertvede praises that “the builders we hope to see in Macau this year are already familiar with this innovation, through their experience in the FIA's LMGT3 LMGT3 class, and the decision to adopt torque sensors resulted from the dialogue we kept with them.”
This is the second news that the FIA ​​introduces in the mashed race, having announced last month that the second qualification segment will have a super pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification laps. The eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will take place from November 13 to 16, as part of the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 17:11:10</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | FIA confirms GT World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/gp-macau-fia-confirma-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The World Council of the FIA ​​last Wednesday confirmed the expected, that the eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be held as part of the Macao's 72nd Grand Program, from November 13 to 16. However, there is a big news for this year's edition
 
The International Federation, which co-organizes this race in partnership with Sro Motorsports Group and the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), took the opportunity to announce a new qualification model for the race. In addition to the 30 -minute qualification session equal to the previous editions (Q1), a second qualification segment (Q2) was added, reserved for the top ten pilots of the first session.
The Q2 session will be held in Super Pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification turns, and each pilot is also allowed to use a new tire set at this session. This novelty will allow qualification to be decided without interference from third parties.
The remaining program of the Queen of GT will remain the same as the previous editions, with the free training session, the traditional 12-lap classification race on Saturday afternoon, followed by the 16-lap main race that will decide the world's Cup winner on Sunday.
Veterans compliments
These measures introduced by the FIA ​​were very well received by the most experienced GT riders. This is because traffic has always been a huge obstacle in obtaining a good qualification return on the guide circuit, something essential for those who aim to win this title.
"It's an excellent idea to introduce the Super Pole session in Macao," said German Maro Engel, the winner of the World Cup last edition by Mercedes-AMG. This will be one of the most spectacular and exciting sessions of the season and should also secure sports justice.
Raffaele Marciello, for two occasions winning of this trophy, and one of the BMW factory riders, also reacted positively, adding: “In Macao, it was always complicated to make a clean lap. With this new format, you will not hear the excuse of traffic or a red flag. Having only two laps will be very challenging, but now the fastest pilot will probably be in pole.”
This is an opinion shared by Laurens Vanthoor, the World Cup winner in 2016, who said there will no longer be “apologies” in the qualification. Porsche's experienced Belgian pilot believes that “there will be an added pressure because you only have these two turns”, because in a difficult circuit like this, “if you make an error, there is nothing more to follow. In a normal qualification, you have more opportunities. Personally, a shootout is always something that I appreciate a lot. For pilots like this, it will be almost the highlight of the weekend.”
And the younger ones too
Chinese pilot Yifei Ye premiered at the Grand Prix last November at the World Cup. Ferrari's official pilot, which competes in the Endurance Fia World Championship (WEC), has left a good impression on the guide circuit, and he also welcomes the now introduced measurements.
“It's good to eliminate these red flag interventions and yellow flags, so that in the end, the one that really is the fastest to get pole position,” said Yifei Ye that she could return to the race this year. "In Macao, everyone is very close in terms of times, so it will be extremely difficult for pilots to try to get to 'Super Pole'. I think it will also be great for viewers."</description><pubDate>2025-02-28 01:03:51</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Célio Alves Dias will continue to run this season</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/gp-celio-alves-dias-vai-continuar-a-correr-esta-temporada/</link><description>Macaense pilot Célio Alves Dias was one of the long -term returns of the 2024 car.
 
The Macao Cup winner of Macau in 2021 was removed from motorsport at the time of 2023 for personal reasons, but last year made his debut in the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8). Despite the vast experience in tests of the specialty, having conducted several generations of tourism cars, Célio Alves Dias had never managed the new bobbinns that the Macao-China General Association (AAMC) introduced in its competition in 2023. Last time turned out to be of learning, with some difficulties in the tuning and behavior of the Japanese car.
Participation in races at the Zhuzhou International Circuit and the Macau Grand Prix made Célio Alves Dias realize that his Toyota GR86 was not at the strongest competition level. Based on the conclusions drawn from these experiences, he decided to start preparing for the new season.
"The car had to be all dismantled. My car was bought in Monday, and the chassis and the security arc, for me, were not well done," explained Fu Lei Racing Team pilot to HM. "This, I made the car too hard and very difficult to bow. I tried a well -mounted China car, and there is a difference. I had a long time in January, in China, with this car. Our cars, made in the same workshop, were very hard, which made it difficult to get around quickly."
If in the Macao Grand Prix, the house riders, excellent guide circuit, managed to equate the progress to their hong Kong opponents and the interior of China, in the initial races on the Zhuzhou track in Hunan province, it wasn't quite like that. "There are many differences between cars, but especially in chassis, because the engines, in terms of power and horses, are almost all at the same level. Our opponents have also experienced many pieces, many engines, even speed boxes, and chassis. Competition cars are always the same.
Silver Jubilee in November
Being a usual Portuguese name in the Macao Grand Prix in recent decades, Célio Alves Dias debuted at the Guide Circuit in 2000 and from then was a frequent presence and no faults in the race until 2023. This year, its objective is to account for its twenty-fifth participation in the biggest sports event of RAEM, but will have to align in the findings.
While awaiting the announcement of the 2025 calendar by AAMC, Célio Alves Dias details details to start his test program, because his Toyota, after being reviewed, "is ready to test" in the interior of China, something that will happen "very soon," says the pilot.
In the last edition of the Grand Prix, Célio Alves Dias qualified in 12th place for the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. However, his participation was short and unhappy: at the wheel of Toyota with dorsal No. 11, was forced to give up after being immobilized on the climb of San Francisco. The Macanese pilot was out of the race on the first lap, in an incident that caused the Safety Car.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:50:53</pubDate></item></channel></rss>