<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Panama | Beijing criticizes economic coercion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/panama-pequim-critica-coercao-economica/</link><description>China yesterday avoided commenting on the deal reached by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison conglomerate to sell its participation in the ports of the Panama channel to the Blackrock US fund, merely rejecting “economic coercion” on the international scene.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning has called on “consultation of the competent Chinese authorities” to obtain specific business details without referring directly to the transaction or reports of a possible Beijing interference to prevent the sale.
But he added that China rejects “economic coercion, hegemony and intimidation” at the international scene. The statements arise in a context of growing tension on the agreement, after criticism spread by a Hong Kong newspaper affiliated with Beijing.
The official portals of the Chinese administration in Macao and Hong Kong released on Friday the comment, widespread by the newspaper Ta Kung Pao, a publication of the former British colony seen as close to Beijing.
The newspaper considered that the deal it transferred to a consortium that includes Blackrock and the Investment Limited Terminal a participation of 80 percent in a set of port subsidiaries, which generate 43 ports in 23 countries, including ports at both ends of the Panama and Cristobal channel, "is not a normal commercial practice."
"Many [Chinese] Internet users have strongly criticized this agreement and CK Hutchison Holdings, considering it as a spineless assignment, aiming only at profit and forgetting justice, ignoring national interests and major national principles, betraying and selling all the Chinese people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:56:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Possession of the new director was held yesterday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/dsal-tomada-de-posse-do-novo-director-realizou-se-ontem/</link><description>The new director of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), Chan Un Tong, and the subdirector, Chan Tze Wai yesterday took an oath at the inauguration ceremony.
The ceremony was chaired by the Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, who expects leaders to “further promote global development of the Macao labor market, protect work rights and interests under the law and build, with new ideas, a harmonious society between employers and workers”.
Dsal's new leader Chan Un Tong indicated to feel “deeply the weight of responsibility and stated that, according to the spirit of President Xi Jinping's important speech, it will persist in the effective resolution of the population -based employment problem and reinforce training resources to form high quality qualified frames for Macao”.
Chan Un Tong has also pledged to improve labor legislation, the creation of harmonious labor relations and to “make efforts to support the development of micro, small and medium enterprises”.
Chan Un Tong began working in the Government of MSAR in 2002, performing between May 2014 and May 2016, the position of Deputy Coordinator of the Human Resources Office, and from May 2016 to date, the position of subdirector of DSAL.
Chan Un Tong has a degree in Economic Law at the Faculty of Economics of the University of Jinan in Guangzhou.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:32:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | José Cesário warns of CTT problems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/eleicoes-jose-cesario-alerta-para-problemas-com-ctt/</link><description>José Cesário, Secretary of State for the Portuguese Communities, defended Radio Macau that the usual conditions in the operation of the elections in Portugal, namely the May 18 legislatures, will occur again due to the functioning of the CTT. For José Cesário, these system conditions will affect the electoral participation of the emigrated Portuguese.
"The Assembly of the Republic has not produced any kind of legislative change that may be considered in a current electoral process. Therefore, if there is no change, the method will be exactly the same," said the official.
In practice, the voter will continue to have to receive the voting report by the mail at the indicated address, then deliver it to the CTT. However, delays in the operation of services or other bureaucracies make it possible to receive the bulletin on time and hours, for example, generating potential increase in abstention.
"We are fully aware that there are very varied difficulties in the domain of the functioning of the post office systems in various countries, and this is a difficult matter to overcome," he said. The Secretary of State hopes that the May Legislative Elections can take place "in the best way possible". "Unfortunately, I know very well that there are countries where the post office works will strongly limit electoral participation," he said.
The problems are of various order and go through situations where "people, for various reasons, or have changed residence, or not voting in several successive elections, may not receive the vote."
The Portuguese again go to elections on May 18 following the lead to the motion of confidence presented by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, in the Assembly of the Republic, leading to the dissolution of Parliament.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:58:02</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC presents “Law themes” by the end of the month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/frc-apresenta-temas-de-direito-ate-final-do-mes/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) promotes today, tomorrow and then next week, on March 26 and 27, at 6.30 pm, a set of lectures on law topics, on the “vicissitudes of the process (I)”, which aims to identify possible incidents in the judicial proceedings and address the respective regimes. The sessions will take place in parallel, in the Portuguese and Chinese languages, coordinated by Teresa Leong.
The sessions are organized by CRED-DM-Center for Reflection, Study and Dissemination of the FRC Macao Law. This cycle of conferences aims to address, in a practical and explanatory way, relevant daily topics of all Macao judicial operators, a project started in previous years and which had great adhesion of the class.
According to Teresa Leong, "the judicial process begins with the dispute and ends with the decision to end this dispute." "If the process follows its normal course, without major starters, justice is naturally served without inconvenience. However, most varied incidents make this difficult, sometimes difficult to achieve. These incidents, in addition to causing some inconvenience to the ongoing process, may even undermine the acts laboriously practiced, including the final decision itself," he explains.
With “process vicissitudes (i)” begins this approach with the analysis of the circumstances in which it can, or has to modify the subjects of a judicial process and their implications for the ongoing process. In the first session, that is, today, it will speak of the “subjective modification: subjective substitution vs. subjective cumulation” and “third party intervention: main intervention”. In the second session, a week later, it will be the turn of the presentation of the module “Third Party Intervention: Accessory Intervention and Opposition”.
The lectures in Portuguese are held today and on March 26, and the counterparts in Chinese are held tomorrow, 20, and March 27, at the FRC gallery.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:52:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate | Room transactions go up. Down prices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/imobiliario-sobem-transaccoes-descem-precos/</link><description>In February, 176 dwellings were purchased and sold at an average of 76,243 patacas per square meter. Compared to what was happening a year ago, prices suffered a 11.6 percent reduction, but 44 transactions were registered
 
Last month, the house price reduced 11.6 percent, compared to the same period, to an average of 76,243 patacas per square meter. The information was released by the Directorate of Finance Services (DSF). In February last year, the average price of the square meter of housing was 86,225 patacas, 9,982 patacas above the latest amounts released on Monday.
However, when the comparison is between January and February this year, the average price of dwellings has a valuation of 6 percent, from 71,917 patacas per square meter to 76,243 patacas per square meter.
At the price level, the reality is now different from what was happening in 2019. Before the pandemic, the average price per square meter was 98,618 patacas, which represents a reduction of 22.7 percent, or 22,375 patacas, compared to the data provided on Monday.
The information about last month shows that Colaane was the most expensive area in the territory, with an average of 83.5 71 patacas per square meter. In the mud, the average price of the square meter was 82,471 patacas, and on the Macao peninsula of 72,986 patacas.
Greater demand
The highest price reduction seems to have resulted in an increase in the number of purchases and housing sales. In February, 176 transactions were reported, 44 more than in the same period, when 132 were accounted for, which means growth of one third.
When the comparison is made between last month and January, there were 94 transactions, a break of 34.8 percent, from 270 purchases and sales to 176 transactions in February.
However, in 2019, before the COVID-19 pandemic, the market was more active than currently happens. In February 2019, 279 transactions were registered, 103 more than last month. However, in terms of the volume of transactions, February 2019 numbers approach the January registration this year.
The latest data also reveals that the Macao Peninsula was the place with the most transactions, a total of 126 housing purchases and sales. In second place comes the mud with 36 transactions and coloane, where 14 purchases and housing sales were registered.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:38:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | Announced new guidelines for filming</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/cinema-anunciadas-novas-orientacoes-para-filmagens/</link><description>The running over 12 people during the recording of a persecution scene will lead the cultural institute to change instructions to filming teams in the territory. Authorities want to have more information about the recorded plans and scenes
 
The president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Deland Leong Wai Man, revealed that new guidelines will be issued for filming teams to work in the territory. The information was revealed yesterday, and appears following a road accident in February during the shooting of a movie.
According to Deland Leong, the different government departments are currently in communication to last the new plans and instructions. From the moment new filming teams want to come to Macau, the instructions will be distributed and will have to be followed.
The new guidelines also predict that production teams have to provide more detailed plans about filming in Macau, with the need to indicate the use of roads, street closure and vehicle driving. From these plans, the authorities will listen to the different departments, such as the Public Security Police Corps and the Traffic Affairs Services Directorate, to ensure that filming take place in a safer and more controlled environment.
To the media, Deland Leong Wai Man argued that following this new method, with more detailed information, the cinema industry will have a healthier development, given the current context.
Suspended shooting
At the same time, the IC official confirmed the maintenance of the suspension order of the film that was the source of an accident with 12 injured, including two 5 and 6 years old children. The accident happened in late February, when a driver lost control of the car while filming a chase scene.
Later, the case gained other dimensions when authorities revealed that the chase scene was being filmed by the interior team on the sidelines of the oriented guidelines.
About this episode, Leong reported that he is still being discussed, so no conclusions can not be issued. However, the official admitted that the hypothesis of canceling the license to record in Macao is on the table, as the team did not follow the initially issued guidelines.
The president of the IC has also been questioned whether the incident can contribute to large productions to avoid the territory. However, Leong dismissed this scenario and pointed out that last year more than 300 outdoor filming teams were in Macao, which said it was the highest number in history. The IC leader also pointed out that Macau is an increasingly attractive destination for movie recording.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:35:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture | Miguel de Senna Fernandes distinguished as ambassador</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/cultura-miguel-de-senna-fernandes-distinguido-como-embaixador/</link><description>The name of Macaense is on a list, with 942 individualities, prepared by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of China. The ambassador has as its functions the promotion and protection of immaterial cultural heritage
 
Miguel de Senna Fernandes was distinguished as Ambassador of National Intangible Cultural Heritage. The list of 942 names was announced on Monday night by China's Ministry of Culture and Tourism.
Since 2021 the theater in Patuá has been part of China's Intangible Cultural Heritage List. Miguel de Senna Fernandes was chosen as an ambassador for his role in the Dóci Papiaçám group, as well as co-founder is the playwright and director.
"I feel very honored and naturally happy. But mainly honored to have been chosen. Now, the responsibility, which was already big, becomes greater," said Senna Fernandes, in statements to HM. "Over these years, I have always had a group of very talented people and this award is theirs. This distinction is not individual, in this kind of things is never an individual work, it is a group work. It was through the group that it was externalized what was created," he added.
According to the official statement of the central government, the figure of the ambassador of National Intangible Cultural Heritage has as its functions to ensure the promotion and protection of cultural heritage. In addition to connecting protected cultural manifestations, the statement indicates that people are chosen for presenting “good morals” and “excellent competence” to protect and ensure the transmission of intangible cultural heritage. “The ambassadors of national immaterial cultural heritage are expected to play an exemplary role, actively perform inheritance activities, cultivation successors and contribute more to the protection of immaterial cultural heritage,” was indicated in the statement with new appointments.
More guarantees
Speaking to HM, Miguel de Senna Fernandes also revealed to see the distinction as a “very important guarantee” for the survival of the theater in Patuá, with the characteristics of the Macaense Theater. "It is a very important guarantee of the survival of theater with all the characteristics that over the years we have been establishing," said the playwright. "When we used to talk to people who did not understand this kind of jokes, humor, we had some reticence.
"The Dóci Papiaçá Group has always presented a satirical theater, which aimed at customs, whatever, with social criticism, derision and curse. It is the history of the maricon theater. The Macaense Theater is this. Of course we can do theater in Patuá, but without these characteristics it may not be a maricon theater," he argued.
Space for the community
Miguel de Senna Fernandes also highlighted the importance of distinction to the community. "It's very good, because at least in this area of ​​culture, the community has a role that is still relevant and this is important," he said. "We are seeing a macao quite different from what it was and in this sea of ​​people, in a kind of culture - the lack of better expression - more monolithic, the theater, the cultural Macaense is relevant is something good for the community and this is important," he said.
The next performance of the Dóci Papiaçá Group is scheduled for May 30 and 31, under the 35th of the Macao Arts Festival, with the name Cuza Tá Reni? (What is going on?, In Portuguese). The play will be presented at the large auditorium of the Macao Cultural Center. Macanese does not risk anticipating that the distinction will reflect on a greater impact on the level of public presence. However, it admits that the expectation of the organization of the festival is a full house.
Dreams for fulfilling
Regarding the future of the theater in Patuá and the Dóci Papiaçám, Senna Fernandes confesses that the “big dream” at this stage is going to return to Portugal to act.
The last time the group acted in Portugal was in 1999, even before the transfer of sovereignty from Macau to China. “The dream is to go to Portugal,” he confessed. "It's a matter of money and logistics. Last year, the choir has been to Portugal, but now we want to take the theater and I'm seriously working on it," he said. "The last time the theater went to Portugal was in 1999. And we have never been there!
However, Portugal is not the only objective. The co-founder also believes that in the future it will be possible to have an action inside China, although admitting that the molds of this performance, despite the will, are not thought out.
Belief and custom
Regarding Macao, besides Miguel de Senna Fernandes, the name of Lo Seng Chung, as Ambassador of the belief and customs of Tou Tei.
The beliefs of Tou Tei concern one of the best known Chinese gods, also called "Tou Tei Kong", "Foc Tac Cheng San" or "Tai Pak Kong". According to the Cultural Institute, it is "one of the most popular Chinese gods" and regarded by believers "as responsible for matters such as the protection of life, the health and wealth of residents, among other aspects."</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:33:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal | Meeting with schools due to subscriptions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/caeal-reuniao-com-escolas-devida-a-recolha-de-assinaturas/</link><description>Allegations that it would have been asked from school teachers managed by associations to collect signatures for the next elections will lead the Electoral Commission to meet with representatives of educational establishments. The commission also received the complaint from an association member who claims to have been required a minimum number of signatures to a list
 
Complaints from alleged school teachers managed by associations they would have been asked to collect signatures to candidate lists to the next legislative elections, scheduled for September 14, were shared on social networks. After yesterday's meeting of the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), the president of the entity, Judge Seng Ioi Man, said he will mark meetings with school representatives in early April to share the values ​​of justice, integrity and equality. In general, the official also indicated that the use of coercion or misleading methods to raise signatures is a crime.
At a press conference held yesterday, the magistrate said that if the investigation confirms the allegations of the teachers, the forms to constitute candidacies will be considered invalid, according to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau.
The interference in the electoral process of schools managed by associations with representation in the Legislative Assembly, and funded by the government, has been a constant in previous suffrage, namely with the request for teachers and employees to sign propositions of candidacies and even guardians. For example, in 2021, a teacher at Choi Nong Chi Tai School, linked to the Macao Workers' Associations Federation (Faom), will have appealed to in charge of signing documents from the application committees for legislative elections.
In the suffrage of 2017, there were also similar complaints, without repercussions for the lists involved.
In the chapter of the repercussions, the president of Caeal was asked yesterday about the possibility that disqualified candidates could or may not submit candidates in these elections, which are the first after the exclusion of five lists and 21 candidates, most of the pro-democracy field, in 2021. Without responding directly to the issue, Seng Ioi Man recalled that, according to the electoral law, who does not support the basic law and not loyal to law. Manda is away from the elections for five years.
Track
Regarding the suspicions that an elderly woman was invited to sign a candidacy report to legislative elections when exchanging the Macau Pass card to the elderly, the president of Caeal revealed that the case was investigated, but it was not possible to collect concrete information.
In addition, Caeal will have received the complaint from an association member who was responsible for collecting a certain number of signatures to a list. Seng Ioi Man has assured that he will follow this case. The official stressed that anyone who helps raise support to form a list for the elections must sign the appointment form and provide assistance voluntarily and clearly. In addition, Caeal's president reiterated that list leaders or campaign organizers cannot resort to coercion, fraud, professional pressure or promises of benefits to influence voters to support a particular list, either through vote or signature to constitute a candidate list.
For now, nine CAEAL forms were requested for constitutions of lists for legislative elections, but none have been delivered. The deadline for presenting the application commissions ends on June 6.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:30:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby Hui, President of the Macao Autism Association: “Autism differs from person to person”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/ruby-hui-presidente-da-associacao-de-autismo-de-macau-autismo-difere-de-pessoa-para-pessoa/</link><description>Created in 2012, the Macao Autism Association continues to fight for more care for children and young people with this development disturbance. But the association's president, Ruby Hui, warns of the need for more incisive policies for adolescents and their specific needs, especially in access to employment
 
 
What balance does the work done by the association in recent years?
My work is above all to establish a connection with all the entities and resources made available by the government and also the game industry, as the authorities have started to [the context of the new game concession contracts] that develop more social support activities. Therefore, we have gathered all these resources to organize recreational activities for children and youth. In addition, we organize therapy sessions for our members. Usually, we request financial support from private companies and the government, covering 30 to 50 percent of these expenses.
The support of the game sector is therefore quite important.
Yes, but it has not really been a great support. For example, the government covers part of our monthly expenses, about 40,000 patacas. But this amount comes only to hire two full -time employees and one part -time employee. They are the ones who organize all activities, deal with the bureaucratic part, which includes the presentation of many reports to the government, because we ask for subsidies for almost half of our expenses.
Therefore, do you consider that they need more support from the executive to be able to hire more professionals?
Yes, it would be ideal. Associations like ours are getting bigger and the children we support are growing. I would say that 60 percent of our members are 11 or more, and about 20 percent are even larger, over 14 years old. We have to think about their future and the needs of therapy and treatment for adolescents, as it is not only small kids who need therapies such as speech or occupational therapy. They are young people who are still in high school and need to acquire different types of social skills, boys need to know how to deal with girls and vice versa. Then, when they become adults, they need to know how to deal with bosses in jobs. There are many valences to explore, but at this moment I would say that the supports are not enough.
Are schools not yet prepared to receive these students, for example?
Autism may be different from person to person. Students with autism, but who have better learning skills, are in normal schools. But parents tell me that there are not enough teachers with certain skills to deal with and teach these children. There are teachers who still have a very traditional mindset to treat these young people, who often have to deal with alone with bullying, for example. I would say that there are many children and young people with autism with psychological problems because of the school.
When it speaks of the traditional mindset, what does this mean in concrete?
In the case of my son, for example, he is obliged to always be sitting at school, but often likes to move and get up from his chair. From the point of view of parents who have children with this problem, there would be no problem, as long as it did not bother others, but for teachers it cannot be, and complain. They say things of the genre: "He will beat the table, he will move the painting, makes a lot of noise." Every day I receive complaints from parents to connect with the school, and for small situations like this.
What are the main difficulties or challenges that Macao families face when they deal with an autistic child?
In my case, my family is middle class, and we are financially well. But when my son was younger needed to do therapy and it was very expensive. Now these therapies cost even more. At the time my son was in primary education, 600 to 700 patacas was paid for each therapy session, but there are days a father told me that the sessions now cost about 1000 patacas per class, which is very expensive. Families of lower social classes cannot afford. Therefore, this support is one of the great objectives of our association, raising money so that we can provide explanations, therapy sessions or other type of support. All so that our members can attend classes with 50 percent discount, where the association pays half the amount.
When the association was created, what were its main objectives?
In 2012 autism was not a very spoken theme. Therefore, we joined [some parents and families] and we started to ask for support from the government and try to draw attention to the subject. We got some things because the government now gives more support to these young people, at least for those under 12. The problem we feel is that these young people are growing and adolescents need other types of supports that do not exist.
What is necessary to change in mindsets and society in relation to autism?
In Macao there are not many companies willing to hire young people with autism. Situation that is not seen in Hong Kong, where there are several hiring programs with social companies. Macau needs to follow this path.
One day in Rio
World Autism Consciousness Day is celebrated on April 2 and, in this context, the Macao Autism Association joined Sands China for a series of activities with children and parents, which took place last March 10th. Through the program “Sands Care”, the game operator provided a visit to the exhibition “Coastal Fantasia”, with the figure of “King Lobster”, a creation of Philip Colbert artist ” A boat trip through the Delta of the Pearl River.
In total, 70 people participated. Quoted by a game operator statement, Ruby Hoi said the tour "allowed children to enjoy the maximum of the trip." "Thank you for all the support provided to people with autism in Macau, and I hope that all sectors of society can continue to support the development of these people and promote their inclusion in society," he said.
For the game operator, this type of events can help “reinforce the cohesion of families dealing with autism, but also promote the awareness of society and support for the community of people with autism fostering a more inclusive and supportive social environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Panama | Beijing criticizes economic coercion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/panama-pequim-critica-coercao-economica/</link><description>China yesterday avoided commenting on the deal reached by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison conglomerate to sell its participation in the ports of the Panama channel to the Blackrock US fund, merely rejecting “economic coercion” on the international scene.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning has called on “consultation of the competent Chinese authorities” to obtain specific business details without referring directly to the transaction or reports of a possible Beijing interference to prevent the sale.
But he added that China rejects “economic coercion, hegemony and intimidation” at the international scene. The statements arise in a context of growing tension on the agreement, after criticism spread by a Hong Kong newspaper affiliated with Beijing.
The official portals of the Chinese administration in Macao and Hong Kong released on Friday the comment, widespread by the newspaper Ta Kung Pao, a publication of the former British colony seen as close to Beijing.
The newspaper considered that the deal it transferred to a consortium that includes Blackrock and the Investment Limited Terminal a participation of 80 percent in a set of port subsidiaries, which generate 43 ports in 23 countries, including ports at both ends of the Panama and Cristobal channel, "is not a normal commercial practice."
"Many [Chinese] Internet users have strongly criticized this agreement and CK Hutchison Holdings, considering it as a spineless assignment, aiming only at profit and forgetting justice, ignoring national interests and major national principles, betraying and selling all the Chinese people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:56:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Possession of the new director was held yesterday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/dsal-tomada-de-posse-do-novo-director-realizou-se-ontem/</link><description>The new director of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), Chan Un Tong, and the subdirector, Chan Tze Wai yesterday took an oath at the inauguration ceremony.
The ceremony was chaired by the Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, who expects leaders to “further promote global development of the Macao labor market, protect work rights and interests under the law and build, with new ideas, a harmonious society between employers and workers”.
Dsal's new leader Chan Un Tong indicated to feel “deeply the weight of responsibility and stated that, according to the spirit of President Xi Jinping's important speech, it will persist in the effective resolution of the population -based employment problem and reinforce training resources to form high quality qualified frames for Macao”.
Chan Un Tong has also pledged to improve labor legislation, the creation of harmonious labor relations and to “make efforts to support the development of micro, small and medium enterprises”.
Chan Un Tong began working in the Government of MSAR in 2002, performing between May 2014 and May 2016, the position of Deputy Coordinator of the Human Resources Office, and from May 2016 to date, the position of subdirector of DSAL.
Chan Un Tong has a degree in Economic Law at the Faculty of Economics of the University of Jinan in Guangzhou.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:32:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | José Cesário warns of CTT problems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/eleicoes-jose-cesario-alerta-para-problemas-com-ctt/</link><description>José Cesário, Secretary of State for the Portuguese Communities, defended Radio Macau that the usual conditions in the operation of the elections in Portugal, namely the May 18 legislatures, will occur again due to the functioning of the CTT. For José Cesário, these system conditions will affect the electoral participation of the emigrated Portuguese.
"The Assembly of the Republic has not produced any kind of legislative change that may be considered in a current electoral process. Therefore, if there is no change, the method will be exactly the same," said the official.
In practice, the voter will continue to have to receive the voting report by the mail at the indicated address, then deliver it to the CTT. However, delays in the operation of services or other bureaucracies make it possible to receive the bulletin on time and hours, for example, generating potential increase in abstention.
"We are fully aware that there are very varied difficulties in the domain of the functioning of the post office systems in various countries, and this is a difficult matter to overcome," he said. The Secretary of State hopes that the May Legislative Elections can take place "in the best way possible". "Unfortunately, I know very well that there are countries where the post office works will strongly limit electoral participation," he said.
The problems are of various order and go through situations where "people, for various reasons, or have changed residence, or not voting in several successive elections, may not receive the vote."
The Portuguese again go to elections on May 18 following the lead to the motion of confidence presented by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, in the Assembly of the Republic, leading to the dissolution of Parliament.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:58:02</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC presents “Law themes” by the end of the month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/frc-apresenta-temas-de-direito-ate-final-do-mes/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) promotes today, tomorrow and then next week, on March 26 and 27, at 6.30 pm, a set of lectures on law topics, on the “vicissitudes of the process (I)”, which aims to identify possible incidents in the judicial proceedings and address the respective regimes. The sessions will take place in parallel, in the Portuguese and Chinese languages, coordinated by Teresa Leong.
The sessions are organized by CRED-DM-Center for Reflection, Study and Dissemination of the FRC Macao Law. This cycle of conferences aims to address, in a practical and explanatory way, relevant daily topics of all Macao judicial operators, a project started in previous years and which had great adhesion of the class.
According to Teresa Leong, "the judicial process begins with the dispute and ends with the decision to end this dispute." "If the process follows its normal course, without major starters, justice is naturally served without inconvenience. However, most varied incidents make this difficult, sometimes difficult to achieve. These incidents, in addition to causing some inconvenience to the ongoing process, may even undermine the acts laboriously practiced, including the final decision itself," he explains.
With “process vicissitudes (i)” begins this approach with the analysis of the circumstances in which it can, or has to modify the subjects of a judicial process and their implications for the ongoing process. In the first session, that is, today, it will speak of the “subjective modification: subjective substitution vs. subjective cumulation” and “third party intervention: main intervention”. In the second session, a week later, it will be the turn of the presentation of the module “Third Party Intervention: Accessory Intervention and Opposition”.
The lectures in Portuguese are held today and on March 26, and the counterparts in Chinese are held tomorrow, 20, and March 27, at the FRC gallery.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:52:44</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Arte Gongbi, from Zou Li, to be seen until April 5</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/frc-arte-gongbi-de-zou-li-para-ser-vista-ate-5-de-abril/</link><description>“Burning Like a Lotus” is the name of the new exhibition patent at the Rui Cunha Foundation until April 5th. This is an opportunity to get to know the Gongbi Art Gender, with works by Zou Li. Gongbi Art is known for the extreme detail painting with fine brushes
 
Since this Tuesday there is a new show to visit in the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery (FRC). This is “Burning Like a Lotus”, by artist Zou Li, which is an example of the Gongbi art genre, characterized by the use of the traditional thin and delicate brush technique, about Japanese rice role, silk fabric or oriental silk fans.
Zou Li is considered "a renowned painter with more than fifty years of career and experience, whose artistic focus is mostly around themes related to the history of Chinese women." The three dozen works now exhibited at the HRF were held between 1997 and 2022.
In the artist's work there is a “awareness of femininity through his extraordinary artistic expression”, being present in the creations “harmonious and moving of the beauty of the body and soul of women”, according to a FRC note, Ung Si Meng, honorary president of the Association for Friendship and Coordination of former Macao's Chinese Popular Advisory Conference.
It is also described that "for a long time, and to fulfill his social responsibilities and his vocation as a professional painter, Zou Li actively participated in several important historical creations."
It is the scroll roll entitled “Imperatriz Wu Zetian” or the “Hundred Chinese Concubin Images” collection. Ung Si Meng also described Zou Li as "widely recognized and appreciated by experts, academics, colleagues and the Chinese artistic society."
Large
Also according to the same note, it refers that Zou Li's works “reflect the dimension of his academic and artistic knowledge, which have already attracted the wide attention of national and international artistic circles”.
In addition, "his works have been much appreciated by art galleries, museums, art institutions, public and private, and collectors." Zou Li has created, throughout his career, more than a thousand works, as well as more than fifty individual exhibitions, in his country and abroad, having also published more than ten individual art catalogs. Recently, in April 2024, the National Museum of Women and Children of China acquired a collection of 593 of his pieces.
Zou Li is a member of the China Artists Association, a researcher at the Wenshi Research Hall of the Guangdong Popular Government, director of the Guangdong Province Institute of Chinese Painting and honorary president of the Foshan Artists Association. In the past, he performed the functions of deputy director of the southern branch of the China Central and History Institute of Culture and History, where he also did research work.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:51:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says Chinese president visits Washington in a “not too distant future”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/trump-diz-que-presidente-chines-visita-washington-num-futuro-nao-muito-distante/</link><description>US President Donald Trump said on Monday that his Chinese counterpart Xi Jinping will visit Washington in a "not too distant future" in the face of the growing commercial tensions between the world's two largest economies due to the imposition of tariffs.
"This will happen in the not too distant future," Trump said to journalists during a meeting of the new Kennedy Center board, a famous cultural center of the capital Washington.
The US head of state also noted that senior Chinese government officials, “below” XI, will soon visit the US capital, although it has not advanced names or details about possible dates.
Trump mentioned Xi's visit when he said he received visits from foreign leaders in the White House in recent weeks and asked them how Washington was. The Republican stressed that he is “cleaning Washington”, including trying to clean tents used by homeless and graphitis.
Last week the US media had reported that Washington and Beijing began discussions about a summit between the leaders of both countries in June.
The Chinese press had already suggested the possibility of a meeting in April. Also the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper has advanced that Trump could move to China in April to meet Chinese homologist Xi Jinping.
Since the Republican's victory in US presidentials in November that Trump and Xi have expressed interest in holding a summit.
Open future
Since Trump's inauguration in January, US administration has threatened, and then suspended customs rates about Mexico and Canada, while committing to punish Europe and other business partners as well.
So far, China is the only country that has effectively faced widespread increases in Trump's rates decided.
The White House has imposed additional 20 percent rates on all goods from China, citing the role of the Asian country in the US Fentanil crisis. Beijing retaliated quickly at his own rates, adapting the answer to avoid climbing the tensions.
Other actions that are being considered by the Trump business team include restricting Chinese investment in the US and US investment in China, aiming at China-dominated industries such as shipbuilding, and further limiting the sale of high-tech products to Chinese companies.
Trump and Xi had already talked by telephone in January, days before the inauguration of the American for his second term, in a conversation in which they discussed business relations and the future in the United States of the Chinese company by the company bytedance.
Donald Trump said he was open to negotiating a new trade agreement with China and praised Xi repeatedly.
The two leaders reached an agreement in 2020 to end the trade war that harmed both economies. However, bilateral relations deteriorated with the covid-19 pandemic, which Trump attributed to China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:47:28</pubDate></item><item><title>World Games | Special Olympics Macau win four gold medals</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/jogos-mundiais-special-olympics-macau-conquistam-quatro-medalhas-de-ouro/</link><description>The Special Olympics Macao Movement entourage has won 14 medals, including four gold at the Winter Games for people with intellectual disabilities in Italy. In a statement, the movement stressed that the entourage had only eight athletes, and “for most of them” was the first time they competed in the world winter games.
This is because the latest edition of the competition, which was scheduled to take place in 2022 in Kazan, Russia, was initially postponed due to Covid - 12 pandemic and then canceled due to the Russian invasion of Ukraine.
The star of the Macao entourage was the 18 -year -old Chio Hao Law, who won two gold medals on the 100 -meter and 200 meters of snow races. In September, Chio was Macao's first athlete to compete in the Paralympic Games, finally ending the length heel race for athletes with intellectual disabilities in Paris2024.
Also in the Snow Race, 17 -year -old Huang Hou won a gold medal in the 200 meter race and one bronze in 100 meters. The other gold medal for Macao was for Sou Fai in the 500 -meter race in the speed skating. The 25 -year -old athlete also got a silver medal in the thousand meters race.
In the dance modality, the territory won two bronze medals in the individual race and two more medals in the mixed peer race, thanks to Chang Chak Kuan, 19, and Lam Cheng I, 16. The Turin2025 Winter Games took place between 8 and 15 March, with the participation of more than two thousand athletes from 103 countries.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:44:24</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Chen Jiru (1558-1639), the painter who wanted to be free from the ties of court staff to devote himself to knowing everything around him and pronounce independently, was therefore called the "Great Chancellor of the Mountains", the space where there are always new perspectives for the look and there are no cities limits.
Referring to the works that circulated among the collectors and lovers of his friend's paintings, the influential thinker of Huating (current Songjiang, Shanghai) Dong Qichang (1555-1636) had said without fate that "less than one in ten" of the paintings that were attributed to him would effectively works of his brush.
This will not be admired given the multiplicity of tasks required by a man of culture at the end of the Ming Dynasty and which, in his case, included the demonstration of his theories in caligraffes and paintings.
The names of some painters are known, which helped him in this function from the knowledge of the history of painting, studied in his valuable collection, such as his friend Zhao Zuo (C.1570- After 1630) or Shen Shichong (Act.C.1602-41).
The latter also originally from Huating, he would recreate an album of 1625, twelve perspectives from the Lejiao Yuan Private Garden, "Pleasures of the suburbs" of the distinguished painter Wang Shimin (1592-1680), where he has realized the eloquence of certain figures placed in favorable places.
The creation of gardens, Zaoyuan, a privileged space for the exercise of subjectivity, one of the activities to which the intellectuals were dedicated, had the prestige associated with the Zaowu or Zaohua expressions, the "creator of strength" or "transformation" used in Zhuangzi, with intrinsic affinities to the painter's or man of letters.
As Qi Baojia wrote (1602-1645) creating a garden is like “the painting of a great artist: not a single uninspirated brushstroke is allowed; just as a careful author writing: not a distant word is authorized.
Shen Shichong would make it in its own name, several paintings affirming its relationship with free space for walking, in a style that takes advantage of the abstract forms of Dong Qichang mountains with the nebula atmosphere and the noted spatial recession between professional painters.
Long horizontal rollers, exemplary of these characteristics are the landscape paintings of the four stations (Shangao Shuifang, High Mountains, Long Rivers, Ink and Paper Color, 28.6 x 761 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts of Boston) or the one that is considered his masterpiece, Tianxia Diyi, "first under the sky". Today known as mountain retreat (ink and color on paper, 33 x 1527 cm, for sale at Christies) in it are visible you are visible, bridges over the rivers, pines and walkers fearless in the fimbrias of the mountains in a figuration of the playful determination of its own time.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Chen Jiru (1558-1639), the painter who wanted to be free from the ties of court staff to devote himself to knowing everything around him and pronounce independently, was therefore called the "Great Chancellor of the Mountains", the space where there are always new perspectives for the look and there are no cities limits.
Referring to the works that circulated among the collectors and lovers of his friend's paintings, the influential thinker of Huating (current Songjiang, Shanghai) Dong Qichang (1555-1636) had said without fate that "less than one in ten" of the paintings that were attributed to him would effectively works of his brush.
This will not be admired given the multiplicity of tasks required by a man of culture at the end of the Ming Dynasty and which, in his case, included the demonstration of his theories in caligraffes and paintings.
The names of some painters are known, which helped him in this function from the knowledge of the history of painting, studied in his valuable collection, such as his friend Zhao Zuo (C.1570- After 1630) or Shen Shichong (Act.C.1602-41).
The latter also originally from Huating, he would recreate an album of 1625, twelve perspectives from the Lejiao Yuan Private Garden, "Pleasures of the suburbs" of the distinguished painter Wang Shimin (1592-1680), where he has realized the eloquence of certain figures placed in favorable places.
The creation of gardens, Zaoyuan, a privileged space for the exercise of subjectivity, one of the activities to which the intellectuals were dedicated, had the prestige associated with the Zaowu or Zaohua expressions, the "creator of strength" or "transformation" used in Zhuangzi, with intrinsic affinities to the painter's or man of letters.
As Qi Baojia wrote (1602-1645) creating a garden is like “the painting of a great artist: not a single uninspirated brushstroke is allowed; just as a careful author writing: not a distant word is authorized.
Shen Shichong would make it in its own name, several paintings affirming its relationship with free space for walking, in a style that takes advantage of the abstract forms of Dong Qichang mountains with the nebula atmosphere and the noted spatial recession between professional painters.
Long horizontal rollers, exemplary of these characteristics are the landscape paintings of the four stations (Shangao Shuifang, High Mountains, Long Rivers, Ink and Paper Color, 28.6 x 761 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts of Boston) or the one that is considered his masterpiece, Tianxia Diyi, "first under the sky". Today known as mountain retreat (ink and color on paper, 33 x 1527 cm, for sale at Christies) in it are visible you are visible, bridges over the rivers, pines and walkers fearless in the fimbrias of the mountains in a figuration of the playful determination of its own time.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>José Cesário, Secretary of State for the Portuguese Communities, defended Radio Macau that the usual conditions in the operation of the elections in Portugal, namely the May 18 legislatures, will occur again due to the functioning of the CTT. For José Cesário, these system conditions will affect the electoral participation of the emigrated Portuguese.
"The Assembly of the Republic has not produced any kind of legislative change that may be considered in a current electoral process. Therefore, if there is no change, the method will be exactly the same," said the official.
In practice, the voter will continue to have to receive the voting report by the mail at the indicated address, then deliver it to the CTT. However, delays in the operation of services or other bureaucracies make it possible to receive the bulletin on time and hours, for example, generating potential increase in abstention.
"We are fully aware that there are very varied difficulties in the domain of the functioning of the post office systems in various countries, and this is a difficult matter to overcome," he said. The Secretary of State hopes that the May Legislative Elections can take place "in the best way possible". "Unfortunately, I know very well that there are countries where the post office works will strongly limit electoral participation," he said.
The problems are of various order and go through situations where "people, for various reasons, or have changed residence, or not voting in several successive elections, may not receive the vote."
The Portuguese again go to elections on May 18 following the lead to the motion of confidence presented by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, in the Assembly of the Republic, leading to the dissolution of Parliament.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>José Cesário, Secretary of State for the Portuguese Communities, defended Radio Macau that the usual conditions in the operation of the elections in Portugal, namely the May 18 legislatures, will occur again due to the functioning of the CTT. For José Cesário, these system conditions will affect the electoral participation of the emigrated Portuguese.
"The Assembly of the Republic has not produced any kind of legislative change that may be considered in a current electoral process. Therefore, if there is no change, the method will be exactly the same," said the official.
In practice, the voter will continue to have to receive the voting report by the mail at the indicated address, then deliver it to the CTT. However, delays in the operation of services or other bureaucracies make it possible to receive the bulletin on time and hours, for example, generating potential increase in abstention.
"We are fully aware that there are very varied difficulties in the domain of the functioning of the post office systems in various countries, and this is a difficult matter to overcome," he said. The Secretary of State hopes that the May Legislative Elections can take place "in the best way possible". "Unfortunately, I know very well that there are countries where the post office works will strongly limit electoral participation," he said.
The problems are of various order and go through situations where "people, for various reasons, or have changed residence, or not voting in several successive elections, may not receive the vote."
The Portuguese again go to elections on May 18 following the lead to the motion of confidence presented by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, in the Assembly of the Republic, leading to the dissolution of Parliament.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>José Cesário, Secretary of State for the Portuguese Communities, defended Radio Macau that the usual conditions in the operation of the elections in Portugal, namely the May 18 legislatures, will occur again due to the functioning of the CTT. For José Cesário, these system conditions will affect the electoral participation of the emigrated Portuguese.
"The Assembly of the Republic has not produced any kind of legislative change that may be considered in a current electoral process. Therefore, if there is no change, the method will be exactly the same," said the official.
In practice, the voter will continue to have to receive the voting report by the mail at the indicated address, then deliver it to the CTT. However, delays in the operation of services or other bureaucracies make it possible to receive the bulletin on time and hours, for example, generating potential increase in abstention.
"We are fully aware that there are very varied difficulties in the domain of the functioning of the post office systems in various countries, and this is a difficult matter to overcome," he said. The Secretary of State hopes that the May Legislative Elections can take place "in the best way possible". "Unfortunately, I know very well that there are countries where the post office works will strongly limit electoral participation," he said.
The problems are of various order and go through situations where "people, for various reasons, or have changed residence, or not voting in several successive elections, may not receive the vote."
The Portuguese again go to elections on May 18 following the lead to the motion of confidence presented by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, in the Assembly of the Republic, leading to the dissolution of Parliament.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>IC | Launched book on the historical roots of Rua das Estlagês</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/ic-lancado-livro-sobre-as-raizes-historicas-da-rua-das-estalagens/</link><description>“In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Street of Estalagins” is the name of the work Bilingual, launched in digital format, which tells the story of this historic street of Macao, revealing the business that survived the passage of time. Production was in charge of the Macao Artists Society, with the support of the Cultural Institute and Sands China
 
The history serpes through the stalage street since the end of the nineteenth century. The narrow artery has always been the scene of an intense social and commercial rebolement and it was where Sun Yat-Sen, considered the father of modern China and the Republican Revolution, opened pharmacies and drugstores, especially from 1893. Over the years, Rua das Estalagem, in Porto, was a living example of commerce, and the Portuguese governors were progressively expanding the street, composed of the street Chinese -style buildings and temples, such as the Temple of the Bazaar and Goddess Temple NOVA WO.
All these pieces of history are now counting on the digital publication “In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Rua das Estlagês”, a work produced by the Society of Macao Artists and authored by Siguo Chen in Shirley Lule's texts and illustrations. Those responsible for the edition are the Cultural Institute (IC) and the game operator Sands China.
According to a press release of Sands China, the book, in Chinese and English, intends to “highlight the fascinating past of the historic Macau Street and the beauty of its legacy”, containing interviews with street -related figures, whether merchants or residents. Thus, it is intended to bring “residents and visitors to rediscover the preciousness of the centenary stores and the cultural heritage of the street through legendary stories” so that they can “widen their understanding of the transformation of the neighborhood and its inhabitants”.
The content of the book results from “close conversations with representatives of associations, business entities and residents of the neighborhood,” having dozens of oral stories that can easily be lost if not recorded. This work is not closed in the digital world, having been printed to appear in the public libraries of Macao and schools, in order to “promote the meaning of cultural heritage and enhance mutual ties among the people of Macao”, intending to be “a valuable community resource to deepen the understanding and appreciation of Macao and the street”.
200 years of history
One of the highlights given in the book is to the textile sector that has always predominated on Rua das Estlagenas. In the chapter entitled "Two Centuries of Prosperity: Spinning A Legacy in the Textiles Trade" [two centuries of prosperity: the construction of a legacy in the textile trade], it is read that "Street of Estlagins has always been a center for the textile industry." In the years when the textile sector had a larger presence in the territory, between the 70's and 90's, "Rua housed more than 20 stores with factory products, including three spaces from the Veng On Farm Store." “Around 30 businesses related to these stores, such as tailors, clothing stores, western products and funeral ornament stores, which brought a reputation to the street,” he reads. In Rua das Estlagenas “Tissue trade is over 200 years old,” says the same text.
Other chapters of the book speak of the presence of the republican revolutionary in Macao in “The Starting Point of Sun Yat-Sen’s Story” [The Starting Point of the story of Sun Yat-Sen] or stories of street-linked personalities and their commerce.
In the conclusion of the work, it refers that after the transition, the street "faced new challenges: the global financial crisis, the SARS epidemic, the COVID-19, and the uncertainty of the economy, leaving the need for renewal again."
“In the past, the business has flourished, by themselves, thanks to hard work and resilience. But nowadays the community joins with a shared view, planning in an active way [the development of the street] with the support of the Macao government and the integrated resort companies.
Institutional view
IC President Deland Leong Wai Man pointed out that the book results from the “weighted effort to widen the discussion around preservation and revitalization [of the street],” according to the same press release. "Street renewal is expected to inspire more people to learn about the historic neighborhoods of Macao and participate in their preservation, combining ideas and resources to ensure that the city's culture and history continue to prosper during generations," he said.
In turn, Wilfred Wong, CEO of Sands China, argued that "Street of Estalagues is a microcosm of Macao itself, a place where a rich story meets a modern future."
"The walls of their alleys witnessed the transformation of Macao, and their stories and people deserve to be remembered, as they are precious sources of the Macao cultural heritage. Our effort to publish the book was possible thanks to the collaboration of our local team to conduct interviews with owners of historical stores, create illustrations and photographs, among other works," he said.
New facades
It is recalled that this publication arises after the Government was announced by the Sands performance at the Rua das Estalagens Revitalization Plan, namely with the “Entrepreneurs Recruitment Program for Rua das Estlagês”, launched in April last year.
The game operator explains that the seven businesses selected for the initiative “have been opening through phases, bringing energy to the zone along with other new businesses, providing a platform for young ambitious entrepreneurs to realize their dreams”.
In addition, the game operator intends to revitalize stores' façades “with drawings that enhance their characteristics, resonating the history of the street and the city”. For this initiative, Sands has also collaborated with the Macao Artist Society, and the drawings will be created by two young local artists, Chek On Law and Sit Kat Kit.
"The aim is that, with a collective effort like this, the community can rediscover the history of the street and learn about its past stories and stores through the visual interpretations of these local artists from Macao and their perceptions of the territory," he reads.
Siguo Chen, the book's author, is a veteran journalist with a career of over 60 years who has been deeply linked to the media area in Macau and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 01:50:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Sun Yat-Sen | Marked centenary of the death of the “father of modern China”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/13/sun-yat-sen-assinalado-centenario-da-morte-do-pai-da-china-moderna/</link><description>Sun Yat-Sen died on March 12, 1925. Unavoidable figure in the political history of modern China and the father of the movement that led to the fall of the imperial regime, Sun Yat-Sen was celebrated yesterday in Guangzhou, where he was born, Beijing and Taiwan
 
The first president of China post-imperial and considered the father of the country's modern era, Sun Yat-Sen, was remembered yesterday in mainland China and Taiwan, the 100th anniversary of his death.
In Beijing, there was a “brief and solemn ceremony” of honor to Sun in Beijing Park that has its name. Authorities and “people from all the sectors of society” were present, kept silence and made three venias in front of their statue, the Xinhua official news agency said.
The Chinese Academy of History praised the political figure in his Weibo account, describing him as "a great national hero, a great patriot and a major precursor of the Democratic Revolution of China."
The city of Guangzhou, the capital of Guangdong Province, where Sun Yat-Sen was born, inaugurated on Tuesday an exhibition of old objects related to the man who was one of the promoters of the revolution that overthrew the Qing Dynasty (1644-1911). The Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Building in the city welcomed the first performance of a musical based on the revolutionary's youth.
In Guangzhou, where there is also a university named Sun Yat-Sen, this exhibition is exhibited, which includes objects such as the Sun Yat-Sen Graduation Exam report at the College of Medicine for Chinese, in Hong Kong, from 1892. The certificate of marriage between Sun Yat-Sen and Soong Ching-Ling is also highlighted in 1915, a woman later, woman later, Vice-President of China during the government of Mao Tse-Tung, embracing communism. In the same exhibition you can also see the bronze bust of Sun Yat-Sem itself, made by order of the Japanese friend Umeya Shokichi in 1929.
The "father" of modern China was also remembered in Taiwan, with a ceremony by the Sun Yat-sen memorial in Taipei, where flowers were deposited and express respect.
Double memories
Despite founding, in 1919, the Kuomitang, which would become the main rival of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Sun is remembered in both mainland China and Taiwan. The Board of State's Taiwan Cabinet stated that Sun Yat-Sen “sought China's national unity and revitalization throughout his life,” appealing at the same time to the “compatriots of Taiwan to join us in the inheritance of his legacy” and to “oppose secession” of the island.
Born in 1866, Sun studied medicine in Hong Kong - then a British colony - and, after leading several revolts, gained notoriety as a revolutionary leader and as a driving force of an attempt to modernize the country.
In 1911, the Xinhai Revolution led to the fall of the Qing and Sun Yat-Sen dynasty was appointed provisional president of the New Republic of China in January 1912, but quickly gave power to the country's main military leader, Yuan Shikai, who, far from consolidating republican ideals, dissolved the parliament in 1914 and proclaimed herself in 1915, annulling Grande, annul Part of the democratic progress by which Sun had fought.
From then on, he continued to promote his ideal of a unified and republican China, reorganizing the KMT and seeking international support for his cause. In 1923, he established an alliance with the newly founded CCP and received the support of the Soviet Union to reinforce the political movement. However, he failed to consolidate a stable government before his death in 1925.
A LIFE OF FIGHT
In the work “Sisters Soong-the oldest, younger and redest,” by Jung Chang, some details of Sun Yat-Sen's life are described before embracing the revolutionary cause and the way he left his parents' house in Guangzhou, looking for a better life.
The place of destination was Hawaii, which on July 4, 1894 declared itself as a Republic, an event that, according to the book, "helped shape today's China." “A 27-year-old radical Chinese, Sun Yat-sen, landed in the archipelago and entered a world where the word 'republic' was in every mouth,” he is described.
In China, the agitation against the power of the empire became strong. The Republic "was a new concept," for "the monarchy was the only political system that China knew." "At the time, the country was governed by the Manchu dynasty," the Manchus "were not natural from China, but they had conquered the territory in the mid -seventeenth century." "Since they did not get more than one percent of the population, they were considered a minority of foreign rulers and had never been lacking opposition from the native rebels Han. Sun was one of them," he describes in the same work.
Sun Yat-Sen was "a low, dark man with well-proposed and pleasant traits." Its home village, Cuiheng, had soils inappropriate for agriculture, which provided “a life of extreme misery” to those who lived there. As such, the revolutionary's family did not escape adverse conditions.
In his first escape from the context of poverty, Sun went to Hong Kong, finding shelter to the diocesan school and boys orphanage, then accepted a marriage arranged by the family as a gimmick to return to the village. Sun Yat-Sen married Mu-Zhen, had children, but was an absent figure and something carefree in the face of family responsibilities, traveling the world to seek support for the revolution he wanted for China.
A obra de Jung Chang descreve como o percurso de Sun se ligou ao pai das “três irmãs”, Ei-ling, May-ling e Ching-ling. Charlie Soong funded and supported Sun Yat-Sen in her revolutionary causes, one of her daughters, Ei-Ling, became the republican secretary. This, although married, had made attempts to approach loving and EI-Ling, but eventually had a relationship with Ching-Ling, who was nationalist, but later embraced communism, being known as the "red sister." Ching-ling was also known as the Madame Sun Yat-Sen, but at the time of Sun Yat-Sen's death, the relationship between them had cooled.
After the establishment of the Popular Republic of China, Ching-Ling was vice president of the country, between 1949 and 1954, and then between 1959 and 1975, and was vice president of the Permanent Commission of the National Assembly.
Passage through macau
Moreover, Sun Yat-Sen's life crossed Macao several times, where he lived a short time, unlike his woman, Mu-Zhen, and the children who remained in the territory longer. To remember the short period in which the Republican lived in the territory, at the time under Portuguese administration, the memorial house of dr. Sun Yat-Sen, where he "witnesses the short but significant stay in Macao in the early twentieth century when, running away from the power of imperial mandarins, tried to move his supporters forces in order to implement a new regime in China." “In Macau received support from some friends who were illustrious and influential figures of social and political life at the time,” reads the description of the museum.
Another interesting detail of the 1911 Republican Revolution is the proximity of dates against the establishment of the Republic in Portugal, which took place on October 5, 1910. Macau, in the midst of events in China and Portugal, was only aware that the constitutional monarchy had fallen into Lisbon thanks to the sending of a telegram published in an official bulletin on October 10, 1910, changing the governor in this context. Lame</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 01:04:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Clinical Psychology | The benefits and risks of the introduction of AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/12/psicologia-clinica-os-beneficios-e-riscos-da-introducao-da-ia/</link><description>Artificial intelligence is there to stay and its use in the field of psychology begins to be spoken. Recently, Deputy Lam Lon Wai defended its use and, in Portugal, the Order of Psychologists created the “PSIA” platform, which allows it to detect symptoms. Nuno Gomes and Goreti Lima, two resident therapists, talk about the benefits, risks and potential uses of technology
 
Understanding whether emotions can result in psychological forum diseases is something that is already possible to do using Artificial Intelligence (AI). The issue begins to discuss in Macao still shyly, namely through Deputy Lam Lon Wai, who in February interpelled the government about the need to apply AI tools in clinical cases with young people.
HM spoke to two clinical psychologists who work with residents of Macao, in person or distance, about the benefits and risks of betting on AI. Nuno Gomes, a psychologist in a local clinic, says that “is, for now, a help, and it will always be”.
"AI is an irreversible process and it is inevitable that it covers all fields of our life, and in them is psychology and helps people.
Nuno Gomes believes that AI can help in the diagnostic phase, although he thinks "the psychologist will always be the central character." "AI can be an advantage in Macau for people who have difficulty asking for help.
Nuno Gomes also recalls that for those who want to talk to someone, AI "can give the feeling that we are not alone and that is someone on the other side." It is a feeling that is still "strange", but "in the future will no longer be, because AI will be part of our day."
The psychologist believes that AI "may work as long as it is ethically well regulated and can help in brief therapies, but always as a complement to a larger process."
Goreti Lima, who has lived in Macao, continues to do clinical psychology at a distance with residents living in the territory. It is more skeptical in relation to the use of AI, arguing that human relationship is always fundamental for quality monitoring.
“Therapy is made in the relationship and these applications do not contemplate this. I think we can use the AI ​​to diagnose, see symptoms, but we can also do with a book or article. Data are stored like?
Recommendations in Portugal
In a written interpeação directed to the Government of MSAR, Deputy Lam Lon Wai questioned whether there will be “cooperation” between government departments, technological companies and local academic institutions in the use of AI in the area of ​​mental health. However, Goreti Lam regrets that deputy "do not speak in the figure of the psychologist."
“Academics have a different experience from psychologists and therapists, who have acquired this experience in practical terms. This develops over time. All these questions have to be thought when applying AI. AI can identify what the person has and even use, but then we have to take into account deontological conditions. Undersisted, ”he added.
Portugal is one of the countries where the application of AI in Psychology begins to gain some form, to the point of the Order of Portuguese Psychologists (OPP) has created the online “Psia” tool, which allows you to state a series of symptoms and reach a diagnosis. Personal data appear to be protected with the introduction, on the website, the citizen card number, with the digital mobile key.
In addition, OPP has created a manual of good practices, entitled “The Human Factor in Artificial Intelligence - Strategic Recommendations for Sustainability”, which states that there are “virtual therapists who can identify, in communication with people, emotional difficulties that facilitate deliberate psychological education”, as well as enhancing “the learning of techniques and skills that aim, for example, to reduce anxiety”.
In addition, the OPP document concludes that "some studies suggest that these chatbots, developed based on validated therapeutic models, may be effective in reducing depressive symptoms and even that some people establish a bond similar to that of a human relationship." However, “these evidence is not consolidated and security-related (people and data), eventual dependence on technologies and the responsiveness of support given to different psychological difficulties are not clarified”, it reads.
Regarding PSIA, it is referred to the OPP website that "on very specific or complex issues should not be used in tasks that require specialized judgment and evaluation, deep technical analysis or professional counseling." It is also clarified that the answers provided are based on “available documents and information” until July 31 last year, and PSIA “does not replace the role of a psychologist or any supervision activities”.
In the case of Hong Kong, some solutions are also beginning to emerge, which motivated, by the way, the interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai. This is the case of Hollo, a mobile phone application developed in connection with the University of Hong Kong (UHK) that aims to “make mental health care more accessible to patients, service platforms and organizations”.
Hollo uses AI power and technologies to bring clinical practices standardized to another level of productivity, intelligence and digital connectivity. According to Cameron Van Breda, Hollo's CEO and co-founder, the company aims to be "an easily accessible tool in stress times, offering analysis and friendship suggestions for better mental health exercises." In practical terms, “focuses on young people from 12 to 24 years old, works in English and Chinese and introduce them to therapy and counseling practices through mindfulness activities and daily games,” reads UHK's website.
Almost the same
Asked about Macao's mental health landscape, Nuno Gomes understands that he persists "some conservatism and ignorance not only in what is AI and areas where one can apply, but also what psychology can do."
“Psychology is here to help people and in the context of Macau there is no such understanding. This stigma prevents many people from looking for help and AI can give this support.
In general terms, "the picture of mental health has changed little from the pandemic," because "in general, people do not feel the need to express emotions and since they are encouraged to keep emotions that when they are bad and stored a long time, they begin to do harm. Goreti Lima also understands that in the area of ​​mental health there is still some ignorance in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:36:41</pubDate></item><item><title>The garden of Almerindo in Timor-Leste can be watered from Portugal or England</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/a-horta-de-almerindo-em-timor-leste-pode-ser-regada-de-portugal-ou-inglaterra/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
"It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It's the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden," he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth formation center,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:19:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Architecture | Liu Jiakun won Pritzker 2025 prize</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/07/arquitectura-liu-jiakun-venceu-premio-pritzker-2025/</link><description>Liu Jiakun won this year's Pritzker Prize. Chengdu's natural architect was chosen by the work “coherent”, in peace with nature and the surrounding world. The organization of the prize highlights the “path that was neither linear nor expected”, and architectural projects with “convincing answers” ​​in environmental terms
 
In Liu Jiakun's work is the citizen who rules, without fixed lines or barriers, combining the old and the modern. But above all, there is a kind of consistency. The Chinese architect, born in 1956 in Chengdu province, won this year's Pritzker Prize, a distinction often described as the Nobel Prize in Architecture. With this week's announcement, the point that was missing to consecrate the talent of a man who lived and worked in a changing China was added and who narrowly did not give up architecture. By the way, according to the official information of the Pritzker Award on Liu Jiakun, his journey “until architecture was neither linear nor expected”.
The mother was an internal doctor at Chengdu Second People's Hospital and it was there that much of her days spent during her childhood. In the years when China lived intensely Maoism and then during the process of reform and openness, Liu underwent all political and social transformations as it grew. He attended the program for “educated young people” in the area of ​​agriculture, and then the Chongqing Institute of Architecture and Engineering, later called the University of Chongqing University in 1978. “As in a dream, I suddenly realized that my life was important,” he said, according to the official information of the Pritzker award.
The studio in his own name, Jiakun Architects, only emerged in 1999 in his hometown, Chengdu, the capital of Sichuan province.
About himself and his work, Liu Jiakun said: "Aspire always being like water-permeating a place without having a fixed shape of his own and infiltrating me in the local environment and in the place itself." "Over time, water gradually solidifies, becoming architecture and perhaps even the highest form of human spiritual creation. However, it maintains all the qualities of this place, both good and bad," he added.
Regarding the attribution of Pritzker, the jury considered that the Chinese architect knew how to innovate, keeping the side more traditional than the profession can have. "Identity has as much to do with the individual and with the collective meaning of belonging to a place. Liu Jiakun revisits the Chinese tradition without nostalgic approach or ambiguity, but as a trampoline for innovation. Creating a new architecture that is simultaneously historical record, an infrastructure, a landscape and a remarkable public space," says the organization.
Spatial commitment
Building houses or buildings can be much more than simple building, establishing a commitment to space and the environment. For the Pritzker jury, "in a global context where architecture strives to find adequate answers to rapidly evolving social challenges, Liu Jiakun gave convincing answers that also celebrate people's daily lives as well as their community and spiritual identities."
Also according to the jury, "through a remarkable work of deep consistency and constant quality, Liu Jiakun imagines and builds new worlds, free from any aesthetic or stylistic embarrassment."
“Instead of a style, it has developed a strategy that is never based on a recurring method, but rather the evaluation of the specific characteristics and demands of each project differently. That is, Liu Jiakun takes the current realities and manipulates them to the point of offering a totally new scenario of everyday life. In addition to knowledge and technique, it adds common sense and wisdom to the designer's tool box,” he adds.
The note that presented the award states that the architect can project “a built environment that is often being pulled in opposite directions”, rethinking “the foundations of density through cohabitation, creating an intelligent solution that balances the opposite forces at stake”.
The jury also describes that "through a remarkable work of deep consistency and constant quality, Liu Jiakun imagines and builds new worlds, free from any aesthetic or stylistic embarrassment."
The largest projects
This year's Pritzker statement highlights the “West Village” project in Chengdu, classified as “transformative”, where Liu Jiakun knew “reformulate the paradigm of public spaces and community life”, “inventing new independent and shared forms of living together, where density does not represent the opposite of an open system”. The architect created here a space that allows "adaptation, expansion and replicability."
Also noteworthy are “subtle and memorable museums” created by themselves, such as the Suzhou Museum of Imperial Kiln Brick or the Shuijingfang Museum, also in Chengdu. In turn, at the Huishan Memorial in Chengdu, the architect "understands that identity is a matter of collective and personal memory, brilliantly raising the individual perspective to a fundamental element of place creation in order to revive a community dimension."
Degree in 1982, Liu was part of the first generation of students responsible for the major projects of the so -called “Nova China”, already with Deng Xiaoping to the rudder of the central government. At the beginning of his career, he was linked to Chengdu's Institute for Research and Architectural Design, a state-owned entity, having moved to Nagqu in Tibeta, where he lived two years in the 1980s.
About this time, the architect recalled his “greatest strength at the time seemed to be my fear of nothing, beyond the abilities of painting and writing,” pionering books and writing at night when he did not project.
His career in architecture was almost set aside until Liu Jiakun saw Tang Hua's solo architecture exhibition, a former university colleague at the Shanghai Art Museum in 1993. Such “rekindled his passion for the profession and fueled a new mindset that he could also be diverted from prescribed social aesthetics,” describes the pritzker jury.
For Liu, "architecture must reveal something - abstract, distill and make visible the qualities inherent to local people," "the power to shape human behavior and create atmospheres, offering a sense of serenity and poetry, evoking compassion and mercy, and cultivating a meaning of shared community."</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 02:59:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | “Two sessions” start today focusing on the economy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/pequim-duas-sessoes-arrancam-hoje-com-foco-na-economia/</link><description>The month of March is synonymous with political movements in Beijing, with the political advisory conference of the Chinese people, which begins today, and the session of the National Popular Assembly, which begins tomorrow. At meetings will be discussed goals and political and economic plans for this year, without forgetting the evolution of the International Panorama
 
Today begins another session of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), in Beijing, while for tomorrow is scheduled the start of the National Assembly (APN). The two events are the most important of the Chinese political system, materializing the country's political representativeness system, with the participation of delegations all provinces and regions of China, including the special administrative regions of Macau and Hong Kong. CCPPC has, as the name implies, an advisory character, while APN is the most important legislative body in the country.
The so -called “two sessions”, with annual periodicity, draw the attention from around the world because it is at this time that the Chinese government presents its economic goals and main political measures for the rest of the year.
According to the Xinhua state agency, data related to the country's gross domestic product (GDP) is one of the most attention points attracts, but the "two sessions" will also serve to shed some lights on China's foreign policy, something particularly remarkable in a turbulent global scenario.
Until March 11, the expected date for the closure of the work, there are objectives, calendars and essential policies, shaping “the political direction of the country” in a “complex and challenging global environment”, reads in Xinhua.
Let us look, then, to what we can expect in matters of GDP values. "As the Chinese economy is oriented towards high quality development, GDP is not the only measure of the economy, but it remains an important indicator. In 2024, China has achieved its objective economic growth of about five percent, thanks largely to a series of significant macroeconomic measures introduced to compensate for the pressure of economic recession," he reads.
Thus, "more concrete policies to stimulate economic activity are expected." According to Xinhua, "China has already given signs of change in its macroeconomic orientation." "At the last central conference of economic labor in December, political officials committed to apply more proactive macroeconomic policies in 2025."
Thus, the adoption of a “monetary policy‘ moderately flexible ’was decided, which represents a significant removal from the 'prudent' approach adopted in the last 14 years,” the agency describes. In this meeting were also defined “nine fundamental priorities”, the first “the increase of consumption”.
Thus, it is expected that in the “two sessions”, “China emphasizes internal demand as the main economic priority”, and this year it is expected “that large-scale equipment updates and consumer exchange programs will be promoted with greater intensity and more extended”.
It is indicated that "China will actively use the maneuver margin for a higher deficit and increase the issuance of special obligations of local administrations", as well as "continuing to issue Special Treasury obligations with a longer term and increase central government transfer payments to local administrations." The "two sessions" will reveal more details in this regard.
Featured
Still on the economic level, Xinhua describes how President XI Jinping underlines on other occasions “the main priorities, such as support for the growth of the private sector”, “the acceleration of the development of the digital economy” and the deepening of the country's opening.
APN members “will analyze the annual budget and government development plan”, and proposals and suggestions related to Artificial Intelligence (AI) ”are also expected to be expected. In fact, this is “one of the main points of interest to China observers”, along with GDP values. It should be noted that, in this field, the country has sought to score points and gain a growing positioning in the market with the creation of the Deepseek platform.
According to the Global Times newspaper, Chinese companies such as Tencent, Baidu and Byd are part of DeepSeek in the products and services they make available, and "some local governments have also announced collaborations with Deepseek IA models to improve public services."
“Many AI-related plans mentioned in the work reports of provincial governments [from China] focus on building innovation platforms, promoting industry's deeper integration and improving political staff. It is important to note that the rise of platforms such as Deepseek reflects China's commitment to taking the lead in technological advances and a greater strategic focus on talent cultivation and existence cultivation and existence From an environment conducive to innovation, ”he reads.
The “two sessions” also constitute “a crucial platform for political legislators and counselors to present suggestions and promote ample consensus on national development” in the AI ​​area, and “some of them are executives of renowned companies and researchers”.
GDP: Maintenance
Still with regard to Chinese GDP, an analysis by Neil Thomas and Jing Qiang of the Asia Society Policy Institute argues that the “two sessions” should reveal “an even more agenda for growth than last year, with approximate objectives of five percent for GDP growth, four percent for the GDP tax deficit and two percent inflation in terms of consumption ”. "Measures should also be introduced to increase consumption and encourage the private sector in innovation," the authors write.
The same analysis of the Asia Society Policy Institute also highlights economic measures to prevent and combat unemployment, a problem that has affected the Chinese economy in recent times.
"China will also announce the annual goals for new jobs in urban areas and the urban unemployment rate. Last year, Beijing has settled in 12 million new jobs and 5.5 percent unemployment rate, and this year's figures will be likely to be said.
With regard to domestic consumption, China is intended to be more and more “a hub for product launch, winter tourism and has a 'silver savings' focusing on the area of ​​restoration for an elderly population”. Also according to the analysis of the Asia Society Polycy Institute, "other priorities include rebalancing economic platform regulations, stimulating economic activity in small towns, greater integration into the area of ​​the large bay and expanding investment in maritime industries."
Attention to Investment
The "two sessions" take place with Donald Trump to return to the presidency of the United States of America and certainly that this point will mark the external agenda of the meetings in Beijing throughout the week.
But still regarding the economy, the Chinese authorities will seek to present and discuss measures that may maintain foreign investment attraction in the country, after the launch of the “Action Plan to stabilize foreign investment”, on February 19.
Here is a “strategic change in Beijing's approach, moving away from tax benefits and subsidies and addressing the liberalization of specific sectors, rationalizing regulation and incentives for re-inbackets,” the same analysts point out.
Therefore, Beijing intends to “frame foreign companies into China's regulatory framework to turn them into long -term stakeholders, making local expansion more attractive than capital reafect to other markets”. Analysts also expect the "two sessions" to reveal concrete policies in this regard.
Sam Hou Fai in Beijing
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, has been in Beijing since yesterday to attend the opening ceremony of the third session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (APN), which takes place tomorrow.
Sam Hou Fai will be in the Chinese capital until Thursday of this week. According to a statement from the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai will be replaced by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, who acts interimly, the functions of Chief Executive.
In the 14th APN, the Government's work report will be reviewed and the analysis of the report on the implementation of the Annual National Economic and Social Development Plan for 2024. The agenda also includes analysis to the National Economic and Social Development Project for this year. The report on the implementation of the central and local budgets for 2024 will also be analyzed, as well as the central and local budget projects for 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:50:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Trips to China increase due to diversity and low prices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/03/economia-viagens-a-china-aumentam-devido-a-diversidade-e-precos-baixos/</link><description>Going to China has never been so easy, fast and cheap. Two residents of Macao of Portuguese nationality reveal to HM which leads them to cross the border frequently, especially the weekend. Cultural diversity, low prices and higher quality of service in bars and restaurants make all the difference
 
Macao Small and Medium-sized (SME) have faced, since the reopening of borders in the postpandeia period, huge difficulties to recover the business, especially those that are further away from the tourist areas. At a time when traveling to China has become extremely easy and cheap, two residents explain why they prefer to move often to the neighboring city of Zhuhai, or even Shenzhen, and consume there instead of being in Macao. Options like dinner outside, catching a taxi or drinking a glass are much cheaper, and the possibility of driving outside the territory has made this option more frequent. But electronic trade has also contributed to the fall of local consumption, they ensure.
Nelson Moura, journalist and resident of Portuguese nationality, goes to Zhuhai whenever he has a free weekend or holidays. It even goes between three to four times a month. “The costs are lower in the interior of China, and then there is the news factor. It has never been easier for a non -Chinese resident of Macau to go to China. He had a time to ask for a time, and this was limited to my trips, and always chose more And developed, especially hengqin, with the connection to the light meter, allows easier calls, ”he told HM.
Since China has flexed the policy of visas and increased the offer of border circulation, traveling to the country is no longer seen as a great trip. “As a foreigner to reside in Macau, to go to China was a bit like going traveling to another Asian country. We have not practically left in Macau, but now since the policy of visas to Portuguese has been flexible, it is possible to go to China whenever we want,” said Nelson Moura.
“I am likely that a Chinese resident has, and it has been a viable option to pass the weekends and holidays to China, knowing different sites. Food is a third of what is practiced in Macau, with fresh products, the host offers are better. than before. ”
Nelson Moura also considers that "for the Chinese community of Macao and Hong Kong there is a greater convenience of travel," as "there are many residents leading all weekends to China just to go to large commercial surfaces, which allows you to buy large amounts of food."
"Traffic near the border of the siege or hkzm bridge is at a level never seen before.
PME, the eternal problem
On the side of Macau, associations linked to the Chinese community's commercial sector call for help, asking for more measures such as the great consumption award, or even consumer cards, that is, more campaigns and initiatives so that residents can buy more in Macao with discounts or support.
One of the last voices showing concern about this scenario was Stanley Au, president of the Macao SME association. To TDM Canal Macau, the official argued that in the next lines of government action the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, has to show effective measures to avoid closing and, consequently, more unemployment. “The most urgent and current situation is the closure of companies. I believe the population saw many stores closed in different neighborhoods of the territory.
However, according to Nelson Moura, it will always be difficult to combat the attraction of the consumption of Greater China. “Macao local trade is a complicated issue. There is a major reduction in consumers, especially on weekends and days when people have time to leave the city.”
Electronic trade also enhances a reduction in local consumption. “Residents know that they find more and cheaper out there. There are Chinese Electronic Commerce companies, such as Taobao, which allows purchases from all over China to Macau without transportation charges, which has reduced domestic consumption.
The resident also draws attention to the fact that it is now easier to use online payment platforms in China with foreign cards or Macao banks, namely through MPay.
Nelson Moura believes that local SMEs have only endured so much time because they were in a kind of closed economic circuit. "Local businesses lived a little in an island economy, and they survived because the Macao market is in the territory, without people could go out so much. Now that there has been competition with what China has to offer, companies suffer because they don't offer so much quality service and at such an attractive price. I know the situation in Hong Kong is similar."
“Like” in China
Macaense Miguel Rosa Duque has always worked in Macau and spent in the territory most of the days of the week, but since he started teaching in Zhuhai his life has become more across the border. Highlights the much cheaper night exits as well as the restoration offer. “Macao has no variety and people are fed up with the fact that the territory is small. We have hotels and restaurants, but they are expensive because the lace are expensive. Given China, in terms of price, the difference is like between the sky and the earth. I give an example: to take a taxi from the gates where I give classes are 40 minutes of travel, 28 kilometers, and paid about 60 to 80 renminbis. From the doors of the siege to Coloane we pay 150 patacas or more, the price difference is huge. ”
Miguel Rosa Duque says that the trips to China in her circle of friends have become so frequent that they even created a group on the WhatsApp social network to facilitate group walks. “I prefer to go to China a thousand times for fun. Macao, in China we spend 400 Renminbis and we are treated as kings. The variety is infinite in terms of restaurants.
Miguel Rosa Duque says he has friends who, even with a car in Macau, eventually acquired another Chinese enrollment car who are parked in the border parking park because it is cheaper to rent a place to park.
Macanese understands that between local SMEs and trade in China “there is no possible competition”, especially with online sales platforms. "People no longer go to stores here, there are a thousand choices and you can buy it from home. My girlfriend rarely goes to the supermarket, does everything online, for example," he added.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Dsal | Possession of the new director was held yesterday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/dsal-tomada-de-posse-do-novo-director-realizou-se-ontem/</link><description>The new director of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), Chan Un Tong, and the subdirector, Chan Tze Wai yesterday took an oath at the inauguration ceremony.
The ceremony was chaired by the Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, who expects leaders to “further promote global development of the Macao labor market, protect work rights and interests under the law and build, with new ideas, a harmonious society between employers and workers”.
Dsal's new leader Chan Un Tong indicated to feel “deeply the weight of responsibility and stated that, according to the spirit of President Xi Jinping's important speech, it will persist in the effective resolution of the population -based employment problem and reinforce training resources to form high quality qualified frames for Macao”.
Chan Un Tong has also pledged to improve labor legislation, the creation of harmonious labor relations and to “make efforts to support the development of micro, small and medium enterprises”.
Chan Un Tong began working in the Government of MSAR in 2002, performing between May 2014 and May 2016, the position of Deputy Coordinator of the Human Resources Office, and from May 2016 to date, the position of subdirector of DSAL.
Chan Un Tong has a degree in Economic Law at the Faculty of Economics of the University of Jinan in Guangzhou.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:32:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal | Meeting with schools due to subscriptions</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/caeal-reuniao-com-escolas-devida-a-recolha-de-assinaturas/</link><description>Allegations that it would have been asked from school teachers managed by associations to collect signatures for the next elections will lead the Electoral Commission to meet with representatives of educational establishments. The commission also received the complaint from an association member who claims to have been required a minimum number of signatures to a list
 
Complaints from alleged school teachers managed by associations they would have been asked to collect signatures to candidate lists to the next legislative elections, scheduled for September 14, were shared on social networks. After yesterday's meeting of the Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), the president of the entity, Judge Seng Ioi Man, said he will mark meetings with school representatives in early April to share the values ​​of justice, integrity and equality. In general, the official also indicated that the use of coercion or misleading methods to raise signatures is a crime.
At a press conference held yesterday, the magistrate said that if the investigation confirms the allegations of the teachers, the forms to constitute candidacies will be considered invalid, according to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau.
The interference in the electoral process of schools managed by associations with representation in the Legislative Assembly, and funded by the government, has been a constant in previous suffrage, namely with the request for teachers and employees to sign propositions of candidacies and even guardians. For example, in 2021, a teacher at Choi Nong Chi Tai School, linked to the Macao Workers' Associations Federation (Faom), will have appealed to in charge of signing documents from the application committees for legislative elections.
In the suffrage of 2017, there were also similar complaints, without repercussions for the lists involved.
In the chapter of the repercussions, the president of Caeal was asked yesterday about the possibility that disqualified candidates could or may not submit candidates in these elections, which are the first after the exclusion of five lists and 21 candidates, most of the pro-democracy field, in 2021. Without responding directly to the issue, Seng Ioi Man recalled that, according to the electoral law, who does not support the basic law and not loyal to law. Manda is away from the elections for five years.
Track
Regarding the suspicions that an elderly woman was invited to sign a candidacy report to legislative elections when exchanging the Macau Pass card to the elderly, the president of Caeal revealed that the case was investigated, but it was not possible to collect concrete information.
In addition, Caeal will have received the complaint from an association member who was responsible for collecting a certain number of signatures to a list. Seng Ioi Man has assured that he will follow this case. The official stressed that anyone who helps raise support to form a list for the elections must sign the appointment form and provide assistance voluntarily and clearly. In addition, Caeal's president reiterated that list leaders or campaign organizers cannot resort to coercion, fraud, professional pressure or promises of benefits to influence voters to support a particular list, either through vote or signature to constitute a candidate list.
For now, nine CAEAL forms were requested for constitutions of lists for legislative elections, but none have been delivered. The deadline for presenting the application commissions ends on June 6.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:30:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Gongbei | Renewal of border post costs 500 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/gongbei-renovacao-de-posto-fronteirico-custa-500-milhoes/</link><description>An investment of about 500 million Renminbis is foreseen for the remodeling of various areas of the Gongbei Border Post, near the siege gates, which is daily used by thousands of people. The renewal is expected to take two years, it was announced yesterday
 
Here comes a new Gongbei border post. The information was advanced yesterday by the authorities and reported by the Macau News Agency (MNA) portal, which describes that an investment of about 500 million Renminbis (553 million patacas) will be made for a renewal project that should take two years to be completed.
According to the portal, "the project is part of a broader revitalization initiative in the Xiangzhou district" in Zhuhai, and includes a total of 144 plans, valued at 32.9 billion Renminbis, which are already "in the preparation phase".
For now, it is known that the first phase of the renewal project “also includes auxiliary transport infrastructures” and changes in the underground shopping center, very close to the customs and passports. That is, the bus zone will be improved, and the Zhuhai Train Station, very close to the border post, will also be integrated into this renewal process.
MNA describes that for this area is still being planned to build housing and office spaces.
Works, a year later
The revitalization of the Gongbei Border Post is announced a year after a renewal work was done to the main building of the post, which covered 33,000 square meters and which improved energy supply, air conditioning and water supply infrastructures.
The building was also the target of improvements abroad, main entrance and surrounding environment. Gongbei's border post remains one of the most used by residents, tourists and residents of Zhuhai. Only on January 18, 430 thousand people entered, being considered by the authorities the largest number of entries and exits of the last five years.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:06:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Old buildings | Pereira Coutinho questions Funds System for Renewal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/edificios-antigos-pereira-coutinho-questiona-sistema-de-fundos-para-renovacao/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho challenged the government about the need for “transparency and responsibility in renewal and urban rehabilitation”, namely as “the high funds raised for repair and renewal” without transparency of accounts and without these values ​​include works within the apartments.
Thus, the deputy questions "if there is any control system on the rules of collection, office and decision limits for maintenance works of old buildings."
"How does the Government of MSA guarantee equity in the division of fees and transparency in the decision mechanism? The current legislation provides only to be necessary 15 percent of the consent of the owners, but is this ratio representative of the owners' total will?" He asks.
The deputy also believes that the government should "review and improve the process of candidacy for the incentive regime for the maintenance of buildings, allowing the early payment of a percentage of loans in the early phase or when completion of the works, to relieve financial pressure on owners."</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:05:25</pubDate></item><item><title>SEAC PAN VAN | Recycled water until the end of 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/seac-pan-van-agua-reciclada-ate-ao-fim-de-2026/</link><description>The Director of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA), Susana Wong, predicts that by the end of 2026 Seac Pai Van public housing and the University of Macau campus begin to be served with recycled water supply.
This is a type of water used, with a treatment that does not make it potable, but allows use for discharges from self -delighting and other less demanding uses such as watering. The information was released by the official during an activity organized by Dsama on Sunday.
Speaking cited by the newspaper or Mun, Susana Wong failed to indicate the price of supply, but promised to be cheaper than the water currently supplied through the taps. Wong also explained that as the channeling in Seac Pai Van public housing were prepared for this supply, residents cannot choose not to be supplied by recycled water.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:03:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Counselors | Meeting with Timor Delegate at the Forum</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/conselheiros-encontro-com-delegado-de-timor-no-forum/</link><description>Rui Marcelo, Portuguese communities advisor, gathered yesterday, along with other counselors, with António Ramos Silva, Timor-Leste delegate with the Macau Forum, and Danilo Afonso Henriques, Deputy Secretary General of the Forum.
One of the points of the agenda was the face-to-face meeting of the Asia Regional Council and Oceania of the Portuguese Communities Council held Thursday and Friday in Dili, Timor-Leste.
In the Timorese capital, the counselors will meet with Ramos Horta, President of the Republic of Timor-Leste, and Manuela Freita Bairos, Portuguese ambassador in the country. “Matters of common interest, focusing on the promotion of Portuguese language and culture, were also addressed, reinforcement and cooperation in the education sector, exchange in economic cooperation between Macao and Timor-Leste and also the strengthening of relations between the Portuguese communities of the Regional Council of Asia and Oceania”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:01:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Requested changes in public lease</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/comercio-pedidas-mudancas-no-arrendamento-publico/</link><description>The legislator linked to the Federation of Macao Workers' Associations, Leong Sun Iok, asks the government to have alternatives to end vacant stores for several years and promote economic diversification
 
Representative Leong Sun IOK defends a new policy of leasing of government commercial spaces in public housing buildings. The position was taken through a written interpellation to face the reduction in the number of leases.
In order to promote the diversification of the economy, Leong indicates the need to apply to the lease of these spaces the same kind of strategy that was adopted in the lease of Patane market restoration spaces.
In this space, indicates the deputy linked to the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom), the choice of tenants was based on criteria such as “the business plan, the experience, qualifications and the diversity of products” sold. This was a method that Leong indicated to be more “flexible” and which translates a “more conscious” government posture of current reality.
However, the legislator regrets that in stores leased in public housing the choice is still made through a draw among interested candidates, as determined by the decree-law on the regulation of the grant, lease and free assignment of spaces in social housing buildings for the exercise of commercial activities.
This is a document that deputy considers out of date, because he is “in force for over 30 years”, so he questions the executive about the desire to replace him to “take into account factors such as the current social environment and the market situation”.
Thinking about change
According to the version presented by the deputy, in April last year there were 12 vague stores and some without any tenant since March 2018. "The lack of regularity in the public housing stores does not favor the revitalization and effective functioning of resources and hinders the early planning of residents according to prevailing demand in the market," he criticized.
Therefore, Leong questions the government about the possibility of creating a mechanism to attribute the lease of these spaces every three months or every six months, to end situations where stores have been unoccupied several years.
At a time when several commercial spaces in residential neighborhoods end doors or have difficulty competing with prices in Zhuhai, Leong Sun IOK argues that the example of Hong Kong follows. From the legislator's perspective, the government should consider creating a new program for young entrepreneurs, under 35, where there is no fixed income, and tenants only have to pay 20 percent of net profits obtained with the business.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:00:02</pubDate></item><item><title>A LIBRET OF PERDITION</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/um-libreto-de-perdicao/</link><description>Some of us belong to that generation that spent the summer holidays reading "The Five" and there were so many adventures, so dangerous the paths, so succulent the picnics, that we fattened by the very English descriptions of those deletions in these afternoons where no one wanted to know from us beyond the essentials, but we wanted exactly as in these books, jams, milk, bacon, bacon, bacon and bread scones.
For each passage, after discovering the criminal sources, redoubled appetite and towel on the floor. The fifth element of this group was a dog that announced everything, predicted, and instigated the petitions. That was so hypnotic that we never knew why Zé wanted to be a boy. Now at a distance we can talk about an androgynous character who has never been linked to his feminine genre, where Ana, a hyper-sensitive, denoted a more intuitive pattern that was imposed on a highly passionate and dysfunctional group. It could be a libretto for the disturbing pentagon of a national reality that always culminates in five but never with children's craves. However, it is good to remember that there is still a very recent and searched Sebastião that would fit this prosody where strange corners and things would fit perfectly.
We are in March and we remember as if life was a first eternal time. After this comes Camilo Castelo Branco soon, and everything was headed to another much more radical tonic than any adventure between cousins, holidays, smugglers, and that's where we understand that a stage ended to enter another, more severe, complex and fierce in love. We realize that adventures never made us cry, but that our growing members and the pain of all this, for the first time distill other tears that would also bring that unknown element that is the first love. We went into puberty with a book in flames: "Love of perdition."
In order not to hurt the numerous “Camilians” passing through his birthday, it is worth remembering at this moment Alexandre Cabral, and also the libretto of António S. Ribeiro, a play based on the novel that made debut in the Theater of St. Charles in 1991, which is in fact a precious synthesis of the narrative of a jail that had to lengthen the driving threads of a dungeon in the dungeon: the dialogues: They bring us to the idea all the passages of the novel and leave us in an amaze that we no longer expected. Readings in this rereading become interpreters of the same voltage. Integration, disintegration, and the text continues. And this is where the literary act begins: we no longer talk about our lives, emotions, things, but of an abstract, sensitive and larger archetype that produces a metalanguage that can challenge us as a human vibration that only a great author knows how to lead.
It was the fiero destination blows that Camilo wakes up to an absolutely monumental loving process where Ana Placido's late wounds will always be smaller things. It was this dimension between the liberal lover, bohemian, young and beautiful, and the graceful sap of Teresa de Albuquerque, hostage to absolutists and their reactionaries leaders, which the drama takes place as a victory of disinquued elements. The same country that did not allow love remains strangely unable to love. This love is an act of uniqueness and we must collectively take away the appropriate elections. It is also the tenderness of the fresh spring of life that makes desires a greater law, but…: And this is where we bump into the double condition. What does Mariana do as an element of this plot? We are in the presence of a great sacrificial archetype. Camilo has never ceased to be polygamous, and his transcendent desire to be loved finally finds the preferred victim.
Friend! My friend!
Now I touch you and you are real
And burns more than ancient delirium.
Now look at me and I grow up
I grow loud and very
More than the foam of the sea!
Simon Botelho would leave for the Indies at dawn on March 17, Teresa Albuquerque would die, Mariana would follow him until the ocean serves as a shroud. It is indeed a monumental instant. Camilo Castelo Branco was a writing professional, not a "parvenu".  Writing is a profession, so nothing is more worthy than your example done in an absolutely talented way. All moral considerations are now on two hundred years, and the most impressive is still the terms of knowing all other things.
When they ask; Are you a robot? I say no. Just for reading "love of perdition".</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:55:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Budget for 2025-2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/orcamento-de-hong-kong-para-2025-2026/</link><description>Recently, the Hong Kong government presented its budget. In the fiscal year of 2024-2025, he obtained revenue of $ 559.6 billion of Hong Kong, the expense ascended at 754.8 billion, the actions issued reached 130 billion, debt reimburses were 22.1 billion, the fiscal deficit was 87.2 billion and fiscal reserves in 647.3 billion.
Tax revenues have fallen 45 percent over the past six years. The tax deficit was due to the fall of taxes on the sale of unprofit and the continuous increase in spending on infrastructure, investments and health services.
In the budget of 2025-2026, the Hong Kong government estimates that revenues reach 659.4 billion HKD, expenses are in the order of 822.3 billion, the actions issued reached 150 billion, debt reimbursement if they are 54.1 billion, the fiscal deficit of 67 billion and tax reserves reach 580.3 billion.
To reduce the fiscal deficit to 67 billion, the government has proposed measures to increase revenue and reduce costs. To increase revenues, the main measures will be the increase in actions from 150 billion to 195 billion in a five -year period, with more than three and five years, mainly for long -term projects such as the North Metropolitan Area and for the payment of short -term debt.
Another measure that is being considered is the application of “charging border fees to private cars that leave”, charging 200 hkd per car, although tourist buses and trucks are exempt from this rate.
As for expenses, the government provides to lower them to 113.4 billion over the next few years, freezing the salaries of civil servants, and eliminating 10,000 jobs over the next two years, reviewing the “reduced rates of public transport to elderly and people with disabilities” and reducing funding to universities.
After implementing these measures, the government expects to reach the budgetary equilibrium three years later, that is, in 2028-2029, standing in line with the precepts of the Hong Kong Basic Law that stipulates that it should be lived within the possibilities.
Looking at the budget in its entirety, there are three points worthy of attention. The first is that tax reserves are insufficient to meet unexpected large expenses. Tax year expenses of 2024-2025 were 754.8 billion, but the current tax reserves are 647.3 billion. If the government has no revenues for a year, tax reserves are not enough to cover expenses. This also means that if there is an emergency that implies large expenses between 2025 and 2026, such as if the pandemic is active again, the government will have financial resources very limited to its disposal.
The second is the non -existence of negative capital. In the fiscal year of 2025-2026, the revenues were 659.4 billion and the expense of 822.3 billion. The difference between revenues and expense was 162.9 billion, which represents 25 percent of the total expense. During this period, the government's main source of revenue from “personal taxes” and “profit taxes”, which reached about 301.2 billion.
As the population of Hong Kong is gradually aging the government continues to cut into taxes to benefit people, and the amount of “personal taxes” and “profit taxes” will be reduced. Issuing actions is a way of contracting a loan. Although it can solve short -term tax problems and ensure that the government has sufficient cash flow, it does not solve the budget deficit problem and tax reserves will continue to decrease. In the long run, these two factors may affect Hong Kong Statute as an international financial center.
The most viable way of resolving the budget deficit is to ensure that revenues are higher than expense. “Charging border rates to private cars that leave” can be an effective measure to increase government revenues while encouraging people to make their shopping in Hong Kong, which will undoubtedly help the city's economy. Of course this measure may have some impact on Hong Kong's integration into the Great Bay area.
The third question is the number of measures to reduce expenses that can be taken. The government is thinking of freezing the salaries of civil servants, as well as eliminating some civil service jobs by reducing subsistence and social security expenses. As the population is aging, spending on subsistence benefits increase progressively and there is not much room for cuts in well-being benefits. In the long run, it may not be easy to get the goal of balance between revenue and expense by reducing government spending through austerity measures.
With an aged population and expenses to increase, the financial problem will only get worse. To obtain the budget balance, the government will have to have stable and long -term fiscal recitas. A few years ago, the government studied the possibility of applying a "rate for land and sea departures", similar to the "collection of border fees to private cars that leave." However, as the “Terra and Mar Departures Rate” is calculated on a per capita base, with the number of Hong Kong cars traveling to the city, for city residents to shop in mainland China, this rate would bring considerable revenues to the Hong Kong government and encourage people to consume in the city by helping their economy.
Another tax that was considered was the sales rate, a way to guarantee the government stable long -term revenues. According to a 2003 study, if the sales fee were 5 percent, the government would raise about 30 billion in tax revenues per year. With this tax, the fiscal deficit can be reduced. In addition, the government can impose higher rates on the highest and lower products on the first -need products, thus achieving the objective of wealth redistribution and reducing the moat between the poor and the rich.
Looking at the budget in its entirety, if the government does not increase revenues it will not be able to meet the expenses. If this situation continues, it will easily exhaust the tax reserves. Therefore, only increasing revenues can gradually get out of a complicated financial situation. In addition, social progress and various measures to the welfare of the population require capital. If the financial problem is not resolved, governance will be difficult.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:38:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Fell from the power chair</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/caiu-da-cadeira-do-poder/</link><description>Possibly younger readers will not even know the history of dictator António Oliveira Salazar. But, I tell you a tragic-komic story that happened to the former chairman of the Council of Ministers during the time of the dictatorship that reigned before April 25, 1974.
Sources close to the dictator, Dona Maria, told us that the dictator was a daily listener of the humorous programs of the 'parody of Lisbon'. On one day, the dictator was in the ripation of the São Julião da Barra Fort, sitting in a canvas chair, catching his sun's rays and listening to a radio show from the team of Lisbon humorists. At one point, he found it so funny to a radio program that laughing several laughter and fell from his chair hitting his head on the floor stone and never recovered from the brain injury.
Now, after more than 50 years, another head of government has also fallen from the chair, but this one of power. Luís Montenegro when he took office as Prime Minister, due to AD's tangential victory, he said he was ready to rule for four years with transparency and stability. Two terms of the greatest importance in politics, but which were in no way fulfilled by the Prime Minister.
Last week, Luís Montenegro fell from the power chair for his sole fault. The politician, the PSD leader and prime minister in management began to walk in the mouths of the world for lack of transparency in his business that allegedly continued when he took seriousness and the lack of stability in his government due to the many cases that were registered in just over 300 days of governance, namely the 16 Portuguese who died that I INEM has made a strike and did not give clinical support to these people. About transparency it seems to me that everything is told and in the last chronicle we specified in detail the cambalachos of his family business and about the real estate of politicians who make them belong, while falling a singing star, in men wealthy with luxury houses, good Thursdays or a lot in Alentejo.
It happened that after two motions of censorship to the government had been failed, the Socialist Party entered the Assembly of the Republic with a potestative request for a parliamentary commission of inquiry into doubts in the activity of the Prime Minister's family business and which he never wanted to respond in full.
In the face of the socialist attitude, Luís Montenegro decided to gather the Council of Ministers and announce the presentation of a motion of trust in Parliament. Okay, it was the cradled broth. Everyone saw that Luís Montenegro had taken the blackmail and would confront the socialists in the sense if they withdrew the request for a parliamentary commission of inquiry, he also collected the motion of confidence. The parliamentary session that discussed and voted for the motion of trust was a shame in the history of 50 years of democracy. The government and parliamentary leader of the PSD made a very sad and disgusting figure who led to the condemnation of all parliamentarians, except a group called liberal initiative that still hopes to ally with AD and one day go to the Portuguese government. With the vote expressed in an absolute majority against the motion of trust we watched the fall of Montenegro, and its peers, from the chair of power.
Then the President of the Republic, who always disagreed with Montenegro in the presentation of a trusted motion, received the parties and gathered the Council of State announcing that the elections will be held on May 18.
The mess of the election campaign to end an election cycle never seen will begin. Montenegro is convinced that he will win and Pedro Nuno Santos convinced is. There are surveys for all tastes, some give AD to the socialist party. One thing is certain: the arrival will have much less deputies than it had in this legislature that now ends. We now surpass the electoral turbulence recorded in the second half of the 1st Republic, of bad memory.
During this period, four general elections were called to fill parliamentary seats: May 1919, July 1921, January 1922 and November 1925. Four electoral acts in six years and six months. Nonetheless, in a more dilated range than the hallucinating series of recent legislative elections: October 2019, January 2022, March 2024 and those that will follow on May 18. One hundred years ago, nothing substantial was being solved with successive calls to the polls. On the contrary, each touch the electoral rebound made the political and governing picture always more convivial. The story seems to indicate that everything will be repeated. The politicians of our day, whatever the quadrant, should assimilate the lessons of history. Before, however, it is indispensable to know her…</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:09:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian women</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/mulheres-palestinianas/</link><description>It took me too long to address the Palestinian issue in this space. I can't explain the delay. It is a complex and emotionally demanding theme. I am perplexed to see how, in my social circles, the legitimacy of the Palestinian struggle is widely recognized, while in other spaces, any support for the Palestinian people is quickly confused with an anti-Semitic attitude.
We live in an extreme world, where division persists into parallel realities, with no room for dialogue. And so the critical situation continues. What else can I say, but I feel revolt? Season my food with Za'Atar every day as a symbolic gesture to keep the conscience of a people who suffers from hunger and deprivation alive. We have seen an unprecedented ethnic cleansing, and Palestinian occupation, refugee camps and rubble are the epicenter of sociopolitical degradation of the modern world.
On Women's Day, I had the opportunity to listen to Shahd Wadi, a researcher and writer Palestinian, who has exploited the occupation and the arts as a form of witness to women's lives and experiences. Recently, he launched the poetry book “Rain of Jasmine”, where experiences and languages ​​are intertwined. Shahd chose Portugal as a refuge while awaiting the day when he can return to his family village, where his grandmother was forced from 1948. In this informal conversation, fundamental issues were discussed: women's narratives, the imposition of Western feminism that insists on seeing the Arab woman as a victim, the body as a memory instrument of an extermination.
The concept of intersectionality proves essential in this context, as it allows us to understand the resistance of a people in parallel with the social emancipation of women. It is a struggle against occupation, injustice and systemic violence. The stories shared by Shahd Wadi brought a new light to the way we perceive the creativity and resilience of Palestinian women. Like that woman who, seeing a man being arrested by Israeli soldiers, gives her baby to her arms and stages a discussion, pretending to be fed up with her husband's constant arrests, leaving her alone with the child. The soldiers, disconcerted with the situation, free it. The man returns the baby to this woman, who had never seen before. Or as, in the face of the threat of violation, some women say goodbye, destroying the pleasure that the aggressors expect to obtain by stealing their honor.
To reflect on the resistance of Palestinian women is also to recognize how their body has become a war target. It is the body that generates and ensures the continuity of a people at risk of extermination. Restrictions on access to sexual and reproductive health care are not accidental. A checkpoint can prevent a woman from arriving at the hospital to give birth, endangering the life of the baby and mother. Small details such as this highlight the insidious dimension of the ongoing ethnic cleaning process.
Shahd Wadi shared these and many other stories, assuming an essential role in preserving the Palestinian experience. He gave us permission to make them ours, integrating them into our political imagination of struggle and resistance. On Women's Day, and in so many others, who reflect on Palestinian women who continue to resist, not only for the right to decide on their bodies and future, but also for the right to exist with dignity, freedom and sovereignty.
His struggle is a testimony of courage and resilience and reminds us that feminism, anywhere in the world, must adapt to local realities. His stories and experiences are part of the struggle for the freedom of the Palestinian people, a struggle that belongs to all.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:43:21</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC presents “Law themes” by the end of the month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/frc-apresenta-temas-de-direito-ate-final-do-mes/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) promotes today, tomorrow and then next week, on March 26 and 27, at 6.30 pm, a set of lectures on law topics, on the “vicissitudes of the process (I)”, which aims to identify possible incidents in the judicial proceedings and address the respective regimes. The sessions will take place in parallel, in the Portuguese and Chinese languages, coordinated by Teresa Leong.
The sessions are organized by CRED-DM-Center for Reflection, Study and Dissemination of the FRC Macao Law. This cycle of conferences aims to address, in a practical and explanatory way, relevant daily topics of all Macao judicial operators, a project started in previous years and which had great adhesion of the class.
According to Teresa Leong, "the judicial process begins with the dispute and ends with the decision to end this dispute." "If the process follows its normal course, without major starters, justice is naturally served without inconvenience. However, most varied incidents make this difficult, sometimes difficult to achieve. These incidents, in addition to causing some inconvenience to the ongoing process, may even undermine the acts laboriously practiced, including the final decision itself," he explains.
With “process vicissitudes (i)” begins this approach with the analysis of the circumstances in which it can, or has to modify the subjects of a judicial process and their implications for the ongoing process. In the first session, that is, today, it will speak of the “subjective modification: subjective substitution vs. subjective cumulation” and “third party intervention: main intervention”. In the second session, a week later, it will be the turn of the presentation of the module “Third Party Intervention: Accessory Intervention and Opposition”.
The lectures in Portuguese are held today and on March 26, and the counterparts in Chinese are held tomorrow, 20, and March 27, at the FRC gallery.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:52:44</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Arte Gongbi, from Zou Li, to be seen until April 5</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/frc-arte-gongbi-de-zou-li-para-ser-vista-ate-5-de-abril/</link><description>“Burning Like a Lotus” is the name of the new exhibition patent at the Rui Cunha Foundation until April 5th. This is an opportunity to get to know the Gongbi Art Gender, with works by Zou Li. Gongbi Art is known for the extreme detail painting with fine brushes
 
Since this Tuesday there is a new show to visit in the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery (FRC). This is “Burning Like a Lotus”, by artist Zou Li, which is an example of the Gongbi art genre, characterized by the use of the traditional thin and delicate brush technique, about Japanese rice role, silk fabric or oriental silk fans.
Zou Li is considered "a renowned painter with more than fifty years of career and experience, whose artistic focus is mostly around themes related to the history of Chinese women." The three dozen works now exhibited at the HRF were held between 1997 and 2022.
In the artist's work there is a “awareness of femininity through his extraordinary artistic expression”, being present in the creations “harmonious and moving of the beauty of the body and soul of women”, according to a FRC note, Ung Si Meng, honorary president of the Association for Friendship and Coordination of former Macao's Chinese Popular Advisory Conference.
It is also described that "for a long time, and to fulfill his social responsibilities and his vocation as a professional painter, Zou Li actively participated in several important historical creations."
It is the scroll roll entitled “Imperatriz Wu Zetian” or the “Hundred Chinese Concubin Images” collection. Ung Si Meng also described Zou Li as "widely recognized and appreciated by experts, academics, colleagues and the Chinese artistic society."
Large
Also according to the same note, it refers that Zou Li's works “reflect the dimension of his academic and artistic knowledge, which have already attracted the wide attention of national and international artistic circles”.
In addition, "his works have been much appreciated by art galleries, museums, art institutions, public and private, and collectors." Zou Li has created, throughout his career, more than a thousand works, as well as more than fifty individual exhibitions, in his country and abroad, having also published more than ten individual art catalogs. Recently, in April 2024, the National Museum of Women and Children of China acquired a collection of 593 of his pieces.
Zou Li is a member of the China Artists Association, a researcher at the Wenshi Research Hall of the Guangdong Popular Government, director of the Guangdong Province Institute of Chinese Painting and honorary president of the Foshan Artists Association. In the past, he performed the functions of deputy director of the southern branch of the China Central and History Institute of Culture and History, where he also did research work.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:51:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Writer Mário Lúcio speaks of the power of women in Africa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/escritor-mario-lucio-fala-do-poder-das-mulheres-em-africa/</link><description>Women can save the African continent when they come to power, because their sensitivity prevents them from killing others from others, unlike African dictators. This is the theme of the next book of writer Mário Lúcio.
In an interview with Lusa agency, the author of “The Devil was my baker,” said the work should be published next year, being in the revision phase and on the way to the 60 readings it does before giving a book by completed.
This time, the theme is the African presidents, who classifies “extraordinary literary figures”, giving the example of Kumba Yalá, former president of Guinea-Bissau, who died in 2014. The reader will never find the names of the presidents in the book, being only referred to as “the president” and having all in common being a “source of the delay in Africa's development”.
"We have had external interventions that have surrounded the development of Africa, such as slavery, such as colonization. After we release these processes, they came the dictators and they are clearly the source of disrespect for human rights, the source of delays, of pile, crime.
Home in Kumba
The narrative begins precisely with Kumba Yalá, although without the name and because in the book they are figures of fiction, then passing through several African presidents, such as the one who brings together the family in a Christmas dinner, during which he distributes strategic places.
“Mile daughter, from tomorrow the transport is with you; from tomorrow the planes are with you, my first woman;
The Cape Verdean writer also writes about another president who thought the Belgians were in collusion with an ethnic group to overthrow him and, to solve the problem, buys $ 144 million in Machins, Catanas, dagged and hoe that delivers one ethnicity to end the other, ”resulting in three months in the largest genocide in human history, with 800,000 people killed in 1994.
The work also features a character that crowns emperor and spends millions of dollars in Mercedes to receive guests for the coronation in Africa, at a time when the people lived with less than a dollar a day, regarding the figure of former Central President and Central African emperor Jean-Bokassa.
From president in president, history flows until reaching the only name revealed, precisely a woman: Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf, former president of Liberia (2006–2018) and Nobel Peace Prize (2011).
The election of this woman, who "managed to take a country devastated by civil wars - Liberia - and stabilize the country," is "a message of hope." "I would say that women are more sensitive and this should probably have a genetic reason. That is, women get pregnant and men do not and the book even talks about it, because there is a pregnancy epidemic and the 72 -year -old president," he said.
In the book, the pregnancy epidemic reaches all women in the country and no one knows why and even some belly men go to the doctor. These belly men are afraid that at the source of pregnancy is a lesson: to know what the pain of delivery is. "The day [men] know what the pain of childbirth is, they will never kill the son of others again," he said.
The Bosses
The author recalls that, in Africa, as in his country Cape Verde, women are heads of family: educate, raise, work and their son is always there.
"I do not see a woman send the children of others, so in catadupa," he said, continuing: "I am convinced that women can save the African continent and the world, but not women who want to rule as dictators, but who really have access and support to actually rule with another sensitive, because I am not seeing another way out."</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:22:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Letters Route | Poster starts this weekend with poetry, photography and other stories</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/rota-das-letras-cartaz-arranca-este-fim-de-semana-com-poesia-fotografia-e-outras-historias/</link><description>The Rota das Letras Literary Festival starts this weekend and the public can expect a series of events around lyrics, music and arts in general. Highlight, on Sunday, for a guided tour of the Barra Zone with Jason Wordie, historian and author. On Saturday, the “New Nomadic Time-Observing Uniquely” photography workshop is held
 
Lovers of the history of Macao and the world of literature have this weekend the opportunity to explore a series of initiatives integrated in this year's edition of the Rota das Letras Literary Festival. One of the events takes place this Sunday, and it is a guided tour of the Barra zone with its historical and iconic places in the company of Jason Wordie, author and historian.
Between 10am and 1pm, therefore, “Macao, People and Places, Past and Present. Gued Walk Throughout the Historial Barra District”, a limited tour to 20 people per session that ends with the A-MA temple.
Jason Wordie is the author of the book “Macao: People and Places, Past and Present”, who met a new edition last year, with the Praia Grande Editions seal, due to “the high search”. Jason Wordie graduated in History at the University of Hong Kong and for 25 years he has written for South China Morning Post, focused on historical places and his culture.
"The tour will include the main points of the built heritage [in the Barra Zone] and the social history as documented, analyzed and described in" Macao: People and Places, Past and Present "," is described. The event is repeated the next weekend.
Rota das Letras also features a photography workshop this Saturday. This is “New Nomadic Time-Observing Uniquiely”, with Jessie Rao Yongxia, which takes place in the old slaughterhouse, in Barra, between 11h and 12h. The second session takes place Sunday at the same time, and on the first day the photographer will share his ideas about photography with participants in order to share the workshop experience and the art of photographing. The presentation of each one's photographic project follows.
Jessie Rao Yongxia will, above all, bring to the workshop their own experiences with the image. “When I first put my feet in the pastures of Mongolia in the inner Mongolia, I found that it was different from what I imagined. This difference comes from the books I enjoyed and the related stories I heard, so it can be said to be an uncontrolled but active behavior. in the event description.
Spoken words
This Friday, from 9 pm, a poetry recital with Peace Wong, entitled "It's Caffeine Dancing". It is a performance with Peace Wong itself in collaboration with visual artist Suze Chan. The event takes place in the old slaughterhouse, where, in fact, much of the events of Rota das Letras happen.
This Friday, also marks the inauguration of an exhibition by Portuguese photojournalist Alfredo Cunha, who captured images of the Portuguese decolonization process. This is one of the ways that Rota das Letras found to celebrate the 50th anniversary of this historical event.
Alfredo Cunha's show can be seen until March 31 in the old slaughterhouse of Barra. The career of this photojournalist also began during the Estado Novo regime in Portugal in 1971, having been an official photographer of two presidents of the Republic, Ramalho Eanes and Mario Soares. Alfredo Cunha is also known for his photographic work on April 25, 1974.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:20:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | José Cesário warns of CTT problems</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/eleicoes-jose-cesario-alerta-para-problemas-com-ctt/</link><description>José Cesário, Secretary of State for the Portuguese Communities, defended Radio Macau that the usual conditions in the operation of the elections in Portugal, namely the May 18 legislatures, will occur again due to the functioning of the CTT. For José Cesário, these system conditions will affect the electoral participation of the emigrated Portuguese.
"The Assembly of the Republic has not produced any kind of legislative change that may be considered in a current electoral process. Therefore, if there is no change, the method will be exactly the same," said the official.
In practice, the voter will continue to have to receive the voting report by the mail at the indicated address, then deliver it to the CTT. However, delays in the operation of services or other bureaucracies make it possible to receive the bulletin on time and hours, for example, generating potential increase in abstention.
"We are fully aware that there are very varied difficulties in the domain of the functioning of the post office systems in various countries, and this is a difficult matter to overcome," he said. The Secretary of State hopes that the May Legislative Elections can take place "in the best way possible". "Unfortunately, I know very well that there are countries where the post office works will strongly limit electoral participation," he said.
The problems are of various order and go through situations where "people, for various reasons, or have changed residence, or not voting in several successive elections, may not receive the vote."
The Portuguese again go to elections on May 18 following the lead to the motion of confidence presented by Prime Minister Luís Montenegro, in the Assembly of the Republic, leading to the dissolution of Parliament.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:58:02</pubDate></item><item><title>World Games | Special Olympics Macau win four gold medals</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/jogos-mundiais-special-olympics-macau-conquistam-quatro-medalhas-de-ouro/</link><description>The Special Olympics Macao Movement entourage has won 14 medals, including four gold at the Winter Games for people with intellectual disabilities in Italy. In a statement, the movement stressed that the entourage had only eight athletes, and “for most of them” was the first time they competed in the world winter games.
This is because the latest edition of the competition, which was scheduled to take place in 2022 in Kazan, Russia, was initially postponed due to Covid - 12 pandemic and then canceled due to the Russian invasion of Ukraine.
The star of the Macao entourage was the 18 -year -old Chio Hao Law, who won two gold medals on the 100 -meter and 200 meters of snow races. In September, Chio was Macao's first athlete to compete in the Paralympic Games, finally ending the length heel race for athletes with intellectual disabilities in Paris2024.
Also in the Snow Race, 17 -year -old Huang Hou won a gold medal in the 200 meter race and one bronze in 100 meters. The other gold medal for Macao was for Sou Fai in the 500 -meter race in the speed skating. The 25 -year -old athlete also got a silver medal in the thousand meters race.
In the dance modality, the territory won two bronze medals in the individual race and two more medals in the mixed peer race, thanks to Chang Chak Kuan, 19, and Lam Cheng I, 16. The Turin2025 Winter Games took place between 8 and 15 March, with the participation of more than two thousand athletes from 103 countries.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:44:24</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate | Room transactions go up. Down prices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/imobiliario-sobem-transaccoes-descem-precos/</link><description>In February, 176 dwellings were purchased and sold at an average of 76,243 patacas per square meter. Compared to what was happening a year ago, prices suffered a 11.6 percent reduction, but 44 transactions were registered
 
Last month, the house price reduced 11.6 percent, compared to the same period, to an average of 76,243 patacas per square meter. The information was released by the Directorate of Finance Services (DSF). In February last year, the average price of the square meter of housing was 86,225 patacas, 9,982 patacas above the latest amounts released on Monday.
However, when the comparison is between January and February this year, the average price of dwellings has a valuation of 6 percent, from 71,917 patacas per square meter to 76,243 patacas per square meter.
At the price level, the reality is now different from what was happening in 2019. Before the pandemic, the average price per square meter was 98,618 patacas, which represents a reduction of 22.7 percent, or 22,375 patacas, compared to the data provided on Monday.
The information about last month shows that Colaane was the most expensive area in the territory, with an average of 83.5 71 patacas per square meter. In the mud, the average price of the square meter was 82,471 patacas, and on the Macao peninsula of 72,986 patacas.
Greater demand
The highest price reduction seems to have resulted in an increase in the number of purchases and housing sales. In February, 176 transactions were reported, 44 more than in the same period, when 132 were accounted for, which means growth of one third.
When the comparison is made between last month and January, there were 94 transactions, a break of 34.8 percent, from 270 purchases and sales to 176 transactions in February.
However, in 2019, before the COVID-19 pandemic, the market was more active than currently happens. In February 2019, 279 transactions were registered, 103 more than last month. However, in terms of the volume of transactions, February 2019 numbers approach the January registration this year.
The latest data also reveals that the Macao Peninsula was the place with the most transactions, a total of 126 housing purchases and sales. In second place comes the mud with 36 transactions and coloane, where 14 purchases and housing sales were registered.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:38:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Transfrontic ambulances begin to operate</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/saude-ambulancias-transfronteiricas-comecam-a-operar/</link><description>It is already possible to transport an ambulance of a patient between Zhuhai and Macau, without the need to change vehicles on the border. According to the Unit Police services, the “launch ceremony of the Transfronho Transport Service was held on point point to point 'hospital' between Zhuhai and Macau” in the main building of the popular government of the city of Zhuhai.
To activate the mechanism, a “prior agreement between the issuing hospital and the receiving hospital is required, taking into account the needs, safety and interests of patients”. This process will operate in parallel with the old “ambulance-ambulance” model, which forces patients to change ambulance in the areas of border control, allowing “those who do not meet the conditions for direct transfringe transportation of ambulance” to resort to the old model.
The hospitals involved in the new service are the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, the popular hospital in the city of Zhuhai, the fifth affiliate hospital at Sun Yat-Sen University, the Zhuhai Hospital of the Guangdong Traditional Medicine Hospital and the Chinese and Western Integrated Hospital of Zhuhai.
The transionic ambulance service was launched to respond to the expected “addition of the demand for transfronight health care”, resulting from the “increase in the displacements of the large bay residents”. According to the government, it is "a new step in health cooperation between Zhuhai and Macau, injecting a new dynamic in the integrated development of regional health services."</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:36:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinema | Announced new guidelines for filming</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/cinema-anunciadas-novas-orientacoes-para-filmagens/</link><description>The running over 12 people during the recording of a persecution scene will lead the cultural institute to change instructions to filming teams in the territory. Authorities want to have more information about the recorded plans and scenes
 
The president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Deland Leong Wai Man, revealed that new guidelines will be issued for filming teams to work in the territory. The information was revealed yesterday, and appears following a road accident in February during the shooting of a movie.
According to Deland Leong, the different government departments are currently in communication to last the new plans and instructions. From the moment new filming teams want to come to Macau, the instructions will be distributed and will have to be followed.
The new guidelines also predict that production teams have to provide more detailed plans about filming in Macau, with the need to indicate the use of roads, street closure and vehicle driving. From these plans, the authorities will listen to the different departments, such as the Public Security Police Corps and the Traffic Affairs Services Directorate, to ensure that filming take place in a safer and more controlled environment.
To the media, Deland Leong Wai Man argued that following this new method, with more detailed information, the cinema industry will have a healthier development, given the current context.
Suspended shooting
At the same time, the IC official confirmed the maintenance of the suspension order of the film that was the source of an accident with 12 injured, including two 5 and 6 years old children. The accident happened in late February, when a driver lost control of the car while filming a chase scene.
Later, the case gained other dimensions when authorities revealed that the chase scene was being filmed by the interior team on the sidelines of the oriented guidelines.
About this episode, Leong reported that he is still being discussed, so no conclusions can not be issued. However, the official admitted that the hypothesis of canceling the license to record in Macao is on the table, as the team did not follow the initially issued guidelines.
The president of the IC has also been questioned whether the incident can contribute to large productions to avoid the territory. However, Leong dismissed this scenario and pointed out that last year more than 300 outdoor filming teams were in Macao, which said it was the highest number in history. The IC leader also pointed out that Macau is an increasingly attractive destination for movie recording.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:35:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture | Miguel de Senna Fernandes distinguished as ambassador</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/cultura-miguel-de-senna-fernandes-distinguido-como-embaixador/</link><description>The name of Macaense is on a list, with 942 individualities, prepared by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of China. The ambassador has as its functions the promotion and protection of immaterial cultural heritage
 
Miguel de Senna Fernandes was distinguished as Ambassador of National Intangible Cultural Heritage. The list of 942 names was announced on Monday night by China's Ministry of Culture and Tourism.
Since 2021 the theater in Patuá has been part of China's Intangible Cultural Heritage List. Miguel de Senna Fernandes was chosen as an ambassador for his role in the Dóci Papiaçám group, as well as co-founder is the playwright and director.
"I feel very honored and naturally happy. But mainly honored to have been chosen. Now, the responsibility, which was already big, becomes greater," said Senna Fernandes, in statements to HM. "Over these years, I have always had a group of very talented people and this award is theirs. This distinction is not individual, in this kind of things is never an individual work, it is a group work. It was through the group that it was externalized what was created," he added.
According to the official statement of the central government, the figure of the ambassador of National Intangible Cultural Heritage has as its functions to ensure the promotion and protection of cultural heritage. In addition to connecting protected cultural manifestations, the statement indicates that people are chosen for presenting “good morals” and “excellent competence” to protect and ensure the transmission of intangible cultural heritage. “The ambassadors of national immaterial cultural heritage are expected to play an exemplary role, actively perform inheritance activities, cultivation successors and contribute more to the protection of immaterial cultural heritage,” was indicated in the statement with new appointments.
More guarantees
Speaking to HM, Miguel de Senna Fernandes also revealed to see the distinction as a “very important guarantee” for the survival of the theater in Patuá, with the characteristics of the Macaense Theater. "It is a very important guarantee of the survival of theater with all the characteristics that over the years we have been establishing," said the playwright. "When we used to talk to people who did not understand this kind of jokes, humor, we had some reticence.
"The Dóci Papiaçá Group has always presented a satirical theater, which aimed at customs, whatever, with social criticism, derision and curse. It is the history of the maricon theater. The Macaense Theater is this. Of course we can do theater in Patuá, but without these characteristics it may not be a maricon theater," he argued.
Space for the community
Miguel de Senna Fernandes also highlighted the importance of distinction to the community. "It's very good, because at least in this area of ​​culture, the community has a role that is still relevant and this is important," he said. "We are seeing a macao quite different from what it was and in this sea of ​​people, in a kind of culture - the lack of better expression - more monolithic, the theater, the cultural Macaense is relevant is something good for the community and this is important," he said.
The next performance of the Dóci Papiaçá Group is scheduled for May 30 and 31, under the 35th of the Macao Arts Festival, with the name Cuza Tá Reni? (What is going on?, In Portuguese). The play will be presented at the large auditorium of the Macao Cultural Center. Macanese does not risk anticipating that the distinction will reflect on a greater impact on the level of public presence. However, it admits that the expectation of the organization of the festival is a full house.
Dreams for fulfilling
Regarding the future of the theater in Patuá and the Dóci Papiaçám, Senna Fernandes confesses that the “big dream” at this stage is going to return to Portugal to act.
The last time the group acted in Portugal was in 1999, even before the transfer of sovereignty from Macau to China. “The dream is to go to Portugal,” he confessed. "It's a matter of money and logistics. Last year, the choir has been to Portugal, but now we want to take the theater and I'm seriously working on it," he said. "The last time the theater went to Portugal was in 1999. And we have never been there!
However, Portugal is not the only objective. The co-founder also believes that in the future it will be possible to have an action inside China, although admitting that the molds of this performance, despite the will, are not thought out.
Belief and custom
Regarding Macao, besides Miguel de Senna Fernandes, the name of Lo Seng Chung, as Ambassador of the belief and customs of Tou Tei.
The beliefs of Tou Tei concern one of the best known Chinese gods, also called "Tou Tei Kong", "Foc Tac Cheng San" or "Tai Pak Kong". According to the Cultural Institute, it is "one of the most popular Chinese gods" and regarded by believers "as responsible for matters such as the protection of life, the health and wealth of residents, among other aspects."</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:33:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club | Adopted all available cats</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/jockey-club-adoptados-todos-os-gatos-disponiveis/</link><description>The adoption campaign that aimed to prevent shipping by Macao Jockey Club from about 100 cats to an uncertain destination in Zhuhai ended with all the available animals adopted.
The information was released yesterday by the Macao Animal - Protective Society, in a statement. According to the association, of the 25 cats available for adoption, 22 found a new home. There were three cats that could not be adopted, as they found to be infected with the Feline Panleucopenia virus (FPV). These will be treated and then delivered later to local associations.
The remaining 58 cats will be examined throughout this week to see if there are more cases of FPV infections. After the exams will be sent to associations such as the Association of the Macao Dogs and Cats Angel, Abandoned Animal Protection Association (AAPAM), Catfee or Anima.
“We would like to thank all the public members who participated in yesterday's event for their support, as well as the nine volunteers who helped us,” reads the statement. "In addition to the 22 cats who will have a happy home forever, the remaining 61 cats will also receive better reset conditions, so they don't need to be transported to Zhuhai, which is the happiest news of all," he was added.
At this point, it is estimated that there are still about 15 cats that are on the run and that need to be captured, and then sterilized. The anima has stated that there is a hope that the work will be completed by March 25.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:16:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over the referected zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Panama | Beijing criticizes economic coercion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/panama-pequim-critica-coercao-economica/</link><description>China yesterday avoided commenting on the deal reached by the Hong Kong Ck Hutchison conglomerate to sell its participation in the ports of the Panama channel to the Blackrock US fund, merely rejecting “economic coercion” on the international scene.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning has called on “consultation of the competent Chinese authorities” to obtain specific business details without referring directly to the transaction or reports of a possible Beijing interference to prevent the sale.
But he added that China rejects “economic coercion, hegemony and intimidation” at the international scene. The statements arise in a context of growing tension on the agreement, after criticism spread by a Hong Kong newspaper affiliated with Beijing.
The official portals of the Chinese administration in Macao and Hong Kong released on Friday the comment, widespread by the newspaper Ta Kung Pao, a publication of the former British colony seen as close to Beijing.
The newspaper considered that the deal it transferred to a consortium that includes Blackrock and the Investment Limited Terminal a participation of 80 percent in a set of port subsidiaries, which generate 43 ports in 23 countries, including ports at both ends of the Panama and Cristobal channel, "is not a normal commercial practice."
"Many [Chinese] Internet users have strongly criticized this agreement and CK Hutchison Holdings, considering it as a spineless assignment, aiming only at profit and forgetting justice, ignoring national interests and major national principles, betraying and selling all the Chinese people.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:56:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Trump says Chinese president visits Washington in a “not too distant future”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/trump-diz-que-presidente-chines-visita-washington-num-futuro-nao-muito-distante/</link><description>US President Donald Trump said on Monday that his Chinese counterpart Xi Jinping will visit Washington in a "not too distant future" in the face of the growing commercial tensions between the world's two largest economies due to the imposition of tariffs.
"This will happen in the not too distant future," Trump said to journalists during a meeting of the new Kennedy Center board, a famous cultural center of the capital Washington.
The US head of state also noted that senior Chinese government officials, “below” XI, will soon visit the US capital, although it has not advanced names or details about possible dates.
Trump mentioned Xi's visit when he said he received visits from foreign leaders in the White House in recent weeks and asked them how Washington was. The Republican stressed that he is “cleaning Washington”, including trying to clean tents used by homeless and graphitis.
Last week the US media had reported that Washington and Beijing began discussions about a summit between the leaders of both countries in June.
The Chinese press had already suggested the possibility of a meeting in April. Also the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper has advanced that Trump could move to China in April to meet Chinese homologist Xi Jinping.
Since the Republican's victory in US presidentials in November that Trump and Xi have expressed interest in holding a summit.
Open future
Since Trump's inauguration in January, US administration has threatened, and then suspended customs rates about Mexico and Canada, while committing to punish Europe and other business partners as well.
So far, China is the only country that has effectively faced widespread increases in Trump's rates decided.
The White House has imposed additional 20 percent rates on all goods from China, citing the role of the Asian country in the US Fentanil crisis. Beijing retaliated quickly at his own rates, adapting the answer to avoid climbing the tensions.
Other actions that are being considered by the Trump business team include restricting Chinese investment in the US and US investment in China, aiming at China-dominated industries such as shipbuilding, and further limiting the sale of high-tech products to Chinese companies.
Trump and Xi had already talked by telephone in January, days before the inauguration of the American for his second term, in a conversation in which they discussed business relations and the future in the United States of the Chinese company by the company bytedance.
Donald Trump said he was open to negotiating a new trade agreement with China and praised Xi repeatedly.
The two leaders reached an agreement in 2020 to end the trade war that harmed both economies. However, bilateral relations deteriorated with the covid-19 pandemic, which Trump attributed to China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:47:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Commerce | Beijing wants to integrate exporters in the domestic market compared to protectionism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/comercio-pequim-quer-integrar-exportadores-no-mercado-interno-face-a-proteccionismo/</link><description>Changes in world economic structure, triggered by US protectionist measures, lead the Chinese government to intensify the promotion of domestic consumption
 
China is studying measures to help export-dependent companies expand in the domestic market at a time when it seeks to compensate for the impact of protectionist measures on the United States and other markets.
The Chinese Ministry of Trade is currently exploring the most effective ways to help exporters reorient themselves to the domestic market. Minister Wang Wenta visited a Wide Textile Commerce Company this weekend, according to Yuyuan Tantian, an account on the Chinese social network affiliated with state television CCTV.
For Chinese exporters, a change of focus to the domestic market brings a number of challenges, including adapting to different preferences of consumers, payment systems and regulatory regimes.
"Integrating domestic and external trade and supporting exporting companies in expanding their local sales will be a long-term strategy rather than a temporary response to external shocks," reads Yuyuan Tantian.
The measure arises after US President Donald Trump has an additional 20 percent customs taxes on all Chinese products. Washington will also be preparing to launch a broader reciprocal tariff regime next month.
Beijing retaliated with the imposition of customs rates on a series of US agricultural products and restricted the export of various essential minerals.
But the trade war is already felt throughout the Chinese economy. China exports grew 2.3 percent, in homologous terms, during the first two months of 2025, a significant slowdown compared to the 10.7 percent growth in December.
Beijing also summoned Walmart executives for conversations last week, after being reported that the US retailer giant pressed Chinese suppliers to lower prices to compensate for the impact of increasing customs rates.
But Chinese companies face protectionist measures on other markets as well, including Europe and developing countries. Indonesia, for example, imposed up to 200 percent rates on Chinese textile products in order to protect the country's small and medium -sized companies against what it considers to be unfair competition.
The US is also an important market for China's textile and clothing industry. About 17 percent of Chinese textile exports and clothing went to that country last year, according to Yuyuan Tantian.
Look inside
To support the transition to domestic sales, the Ministry of Commerce plans to organize a series of exhibitions across the country to advise exporters to adapt their sales channels and product standards to the domestic market.
"The expansion of domestic sales to foreign trade companies is not about the flow of exports not sold - it has to do with the introduction of high quality foreign trade products in the domestic market," said CCTV -affiliated account.
The strategy fits the growing efforts of Beijing to increase domestic demand. On Monday, the government revealed a vast plan to stimulate consumption, which includes from reducing the costs of child care to stabilization of real estate markets and scholarships.
Signs of improvement are gradually emerging. Data released on Monday showed that retail sales in China increased 4 percent, in homologous terms, in the first two months of 2025, exceeding analysts' expectations.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:46:02</pubDate></item><item><title>London | Hong Kong names new cabinet leader</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/londres-hong-kong-nomeia-nova-lider-do-gabinete/</link><description>Hong Kong yesterday named Fiona Chau Suet-Mui as a new director general of the Chinese semi-autonomous commercial office in London, ten months after a spy scandal involving a leader of this cabinet.
In a statement, the Hong Kong government said Fiona Chau will immediately take over the position that has so far belonged to Gilford Law Sun-On, highlighted in the United Kingdom capital since 2021. Chau will be responsible for promoting Hong Kong bilateral relations with the United Kingdom, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Lithony, Norway, Russia and Sweden.
Cited in the statement, the manager promised to work to promote Hong Kong's “international competitiveness” and “strengthen economic, commercial and cultural bonds” with nine countries. Chau, who had already worked at Hong Kong's commercial offices in Washington and Brussels, was until yesterday responsible for urban renewal policies in the Department of Development of the Territory Government.
This appointment comes ten months after Bill Yuen Chung-Biu, 63, an office manager, was accused of helping Hong Kong information services and foreign interference.
Yuen and two other suspects, Peter Wai Chi-Leung, 38, and 37-year-old Matthew Trickett were arrested in early May and placed under coercion measures. Trickett was found dead a week after going to court in a park in Maidenhing, west of London, and British police started an investigation into the case.
At the time of the detention, the representation of the Chinese Foreign Ministry in Hong Kong “vehemently condemned the British government for“ making accusations, arbitrarily arresting Chinese citizens and defaming ”the Hong Kong government.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:43:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Russia | Announced telephone contact between Putin and Trump</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/russia-anunciado-contacto-telefonico-entre-putin-e-trump/</link><description>The presidency of Russia announced yesterday that the Russian and American presidents will talk on the phone today, for the second time since Donald Trump took office as head of state in January.
"This conversation is indeed prepared," Russian presidency spokesman Dmitri Peskov told a press conference in Moscow. According to Peskov, this is a telephone contact scheduled for today.
Last week, Russian President Vladimir Putin said he was willing to argue with US counterpart Donald Trump, “doubts” about the 30-day respite in Ukraine, which Kiev has already accepted.
In response to the proposal, Putin said Russia supports a truce, but sees many problems in the implementation and verification of a ceasefire. Moscow also indicated that Kiev uses the break to regroup and rear.
Putin and Trump first spoke on February 12. In the first (official) telephone contact, the two leaders agreed to start a negotiation process to end the conflict in Ukraine. Ukraine was invaded by Russia in 2014, when the Crimea Peninsula was attached and, in 2022, launched a large military offensive against the Ukrainian territory.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:41:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Timor-Leste received over a billion euros from extractive industry in 2022</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/timor-leste-recebeu-mais-de-mil-milhoes-de-euros-de-industria-extractiva-em-2022/</link><description>Timor-Leste received $ 1.4 billion from the extractive industry in 2022, according to an initiative for Transparency in Extractive Industries (EITI).
"Regarding the amount of revenues paid by companies to the state there was a difference between 2021, with a total budget of $ 729 million [669 million euros], and 2022, where the total budget reached $ 1.401 billion," said EITI's Timorese coordinator, Emília de Jesus.
Emilia de Jesus spoke during the presentation of the EITI Annual Report for the year 2022, in Dili, which was attended by the Minister of Oil and Mineral Resources, Francisco Monteiro, civil society and university students. According to the coordinator, the recipes were obtained through taxes, FTP (First Tronche Petroleum), 'royalties' and rates.
The report also recalled that in April 2022 Timor-Leste obtained the "high global" score in the implementation of EITI standards for 2019, with a total of 58 points.
But EITI has recommended “corrective measures”, which should be implemented before the next validation, related to coordination, priority alignment, impact of data on public debate on the sector and with limitations on new project information.
During the presentation, EITI's Timorese coordinator stressed that there were delays in the dissemination and dissemination of information because of the Covid-19 pandemic.
Shared wisdom
Timor-Leste joined this initiative in 2003, with the aim of ensuring transparency and accountability in the management of natural resources, namely oil, gas and minerals. In addition, one of EITI's fundamental roles is to facilitate public access to information, promoting their dissemination by various means.
"The purpose of this seminar is to ensure transparency in the mining sector and facilitate access to information to the public, in order to stimulate debates on the management of natural resources in the country. Timor-Leste continues to be considered an example in the transparent management of its natural resources," said the coordinator.
The Minister of Oil and Mineral Resources, Francisco da Costa Monteiro, highlighted the importance of spreading that information, since it allows to gather various sectors of society to discuss the natural riches of Timor-Leste.
"This is an activity performed annually through independent audits conducted by international entities, which analyze the values ​​that Timor-Leste receives from the strategic sector of oil and minerals.
The document also states that Timor-Leste is already creating a legal framework that favors the energy transition and green energy, including the development of carbon capture, use and storage initiatives, and to finalize the publication of EITI reports for the years 2023 and 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:40:00</pubDate></item><item><title>G7 | Beijing denounces “duplicity of criteria” on military spending</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/g7-pequim-denuncia-duplicidade-de-criterios-sobre-gastos-militares/</link><description>China yesterday accused the G7 of applying “two weights and two measures” in defense, rejecting the concerns expressed in a recent bloc summit on Beijing's military expenses and cooperation with Russia.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning expressed Beijing's “firm rejection” about what she called “unfounded distortions and attacks” in the joint statement of G7's foreign ministers (Germany, Canada, the United States, France, Italy, Japan, the United Kingdom and the European Union).
"China's defense expenses are necessary to safeguard our sovereignty, security and development interests.
Mao criticized the western group of countries for "neglecting his own responsibilities" and "avoiding talking about the risks of nuclear proliferation generated by the Aukus Alliance between the United States, the United Kingdom and Australia." The Chinese spokeswoman added that "instead of approaching these dangers, the G7 chooses to aim at China, which is a blatant duplicate of criteria."
The diplomat rejected the accusations of the alleged supply of military equipment to Russia in the context of the conflict in Ukraine, ensuring that "China has never provided lethal weapons to either party involved" and that the export policy of double -use products "is governed by strict controls."
Regarding the G7's allegations that "Chinese overproduction" distorts global markets, Mao said such accusations "were denied by the facts" and accused the "politicity of economic and commercial relations" countries.
The G7 statement also reiterated the opposition to any unilateral attempt to "change the status quo by force" in Taiwan's narrow, a reference that China has rejected strongly.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:36:24</pubDate></item><item><title>China | Announced plan to “vigorously boost” spending</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/china-anunciado-plano-para-impulsionar-vigorosamente-gastos/</link><description>China yesterday announced a plan to revitalize domestic consumption, at a time when Beijing struggles to promote consumer confidence and combat deflationist pressures in the world's second largest economy.
The government will “propel vigorously consumption” and “expand internal demand in all directions,” said the Official News Agency Xinhua, echoing the appeal of Chinese President Xi Jinping at the end of last year, for political decision makers to support demand, following a sustained impulse to drive the industry.
The Council of State (Executive) plan will focus on increasing income, stabilizing the real estate sector and the scholarship market and improving medical and pension services, although political officials have provided few details on tax expenses during a press conference in Beijing.
During the conference, the authorities largely repeated the figures published in the annual budget last week during the plenary session of the National Popular Assembly, where delegates reaffirmed consumption as a top priority.
The Hang Seng Kong Hang Index rose 0.8 percent, while Brent's oil futures, the international reference of oil, rose 0.6 for a central to $ 71 per barrel. The CSI 300 index of mainland China, which brings together the largest companies quoted in Shanghai and Shenzhen, ended with a drop of 0.2 percent.
Consumer spending on China has been weak since the end of the Covid-19 pandemic for more than two years, as families have been cautious about expenses. Consumer prices registered deflation in February, although reading was affected by the Lunar New Year holiday.
The softening of China's vast real estate sector, partly driven by a government's breakdown initiative that is already in its fourth year, has also revived economists' appeals to reinforce internal demand.
New targets
Last September, the political decision makers revealed a long-awaited package to support the economy, but the measures focused mainly on scholarship markets.
The new consumer plan includes promises to increase the minimum wage, reinforce support for education, and create a child custody subsidy system, a pressing issue, as China's population has been decreasing for three consecutive years.
Lynn Song, chief economist at Dutch Bank Ing to Greater China, wrote that the plan puts "a considerable emphasis on increasing families' ability and willingness" and could "help China's economic transition to a consumer-oriented growth model."
Data released on Monday also showed that industrial production grew 5.9 percent in homologous terms in the first two months of 2025, slowing over the 6.2-one hundred recorded in December, but exceeding the expectations of analysts of a 5.3 percent increase.
The new measuring package will also promote “internal” consumption. Beijing widened the exemption of visas to dozens of countries last year, in an effort to relaunch international tourism after pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:34:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Real Estate | Prices of the new houses fall for the 21st consecutive month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/18/imobiliario-precos-das-casas-novas-caem-pelo-21o-mes-consecutivo/</link><description>New houses prices in China fell for the 21st consecutive month in February, at a faster pace than in January, despite government measures to face the long sector crisis.
Prices in 70 selected cities fell 0.14 percent, according to calculations made based on the figures released yesterday by China's National Statistics Office (NBS), which had reflected a 0.07 percent contraction in January.
Among the localities mentioned, 45 registered reductions in housing prices compared to 42 in January, while 18 - including some important ones such as Beijing, Shanghai and Shenzhen - to record increases, less than the previous month (24).
The calculations made based on NBS data also reflect a 0.34 percent reduction in the price of secondhand houses in February, the same rate as in the previous month. In the case of this type of real estate, 65 of the 70 cities registered descents, two remained at the same level as January and three registered climbs.
In recent months, Chinese authorities have announced measures to wrap the real estate market, an issue that worries Beijing due to implications for social stability, as housing is one of the main investment vehicles of Chinese families.
One of the main causes of the recent slowdown of the economy is precisely the crisis in the real estate sector, whose weight in the Chinese Gross Domestic Product (GDP) - adding the indirect factors - was estimated at about 30 percent by different analysts.</description><pubDate>2025-03-18 00:32:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Ruby Hui, President of the Macao Autism Association: “Autism differs from person to person”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/19/ruby-hui-presidente-da-associacao-de-autismo-de-macau-autismo-difere-de-pessoa-para-pessoa/</link><description>Created in 2012, the Macao Autism Association continues to fight for more care for children and young people with this development disturbance. But the association's president, Ruby Hui, warns of the need for more incisive policies for adolescents and their specific needs, especially in access to employment
 
 
What balance does the work done by the association in recent years?
My work is above all to establish a connection with all the entities and resources made available by the government and also the game industry, as the authorities have started to [the context of the new game concession contracts] that develop more social support activities. Therefore, we have gathered all these resources to organize recreational activities for children and youth. In addition, we organize therapy sessions for our members. Usually, we request financial support from private companies and the government, covering 30 to 50 percent of these expenses.
The support of the game sector is therefore quite important.
Yes, but it has not really been a great support. For example, the government covers part of our monthly expenses, about 40,000 patacas. But this amount comes only to hire two full -time employees and one part -time employee. They are the ones who organize all activities, deal with the bureaucratic part, which includes the presentation of many reports to the government, because we ask for subsidies for almost half of our expenses.
Therefore, do you consider that they need more support from the executive to be able to hire more professionals?
Yes, it would be ideal. Associations like ours are getting bigger and the children we support are growing. I would say that 60 percent of our members are 11 or more, and about 20 percent are even larger, over 14 years old. We have to think about their future and the needs of therapy and treatment for adolescents, as it is not only small kids who need therapies such as speech or occupational therapy. They are young people who are still in high school and need to acquire different types of social skills, boys need to know how to deal with girls and vice versa. Then, when they become adults, they need to know how to deal with bosses in jobs. There are many valences to explore, but at this moment I would say that the supports are not enough.
Are schools not yet prepared to receive these students, for example?
Autism may be different from person to person. Students with autism, but who have better learning skills, are in normal schools. But parents tell me that there are not enough teachers with certain skills to deal with and teach these children. There are teachers who still have a very traditional mindset to treat these young people, who often have to deal with alone with bullying, for example. I would say that there are many children and young people with autism with psychological problems because of the school.
When it speaks of the traditional mindset, what does this mean in concrete?
In the case of my son, for example, he is obliged to always be sitting at school, but often likes to move and get up from his chair. From the point of view of parents who have children with this problem, there would be no problem, as long as it did not bother others, but for teachers it cannot be, and complain. They say things of the genre: "He will beat the table, he will move the painting, makes a lot of noise." Every day I receive complaints from parents to connect with the school, and for small situations like this.
What are the main difficulties or challenges that Macao families face when they deal with an autistic child?
In my case, my family is middle class, and we are financially well. But when my son was younger needed to do therapy and it was very expensive. Now these therapies cost even more. At the time my son was in primary education, 600 to 700 patacas was paid for each therapy session, but there are days a father told me that the sessions now cost about 1000 patacas per class, which is very expensive. Families of lower social classes cannot afford. Therefore, this support is one of the great objectives of our association, raising money so that we can provide explanations, therapy sessions or other type of support. All so that our members can attend classes with 50 percent discount, where the association pays half the amount.
When the association was created, what were its main objectives?
In 2012 autism was not a very spoken theme. Therefore, we joined [some parents and families] and we started to ask for support from the government and try to draw attention to the subject. We got some things because the government now gives more support to these young people, at least for those under 12. The problem we feel is that these young people are growing and adolescents need other types of supports that do not exist.
What is necessary to change in mindsets and society in relation to autism?
In Macao there are not many companies willing to hire young people with autism. Situation that is not seen in Hong Kong, where there are several hiring programs with social companies. Macau needs to follow this path.
One day in Rio
World Autism Consciousness Day is celebrated on April 2 and, in this context, the Macao Autism Association joined Sands China for a series of activities with children and parents, which took place last March 10th. Through the program “Sands Care”, the game operator provided a visit to the exhibition “Coastal Fantasia”, with the figure of “King Lobster”, a creation of Philip Colbert artist ” A boat trip through the Delta of the Pearl River.
In total, 70 people participated. Quoted by a game operator statement, Ruby Hoi said the tour "allowed children to enjoy the maximum of the trip." "Thank you for all the support provided to people with autism in Macau, and I hope that all sectors of society can continue to support the development of these people and promote their inclusion in society," he said.
For the game operator, this type of events can help “reinforce the cohesion of families dealing with autism, but also promote the awareness of society and support for the community of people with autism fostering a more inclusive and supportive social environment”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-19 01:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul French, writer: Looking for Wallis Simpson in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/paul-french-escritor-a-procura-de-wallis-simpson-na-china/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival, which starts on Friday, will feature the presence of writer Paul French, who launched last year a new biographical book, "Her Lotus Year", which describes Wallis Simpson's experience in China before being a Duchess of Windsor. The British author will also talk about “Destination Macau”, a nostalgic and almost cinematic account of the city's history
 
How did you come to the history of Wallis Simpson's life experience in China?
I lived in Shanghai for many years and many visitors knew that Wallis Simpson had spent time in the city. Rumors ran on what he had done, and visitors always wanted to know if the rumors were true, such as the idea that she had learned esoteric sexual techniques or had posed naked for photographs. It was also said that he had belonged to a group of opium smuggling, or a group of bets that combined horses races. For me, as an author and expert in foreign experiences in Shanghai in the first half of the twentieth century, none of this made sense. So I thought this was the ideal time to really find out what Wallis had done in China. The fact that she was in the country in 1924 and 1925, two of the most fascinating years in the history of modern China, helped a lot.
How do you describe the life of the duchess in the country during that specific political period?
China was in total chaos when she was there, because Puyi, the last emperor, had been expelled from the forbidden city and occurred the biggest strikes ever in Hong Kong history. In addition, political fractions were recorded in Guangzhou, warlords of war in Shanghai and northern China. These were also the most wet years that there is a record in China, with crop production breaks and the occurrence of tiphoid and cholera fever outbreaks. He fired the number of bandits and pirates. Then, in March 1925, Sun Yat-Sen, leader of the Republican Revolution of 1911, died without leaving an obvious successor. Wallis came across all this, as he was retained on the island of Shamian, Guangzhou, while the city struggled; In Shanghai, he saw corpses to be brought to the city from the battles of the warlords; He saw victims of typhus and anger in Tianjin; and troops of the warlords threatening Beijing. But he was also largely in a foreign protective bubble that protected her from foreign soldiers and her white skin. He could delight in China's culture and aesthetics, while around him the whole country threatened to explode.
How was the personality of Wallis Simpson, a controversial figure in the context of the marriage to the Duke of Windsor?
It is very important not to confuse Wallis of 1924 with the later Wallis, from the long years of exile and controversy as Duchess of Windsor. In 1924 Wallis was only 28 years old, fleeing from a physically abusive husband (her first husband, Win Spencer, an American Navy commander) and was not yet particularly sophisticated or cosmopolitan. These were characteristics that would learn in China, mingling in the “colonies” [concessions] international foreign and bohemiums of Shanghai and Beijing. In fact, it was in Beijing that it first mixed with ambassadors, high -level Chinese politicians, high -ranking military officers and a stretch, and from them learned everything from playing Bridge and enjoying Jade to how to behave in high society. Obviously, this was useful a decade later when he met the Prince of Wales in England. Admittedly, the posterior Wallis, the Duchess, is a more difficult figure to like. Perhaps she and the Duke have made some bad political decisions and made some friendships, perhaps Wallis became a little bitter for not being accepted by the British royal family. But the truth is that in 1924 she was young, free of a bad husband and was in one of the most fascinating countries in the world.
What can readers perceive this figure and about China of that time, with "Her Lotus Year"?
China in 1925 was on the brink of potential explosion, as the whole country could have fallen into total chaos, dividing into the size of Portugal managed by warlords with private armies, or a resurgent Qing Dynasty supported by Japan in the North [China], the South and, of course, the foreign powers-England, America, France and Japan-who had Chinese lands like colonies. Ultimately, this did not happen, but no one knew this in 1925. Wallis herself oscillated between feeling incredibly comfortable and happy in what was her "year of lotus," as he described him, quoting Homer's Sopoifers who never want to return home; and feel terrified of the violence of the warlords or those who were against foreigners.
What are the biggest challenges, as a writer, in the process of researching the history of Wallis?
Wallis probably became the most photographed and spoken woman in history, more than Marilyn Monroe, more than Queen Isabel II. But in 1924 she was not famous at all. So it left a very difficult trail to follow. He wrote his memories, but these were "disinfected." A big problem was also the rumors that the British government and secret services circulated in 1936 in an attempt to destroy the idea of ​​a marriage between King Eduardo VIII and Wallis. The attempt failed because he abdicated the throne and they married, but these sexual rumors and insinuations, many of them racist and misogynists, have remained to this day, and they continue to be regularly recycled in the British and American Tabloid Press. I found the real Wallis a much more friendly character than I expected, and I hope readers will feel that too.
É convidado de mais uma edição do Rota das Letras. Como se sente por fazer parte do festival? 
I love to be part of the Macao Literary Festival. Although he had spoken before in Macao, namely in the Portuguese bookstore and other places, he had never participated in the festival. I look forward to being able to talk about Wallis Simpson and also about my new collection of rehearsals about Macau, entitled "Destination Macau". Some stories of Macao that have pleased me over the years, some of them presented with a more English look, as it were, may be interested and will be new to the local public.
Livro | “Destination Macau”, a cidade entre “o imaginário e o real” 
Paul French has just launched the third volume of the “Destination” collection, which had editions of Shanghai or Beijing, and is now dedicated to telling stories of the ancient macao, a “place as imaginary as real”, as described the synopsis of the work. The work of the British author presents "The Macao by artists George Chinnery and George Smirnoff, the writers Deolinda da Conceição and Maurice Dekobra, to the fantasies of" Pulp Fiction "and febrile dreams of Josef Von Sternberg and Jean Delannoy."
There is still no shortage of Paul French, stories around historical figures such as Pedro José Lobo and Ian Fleming, author and creator of James Bond. Macao of the time of World War II, those who “came to Macao in search of gold, and those who sought war refuge” is described, not forgetting “the combatants looking for a secret passage through the 'neutral' macao”.
Paul French unveil mysteries or tells forgotten stories to many, such as the idea that Japan had tried to buy Macau in 1934 or the person who sailed with the Macau pirates queen, Lai Choi San. There are, in all, 18 stories “true of fascinating people who lived or visited Macau in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Augusto Nogueira, President of Artm: “Macau is ahead of Hong Kong”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/augusto-nogueira-presidente-da-artm-macau-esta-a-frente-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Macao toxicode dependent rehabilitation association is 25 years old this year. Augusto Nogueira makes a positive balance of the fourth century that began with a small therapeutic community and reached international recognition. The Association's president argues that, in prevention, Macau is at the head of Hong Kong and that the use of synthetic drugs is not yet problematic in the territory
 
 
What balance does the work developed by ArtM in these 25 years?
We do the balance very positive, because we started with a small area and a small therapeutic community. Nowadays we have a community with a capacity of 60 people, much more than the 15 we had at the time. We have developed several programs, namely the syringe distribution, which is a success, because it has led to a reduction and almost suppression of HIV contagion by people who inject drugs. For nine years there is the program and we have zero cases of infection. We developed support for social integration and follow -up after treatment, with “After Care”. We do preventive work in schools with the “Be Cool” program. We have the project “Hold on To Hope”, betting on vocational education, through coffee and the art gallery. It is a project that is well achieved and that turns out to be turned to tourism. We have visits from international entities and various non-governmental organizations, and the United Nations themselves. The most positive for us is to know how many people are recovered and who are well today. Unfortunately, we could not recover all people, but in each relapse there is always the possibility of the person coming again to do treatment.
How many people have recovered in 25 years?
We couldn't get this notion. We maintain contact with many people, but others have already left Macau, followed their lives. We have some contacts in the first two years after treatment, but then life goes on. People also want to go on a lifetime with no connection with the artm, sometimes marry and new companions don't know about their previous life and want to keep some confidentiality. But sometimes we meet. The other day they paid me a water without me knowing (laughs). These are small gestures that give us satisfaction to continue and make us believe that recovery is always possible.
What are the big challenges to maintain the ArtM project in terms of space and financing?
In terms of space and places for treatment we are well. The facilities are ten years old, there are maintenance problems, but this is more related to the panorama of construction in Macao. We need a space for the After Care, because what we have currently rented and is deteriorated. We are talking to the Institute of Social Action (IAS) to have a new space. With regard to the back, all our departments have financing, but we obviously seek support for our activities otherwise.
Regarding the authorities' posture regarding consumption and treatment, do you understand that it is still conservative in relation to other countries and regions?
This question is a little ambiguous. In terms of treatment and strategy in combating consumption, I think Macau is very ahead of Hong Kong, for example. In Macao, we have therapeutic community, we work on prevention and treatment, as well as our syringes and methadone distribution program. We have a range of treatments available to those in need. In the area of ​​prevention, the government has given a lot of support. The IAS has been quite open in strategies to combat consumption and prevention. In Hong Kong, for example, there is no syringe distribution program. Macao is from the few regions of Southeast Asia that has a government -supported syringes distribution program. But there could be another different interpretation of the law, with a differentiation between what is trafficking and their own consumption. For example, at this time if the person has a higher amount than that stipulated is soon considered trafficking, without proof. We think that in this case there should be a differentiation. It is then up to the police to investigate whether the quantities found are for consumption or trafficking. There should be an opening to give people more opportunities to be referred for treatment instead of going to prison. But lately, there have not been as many cases as that.
How do you describe the current consumer profile in Macau?
There is a large reduction in heroin consumption, and the few people who did so consume it today, or sleep. At this time the highest consumption is metabetamin, cannabis and some ketamine residues. As for the new synthetic drugs, there have been some records, but so far nothing alarming. But of course we have to be alert, we have to continue to do a good prevention job so that people are aware of the problems related to drug use. Regarding trafficking, we know that before the pandemic there was much cocaine trafficking to Macao, and after Covid-19 this situation almost ceased to happen. A good dissuasive work has been done and has to continue to be done so that there is less traffic to pass through Macau. It does not mean that there are no situations currently, but we are not in such a chaotic situation as that.
Speaking of synthetic drugs and their consumption, which according to the latest United Nations report has reached a worrying situation around the world. What is your comment to the scenario described in the annual report of the International Narcotics Control Board?
It is evident that the use of this type of drugs has been increasing over the years. Synthetic drugs are a real problem in the United States of America, for example, with fentanyl consumption, and Asia in some countries. It is a global problem because consumption and production are easy. Some of these drugs are made with other chemicals and many other products that are not well known to the origin and that can cause many overdoses. The UN suggests combating the production of ingredients that are used to produce these drugs, continue to reinforce the investigation to catch traffickers. But there are points of this report that it is necessary to follow, for many countries, which is the struggle between ideologies.
In what sense?
There is a struggle between those who argue that harm reduction is sufficient to combat all these problems that are arising, and that it is the solution to everything. Then we have those who think that harm reduction is not missing. In the artm we consider that there has to be a balance, because prevention is something important that cannot stop. What happened in Portugal, for example, when they liberalized the drug and failed to prevent and support treatment, [it was not good], and today Portugal is again in a slightly chaotic situation at consumption and trafficking. This means that prevention can never cease to exist. There should be quality treatments, with supervision of entities. The speed of access to treatment has to exist, and it can not be like in some countries where people have been waiting for a vacancy or permission to enter, as non -governmental organizations do not let the person enter until they receive the subsidy for each bed and patient. In these months a lot can happen. Damage reduction should be seen as a continuity for recovery, with rooms for consumption with medical and technical support, or syringe management programs. There is another problem, especially in Europe, which is heroin consumers, when they reach a more advanced age, already have many health problems and need sites to be, of a certain dignity. We have been wasting a lot of time with these ideological wars, and some of them exist for the sake of power, to influence the liberalization of drugs, and this is quite harmful. People's rights end when it is beginning to harm the rights of all other people, there must be a balance. As the report also says, there is a lack of medicines for some countries in Africa.

Art
To commemorate the 25th anniversary, the artm inaugurated on Friday the “Exhibition of the 25th Anniversary of Artm”, which is evident in the Hold on To Hope Gallery until the 23rd of this month. In the cultural space in the village of Nossa Senhora in Ká-Hó, which is part of the Occupational Therapy Program for the Arts users, you can see an art show done by these, with 45 works of ceramic, painting and wooden works. According to a press release of the association, the exhibition “celebrates resilience, creativity and healing”. “Throughout the last quarter of the century, the artm has been a symbol of hope for individuals in its journey of recovery of dependence. This exhibition presents the extraordinary works of art created by our residents,” he is also read.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Debbie Lai, director of the center of the good shepherd | “Victims need more protection”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/debbie-lai-directora-do-centro-do-bom-pastor-vitimas-precisam-de-mais-proteccao/</link><description>Regarding International Women's Day, which was celebrated around the world on Saturday, HM talked to Debbie Lai, director of the center of the good shepherd, one of the entities that welcomes victims of domestic violence in the territory. The official defends speed in investigations of cases of domestic violence and more days of maternity leave
 
 
Regarding domestic violence, the law remains not revised, with many cases where it cannot be accused or condemned the aggressor. What needs to be changed in current legislation?
You should accelerate the time spent in investigating the case, as well as to make a simple promotion of the law, to let people understand what they will face if they report the situation to the police. There is still afraid of the complaint to the police, so what happens is that the aggressor, before a complaint, gets angry, again committing violence and the family is departed.
How many women are currently at the center of the good shepherd?
According to the License of Service granted by the Institute of Social Action (IAS), we can welcome 14 people, including children. We currently have 11 people, six women, three children and two girls living in our center. Some of these women have problems due to emotional conflicts, and although they already have some stability at this level, they continue to have financial difficulties. Many of these women are not permanent residents, so they are unable to apply for government social housing, and they need more time to save money to pay an income in Macao, which is not cheap. If young children exist, it is harder for them to find a full -time job, so these women cannot move in a short time for a home, staying in our center a year. And in this situation, the center cannot have more empty rooms to help other women in crisis.
Do you consider that more reception centers are needed for victims of violence in Macao, or more resources to ensure the victim's safety, since the territory is so small?
I think the resources are sufficient, but the investigation process is time consuming. Victims need more protection, as there is always the risk that the perpetrator continues to threaten them.
What is necessary to increase the birth rate and ensure that women continue to have access to equal economic and employment opportunities?
Promotion needs to be continuous, and should increase maternity leave, as in other countries there are more maternity leave. The monthly value of day care centers could also be decreased. The attribution of a subsidy by each child could also be considered if the family has financial problems.
There is a lack of support for single -padded families, where women are alone with dependent children, or where women are caregivers? In concrete terms, what needs to be improved?
I think yes. I think some of them do not know that there are resources in society to help them, or may not have motivation to seek help. Many of these women also do not want to rely on government, not even non -governmental associations or organizations that provide services to the family. But these women can always apply for the subsidy attributed by the Institute of Social Action, which gives them some money and allows you to stay at home to take care of their children.
How do you describe women in Macao currently, especially the Chinese community? Are you more emancipated and equal to men regarding their rights?
Nowadays the capacity of women has changed a lot, as they have equal opportunities and the right to develop. Many local companies are already chaired by women, for example. In addition to having physical strength, they can choose their jobs, attend higher education, marry and have the ability to take leadership positions. However, there are many women who come to Macau and marry residents and have a lower social position, suffering from various family problems. I speak of machismo that still exists, the addiction of the game, situations of toxicodependence or lack of communication. There are men who control everything, creating a climate in which the wife has to hear her husband and is devoid of self-esteem to get out of this situation. In such cases, it is very easy to have discussions, conflicts and even cases of violence between the couple. These are situations that obviously also affect their children.
International Women's Day celebrated in Macau
International Women's Day was celebrated in Macao in very diverse ways. In the case of Sands China, flowers were offered to the operator's workers as a way of expressing “the appreciation for the indispensable contributions that women make in the workplace, in the family and society”, can read in a company statement. It was also organized a debate that focused on the issues around women, organized by the Sands Empowher volunteer team, a “global initiative of diversity and inclusion led by women, which aims to connect the team's female members to create network job opportunities”. This event was broadcast live on Sands China's various digital platforms.
Sands Empowher is, above all, to organize training and mentoring actions so that women can develop in professional and career terms.
In the same note, it states that the company “is committed to building and maintaining a workplace with respect and equality”, defending and guaranteeing women's rights. Regarding sexual harassment, Sands states that it has carried out a campaign to prevent cases since July 2018, as well as actions that reduce cases of discrimination against women.
This was “the first in Macao”, and a “training action with all team members” on these themes was also carried out. Regarding support for maternity, "the company also offers breastfeeding rooms for mothers and performs a wide variety of activities for parents and children to promote family harmony."
At the Portuguese School of Macao, International Women's Day was celebrated on Friday with the DAC project-“Women who inspire”, an initiative organized by the teachers of the disciplines of Portuguese, Philosophy and Mathematics, among others. The 10th grade students have developed several works on inspiring women in the most diverse areas. One of them was the recently deceased poet Maria Teresa Horta.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 03:54:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP Macau | FIA confirms GT World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/gp-macau-fia-confirma-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The World Council of the FIA ​​last Wednesday confirmed the expected, that the eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be held as part of the Macao's 72nd Grand Program, from November 13 to 16. However, there is a big news for this year's edition
 
The International Federation, which co-organizes this race in partnership with Sro Motorsports Group and the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), took the opportunity to announce a new qualification model for the race. In addition to the 30 -minute qualification session equal to the previous editions (Q1), a second qualification segment (Q2) was added, reserved for the top ten pilots of the first session.
The Q2 session will be held in Super Pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification turns, and each pilot is also allowed to use a new tire set at this session. This novelty will allow qualification to be decided without interference from third parties.
The remaining program of the Queen of GT will remain the same as the previous editions, with the free training session, the traditional 12-lap classification race on Saturday afternoon, followed by the 16-lap main race that will decide the world's Cup winner on Sunday.
Veterans compliments
These measures introduced by the FIA ​​were very well received by the most experienced GT riders. This is because traffic has always been a huge obstacle in obtaining a good qualification return on the guide circuit, something essential for those who aim to win this title.
"It's an excellent idea to introduce the Super Pole session in Macao," said German Maro Engel, the winner of the World Cup last edition by Mercedes-AMG. This will be one of the most spectacular and exciting sessions of the season and should also secure sports justice.
Raffaele Marciello, for two occasions winning of this trophy, and one of the BMW factory riders, also reacted positively, adding: “In Macao, it was always complicated to make a clean return with this new format, you will not hear the excuse of traffic or a red flag.
This is an opinion shared by Laurens Vanthoor, the World Cup winner in 2016, who said there will no longer be “apologies” in the qualification. The experienced Belgian pilot of Porsche believes that “there will be an added pressure because you only have these two turns”, because in a difficult circuit like this, “if you make a mistake, there is nothing more.
And the younger ones too
Chinese pilot Yifei Ye premiered at the Grand Prix last November at the World Cup. Ferrari's official pilot, which competes in the Endurance Fia World Championship (WEC), has left a good impression on the guide circuit, and he also welcomes the now introduced measurements.
“It's good to eliminate these red flag interventions and yellow flags, so that in the end, the one that really is the fastest to get pole position,” said Yifei Ye that she could return to the race this year. "In Macao, everyone is very close in terms of times, so it will be extremely difficult for pilots to try to reach Super Pole.</description><pubDate>2025-02-28 01:03:51</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Célio Alves Dias will continue to run this season</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/gp-celio-alves-dias-vai-continuar-a-correr-esta-temporada/</link><description>Macaense pilot Célio Alves Dias was one of the long -term returns of the 2024 car.
 
The Macao Cup winner of Macau in 2021 was removed from motorsport at the time of 2023 for personal reasons, but last year made his debut in the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8). Despite the vast experience in tests of the specialty, having conducted several generations of tourism cars, Célio Alves Dias had never managed the new bobbinns that the Macao-China General Association (AAMC) introduced in its competition in 2023. Last time turned out to be of learning, with some difficulties in the tuning and behavior of the Japanese car.
Participation in races at the Zhuzhou International Circuit and the Macau Grand Prix made Célio Alves Dias realize that his Toyota GR86 was not at the strongest competition level. Based on the conclusions drawn from these experiences, he decided to start preparing for the new season.
"The car had to be all dismantled. My car was bought on Monday, and the chassis and the security arc, for me, were not well done," explained Fu Lei Racing Team pilot to HM. "This, it made the car too hard and very difficult to bow. I tried a well -assembled car, and there is a difference in January, in China, with this car.
If in the Macao Grand Prix, the house riders, excellent guide circuit, managed to equate the progress to their hong Kong opponents and the interior of China, in the initial races on the Zhuzhou track in Hunan province, it wasn't quite like that. "There are many differences between cars, but especially in chassis, because the engines, in terms of power and horses, are almost all at the same level. Our opponents have also experienced many pieces, many engines, even speed boxes, and chassis. Competition cars are always the same.
Silver Jubilee in November
Being a usual Portuguese name in the Macao Grand Prix in recent decades, Célio Alves Dias debuted at the Guide Circuit in 2000 and from then was a frequent presence and no faults in the race until 2023. This year, its objective is to account for its twenty-fifth participation in the biggest sports event of RAEM, but will have to align in the findings.
While awaiting the announcement of the 2025 calendar by AAMC, Célio Alves Dias details details to start his test program, because his Toyota, after being reviewed, "is ready to test" in the interior of China, something that will happen "very soon," says the pilot.
In the last edition of the Grand Prix, Célio Alves Dias qualified in 12th place for the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. However, his participation was short and unhappy: at the wheel of Toyota with dorsal No. 11, was forced to give up after being immobilized on the climb of San Francisco. The Macanese pilot was out of the race on the first lap, in an incident that caused the Safety Car.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:50:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Iame Asia finals of Karting back in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/finais-da-iame-asia-de-karting-voltam-em-dezembro/</link><description>The Macao Karting International Award will receive again, from December 11 to 14, the Iame Asian finals. Like last year, the coloane karting race will give invitations to the very coveted world end of Iame in 2026.
Organized by the Institute of Sport, Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Otk Kart Asia and Iame Asia, the 2024 event brought back the international spirit to one of the largest competitions of the sport on the Asian continent. Coloane's karting received several races and different categories of Iame Series Asia, recovering the international prestige of an event that has been the scene of the Cik-Fia World Championship events.
Pilots from the interior of China, Singapore, Philippines, Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Japan, India, Sri Lanka, Australia, New Zealand, Sweden, Italy, France, Austria, the United States of America, Brazil, Hong Kong, and, of course, Macao, filled the track from the mashes in 2024 for four days of intense Competition, something that has not been seen for several years.
After the success of the previous edition, the formula is repeated this year. Singapore's organization again chooses Coloane's karting for its biggest event of the season, confirming the presence of the usual categories: Cadet, Junior, Senior and Master.
Thank you Macau!
A IAME (Italian American Motor Engineering) é um dos principais fabricantes mundiais de motores para a modalidade de karting. Founded in 1968 by Bruno Grana, the company is headquartered in Italy and is one of the references in Karting Internacional, having bet strongly in the Asian market in recent years. A presença em Macau faz parte dessa estratégia de crescimento e expansão.
The announcement of the return to the territory was made on social networks: “After an incredible debut in 2024, we are back with the Karting International Award of Macau and the Iame Asia final for another epic confrontation!
Satisfied with the reception in 2024, Iame Asia organizers took the opportunity to leave a "huge thanks to AAMC and the Macao government for their continuous support and confidence to make it possible!"
In addition to the Macao test, the 2025 calendar of Iame Series Asia includes three events in Malaysia and three events in Thailand. However, for the first time, last weekend of March, the Iame Asia Cup will be held at the International Shanghai Circuit Karting.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 01:04:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to GIC | Local tests return to Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/regresso-ao-gic-provas-locais-voltam-a-zhaoqing/</link><description>The dates for the Macao of Tourism Car Championship (MTCs in the English acronym) were made known on the past Friday by the General Automóvel Association of Macau-China (AAMC) through a newsletter. The competition for local pilots and decides to find out the Macao Grand Prix in November will again return to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC).
After a year when the MTCS headed to the Zhuzhou International Circuit in Hunan province, AAMC listened to most of the territory pilots and chose to make these important races closer to the main interveners' house - the pilots. In recent years, the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing has been the preferred stage for the realization of these races, due to the proximity and the fact that it serves as an operational basis to most teams.
The first of the two events scheduled for the 2025 MTCS is scheduled from 18 to 20 April, while the second round is scheduled from 16 to 18 May. The AAMC newsletter says that "all riders must go through a selection process before they can participate in the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix - Macau Touring Car Challenge."
Registration, for the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), are open until March 29 and after the end of the registration period, "all applications will be subject to AAMC approval, which reserves the final right to accept or reject any registration."
The technical regulation was also published, as was officially confirmed the use of tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, which belongs to the Chinese conglomerate Sinochem, as had already happened on the last edition of the Macao Grand Prix.
Confirmation of the Great Bay
AAMC also confirmed the two findings for the GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4), which will be concomitant with the new Chinese Championship Sro GT Cup. The first race will be played from March 21 to 23, at the International Circuit of Shanghai, in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix. Zhuhai International. Also here Pirelli will be the only tire supplier.
These two tests will be determined for the big holiday party on the guide circuit, and it is defined that only 28 cars will be accepted on the starting grid in the mashed race. The 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix runs from November 13 to 16.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 04:17:32</pubDate></item><item><title>GP TCR | Australia confirms presence in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/19/gp-tcr-australia-confirma-presenca-em-macau/</link><description>The 2025 season of TCR Australia will end largely when joining the TCR World Tour in the race of the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, which will take place from 13 to 16 November
 
After welcoming TCR China by 2024, the FIA ​​TCR World Tour “worldwide” will have the company of the Australian competitors in the most demanding race of the season, as HM had already foreseen at the end of last year.
This announcement is the second news in the calendar of one of the largest national TCR competitions in the world, after the announcement of a new promoter for the championship.
One pilot who was certainly pleased with the news was Australian Ben Bargwanna, who ran on the streets of Macao in 2023. TCR Australia's first international participation was made possible by the global rights holder, the WSC Group, which will ensure full transportation costs for Australian teams traveling to Macau.
"TCR Australia has always been one of TCR's most important and exciting competitions, rooted in the long tradition of tourism motorsport in the country," said WSC Group president Marcello Lotti. The Italian businessman made it clear that “when logistical issues forced us to cancel the Australian rounds of Kumho Fia TCR World Tour last year, we immediately started working to return in 2025. It is fantastic to extend cooperation for a second event and offer Australian competitors the unique opportunity to finish the season in Macau.”
Other applause
TCR Australia Prosecutor David Sonenscher, an old acquaintance of Macao, highlighted the importance of the moment for the category.
"I am very happy to bring TCR Australia to one of the most iconic circuits in the world and certainly one of the biggest challenges for a pilot," said former Malaysian-based English driver and entrepreneur and co-founder of TCR Asia. “The opportunity to expand our cooperation with the TCR World Tour FIA and to show the talented Australian riders on the highest international stage in Macau demonstrates the unique opportunity that TCR Australia and the TCR Global Platform provide all participants.”
Confirmation of the presence of TCR Australia in the Guide Race should not be impeded to the participation of local pilots and the interior of China in the most celebrated tourist car race on the Asian continent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 01:54:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorcycling | FHO RACING WITH NEW FOCUS IN 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/13/motociclismo-fho-racing-com-novo-foco-em-2025/</link><description>Doubts dissipated this week. Macau's businesswoman Foye Ho's FHO Racing will continue to active in the 2025 season, but without the initially announced riders. Peter Hickman and Davey Todd are leaving and goes to a new team called 8ten Racing
 
According to a statement sent by FHO Racing, BMW Motorrad UK has restructured its training for the 2025 British Superbike Championship, and FHO Racing BMW will compete with a single pilot aboard a BMW M 1000 RR. German 2024 Superbike Champion and Resistance World Cup driver, Ilya Mikhalchik, will make his debut in the British competition, at a time when team owner Faye Ho, realinhas the objectives of his team “to explore new activities in motorized new markets, with the support of BMW Motorrad Motorsport”.
Currently in his fifth year at the British Superbike Championship Paddock, Faye Ho has been a strong presence in the British competition, as well as in the popular road races, such as the Macao Grand Prix, as well as supporting several young female riders, helping them progress in their careers since the lower classes. Faye Ho, Stanley Ho's granddaughter and Clementina Leitão, has supported Kate Walker and Jamie Hanks-Bliott on BMW F 900 R Cup and, it seems, which will continue to support.
To be
Contrary to the rumors that put her from Paddock's departure, Faye Ho made it clear that she is a “great advocate of the British Superbike Championship, one of the world's most exciting and competitive competitions” and will keep her commitment to discipline. However, the territory entrepreneur now has new objectives for herself and its structure. The future will be in Asia and support for young female talents.
"Given my long -term objectives, which include expanding motor sport activities in Asia and continuing to support young women in motorcycling, I realized that I cannot dedicate the same time, to the British Superbike Championship and the road races, which I gave them since I became the owner of the team in 2021, due to additional commitments I have in Macao," Faye Ho said.
Another chapter
This announcement has put an end to a successful partnership, particularly on the island of Man TT, between Peter Hickman, four times winner of the Macao Motorcycle Grand Prix, and Fho Racing. Hickman left some words of thanks to his now former boss.
“I want to leave a huge thanks to Faye [Ho] and Fho Racing for all they have done for me over the past four years,” Hickman wrote in a Facebook social network post. “As it is normal in motorized sport, we had amazing and more difficult times, but Fho has always been and always will be a fundamental part of my career.
The new 8Ten Racing team, which will be officially presented on February 26, will be mostly composed of former FHO Racing elements. Hickman and Todd will maintain the important support of BMW Motorrad UK and are expected on the big prize starting grid in November.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 01:30:05</pubDate></item></channel></rss>