<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Avian flu | China prohibits imports of poultry products from Spain</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/gripe-aviaria-china-proibe-importacao-de-produtos-avicolas-de-espanha/</link><description>China has prohibited the importation of Spain poultry products due to high pathogenicity aviary outbreaks, suspending exports planned under an agreement in April to open the Chinese market to Spanish producers.
In a statement, the China's General Customs Administration indicated that the decision aims to "prevent the spread of the disease and protect the safety and biosecurity of national cattle." Since August 7, direct and indirect imports of poultry and derivatives, including processed, are prohibited.
The measures also provide for treatment, under customs supervision of all animal or agricultural waste that reach Chinese territory in any means of transport from Spain, as well as sanctions for those who violate the prohibitions.
For now, a deadline for the end of the restrictions, similar to those imposed in May to Brazilian chicken imports, also due to aviary flu has not been settled in May.
In April, the Spanish Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Luis Plan, and China's deputy minister of customs, Lu Weihong, signed a new export protocol that would allow Spanish poultry producers to access the Asian country to diversify foreign sales.
At the time, the Spanish ministry stressed that China "is a large buyer of bird meat and other products with reduced placement capacity in other markets."</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:50:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Interest | Banking with more than two thousand bonus requests</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/juros-banca-com-mais-de-dois-mil-pedidos-de-bonificacao/</link><description>The bank sector has already received two thousand requests under the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (PME), launched by the Executive in April.
According to the newspaper or Mun, IP Sio Kai, deputy and president of the Macao Banks Association, said that if all requests are approved, this represents an amount of 30 billion patacas. IP Sio Kai stated that more than half of the available quotas are free for assignment.
The official said that about 80 percent of these requests represent new loans, while 20 percent of orders were made to refund old loans granted. The deputy stated that traditional sectors such as retail restoration or sale continue to suffer from the breach of dislocated consumption to the interior of China, or even to digital buying platforms such as Taobao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:28:14</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Detained for receiving money from burlas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/pj-detida-por-receber-dinheiro-de-burlas/</link><description>A woman from the interior of China was detained at the siege gate border post after using five bank accounts on her behalf to receive about half a million dollars from Hong Kong -determined in circumvents.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the Judiciary Police (PJ) revealed that the suspicion will have received 12,200 Renminbis to create accounts in Hong Kong banks to be used to transfer money from circumvents.
According to the PJ version, the detained woman will have received Hong Kong's half million dollars from a resident who thought she was helping a family member. Authorities said there are more people involved in the case and that investigations to investigate their paradeiros continue. The woman was referred to the Public Prosecution Service on suspicion of high value scam crimes and money laundering.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:37:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal | Folio Festival returns to Óbidos with two Nobel Program Nobel Program</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/portugal-festival-folio-regressa-a-obidos-com-dois-nobel-da-literatura-no-programa/</link><description>The Folio-International Obidos Literary Festival, which will take place between October 9 and 19, will feature in this edition with two Nobel Prizes of the Literature: Belarusian Svetlana Alexievich and South African J. M. Coetzee, the organization announced.
In its 10th edition, the festival will bring Óbidos, in the district of Leiria, two laureates with the Nobel Prize for Literature, reinforcing “the international dimension and the growing prestige of the event in the European and worldwide cultural scenario”, said the City Hall, organizer of the event.
Belarussian writer and journalist Svetlana Alexievich, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 2015, will participate in the folio on October 11, at a table of authors scheduled for 9 pm.
Svetlana Alexievich is the author of five prose books that constitute the literary project “Voices of Utopia”, of which the works “Voices of Chernobyl,“ War has no woman's face ”,“ The End of Soviet Man ”,“ The Last Witnesses ”and“ Zinc Boys ”are part.
On October 17, the folly will host John Maxwell Coetzee, a South African writer who received the Nobel Prize in Literature in 2003. J. M. Coetzee is the author of several novels and rehearsals, most of them translated into Portuguese, including “the life and time of Michael K.”, with which he first received the Booker award in 1983 and “ Disgrace ”, which earned him the same prize in 1999.“ Waiting for the barbarians ”,“ The Island ”and“ The Iron Age ”are other works of the writer.
“Your folio intervention will be one of the highlights of this edition and a unique contact opportunity with a central figure of contemporary literary thinking,” says the festival organization.
In addition to the two Laureates with the Nobel Prize in Literature, they are confirmed in the 2025 authors such as American journalist Anne Applebaum, Israeli historian Avi Shlaim, Irish writer Paul Murray and American Carmen Maria Machado.
For reflection
The 2025 edition of the festival has as its theme “Borders” and, according to the House, the program, which should be presented in the coming weeks, “proposes a critical and plural reflection on the geographical, political, linguistic, identity”.
The festival will feature roundtables, conversations with authors, reading sessions, concerts, exhibitions, performances, book launches, school public initiatives, children's programming and various network actions with schools, universities, libraries and bookstores.
Organized by the Municipality of Óbidos, in partnership with the Municipal Company Óbidos Criativa, Read slowly and the Inatel Foundation, the folio had its first edition in 2015, only interrupted in 2020 due to the Covid-19 pandemic.
The 2024 edition attracted more than 100,000 people to the municipality of Óbidos, a creative city of UNESCO literature since 2015.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:42:25</pubDate></item><item><title>“Podul” | Sign 1 of will be today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/podul-sinal-1-de-sera-hoje-icado/</link><description>Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) should today be signal 1 of tropical storm due to the influence of a “peripheral subsidence” caused by the “podul” tropical cyclone, located east of the Taiwan region.
The thunderstorm of the storm signal is given that the “Podul” should be 800 kilometers from the territory, heading towards the southern coast of Fujian and East Coast of Guangdong Province.
Today the time in the territory should be "extremely hot", and the high temperatures "can cause thunderstorms and rain with gusts of strong wind." Between today and Friday the weather should be “unstable, occurs occasional, sometimes strong, accompanied by thunderstorms”, also the SMG.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:36:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | Profits grow 19 percent in the first half</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/galaxy-lucros-crescem-19-por-cento-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>In the first half of 2025, the Galaxy Entertainment group registered $ 5.24 billion of Hong Kong, an increase of 19.4 percent over the same period last year. In the note sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the company also announced the distribution of dividends from the end of October
 
In the first six months of 2025, the Galaxy Entertainment Group registered an annual profit rise of almost one fifth. According to a note released yesterday, the game concessionaire found $ 5.24 billion from Hong Kong (HKD) in the first half of this year, the equivalent of an annual increase of 19.4 percent.
According to information given to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, cited by the GGR Asia portal, the dealership will distribute dividends of 0.7 hkd per action from October 31st.
The growth was also found at the level of net profits, which reached at the end of the first semester nearly 23.25 billion HKD, which is equivalent to an increase of 8.3 percent compared to the same period of 2024.
Regarding the group's global results, the concessionaire reported a margin of profits before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of about 6.87 billion HKD in the first half of the year, which represented a 14.2 percent per year.
The note sent by the group to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange also reveals that in the second quarter of 2025 the concessionaire had net profits of 12 billion HKD, more 10 percent than in the same period of 2024. The Ebitad between April and June this year registered an annual rise of 12 percent to a total of 3.6 billion HKD.
Regarding net profits only of the group's casinos, the first semester was synonymous with an annual rise of 10.7 percent to an approximate total of 18.58 billion HKD. On the other hand, the group's non-game net revenues ascended nearly 3.17 billion HKD in the period under analysis, the equivalent of an annual increase of 2.5 percent.
Effort proof
"I am happy to announce the solid performance of the Macao market and the Galaxy Entertainment in the second quarter and first half of 2025. Despite the disruptions brought by tariffs, continuous economic slowdown and regional competition, Macau remained resilient."
Galaxy's strong man highlighted the growth of all market segments, “in particular the premium mass segment”, as well as the group's financial health.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:34:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Islands Hospital | More than 100 operations to Falls in a month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/hospital-das-ilhas-mais-de-100-operacoes-as-cataratas-num-mes/</link><description>A medical team from the Conde de São Januário Hospital and Hospital Hospital performed more than a hundred surgeries to cataracts since mid -July. Three surgeons from both hospitals have worked daily in a process that, from preparation to discharge, lasts less than three hours
 
Since mid -July, more than a hundred people have been operated on the cataracts at Hospital das Ilhas, the institution yesterday indicated in a statement. Operations have been performed daily by a team of three surgeons from the Ophthalmology Department of Hospital das Ilhas and the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, in coordination with health services.
The new hospital center states that, to increase efficiency, the islands hospital adopted the surgery model implemented by the department of ophthalmology of Peking Union Medical College Hospital. According to the model used at the Chinese capital hospital center, on the day of surgery, approved patients who meet the requirements usually go through the whole process, from admission to pre-surgery preparations to hospital discharge in less than three hours.
For patients who cannot leave the hospital on the same day due to special circumstances, the model allows them to change quickly and easily from the outpatient surgery program for hospitalization. Those responsible for the islands hospital to make sure that the flexibility of the personalized service model allows the discharge from the day after the operation, after an assessment of the surgeon. Authorities emphasize the convenience that the Beijing model gives to the elderly patients.
Continue to grow
In addition, it has been said that for a small number of more complex cataract surgeries, the islands hospital has experts from the Union Medical College and regularly invite expert teams with vast experience in cataract surgeries. As such, the institution emphasizes the importance of cooperation between Beijing and Macau to ensure the quality and safety of medical procedures performed at Hospital das Ilhas.
It is also indicated that ophthalmological problems will continue to increase in complexity and frequency as the population of Macao ages.
The medical institution is committed to continuing to optimize surgery services to cataracts, as well as the gradual integration of personnel from various departments, estimating that the number of patients ”that the hospital unit may meet will increase in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:31:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin | Open contest for remodeling of Praça Dezhi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/hengqin-aberto-concurso-para-remodelacao-da-praca-dezhi/</link><description>The idea is to create a new city linked to the university, instead of the old plan for the replica of a German city. The public tender is open for the remodeling of Praça Dezhi, in Hengqin, with apartments next to the new neighborhood of Macau and the Campus of the University of Macau
 
A public tender is opened for the remodeling of Praça Dezhi, in the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, in the space that has been designed to house the replica of a typically German city.
Now, what is intended to be that Praça Dezhi will become a future university city, with apartments and other services, because it is so close to the new Macau neighborhood in Hengqin and also the campus of the University of Macao in this neighboring region.
The contest, open until the 29th of this month, involves the transformation of a space with 13 buildings, in a total area of 49 thousand square meters, and the area intended for construction is 65 thousand square meters. In the new tenhi square, high buildings are expected for student activities, offices, apartments, a hotel and ten buildings for auxiliary teaching activities.
The newspaper or world describes some details of the project, and it can be read that the specific location of Hengqin “brings strategic importance to this work, which means that cooperation between Macau and Hengqin has already entered a new stage in order to support Macau in a better integration in national development” in the country.
Response to scarcity
Still in the details of the project cited by the or world, it is described that the renewal of the Praça Dezhi also aims to respond to the scarcity of space in the masters.
“The scarcity of land in Macao limits, in the long run, the expansion of higher education institutions and their academic update. The completion of this transient campus not only satisfies the needs of Macao higher education and research for a certain period, but also encourages a deeper integration of advantageous areas for universities, such as traditional Chinetic medicine and the field of microelectronics.”
Thus, it is added, “in conjunction with the hengqin industries, through the 'Campus + Industrial Park' model contributes to Macau to form new production forces and reach a diverse [economic] development,” is quoted.
Praça Dezhi was thought, before the pandemic, to be the German City Hengqin, the replica of a typical German city with 150,000 square meters where German and Chinese cultures would converge. According to an article from the 2020 South China Morning Post newspaper, the project intended to attract investments from the large bay zone, with US $ 229 million investment from TFG International, a company listed on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange. An International Center for Convention and Exhibitions would also be built, as well as hotels and offices.
The sale of properties started in 2019, but was stagnant due to the pandemic years. In addition, there were several disputes and many owners could not receive the houses where they had invested the money.
In the announcement of the new project, it is read that the work for Praça Dezhi continues to maintain “the European architectural characteristics”, highlighting the future characteristics of the university city in interior and outer spaces, designed for leisure zones and shows.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Caeal | Information Search reflects interest from voters</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/caeal-busca-de-informacao-reflecte-interesse-dos-eleitores/</link><description>The president of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly said yesterday that in a week about 116,000 people consulted information about the polling place. Song Ioi Man considers that the volume of consultations demonstrates the electoral's interest in the electoral act
 
In the space of one week, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) registered about 116,000 information on the vote, yesterday said the president of the body that organizes the suffrage of September 14. Song Ioi Man considers that the volume of consultations reflects the interest with which the population accompanies the work related to the electoral process.
Last Tuesday, several means of consultation were launched for voters to learn about the voting assembly attributed through the Single Account application, an open line, the Caeal page and in self-service kiosks for public services.
At a press conference on the way out of another body meeting, the judge also said that on Friday the distribution of public spaces that will be destined for election campaign activities. Thus is completed another step for the beginning of the campaign period, which starts on August 30 and will last 14 days.
When asked what happens if a list conducts election campaign actions outside Macao and the established deadline, the president of Caeal stressed that the electoral law also applies outside Macao. According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the official said he hoped the police authorities will have the means capable of dealing with the situation and overseeing activities outside the MSAR, namely through police cooperation mechanisms with abroad authorities.
Act Guardians
During the suffrage, while the ballot boxes are open, between 09h and 21h, each list can appoint two representatives (one staff and an alternate), to oversee the electoral process in each of the voting assemblies.
The president of Caeal said that the lists may present the names of representatives between next Saturday and 25 August, so that they obtain an entity certificate, which should be lifted at the Caeal reception counter, in the public administration building, on Rua do Campo, until two days before election day. One of the requirements of these representatives is to vote at the voting assemblies they will oversee.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:23:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Avian flu | China prohibits imports of poultry products from Spain</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/gripe-aviaria-china-proibe-importacao-de-produtos-avicolas-de-espanha/</link><description>China has prohibited the importation of Spain poultry products due to high pathogenicity aviary outbreaks, suspending exports planned under an agreement in April to open the Chinese market to Spanish producers.
In a statement, the China's General Customs Administration indicated that the decision aims to "prevent the spread of the disease and protect the safety and biosecurity of national cattle." Since August 7, direct and indirect imports of poultry and derivatives, including processed, are prohibited.
The measures also provide for treatment, under customs supervision of all animal or agricultural waste that reach Chinese territory in any means of transport from Spain, as well as sanctions for those who violate the prohibitions.
For now, no deadline for the end of the restrictions, similar to those imposed in May to Brazilian chicken imports, also due to aviary flu has not been set in May.
In April, the Spanish Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Luis Plan, and China's deputy minister of customs, Lu Weihong, signed a new export protocol that would allow Spanish poultry producers to access the Asian country to diversify foreign sales.
At the time, the Spanish ministry stressed that China "is a large buyer of bird meat and other products with reduced placement capacity in other markets."</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:50:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Interest | Banking with more than two thousand bonus requests</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/juros-banca-com-mais-de-dois-mil-pedidos-de-bonificacao/</link><description>The bank sector has already received two thousand requests under the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (PME), launched by the Executive in April.
According to the newspaper or Mun, IP Sio Kai, deputy and president of the Macao Banks Association, said that if all requests are approved, this represents an amount of 30 billion patacas. IP Sio Kai stated that more than half of the available quotas are free for assignment.
The official said that about 80 percent of these requests represent new loans, while 20 percent of orders were made to refund old loans granted. The deputy stated that traditional sectors such as retail restoration or sale continue to suffer from the breach of dislocated consumption to the interior of China, or even to digital buying platforms such as Taobao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:28:14</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Detained for receiving money from burlas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/pj-detida-por-receber-dinheiro-de-burlas/</link><description>A woman from the interior of China was arrested at the siege gate border post after using five bank accounts on her behalf to receive about half a million dollars from Hong Kong -determined in circumvents.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the Judiciary Police (PJ) revealed that the suspect will have received 12,200 Renminbis to create accounts in Hong Kong banks to be used to transfer money from burlas.
According to the PJ version, the detained woman will have received Hong Kong's half million dollars from a resident who thought she was helping a family member. Authorities said there are more people involved in the case and that investigations to investigate their paradeiros continue. The woman was referred to the Public Prosecution Service on suspicion of high value scam crimes and money laundering.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:37:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal | Folio Festival returns to Óbidos with two Nobel Program Nobel Program</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/portugal-festival-folio-regressa-a-obidos-com-dois-nobel-da-literatura-no-programa/</link><description>The Folio-International Obidos Literary Festival, which will take place between October 9 and 19, will feature in this edition with two Nobel Prizes of the Literature: Belarusian Svetlana Alexievich and South African J. M. Coetzee, the organization announced.
In its 10th edition, the festival will bring Óbidos, in the district of Leiria, two laureates with the Nobel Prize for Literature, reinforcing “the international dimension and the growing prestige of the event in the European and worldwide cultural scenario”, said the City Hall, organizer of the event.
Belarussian writer and journalist Svetlana Alexievich, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 2015, will participate in the folio on October 11, at a table of authors scheduled for 9 pm.
Svetlana Alexievich is the author of five prose books that constitute the literary project “Voices of Utopia”, of which the works “Voices of Chernobyl,“ War has no woman's face ”,“ The End of Soviet Man ”,“ The Last Witnesses ”and“ Zinc Boys ”are part.
On October 17, the folly will host John Maxwell Coetzee, a South African writer who received the Nobel Prize in Literature in 2003. J. M. Coetzee is the author of several novels and rehearsals, most of them translated into Portuguese, including “the life and time of Michael K.”, with which he first received the Booker award in 1983 and “ Disgrace ”, which earned him the same prize in 1999.“ Waiting for the barbarians ”,“ The Island ”and“ The Iron Age ”are other works of the writer.
“Your folio intervention will be one of the highlights of this edition and a unique contact opportunity with a central figure of contemporary literary thinking,” says the festival organization.
In addition to the two Laureates with the Nobel Prize in Literature, they are confirmed in the 2025 authors such as American journalist Anne Applebaum, Israeli historian Avi Shlaim, Irish writer Paul Murray and American Carmen Maria Machado.
For reflection
The 2025 edition of the festival has as its theme “Borders” and, according to the House, the program, which should be presented in the coming weeks, “proposes a critical and plural reflection on the geographical, political, linguistic, identity”.
The festival will feature roundtables, conversations with authors, reading sessions, concerts, exhibitions, performances, book launches, school public initiatives, children's programming and various network actions with schools, universities, libraries and bookstores.
Organized by the Municipality of Óbidos, in partnership with the Municipal Company Óbidos Criativa, Read slowly and the Inatel Foundation, the folio had its first edition in 2015, only interrupted in 2020 due to the Covid-19 pandemic.
The 2024 edition attracted more than 100,000 people to the municipality of Óbidos, a creative city of UNESCO literature since 2015.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:42:25</pubDate></item><item><title>GARDEN House | Inaugurated “After Eastern Garden” with works by local and foreign artists</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/casa-garden-inaugurada-after-oriental-garden-com-obras-de-artistas-locais-e-estrangeiros/</link><description>Since yesterday, the Oriente Foundation welcomes another exhibition, integrated into the annual program of “Macao Art: Macao International Art Biennial”. It is “After Eastern Garden”, curated by Kathine Cheong, who welcomes Charlie Perez-Tlatechi, Elói Scarva, Ho Tzu Nyen, Jinjin Xu and Vividly, name of duo Jay Lee and Jay Lei
 
Since yesterday it is possible to visit at Casa Garden, headquarters of the Oriente Foundation (FO) in Macau, a new exhibition. It is “After Eastern Garden” [after the Eastern Garden ”, a collective show that can be seen until October 5th and is another initiative of“ Macao Art: International Art Biennial of Macao ”.
With free admission, the curatorship of this project was in charge of Kathine Cheong, revealing works where “Macau is the anchor to navigate the city's multifaceted memories, reflecting on the interconnection between colonial history, commercial flows and ecological changes,” describes a press release about the event.
The public will be able to see works by five groups of local and foreign artists, namely Charlie Perez-Tlatechi, Elói Scarva, Ho Tzu Nyen, Jinjin Xu and Vividly, name of the duo Jay Lee and Jay Lei. They all "transformed personal experiences into artistic creations in the form of files, sculptures, videos and sound installations."
In "After Oriental Garden", we seek to "destabilize stereotyped metanarratives, allowing hidden voices to surface and" other invisible "to be present in space." In the Garden house there will be, therefore, the “convergence of different artists” in a “interdisciplinary” format.
Multiple views
The exhibition presents the work of Elói Scarva, a Portuguese artist from Macau and who also works as a journalist. Scarva presents the sculpture work “Capsules - Eco Chambers”, composed of “eight temporal capsules that confront the physical evidence of cultural exchanges”. Founder of the “Republic of Arts of Coloane” Association, Elói Scarva has been promoting initiatives linked to contemporary art in the territory.
Another artist present in this show is Jinjin XU, whose art ways between Macau, Shanghai and New York. This responds to the appeal launched by the show with the work "poetic of the witness". The artist was recognized by the Chinese edition of Forbes as "one of the 100 most influential Chinese personalities."
Also noteworthy is for Singapore artist Ho Tzu Nyen, who presents the video “O of Opium”, where the historical impact of opium trade in the Asian region is reexamined. His most recent works address historical transformations and future visions of Asia.
Casa Garden also welcomes the work of emerging New York artist Charlie Perez-Tlatechi, who displays new and old works, which uses "materials and images as fables to reflect on hidden stories in the process of globalization."
Also present is the duo who adopted the name Vividly, and has been nominated four times for the Hong Kong Theater Libre awards. In Macau, the pair of artists presents "a new commissioned project on the journey of cities, memory and objects", entitled "Pulse of Things: A Memory under the missing stream."
This show is divided into three parts, namely “wandering echoes”, “East Journey” and “Palimpseste da Fénix”. The works arranged in the "wandering echoes" can be seen right on the stairs of Casa Garden, followed "trip to the East" with "three doors that head [the visitors] to different narrative spaces." In the final phase, "Palimpseste da Phenix", allows for a prolongation of all narratives counted above, "intertwining historical memory and contemporary experience, transforming them into recreation, establishing a space for open thinking."
In addition to the show itself, during the exposure period there will be parallel activities such as the Sonoro Concert “In the Garden-Flow of the Moon”, the research sharing “Tour Stories” by the Vividly Collective; The conversation of artists “Borders: Research Methods in Interdisciplinary Projects”, the Botany Workshop “Symbiotic Ramos: The Secret Language of Plants in Macao” and also educational workshops for secondary and university students.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:41:10</pubDate></item><item><title>NVIDIA | Beijing Dead Slips Use of Chips H20</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/nvidia-pequim-desaconselha-uso-de-chips-h20/</link><description>Chinese authorities have recommended in recent weeks to local companies that avoid using H20 processors from US manufacturer Nvidia, especially in projects linked to government agencies or national security, Bloomberg agency said yesterday.
According to Bloomberg, warnings sent to several companies included, in some cases, questions about the reasons to choose the H20 over national alternatives, the need for this choice and any security problems detected on the devices. The recommendation would also cover US Artificial Intelligence Accelerators (AI) AMD.
The guidance coincides with recent information released by Chinese organisms and state agencies that question the safety and reliability of the H20, a model designed by Nvidia for the Chinese market with specifications lower than the most advanced versions, in accordance with the restrictions imposed by Washington.
At the end of July, the Chinese Internet regulator (CAC) called on Nvidia to clarify alleged safety risks on chips and have evidence that it does not contain “rear doors”, an accusation that the company has rejected.
On Monday, Nvidia again denying that H20 integrates access or remote control functions, in response to comments released on a social network account associated with state television CCTV, which cited experts that it would be technically possible to incorporate screening capabilities, location or remote shutdown in this type of processors.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:48:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | Uses knife to extort money and is arrested</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/crime-usa-faca-para-extorquir-dinheiro-e-e-detido/</link><description>A Chinese interior citizen was arrested after threatening a casino player, also from the interior of China, with a table knife to transfer 69,000 Renminbis.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the woman met the man when they were both playing in a casino in the early hours of Tuesday, having convinced the player to go to her room.
There, the man carried out a robbery, cutting the woman's wrist with the knife, asking him to transfer the money, and then asked him to take off his clothes. It was then that the man photographed the naked woman, demanding her not to call the police. Only yesterday morning the Judiciary Police (PJ) picked up the man in the Cotai zone, in possession of game sheets and notes with a total value of $ 7.5 thousand from Hong Kong.
The case has already been referred to the Public Prosecution Service, running the risk of being accused of theft crimes, by stopping a weapon without justification and other instruments, for engraving and photographing illicitly and also for the wanton of private life, in this case against women.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:33:30</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Li Longji (685-762), who would be remembered as Emperor Xuanzong de Tang (R. 712-56), returned to the scene of a crime to start the painful process to which poet Bai Juyi (772-842) would call the 'long remorse'.
In this place of the Hill Mawei where for reasons of state dead, Concubine Yang Yuhuan, better known as Yang Guifei, says the poet: "He and his ministers looked into each other's eyes, his wet clothes with tears." But when the horses reached the gates of the palace, contrary to their feelings, "the lakes and the gardens remained calm;/ the hybisks in the waters of Lake Taiye, the willowers of the Weyang Palace," what doesn't end. " / But the hybisks were their face, the willow will their eyebrows,/ looking at them, how could the tears stop running? The words of the poet of the singing of the eternal remorse (Changhen GE) would resonate many years later, giving an unobvilding way to confused feelings.
In the eighteenth century, of repeated, these words were already a commonplace and an unsubmitted poet dared to challenge them. In the poem Mawei, returning to the fateful Hill, Yuan Mei (1716-1798) wrote: “I will not sing the corner of the perpetual remorse of old,/ since there is the Milky Way, this silver river, which there are separate people. Long Life Pavilion. » Yuan Mei boasted a mirrored freedom in the space of a garden that built as a self-portrait, in the tradition of what literates such as Wang Wei did; "If it is the garden that brings comfort to our eyes, it is also the garden that offers man a refuge of himself." Born in Hangzhou near the West Lake, he took to the ground he acquired in the nanjing area and named Suiyuan, 'Jardim of Accommodation', taking advantage of the name of the previous owner written but otherwise, certain characteristics of the celebrated lake as the twenty -four scenes with their respective poems.
From this garden without walls, the lord of the garden of accommodation, Suiyuan Xiansheng, revealed a boldness that allowed him, for example, to overcome the barriers that separated the education of men and women. As he showed by ordering a rare painting.
Wang Gong and You Shao were the two painters requested by Yuan Mei to execute an unprecedented roller featuring a conventional meeting of literati but in which they only participate, besides Yuan Mei, literate ladies. In The Disciples of the Suiyuan Master (horizontal roller, ink and color on paper, 41 x 308.4 cm, at the Shanghai Museum) literati, such as painter Liao Yunjin (1766-1835) who raises the brush while painting a branch of plum conversation and living, attesting to the boldness of Yuan Mei who did not accept the instruction. of ladies.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>China has prohibited the importation of Spain poultry products due to high pathogenicity aviary outbreaks, suspending exports planned under an agreement in April to open the Chinese market to Spanish producers.
In a statement, the China's General Customs Administration indicated that the decision aims to "prevent the spread of the disease and protect the safety and biosecurity of national cattle." Since August 7, direct and indirect imports of poultry and derivatives, including processed, are prohibited.
The measures also provide for treatment, under customs supervision of all animal or agricultural waste that reach Chinese territory in any means of transport from Spain, as well as sanctions for those who violate the prohibitions.
For now, no deadline for the end of the restrictions, similar to those imposed in May to Brazilian chicken imports, also due to aviary flu has not been set in May.
In April, the Spanish Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Luis Plan, and China's deputy minister of customs, Lu Weihong, signed a new export protocol that would allow Spanish poultry producers to access the Asian country to diversify foreign sales.
At the time, the Spanish ministry stressed that China "is a large buyer of bird meat and other products with reduced placement capacity in other markets."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>China has prohibited the importation of Spain poultry products due to high pathogenicity aviary outbreaks, suspending exports planned under an agreement in April to open the Chinese market to Spanish producers.
In a statement, the China's General Customs Administration indicated that the decision aims to "prevent the spread of the disease and protect the safety and biosecurity of national cattle." Since August 7, direct and indirect imports of poultry and derivatives, including processed, are prohibited.
The measures also provide for treatment, under customs supervision of all animal or agricultural waste that reach Chinese territory in any means of transport from Spain, as well as sanctions for those who violate the prohibitions.
For now, no deadline for the end of the restrictions, similar to those imposed in May to Brazilian chicken imports, also due to aviary flu has not been set in May.
In April, the Spanish Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Luis Plan, and China's deputy minister of customs, Lu Weihong, signed a new export protocol that would allow Spanish poultry producers to access the Asian country to diversify foreign sales.
At the time, the Spanish ministry stressed that China "is a large buyer of bird meat and other products with reduced placement capacity in other markets."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>China has prohibited the importation of Spain poultry products due to high pathogenicity aviary outbreaks, suspending exports planned under an agreement in April to open the Chinese market to Spanish producers.
In a statement, the China's General Customs Administration indicated that the decision aims to "prevent the spread of the disease and protect the safety and biosecurity of national cattle." Since August 7, direct and indirect imports of poultry and derivatives, including processed, are prohibited.
The measures also provide for treatment, under customs supervision of all animal or agricultural waste that reach Chinese territory in any means of transport from Spain, as well as sanctions for those who violate the prohibitions.
For now, no deadline for the end of the restrictions, similar to those imposed in May to Brazilian chicken imports, also due to aviary flu has not been set in May.
In April, the Spanish Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Luis Plan, and China's deputy minister of customs, Lu Weihong, signed a new export protocol that would allow Spanish poultry producers to access the Asian country to diversify foreign sales.
At the time, the Spanish ministry stressed that China "is a large buyer of bird meat and other products with reduced placement capacity in other markets."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Li Longji (685-762), who would be remembered as Emperor Xuanzong de Tang (R. 712-56), returned to the scene of a crime to start the painful process to which poet Bai Juyi (772-842) would call the 'long remorse'.
In this place of the Hill Mawei where for reasons of state dead, Concubine Yang Yuhuan, better known as Yang Guifei, says the poet: "He and his ministers looked into each other's eyes, his wet clothes with tears." But when the horses reached the gates of the palace, contrary to their feelings, "the lakes and the gardens remained calm;/ the hybisks in the waters of Lake Taiye, the willowers of the Weyang Palace," what doesn't end. " / But the hybisks were their face, the willow will their eyebrows,/ looking at them, how could the tears stop running? The words of the poet of the singing of the eternal remorse (Changhen GE) would resonate many years later, giving an unobvilding way to confused feelings.
In the eighteenth century, of repeated, these words were already a commonplace and an unsubmitted poet dared to challenge them. In the poem Mawei, returning to the fateful Hill, Yuan Mei (1716-1798) wrote: “I will not sing the corner of the perpetual remorse of old,/ since there is the Milky Way, this silver river, which there are separate people. Long Life Pavilion. » Yuan Mei boasted a mirrored freedom in the space of a garden that built as a self-portrait, in the tradition of what literates such as Wang Wei did; "If it is the garden that brings comfort to our eyes, it is also the garden that offers man a refuge of himself." Born in Hangzhou near the West Lake, he took to the ground he acquired in the nanjing area and named Suiyuan, 'Jardim of Accommodation', taking advantage of the name of the previous owner written but otherwise, certain characteristics of the celebrated lake as the twenty -four scenes with their respective poems.
From this garden without walls, the lord of the garden of accommodation, Suiyuan Xiansheng, revealed a boldness that allowed him, for example, to overcome the barriers that separated the education of men and women. As he showed by ordering a rare painting.
Wang Gong and You Shao were the two painters requested by Yuan Mei to execute an unprecedented roller featuring a conventional meeting of literati but in which they only participate, besides Yuan Mei, literate ladies. In The Disciples of the Suiyuan Master (horizontal roller, ink and color on paper, 41 x 308.4 cm, at the Shanghai Museum) literati, such as painter Liao Yunjin (1766-1835) who raises the brush while painting a branch of plum conversation and living, attesting to the boldness of Yuan Mei who did not accept the instruction. of ladies.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Iam | Cats captured due to complaints from the University of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/05/iam-gatos-capturados-devido-a-queixas-da-universidade-de-macau/</link><description>The collection of cats from the land of the University of Macao resulted from “university complaints about the large amount of cats in its campus,” the institute for municipal affairs told HM. The public body removes, for now, the scenario of slaughtering animals, feared by the students
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) clarifies that the collection of 15 cats between July 22 and 25 of the University of Macao campus (one) emerged in response to complaints from the institution of higher education in relation to hygiene problems in the campus generated by the presence of animals.
"AMI has constantly receiving complaints from one about the large amount of cats on its campus and food waste that is not removed in time and affecting environmental hygiene," was referred to in the response sent to HM.
UM UM Campus Cats led to a wave of students' indignation, who say Temer the slaughter of animals after the period of complaint and adoption. AMI will move away, this scenario.
"Regarding cats captured, if they are not claimed by the owner after the period of complaint, AMI will implement the policy of" open capture, sterilization and adoption "(TNA), prioritizing finding appropriate adopters for cats. It should be noted that AMI does not set a deadline for retention of the adopted animals."
In the same answer it is said that during the waiting period for host families, AMI “will continue to provide clinical care and daily care to animals, never existing their slaughtering situation due to the term of retention period”.
In this sense, it is explained that AMI veterinarians “are performing a series of medical care that include body examination, vaccine administration and microchips.” In addition, “cats can only be available for adoption after being sterilized,” Iam said.
“Lack of sensitivity”
The warnings for the adoption of these animals continue on social networks, and in a note sent to HM and signed by “a member of the UMERS - UMM groups”, is questioned the “worrying situation” that occurred during the summer vacation and therefore the absence of most students.

“These cats, considered an integral part of the university community, survived the sign of signal 10, but unfortunately they could not escape these AMI capture operations in recent days. For many students and teachers, these cats were like 'veterans' of campus, following them during significant moments of academic life and providing comfort and joy in the university environment.”
The note explains that "UMERS" members cannot adopt cats "due to various circumstances," such as family allergies, possession of other animals, or "additional restrictions" for students in the interior of China.
The alerts on social networks aim to “sensitize the public for this situation and encourage people with adequate conditions to adopt these cats in the municipal Kennel of Macau.
On the Red Note platform there is even the group “A CatStories”, where the stories of cats captured by AMI are shared, and only one publication generated 460 tastes and 160 comments. A group was also created on Facebook, “Macao Cats II”, and there is also publications on Threads, with a total of 500 tastes and 500 shares, including the ten thousand views.
One of the profiles of the "a catstories" concerns a "slight little cat," described as "a" unnamed "file, just created on the computer: still blank, slowly exploring the world and trying to type loose fragments to write" his own story.
“Hurryned to a corner, I watch the people who pass, evaluating who can become an important character of my plot. So far, few people have been written in my story, and I have also left few brands in someone's life. Before leaving the campus maybe this" unnamed "file is only 5kb, recording some shy explorations and a soft desire for human warmth," reads the adoption.
The HM questioned one on this subject, given that the animals were being cherished by the students, but until the closing of the edition did not receive an answer. "UMERS" members also question how one can one, "an institution that seeks academic excellence and better classifications in the world rankings, demonstrate such a lack of sensitivity, allowing the capture of these animals without any alternative solution."
Aborted association
In the same grade it is said that students considered creating an association to “organize the sterilization of campus cats, but the university did not approve the creation of such a student association”.
UMERS members enhance “contrast with renowned universities in the interior of China, such as the University of Beijing, where there is a student association dedicated to the care of university campus cats, and at the University of Zhejiang, where UM UM Rector Song Yonghua has previously worked an association to protect university campus animals since 2005”.
Regarding animal collection and treatment actions, AMI says that "TNA policies correspond to the guiding principles of the World Animal Health Organization (WOAH), which contribute to reducing the possibility of stray animals being exposed to disease and facing unfavorable environmental factors."
Such policies also contribute to the reduction of the number of animals "and their excessive long -term reproduction." It is also noted that "TNA policies still take into account the state of survival and welfare of animals, in order to find adopting families for animals with conditions, dedicating themselves to helping them to obtain permanent and stable proper care."
The AMI also says it has "constantly optimized the municipal kennels", and in recent years, "complementary facilities and equipment have been perfected." In addition, there is also cooperation “with animal protection associations”, and joint projects in schools and community neighborhoods for animal adoption and care.
Official data available on the AMI website indicates that in the first quarter of this year 264 animals were captured without microchip, which increased to 280 in the second quarter. The numbers are similar to the first two quarters of 2024: the first were caught 266 animals without microchip, followed by 327 animals in the second quarter. In the third and fourth quarters of last year 258 and 203 animals were caught, respectively.
Regarding sterilization actions, in the first quarter of this year 289 were made, followed by 211 actions of this kind in the second quarter. In the first quarter of this year were claimed, or adopted, 102 cats and 29 dogs, and in the following quarter, 93 cats and 49 dogs were adopted.
As for the number of animals slaughtered, in the first quarter of this year alone 32 cats and 69 dogs were killed. If in cats this number reduced in the second quarter to 11, the same did not happen with the dogs: 101 were slaughtered.</description><pubDate>2025-08-05 01:24:52</pubDate></item><item><title>CCCM | Fusion with Foundation for Science and Technology creates new agency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/04/cccm-fusao-com-fundacao-para-a-ciencia-e-tecnologia-cria-nova-agencia/</link><description>Operating since 1999, the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center will merge with the Foundation for Science and Technology and the National Innovation Agency, creating a new institution. The practical consequences for the CCCM that aims to promote studies on Macao, China and Asia in Portugal are unknown. The president of the center says it is early to make comments
 
It is not known whether it will maintain its name, the number of scholarships for studies on China, Macao and Asia, or whether to change staff, but what is certain is that the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) will merge with the Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT) and the National Innovation Agency. Of these three entities will be born the new agency for research and innovation.
The process is linked to the desire to reform the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology by the Portuguese government led by Luís Montenegro, and the changes were announced on Thursday.
However, there is still no great information about the consequences of this merger to the CCCM. At HM, Carmen Amado Mendes, its president, chose to refer to clarification for the future operation of the center, considering that it is "premature" to give answers about something "that is not yet defined."
On Thursday, Minister Fernando Alexandre announced the reform of the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation with the extinction of several entities, including FCT that has been the main financier of PhD and other research projects in Portugal.
The reform of the ministry was approved by the Council of Ministers and, at a press conference at the end of the meeting, Fernando Alexandre justified the restructuring by describing his ministry as an “anacronic structure”, with fragmented organizations, disintegrated information systems and disarticulated governance.
With 18 entities and 27 higher leaders between the services of the non -higher education system and higher education, science and innovation, the ministry will have only seven entities and 27 higher leaders, with the integration of extinguished entities into new entities.
Regarding the extinction of the FCT, the minister assured that the financing of science will be preserved, with funding for four years that guarantees stability, predictability and “the protection of the financing of the most basic fundamental investigation”.
“When we started thinking about this reform, we do it with a vision: to ensure equal opportunities to access quality education,” said Fernando Alexandre, also underlining the reinforcement of the education system.
Marcelo can veto
The extinction of FCT has generated some less good reactions in Portugal because it fears a reduction in investment in science and research. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, president of the Portuguese Republic, said he had “the sensation” that the foundation was replaced “with an agency in which he was integrated, and had other functions beyond those of FCT.”
Marcelo acknowledged that the Foundation was a “very old structure” and that “it had many aspects that deserved to be rethought”, but said: “Just seeing what the new agency will do can I answer if this extinction is a good or bad idea.”
As for the eventual 'green light' from Belém, Marcelo said that if he thinks this extinction is "good", promulgates the diploma "without anguish." "If you have doubts about a point that is this diploma that is very important I ask the government to rethink. It has happened. I may not veto soon. If the government insists, I can come to veto, if it is until the end of my mandate," he also admitted.
A history of the transition
The CCCM was born in 1995 during the administration of Vasco Rocha Vieira, the last Portuguese governor of Macao, intending to be “a place of excellence for the dissemination of Macau, its history, its culture and its economy”, reads in the memories of Rocha Vieira, “to all the ports I arrived”.
This entity, operating in the Alcântara area, in Lisbon, was inaugurated in November 1999 by the then President of the Republic, Jorge Sampaio, and had as first president Alexandra Costa Gomes.
On the CCCM website it is read that the institution is endowed with administrative autonomy and its own heritage, being a public institute integrated in the indirect administration of the state and under the tutelage of the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation.
In the objective booklet, it is read that the CCCM “has as its mission to produce, promote and disseminate knowledge about Macao as a platform between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China, as well as between Europe and Asia”, also presenting itself as “a space dedicated to the study and teaching of Chinese language, culture and history”. The center has also been established as "a center for scientific research and continuous and advanced training on the relations between Portugal and China, as well as between Europe and Asia."
After the long presidency of Luís Filipe Barreto, academic at the University of Lisbon, the CCCM began to be chaired, from February 2020, by Carmen Amado Mendes. The leader recently saw her service committee renewed by 2030.
A few months after taking office as president, Carmen Amado Mendes presented, on September 18, 2020, the new “Strategic Development Plan of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center 2020-2030”.
Since then, the CCCM has awarded dozens of doctoral scholarships for the studies of Macao, China and Asia, and the “Spring Conferences”, which bring together academic performances around the same themes every year. Also noteworthy that the CCCM opened, in December last year, the “Gallery of Governors”, with 41 paintings of the former Portuguese governors of Macao. A new building that houses the file and library was also inaugurated.
This plan sets objectives by 2030, "the reinforcement of scientific and cultural cooperation in the domain of past understanding, present and future trends of relations between Europe and Asia."
With regard to archives, it is intended to “modernize and dynamization within a network of documentation centers and international reference file on euro-seatic themes, with emphasis on the various files in Lisbon, but also in Portugal and Europe”.
Given that CCCM houses, in its facilities, the Macao Museum, the board points to the “insertion and appreciation in the museum network at the level of Lisbon and National”.
The central idea of the plan was to develop, by 2030, “CCCM facilities as a pole of streamlining scientific, cultural and economic relations between Portugal and China, including the installation of entities such as the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry, the Erasmus+Youth Entrepreneurs Association, as well as research nuclei in eurical studies”. It remains to be seen if, with the merger, all these initiatives will continue their initial course.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 07:39:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs: Seven agreements since Trump arrived at the White House</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/29/tarifas-sete-acordos-desde-que-trump-chegou-a-casa-branca/</link><description>The United States have reached seven bilateral trade agreements since Donald Trump returned to the White House in January and the latest, signed on Sunday with the European Union (EU), is the largest in terms of business volume.
In addition to the EU agreement, the US government has agreed new commercial terms with the United Kingdom, China, Vietnam, Japan, Philippines and Indonesia, while negotiations continue with dozens from other countries, US authorities.
Here is the data from the list of the seven bilateral trade agreements that Trump was able to obtain since January, when he returned to the White House for a second presidential term.
+++ United Kingdom +++
Signed on May 8, it was the first bilateral agreement signed by Trump since the US government announced a new tariff plan.
This agreement establishes the reduction of tariffs on British cars from 25% to 10% - up to 100,000 vehicles per year - and the elimination of steel and aluminum tariffs; Reciprocal permissions for export of beef and agricultural products, as well as reduction of non -tariff barriers and simplification of customs procedures.
+++ China +++
On June 26, after reciprocal threats of tariffs up to 115%, the United States and China have reached an agreement of principle that is still being developed.
Although it keeps high rates-55% for exporting certain Chinese products to the United States-facilitates the export of rare land in China, eliminates mutual retaliation measures and softens controls on Chinese products to the US market.
+++ Vietnam +++
The US and Vietnam agreed on July 2 to increase the vietnamese exports to the US to 20% (with a 40% rate on the products suspected of being Chinese origin). Trump's previous threat was to establish tariffs in the 46%.

++ Japan ++
Japan agrees with a 15% rate on all its exports to the United States compared to the 25% rate with which Trump had threatened. The country was committed to investing $ 550 billion (about 470 billion euros) in the US and opening its markets to sectors such as car, rice and agricultural products.
++ Philippines ++
The US now imposing a 19% rate on Philippine products, less a percentage point than the 20% that had threatened, in exchange for the exemption of tariffs on US products that enter the Philippines. The announcement was made on July 22, after the visit of Filipino President Ferdinand Marcos Jr., to the White House.
++ Indonesia ++
On the same date, July 22, and with almost identical content, Trump's agreement with Indonesia establishes 19% rates on exports to the United States and, in parallel, includes aircraft purchase commitments, US agricultural and energy products.
++ European Union ++
On Sunday, July 27, the trade agreement between the United States and the EU was announced, which states that most European exports will be subject to 15% fees - Trump had threatened with 30% - but included tariff exemptions for certain products.
In the agreement, the EU is committed to buying $ 750 billion (about 650 billion euros) in the United States, investing $ 600 billion (about 510 billion euros) in the country and increasing its US military equipment purchases.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 02:33:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia | Great Coral Barrier has been declining since there is a record</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/australia-grande-barreira-de-coral-sofre-maior-declinio-desde-que-ha-registo/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values “the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's World Heritage Site, has a "high to extreme" prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the larger and more severe laundering that there is registration to date,” it reads in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot quickly recover sufficiently between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:22:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Economic Report Highlights Startup “Historical Record”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/hong-kong-relatorio-economico-destaca-recorde-historico-de-startups/</link><description>"Hong Kong's startups are on the rise." This is how the executive in the neighboring region describes the business environment in the region, where they were created in 2024 about 4,700 startups, plus 10 percent of 2023. In the "Report of Hong Kong's Business Environment 2025" it is read that the territory is far from losing economic competitiveness
 
The Hong Kong government released last July 30 the latest report on the neighboring region's economic scene. And one of the highlights is given to the scenario of growth of entrepreneurship.
In the “Report of Hong Kong's Business Environment 2025” [Hong Kong 2025 Business Environment Report] it is noteworthy that “Startups in Hong Kong are on the rise”, given that last year there were “about 4,700 startups in the city, a historic record and an increase of 10 percent from the previous year”.
The document explains that "more than a quarter of these startups has founders from outside Hong Kong," it is companies that operate in a "broad spectrum of sectors, including Fintech [High Technology], Electronic Trade and Information, Informatics and Technology", having hired more than 17,000 people. This number of human resources also represents an increase of seven percent compared to 2023. "All this is proof of Hong Kong's strong appeal for startup entrepreneurs," the authorities highlight.
But it is not only startups that record growth, with the report to point out that the current government, led by executive head John Lee, "achieved remarkable results in attracting companies, investments and talents."
"For example, in 2024, the number of companies in Hong Kong with headquarters outside the territory increased significantly by about 10 percent, reaching almost 10,000." The “Office for the attraction of strategic companies, created more than two years ago, attracted 84 strategic companies to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, including companies with market capitalization or valuation of over $ 10 billion, involving cutting -edge technology”, it is added.
The report also points out that between January 2023 and the first half of this year, Invest Hong Kong, linked to the Raehk government's direct foreign investment department, "helped over 1300 foreign and continent companies establishing or expanding their business in Hong Kong, bringing investments of over $ 160 billion."
Still with regard to Invest Hong Kong, the entity helped "539 companies from the continent or foreign to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, which represents an annual growth of over 40 percent."
At the end of June this year, Hong Kong had 1.5 million local companies, while the total number of companies not registered in Hong Kong reached 15 509. "Both numbers represent historical records," it reads, and for the government of the neighboring territory the data "demonstrate the great confidence that continent and abroad companies have in the future of Hong Kong."
Given that Hong Kong also has a talent capture program, the Hong Kong Talent Engage, reads in the report that by June this year "were received about 500,000 candidates in the shelter of various talent admission programs, of which about 330,000 were approved." Of these numbers, Hong Kong actually arrived to work 220,000 qualified frames.
Good scholarship scenario
Quoted on an official press release, a government spokesman stated that "in a complex and volatile external environment, Hong Kong is undergoing a phase of economic update and transformation, but there are more opportunities than challenges."
Given that the territory has always positioned itself as a strong financial market worldwide, this scenario seems to have recorded a recovery in recent years.
“This year Hong Kong's financial market performance has been constantly improving. The Hang SENG Index has a 18 percent increase last year and an increase of more than 25 percent this year so far. The average daily business volume in the first half of the year was about $ 240 billion, with an increase of about 120 percent.”
Authorities highlight the maintenance of the economic competitiveness of the territory, pointing out that "over the years Hong Kong has been constantly classified as a global leader in economic freedom and competitiveness."
Attention to the trade war
In conclusion, Raehk's government clarifies that territory seems to maintain economic stability in times of constant commercial conflicts, with Donald Trump threatening and imposing tariffs on a number of countries.
“As volatile and turbulent as the world may be, we remain firmly committed to the rules -based multilateral commercial system, with the WTO [World Trade Organization] as a nucleus, while actively participating and supporting regional economic cooperation.”
The “numerous advantages of Hong Kong” are referred to, with its “highly internationalized business environment, a flexible and solid financial system, a simple and secure tax regime with low tax rates and a robust and independent legal system”.
However, in the document it is also stressed that the “tariff war caused a global reallocation of capital”, and Hong Kong wants to bet on the attraction of “foreign companies and capital” to the region.
The report also tells that "international organizations and foreign trade chambers in Hong Kong are confident in the future perspectives" of the territory, and that for the authorities "there is no reason to worry about some excessively pessimistic feelings."
"In fact, the Raehk government is creating a new momentum and expanding the ability to support Hong Kong's economic growth, thus increasing its overall competitiveness and achieving high quality development," is still added.
The executive spokesman also established a parallelism between good economic situation and political stability. "In recent years, the implementation of the National Security Law has restored a stable social environment in Hong Kong. This not only protected the rights and freedoms of the general public, but also made Hong Kong a safe haven to attract international capital and investment," he concluded. The report was presented by the secretary for Hong Kong finances, Paul Chan.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Rain | HK alerts and more than 80,000 residents of Beijing removed from home</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/chuva-alertas-em-hk-e-mais-de-80-mil-residentes-de-pequim-retirados-de-casa/</link><description>China and Hong Kong have faced periods of heavy rainfall in recent days that have forced extra care and residents' travel. In the Chinese capital 82,000 people had to leave their homes, while in Hong Kong streets and a hospital suffered floods and some subway stations were closed
 
Strong rains continue not to give respite, not only in Macau (see page 7), but in Hong Kong and in the interior of the country. In the case of China, Beijing authorities moved more than 82,000 people from home due to torrential rain, a week after deadly floods that led those responsible for recognizing failures in the response, the official news agency Xinhua said yesterday.
Thus, tens of thousands of residents were removed from the most affected areas by rain until 9 pm on Monday, local time, according to the Municipal Flood Response Center. The center warned of the high risk of floods in the districts of Miyun (northwest), Fangshan (southwest), lied (west) and Huairou (north).
The Chinese capital kept in force the red alert-the highest-until yesterday morning, before predictions of heavy rainfall between Monday to noon and the morning of Tuesday.
Last week, these same rural districts north of Beijing were the most affected by the weather that caused 44 dead and nine missing, according to official data. Most of the deadly victims were registered in a home of elderly in Miyun.
New measures in agriculture
The severity of the catastrophe led municipal authorities to recognize “gaps” in the preparation of emergency services. Natural disasters are frequent in China during summer, with some regions subject to torrential rainfall and others to severe droughts.
However, the Chinese authorities have reinforced the device to respond to the adverse effects of intense rainfall and heat waves on agricultural crops in various regions of the country, at a crucial time for autumn harvesting.
Since the beginning of the rainy season, east and northern China zones have recorded episodes of extreme precipitation, while provinces such as Henan (center) and Anhui (East) face prolonged periods of drought and high temperatures.
This combination of meteorological phenomena represents a challenge for farmers, especially when about two months left to harvest the main autumn cereals, the official news agency Xinhua yesterday pointed out.
In the province of Shaanxi (Center), where precipitation recently exceeded 100 millimeters in less than 24 hours, local authorities adopted preventive measures such as channel cleaning and reinforcement of dikes, which allowed to protect most of the cultivated lands.
However, Henan agricultural cooperatives affected by drought opted for gout watering systems and localized application of fertilizers to conserve moisture and minimize losses.
Authorities have given priority to the rehabilitation of water infrastructure and the dissemination of efficient water management techniques in the absence of precipitation in some areas. The autumn campaign represents a fundamental component of China's annual cereal production.
In a statement issued yesterday, the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs warned that weather conditions in the coming weeks will be determining and appealed to "all efforts to protect the harvest and give strong support to the country's food security."
Chinese President Xi Jinping said in 2023 that, although “1,400 million Chinese eat well” currently, “the food issue should not be careless”, stressing that the supply of food “is not an insignificant issue”.
China has less than nine percent of the planet's aurable land, although it represents about 18 percent of the world's population. In the last summers, weather disasters have caused significant damage in the country: the 2023 scirred months were marked by flooding in Beijing, which caused more than 30 dead, while by 2022 several extreme and dried heat waves hit the center and east of China.
Hong Kong on Alert
With regard to the panorama of heavy rains in neighboring territory, they have not given respite either. According to public broadcaster RTHK, some hong Kong stations were closed yesterday due to the risk of flooding, given that the Hong Kong Observatory kept the black signal of storm [Black Rainestorm Warning Signal] until around 17 hours.
Winds of about 110 kilometers per hour were recorded in some areas of the territory, and thunderstorms were also registered. The rthk channel also reveals that more than 10,800 lightnings were counted in the territory between midnight and 10 am yesterday, half of them occurred on Lantau Island.
Until 11 am yesterday, the authorities responsible for the drainage systems recorded 21 episodes of flooding, and 180 emergency responses were made in 240 different locations.
Highlight for the occurrence of an episode at Queen Mary Hospital this Tuesday, namely “on some roads” hospital access in Pok Fu Lam, and patients were displaced by firefighters to Ruttonjee Hospital in the Wanchai area. In some zones of the hospital the water reached the knees, and sand bags were placed to stop the flow of the rains. At about 11 am yesterday this scenario was resolved, with the normal one returning to the Queen Mary Hospital near noon.
The rains also led to the large increase in water level in the Lower Shing Mun reservoir in the Sha Tin area, which led to the notification of nearby housing complexes, such as Mei Lam Estate, May Shing Court, Mei Chung Court and Granville Garden.
Despite the heavy rains, some people went to work normally doing alternative routes. This was the case of Mak, a woman who, to the RTHK channel, said she had to make a deviation to get to the office. “I couldn't go straight to there and had to make a longer route. The metro [mtr] made some warnings [about the storm and closures], but I would like them to do them in the carriages as well, because I only realized that access was closed when I got to the exit,” he described.
The sun
Information provided by the Hong Kong Observatory speaks of the passage of an active "southwest monsoon and high altitude disturbances that are bringing heavy rainfall and violent thunderstorms to the southern coast of China and the northern part of the southern China Sea."
Yesterday the highest daily precipitation record was broken to August since 1884, upon registered, until 14h, 355.7 millimeters of precipitation at the Observatory's headquarters.
For today time should stay unstable in Hong Kong, with “heavy rains at the beginning” of the day. However, these "should gradually decrease" tomorrow, expected "a lot of heat with sunny periods in the next two days."
Also the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) leave a heavy rain alert to this day with “frequent, sometimes intense, thunderstorm”. The sun is expected to start appearing at the MSAR from tomorrow, still with some clouds, extending this weather scenario until next Monday. Temperatures should reach 33 degrees.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:29:54</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ | Researchers discover a new species of bacteria in Portugal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/08/usj-investigadores-descobrem-nova-especie-de-bacteria-em-portugal/</link><description>A team of local university researchers identified a new species of bacteria in the Salinas of Rio Maior, Portugal. The type of discovered organism, which lives in extreme environments, widens the limits of biological knowledge and may have implications in areas such as biomedicine, pharmacy or even spatial exploration
 
There is news in the field of microbiology thanks to the latest discovery of a team of researchers linked to the University of São José (USJ), led by André Antunes, interim director of the Institute of Sciences and Environment of the same educational institution.
It is the discovery of a new species of bacteria from 12 samples collected in the Salinas of Rio Maior, in Portugal, which led to the establishment of the new species “Fodinibius alkaliphilus”. The species of bacteria previously known as “Alifodinibius salipaludis” for “Fodinibius salipaludis” was also reclassified.
The conclusions appear in the article “Fodinibius alkaliphilus sp. Nov., Moderately halophilic and alkaliphilic bacterium isolated from an Inland Saltern in central and reclassification of aliifodinibius salipaludi as fodinibius salipalis sp. SYSTEMATIC AND EVOLUTIONARY MICROBIOLOGY. The scientific journal is a publication “reference for new macrobial data”, being the official publication of the International Procaryotes Systematic Committee and the Applied Bacteriology and Microbiology Division of the International Union of Microbiological Societies, describes a USJ note.
In addition to André Antunes, the authors team includes researchers from the University of Science and Technology of Macau, coordinated by Marta Filipa Simões; Researchers at the University of Minho and Seville University.
According to the same USJ note, "the new [bacteria] species grows better in salinities about four times higher than those of seawater and also prefers alkaline conditions, combining the ability to grow in different extreme environmental conditions."
The importance of this type of studies, including analyzes to “such extreme environments”, is “future applications in a wide range of fields, including biomedical and pharmaceutical, but also extends to the discovery of new useful materials and the provision of useful information for future space exploration”.
The same team of investigators is not stopped, as "other samples of these places are currently being investigated and new publications describing other new species are expected in the coming months."
“This publication highlights the strengths of Macao in articulation with partners from Portuguese and Spanish -speaking countries, as well as its growing importance in the fields of biodiversity and biotechnology,” is still described.
The Power of Salinas
The researchers explain that "the species Aliifodinibius Salipaludis has been described, but their name has not yet been validly published." In field work the team isolated these species from “hypersaline environments, including saline, salt mines and saline soils”.
Prior to the field work itself, the team conducted “an investigation to the microbial diversity of hypersaline environments in downtown Portugal”, with samples in the Rio Maior zone in July 2019, 12 genera bacteria were isolated from the Rio Maior salines.
Located in the central area of Portugal, in these Salinas there is the “brine, which is about seven times more salty than seawater”, being “pumping from a well and generated by the crossing of a local underground course with an extensive salt deposit”.
The article also gives a historical context of this location. "Although they were first referred to in twelfth-century documents, these places are believed to have been linked to salt extraction from prehistoric times. They offer a single scenario, as they are the only interior saline in Portugal and the only ones in full functioning throughout Europe."
Thus, the study in question “was part of a bioprospecting campaign centered on this place”, resulting in “the isolation of a bacterial strain (N2T) and the discovery of a new putative species within the genus Fodinibius”.
In this work is determined “the taxonomic position of this new isolated based on the phenotypic, chemotaxonos and molecular properties”, is described.
Importance for Science
At HM, André Antunes explained that this discovery is, first of all, interesting to the scientific community, by bringing “additional information” and constituting a discovery “about the biodiversity that exists on our planet, more concretely at the macrobial level”.
"So far, we have been able [general scientific community] to study less than 1 percent of all microbes species on the planet. In over 99 percent we have no idea what they are, what they do and what their abilities, or what impact on the environment and our lives," he explained.
The researcher also said that "the microbes that come from extreme environments, and above all from environments with a lot of salt, which is the case of this species we now discover, are very interesting for a large range of biotechnology applications."
"We can include things like the medical area, biomedicine, the production of new pharmaceutical compounds or the production of new biomaterials, such as bioplastics," said André Antunes. The academic even talks about applications in “more exotic areas, which are now beginning to have a little more visibility, such as the potential application in construction, the production of more sustainable cements or concrete structures that have the self -repair capacity”.
This discovery also has some impact "for space exploration, more specifically to better understand what the limits of life are and where to seek life outside our planet." It is also included "very important implications for missions that are exploring Mars, namely as to the type of environments where it may be feasible to find past signs of life or present or other parts of the solar system."
A job that continues
The investigation is not for the Salinas of Rio Maior, and the team led by André Antunes last year, an expedition to Antarctica. “There are antarctic samples that we are currently studying and we have samples taken from the red sea bottom, where salt concentration is also quite high.” Therefore, the saga of discovering new bacteria and potential reclassifications in those that already exist.
André Antunes says that the discovery of a new species of microbes "is quite important to science, not only for the perspective of science at the basic level, but because we can have a better perspective of diversity we have on the planet."
“As we study extreme environments we can have additional information about what the limits of life are and how life adapts to extreme conditions.” Thus, André Antunes advocates investment in science so that there is later “an associated practical component, so it is not always easy to convince the financing entities”, as to this point.
The researcher also points out that the article and the investigation fits “very well in the priorities of Macau and the USJ itself, with regard to the focus in the area of environment, biodiversity and biotechnology, anchored in connection with Lusophony”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:04:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin | Open contest for remodeling of Praça Dezhi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/hengqin-aberto-concurso-para-remodelacao-da-praca-dezhi/</link><description>The idea is to create a new city linked to the university, instead of the old plan for the replica of a German city. The public tender is open for the remodeling of Praça Dezhi, in Hengqin, with apartments next to the new neighborhood of Macau and the Campus of the University of Macau
 
A public tender is opened for the remodeling of Praça Dezhi, in the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, in the space that has been designed to house the replica of a typically German city.
Now, what is intended to be that Praça Dezhi will become a future university city, with apartments and other services, because it is so close to the new Macau neighborhood in Hengqin and also the campus of the University of Macao in this neighboring region.
The contest, open until the 29th of this month, involves the transformation of a space with 13 buildings, in a total area of 49 thousand square meters, and the area intended for construction is 65 thousand square meters. In the new tenhi square, high buildings are expected for student activities, offices, apartments, a hotel and ten buildings for auxiliary teaching activities.
The newspaper or world describes some details of the project, and it can be read that the specific location of Hengqin “brings strategic importance to this work, which means that cooperation between Macau and Hengqin has already entered a new stage in order to support Macau in a better integration in national development” in the country.
Response to scarcity
Still in the details of the project cited by the or world, it is described that the renewal of the Praça Dezhi also aims to respond to the scarcity of space in the masters.
“The scarcity of land in Macao limits, in the long run, the expansion of higher education institutions and their academic update. The completion of this transient campus not only satisfies the needs of Macao higher education and research for a certain period, but also encourages a deeper integration of advantageous areas for universities, such as traditional Chinetic medicine and the field of microelectronics.”
Thus, it is added, “in conjunction with the hengqin industries, through the 'Campus + Industrial Park' model contributes to Macau to form new production forces and reach a diverse [economic] development,” is quoted.
Praça Dezhi was thought, before the pandemic, to be the German City Hengqin, the replica of a typical German city with 150,000 square meters where German and Chinese cultures would converge. According to an article from the 2020 South China Morning Post newspaper, the project intended to attract investments from the large bay zone, with US $ 229 million investment from TFG International, a company listed on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange. An International Center for Convention and Exhibitions would also be built, as well as hotels and offices.
The sale of properties started in 2019, but was stagnant due to the pandemic years. In addition, there were several disputes and many owners could not receive the houses where they had invested the money.
In the announcement of the new project, it is read that the work for Praça Dezhi continues to maintain “the European architectural characteristics”, highlighting the future characteristics of the university city in interior and outer spaces, designed for leisure zones and shows.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Interest | Banking with more than two thousand bonus requests</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/juros-banca-com-mais-de-dois-mil-pedidos-de-bonificacao/</link><description>The bank sector has already received two thousand requests under the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (PME), launched by the Executive in April.
According to the newspaper or Mun, IP Sio Kai, deputy and president of the Macao Banks Association, said that if all requests are approved, this represents an amount of 30 billion patacas. IP Sio Kai stated that more than half of the available quotas are free for assignment.
The official said that about 80 percent of these requests represent new loans, while 20 percent of orders were made to refund old loans granted. The deputy stated that traditional sectors such as retail restoration or sale continue to suffer from the breach of dislocated consumption to the interior of China, or even to digital buying platforms such as Taobao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:28:14</pubDate></item><item><title>FM | Support applications end Friday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/fm-candidaturas-a-apoios-terminam-sexta-feira/</link><description>The Macau Foundation (FM) yesterday launched an alert for the deadline for delivering applications to the three plans to assign financial support for 2026, which ends next Friday at 5:30 pm. "After this date, it will not be accepted any candidacy, so we draw the most attention of the stakeholders," added the body.
The three financial support plans are divided between “academic projects”, “community activities” and “exchanges”. Interested parties who have not yet submitted applications can do so through the FM online platform and the company and association platform.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:27:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Synergy | Ron Lam podcast comes to an end</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/sinergia-de-macau-podcast-de-ron-lam-chega-ao-fim/</link><description>After eight years of live transmission, the Macau Synergy Association podcast, led by Ron Lam, will end in episode 346, broadcast today at 9 pm.
According to a Facebook shared publication, the episode will outline a retrospective and balance of the broadcasts of the last eight years.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:26:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal | Information Search reflects interest from voters</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/caeal-busca-de-informacao-reflecte-interesse-dos-eleitores/</link><description>The president of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly said yesterday that in a week about 116,000 people consulted information about the polling place. Song Ioi Man considers that the volume of consultations demonstrates the electoral's interest in the electoral act
 
In the space of one week, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) registered about 116,000 information on the vote, yesterday said the president of the body that organizes the suffrage of September 14. Song Ioi Man considers that the volume of consultations reflects the interest with which the population accompanies the work related to the electoral process.
Last Tuesday, several means of consultation were launched for voters to learn about the voting assembly attributed through the Single Account application, an open line, the Caeal page and in self-service kiosks for public services.
At a press conference on the way out of another body meeting, the judge also said that on Friday the distribution of public spaces that will be destined for election campaign activities. Thus is completed another step for the beginning of the campaign period, which starts on August 30 and will last 14 days.
When asked what happens if a list conducts election campaign actions outside Macao and the established deadline, the president of Caeal stressed that the electoral law also applies outside Macao. According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the official said he hoped the police authorities will have the means capable of dealing with the situation and overseeing activities outside the MSAR, namely through police cooperation mechanisms with abroad authorities.
Act Guardians
During the suffrage, while the ballot boxes are open, between 09h and 21h, each list can appoint two representatives (one staff and an alternate), to oversee the electoral process in each of the voting assemblies.
The president of Caeal said that the lists may present the names of representatives between next Saturday and 25 August, so that they obtain an entity certificate, which should be lifted at the Caeal reception counter, in the public administration building, on Rua do Campo, until two days before election day. One of the requirements of these representatives is to vote at the voting assemblies they will oversee.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:23:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Ticket Sale | IC says he is attentive to any circumvents</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/venda-de-bilhetes-ic-diz-estar-atento-a-eventuais-burlas/</link><description>The president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Leong Wai Man, ensures that everything is being done to wage the occurrence of tickets associated with the sale of tickets for shows.
In response to Deputy Nick Lei's questioning, it is stated that “the government has been aware of ticket sales or streams in the sale of tickets for concerts and major shows”, applying the legal regime of infractions against public health and the economy, 1996.
It is referred to, in the same answer, that the Judiciary Police (PJ) have been “doing diverse police work, intensifying the prevention and combating crimes related to the sale of tickets for shows”, making “regular inspections on the network [platforms] of sale”.
In the same response, the resolution of a case discovered in July, which was a scam that involved 560,000 Renminbis starring “a woman from Macao who claimed to be selling tickets in an online group communication application”.
Leong Wai Man says the IC began to implement the registration system of spectator names, with a "previous registration, draw and later purchase" process, and the person's identification is made, as well as "taking steps to combat illegal conduct, such as high prices ticket resale." It is also mentioned that the idea behind the creation of an outdoor spectacle place of Macao "is in the experimental phase."</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 23:50:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Food Waste | Pereira Coutinho suggests combat plan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/desperdicio-alimentar-pereira-coutinho-sugere-plano-de-combate/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho wants the government to combat food waste and the abundance culture of banquets and buffets to be coordinated with food banks and charities. The deputy asked if legislation is expected to encourage or oblige the separation of organic waste
 
Food waste in Macau is a problem for which Pereira Coutinho would like to see an integrated combat strategy. In a written interplies released yesterday, the deputy highlights the gap between the culture of abundance of social events and the operational difficulties in the collection of food surpluses for distribution to needy families and solidarity institutions.
This culture, banquets, buffets and celebrations, “associated with commercial practices that oversee productions, generates critical volumes of surpluses, especially prepared breads, cakes and meals, aggravating the inefficiency of the food chain”, denounces the deputy.
To solve food waste in the commercial sector, Pereira Coutinho asks the government if he intends to introduce “standards that encourage or oblige supermarkets, restaurants and other food companies to donate food surpluses still suitable for consumption to social solidarity institutions”. The deputy cites examples of laws in force in Portugal and France, which could be followed by the executive.
In addition, it asks if it is possible to implement measures, such as tax incentives, logistical support, simplification of procedures or certification programs, to “facilitate the creation of systematic partnerships between commercial food establishments (supermarkets, restaurants, bakeries, hotels and others) and private entities such as food banks or charities”.
So what about the environment?
Putting the issue of food waste from the perspective of the popular concept of sustainability, Pereira Coutinho points out not only ethical challenges and their social and economic implications, but also environmental.
Firstly, it is urgent to sensitize the population to the need to reduce food waste. The deputy then emphasizes the need to correct the “critical infrastructural disabilities in the management of organic waste, manifested in the absence of industrial composting centers and intelligent logistics networks to donate surpluses in time”.
Also the ecological consequences, with greenhouse gas emissions, decomposition in landfills and incinerators, should be addressed. As such, Coutinho asks if the government considers it to create a legal framework that “encourages or obliges the separation of organic waste, namely eating waste, origin (domestic, commercial and institutional)”. The objective is to give proper treatment to waste, such as composting or anaerobic digestion, rather than the use of the landfill.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paradise Lost</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/paradise-lost/</link><description>Apollonian August is not the right time to take a book of this dimension in the luggage, which the notion of paradise may not coincide with thousands of lines of verses organized in twelve books, which time appeals to it, to paradise, but it is necessary to safeguard other more components. This split between paradises, by the way, was felt by multiple authors leading to great theories, discussions, interpretations, and debates, in what would be known as the Miltonian criticism in the twentieth century, that the first version of the work, this one published in 1667. For all this there will be and always people who are bored.
The epic style should not dismantle those who want to enter the foliage of this paradise, the blank verse that is armed is a kind of free verse that has to do with the syntactic complexity of descriptions that require great flexibility in a consecutive network between classic and biblical. There are many acrostics, which makes the poem an initiation to what would later become visual poetry. Two columns are outlined here: Lucifer, Adam, and Eve, then the angelic wars and the archangels in a three -day battle in which the rebels banned, God creates the world. The story goes on a intricate parade about free will, which sliding in the fall, Lucifer ends up close and transformed in the face of the two creatures that God created for a different design from what happens.
Problems in paradise are not often factual, but almost always, symbolic, if among the network of blessings there is one that will betray the harmonic movement for which any paradise is created, the eye of God who sees everything, takes forum of justice and distance. William Blake said: "The reason that led Milton to write chained when he did it over angels and God, and in freedom when he wrote about demons and hell, is because he was a true poet and was part of the devil's party unknowingly."
English romanticism saw this in Milton.  Giovanni Papini would not have been more logo.
In the hot summer paradise this will not be unmeasured by a less routine stop, and it can still be thought that paradises are many but not as many as what is mentioned here. Milton was blinded and dictated his poem, which already tells us a lot about the activity of scribe, here, where there is always salvation for the defeated. We will read Book IV as we read Canto IX of the Lusíadas, which is where Adam and Eve appear to us, but a bad angel escapes from the abyss to turn lovers into future martyrs- and Gabriel the most moving angel of heaven- he always appears to save lovers, announce pregnancy, unite the Abraamic tribes. He appears. [Sleep packed night night, and in both naked rain roses from the ceiling in flower that the alvah replenishes. Sleep happily… 768]
The first Portuguese translation is in 1789, others would be followed in a small public space as paradise are after all.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:46:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Silent angels</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/12/anjos-silenciosos/</link><description>Last July 10, the Hong Kong TVB news reported that in Australia, Melbourne and Sydney, the courts started to have dogs to support the victims while witnessing in court.
Labradors and Golden Retriever are preferred dogs for this function. They are sweet and can support the victims. It takes two years to train a “court dog” and costs approximately 150,000 hkd, a value similar to the training of a guide dog.
Victims are usually women and children. They are mostly witness to the Family Court in domestic violence processes and are subject to great emotional tension. The monitoring of court dogs allows victims to relax, that interrogation time is reduced and the process to be facilitated.
Tribunal dogs are trained by Guide Association, the training is paid by the Law Society, Australia, and are accommodated on the court's premises.
Scientific research shows that dog monitoring can reduce the secretion of tension hormones, make thinking clearer and reduce stress more effectively. From a legal point of view, they have the advantage of not talking and cannot affect the witness of the victims. This measure is easily accepted by the accusation and defense.
Australia is not the first country to appeal to court dogs. Already in 2021, Japan used them. There are currently four court dogs in Japan and are mainly used to accompany children while their testimonies are recorded. In an old case of children's abuse, a girl refused to go to court. Later, he bravely confronted the aggressor in public, accompanied by one of these "silent angels." This was the first time in Japan where a dog attended a trial. This is why these dogs are called “silent angels.”
According to Japanese official data, 160,000 cases of child abuse were reported in 2019. If the number of court dogs will be increased to deal more effectively with these cases.
In addition to Australia and Japan, court dogs are also used in the United Kingdom, the United States, France, Canada and Chile. There are currently 240 tax dogs in the United States, divided by 35 states.
The law gives all equal rights. The Court uses standard procedures to hear the testimonies of the victims, the defendants and the witnesses of each case. Regardless of the equal rights of the complaint and the defendant, and the standardization of the court's procedures, each case presents its own difficulties. When the victim witness is emotionally disturbed and the details and the accuracy of the testimony are questionable. So, how can the court accept the testimony? How can vague testimony help but in the defendant's acquittal? The presence of court dogs to stabilize the emotions of the victims is important so that they can boldly report the facts and allow a fair judgment to be allowed. This measure reduces the suffering of those who revive a painful experience and manifest empathy with the victims. No wonder it is called the “silent angels” tax dogs.
It is certainly appropriate to give good use to the special qualities of dogs for the benefit of humans. From these successful experiences, Hong Kong and Macao courts may consider implementing measures to improve the effectiveness of their procedures. In addition, there may be the need to adapt the court's premises to put, for example, dog bathrooms. Questions such as this should be considered before the use of court dogs is used.
The measures needed to introduce tax dogs remind us many others that were previously implemented in the Hong Kong courts to help with the trials. For example, in the case of Donald Tsang, the former head of the Raehk executive, the case was broadcast live on television to allow it to be seen by all. Another example is the testimony of the victims of sexual abuse hidden by a screen; or of witnesses that are questioned by video called. None of these measures have to do with the law of the law, but have improved the effectiveness of judgment and are the demonstration that the feeling of the victims is taken into consideration. The implementation of measures aimed at the protection of the victims must be considered, either in the system of consummented law or in the civil law system.
Finally, in addition to the use of court dogs, society should take steps to reduce cases of abuse, violation and violence against women and children. This is the correct approach to attacking the root of the problem and building a peaceful and friendly society.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 00:24:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Valia immigrants</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/imigrantes-mais-valia/</link><description>In any city in the country we go to or faced a hotel, restaurant, hypermarket, construction work, home support, hospital, commercial store, factory, vintage, olive or other fruits harvest, we find immigrants from Angola, Guinea-Bissau, Sao Tome, Brazil, Cape Verde, Nepal or Bangladesh. All speaking Portuguese, integrated in the great need that Portugal has a lack of labor and to contribute to the support of social security. It is with great satisfaction that we are served in a good restaurant where employees, dressed in rigor, extreme education and exemplary kindness convey to us that they are from Angola, Guinea-Bissau or Brazil.
They are human beings like the Portuguese who opted for Spain, France, Germany, Finland, the US, Australia, Canada or Timor-Leste. Portuguese who were learning the local language, integrating in society and, essentially, received with the social benefits in force in these countries. In Portugal, we have not yet received immigrants with the dignity they deserved. Most still have to lease a room or a house or, once integrated, assume a bank credit to purchase a property.
Some already working immigrants who discount social security are still dominated by the impossibility of living with dignity because they await the title of residence, fall into the hands of the mafias that sell a tent on the outskirts of big cities. Often, there are mayors who before building social housing are embarked on the demolition of tents, leaving these families without ceiling and sleeping in the open, in a gesture of great cruelty and misunderstanding.
Of course, immigrants who move to Portugal with a tour visa and then get here illegally and living 20 in a room, they cannot think of acquiring the status of residents. They live in the penance, exploited by the own compatriots and illegal before the Portuguese law. In this regard, the government is taking regulation measures for the entry of immigrants. However, this regulation cannot be radical as André Ventura argues, who, in turn, only wants not to enter Portugal or a neo -fascist's will and will even be expelled all immigrants. Ventura has claimed that crime in Portugal is due to the presence of immigrants. Nothing more wrong.
The theory that immigration is responsible for increasing crime, that the latest vacancy of immigration, whatever their nationality, is less desirable than the previous ones, that all newcomers must be faced with an attitude of suspicion is an almost old theory as the English-created colonies on the coast of New England. Recently, the director of the Judicial Police cited figures regarding violent crime, which has been decreased for 20 years and the fact that the ratio of prisoners have evolved in the opposite reason for the increase of the immigrant population.
The same kind of evolution happened to those detained by the police that Luís Neves directs. Thus, if in 2009, when the resident foreign population totaled less than half a million (454 191), the PJ detained 631 foreigners (corresponding to 138.9 detained per 100,000 immigrants), in 2023, with the number of more than duplicate resident foreigners (1 044 605), there were 513 detainees, corresponding to 49.1 per 100,000 residents.
To substantiate his statements, the PJ director explained more: not only this reduction in the ratio of foreign detainees compared to the number of non -Portuguese residents has been consistent in the last 14 years, but a considerable part of foreign detainees and prisoners, especially related to drug trafficking, not immigrants, but elements of what gives the name of “transnational crime” - with the “mules of mules” drug ”.
Another demonstrative fact that increased crime is not directly linked to immigrants is the evidence that municipalities have released. Municipalities with the highest weight of immigrants have less crime.
Some examples of municipalities where foreign population has a significant impact on the resident population, with data from 2023: Vila do Bispo (where immigrants represent 43.68%of the total population), Odemira (41.8%) and Lisbon (28.7%). If there was a direct relationship between immigration and crime, it would be expected that the increase of resident foreigners would be reflected directly on a climb of crimes registered by police authorities.
But nothing more wrong. Municipalities with the highest weight of immigrants have less crime. Regarding Porto, where immigrant crimes have increased by the media, the growing evolution of foreign residents is also not accompanied by an increase in crime, and even a decrease in crime in years of increased immigration. In 2009 a total of 17,383 crimes was recorded, the year in which 8809 foreigners resided there. In 2019, the crimes went down to 15,422 and resident foreigners increased to almost double: 14,558. In 2023, foreigners resident in Porto again doubled - to 35,653 - and the total of crimes registered from 14,552. In Porto, foreigners currently represent 14.3% of the population.
Of all this, we can understand that what André Ventura and his party propagate at all times relating the increase of crime with immigrants is just a racist bullshit to match the attitudes of neo -Nazi that have done everything violently against immigrants.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 06:13:17</pubDate></item><item><title>COP30 - A challenge for Brazil</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/cop30-um-desafio-para-o-brasil/</link><description>The last two conferences of the United Nations Convention in the United Nations Convention on Climate Change took place in 2023 and 2024, respectively in the United Arab Emirates (COP28) and Azerbaijan (COP29), which, as oil producing countries, should not be very interested in energy transition.
Now it is up to Brazil to organize CPO30, from November 10 to 25, 2025, in Belém, Pará. This is not the first time this country has been predisposed to organize such a conference. He had already been invited, and accepted the invitation to organize COP25. However, the government headed by Bolsonaro, a convinced negotiation such as his American mentor Donald Trump, "Roi the rope," said it as a said, claiming that the problem of climate change would be just a commercial game.
Chile was then tasked with being the new host, but the great disorders that occurred in this country before the scheduled dates, made the conference to Madrid, between December 2 and 13, 2019. It was an opportunity that was lost to project Brazil as one of the leading countries of the fight against climate change.
It turns out that Brazil is among the ten largest producers of gross oil and there are those who doubt that the Brazilian government is greatly interested in the energy transition. Undoubtedly, Lula da Silva's governments have taken into consideration, to some extent, the preservation of the Amazon and the well-being of indigenous populations, and have been committed in oil exploration in areas that may affect them. However, the great commercial value of oil makes it often subaltern the fact that fossil fuels are proven to be the main factor in increasing greenhouse gas concentration in the atmosphere and, consequently, global warming. There was even someone1 in Brazil who even said that oil exploration would contribute to funding the energy transition.
There is no doubt that COP30 in Belém will contribute to Brazil has an increasingly important role in the context of the problem inherent in climate change. It will be necessary, however, much skill on the part of the Brazilian government to convince the international community about its intentions to the commitment made when the Paris Agreement signed, in which the need to limit global warming up, until the end of the 21st century, to a maximum of 2 ° C, preferably to values less than 1.5 ° C. In this context, the Brazilian official policy seems not to be very coherent, especially since it has already been approved by the House of Representatives and the Senate, the infamous project-Law No. 2159 of 2021, nicknamed “PL of devastation”, because it opens the way to potentially serious ventures to the environment, such as the much discussed “offshore” oil exploration near the Amazon River mouth. This project, also called “equatorial margin”, may, in the face of the risk of oil spill, affect indigenous communities and biodiversity in the vicinity of the exploration zone. In case of such happening, it would not be the first time in Brazil, meeting that, in 2001, a platform operated by Petrobras suffered several explosions, which caused its sinking with about 1,500 tons of gross oil and the death of 11 people.
Incidents of this type in ocean facilities where perforation is not rare. Examples can be mentioned recurring strokes in the nineties of the last century in the North Sea on Shell-operated platforms, with serious consequences for the maritime environment. More recently there was a stroke in the Gulf of Mexico in 2010, where the damage of a security valve on a BP platform caused an explosion that caused the death of 8 workers and a stroke of about 780 million liters of oil, causing irreparable damage to maritime fauna. Incidents of this type may also affect ecosystems that mangais are part, causing damage to the transition zones between the coast and the sea, resulting in the destruction of ecosystems and the increase of erosion caused by the associated waves, or not, to storm tides.
Aware of these inconvenient potentials, the Brazilian Institute of Environment and Renewable Natural Resources (Ibama), has been denied licenses for oil exploration several times in the vicinity of the mouth of the Amazon River. According to the “PL of devastation”, “special environmental licenses” may occur for projects considered strategic, which, after submission to the entity responsible for licensing and in the absence of response within one year, would automatically be licensed. Considering that Ibama is characterized by staff scarcity, there will be the risk of projects submitted to be approved, after this period.
Given that the president can completely or partially veto the project-law, within 15 days after his submission by Congress2, it is now liable for Lula da Silva to take this attitude. There are only a few days to do so, because the deadline will in principle end on August 8.
Throughout this process, President Lula da Silva, unlike the minister of the “Environment and Climate Change”, Marina Silva, has shown a certain passivity, which causes some fear about her attitude regarding the promulgation of the decree. According to the most progressive means in Brazil, Lula da Silva should not have been silent after the approval by Congress, but staying firm vetoing the project “PL of devastation” and other potentially disastrous and attentive projects of forests and populations. In case of veto, it needs to be explained by invoking legal or political reasons, such as unconstitutionality or not convenience or opportunity.
In the meantime, an international campaign of Avaaz “Brazil: Stop the Devastation Bill” is underway, with about one million supporters.
But not everything is in the hands of Lula, as, in case of veto, the project-Law returns to Congress, which may impose the promulgation of the respective law, if the veto is overthrown by the absolute majority of the votes of the deputies and senators. The last word is, therefore, from Congress. However, there is a great expectation of what will be the attitude of Lula da Silva.
It is a tremendous challenge about the balance between environmental protection and economic development.
(Meteorologist)
References:
Jean Paul Prates - President of Petrobras from January 26, 2023 to May 14, 2024
National Congress - Maximum body of the Legislative Power, composed by the Chamber of Deputies and the Federal Senate.
AVAAZ - Global scale movement that seeks to give voice to civil society in the areas of democracy, human rights and sustainability of the land.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:04:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal | Folio Festival returns to Óbidos with two Nobel Program Nobel Program</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/portugal-festival-folio-regressa-a-obidos-com-dois-nobel-da-literatura-no-programa/</link><description>The Folio-International Obidos Literary Festival, which will take place between October 9 and 19, will feature in this edition with two Nobel Prizes of the Literature: Belarusian Svetlana Alexievich and South African J. M. Coetzee, the organization announced.
In its 10th edition, the festival will bring Óbidos, in the district of Leiria, two laureates with the Nobel Prize for Literature, reinforcing “the international dimension and the growing prestige of the event in the European and worldwide cultural scenario”, said the City Hall, organizer of the event.
Belarussian writer and journalist Svetlana Alexievich, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 2015, will participate in the folio on October 11, at a table of authors scheduled for 9 pm.
Svetlana Alexievich is the author of five prose books that constitute the literary project “Voices of Utopia”, of which the works “Voices of Chernobyl,“ War has no woman's face ”,“ The End of Soviet Man ”,“ The Last Witnesses ”and“ Zinc Boys ”are part.
On October 17, the folly will host John Maxwell Coetzee, a South African writer who received the Nobel Prize in Literature in 2003. J. M. Coetzee is the author of several novels and rehearsals, most of them translated into Portuguese, including “the life and time of Michael K.”, with which he first received the Booker award in 1983 and “ Disgrace ”, which earned him the same prize in 1999.“ Waiting for the barbarians ”,“ The Island ”and“ The Iron Age ”are other works of the writer.
“Your folio intervention will be one of the highlights of this edition and a unique contact opportunity with a central figure of contemporary literary thinking,” says the festival organization.
In addition to the two Laureates with the Nobel Prize in Literature, they are confirmed in the 2025 authors such as American journalist Anne Applebaum, Israeli historian Avi Shlaim, Irish writer Paul Murray and American Carmen Maria Machado.
For reflection
The 2025 edition of the festival has as its theme “Borders” and, according to the House, the program, which should be presented in the coming weeks, “proposes a critical and plural reflection on the geographical, political, linguistic, identity”.
The festival will feature roundtables, conversations with authors, reading sessions, concerts, exhibitions, performances, book launches, school public initiatives, children's programming and various network actions with schools, universities, libraries and bookstores.
Organized by the Municipality of Óbidos, in partnership with the Municipal Company Óbidos Criativa, Read slowly and the Inatel Foundation, the folio had its first edition in 2015, only interrupted in 2020 due to the Covid-19 pandemic.
The 2024 edition attracted more than 100,000 people to the municipality of Óbidos, a creative city of UNESCO literature since 2015.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:42:25</pubDate></item><item><title>GARDEN House | Inaugurated “After Eastern Garden” with works by local and foreign artists</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/casa-garden-inaugurada-after-oriental-garden-com-obras-de-artistas-locais-e-estrangeiros/</link><description>Since yesterday, the Oriente Foundation welcomes another exhibition, integrated into the annual program of “Macao Art: Macao International Art Biennial”. It is “After Eastern Garden”, curated by Kathine Cheong, who welcomes Charlie Perez-Tlatechi, Elói Scarva, Ho Tzu Nyen, Jinjin Xu and Vividly, name of duo Jay Lee and Jay Lei
 
Since yesterday it is possible to visit at Casa Garden, headquarters of the Oriente Foundation (FO) in Macau, a new exhibition. It is “After Eastern Garden” [after the Eastern Garden ”, a collective show that can be seen until October 5th and is another initiative of“ Macao Art: International Art Biennial of Macao ”.
With free admission, the curatorship of this project was in charge of Kathine Cheong, revealing works where “Macau is the anchor to navigate the city's multifaceted memories, reflecting on the interconnection between colonial history, commercial flows and ecological changes,” describes a press release about the event.
The public will be able to see works by five groups of local and foreign artists, namely Charlie Perez-Tlatechi, Elói Scarva, Ho Tzu Nyen, Jinjin Xu and Vividly, name of the duo Jay Lee and Jay Lei. They all "transformed personal experiences into artistic creations in the form of files, sculptures, videos and sound installations."
In "After Oriental Garden", we seek to "destabilize stereotyped metanarratives, allowing hidden voices to surface and" other invisible "to be present in space." In the Garden house there will be, therefore, the “convergence of different artists” in a “interdisciplinary” format.
Multiple views
The exhibition presents the work of Elói Scarva, a Portuguese artist from Macau and who also works as a journalist. Scarva presents the sculpture work “Capsules - Eco Chambers”, composed of “eight temporal capsules that confront the physical evidence of cultural exchanges”. Founder of the “Republic of Arts of Coloane” Association, Elói Scarva has been promoting initiatives linked to contemporary art in the territory.
Another artist present in this show is Jinjin XU, whose art ways between Macau, Shanghai and New York. This responds to the appeal launched by the show with the work "poetic of the witness". The artist was recognized by the Chinese edition of Forbes as "one of the 100 most influential Chinese personalities."
Also noteworthy is for Singapore artist Ho Tzu Nyen, who presents the video “O of Opium”, where the historical impact of opium trade in the Asian region is reexamined. His most recent works address historical transformations and future visions of Asia.
Casa Garden also welcomes the work of emerging New York artist Charlie Perez-Tlatechi, who displays new and old works, which uses "materials and images as fables to reflect on hidden stories in the process of globalization."
Also present is the duo who adopted the name Vividly, and has been nominated four times for the Hong Kong Theater Libre awards. In Macau, the pair of artists presents "a new commissioned project on the journey of cities, memory and objects", entitled "Pulse of Things: A Memory under the missing stream."
This show is divided into three parts, namely “wandering echoes”, “East Journey” and “Palimpseste da Fénix”. The works arranged in the "wandering echoes" can be seen right on the stairs of Casa Garden, followed "trip to the East" with "three doors that head [the visitors] to different narrative spaces." In the final phase, "Palimpseste da Phenix", allows for a prolongation of all narratives counted above, "intertwining historical memory and contemporary experience, transforming them into recreation, establishing a space for open thinking."
In addition to the show itself, during the exposure period there will be parallel activities such as the Sonoro Concert “In the Garden-Flow of the Moon”, the research sharing “Tour Stories” by the Vividly Collective; The conversation of artists “Borders: Research Methods in Interdisciplinary Projects”, the Botany Workshop “Symbiotic Ramos: The Secret Language of Plants in Macao” and also educational workshops for secondary and university students.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:41:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Comic Band | Felix IP featured in the new FRC show</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/banda-desenhada-felix-ip-em-destaque-na-nova-mostra-da-frc/</link><description>Today is the exhibition “Comics 2025 + Hong Kong Machines”, hosted by the Rui Cunha Foundation. With works from various creators, the highlight goes to Felix IP, Hong Kong artist widely known for his work in this area and who worked as an animation cinema creative director
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) presents today, from 6.30 pm, the initiative “Comics 2025 + Hong Kong Machines” [Mango Artists Exhibition of the Great Bay "Macao Comics 2025 + Hong Kong Machines" Great Banda Bay. August. These are two productions co-organized by the Association of Promotion of Cultural Exchange of Comics and Animation of Macao. The opening of the exhibition today will be attended by Felix IP.
The curatorship is in charge of Howard Chan, president of that association. The exhibition features more than 60 artistic works, with 30 to be exhibited this week, signed by five artists of comics, mango and illustration by Macau. They are Leung Wai Ka, Nasu, Vincent Ho, Yeung Siu, and ST, highlighting the fact that they are all members of the association that co-organizes the event.
Star
In the second week, there is a presentation of 30 Felix IP works, which besides being a comic book artist, has worked as an illustrator and director in the area of animation, having also participated in the production of toys. Felix IP was creative cinema director of Imagi Animation Studios and Unicorn Animation Studios, and some of his best known works are “Zentrix”, “Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtle”, “Astroboy” and “Monkey King Reloaded”.
In 2012, the martial arts -adapted band “Blood and Steel”, by his own, won the Golden Dragon Prize for Best Cabolation Band for Adults. In 2019, the Illustrations Book “Hong Kong Machines 1”, which features a series of “rustic” robots with the connection of its nostalgic childhood memories, won the award for Best Art Book in the Asia-Pific animation and comic book category. The series “Hong Kong Machines” is the most popular among their work and has great support from the public and several companies.
Since 2023, this series has been expanding to the foreign market, such as Singa Machines, Malaysia Machines, Taiwan Machines and Thailand Machines. Recently, the "Blind Box" series of "Hong Kong Machines" - Tourist won the Golden Prize in the Hong Kong Smart Design Contest.
Felix IP's latest work, “Daydream Notebook”, won the silver award at the HK Comics Support Program, sponsored by Createhk.
The Macao's Cultural Exchange and Animation Promotion Association emerged in 2014 to support industry's professional development, technical exchange and cooperation between local and foreign illustrators, with a view to ensuring more high quality and large -scale projects, as well as publications, lectures and other activities that benefit the community of Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 23:55:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Gastronomy | Government promotes zape zone with tourist attraction</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/gastronomia-governo-promove-zona-do-zape-com-atraccao-turistica/</link><description>This week takes place the tourist and gastronomic initiative “Zape with Flavors”, between the pedestrian zones of Cantão Street and Xangai Street. From the 15th to the 24th of this month it will be possible to participate in a fair with the participation of local traders and that brings musical attractions and entertainment
 
The Zape area [landfill zone] has been on the agenda with requests for urban requalification and tourism, taking into account the closure of some satellite casinos at the site. In this context, the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), in partnership with the General Association of the Overseas Chinese of Macau (Agcum), decided to gather efforts and make a fair with gastronomy mixed with entertainment.
“Zape with flavors” is the name of the event that runs between the 15th and 24th of this month, taking place in the pedestrian zones of Cantão Street and Rua de Shanghai. According to a statement from STD, the fair "will feature the participation of traders and local shows, combining diverse gastronomy and cultural and creative elements." The idea is that, presenting such a project in Zape, it can be “showing the Macao Community Charm”.
Thus, it is intended to foster tourism in this area, with the snacks to be served between 15:30 and 22h under the theme “Flavors of Street Food in Food Truck”. “Southeast Asian customs and macao gastronomic diversity” are combined with six food and theme rulots and more than 30 stalls.
Music for all
This Zape fair will serve, in addition to food, games and entertainment for all tastes, as “local artists and associations will present dances and songs on stage, providing visitors with diverse experiences”, within the tourist ideas associated with gastronomy and, in turn, consumption.
There will be a hundred meals places and "an area with several facilities for the public to take photographs."
There are also incentives for consumption, because "during the fair period, if the public wants to buy any product on site, for every 100 patacas in purchases will have an opportunity to enter a claw game to take toys", and the higher the consumer value, the greater the number of offers. " There are also online promotions integrated in the program of “Zape with Flavors”.
The organizing entities of this event say they have consulted the associations of traders in the zone “to explain the content of this activity and collect opinions”, in order to ensure the event without startle or great impact on noise and urban management.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 06:11:05</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Detained for receiving money from burlas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/pj-detida-por-receber-dinheiro-de-burlas/</link><description>A woman from the interior of China was arrested at the siege gate border post after using five bank accounts on her behalf to receive about half a million dollars from Hong Kong -determined in circumvents.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the Judiciary Police (PJ) revealed that the suspect will have received 12,200 Renminbis to create accounts in Hong Kong banks to be used to transfer money from burlas.
According to the PJ version, the detained woman will have received Hong Kong's half million dollars from a resident who thought she was helping a family member. Authorities said there are more people involved in the case and that investigations to investigate their paradeiros continue. The woman was referred to the Public Prosecution Service on suspicion of high value scam crimes and money laundering.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:37:41</pubDate></item><item><title>“Podul” | Sign 1 of will be today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/podul-sinal-1-de-sera-hoje-icado/</link><description>Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) should today be signal 1 of tropical storm due to the influence of a “peripheral subsidence” caused by the “podul” tropical cyclone, located east of the Taiwan region.
The thunderstorm of the storm signal is given that the “Podul” should be 800 kilometers from the territory, heading towards the southern coast of Fujian and East Coast of Guangdong Province.
Today the time in the territory should be "extremely hot", and the high temperatures "can cause thunderstorms and rain with gusts of strong wind." Between today and Friday the weather should be “unstable, occurs occasional, sometimes strong, accompanied by thunderstorms”, also the SMG.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:36:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy | Profits grow 19 percent in the first half</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/galaxy-lucros-crescem-19-por-cento-no-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>In the first half of 2025, the Galaxy Entertainment group registered $ 5.24 billion of Hong Kong, an increase of 19.4 percent over the same period last year. In the note sent to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, the company also announced the distribution of dividends from the end of October
 
In the first six months of 2025, the Galaxy Entertainment Group registered an annual profit rise of almost one fifth. According to a note released yesterday, the game concessionaire found $ 5.24 billion from Hong Kong (HKD) in the first half of this year, the equivalent of an annual increase of 19.4 percent.
According to information given to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange, cited by the GGR Asia portal, the dealership will distribute dividends of 0.7 hkd per action from October 31st.
The growth was also found at the level of net profits, which reached at the end of the first semester nearly 23.25 billion HKD, which is equivalent to an increase of 8.3 percent compared to the same period of 2024.
Regarding the group's global results, the concessionaire reported a margin of profits before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) of about 6.87 billion HKD in the first half of the year, which represented a 14.2 percent per year.
The note sent by the group to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange also reveals that in the second quarter of 2025 the concessionaire had net profits of 12 billion HKD, more 10 percent than in the same period of 2024. The Ebitad between April and June this year registered an annual rise of 12 percent to a total of 3.6 billion HKD.
Regarding net profits only of the group's casinos, the first semester was synonymous with an annual rise of 10.7 percent to an approximate total of 18.58 billion HKD. On the other hand, the group's non-game net revenues ascended nearly 3.17 billion HKD in the period under analysis, the equivalent of an annual increase of 2.5 percent.
Effort proof
"I am happy to announce the solid performance of the Macao market and the Galaxy Entertainment in the second quarter and first half of 2025. Despite the disruptions brought by tariffs, continuous economic slowdown and regional competition, Macau remained resilient."
Galaxy's strong man highlighted the growth of all market segments, “in particular the premium mass segment”, as well as the group's financial health.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:34:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | Uses knife to extort money and is arrested</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/crime-usa-faca-para-extorquir-dinheiro-e-e-detido/</link><description>A Chinese interior citizen was arrested after threatening a casino player, also from the interior of China, with a table knife to transfer 69,000 Renminbis.
According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the woman met the man when they were both playing in a casino in the early hours of Tuesday, having convinced the player to go to her room.
There, the man carried out a robbery, cutting the woman's wrist with the knife, asking him to transfer the money, and then asked him to take off his clothes. It was then that the man photographed the naked woman, demanding her not to call the police. Only yesterday morning the Judiciary Police (PJ) picked up the man in the Cotai zone, in possession of game sheets and notes with a total value of $ 7.5 thousand from Hong Kong.
The case has already been referred to the Public Prosecution Service, running the risk of being accused of theft crimes, by stopping a weapon without justification and other instruments, for engraving and photographing illicitly and also for the wanton of private life, in this case against women.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:33:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Islands Hospital | More than 100 operations to Falls in a month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/hospital-das-ilhas-mais-de-100-operacoes-as-cataratas-num-mes/</link><description>A medical team from the Conde de São Januário Hospital and Hospital Hospital performed more than a hundred surgeries to cataracts since mid -July. Three surgeons from both hospitals have worked daily in a process that, from preparation to discharge, lasts less than three hours
 
Since mid -July, more than a hundred people have been operated on the cataracts at Hospital das Ilhas, the institution yesterday indicated in a statement. Operations have been performed daily by a team of three surgeons from the Ophthalmology Department of Hospital das Ilhas and the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, in coordination with health services.
The new hospital center states that, to increase efficiency, the islands hospital adopted the surgery model implemented by the department of ophthalmology of Peking Union Medical College Hospital. According to the model used at the Chinese capital hospital center, on the day of surgery, approved patients who meet the requirements usually go through the whole process, from admission to pre-surgery preparations to hospital discharge in less than three hours.
For patients who cannot leave the hospital on the same day due to special circumstances, the model allows them to change quickly and easily from the outpatient surgery program for hospitalization. Those responsible for the islands hospital to make sure that the flexibility of the personalized service model allows the discharge from the day after the operation, after an assessment of the surgeon. Authorities emphasize the convenience that the Beijing model gives to the elderly patients.
Continue to grow
In addition, it has been said that for a small number of more complex cataract surgeries, the islands hospital has experts from the Union Medical College and regularly invite expert teams with vast experience in cataract surgeries. As such, the institution emphasizes the importance of cooperation between Beijing and Macau to ensure the quality and safety of medical procedures performed at Hospital das Ilhas.
It is also indicated that ophthalmological problems will continue to increase in complexity and frequency as the population of Macao ages.
The medical institution is committed to continuing to optimize surgery services to cataracts, as well as the gradual integration of personnel from various departments, estimating that the number of patients ”that the hospital unit may meet will increase in the future.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:31:22</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands China | New non -executive director</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/sands-china-novo-director-nao-executivo/</link><description>Patrick Sydney Dumont is the new non-executive director of game operator Sands China, taking office last Friday, replacing Robert Goldstein, who retired.
The information was released by Sands China in a statement to the Hong Kong Stock Exchange and cited by the local media. Patrick will perform the function without a fixed term of appointment, becoming president and executive director of Las Vegas Sands, which controls Sands China, from March 2026, positions that were occupied by Goldstein. Since January 2021, Patrick Dumont has been president, director of operations and financial guardian of Las Vegas Sands, as well as director of the same company since April 2017. Patrick Dumont will also be part of the Sands China board of directors.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 23:53:50</pubDate></item><item><title>SMG | Tropical Cyclone may be tomorrow 800km from Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/11/smg-ciclone-tropical-podera-estar-amanha-a-800km-de-macau/</link><description>The Tropical Cyclone Podul is intensifying east of Taiwan and will approach the southeast coast of China throughout the week. Meteorological and geophysical services estimate that they reach the degree of typhoon and is 800 kilometers from Macau on tomorrow afternoon and 400 kilometers on Thursday, when it will be tropical depression
 
After a few days of truce, the intense and thunderstorm rains will be able to hide Macao from mid -week as the impact of the Severo “Podul” tropical cyclone will intensify, which was yesterday located in the Northwest Pacific, east of Taiwan.
Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) yesterday indicated that the storm is intensifying gradually and moving west at a speed of about 25 kilometers per hour. The latest forecast points to “Podul” intensify to the typhoon category when it is about 800 kilometers from Macau, tomorrow around 14h, when Taiwan will arrive. About 24 hours later, already on Thursday afternoon, predictions point to the reduction of the intensity of “Podul”, which will become a tropical depression, entering continental territory, about 400 kilometers northwest of Macao.
Intensity questions
Yesterday morning, the SMG still did not risk predicting a trajectory for the storm, pointing to two distinct predictions, before revealing the above estimate.
"Different forecast models still have significant differences in their trajectories and subsequent development. Numerical models predict that the‘ Podul ’follow a more north trajectory towards the areas between Fujian and Zhejiang, but some numerical and artificial intelligence models predict a south more trajectory, approaching the east coast of Guangdong," said SMG.
For now, the authorities report that the circulation of ‘podul’ is relatively small due to unfavorable development conditions, and it is expected to weaken after reaching Earth in Taiwan.
The SMG warned yesterday to the continuation of “extremely hot in the coming days” due to the influence of “an anticyclone at high altitude”. However, with the approach of “Podul”, the weather on the coast of Guangdong will become unstable, with the likelihood of intense rain in the end of this week. If “Podul” follows a closer trajectory to the eastern coast of Guangdong, the wind and the rain in Macau will be more intense.
The SMG appealed to the population to pay attention to the latest weather information, so that they can take contingency measures as soon as possible.</description><pubDate>2025-08-11 23:52:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed with scholastic rigor stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I do not always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funeral trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells will we have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts him a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people, which always seems the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Avian flu | China prohibits imports of poultry products from Spain</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/gripe-aviaria-china-proibe-importacao-de-produtos-avicolas-de-espanha/</link><description>China has prohibited the importation of Spain poultry products due to high pathogenicity aviary outbreaks, suspending exports planned under an agreement in April to open the Chinese market to Spanish producers.
In a statement, the China's General Customs Administration indicated that the decision aims to "prevent the spread of the disease and protect the safety and biosecurity of national cattle." Since August 7, direct and indirect imports of poultry and derivatives, including processed, are prohibited.
The measures also provide for treatment, under customs supervision of all animal or agricultural waste that reach Chinese territory in any means of transport from Spain, as well as sanctions for those who violate the prohibitions.
For now, no deadline for the end of the restrictions, similar to those imposed in May to Brazilian chicken imports, also due to aviary flu has not been set in May.
In April, the Spanish Minister of Agriculture, Fisheries and Food, Luis Plan, and China's deputy minister of customs, Lu Weihong, signed a new export protocol that would allow Spanish poultry producers to access the Asian country to diversify foreign sales.
At the time, the Spanish ministry stressed that China "is a large buyer of bird meat and other products with reduced placement capacity in other markets."</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:50:28</pubDate></item><item><title>NVIDIA | Beijing Dead Slips Use of Chips H20</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/nvidia-pequim-desaconselha-uso-de-chips-h20/</link><description>Chinese authorities have recommended in recent weeks to local companies that avoid using H20 processors from US manufacturer Nvidia, especially in projects linked to government agencies or national security, Bloomberg agency said yesterday.
According to Bloomberg, warnings sent to several companies included, in some cases, questions about the reasons to choose the H20 over national alternatives, the need for this choice and any security problems detected on the devices. The recommendation would also cover US Artificial Intelligence Accelerators (AI) AMD.
The guidance coincides with recent information released by Chinese organisms and state agencies that question the safety and reliability of the H20, a model designed by Nvidia for the Chinese market with specifications lower than the most advanced versions, in accordance with the restrictions imposed by Washington.
At the end of July, the Chinese Internet regulator (CAC) called on Nvidia to clarify alleged safety risks on chips and have evidence that it does not contain “rear doors”, an accusation that the company has rejected.
On Monday, Nvidia again denying that H20 integrates access or remote control functions, in response to comments released on a social network account associated with state television CCTV, which cited experts that it would be technically possible to incorporate screening capabilities, location or remote shutdown in this type of processors.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:48:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Thailand / Cambodia | Disturbed Treley by Mine Explosion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/tailandia-camboja-tregua-perturbada-por-explosao-de-mina/</link><description>A Thai soldier was injured following the explosion of an earthly mine near the border between Thailand and Cambodia, with the admitted Bangkok army to exercise the right to self -defense.
The incident occurred yesterday, disturbing the truce between Thailand and Cambodia who ended the war between the two countries last July. In a statement, General Winthai Suvari, a spokesman for the Thai Army, said that “if the situation demands him” Bangkok's armed forces can exercise the right to “self-defense” according to international laws.
The injured military man was on a patrolling mission near the Ta Muen Thom temple, an area claimed by both countries and located between the Thai province of Surin and the Cambodian province of Oddar Meanchey when the explosion occurred.
Thai soldier, who was accompanied by a group of seven other military personnel, is "out of danger" after suffering "serious injuries on his left ankle."
Two previous incidents, on July 16 and 23, led to the deterioration of diplomatic relations between the two countries and triggered the violent confrontations that lasted for five days at various points along the common border of almost 820 kilometers.
The war made at least 44 dead. The Cambodian government rejected the accusations and stated that “it did not 'plant', nor will it 'plant', new terrestrial mines,” stating that military mills were placed decades during the Cambodian civil war.
Ancient
On July 28, the Bangkok and Phnom Penh governments signed a ceasefire, which remains in force despite accusations of violation of ceasefire. Last Thursday, the two countries agreed to allow observers of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean) to monitor compliance with the agreement on the ground.
Bangkok and Phnom Penh, whose border was cartographed by France in 1907, when Cambodia was a French overseas colony, are involved in a longtime territorial disposal.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:48:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lee Jae-Myung gathers with Trump on August 25</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/13/lee-jae-myung-reune-com-trump-a-25-de-agosto/</link><description>South Korean President Lee Jae-Myung will meet on 25 August with US counterpart Donald Trump in Washington to discuss topics such as trade, defense and strategic cooperation against North Korea.
The summit occurs after a trade agreement in July, in which Washington agreed to reduce from 25 percent to 15 percent the reciprocal tariff applied to South Korea and extend the same rate reduced to South Korean cars, the country's main export to the United States.
Seoul has also pledged to buy $ 100 billion in US energy and invest $ 350 billion in the United States, and Lee and Trump are expected to discuss the structure and management of this investment package.
Conversations should also address the expansion of cooperation in strategic sectors such as semiconductors, batteries and shipbuilding, yesterday the spokesman for the South Korean executive, Kang Yu-Jung.
Lee, a liberal elected in June in an early election to replace the depleted conservative Yoon Suk-Youol, has put the economy at the center of his agenda, seeking to protect the nation, dependent on exports, impacts of Trump's imposed tariffs and their demands, so that allies reduce Washington's dependence and take on greater defense costs.
Risks and Fears
The meeting takes place in a context of fears in Seoul that the Trump administration can change the alliance of decades, requiring higher payments to the presence of the US 28,500 military personnel in the country and pondering reduced it as the US focuses on containing China.
According to Kang, the two leaders will discuss the reinforcement of the defensive posture against the growing threats of North Korea and the development of bilateral partnership in a “comprehensive strategic alliance oriented to the future, adjusted to changes in global security and economy.
Trump argues that Seoul must pay more for the US military presence. Recent comments from administration officials, such as Defense Undersecretary Elbridge Colby, suggest desire to restructure the alliance, which, experts, may affect the dimension and role of US forces on the peninsula.
The US forces commander in Korea, General Xavier Brunson, defended last week the need to “modernize” the alliance to respond to the evolving safety environment, including the North Korean nuclear program, the approach of Pyongyang to Moscow and what he classified as Chinese threats to a free and open “Indo-Pacific”.
Asked about a possible reduction in troops, Brunson stressed the importance of capabilities, rather than numbers, pointing out advanced systems such as fifth generation fighters, and defended strategic flexibility, recalling the recent travel of South Korea's Patriot defense systems to the Middle East.
During the first term, Trump suspended a joint military exercises with Seoul while trying to negotiate with North Korean leader Kim Jong-un. The two leaders gathered three times between 2018 and 2019, but the conversations collapsed due to divergences about the exchange of sanctions for Pyongyang's concrete steps to dismantle the nuclear and missile program.
Since then, Kim has suspended virtually all diplomacy with Washington and Seoul, accelerating the development of weapons and prioritizing the relationship with Russia, to which he provided weapons and troops to support the war in Ukraine.</description><pubDate>2025-08-13 00:45:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Israelite attack killed six journalists on Sunday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/12/gaza-ataque-israelita-matou-seis-jornalistas-no-domingo/</link><description>The Gaza government yesterday raised the number of journalists killed on Sunday night in an Israeli attack after the death of Mohamed Al Khalidi, from the Palestinian media Sahat. The precision attack hit the journalists tent at Al Shifa Hospital in the city of Gaza.
Qatar television correspondents died in the attack al-Sharif and Mohamed Qraiqea, photojournalists Ibrahim Zaher and Moamen Aliwa, photojournalism assistant Mohamed Nofal and Al Khalidi.
The Hamas Government Information Office, the extremist group that has controlled the Gaza range since 2007, condemned in a statement to the “systematic persecution and murder” of Palestinian journalists by Israel. The organization appealed to international federations of journalists and journalistic organizations from around the world to condemn Israel, according to the statement quoted by the Spanish news agency Efe.
He also asked the international community to take Israel to international courts and "exercise serious and effective pressure to end the crime of genocide."
Since the beginning of the war in Gaza in October 2023, they were killed during the Israeli offensive 238 journalists, influencers and other content creators. On July 24, the Journalist Protection Committee (CPJ) expressed concern about the security of Anas Al-Sharif.
The committee set up at the time that the 28 -year -old journalist was "being the target of an Israeli military defamation campaign," which considered "a springboard for his murder."
The Israeli army admitted to killing journalists in a precision bombing and stated that Al-Sharif was linked to Hamas, presenting as proof two documents whose origin did not detail and cannot be verified, according to EFE.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 00:31:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Pacific | Ramos-Horta asks for more financing to combat climate change</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/12/pacifico-ramos-horta-pede-mais-financiamento-para-combater-alteracoes-climaticas/</link><description>The Timorese President, José Ramos-Horta, defended yesterday further financing for Timor-Leste and Pacific countries due to climate change in a region that little contributes to emissions of gas.
"Climate change is not a distant threat-they are a present crisis for Timor-Leste and our Pacific neighbors," the head of state said in a press release after traveling to Melbourne, Australia, to participate in a summit on reducing gas emissions in Australlasia.
"In this summit, I will stress that global carbon-neutral ambitions should include justice, financing and tangible support for those who least contribute to emissions, but who suffer the most with their impacts. Australia's leadership is vital and together we must ensure that no community is behind the fight for a sustainable future," added Ramos-Horta.
According to the Timorese Presidency statement, the participation of the Nobel Peace Prize in the Meeting demonstrates the “Commitment of Timor-Leste to Global Climate Action, Sustainable Development and Regional Cooperation”.
During his stay in Melbourne, which ends on Wednesday, the Timorese President will grant the Order of Timor-Leste various personalities and organizations that contributed to the country's development.
José Ramos-Horta will also visit the “Corner Store Café”, the largest Australian company specializing in toasting Café Timorese, to highlight the “importance of sustainable trade and economic initiatives led by the communities”, can read in the presidential statement.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 00:29:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan | Torrential rains cause flooding and make several injuries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/12/japao-chuvas-torrenciais-provocam-inundacoes-e-fazem-varios-feridos/</link><description>Intense rainfall on Kyushu's main Japanese island yesterday caused flooding and landslides, causing several injuries, missing and disruption disturbances during Bon Bon Holiday Week.
The low pressure system that has been held in the region since last week has caused torrential precipitation in the province of Kagoshima, in the south, and in the northern part of the island.
The Japan Meteorological Agency has issued the maximum alert in the province of Kumamoto yesterday, indicating that the precipitation has exceeded 40 centimeters in the last 24 hours and predicting more rains until this afternoon in Kyushu. As the clouds advance to the east, towards the Tokyo region, the agency foresees up to 20 centimeters of rain in western Japan.
According to the fire and disaster management agency, local authorities have issued exit orders to tens of thousands of people in Kumamoto and in other six provinces. Defense forces troops were sent to Kagoshima to provide drinking water to the affected populations, the government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi said.
Search for missing
In Kumamoto, rescue teams were looking for three people from a family hit by a landslide while moving to an evacuation center. Two were rescued alive, but the third remained missing. Two other people were missing in other areas of the province.
Several people were also given as missing after falling into rivers that overflowed in Kumamoto and the neighboring province of Fukuoka.
In the city of Kamiamakusa, about 20 people arrested in a campsite and other residential areas were awaiting rescue, public television reported NHK. Television images showed flood of muddy water to drag trees and broken branches while residents walked with the water for the height of their knees.
Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba said the government is supporting search and rescue operations and assisting affected areas, appealing to the population to "use the maximum caution" and "prioritize actions to save lives." The heavy rains also affected trips during the Bon holiday.
High -speed trains between Kagoshima and Hakata in northern Kyushu, as well as local rail services, were suspended yesterday. Although circulation was partially resumed in Kyushu, services began to be affected in western Japan as rain advanced to the east.
About 6,000 dwellings were left without electricity in Kumamoto, according to the company Kyushu Electric Power. Last week's torrential rains left a missing and four injured in Kagoshima.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 00:28:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Chikungunya fever | Guangdong records decrease in cases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/12/febre-de-chikungunya-guangdong-regista-queda-de-casos/</link><description>The Chinese province of Guangdong, in the southeast of the country, reported 1,387 new local cases of chikungunya fever between August 3 and 09, a descent against 2,892 counted the week before the outbreak started in July.
Most recent infections focused on the city of Foshan, followed by the provincial capital, Canton, and Zhanjiang. During this period, no serious cases or deaths associated with the disease were recorded, according to the Guangdong Disease Control and Prevention Center, quoted on Sunday by state television CCTV.
Chikungunya fever is a viral disease caused by the homonymous virus and transmitted mainly by Aedes gender mosquitoes, which reproduce in small water accumulations. The most common symptoms include high fever, joint pain and rash.
Quoted by CCTV, the director of the Institute for Prevention and Control of Infectious Diseases of Guangdong, Kang Min, said the increase in cases in Foshan shows signs of containment and that the total weekly maintains fall trend. However, he warned that the disease continues to cover a vast geographical area and that the high international mobility of the province, known as the “factory of the world”, increases the risk of imported cases.
Health authorities have recalled that the elimination of mosquito breeding sites, controlling adult specimens and bites protection are the main measures to lock transmission. The provincial government, which manages a population of about 126 million, had notified by 4 August more than 7,000 cases of the disease.
The time of typhoons and rainfall intensified the activity of mosquitoes in the region, which, according to the authorities, requires maintaining surveillance and control measures.
The World Health Organization (WHO) requested in July preventive measures to avoid epidemics such as 20 years ago, after detecting large -scale outbreaks on Indian islands such as Mayotte, meeting or mauria, and the spread of disease to nearby countries such as Madagascar, Somalia or Kenya.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 00:21:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | ORDER SETTLEMENT OF REAL ESTATE PROMOTER CHINA SOUTH City</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/12/hong-kong-ordenada-liquidacao-da-promotora-imobiliaria-china-south-city/</link><description>A Judge of Hong Kong yesterday ordered the settlement of Promoter China South City, the largest for assets to face this process since the decision against Evergrande in January 2024, the Bloomberg agency yesterday reported.
The magistrate decided in favor of Citicorp creditor, fiduciary of the dollars issued in dollars, after China South City could not gather sufficient support among its creditors, after months of negotiations for a restructuring plan. At the end of the last year, the group's liabilities rose to Hong Kong's $ 60,900 million.
Several Chinese prosecutors, such as Evergrande or Country Garden, have been defaulting since the real estate crisis in China in 2021 and faced settlements in Hong Kong, whose courts have already ruled against at least six cases.
The decision against Evergrande began a long and uncertain process, due to doubts about its recognition in mainland China, where the majority of the assets are, as Hong Kong's judicial system is distinct from the Chinese, under the semi-autonomy status of the territory.
The financial situation of many Chinese real estate agreed after Beijing was announced in August 2020 restrictions on access to banking financing for promoters with high levels of debt, including Evergrande, whose liability was around $ 330 billion.
In the face of the juncture, the Chinese government has announced support packages and state banks opened credit lines of thousands of dollars to several promoters. The completion of plant housing has become a priority due to the implications for social stability, as the real estate sector is one of the main investment channels of Chinese families.</description><pubDate>2025-08-12 00:20:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Anabela Santiago, Academic: “China is a reformist and moderate”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/anabela-santiago-academica-a-china-e-reformista-e-moderada/</link><description>Anabela Santiago has just defended at the University of Aveiro the doctoral thesis that analyzes how China has been positioned in recent decades as an important actor in the “global health governance”. Today, Beijing seeks “alternative mechanisms” of cooperation in the “global south” and tries to build an alternative model to the World Health Organization
 
 
Let's start with the concept of Global Health Governance (GGS). Is this a more contemporary concept or relating to the post-war period and the Foundation of the World Health Organization (WHO)? What have been the main actors of this governance until China's growth?
GGS is a concept whose prominence and relevance have grown significantly in the 21st century, largely driven by economic globalization and worldwide interconnection. Although global health has always transcended national borders, demanding multidisciplinary approaches and international cooperation, only from the 1990s it was made greater awareness of it. Historically, GGS has been predominantly influenced by western powers and neoliberal values. The main actors of this governance, until China's growth, were historically marked by interventions of entities such as WHO and non-governmental, predominantly American and European organizations.
One of the findings of its doctoral thesis is that China has been progressively positioning itself in this leadership. This position started specifically when and why?
Yes, China has been progressively positioned as a relief actor in the evolution of the GG system. Although it is not possible to point out an exact date of start, China has evolved from a relatively isolated country to a main actor in global political, economic and technological arenas. Its growing economic and political influence also represents a change in GGS's historical dynamics, and in the 1960s China tried to play a humanitarian health care role in neighboring countries and Africa. The thesis points out that China's experience can be seen as an example of what is achievable when a state chooses its own way rather than a pre-established model, aligning itself with the 21st century prediction as the "century of Asia."
Did the pandemic years influence this position? How?
Covid-19 pandemic highlighted the need for global health cooperation, as well as the potential consequences of the failure to prioritize global health. The thesis explores the evolution of the Health Silk Route before and after the pandemic, indicating that the pandemic years allowed greater awareness of the need for instruments such as the Health Silk Route as the most effective cooperation platforms among nations. Although not detailed in this specific section, it is implicit that the pandemic intensified China's performance in health diplomacy and health development assistance.
Looking at the internal reforms that China has carried out in the health area, which highlights as the most important?
I approach, in the thesis, the reforms of the China Health System and I point out that the Chinese governance model is a unique combination of state -oriented economic reforms and development by the state, incorporating elements of neoliberalism and authoritarianism into political issues in general, and the health sector is nothing different from the rest. One of China's mentioned contributions, recognized by WHO, is its primary health care model based on the recognized good practice of “barefoot doctors” (barefoot doctors). In addition, the thesis analyzes the main reform policies and their progress and challenges in the period 2009-2018, which comprise the reforms of primary health care, hospital and pharmaceutical reform. The “Healthy China 2030” program is also an important and ambitious reference of China's domestic reforms in health, also encompassing social determinants.
Is Beijing's intention to create an alternative entity to WHO, or simply create an alternative movement that can coexist with WHO, in the context of the relationship with the global south? How could this work?
The thesis suggests that China adopts a "dual approach": while integrating in existing global structures, forging simultaneously alternative paths, particularly through regional alliances such as BRICS and partnerships with Global South. This indicates an intention to create an alternative movement that can coexist and complement the role of WHO, rather than a direct alternative entity. China demonstrates a clear commitment to align the objectives of the “Belt and Road” initiative with the united nations sustainable development objectives, showing their willingness to present these initiatives as complements to the existing cooperation mechanisms in the international liberal order. President Xi Jinping's view of a “future community shared for humanity”, which includes the notion of a “global health community for all”, also points to a new perspective in international cooperation.
Traditional Chinese Masks, Vaccines and Medicine (MTC): What are China's products or instruments to position itself as an increasingly global actor in GGS?
The thesis points out that China is an indispensable provider of global public health, essential for the product supply chain, such as masks and vaccines. The MTC is also mentioned as one of China's great contributions to global health governance, with its chinese herbs treatments, some of which already recognized by WHO in 2017. In addition, Chinese medical assistance and medical teams sent to other regions of the globe are important instruments of Chinese health diplomacy.
In creating an alternative movement or reality to WHO, China may be taking advantage of the lack of full representativeness in the same WHO, or gaps in its operation?
The thesis does not address directly whether China is taking advantage of a lack of full representativeness in WHO or gaps in its operation. However, it emphasizes that the work aims to fill a gap in scientific knowledge in relation to the paradigm of health governance from a non-western and liberal perspective, emphasizing China as an actor of the global south. This suggests that China seeks to strengthen alternative models that can offer more personalized health challenges, different from those defended by Western countries, positioning itself as a moderate reformist actor.
How has the European Union (EU) foreign policy in relation to China affecting or influenced this position of the country in global health governance?
In the thesis, the fourth publication, entitled "Challenges on the European Union-China Cooperation in Higher Education from" People-To-People Dialogue ’Perspective: The Case of Health-Related Joint Projects," explores cooperation in higher education, in particular that includes health-related projects. Therefore, despite the strategic and economic dialogue, the deterioration of UE-china bilateral relations intensified, with the commission to assume a decline of enthusiasm due to “China's countermeasures to EU human rights sanctions, economic coercion and commercial measures against the single market, and the positioning of China in the war in Ukraine”. Although challenges and tensions are recognized, cooperation in higher education, including health projects, is seen as part of a broader picture of strategic partnership between EU and China. However, it is evident that there is no long tradition of health cooperation between EU and China in higher education, and that there are few joint projects compared to the general panorama. It is suggested that both EU and China should make more efforts to align medical study curricula and promote more joint research in areas related to health, infectious diseases, among others.
In the Trump 2.0 era, and without pandemic, what could be China's role in global health governance?
Although the thesis is published this year, it focuses on the preceding period and includes the pandemic, where it does not speculate directly on a future scenario of “Trump 2.0” without pandemic. However, the thesis argues that China is not just a participant, but a moderate reformist force in the formation of global health standards. Regardless of future political scenarios, their growing economic and political influence, strategic health diplomacy, internal reforms and initiatives such as the Health Silk Route will continue to shape their role in global health governance. The view of a “global health community for all” also remains a guiding principle for China's efforts.
Does this power of China in GGS verify more with bilateral or multilateral agreements?
The thesis suggests that China's power in global health governance manifests itself through both bilateral and multilateral agreements, but with a growing emphasis on certain forms of cooperation that strengthen their role in the global south and through alternative mechanisms. Although the thesis does not explicitly quantify the predominance between bilateral and multilateral, the focus on regional alliances (BRICS) and partnerships with the Global South (which often involve bilateral agreements and group cooperation initiatives) and the Health Silk Route indicate a hybrid approach.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 23:46:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Forum | Secretary-General says it has never discussed widening to Hispanic countries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/forum-macau-secretario-geral-diz-que-nunca-se-discutiu-alargamento/</link><description>In an interview with Lusa agency, the secretary general of the Macau Forum, Ji Xianzheng, assured that “never discussed” the widening of action to Hispanic countries, but that the willingness already stated by the government of Sam Hou Fai will have to be the authorities to decide a new direction to the cooperation strategy.
 
The Secretary-General of the Macau Forum stated that the institution “never discussed” the creation of an entity to extend to Hispanic countries to promote economic cooperation similar to those that provide the connection between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
“Within the Macao Forum, we have never discussed this topic,” said the Forum Secretary-General for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries Ji Xianzheng.
The official acknowledged that, "in society, there were some conversations to discuss or address the possibility of promoting more contact and cooperation with Spanish -language countries, but at the Forum level we have never addressed this theme."
The Macao executive announced in mid -April the intention of creating a center to promote economic services between China and the Portuguese and Spanish languages in the neighboring special Economic Zone of Hengqin.
The idea is to provide companies in Hispanic countries services in the “linguistic, legal, fiscal, verification of compliance with norms, formation, arbitration and mediation”, according to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong.
Days earlier, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, had also announced the intention of “promoting exchange and cooperation” through Macao between China and the universe of Spanish -speaking countries.
Although Macau wants to widen focus to Castilian -speaking countries, “the forum will remain the forum for China and Lusophony countries,” said Ji Xianzheng. The secretary general clarified that the institution that directs "can contribute contributions to the greater opening of Macao in international cooperation", as is the intention announced by the new government of MSAR.
Complementary forum
Personally, the secretary-general guaranteed to have "all the pleasure of working with all parties," but stressed that this is a "decision that is up to the central governments to make" and that the forum was never contacted in this regard.
"Yes, I worked in Latin America, Spain, nine years in Madrid and Caracas. But this is not a decision of personal interest, it is up to politicians to make the decision," he said, explaining that the idea will be to promote the relationship between Macao and Brazil and then to other Latin American countries, as well as expanding the relationship with Portugal to Spain.
"There is no limit. The Macao Forum is complementary. It does not restrict any promotion of the cooperation of the other parts," he said.
According to the Macao Government Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai admitted on June 21 that he postponed a trip to Portugal, scheduled for July, and should also pass through Spain and the European Union headquarters in Brussels.
Bad interpretations
In the same interview with Lusa, the secretary general of the Macao Forum imputed to national governments the responsibility for conducting economic development and cooperation policies, stressing that the institution “has no investment projects”.
Ji Xianzheng attributes criticism to the Macao Forum to an wrong interpretation regarding the body's mission. "The forum is a mechanism of cooperation between central governments. Many people think it is to the secretariat that it is up to the execution of policies, but we have a limited number of people," added Ji.
"The secretariat has no investment projects, it is a mechanism for preparing the ministerial conference, connecting with governments, not a promotion agency. It has not been thought of, connects with the promotion agencies. We are four people sent by China and one delegate for each country," he said.
At the last ministerial conference, in April 2024, then Portuguese Economy Minister Pedro Reis argued that the Portuguese Language China-Parais Cooperation and Development Fund should bet more on small and medium enterprises (SMEs).
The Cooperation Fund was created in 2013 by the China Development Bank and the Macao Industrial and Commercial Development Fund, with a thousand million dollars, of which about 60 percent have already been invested, according to the secretary general.
Action plans
Ji Xianzheng has admitted that SMEs are "a difficult theme for any government" and that "international cooperation for the promotion of development and cooperation of small and medium enterprises is even more difficult. It is a topic that is being debated daily worldwide." But admitted, "here, little."
"But it is stipulated in the action plan [2024-2026]. It is up to central governments and commerce chambers, promotion agents, to work together to do this. The secretariat assumes responsibility as authorized by the central governments, specifically, in the activities program," he said.
Politicians from various countries, including Portugal, Angola and Mozambique, have appealed to a change in the rules of the fund's candidacy. Current rules require, for example, that candidate projects have a minimum investment of five million dollars, and the fund only covers 20 percent of total investment, referring the rest to governments or companies.
Ji Xianzheng said the new direction of the fund "is committed to promoting a broader investment, with better coverage for all forum countries, [relatively] to projects that have a strategic or significant impact on the socioeconomic development of participating countries."
According to the secretary general, "the terms of application [of the rules of access to the background] will be more flexible and the forms of application will also be more diverse." “Instead of being just direct investment, they are also studying ways to apply the fund, in cooperation with other funds or with other financial institutions,” he gave as an example.
"This fund has an operation according to market rules. It is not a humanitarian aid fund. Therefore, it has to guarantee the minimum return of benefit. But, on that, they are very open to study, in this case, the conditions of each project," added Ji Xianzheng, but to give examples of "flexibilization of the rules."
Regarding the approximation of the China universe and countries of the Iberian Peninsula, already cemented in official speeches, economist Maria Fernanda Ilhéu, president of the Seda's New Route Association, told HM, earlier this month, that this intention is “very objective and pragmatic and can be summarized to the Macao economy diversification project, for which companies and investors are not only in Macao, but also from Macao, but also from Macao, but also from countries, but countries Portuguese Language ”.
"But the fact is that companies and institutions from Portuguese-speaking countries are not being effective in responding to this need for Macao. Therefore, widening companies and Spanish-speaking institutions this invitation to cooperation seems logical to me," the economist said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Isabel Rio Novo, author of the biography of Luís de Camões: “Time in Macau was of tranquility”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/26/isabel-rio-novo-autora-da-biografia-de-luis-de-camoes-tempo-em-macau-foi-de-tranquilidade/</link><description>It will be launched tomorrow, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, the biography of Luís de Camões, by Isabel Rio Novo. In an interview with HM, the author unravels some secrets about the poet's life in Macau, a period of relative calm in the middle of a almost always turbulent life
 
Why did you decide to get in the writing of another biography of Camões?
It is true that Luis Vaz de Camões has been biographed many times over 500 years. However, 50 years ago there was no biography about him. From my point of view and the editor, Camões deserved a more current biography that revised all kinds of prejudices, seeking known sources, the uncovered information research and where the rereading of all previous works were rereading. This biography is not only a summary, but also the reinterpretation of what has been known, but which had rarely been related. The book also brings some new data with some documentation that was discovered.
How was your relationship with the writing of Camões born?
I fell in love and went to those young readers who was not tormented with Camões. On the contrary, I liked it soon and let myself be seduced by Camões Lyric. I am from the areas of comparative literature and history, and in this sense I always understood the dimension and importance of the work of Camões.
And what are they?
It is a work and an author of its time and its time, which was extraordinary, with the Renaissance, Humanism and the travels of navigation. But at the same time, it is a work that is the product of an outstanding literary genius, one that we can tell a handful in the history of universal literature.
What camões we find in this biography?
I tried to go to the bottom, remove layers of the meaning that these 500 years were adding to Camões, in the sense that each season read its Camões and produced its interpretation. I wanted to discover the substrate, the man of flesh and bone he lived and wrote 500 years ago.
He was a man suffered, with many financial difficulties.
He was a man with a complex and difficult relationship with reality, not only of his time, but also with reality [itself]. The theme of the time, the disconcerting of the world, how society seems to work instead of what should work, being a literary topic of the Renaissance, it was something Camões felt personal and genuinely.
How?
He lived a series of disagreements, of extreme experiences. Suffice it to say that you have been stuck several times and for various reasons. He made great trips at a time when these were absolutely risky, long, and complicated enterprises. Camões was involved in military expeditions, and almost all his life was soldered. But this set of experiences allowed him to be almost everything that someone could be at the time he lived.
He was one of the most traveled authors of the time, having been in Brazil, Goa…
Yes. Even the connection to Macau, which is contested by some scholars, but not by me… I am persuaded, given the existing documentation and indirect testimonies, which Camões passed through China with the position of Dead and Missing Provider. When this happened, albeit very incipiently, the Portuguese establishment in China, which was already Macao. It is not known whether Camões held this position assigned to him by Viceroy D. Francisco Coutinho, if he was exactly assigned to be a provider during the trip, or a provider at Macao's establishment. But what he knew from China was surely this little warehouse that Portugal had achieved, at a lot of cost, with great difficulty and after many attempts to obtain in China.
What did a deceased provider?
Whenever a Portuguese died in the East, a soldier or merchant, it was necessary to ensure the rights of the heirs, the families who were normally in Portugal. The provider had to identify the deceased, his naturalness, origin and make the heirs known. He also had to keep the deceased's assets before they were stolen, auction them, keep the coins that would result in, and then take it all to Lisbon. It was a process that, if it went well, took many months, because it was necessary to send this money to the authorities of Goa who later sent him in the career from India to Lisbon.
Can we talk about a period of stability in Camões's life in Macau?
Yes. Until this appointment as a deceased provider, everything Camões knew from the East had been as a soldier. As soon as Goa [1553] arrives weeks later in a first military expedition. We know why: Not because I had some war appeal, but because only participating in expeditions earned your welding. Although everyone said that the soldiers lived very poorly, the welding was what Camões had to survive. The time lived in Macao, when he was free from soldier obligations, was a time of tranquility regarding subsistence, which was assured. He had some time and calm to continue the work with "the Lusíadas." More than that, as much as the sources allow to deduce, Camões met in Macau a phase of balance in terms of personal and loving life, as, on the return trip, he brought with him, according to the testimony of Diogo do Couto, a Chinese girl.
Dinamene.
This was the term used by the chronicler. We don't know if it would be a Chinese or Asian girl. This girl with whom Camões lived maritally was someone who liked it very much, according to the testimony of Diogo do Couto. But Dinamene would certainly not be her name, as it was a mythological name that, by the way, Camões used in her lyric, even before she boarded the East. Chinese girls with whom soldiers and merchants in Macao lived amanced were baptized and received a Christian name. Therefore, Dinamene would even have a Christian and Portuguese name. But as we do not know her name, and if we are aware that we use a kind of metaphor, we can call it Dinamene.
She dies later on a trip and makes Camões very shaken.
On Macao's return trip to Goa, probably at the end of his mandate as a provider, Camões suffers the celebrated wreck, in which he loses the personal assets he had ease, including the assets of the deceased that he was guardian, and this will bring him complications. It also suffers the loss of dynamine. The wreck went with some in the seas of China, probably by the mouth of the Mekong River.
Considers unlikely to have lost part of "the Lusíadas."
The first biographers say Camões was saved from this wreck with a board. It is not unreasonable that he managed to save the manuscript of the Lusíadas on this board. But it is also no excluding that Camões knew his poem by heart. The memory of people in the sixteenth century was different. They were very used to keeping things from memory. And we know, because the proof is obtained in the work of Camões, that it had an extraordinary memory. I have a way to prove it, of course, that Camões is one of the rare authors who knew his poem by heart.
Do you think Camões had a lower life to his true talent?
Undoubtedly. According to a too extensive set of concordant testimonies, he dies poor, even in miserable conditions, and according to an eyewitness, without having a blanket with which he covered himself. On the other hand, Camões was known to follow the publication of the Lusíadas, who were commented and read [in the poet's life time]. We have the testimony of Faria de Sousa, one of the first biographers of Camões, which says that when he passed the streets, people stop and pointed. Camões also had a figure that stood out, with a leaked eye and using a pale. By then, I would be quite sick, using crutches. But there is a set of poets, which is very unreliable that they did not know Camões, who never refer to them. There are, on the other hand, other humanists, such as Pedro Magalhães Gândavo, who from the outset praises him as the prince of Portuguese poets.
But the king gives him a tendency for deeds provided and the publication of "The Lusíadas."
This famous tendency, which should not be a big deal, because all ancient biographers say it was derisive, is attributed to him as a kind of military reform, because of the 17 years of service in the East, and not as a reward for the publication of "The Lusíadas." D. Sebastião's mercy letter, which attributes him the title of nobleman knight, had no repercussion in practice, but gave him 15 thousand reais. [The publication of “the Lusíadas”] was an additional argument [for the letter] and not the main argument. This leads us to believe that D. Sebastião will not even have read or heard “the Lusíadas”, will have received indirect information, favorable about the poem.
How did the process of editing “Os Lusíadas” occurred?
It was an event, because both the press and the books that were published a year were a very small amount. In the year in which “the Lusíadas” are published were the only work of non -religious caress [to be edited]. To fund the edition, it is more than likely that Camões had the support of a patron, probably D. Manuel de Portugal, from the Condes do Vimioso family. Getting the work was a press was a mere and complicated process, as it had to go through the prior examination of the civil authorities, the royal authority and the censorship of the Inquisition. The resident of the Holy Office does not only let the book pass, but to make an amount of almost unprecedented compliments in the license that authorizes the publication of the work. If we go to the opinions emitted by the same rear, there is no other work on which he is as compliments as it was with the epic of Camões.
In Indonesia, he befriended a slave on the island of Java.
Camões was, at least once, on the island of Ternate, Indonesia, in the archipelago of molucas, at a time when there were conflicts motivated by an extremely cruel Portuguese captain towards the king or sultan of Ternate, which originated a kind of war between the Portuguese and the places. Camões has a song that describes the island of Ternate. We do not know if it was at this time, or in another passage to the Far East, that Camões turned on to a Jaú, or Javanese, but could not be exactly from the Far East, but a freed slave who had been linked by friendship to Camões. And this is because in one of the first biographies of Camões it reads that Jaú, with the Christian name António, asked for alms at night. This freedom of movements of a slave indicates that he would probably be a freed slave. He asked for alms to Camões, for himself and the mother of Camões, with whom Camões will have lived in recent years of life.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 23:30:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the right place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is it for them to be denied this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
What do you talk about is economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | FIA has already defined what the F4 World Cup will be like</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/25/gp-fia-ja-definiu-como-sera-a-taca-do-mundo-de-f4/</link><description>The Macao Grand Prix hosts the first edition of the FIA Formula 4 World Cup, between November 13 and 16 this year. The International Automobile Federation has published the Sports Regulation, which reveals some details about what will be the latest cup in the world integrated into the 72nd Macau Grand Program
 
Registration for the Formula 4 Macao Race - Formula 4 World Cup of the International Automobile Federation (FIA) is open until July 30, and FIA is the selection of the pilots who will participate. FIA responsible will have been pre-selected by the best Formula 4 national championship riders, also encouraging all the pilots interested in directly contacting the FIA and providing details of their sports history to be considered.
The final list of twenty pilots will be confirmed through an official invitation letter, taking into account the current classification of the pilots in the respective championships. The final selection should only be made public in mid -October, as is tradition in the guide circuit test.
At a time when behind the scenes, it is spoken of the possibility of increasing the minimum age of formula 4 to 16 years, the sports regulation stipulates that all pilots must be at least 15 years old, and the birthday is binding. An inscribed pilot may not have participated in more than two races of a championship with any type of monolugar that has been conceived and/or built to achieve a power-to-weight ratio of less than 3.0 kg/hp, which prevents participation in this riders running regional formula seasons or Formula 3.
The sports regulation does not specify technical details, but in previous communications, the FIA had already confirmed that Mintimes - organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship - will be the “unique operator” of the race, together with FFSA (Fédération Française Du Sport Automobile (FFSA), responsible for the world's cup technical support. In practice, all competitors will use Mygale M21-F4 singlesules, recently re-baptized as Ligier JS F422.
These formulas, equipped with 1.3 -liter Turbo Renault engines, will be rented to teams from the interior of China and operated by a single technical team - the same that organizes the French F4 Championship. Pirelli will be the exclusive tire supplier, as is the case with the Macao Grand Prix of Regional Formula and the FIA GT World Cup.
Although the official time of the event has not yet been released, it is known that the World Cup will feature a qualification race played over 8 laps, or at most 60 minutes, most likely on Saturday. The main race will be held on Sunday, with 10 laps or, equally, a maximum of 60 minutes. Prior to that, a 40 -minute free training session will take place, followed by a qualification session with the same duration.
PATACA AND POINTS
About 350,000 patacas in monetary awards will be distributed to the competitors present in this first cup of the world, with the winner of the main race to raise eight thousand US dollars. As a curiosity, all participants will receive three hundred dollars of participation-the same value attributed to the pole-position of Saturday's qualification race and the rider who reaches the highest tip speed during the event.
More important than the monetary awards, the FIA Formula 4 World Cup winner on the streets of Macau will win two points for the super license - points that may be decisive to access the restricted Formula 1 world. The winner will also be forced to attend the FIA awards ceremony, which will take place on December 12 in Tashkentão, USBekistan.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 05:01:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Lamborghini | Charles Leong returns to the Academy of Young Pilots</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/20/lamborghini-charles-leong-regressa-a-academia-de-jovens-pilotos/</link><description>The Lamborghini Squadra Corso, the Automobili Lamborghini competition division, will give Macau pilot a new opportunity for Macao Charles Leong Hon Chio, who was again selected to join the Italian -brand prestigious youth academy, the “Young Driver Program”
 
Charles Leong, who participates for the second year in a row in the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia, by SJM team Theodore Racing, currently leads the Pro category, with four wins in six races already played. This weekend, the territory pilot travels to South Korea to compete in the fourth race of the Sant'Agata Bolognese builder's Asian competition season, a small locality in the Emilia-Romanha region in northern Italy, between Modena and Bologna.
In a statement, the transalpina brand made known that, in all, selodes were pre-selected pilots of the various Super Trofeo championships and five of the various international GT3 championships, including Portuguese Rodrigo Testa, for the annual Lamborghini Squadra Corso program, which focuses on both track and outside performance. The twenty -one pilots will be accompanied and evaluated throughout the season, with specific analysis of their progression, consistency, experience, professionalism and ability to provide technical feedback. In addition, five additional pilots are part of Lamborghini's young professional pilots, receiving direct support from the factory in Sant'Agata Bolognese and Scola Federale ACI Sport, an entity managed by the Italian Federation.
The big news for the 2025 edition of the Young Driver Program is the selection process: it failed to settle only in age criteria, focusing on the most impressive pilots of the first two rounds of the year, based on a classification coefficient covering the three continental championships. The pilots were evaluated by Scoola Federale ACI-Sport chief instructor Niki Cadei, in collaboration with YDP consultants and official Lamborghini drivers Andrea Caldarelli (North America), who has already competed at the Macao Grand Prix, and Marco Mapelli (Europe and Asia), taking into account several performance indicators.
The results of qualification training and racing are thoroughly analyzed, such as track conduct, the pilot's post-end reports and the technical feedback provided to engineers and Squadra corse's technical team. The average score determines the final list of pilots selected for the decisive phase. A group of these young pilots will participate in a dedicated training camp at Lamborghini headquarters in Sant'Agata Bolognese, as well as at the final selection session in Misano. The best of the session will then receive support from Lamborghini Squadra Corso for the 2026 season.
Future is played in Italy
Among Super Trofeo Junior pilots, ten compete in the European series, while the rest come from the American and Asian championships. In addition to Macao's 24 -year -old pilot in Asian representation, Lamborghini also chose Singapore's Ethan Brown and Ireland's Alex Denning, which this year shares the steering wheel with Charles Leong to join this program.
Charles Leong will be evaluated throughout the season, and the final selection - whether or not to integrate Lamborghini's youth professional riders program - will be made in November at the Italian circuit of Misano, after the traditional closing of the Season of the various Super Trofeo, during the Lamborghini world endings. It is recalled that the winner of the Macao Formula 4 Grand Prix in 2020 and 2021 was part of this program last year, but was not selected. At the time, the final assessment took place at the Jerez circuit in Spain - an unknown layout, unlike his opponents.</description><pubDate>2025-07-20 15:23:35</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FR World Cup will have a new car in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/gp-taca-do-mundo-de-fr-tera-novo-carro-em-2026/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) has recently revealed some details about the future of the Regional Formula (FR), the discipline that currently gives body to the Macao Grand Prix and which, from 2026, will finally have a new monolugar - faster and more safe
 
Initially baptized by FIA as F3 Regional, the now designated regional formula (FR) is above the Formula 4 Formula 4 National Competitions and FIA Championship, which, in turn, supports the FIA Formula 2 Championship and Formula 1. Last year, the FIA decided that this category was the one that best filed the Guide Circuit, thus ending four decades of Formula 3 Macao Award.
Last week, the regulator of world motorsport and the Italian national sports association has jointly presented the future monoligue that will compete in the European regional FIA (FREC in English) regional formula championship and will succeed the current freka. The fact that the acronym has lost the letter “A” is due to the exit of the Alpine brand as a partner and engine supplier to the championship. FRECA premiered in 2019, succeeding the Formula Renault Eurocup. In recent seasons, more than 160 pilots, representing 44 nationalities and 22 teams, participated in the championship. This category has gained importance in the FIA monologene pyramid, having as old pilots former champion Andrea Kimi Antonelli, Isack Hadjar, Gabriel Bortoleto and Franco Colapinto-all of them now militate in Formula 1.
The competition will have the FIA support seal and should be the largest supplier of teams and pilots for the FR World Cup of the Macao Grand Prix from next year. FIA involvement in the competition is intended to generate more revenues for it, something that may have reflexes on the price scale. The FR championships in the Americas and Japan, as well as the FIA -certified trophies in the Middle East and Oceania will continue, and progressively will introduce the new car produced in Italy.
FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulayem believes this project "will create a stronger and more support for young pilots. With the full support of the FIA regions and a clear progression vision, we are taking an important step to ensure the future of junior monoliga pyramid." Former Ralis pilot and today maximum leader of automobile sports, who was recently in the territory for the FIA general assembly, said that “accessibility, international credibility and cost efficiency are at the center of this initiative.”
New car promises more
The new Tatuus T-326, the second-generation FR monolugar, is equipped with a 3-cylinder and 1.6 liter Toyota engine, which debits 270 horsepower and 360 Nm of torque, specially adapted and prepared by ATM-Autotechnic Motori. The T-326 represents a natural evolution of the T-318 model, the Tatuus monolugar that defined most FR championships worldwide and says goodbye to the big stages next November, during the weekend of the Macao Grand Prix. The second edition of FR's FR World Cup will continue to use the Tatuus T-318 Monolugar, motorized by a 1.75-liter Turbo Alpha Romeo block, also prepared by ATM-Autotechnic Motori, but the Italian brand has failed to manufacture.
The future car, which will use a new special tire built by Pirelli, will have a fully redesigned aerodynamic profile, shaped by the new FIA technical regulations for the category and inspired by the latest trends in the top categories of single -molding. The result is a general increase in performance, better aerodynamic efficiency and reduction of turbulence effect, which will facilitate overtaking.
Main improvements include weight reduction, optimized direction rack and magazine suspension, offering greater lightness and ease of driving. Security remains a key pillar in all Italian tatus projects, and this car is no exception. Chassis further increased its impact resistance. Crucial elements such as front and rear impact absorption structures, anti-intrusion panels and roll bar have been updated to meet the latest safety standards. In addition to safety, the cockpit is designed to maximize pilot's comfort and ergonomics, welcoming both men and women in a wider range of heights, ensuring the best conditions to compete on track.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:59:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Nürburgring Nordschleife is a new favorite stage of Chinese brands</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/01/nurburgring-nordschleife-e-novo-palco-predilecto-das-marcas-chinesas/</link><description>In the middle of the Eifel forest - in German, Eifelwald - Two cars with Chinese enrollment are parked in front of a hotel unit. The scenario appears to be intriguing at first glance, but it is not.
Nürburgring Nordschleife, in Rhineland-Palatinado, already close to the Belgium and Luxembourg border, has become the favorite stage of new Chinese automobile builders to show the world that they can also measure forces with their European, American and Asian rivals with regard to high performance vehicles.
Chinese automotive industry bet is strongly concentrated in NEVs - “New Energy Vehicles” - as part of the strategy for reducing pollution, reducing dependence on fossil fuels and boosting innovation in the automotive industry. China represented almost two thirds of global electric vehicle sales in 2024, and their builders, all relatively new, discuss Taco the Taco with the large traditional builders a piece of this appetizing market.
It is undisputed that the growth of sales of this type of vehicles in the world has not been accompanied at the same speed by the evolution of technology applicable to automobile sport, especially with regard to electric vehicles (EVs).
The World Formula World Championship and is the only truly global competition for electric vehicles, after the fiasco and the premature death of the FIA - FIA etcouring world cup. With no alternatives to affirm their everyday products on the tracks, Chinese brands headed in weight to Nürburgring Nordschleife, known to be one of the favorite places of European car manufacturers to test high performance cars.
The “green hell”, a name given by the legendary pilot Jackie Stewart due to its difficulty and the density of the surrounding forest, is a circuit with over 20 kilometers and 170 curves, combining fast lines, technical sections and sharp unenforcement. Many return records are measured here for sports and super -sports car cars, making Nordschleife an unavoidable reference to car performance.
Chapters for History
In 2017, Nio became known to the western world when it established a record with its EP9 electric supercar. The vehicle completed a circuit of 20.8 km in 6 minutes and 45.90 seconds, becoming the fastest production car at the time to travel the famous Germanic layout.
This feat has evidenced the ability of Nio and Chinese industry to compete with brands established in the high performance cars segment. Two years later, Lynk &amp; Co, the first Chinese brand to win a race in the guide circuit, with model 03 Cyan Concept, a high performance version of the Sedan 03, reached a time back in 7 minutes and 20,143 seconds, setting a new record for four -door cars.
Brands such as Zeekr, MG and Lotus passed the old stage of the Formula 1 German Grand Prix, until, in 2024, Xiaomi arrived with a crash. With a production version of the SU7 Ultra, it registered a time of 7 minutes and 4.957 seconds, surpassing rivals such as Porsche Taycan Turbo GT and Rimac Snowra. To keep up with the sales success of your car, the electronic technology brand was even further: Last month, the Su7 Ultra Prototype, built in partnership with Prodrive, reached an impressive 6-minute and 22.091 seconds, becoming the third fastest car of all time on the circuit, behind only the Porsche 919 Hybrid and Volkswagen ID.R.R.
These results from Xiaomi had a significant impact, both in the western and home press, as well as proof of the international affirmation of an industry that wants to be an undisputed leader with regard to Nev vehicles. On the other hand, Xiaomi took the opportunity to “surf the wave” and launched in the market a special limited edition of Su7 -all -how.
More will come
Nürburgring Nordschleife is part of the Chinese auto industry vocabulary and the trend is for an even stronger presence of Chinese brands in the coming years on the German track.
"I believe it was the decision of Xiaomi that brought greater attention to the definition of records back in Nürburgring," explained Chinese journalist Bruno Qi to HM. “With a huge media influence in China and a high profile CEO like Jun Law, Xiaomi attracted a significant focus on this scenario. After Nio's success, this was another strong performance of a Nürburgring high -performance electric vehicle.”
Xiaomi, which already names a bend of the German circuit, may want to improve its time back, while other Chinese brands seek to follow the trend - even to show off on a respected and good memories.
"Brands like Yangwang (BYD's luxury brand) have also sent their models for time attempts around," says Chinese publication journalist Bec Motorsport. “I think Chinese auto builders have now found a relevant opportunity to demonstrate the capabilities of their high performance electrical platforms, and this strategy is already helping to boost sales.” Also, at the end of the day, what weighs is what is sold.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 01:14:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Bay Race learned more pilots for the GP</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/11/corrida-da-grande-baia-apurou-mais-pilotos-para-o-gp/</link><description>The GT Cup Races - Great Bay Race, integrated at the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix, ended with a double journey at the Pingtan Speed Festival last weekend of June. Of the twenty -eight vacancies assigned by the first two GT Cup races, only one Macao pilot got a direct entrance at the great sports event of November.
Following the success of the two races played under the China Formula 1 Grand Prix, both 30 -minute races of the GT4 Chinese Championship had a total of 21 participants at the event held at the International Circuit of Lago Ruyi in Pingtan. This picturesque track, located in Fujian province, replaced the Zhuhai International Circuit, initially included in the provisional calendar released in January, but did not confirm the holding of his event.
In Pingtan's semiurban layout, Chinese pilot Han Lichao won both races behind his Toyota GR Supra GT4 EVO2. In two very lively races, Kevin Leong Ian Veng (BMW M4 GT4) was the only Macau pilot scoring, having reached a sixth and eighth place, respectively.
Although only one Pilot of the Misrem has guaranteed the direct determination, it is possible that more riders in the territory will align on the GT - Great Bay Race, integrated in the Macao Grand Prix. This is because only 21 pilots scored in these four races, which means that even if all these pilots are signed up for the guide circuit race, seven vacancies will still be filled.
In addition to Kevin Leong, seven other pilots from Macau - Miguel Law, Wong Cheng Tou, Fok Wai Ming, Lao Kim Hou, IP Un Hous, Wong Wai Hong and Law Kit Meng - participated in at least one of the two qualification events and may be repaired for local test if the sports committee's sports committee of the Macau Grand Prix so.
Among the riders are some known names of the region's motorsport, such as Darryl O'Young, double winner of the Macau GT Cup; Chen Weian, 12 -hour separate winner; Liu Kaishun, Chinese F4 runner-up; Daniel Lu, former Champion of the Porsche Carrera Asia Cup; or Luo Kailuo, winner of the GT Cup - Great Bay Race at Macao's 70th Grand Prix.
It's not over yet
This debut season, Sro GT Cup still has two more pointed events, the last, naturally, played in the iconic Guide Circuit. The competition, which has the support of the Macao General Automobile Association - China (AAMC), has reached its intermediate point, and the struggle for the title is in the red. Prior to the mandatory visit to Macau, from 17 to 19 October, the GT4 category cars will compete at the first event held on the streets of Yizhuang, in Beijing.
Beijing's Citadino Circuit is one of the most anticipated auto events in the Popular Republic of China and represents an excellent opportunity for Macao GT4 riders - and not only to prepare for the big challenge that are the curves and counterclaces of the territory layout.</description><pubDate>2025-07-11 00:45:06</pubDate></item><item><title>TCR China | André Couto participated in the Zhejiang race</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/01/tcr-china-andre-couto-participou-na-prova-de-zhejiang/</link><description>Over the weekend, André Couto had an unexpected return to the TCR China Championship, in what was his first race of this season. The rider of the sgas showed that "who knows, never forgets", despite having had a troubled passage through the Zhejiang International Circuit
The Portuguese pilot residing in Macao, who has not competed since November last year-when he played the World Lamborghini Super Trofeo World Finals, having won the title in the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia Pro-AM category-received a last-minute invitation from MacPro Racing Team to conduct one of the Honda Civic Fl5 TCR Team in the third race of the Chinese Championship. TCR.
Without any previous workout, André Couto came back to sit in a car he already knew, also with a technical structure that was familiar to him. By 2023, the territory pilot had already played some TCR China events with this set, then at the service of the official team Dongfeng Honda Racing Team, showing a progress right from the beginning.
"Free training did not go wrong, but in qualification a less attentive pilot hit me on my first departure lap to the track. He hit me from behind and did not realize why. Damaged me the rear, dislocated the convergence and the car was crooked. Hm. "Still, I qualified myself in fourth in Q1, five tenths of the first, which, with the car in the conditions it was, was not bad. The car had potential."
In Q2, due to the damage, the Japanese car “became much harder to guide” and Couto ended in tenth. However, this ended up having a positive effect: “With the reversal of the starting grid, the tenth place of Q2 allowed me to start first to the second race.”
The first race, played on Saturday on the shaoxing track, did not go as well as the pilot wanted, not being able to follow the official links, nor the best Honda and Hyundai. "I ended up eighth. The car was not as good as expected and we found that there was a damaged damper, still from the crash in the qualification, which was exchanged for the Sunday race."
Inglorius Sunday
In the 20 Sunday round race, André Couto had everything to shine as he departed from pole-position and Honda finally seemed in a position to fight for the first places. "On the way back, the car was good. I didn't feel strange anymore and I was optimistic."
The idea was to get well to distance themselves from the fastest competitors in the first laps and then manage the race with new tires. However, it all faded quickly when it was wrapped by Wu Yi Fan right in the brake for the first curve.
“That was my mission, but I couldn't,” acknowledged the winner of the 2000 Macao Grand Prix. “He hit me on the first curve and the car was damaged. Sports commissioners, but that does not change the fact that I have given up. ”
With Honda's damaged direction, André Couto had no choice but to leave. "I was a bit disappointed because I hope to get a good result for MacPro Racing Team that had given me a good car.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:26:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>