<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Deepseek | Launched recruitment campaign with high salaries to respond to search</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/deepseek-lancada-campanha-de-recrutamento-com-altos-salarios-para-responder-a-procura/</link><description>The Chinese Artificial Intelligence Platform (IA) Deepseek announced yesterday a recruitment campaign with offers exceeding $ 150,000 a year after achieving worldwide success at its launch.
The company has published at least 37 employment offers for various advanced technology positions, the best paid of which is the deep learning researcher, with an annual salary of about 1.12 million yuan (148,000 euros), according to the Business Journal Securities Times.
Deepseek currently has 150 employees, against about 1,700 from OpenAi, the main American competitor and the most used AI model to date.
According to the newspaper, the company intends to recruit the best talents finished leaving the Chinese universities, for which also launched an offer of scholarships in the main domains of AI, with daily financial compensation far superior to the usual internship and lunch And even dinner are subsidized.
With staff reinforcement, the technology company seeks to respond to the exponential growth of users since launch and improve and stabilize the service, which has suffered interruptions and technical failures allegedly due to the influx of consultation, even more intense due to the Lunar New Year, period in which much of the Chinese population was on vacation.
DeepSeek caused a major excitement in the global AI industry after the launch a few weeks ago from its V3 model, which will have only taken two months to develop and cost less than six million dollars.
On January 20, he released the latest version, called R1. Launched in 2023 by the Chinese investment fund High-Flyer Quant, DeepSeek is open source and offers 95 percent services cheaper than OpenAi's O1 model.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:43:50</pubDate></item><item><title>CPCPS | Patronato Refusa Rise from Minimum Wage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/cpcps-patronato-recusa-subida-do-salario-minimo/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs and representatives of employers in the Permanent Social Concertation Council remove the hypothesis of increasing the minimum wage or reviewing the limits of indemnities for occupational accidents and occupational diseases this year.
The position was taken after this year's first meeting of the Permanent Council for Social Concertation, which took place on Tuesday, while the representatives of the work part promised to support government decisions.
Legally, the amount of salary and the limits of compensation for occupational accidents and occupational diseases should be reviewed in annual or biannual periods. However, Wong Chi Hong, director of DSAL, explained that the term review means that an assessment is made, which may conclude that the best option is not to move the values ​​in force.
“We will review in our work, because there has to be a review every two years. But doing a review does not mean that there has to be an increase, what we do is a data collection, to make a report and then be able to send to the Permanent Social Concertation Council, ”said Wong Chi Hong, quoted by the Macau channel.

Frozen year
In turn, Vong Kok Seng, leader of the Macao Commercial Association, believes that the obligation to revise the minimum salary and limits must be changed. “The economic and social situation is basically identical. Therefore, I ask if it is necessary to review these amounts annually… We question if there is a review or change of legislation, if the annual revision period should not be relaxed, ”said Vong.
In turn, Fong Ka Fai, representative of the workplace, indicated that during the meeting were requested increases of maternity leave, paternity and revision of the boundaries. However, it admits that there was no response, and that ultimately will support the government's choice. "There were not many answers, but of course, as workers we will support the government and make our efforts to promote the economy of Macau, because we had the pandemic, and after the pandemic it takes an effort from everyone," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:50:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | Elderly stable after the fan is connected</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/gripe-idosa-estavel-apos-estar-ligada-a-ventilador/</link><description>A 69-year-old woman recovered from a complicated clinical influenza A, who forced respiratory aid and in the second no longer needed a fan, being currently considered stable, health services indicated yesterday.
The patient went to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center on January 14 where he was diagnosed with bacterial pneumonia and submitted to hospitalization.
About two weeks later, symptoms got worse with fever and shortness of breath. On February 1, it would eventually be diagnosed with flu and pneumonia, which forced the medical team to resort to the mechanical fan. Authorities added that the patient was not vaccinated against seasonal flu this year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:16:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Museum in honor of Cristiano Ronaldo opens in July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/hong-kong-museu-em-homenagem-a-cristiano-ronaldo-abre-em-julho/</link><description>Asia's first Cristiano Ronaldo Life (CR7) museum will be inaugurated in July 2025 at the K11 Museea mall in Tsim Sha Tsui, Hong Kong, according to organizers on Tuesday.
With state -of -the -art interactive exhibitions, rare memorabilia and reports of the various milestones in the career of the footballer, the museum offers visitors an engaging tribute around the football legend, the people's diary indicates.
Tickets were set for sale yesterday, coinciding with Ronaldo's birthday, providing fans around the world the opportunity to be part of the historic inauguration. The organization estimates that the space is expected to attract more than 12 million visitors to Hong Kong over a year.
The opening day of CR7 Life Museum will be attended by several international celebrities, in honor of Cristiano Ronaldo's career. Between March and April, two stores with autographed products in Tsim Sha Tsui and Hong Kong Island will be opened.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:46:48</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT | Macao Retalia and suspends orders from the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/ctt-macau-retalia-e-suspende-encomendas-dos-eua/</link><description>The CTT of Macao temporarily suspended order services between the territory and the United States of America (USA). According to a statement issued yesterday by CTT, postcards such as letters, document sending and air mail were not included. The suspension applies to orders and packages delivery services by maritime and express mail.
The president of the Macao International Logistics and Transport Association, Kuok Fai Law, believes that the local logistics sector will avoid the negative effects of the blockade yesterday by the United States Postal Service (USPS).
Speaking to Radio Macau's Chinese channel, the association's leader acknowledged that some companies with American capital, such as game -related companies, need to regularly send equipment to be maintained in the United States. However, law indicated that the volume of these orders is “little”.
Kuok Fai Law also pointed out that the sector began to ponder other means to send these materials to the US, or, as an alternative, who may also choose to maintain equipment in factories in Singapore or Australia.
On the impacts on the maintenance of aircraft in Macau, Kuok Fai Law devalued the subject, because most aircraft in Macau are from the Airbus brand, indicating that for these devices there are several parts of parts not only in the interior, but also in Southeast Asia .
Morning shocks
News about the “temporary” blockade by USPS to orders from interior and Hong Kong were released yesterday morning, and appear in the latest trade war between the US and China. The duration of the block was not disclosed, but by decision of US President Donald Trump, products imported from China are subject to a new rate of 10 percent.
In a statement, USPS clarified that the measure will not affect “the flow of cards and normal mail”, but only low -value products that previously benefited from exemption from fees.
The USPS measurement can block or delay orders made through Chinese shein, and stared out of low prices, but also from the American Amazon, given that many products come from interior, but also from the American prices. or by Hong Kong.
According to the numbers cited by the Lusa Agency, the exemption from rates in the purchase of low value articles has greatly benefited from the two Chinese platforms and Amazon: the number of fees -free shipments has increased by 600 percent over the past ten years, reaching 1, 36 billion orders last year, against almost 140 million in 2015.
After all there was another
In a last minute turnaround, USPS has announced that it will now accept postal order services from China and Hong Kong, totally contradicting what it had announced. With the announcement arriving at the time of the closing of this edition it was not possible to assess any reaction of the Chinese and local CTT services.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:38:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Banking | Profits with lower value in the last 14 years</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/banca-lucros-com-valor-mais-baixo-dos-ultimos-14-anos/</link><description>Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas last year, as it represented a 21.3 percent reduction compared to 2023. The data were released by the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM)
 
Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas by 2024, a drop of 21.3 percent and the lowest value since 2010.
According to official data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the main reason for decreasing profits was a fall of 18.3 percent, to 16.1 billion patacas, on the interest margin, the difference between loans and deposit expenses.
This after AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
The loans, the main source of revenue of the banking worldwide, decreased 7.2 percent compared to the end of December 2023, setting at 1.01 billion of patacas. On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased 4 percent to 1.27 billion of patacas in late 2024, AMCM said on Monday.
The bank had ended 2023 with a profit of 6.14 billion patacas, 53.5 percent than the previous year. Macao has two currency broadcasters: the local Chinese state bank branch Banco da China and the National Bank Overseas (BNU), which belongs to the Caixa Geral de Depósitos group.
BNU with profits
BNU announced in November net profits of 444.2 million patacas in the first three quarters of the year, a 3.4 percent homologous decrease, in part due to the “prevailing environment of interest rates”.
Malpated credit increased by 30.3 percent by 2024 to 56.1 billion patacas, the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990, still during the Portuguese administration of the territory.
Overdue loans represented 5.5 percent of Macao banks loans, 1.6 more percentage points than at the end of 2023. A percentage that reaches 6.9 percent in the case of credit to institutions or individuals outside the Chinese region .
The European banking authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5 percent of poorly misplaced loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the percentage of bank credit overdue in Macau is far from the 25.3 percent record reached in mid -2001, in the middle of the world economic crisis caused by the buzzing of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:15:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Lunar New Year | Number of tourists below expectations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/ano-novo-lunar-numero-de-turistas-aquem-das-expectativas/</link><description>During New Year's Festivities almost 1.31 million people visited Macau, however, an average of 163,700 tourists per day was below government expectations. In January, the game's recipes also did not correspond to the analysts' predictions
 
Almost 1.31 million people visited Macau during the so -called Golden Week of the Lunar New Year, less 3.5 percent than in the same period of 2024 holidays, it was announced yesterday.
According to data from the Macao Public Security Police (PSP), between January 28 and February 4, more than 163,700 tourists per day entered the territory. On January 17, Macau's Director of Tourism Services (STD), Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, said she expected a daily average of 185,000 visitors during the 'Golden Week'.
The Lunar New Year, the largest mass movement in the world, is the main traditional party of Chinese families and takes place in January or February, depending on the lunar calendar, and the number of days depends on the decision of the State Council. This year, the first day of the year was celebrated on January 28, a Tuesday.
According to PSP data that also cover the previous weekend, Macau received almost 1.7 million visitors over a period of 11 days, between January 25 and February 4. The data released by the PSP did not indicate the origin of tourists, but reported that 38.8 percent entered through the doors of the siege, the main border with the interior.
Alternative Paths
Another 23.2 percent, arrived in the territory by the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge (29.8 percent), a 55.5 kilometers infrastructure that connects Macau and the adjacent Chinese city, Zhuhai, to the neighboring region of Hong Kong.
In fact, the bridge inaugurated in October 2018 recorded on Friday the passage of more than 156 thousand people at the Zhuhai terminal, a new maximum record, according to the state newspaper China Daily. The Lunar New Year is one of the three tall times for tourism and the Macao casinos, along with the 'golden weeks' of Labor Day (May 1) and China National Day (October 1).
The game's revenues in the game fell 5.6 percent in January, compared to the same month of 2024, to less than 18.3 billion patacas, below analyst expectations. Macau received last year 34.9 million visitors, 23.8 percent than the previous year, but still far from the 39.4 million record set in 2019, before the pandemic.
The number exceeded the initial STD forecasts, which were 33 million, as well as the magazine forecast on December 4: 34 million.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:52:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Number of non-resident workers rose almost 5,900</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/trabalho-numero-de-trabalhadores-nao-residentes-subiu-quase-5-900/</link><description>At the end of December more than 182,500,000 non-resident workers were registered in the territory, which represents an increase of almost 5,900 last year
 
Macao employed more than 182,500,000 non-resident workers at the end of December, an increase of almost 5,900 during the year 2024. According to data from the Public Security Police (CPSP), released by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSal ), this number represents an increase of almost 30,700 since the end of the 'Zero Covid' policy in January 2023.
This month, the labor from outside Macao, including from the interior of China, had fallen to less than 152,000, the lowest number since April 2014.
Since the maximum peak of 196,538, hit in late 2019, at the beginning of the pandemic, and until January 2023, the city lost almost 45,000 non-resident workers, which corresponded to 11.3 percent of the active population.
The hotel and restoration sector was the one that hired the most in 2024, earning 4,561 non-resident workers, followed by domestic employees (another 1,678) and cultural and recreational activities, including casinos (plus 1,418), according to data released on Monday.
The hotel and restoration area had been precisely the most affected by loss of labor during the pandemic, having faced more than 17,600 non-resident employees since December 2019.
Low unemployment rate
Macao welcomed 34.9 million visitors last year 23.8 percent than the previous year, and the hotels received more than 14.4 million guests in 2024, establishing a new historical record.
The economic crisis created by the pandemic led the unemployment rate to reach 4 percent in the third quarter of 2022, the highest since 2006. But, despite the increase in the number of non-resident workers, the unemployment rate has been seven for Months in a row at 1.7 percent, equaling the historical minimum reached before the start of the pandemic.
Macao's economy grew 11.5 percent in the first three quarters of 2024, compared to the same period of the previous year, thanks to the resumption of the game, according to official data. Gross Domestic Product (GDP) represented 86.3 percent of the amount recorded in the same period of 2019, before the start of the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:47:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Buses | Almost the whole fleet powered by electricity</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/autocarros-quase-toda-a-frota-movida-a-electricidade/</link><description>In late January, more than 92 percent of public buses were moved to “new energies”, while more than 86 percent of taxis are electric hybrid vehicles. Deputy Lo Choi in suggests subsidies to renew fleets of Takeaway companies with electric scooters
 
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) yesterday indicated that at the end of last January the Transmac and TCM fleets were composed of over 92 percent buses powered by new energies. The percentage had already been advanced by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), but was updated yesterday with the increase of nearly 30 additional electric buses for a total of 929 buses.
The proportion fulfills the goals set by the 2021-2025 environmental protection planning, which was significantly three years ago set the goal of over 90 percent of the fleet of buses in the territory being "moved with new energies" by 2025. According to Panorama Traced in Environmental Protection Planning 2021-2025, the government indicated that by 2020 only 8 percent buses in the territory were moved with new energies.
The update was made on the Macau Forum Program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, where it was also revealed that only about 3 percent of public buses do not fulfill the environmental protection standards provided for in the Euro 4 standard, which came into force in 2005.
Moving silence
Regarding taxi fleets, they operate in Macau 210 “purely electric” vehicles, which represents a proportion of almost 12 percent of all taxis, while the hybrid taxis is 1,526, about 86.2 percent.
DSPA also stated that it continues to follow the evolution of the transport sector and promote the use of newer new energy buses through the two bus companies and encourage the taxis sector to use more electric vehicles or new energy vehicles.
However, Deputy Lo Choi In would like to see the widening of environmental use of environmental energies to all transport, including motorcycles of Take-Away companies and other commercial vehicles. "The government can subsidize Take-Away distributors to promote the use of electrical motorcycles," the deputy told the public broadcaster's microphones.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:32:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deepseek | Launched recruitment campaign with high salaries to respond to search</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/deepseek-lancada-campanha-de-recrutamento-com-altos-salarios-para-responder-a-procura/</link><description>The Chinese Artificial Intelligence Platform (IA) Deepseek announced yesterday a recruitment campaign with offers exceeding $ 150,000 a year after achieving worldwide success at its launch.
The company has published at least 37 employment offers for various advanced technology positions, the best paid of which is the deep learning researcher, with an annual salary of about 1.12 million yuan (148,000 euros), according to the Business Journal Securities Times.
Deepseek currently has 150 employees, against about 1,700 from OpenAi, the main American competitor and the most used AI model to date.
According to the newspaper, the company intends to recruit the best talents finished leaving the Chinese universities, for which also launched an offer of scholarships in the main domains of AI, with daily financial compensation far superior to the usual internship and lunch And even dinner are subsidized.
With staff reinforcement, the technology company seeks to respond to the exponential growth of users since launch and improve and stabilize the service, which has suffered interruptions and technical failures allegedly due to the influx of consultation, even more intense due to the Lunar New Year, period in which much of the Chinese population was on vacation.
DeepSeek caused a major excitement in the global AI industry after the launch a few weeks ago from its V3 model, which will have only taken two months to develop and cost less than six million dollars.
On January 20, he released the latest version, called R1. Launched in 2023 by the Chinese investment fund High-Flyer Quant, DeepSeek is open source and offers 95 percent services cheaper than OpenAi's O1 model.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:43:50</pubDate></item><item><title>CPCPS | Patronato Refusa Rise from Minimum Wage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/cpcps-patronato-recusa-subida-do-salario-minimo/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs and representatives of employers in the Permanent Social Concertation Council remove the hypothesis of increasing the minimum wage or reviewing the limits of indemnities for occupational accidents and occupational diseases this year.
The position was taken after this year's first meeting of the Permanent Council for Social Concertation, which took place on Tuesday, while the representatives of the work part promised to support government decisions.
Legally, the amount of salary and the limits of compensation for occupational accidents and occupational diseases should be reviewed in annual or biannual periods. However, Wong Chi Hong, director of DSAL, explained that the term review means that an assessment is made, which may conclude that the best option is not to move the values ​​in force.
“We will review in our work, because there has to be a review every two years. But doing a review does not mean that there has to be an increase, what we do is a data collection, to make a report and then be able to send to the Permanent Social Concertation Council, ”said Wong Chi Hong, quoted by the Macau channel.

Frozen year
In turn, Vong Kok Seng, leader of the Macao Commercial Association, believes that the obligation to revise the minimum salary and limits must be changed. “The economic and social situation is basically identical. Therefore, I ask if it is necessary to review these amounts annually… We question if there is a review or change of legislation, if the annual revision period should not be relaxed, ”said Vong.
In turn, Fong Ka Fai, representative of the workplace, indicated that during the meeting were requested increases of maternity leave, paternity and revision of the boundaries. However, it admits that there was no response, and that ultimately will support the government's choice. "There were not many answers, but of course, as workers we will support the government and make our efforts to promote the economy of Macau, because we had the pandemic, and after the pandemic it takes an effort from everyone," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:50:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | Elderly stable after the fan is connected</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/gripe-idosa-estavel-apos-estar-ligada-a-ventilador/</link><description>A 69-year-old woman recovered from a complicated clinical influenza A, who forced respiratory aid and in the second no longer needed a fan, being currently considered stable, health services indicated yesterday.
The patient went to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center on January 14 where he was diagnosed with bacterial pneumonia and submitted to hospitalization.
About two weeks later, symptoms got worse with fever and shortness of breath. On February 1, it would eventually be diagnosed with flu and pneumonia, which forced the medical team to resort to the mechanical fan. Authorities added that the patient was not vaccinated against seasonal flu this year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:16:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Museum in honor of Cristiano Ronaldo opens in July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/hong-kong-museu-em-homenagem-a-cristiano-ronaldo-abre-em-julho/</link><description>Asia's first Cristiano Ronaldo Life (CR7) museum will be inaugurated in July 2025 at the K11 Museea mall in Tsim Sha Tsui, Hong Kong, according to organizers on Tuesday.
With state -of -the -art interactive exhibitions, rare memorabilia and reports of the various milestones in the career of the footballer, the museum offers visitors an engaging tribute around the football legend, the people's diary indicates.
Tickets were set for sale yesterday, coinciding with Ronaldo's birthday, providing fans around the world the opportunity to be part of the historic inauguration. The organization estimates that the space is expected to attract more than 12 million visitors to Hong Kong over a year.
The opening day of CR7 Life Museum will be attended by several international celebrities, in honor of Cristiano Ronaldo's career. Between March and April, two stores with autographed products in Tsim Sha Tsui and Hong Kong Island will be opened.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:46:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative Macau | Henry MA presents works in paint from China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/creative-macau-henry-ma-apresenta-obras-em-tinta-da-china/</link><description>Henry MA has been making a career in the arts area, not only in the government but in the gym, and returns, starting next Tuesday, with a new exhibition of ink works from China at Creative Macau. “Searching” is the name of the show that can be seen for free until mid -March
 
Creative Macao presents, from next Tuesday and until March 11, the exhibition “Searching”, with works by Henry Ma, a highlighted name within local arts and also higher education.
This is a show facing the pieces made of ink from China by the creative and teacher who graduated in Fine Arts in Canada, then made a master's degree in History at the University of Jinan, China, and a doctorate in archeology and museology by Beijing University.
A note from Creative Macau cites the author's own words about the exposure of his own. “It has been almost 40 years since I licensed at the Faculty of Fine Arts of Canada. After returning to Macao in the early 1980s, I started working for the government and was responsible for the exhibitions of Fine Arts. Since then, I have organized exhibitions only for others and, occasionally, I participate in joint exhibitions to show one or two of my own works, which does not reflect the scope of my artistic creation, ”he says.
Thus, according to Henry MA, “Searching” is made up of 30 pieces of his sketches made with paint from China, being drawings made on various landscapes and outdoor places in recent years. "Although they cannot be considered as great works of art, they should be considered as a review of my research and development phases." For the artist and creative, “there are still many flaws that need to be improved,” he assumes.
Return and Career
According to the artist, he recalls that when he returned to Macao, he tried to “apply western painting techniques in Chinese art”, as well as “incorporate Chinese handwriting as a means of expression”.
However, success did not always accompany him. “I tried in many ways, but the effect was not significant, so I returned to the starting point with outdoor sketches. At first, he drew with handmade paper fiber pens and then moved to China's ink on rice paper. In the early stages, I could not deal with the reaction between ink and water, but after years of practice, I gradually understood the interrelationship between these two means. ”
Still, the artist assumes that he continues to "think and constantly seek the way he expresses me in my own works of art."
Henry MA was a member of the Executive Committee of the Institute for Macao Municipal Affairs by 2020 and is director and member of the Executive Committee of the Macao Radio and Television station since 2021, the Macao teledifusion.
MA has also taught in institutions such as the University of Beijing and the University of Science and Technology of Macau, having published a book entitled “A Research on Blue and White Porcelain Wares of the Ming Dynasty Unearthed in Macau”, along with articles edited in several magazines academic. His art, which includes paintings, photographs and Chinese calligraphy, was exhibited in Canada, Continental China and Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:21:31</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE | Beijing against rates imposed by Washington</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/mne-pequim-contra-taxas-impostas-por-washington/</link><description>China said yesterday that it resolutely opposed to increasing customs imposed by the United States about its products and appealed to dialogue after revealing a series of retaliation measures on Tuesday.
"China expresses its profound dissatisfaction and is resolutely opposed to US measures," Chinese Foreign Foreign Ministry spokesman at a press conference said. "What we need now is not a unilateral increase in rates, but a dialogue and discussions based on mutual respect," he added.
Target of additional customs of 10 percent customs on all its exports to the United States, Beijing immediately retaliated on Tuesday, promising to increase customs barriers on a series of US products, from crude oil to agricultural machinery.
Beijing also announced new restrictions on critical metal exports used in sectors ranging from mining to aerospace industry. "The measures taken by China are a necessary action to defend their legitimate rights and interests," said the Chinese spokesman.
United States President Donald Trump said on Monday that a call with his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, could take place soon, giving the impression that a quick turnaround was possible. But he later denied the statement, saying that "I was not in a hurry" to talk to Xi.
Asked about a possible future conversation between the two leaders, Chinese diplomacy spokesman did not give details.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:32:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Suspicious transactions broke record in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/jogo-transaccoes-suspeitas-bateram-recorde-em-2024/</link><description>Over last year, suspicious financial transactions related to the game sector increased by 11.8 percent compared to 2023, with a total of 3,837 reports presented to the authorities in 2024, according to data provided by the Financial Information Office (GIF) to GGR Asia Portal. The authorities justified the increase with the economic recovery of the territory and the “significant increase” of the number of tourists who visited Macau.
In addition to the socioeconomic context, GIF states that the increase in suspicious financial transactions is also related to the continuous investment in resources to identify suspicious movements in the game industry.
Last year's number of suspicious transactions has hit the annual record as long as this type of registration is made, ie since 2006. This year, the most common type of gif radar activities includes conversion of game sheets with few or without Betting, exchange of game sheets on behalf of third parties, currency exchange and currency conversion.
In general, the GIF received a total of 5,245 appearances, with 73.2 percent from the casino dealers, while 20.9 percent arrived from banks and insurers and 5.9 percent of other institutions and entities.
The referenced sectors, including pledge, jewelery, real estate and auction houses, are required to communicate to the authorities any transaction equal to or greater than 500,000 patacas. Of the total of 5,245 appearances, the GIF last year 142 suspected transactions to the prosecutor for investigation, 26 more than 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:02:23</pubDate></item><item><title>António Graça de Abreu</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/antonio-graca-abreu/</link><description>"Jorge Mazcarenhas Foy to have the city called Chincheo, where it seems to him that he was richer people than in Canton."
Fernão Lopes de Castanheda, History of the Conquest of India, Book IV, Chapter XLI.
“We arrived at the port of Chinchéu, we found three ships from Portuguese that had been a month ago that were arrived (from Liampó) of which we were very well received and wrapped with a lot of party and contentment and then gave us new land, and the merchant , and the peace and quiet of the port. ”
Fernão Mendes Pinto, pilgrimage, chap.57
"When the Portuguese, in the 16th Century, Recovered China to European Knowledge, Zayton Was in the longing the great haven of forreign trade."
Henry Yule, The Book of Marco Polo The Venetian, London, John Murray, 1874, Chapter LXXXII, II Vol., Pag 221, Note 2.
Among the reports of our 16th century chroniclers and adventurers there is some confusion as to the exact location of the place we called Chincheo. The toponym appears associated with two different but close spaces, the cities of Quangzhou 泉州 and Zhangzhou 漳州 or, by extension, the Chincheos will be the inhabitants of the current province of Fujian, and Chincheo may still be the name of the province itself. Now to Quangzhou, the two characters - who sound like "chuanchou" in Mandarin - have the approximate reading of "Chinchew" in the local pronunciation, in the Hokkien or Fulaohua 福佬话 福佬话, (the old language of Fujian), a subgroup of the great min of the South South spoken in the province of Fujian. From "Chinchew" to the chincheo of the Portuguese in China goes a very short step. Moreover, it is curious that, in addition to the Mandarin, the most spoken dialect in Taiwan, Formosa, is exactly the Hokkien since part of the island's population is originally from the Quangzhou region, emigrated to Taiwan in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries.
Not wanting to enter any other discussion, I believe the city of Quangzhou, such as Liampó or Ningbo 宁波, in the neighboring province of Zhejiang, [1] will be the major ports of commerce and shelter of the Portuguese of the first half of the 16th century, still still Prior to the foundation and fixation in Macau, which will only happen from 1553/55, after our sailors, merchants and adventurers were expelled from these two cities by the Chinese because they are foreigners and have assumed behaviors of true haitao 海偷, the "pirates of the sea" as the Chinese called us. Just read the saga of António de Faria in the pilgrimage of Fernão Mendes Pinto to understand how to trade but also loot, steal, live extremely part of the Portuguese hundredists of the Portuguese by lands of China. Just as they entered the daily lives of other peoples, including Chinese.
Quangzhou or Chincheo, or if we want to Zaiton of Marco Polo that in his book he considers her “a of the two best and Mayors that sound in the world” was one of the first places on China's back to navigation, point of scale and often at the beginning of what is conventionally called the “sea silk route”. From here he left Marco Polo on his long return trip to Italy. It is believed that Zaiton, the Arab name in Quangzhou,-also associated with “olive”-gave rise to the words “satin” in English and “satin” in Portuguese, all related to the many tons of silk that exported by Porto from Quangzhou. [1]
In the dynasties Song and Yuan (from 960 to 1368), the city has reached the zénite of its development as the great warehouse of the seas of Asia. They were Muslim merchants, especially Persians - who since the ninth century they gave body to the expansion of Islam to the vast Southeast Asia - which settled in Quangzhou where they calculate they had reached 150 thousand souls. It was so strong its economic power in the city that between 1345 and 1365 were the subject of a brutal persecution by the Chinese powers, and there were thousands and thousands of dead. In the fourteenth century, Zaiton was also inhabited by Jews, Hindu and Catholics, and the Italian Franciscan Andrea of ​​Perugia was the first bishop in the city in 1332. Then dozens of mosques and three churches, all devastated in the persecution in those years.
In the summer of 2013, I am in search of the city of Zaiton, Quangzhou, Chinchew or Chincheo.
Seventy kilometers of bus since Xiamen and I arrive in the city that seems to me harmonious, well distributed by the valley and the hills that surround it. Where is the river, where is the port? I ask and are saying that Quangzhou has no sea port, only at the mouth of the river, in front of the islands, there is a small port for fishing boats. Path miles along the Jinhera River towards the sea. The river is hardly navigable, everything is blown away, the sand and mud have once deposited in the bed of deep water, the current city lives almost its back facing the Jinhera River and the ocean. The great port of Zaiton, the most likely Chincheo of the Portuguese in China, was swallowed by the mud, the sands deposited in the river and, before its mouth, the waters almost disappeared with the rolling of the centuries.
I get a taxi and tell the driver's wife, an affable and friendly lady, I want to go, always on the bank of the river, to the mouth. It's four or five more kilometers, but the driver asserts me that there is no large port, just a village of fishermen and fishing boats. We advanced on the road. I guess a hundred trainers, all blue, made in China, moved down there. There is even a port at the mouth of the river, also with benches and restingas, with a lot of sand and mud, but a port against the sea.
I leave the taxi and advance to the pier, for fishing boats aligned next to the jetty, I enter the confusion of those who arrive with fish to discharge and to sell. Women carry heavy buckets of fish suspended at the end of bamboo sticks, others sitting in stools clean crabs and oysters, others, still, with an entredious hair that turns on the head in a safe pulling by a kind of chopsticks, packing fish Loose and seafood that sell in small lots. There are men playing Weiqi, Chinese chess, and players loudly hitting the top of makeshift tables. Some fishermen, certainly tired of the sea, are quietly watching the bullied mixed with the calm of these seaside people.
Attraven the street, the way to the village next to the side that seems to keep the past centuries. Low wooden houses, some of one townhouse, decrepit and poor. Narrow streets, quite filth, small shops, one or another house of food, almost only fish and seafood, old planted in the threshold of houses, boys jumping happy by alleys and alleys. I'm in Quangzhou, in the chincheo of five hundred. Porto and the city should be so in the sixteenth century and, when returning, I prove, that I am not in a village but in the extension of the old Quangzhou urban fabric itself. Almost guessed Fernão Mendes paint with the conversation with António de Faria, perhaps his alter ego, in a reed, anchored at the mouth of the Jinhera River, here, Chincheo, the year 1545.
The next day, visit the Quangzhou Maritime Museum, meeting the history and the many navigations for these seas of Fujian, southern China.
In the fundamental Chinese sources there is almost no reference to Portugal and the Portuguese. If we were the first to terrify these stops, in the sea connection between Europe and the Empire of the middle realized in 1513 with the arrival of Jorge Álvares to Toumen, at the current Hong Kong, Guangdong province, we were not the pioneers in the navigations along of the back and in the stay in China. In the thirteenth and fourteenth centuries, Marco Polo, the Franciscan Muslims and missionaries, all journeying for the old Zaiton, deserve the honors of museum exposure, with the exposure of stones and headds recently discovered with extensive texts in Arabic and tumular stones with Christian crosses.
It is interesting to show the different types of boats that in the past have ventured into these seas, from the high-sea junctions of Admiral Zheng He (1377-1433) that with these ships navigated to Mombasa in 1433, to the stems and ships, these yes linked to a Portuguese presence. Also noteworthy is the patriotic figure of Zheng Chenggong (1624-1662) or Koxinga, who from pirate spent the national hero after expelled in 1661 the Dutch seated 38 years ago at Forte Zeelhand, Taiwan, where they controlled Formosa Island.
Even next to the Maritime Museum is another three-story building, which also works as a kind of museum, the Islamic Cultural Center where the Muslim community once resident in Zaiton/Quangzhou is honored. At the entrance we came across a statue of IBN Battuta (1304-1377), Tânger's great natural Arab traveler, just below our Algarve, who in the fourteenth century undertook a very long journey to China and left us a fabulous account of their travels, something similar to the “book of Marco Polo”. Battuta lived for a year in Zaiton, exactly 1346. In the Garden of the Cultural Center we found a cemetery for the deceased illustrious Muslims in the city and it is also worth visiting the great Qingjing mosque, originally built in 1009 by the first proselytes of Islam and that remain restored ruins, and a portico. Taking advantage of the space adjacent to Qingjing, a new mosque has just been built with money from Saudi Arabia, not too large, but witnessing a long -term and relationship, not always affectionate and peaceful, between Islam and China.
Returning to our five hundred sailors will be to remember that the Portuguese of then were not much given to visit mosques, pagodas, Buddhist temples or Taoists. But in Quangzhou/Chincheo, since the year 686, a magnificent set of pavilions and pagodas dedicated to Buddha veneration, the Kaiyuan temple. Around the year 1100, in the Song Dynasty (960-1279) was inhabited by more than a thousand monks. Today, in the temple of Kaiyuan, stand out the two beautiful stone pagodas, equal, not too high, just five floors with the walls covered by low-relevous original, all dated from the thirteenth century when Zaiton or Quangzhou was one of the big cities From China.
Few people visit Kaiyuan. The unfolding of the gaze, a little reverence for the Buddhas, remember Portugal and the Portuguese of Anthony, and dilute me in the serenity of the day.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Fei Zhangfang, a semi-release personality that will have lived in the East Han Dynasty (25-220), was a guard in the market of his city that became an imperfect disciple of an old man who sold potions called Hugong, which he soon realized to be An immortal that ended his exile on earth. From him he received a baton that surprisingly allowed him to travel, as flying, incredible distances.
Fei tried to learn from the master his secrets, but failed to the third test. When Hugong sent him home, he told him to lie down on a nearby lake called Gebei. As he throw him, Fei Zhangfang noticed how he became a blue dragon. The legend that, in his multiple senses, alluded to the ability of the spirit of the Spirit making astonishing changes and unprecedented displacements in space, would be a recurring theme in figurative paintings at the end of the Ming Dynasty.
An Xuzhou painter (Jiangsu) called Wan Shouqi (1603-1652), who lived in the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition, will have added yet another meaning to the figuration in 1650, a representation of amazed Fei on the sidelines of Lake witnessing The emergency of the Blue Dragon, on a fan (paint and color on paper, 20.9 x 46.6 cm, at the Minneapolis Art Institute).
The fan, Zhongli's prop, one of the Ba Xian (the eight immortals), who when he shaken him had, among others according to his will, the power to resurrect dead. Wan Shouqi's willingness to return to the old dynasty in one of the "brush names", Hao, which he chose: Mingzhi daoren, who can have several readings, such as "Daoist with a brilliant ideal »Or" the daoist who recalls the ming. " From his biography he emphasizes the fact that in 1628, when he had not yet obtained the Jini degree, he participated in a large feast offered by Emperor Chongzhen (R.1627-1644) to the most illustrious literate in the Empire.
Wan Shouqi joined in 1632 to the literary and politics 'Society of Renewal', Fushe, which opposed the power of the palace's eunuchs and proposed to eliminate the sterile literary styles of imperial examinations, reviving the lessons of ancients with more useful themes.
In the period of disorder that followed the fall of the Ming, Wan wandered in the territory until she settled on a farm near her hometown. Then, in 1651, in a painting roll in which it is clear his knowledge of the great masters (ink on paper, 20 x 289 cm, at the Guimet Museum), painted his residence in response to a friend's request, as if he was a invitation. He wrote: «Here's my Caotang pee. Master Jin made me promise that he would dedicate a poem, but the poem does not appear; So I painted this roll to my own pleasure. The ancients said, "In all paintings there is a poem." Master Jin will be inside or outside the painting? »</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, coordinator of the Educational Service of CCCM 2025
January 29, 2025
To know more deeply the nature of wooden serpent Yin (乙巳蛇 yǐ sì shé), it will be convenient to analyze the stories related to this reptile of the sixth terrestrial field in close association with the female principle.
It comes closely associated with the matriarchal divinity nϋwa (女娲 nǚwā) in the following myths “nϋwa creates humans” (女娲造人 nǚwā zào fench) and “nϋwa to the sky” (女娲补天 nǚwā bǔ tiān). In myths divinity arises alone, complete in itself, as a creative force, in the first myth, and as a regenerating and constructive force in the second, when mending the sky.
As a mother of humanity, he did not remember being the following one of a visit to Earth, having first created the animals, but as he still felt deep loneliness, he decided to generate human beings: he could do so for containing powerful energy Soul, manifested in his quality of being heavenly, whose physical appearance was distinguished, because although he had a human head, he had a serpent body. It spontaneously generated with the help of the clay, that is, the Earth, an element to which it is indissolibly linked, either in the underground world, in wells, or in its agile climbing by the mountains and trees in an instinctive search for heavenly ascension.
It is still this same figure with a serpent body that will replace order on Earth, when it plunges into chaos, following dignifying titanic forces, as in some versions it is affirmed that he has not wounded the sky after the god of northern Água do Norte, gonggong Founded his head against Buzhoushan (共工怒触不周山 Gònggōng Nù Chù Bùzhōushān), in an attack of fury against Northern Heavenly Emperor, Zhuanxu (颛顼 Zhuānxū), following the defeat inflicted by this.
The way it has not taken the sky, the care it has put in raising its pillars, establishing them with the aid of stones, whose colors (green, yellow, white, dark and red) indicate the presence of the five elements, essential to Life, as well as the foundation of them erected on the paws of a black turtle, in order to ensure their longevity but even eternity; The precious aid he granted to humanity in the fight against beasts that in the bastard of collapse pulled, the works of drainage he then made, transformed this deity with the body of serpent into one of the foundations of Chinese religious culture and civilization.
Note is the powerful ambivalence of this reptile, since if it was not being bodied, Gonggong, the Funning God of Water, is described with the identical body of serpent, otherwise see how portrayed in “Gonggong throws the head against Buzhoushan: “Gonggong was a descendant of Yandi. It had a body of serpent, face and human limbs, as well as red hair, which indicated its fiery, energetic and adamant character ”(WANG, ALVES, 2009: 54).
Serpents have poison, which heals as much as it kills, and can become, by their immense mutation capacity, into excellent humans as in the case of Banga Serpent (白娘子 Bai Niángzi), even in small dragons (小龙 xiǎolóng), when developing The generous and meditative facet, when connecting and advocating superior values, such as love, in the famous legend that came to us, for example, through Zhao Qingge (赵清阁) in 《白蛇传》 (Bai shé zhuàn).
However, by their strength, capacity and intelligence can conflict as in the history of popular literature “discussion between serpent and the sun”, which might be able to find cultural equivalent in the Aesop's fable competition “wind and the sun”.  In “The Serpent argues with the sun” (蛇与太阳的争吵) There is an obvious rivalry between the sun, representative of the yang male element, beautiful, bright, hot and powerful and the equally portentous serpent, considers themselves as much power from the earth.
It challenges the sun, beginning a conflict between the power of the lunar mysterious and hidden forces, represented by the serpent, and the splendid irradiative brightness of solar energy. Finally the fable ends not with the victory of the sun, in the manner of Aesop, but with the need for recognition of complementarity, because without the alternation of night and day, sun and shadow, heat and cold the world, As the Chinese understand it (based on this tension harmony) would not be complete. Moral of History: If there was no sun, it would be the death of the earth, for it would plunge into an infinite night, if there were no snakes, it would be equally the end of the world, because there would be no agility, no ability to transform, plunging “everything that exists under heaven ”(天下 tiānxià) in immense rigidity and monotony.
A serpente, enquanto sexto ramo terrestre do zodíaco chinês (十二生肖蛇 shí´èr shēngxiào) simboliza ainda o animal engenhoso, que, devido à sua poderosa inteligência, é capaz de arquitetar e realizar um plano bem calculado. This is proved by his biography upon entering the heavenly race promoted by the Emperor of Jade (玉皇大帝 Yù Hung dàdì).
The serpent and the dragon used to be good companions and share the same aquatic spaces, when he learned of the emperor's intention to organize a competition so that twelve animals could command the stars and destinations of humans. Given the powerful intelligence of the reptile, he realized that he had no hypothesis or quickness to overcome the dragon, but as he knew how to make good calculations and better plans, he shared discreetly to the horse's back, without the one he was carrying a rival nearby From the goal it jumped to position herself in front of the equity, and so it was, both good friends to our day, since the always generous horse never charged her the ride.  For the Chinese, the serpent symbolizes “a powerful and victorious mill” (以巧胜力 yǐ qiǎo shènglì).
Uma outra história chama a atenção para a importância do perdão no processo ascético da serpente rumo à transformação em Pequeno Dragão: “A Serpente e o Agricultor”(蛇与农夫 Shé yǔ nóngfū). In a harsh winter, a certain farmer went with a stuffed snake. Studying her, he took him home, putting her in a warm place. When he recovered his strength instead of thanking him for being saved, he attacked the poor unprepared man with the aim of injuring him. This, avoiding in time being bitten and repressing the fury, called the reptile to reason with calmly, asking him if that was how he treated a friend who had saved his life. The serpent, played by the proven goodness of the farmer, never attacked him again. Moral of the story that the Chinese tell their children: goodness pays off and can save not only bodies as souls.
The serpent symbolizes the divinity “guardian of the treasures of the earth” in 蛇守护宝藏 (shé shŏuhù bǎozàng), finding himself at the entrance of caves to watch over the infinite riches. The guardians are gigantic, endowed with a prodigious force, but also with deep and mysterious wisdom.  Anyone who tries to penetrate these caves will not achieve it as much as they have. Only someone very special, of heroic spirit and armed with virtuous wisdom will pass the proof, providing access to the treasures of the earth, not for its own enjoyment, but for the benefit of the community and/or humanity.
I end with my translation of another popular story, entitled “White Serpent, Black Serpent” (白蛇与黑蛇 Bái shi yǔi shé), which presents and summarizes and the need for both principles, Yin and Yang, always operate In equilibrium, being the black serpent, representative yin of mysterious and lunar force and the white, symbolizing the radiant force Yang energy, its counterpoint.
很久以前 ， 在一座隐秘的山中 ， 有两条神蛇 有两条神蛇 有两条神蛇 白蛇与黑蛇。白蛇象征纯洁与善良 生活在阳光明媚的山顶 生活在阳光明媚的山顶 守护着清澈的溪流与花草；黑蛇则代表力量与神秘 ， ，栖息在幽暗的山谷 ， 掌控着风暴与黑夜。
一天 ， 一场大旱袭击了山谷 ， 水源枯竭。白蛇认为 ， 只有靠善行和祈愿才能带来水 ， 而黑蛇则主张用力量召唤风暴来解决问题。两蛇因此争执不休 ， 各自施展法力 ， ，山中风暴与烈阳交替 ， 导致自然失衡 ， 生灵涂炭。在看到生灵的痛苦后 ， 白蛇与黑蛇意识到 ， 单靠善良或力量都无法真正拯救山林。它们最终联手 ， 白蛇用其善念唤来生命的春雨 ， 黑蛇用其力量引导水流重回山谷 ， 山林恢复生机 ， 两蛇也化作山中的守护灵。 (https://www.lingoace.com/zh/blog/story-for-the- Year-of-Snake/)
Once a large drought on the valley was slaughtered, exhausting all the sources and water reserves that existed there. The white serpent believed the power of its good deed and prayers to return, while the black serpent argued that only by invoking the strength of storms would the question be resolved.  The two snakes argued nonstop, each displaying and exercising their abilities, sometimes with violent storms, sometimes with they are scorching. This situation led to the loss of balance in nature and the miserable suffering of living beings. When they both saw what they were suffering, they realized that if they just depended on the Benfazeja from the sun or that of the crashes, they would not have to save that mountainous region. Finally, they combined efforts. The white serpent invoked the vital energy of spring rain and the black serpent employed its strength to let the waters flow through the valleys and mountains to recover life. And this is how the two snakes became the Guardian Spirits of the Mountain.
Bibliographic references
Lingoace 新媒体团队 .2024. 蛇年文化故事：给孩子讲述的 10 个有趣传说 .Addenable in:
https://www.lingaace.com/zh/blog/story-for-the-year-of-snake/, accessed January 17, 2025.
"The Wind and the Sun" Anthology may, with World Press. Dysonable at: https://antologiaporventura.wordpress.com/2013/09/02/o-devent-e--sol-fabula-de-esop/, February 9, 2013, accessed on January 30, 2025.
WANG SOYING, Ana Cristina Alves. 2009. “The History of the White Serpent”, in myths and legends of the Dragon Land, Lisbon: Way.
Zhao Qingge (赵清阁) .1998. The Legend of White Snake. Beijing (北京): New World Press (新世界出版社).</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>José Simões Morais</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/jose-sm/</link><description>China, with an existence for seventy -eight cycles, each 60 years, in 2025 has the number 42 to correspond to Yisi (乙巳), green serpent. The lunar year begins on January 29 and will end on February 16, 2026 and for Feng Shui starts at 10:10 pm on February 3, when the Principle of Spring (Lichun) is celebrated. Unlike the previous year, without any Lichun, they are two celebrated, the second due to the double sixth lunar month, counting the year with 384 days.
In the celestial stem (Tian gan, 天干) the Yi (乙) element, wood yin, and in the terrestrial branch (di zhi, 地支) si (巳, serpent) element yin, southern direction. ) Yin wood has the fire element (Si, 巳) underneath and how wood grows fire, the fire will be fed and very strong, and even more nourished by joining the Li water (离, fire) of the period 9 [twenty years started in 2024 and ending in 2043].
Beginning at Lichun of 2025 is entered a period of three years whose dominant element is fire. In 2026, Bingwu Year (丙午), both in the celestial stem and in the earth's field has the Yang Fire element and so called the Red Horse Year. Already in 2027, Dingwei (丁未) is fire yin and then called by Red Range.
Fire represents war, volcanoes, earthquakes, storms, and links to the metal element, [melted by fire], aviation and road accidents. For health, the fire causes heart attacks (as this is fire element) and lung problems (metal element), which are the main organs affected this year.
As fire melts metal, Europe (located in the west direction, metal element) will suffer more, but Portugal wrapped in water can balance and control the intensity of fire.
As for the terrestrial branch (di zhi, 地支) SI (巳), Yin Fire element and southern direction, recognized by the year of the serpent, symbolic animal whose common name is shé (tsz, 蛇), represents for this year, diverting if the normal path. It does not follow the rules. It is also very flexible and has the sensitivity to wait to act at the right time.
Yisi Year (乙巳), yin wood, fire yin, will be financially good because the waves caused to large businesses, especially those related to wood, pharmacist, cultural and agriculture products. People like to make investments as in a game and quickly earn or lose everything.
Rotation of the five planets
For 2025, the fire li (离) of period 9, which started last year for twenty years, means separation and with a strong connection to the planet Mu Xing (木星, Jupiter) will continue to act on Earth, activating seismos, volcanic eruptions, and storms.
It will be an abnormal year due to the change of meaning in the rotation of seven planets, which in a certain period rotate in the opposite direction, in an apparent retrograde movement, because from the “point of view of the earth they seem to stop briefly and reverse the meaning of movement in certain Moments, although in reality they orbet in the same direction around the sun, ”according to information on the Wikipedia explained in the article.
Thus huo Xing (火星, Mars, the Star of Fire, Southern Direction) has already begun to run in the opposite direction (in an apparent retrograde movement) on January 7, 2025 and will continue until April 18. It will be a period of huge problems with fires and other natural calamities, linked to the fire element. This inverted rotation also occurs to Jin Xing (金星, Venus, the West Metal Star) from March 28 to April 30.
Planet Venus is linked to finance and when from March 28 to April 18, Huo Xing and Jin Xing, both overlap with reversed rotation, there will be large waves in the world economy and financial markets [Stock Exchange and the Currency exchange] will suffer with great turbulence, in a foreshadowing of financial crisis.
All remaining five planets that follow change the direction of running in the second half of the year: Tu Xing (土星, Saturn The Earth Star, Center Directorate), linked to Geology and Agriculture, from September 1, 2025 to mid -February 2026 will affect the land and create new morphologies caused by tsunamis. Lots of land will be flooded and in other parts will suffer severe dried.
In meteorology, when it is necessary cold, it is hot, when rain is needed, the intense sun shines, affecting agriculture, leading to lack of food. Already the other planets that of a progressive movement come to circulate in the other direction, in an apparent retrograde movement, opposite to the hitherto, are Shui Xing (水星, Mercury, Water Star, North Directorate); Tian Wang Xing (Uranus); Hai Wang Xing (海王星, nepturnus); Ming Wang Xing (冥王, Pluto). These changes put people to make decisions with the hot head without thinking about the problems they can create. October will be a black month due to what may happen, hopefully not the beginning of a new war.
Alert for Devir
For this year you can be a spectator, do not be actor. The wood element represents culture, being the only theme for relaxing the heart.
With climate change to raise the powers of the elements, everything comes with great intensity leading to large disasters. After the weather, World War expects only a snap of fingers to appear, come true and explode. Pandemics peek and are ready to attack. Everything is about great pressure and extreme, the economy will help a few and many will be left out due to the inflated or undervalued price of work.
Only now is it the awareness of being in the third millennium. The year 2025 will scare people and with this tension the follies of the soul of fire will emerge, an element that will be perpetuated in the next two years. In the overview for 2025 this will be a difficult year, but it is just a warning of what will come in 2026.
In Yi Jing corresponds to hexagram 49, GE (HUA) in the past the skin of animals already without hair and the current means and appears to build a new system possibly through a revolution (the removal of what has become old -fashioned). Water and fire extinguish each other.
Tai sui
The God of the Year (Tai Sui) of 2025 is General Wu Sui. Born in Anhui province he was a magistrate of the Song dynasty and became known for his intelligence, compassion and ability to resolve with the sharpness of his analyzes very complex cases. This led to the governor of Xuning in Anhui in 1240. Due to an extreme drought in the region, he spent three days and nights at the Seng Vong Temple (Cheng Huang) to pray for rain, and his orders are fulfilled.
The rain appeared, but only in its region because around the drought was devastating having a lot of hunger and huge fires, bringing chaos to these areas and only the territory where I ruled had peace and stability. It was an island and having the general organized everything, the region did not fall into chaos with harmony in the population unlike other places where the lootered and only the Huaihe area were dominated to fled 400,000 people there.
With General Wu Sui as Tai Sui 2025, this year brings changes related to conflict sources enhanced by natural disasters and violent discussions, hostilities and tensions intensified by Flying Star 3 Jade (San BI) to end in court.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>José Simões Morais</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/jose-sm/</link><description>China, with an existence for seventy -eight cycles, each 60 years, in 2025 has the number 42 to correspond to Yisi (乙巳), green serpent. The lunar year begins on January 29 and will end on February 16, 2026 and for Feng Shui starts at 10:10 pm on February 3, when the Principle of Spring (Lichun) is celebrated. Unlike the previous year, without any Lichun, they are two celebrated, the second due to the double sixth lunar month, counting the year with 384 days.
In the celestial stem (Tian gan, 天干) the Yi (乙) element, wood yin, and in the terrestrial branch (di zhi, 地支) si (巳, serpent) element yin, southern direction. ) Yin wood has the fire element (Si, 巳) underneath and how wood grows fire, the fire will be fed and very strong, and even more nourished by joining the Li water (离, fire) of the period 9 [twenty years started in 2024 and ending in 2043].
Beginning at Lichun of 2025 is entered a period of three years whose dominant element is fire. In 2026, Bingwu Year (丙午), both in the celestial stem and in the earth's field has the Yang Fire element and so called the Red Horse Year. Already in 2027, Dingwei (丁未) is fire yin and then called by Red Range.
Fire represents war, volcanoes, earthquakes, storms, and links to the metal element, [melted by fire], aviation and road accidents. For health, the fire causes heart attacks (as this is fire element) and lung problems (metal element), which are the main organs affected this year.
As fire melts metal, Europe (located in the west direction, metal element) will suffer more, but Portugal wrapped in water can balance and control the intensity of fire.
As for the terrestrial branch (di zhi, 地支) SI (巳), Yin Fire element and southern direction, recognized by the year of the serpent, symbolic animal whose common name is shé (tsz, 蛇), represents for this year, diverting if the normal path. It does not follow the rules. It is also very flexible and has the sensitivity to wait to act at the right time.
Yisi Year (乙巳), yin wood, fire yin, will be financially good because the waves caused to large businesses, especially those related to wood, pharmacist, cultural and agriculture products. People like to make investments as in a game and quickly earn or lose everything.
Rotation of the five planets
For 2025, the fire li (离) of period 9, which started last year for twenty years, means separation and with a strong connection to the planet Mu Xing (木星, Jupiter) will continue to act on Earth, activating seismos, volcanic eruptions, and storms.
It will be an abnormal year due to the change of meaning in the rotation of seven planets, which in a certain period rotate in the opposite direction, in an apparent retrograde movement, because from the “point of view of the earth they seem to stop briefly and reverse the meaning of movement in certain Moments, although in reality they orbet in the same direction around the sun, ”according to information on the Wikipedia explained in the article.
Thus huo Xing (火星, Mars, the Star of Fire, Southern Direction) has already begun to run in the opposite direction (in an apparent retrograde movement) on January 7, 2025 and will continue until April 18. It will be a period of huge problems with fires and other natural calamities, linked to the fire element. This inverted rotation also occurs to Jin Xing (金星, Venus, the West Metal Star) from March 28 to April 30.
Planet Venus is linked to finance and when from March 28 to April 18, Huo Xing and Jin Xing, both overlap with reversed rotation, there will be large waves in the world economy and financial markets [Stock Exchange and the Currency exchange] will suffer with great turbulence, in a foreshadowing of financial crisis.
All remaining five planets that follow change the direction of running in the second half of the year: Tu Xing (土星, Saturn The Earth Star, Center Directorate), linked to Geology and Agriculture, from September 1, 2025 to mid -February 2026 will affect the land and create new morphologies caused by tsunamis. Lots of land will be flooded and in other parts will suffer severe dried.
In meteorology, when it is necessary cold, it is hot, when rain is needed, the intense sun shines, affecting agriculture, leading to lack of food. Already the other planets that of a progressive movement come to circulate in the other direction, in an apparent retrograde movement, opposite to the hitherto, are Shui Xing (水星, Mercury, Water Star, North Directorate); Tian Wang Xing (Uranus); Hai Wang Xing (海王星, nepturnus); Ming Wang Xing (冥王, Pluto). These changes put people to make decisions with the hot head without thinking about the problems they can create. October will be a black month due to what may happen, hopefully not the beginning of a new war.
Alert for Devir
For this year you can be a spectator, do not be actor. The wood element represents culture, being the only theme for relaxing the heart.
With climate change to raise the powers of the elements, everything comes with great intensity leading to large disasters. After the weather, World War expects only a snap of fingers to appear, come true and explode. Pandemics peek and are ready to attack. Everything is about great pressure and extreme, the economy will help a few and many will be left out due to the inflated or undervalued price of work.
Only now is it the awareness of being in the third millennium. The year 2025 will scare people and with this tension the follies of the soul of fire will emerge, an element that will be perpetuated in the next two years. In the overview for 2025 this will be a difficult year, but it is just a warning of what will come in 2026.
In Yi Jing corresponds to hexagram 49, GE (HUA) in the past the skin of animals already without hair and the current means and appears to build a new system possibly through a revolution (the removal of what has become old -fashioned). Water and fire extinguish each other.
Tai sui
The God of the Year (Tai Sui) of 2025 is General Wu Sui. Born in Anhui province he was a magistrate of the Song dynasty and became known for his intelligence, compassion and ability to resolve with the sharpness of his analyzes very complex cases. This led to the governor of Xuning in Anhui in 1240. Due to an extreme drought in the region, he spent three days and nights at the Seng Vong Temple (Cheng Huang) to pray for rain, and his orders are fulfilled.
The rain appeared, but only in its region because around the drought was devastating having a lot of hunger and huge fires, bringing chaos to these areas and only the territory where I ruled had peace and stability. It was an island and having the general organized everything, the region did not fall into chaos with harmony in the population unlike other places where the lootered and only the Huaihe area were dominated to fled 400,000 people there.
With General Wu Sui as Tai Sui 2025, this year brings changes related to conflict sources enhanced by natural disasters and violent discussions, hostilities and tensions intensified by Flying Star 3 Jade (San BI) to end in court.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Denmark | PM Refusal Sell Grolândia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/04/dinamarca-pm-recusa-vender-gronelandia/</link><description>Denmark Prime Minister Mette Frederiksen was yesterday available to dialogue with the United States over Granelândia, stressing that the autonomous territory “is not for sale”.
"We have been very clear: we all have to respect the sovereignty of all states in the world - and Granelândia is today a part of the kingdom of Denmark - not for sale," he said. The Danish leader spoke at the entrance of the first EU leaders' retreat, an initiative created by European Council President António Costa for more informal debates.
I totally agree with Americans that the region of the far north, the Arctic region, is increasingly important when we talk about defense and security and dissuasion, and it is possible to find a way to ensure a stronger [United States] footprint in Granelândia, where they are already, ”said Mette Frederiksen.
The head of the Copenhagen government also recalled that Danish troops fought alongside the US for many decades. US President Donald Trump has claimed greater access to the Arctic and expressed the interest of acquiring Granelândia, an autonomous territory managed by Denmark.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 01:22:03</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Trump will impose rates on “very soon” European products</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/04/eua-trump-vai-impor-taxas-sobre-produtos-europeus-muito-em-breve/</link><description>United States President Donald Trump said European products will be subject to “very soon” customs rates following the imposition of tariffs on the importation of products from Canada, Mexico and China.
“They are really enjoying us, we have a $ 300 billion deficit. They do not take our cars or our agricultural products, practically nothing, and we all bought millions of cars, huge levels of agricultural products, ”he said on Sunday to the press.
The European Union lamented on the same day the increase in customs rates by the United States of America about products from Canada, Mexico and China, and said it will retaliate strongly if it is targeted by unfair tariffs.
"The EU firmly believes that low customs rights promote economic growth and stability," the European Commission in a statement said through which he considered the imposition of more US tariffs as "harmful to all parties."
If the European bloc is also the target of these measures, the community executive will “retaliate strongly”. Donald Trump signed on Saturday the executive order to apply customs rates to products from Canada, Mexico and China.
The signature, which officializes the decision that had already been announced, determines the imposition of 10 percent rates to China, 25 percent to Mexico and 25 percent to Canada, except in Canadian oil, which will have a tariff of 10 by one hundred.
Trump had threatened the imposition of tariffs to ensure greater cooperation from countries to prevent illegal immigration and the smuggling of chemicals such as Fentanil, an opioid that is causing important additions in the United States. The three countries promise to take action.
Sacrifice (dis) necessary
In the case of the European Union, a decision has not yet been made, but the concern is general and France defended on Sunday a "scathing response" of Europe in the face of threats of new customs tariffs by the US President.
Trump admitted that the new tariffs can cause suffering to the American people, but has ensured that "everything will be worth it" because it will "make America big again."
“Will there be suffering? Yes, maybe (and maybe not). But let's make America big again, and it will all be worth it, ”wrote Donald Trump, in capital letters, on the profile of the social network he founded, Truth Social, quoted by the France-Presse news agency.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 01:18:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Greater life satisfaction associated with relationships and money</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/04/estudo-maior-satisfacao-de-vida-associada-a-relacoes-e-dinheiro/</link><description>A study that evaluates life satisfaction in 65 countries and regions, including China, Taiwan and Hong Kong, concludes that in all countries financial security and a love relationship are key to happiness. However, during the pandemic there was a “great variability in global satisfaction”
 
What is necessary to have a full life with happiness? The question, which can have various connotations and spiritual trends, sought to be answered and quantified by the authors of the study “Life Satisfaction Around the World: Measurement Invariation of the Satisfaction With Life Scale (SWLS) Across 65 Nations, 40 Languages, Gender Identities, and Age groups ”[Life satisfaction around the world: Invariance on Life Sounding Scale (SWLS) in 65 countries, 40 languages, gender identities and age groups].
The study, recently edited by the academic magazine “Plos One”, started from analyzes made by dozens of academics and contributors in 65 countries and regions, including China, Taiwan and Hong Kong, which makes 57,000 people analyzed.
In general terms, the authors conclude that "in all countries a greater satisfaction with life was significantly associated with financial security and the existence of a relationship of commitment or marriage." Thus, the results indicate that “greater satisfaction with life is significantly associated with greater financial security and higher educational qualifications (which may be an indicator of socioeconomic status, although the dimension of this specific relationship was insignificant)) ”.
In general terms, “these results are consistent with the tests that indicate that the satisfaction of basic human needs and material well-being is a strong-possibly the strongest-predictor of psychological well-being and life satisfaction and life specifically".
Admittedly, the authors draw attention to the fact that the idea of ​​well-being can vary from country to country depending on the culture of the populations, but the results “suggest that, when considered at the level of the individual, the association between satisfaction with Life and indicators of material welfare seems to be relatively robust between nations. ”
Regarding relationships, the answers hung more to the importance of not being alone. “We found that marital status was significantly associated with life satisfaction. More specifically, we found that respondents in commitment relationships were more likely to report more life satisfaction than non -married. This result is consistent with the widest literature that shows that marital status is a robust correlate of psychological well-being. ”
However, a satisfactory life is not directly linked exclusively to love relationships, and can also occur when the person has an active social life. "It has been suggested that the formation and maintenance of social relations is fundamental to the promotion of life satisfaction, particularly in cultures or communities that emphasize family values, because they satisfy a basic human need for belonging and are a source of positive affirmation." . In addition, it "reinforces healthy behaviors and protects against the impact of negative events."
Thus, the study considers it to be "likely that people living in commitment relationships can report greater emotional support and social integration, which, in turn, contributes independently to life satisfaction."
COVID-19 TIMES
If socialization is regarded as very important to a satisfactory life, as it was in times of COVID-19, which forced long periods of confinement and isolation? The study resorted to specific and statistics to evaluate the issue, concluding that there was “great variability in global satisfaction with life in the context of Covid-19 pandemic. The respondents in Canada (Francophone) and Israel had the highest SWLs and respondents in Japan and Ukraine to have the lowest averages. ”
Given the large dimension of the sample, the results allow you to conclude “that life satisfaction varied substantially among national groups at the height of the covid-19 pandemic, although the authors highlight,“ care is necessary to be careful when interpreting them Latent averages ”referred to at work so as not to advance with definitive conclusions. Still, academics understand that these data may be important to when "professionals and political decision makers try to understand differences in life satisfaction between nations," as well as being a "way to better support subjective well-being in the era Postpandmic ”.
Also noteworthy is the least life satisfaction by the minority population groups. “We found that identification as part of a racialized minority was associated with less life satisfaction. Although this is consistent with some previous works and probably reflects the deleterious effect of the experiences of racism on life satisfaction, it should be noted that the dimension of the effect of this relationship was insignificant. ”
In addition, the authors point out that “urbanity was associated with life satisfaction in a little significant way”, having been evaluated if living in a city or other urban context changed the level of satisfaction with life.
Means and purposes
To reach data from the SWLS scale described above, the “Body Image In Nature Inquiry” (Bins, English) was made by 253 scientists or academics of the 65 countries involved, who collected data between November 2020 and February 2022.
In total, 56,968 people were interviewed, 58.9 percent were women, 40.5 percent men and 0.6 percent were of another gender identity. In terms of race and ethnicity, the majority, 74.2 percent, "identified as part of a racialized majority," while 11.3 percent "identified himself as part of a racialized or minority ethnic group."
Regarding the site where participants live, 27 percent said living in a capital, 13.7 percent in the suburb of a capital, 25.1 percent in a city of province, that is, with more than 100 thousand inhabitants; While 18.7 percent said residing in a province town with more than 10,000 inhabitants. Only 15.5 percent of respondents lived in a rural area.
As for literary qualifications, 33.5 percent ended higher education, 42 percent were single and 19.5 percent were in a “commitment relationship, but were not married”. In turn, 33.5 percent were married.
Regarding financial security, 24.9 percent of participants reported feeling less safe than others of their age in their country of residence, while 49.6 percent said they felt “equally safe” and 25.5 percent They considered to be "safer".
Inquiry data allowed the study authors to “examine associations between life satisfaction and the main sociodemographic variables at the level of the individual”. Factors such as “Life Satisfaction”, “Financial Security” and “Urbanity” were evaluated, in which participants filled SWLs using a 7 -point response scale, where 1 point represented “totally disagree” and 7 points "I totally agree." Demographic data such as age, education, marital status or race were also evaluated.
With regard to China, the country is divided between “China - Cantonese”, “China - English” and “China - Mandarin”. In the case of “China - Cantonese”, regarding Hong Kong, 409 people responded, with 58 percent of women and only two percent of respondents belonging to a racial minority. All participants live in urban context, while 96 percent ended secondary or higher education. Of respondents, only two percent says it is in a relationship, whether or not marriage.
In the case of “China - Mandarin” 1,231 people participated, 69 percent of which women, in which 95 percent resides in urban areas. 86 percent of respondents have a commitment or relationship.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:20:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese New Year | Tourism and trips boosted consumption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/ano-novo-chines-turismo-e-viagens-impulsionaram-consumo/</link><description>Arrived to the end of Chinese New Year's holidays, official numbers do not lie: China has crossed an intense consumption period, especially related to travel and tourism. Between January 28 and this Tuesday, some destinations in the country broke records of visitors
 
It is at the beginning of each year that the economy awaits the one who is one of the high moments for tourism and consumption in China. The Chinese New Year represents not only a moment of family life, but also the opportunity for many Chinese to travel. This year, to celebrate the year of the serpent, millions of people traveled internally and also out of the country between January 28 and Tuesday, and according to Xinhua the numbers are impressive with regard to purchases or number of visitors in some Destinations.
The Altay City Hall, in the Xinjiang Autonomous Region, is referred to as one of the great ski destinations in the country, having received between January 28 and 31 191,900 visitors, a tourist flow that generated 225 million yuan in revenues.
The agency points out that "skiing has definitely became the most popular activity in Altay during the holidays," leading to "a record number of practitioners, more than 10,000, to visit Jiangjunshan's ski resort on February 2". This represented "an increase of 23 percent over the previous year."
The Altay zone is famous for registering between 170 and 180 days of snow per year, and in the mountainous areas the average snow depth reaches between one and two meters.
Another region of China that reached considerable numbers on the Chinese New Year holidays was Yangshuo County in the Autonomous Guangxi Zhuang region, thanks "to unique natural landscapes and rich cultural activities." Between January 28 and 30, this area received about 410,600 tourists, generating tourist revenues of 589 million Yuan.
In turn, Lhasa (in Tibet) also registered an increase in the number of visitors. Between January 28 and Monday, the city received 1.95 million tourists, representing an increase of 20.6 percent over the previous year, and found in tourist revenues almost 1.76 billion Yuan. This is an increase of 14.75 percent compared to the previous year, according to the Lhasa Municipal Culture and Tourism Office.
Positive data from agencies
Also according to Xinhua, the Chinese New Year's numbers also revealed themselves on travel reserve platforms. In the case of Fliggy, one of the main online agencies, "an increase in reserves, especially for cities such as Shanghai, Beijing and Guangzhou" was recorded. On the other hand, "international travel orders have increased significantly, with international cruise reserves increasing more than six times compared to the previous year."
Regarding air traffic, Shanghai Airport Group reported that passenger traffic on Sunday has reached a new historic record of 404,000 people, with Pudong Airport in Shanghai, to record 259,000 passengers and Hongqiao Airport 145,000 passengers.
There was also a “reinforced coordination of the services of metro, buses and taxis to ensure transport without problems” with the arrival of the end of the holidays, said the group.
On Monday, China State Railway Group Co., Ltd. recorded “a historic milestone” as they were transported on all railways a total of 16.45 million people. This is the “largest passenger traffic in a single day in the history of the Spring Festival Race”.
Only this Tuesday, the last day of the holidays, will have traveled 16.9 million passengers, a number that highlights “further the peak of travel, since hundreds of millions of people returned to their destinations after family meetings” .
Comes and Babies
As far as tourism is concerned, it was found “a growing number of people who sought to know the heritage of China, motivated by the registration of the Spring Festival in the representative list of UNESCO's Immaterial Cultural Heritage, in December 2024”, indicates the state agency.
Data from the Ministry of Commerce show that sales in major retail and restoration companies throughout China, during the first four days of holidays, increased 5.4 percent compared to the same period last year.
There was an increase in consumption of imported food and drinks, such as lobsters, beer and wine. "Due to increased demand during the Spring Festival, our company's imports increased almost 50 percent last month," said Yang Xinyu, who represents a company in the Guangzhou -based international supply chain.
Since January that the customs authorities of Guangzhou Baiyun International Airport have enlarged the importation of food products such as lobsters and crabs, 31.8 percent compared to 2024, translated the total of 14.3 million Yuan.
Many online shopping
And if the Chinese New Year is synonymous with family reunion, the holidays were once again a time for online shopping. Meituan, one of the country's leading electronic service platforms, has recorded an “impressive increase” of 300 percent over the previous year in online reserves for Lunar New Year's Eve.
Note that "group orders for packages with the theme" intangible cultural heritage "have increased more than 12 times since January, year after year, reflecting the growing interest of consumers in cultural experiences."
Sun Jiashan, an associate researcher at the Central Academy of Culture and Tourism Administration, said, according to Xinhua, a change in consumer behavior, especially by young people and families. "Young families are increasingly becoming the driving force of consumption, with a tendency for diverse, high quality and culturally rich experiences," he said.
Meituan Travel data corroborate the analyst's observation that young people increasingly choose to celebrate the Spring Festival in smaller cities, plunging into intangible cultural heritage and historical landmarks.
The increase in tourism and cultural consumption, from equity experiences to successful films, indicate a growing demand for traditional and contemporary cultural activities. "This trend has also led to increased demand for cultural and tourist products and services, giving rise to the introduction of new models and business formats that adapt better to contemporary cultural consumption standards," Sun said, highlighting the potential of the Chinese consumer market and the internal driving forces of the economy.
But not only shopping was made this Chinese New Year, as "the country's film industry proved to be one of the biggest winners during the spring festival's consumer wave." Between January 29 and February 3, the ticket daily revenues exceeded billion yuan for six consecutive days, raising the ticket offices of this year's Spring Festival to 8.02 billion yuans,
According to China's movie administration data, China's total box office on this year's holidays, including real-time pre-sale, exceeded ten billion Yuan.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Study | Academics highlight Christmas “egocentric” side as opposed to the lunar year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/03/estudo-academicos-destacam-lado-egocentrico-do-natal-em-oposicao-ao-ano-lunar/</link><description>A study of three Chinese academics states that while the Chinese New Year has a smaller smaller caress and "is clearly representative of contemporary Chinese society," "Christmas in the West is egocentric, exalts individuality and shows more interactivity." However, the work, published in a magazine of the State University of Bahia, points to the greater convergence of cultural characteristics
 
Chinese New Year and New Year: How are, what do they represent for the West and the East, and what are the points of convergence? It is to these questions that the study “Comparisons of cultures between Chinese New Year and Western Christmas” by Zhen Zhao, Yin Xuelu and Qiao Jianzhen intends to answer. Academic work was recently published in the magazine “Points of Interrogation - Journal of Cultural Criticism”, from the State University of Bahia, Brazil.
The authors highlight, in general terms, that "Christmas in the West is egocentric, exalts individuality and shows greater interactivity", namely with the "participation of the crowd" and demonstration of "passionate carnival emotions of people".
On the other hand, the Chinese New Year “is a national festival, clearly representative of contemporary Chinese society”. In general terms, this kind of celebrations emerges described as “a special sociocultural meaning that intersperses the daily routines”, “a concentrated exhibition of people's colorful life” as well as “a summary and extension of politics, economics, culture and religion from various regions, ethnic groups and countries. ”
They also describe the authors that the Chinese New Year, who can also be called the Lunar New Year or Spring Festival, has roots “in a small peasant economy and is often based on Confucianism, with a mix of Buddhist and Taoist culture”, being linked to "feudal religious rituals."
In turn, Christmas is presented as a larger religious component, being "rooted in Western Christian culture and embodies the values ​​of freedom and equality, original sin and individualism everywhere."
Inevitable interconnections
However, the study describes as inevitable the future exchange of cultural demonstrations at these times of the year: in the case of Christmas, in December; In the case of the Chinese New Year, during the months of January and February of each year, depending on the calendar.
"The future exchange of Chinese and Western cultures, including the festival's culture, is an inevitable part of social and historical development," is described, as well as "an evolutionary process of complementarity between Chinese and Western cultures."
Thus, the authors say, the contact points should be discovered by both cultures “from the differences between the Chinese New Year and Christmas, so that they can be promoted” and so that there is a greater preservation of “their national cultures. ”.
The authors say they note "the acceleration of cultural exchange between the East and West" in this field, as "Chinese celebrate Western festivals and foreigners celebrate Chinese festivals."
"In the age of globalization, and due to the development and deepening of economy and culture, traditional Chinese and Western parties have been gradually accepted by both peoples in mutual tolerance," reads.
Differentiating points
The three authors of the study recall that in China, the most traditional festivals have a connection with agriculture, with traditional customs based on food and drink. "The main reason for this is the pursuit of the Chinese people in going to be oriented to a long and healthy life." Meanwhile, "Western traditional festivals have mainly origin in religion and related events," therefore "strong religious connotations."
It is added that, in the West, “traditional vacation customs are based mainly on the subject of fun”, the main reason for “the pursuit of western ones in life to have the objective of health and happiness”.
In comparative terms, "both Chinese New Year and Christmas is a family reunion time and a wonderful time for people to look back and also to the future," although "with different connotations in Chinese and Western cultures."
One of the differences pointed out in the study is the way the days before these dates are celebrated. “The year's passage [in the Chinese New Year] is the time when people try to go home to their loved ones, no matter where they are. New Year's dinner is the highlight, also known as the reunion dinner, being the most important meal of the year. ”
One of the rituals goes through the sunset, “families start to light the rockets”, starting to prepare meals with this environment. “Although New Year's dinner dishes range from place to place, each dish has a certain symbolic meaning. Chinese like to use harmonics to attract good luck, and for example, chicken harmonics mean 'auspicious', while "yu" yu harmonics mean "year after year".
“New Year's Eve is a custom of the Chinese people Han. After eating the New Year's meal, people gather in family to wait for the coming of the new year at midnight, ”the authors point out, also describing that“ in many parts of China on New Year's night, People prepare sumptuous offerings, light incense and candles, pour wine and burn paper money, paying tribute to their family ancestors to express nostalgia for them ”, as well as waiting for blessings“ for the sons and grandchildren of the sky, inspiring the descendants to work harder and live up to the desires of their ancestors. ”
In the case of Christmas, celebrated on December 25, the day before is marked by a family dinner that also has traditional dishes and sweets, such as the king cake, cod or roast turkey. “Unlike New Year's Chinese vigil, Westerners celebrate Christmas as a unique fantasy party on Christmas Eve who extends throughout the night. At the party there is no rigorous clothing code, just being natural and informal, climbing to say 'Hello' and sending sincere wishes [of good holidays], ”is mentioned.
Another differentiating point pointed out is the offers. If the Chinese New Year is usual the offer of money in the “Lai Si” envelopes, the western Christmas are present between family and friends.
The distribution of money in the Chinese New Year has several connotations, and there is a kind of money to the elders, serving “to wish them a long life”; While there is later the money given from the elders to the youngest, representing a care transmission from the most seniors.
In turn, “the first legends about Christmas gifts refer to the birth of Jesus,” with the offerings of the wise men. “It is currently customary to give gifts between family and friends at Christmas,” is mentioned, and there is also the idea that it is Santa to distribute the gifts. “Sometimes people pretend to be Santa Claus to give gifts to children in order to add the festive spirit,” he says.
Another big difference pointed out by the study is that in the West, Christmas does not have the same connotation as ancestors. “In the West people do not worship their ancestors, and people go to church to celebrate the birth of Jesus. People are not limited to being in family meetings, but inviting [others] in a warm way to their homes, and is not considered rude partying together. During the holidays many people participate in community activities to help the poor and give gifts, reflecting the idea of ​​seeking equality. ”
Similarity
According to the study, the two celebrations have as its common point to serve to "maintain social stability." “In ancient China agricultural production was strongly influenced by the climate. Poor workers who belonged to the lower classes often had to work all year round, which inevitably led to dissatisfaction with the reality of the situation. ” In this sense, the arrival of the Chinese New Year is “a good time to release emotions”, decorating the house and lighting rockets in the creation “the hope that the next year will be good, with good harvests and better days”.
With regard to Christmas, it is described that people “go to church worship [the saints], sing Christmas songs and pray to God, hoping that they will help them get out of difficulties when they are in trouble or when they are sick and face death . They expect God to forgive them for the sins so that they can ascend to heaven after death, ”there is a parallel with the“ liberation of emotions ”above.
In addition, both celebrations constitute forms of culture transmission, according to the authors of the study. “New Year's culture is an accumulation of traditional Chinese culture, being the crystallization of the work and wisdom of the Chinese people, expressing the aspirations of the hardworking people who long for good things.” In addition, these celebrations “carry and convey traditional culture in a subtle manner”, namely with paintings and other decorations of houses, or events such as Dragon and Lion dances or handwriting sessions.
“Through these activities the extremely valuable cultural heritage is transmitted to younger generations,” is referred to. In turn, at Christmas there are the decorations of the time, with the tree, the lights or cribs, in green, red colors and other bright tones.
“People who have been busy working year returns to revive the family heat. People go to the church to celebrate the birth of Jesus, which is a regular event and an inheritance of religious culture. It has become customary to send a Christmas card to friends and family, and all these customs carry profound cultural connotations that are transmitted. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-03 01:40:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | East Asia with low work satisfaction and demotivation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/24/trabalho-asia-oriental-com-baixa-satisfacao-laboral-e-desmotivacao/</link><description>The World Gallup International Association's World Association Report has concluded that in countries and regions of East Asia, such as China, Taiwan or Hong Kong, most workers are looking for a new job. In Hong Kong, only six percent of respondents are committed to their jobs
 
Realizing how workers from around the world feel, and regarding their employment, it is the objective of the Gallup International Association report, entitled “State of the Global Workplace 2024”. If in the worldwide and regional scene, East Asia does well in some indicators, the scenario is not favorable with regard to the commitment or commitment that workers have for the company they are linked to or the functions they perform.
Inside East Asia includes countries and regions such as China, Hong Kong, Japan, Mongolia, South Korea and Taiwan. This area of ​​the globe has “the lowest percentage, at regional level, of employees who feel daily sadness”, but has “the third highest, regional percentage of employees who say they are looking, and actively, of a new job. ” In addition, East Asia has “the third lower percentage at regional level of committed employees” with the work they have (18 percent, which still represents a rise of 1 percent compared to the corresponding period between 2022 and 2023) .
On the contrary, 67 percent of respondents are not, at all, committed or committed to work, plus five percent compared to the same period. In addition, 14 percent says it is totally uncompromising with the company where they work, minus six percent.
As for negative emotions lived daily, and more often, the stress factor leads, with 46 percent response, six percent from the period between 2022 and 2023. percent answers, which did not generate any answers in the last investigation. “Sadness” was a feeling revealed by 12 percent of respondents, 1 more percent compared to the previous inquiry, and “loneliness”, which also has direct entry into this list of less good feelings lived at work, 18 percent.
If dissatisfaction with work is demonstrated in the preceding paragraphs, certainties climb from tone in the category “work environment - good height to find a job”, with 51 percent to respond affirmatively, 11 percent of answers to the previous inquiry . In addition, the category “intention to leave - looking actively for a new work” was chosen for 54 percent of respondents, two percent less from 2022 to 2023.
In the “Life Assessment” category, those who claim to have a prosperous life are 32 percent, seven percent, in contrast to the 62 percent of respondents who claim to be suffering some kind of difficulties, another seven percent in relation to to the last inquiry. The “suffering” category related to the job was chosen for six percent of participants in the inquiry, a direct entry in this study.
Sadness below
For the study of Gallup, 40,428 people were interviewed in 41 countries, and the sample per country contains about 1,000 men and women. The margin of error of the survey “is between +3-5 percent with a confidence level of 95 percent”, is referred to.
The study also compares the data recorded by eastern Asia workers with the other countries. And once again is the lack of commitment and the feeling of “dressing the nightgown” that persists in many companies. In worldwide terms, 62 percent of the answers point to the absence of commitment, when in East Asia this percentage over 67 percent.
Regarding the “life evaluation”, if at the world level 58 percent of respondents says it is having difficulties, the percentage of East Asia is 62 percent. However, suffering meaning is only six percent of the answers, while in the world the bar is eight percent. Regarding this factor, the low percentage of the feeling of “daily sadness”, with 12 percent answers, when the world level rises to the 22 percent.
The feeling of stress is also higher, with 46 percent answers, when at global level is 41 percent.
China: anger and difficulties
Looking at the criteria in each country, 19 percent of China workers said they were committed to work, two more percent annually, while in Hong Kong only six percent of people are committed and who like what they do, the which is a break of one percent.
In the “life assessment”, 36 percent of China workers say they are facing difficulties, plus 1 percent, while in Taiwan 41 percent says they face less good times, representing a direct entry into the classification, with no previous score to compare. In the case of Hong Kong, 17 percent of respondents assume to cross difficulties, plus 1 percent compared to the previous inquiry.
As for the feeling of “daily stress”, China rises first in the ranking with 53 percent answers, still 2 percent in annual terms, with Hong Kong following her footsteps, with 49 percent answers . Japan is third with 41 percent people to feel stress daily.
In response to the question if it felt angry the day before, China leads again with 18 percent answers, despite the annual breakdown of 2 percent; Following South Korea, with 17 percent affirmative answers, and then Hong Kong with 16 percent. In China only 12 percent of workers said they felt sadness, thus putting the country in third place. In relation to Hong Kong there were 11 percent affirmative responses in this domain.
Jon Clufton, CEO of Gallup, leaves an alert about increasing mental health problems worldwide, especially related to the work environment and the form of relationship in the business environment. About 20 percent of workers from around the world “experience daily loneliness”, and this feeling “is greater among total teleworking workers”.
“In this year's report, 41 percent of workers claim to feel 'very stress'. However, stress varies significantly depending on how organizations are managed. Those who work in companies with bad management practices (actively unmotivated) have almost 60 percent more likely to be stressed than people who work in environments with good management practices (committed). In fact, the 'very stress' experience is referred to about 30 percent more often by employees who work under mismanagement than by the unemployed, ”said Gallup CEO.
For the official, "leaders know that stress at the workplace is a problem-they saw the data, heard colleagues and felt themselves themselves." “A quarter of the leaders are frequently exhausted or always, and two thirds feel it at least a few times. Many are trying to solve the problem, but often ineffective, ”he concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-01-24 01:41:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Death | Died Rocha Vieira at 85</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/23/obito-morreu-rocha-vieira-aos-85-anos/</link><description>Vasco Rocha Vieira, the last Portuguese governor of Macau, died yesterday at the age of 85. The general had been sick for a long time. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa recalled him as “one of the most illustrious officers” of the army, but to Macau, Rocha Vieira is for history as the great worker of the measures decided in the 1987 joint statement
 
It has long been sick, even failing some recent events in Lisbon about Macau and the transition. Vasco Rocha Vieira, General, former Chief of Staff of the Army, and the last Portuguese governor of Macau, died yesterday morning at 85 years old.
Born on August 16, 1939, he held the position of Governor of Macao between 1991 and 1999, when the transfer of the territory to China was processed. However, Rocha Vieira already had a connection to Macau, as he was in the territory after April 25. In addition, he was also Minister of the Republic of the Azores between 1986 and 1991.
One of the first personalities to react to his death in Portugal was the President of the Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, who expressed, in a official note, the “deep regret” for the death of Vasco Rocha Vieira, recalling him as “one of the more distinguished army officials and praising its “marked patriotism”.
In a note published on the official website of the Presidency of the Republic on the Internet, the head of state recalls Rocha Vieira as "one of the most illustrious officers of the Portuguese army in the transition to democracy and in the first decades of his statement." “Always closely linked to commands, it has also performed political functions such as Minister of the Republic for the Autonomous Region of the Azores,” is remembered in the note.
Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa also points out that Rocha Vieira was “very close to President António Ramalho Eanes”, having been “designated chancellor of the old military orders”.
“The symbolism of the moment of transferring the Portuguese administration to the Chinese will remain in the memory of many Portuguese as an example of meaning, meaning of the public cause and marked patriotism,” reads the note of regret.
The President of the Republic, who claims to have followed “closely the last months” of Rocha Vieira's life, “presents to his family, and, much in particular, to his widow and children, the testimony of gratitude of Portugal, with very longing friendship".
In his biography, entitled “To all the ports I arrived”, the moment Mário Soares, then President of the Republic, said to Rocha Vieira: “I need yourself. Go to Macao and see if it puts that in order ”, in reference to the case of Macau fax, related to the construction of Macao International Airport, which so many headaches gave its predecessor, Carlos Watermelon, also deceased.
The general will then replied that nothing demanded to go to Macau. “I didn't ask you anything, nor did I put it in conditions. I went to Macau with the same spirit with which I went to the Azores. It was not a political position inherent in a career. It was, in fact, a mission, ”he describes.
Then it was Rocha Vieira and his team to achieve all objectives and ideal for the future of Macao present in the joint statement that had been signed between Portugal and China in 1987. The government led by Rocha Vieira saw the airport was born, built The entire bilingual legislative framework that is still in place today and raised the Macao Cultural Center, inaugurated by Jorge Sampaio on March 19, 1999, among many other initiatives, including in the area of ​​urbanism.
A "GREAT FRIEND"
Rocha Vieira came, by the way, to make the place available to the Macau Executive when Jorge Sampaio was elected President of the Republic, at the turn from 1995 to 1996. “When I went to Macau I didn't know how things were going to run and how long I was going There stayed there, ”he recalled in his biography. However, and despite Sampaio's initial hesitation in change, the truth is that Rocha Vieira turned out to be, because “her replacement would affect the regular sequence of the process” at a time when “the passage was already in sight was already in sight From territory administration to China, ”it is described in“ all the ports I arrived ”.
Speaking to RTP, Chito Rodrigues, a general governor of Macao in office, left words of regret for the death of the one who was a friend.
“I remember him as a great friend and honorary partner of the Combatants League. He has always related to us and is our reference. We knew it was bad and we were not, in a way, surprised [with the news of death], but it is always an unpleasant surprise. ”
Chito Rodrigues recalls him in the exercise of his duties in Macau as someone who contributed "so that Macao was a quiet place for decolonization to be done in a" exemplary "way." “I was with him at the opening of the airport and had close relations with him as governor. It was someone who replaced his predecessors successfully and humble, replacing the tradition of military governors in Macao, ”he added.
In Fernando Lima and Eduardo Cintra Torres's book “Macao Between Two Worlds”, the former Hong Kong governor, Chris Patten, recalled Rocha Vieira as “a brave and judicious man, with enormous integrity and an excellent server of his country”. "I think Portugal was very lucky to have such a good man as the last governor, such a difficult place," he said.
The controversy
The name of Rocha Vieira was, however, wrapped in some controversies, namely with the creation of the Jorge Álvares Foundation and the Oriente Foundation, especially regarding the funds allocated to these two entities. "The bulk of public opinion of the territory and the authorities of Beijing contested the legitimacy of a contract under which an entity based in Lisbon was fueled with resources generated in Macao," reads the biography of Rocha Vieira. This only intended the Foundation to “play a useful role for Macao, and the controversy has been diluted over time.
On social networks, the journalist and former director of Macau today, João Severino said “mourn a lot” the disappearance of Rocha Vieira. “General Vasco Rocha Vieira left us after several weeks hospitalized at the hospital. Macao's last governor was a good man for many people and discriminatory for many. In any case his military career was exemplary and left marks in the administration of Macao. I kept with the illustrious governor some controversial moments, always within the greatest cordiality and consideration by the maximum representative of my country in Macau. I present to your wife Dr. Leonor and his children my condolences and rest in peace, ”he wrote.
An entity that reacted to the disappearance of Rocha Vieira was the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry (CCILC), which on social networks issued a note of regret about the death of the 138th Portuguese Governor of Macao and presided at the CCILC Strategic Council.
“General Rocha Vieira played a striking and exemplary role throughout his life, standing out for his commitment to service to the nation, dedication to relations between Portugal and China, and the historical role in closing the administration cycle Portuguese in Macau. ”
The same note also states that "in the leadership of the CCILC Strategic Council, his strategic vision, wisdom and human values ​​have always been a source of inspiration for the entire direction and executive team."
Also the Lisbon City Council officially reacted to its disappearance. “Rocha Vieira dedicated her life to the defense of the national interest, notably serving Portugal as the army's head of the army and as the last governor of Macao. Vision statesman assured a peaceful transfer from Macao sovereignty to China. Man of courage, contributed to the consolidation of the democratic process, being a fundamental piece of November 25, 1975. It was an honor to count on his testimony in the first evocation ceremony of November 25 in the Paços do County in 2023. ”
Goodbye to Macau
The images of Rocha Vieira to hold the Portuguese flag to her chest are celebrated on December 19, 1999, with a visibly thrilled face, as well as goodbye to the “mission” he agreed to perform in Macao.
After his role as governor, Rocha Vieira was maintaining narrow ties with the territory, and the last time he was in Macau was in 2023, to receive the distinction of Honoris Causal Doctorate from the Macao University of Science and Technology.
Then he stressed that the "good historical relationships" with China are "a trump card for Portugal" and that today the country is "a superpower in affirmation". The general said that “another great asset” for Portugal is interest in China in the Portuguese language, underlining the growing number of Chinese universities that teach Portuguese. At the end of 2020, the coordinator of the Portuguese Language Pedagogical and Scientific Center of the Macao Polytechnic University, Gaspar Zhang Yunfeng, said there were about 50 higher education institutions with Portuguese courses in mainland China.
“China is interested in that Portuguese develops (…) also to be able to have, through Portugal, a narrower relationship with Portuguese -speaking countries,” said Rocha Vieira.
In a last interview with Lusa agency in 2019, Rocha Vieira recalled the times in Macau and her vicissitudes, especially regarding the transition process.
“I had more problems with the Portuguese part than with the Chinese part (…) often, for lack of perception. Usually people are far away in Lisbon - this is a historical thing, which is not just now - and think they know the solutions better than those in Macao, ”he said.
Rocha Vieira assured that when it was necessary to define “the course, the fundamental objectives of Macao policies, were discussed by the Macao government in Lisbon, with whom they should be discussed, with the President of the Republic and the Prime Minister”, there is “always” about this “a great understanding on the part of the Portuguese sovereignty organs and a great proof of confidence in those in the territory”.</description><pubDate>2025-01-23 00:26:24</pubDate></item><item><title>CPCPS | Patronato Refusa Rise from Minimum Wage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/cpcps-patronato-recusa-subida-do-salario-minimo/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs and representatives of employers in the Permanent Social Concertation Council remove the hypothesis of increasing the minimum wage or reviewing the limits of indemnities for occupational accidents and occupational diseases this year.
The position was taken after this year's first meeting of the Permanent Council for Social Concertation, which took place on Tuesday, while the representatives of the work part promised to support government decisions.
Legally, the amount of salary and the limits of compensation for occupational accidents and occupational diseases should be reviewed in annual or biannual periods. However, Wong Chi Hong, director of DSAL, explained that the term review means that an assessment is made, which may conclude that the best option is not to move the values ​​in force.
“We will review in our work, because there has to be a review every two years. But doing a review does not mean that there has to be an increase, what we do is a data collection, to make a report and then be able to send to the Permanent Social Concertation Council, ”said Wong Chi Hong, quoted by the Macau channel.

Frozen year
In turn, Vong Kok Seng, leader of the Macao Commercial Association, believes that the obligation to revise the minimum salary and limits must be changed. “The economic and social situation is basically identical. Therefore, I ask if it is necessary to review these amounts annually… We question if there is a review or change of legislation, if the annual revision period should not be relaxed, ”said Vong.
In turn, Fong Ka Fai, representative of the workplace, indicated that during the meeting were requested increases of maternity leave, paternity and revision of the boundaries. However, it admits that there was no response, and that ultimately will support the government's choice. "There were not many answers, but of course, as workers we will support the government and make our efforts to promote the economy of Macau, because we had the pandemic, and after the pandemic it takes an effort from everyone," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:50:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Work | Number of non-resident workers rose almost 5,900</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/trabalho-numero-de-trabalhadores-nao-residentes-subiu-quase-5-900/</link><description>At the end of December more than 182,500,000 non-resident workers were registered in the territory, which represents an increase of almost 5,900 last year
 
Macao employed more than 182,500,000 non-resident workers at the end of December, an increase of almost 5,900 during the year 2024. According to data from the Public Security Police (CPSP), released by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSal ), this number represents an increase of almost 30,700 since the end of the 'Zero Covid' policy in January 2023.
This month, the labor from outside Macao, including from the interior of China, had fallen to less than 152,000, the lowest number since April 2014.
Since the maximum peak of 196,538, hit in late 2019, at the beginning of the pandemic, and until January 2023, the city lost almost 45,000 non-resident workers, which corresponded to 11.3 percent of the active population.
The hotel and restoration sector was the one that hired the most in 2024, earning 4,561 non-resident workers, followed by domestic employees (another 1,678) and cultural and recreational activities, including casinos (plus 1,418), according to data released on Monday.
The hotel and restoration area had been precisely the most affected by loss of labor during the pandemic, having faced more than 17,600 non-resident employees since December 2019.
Low unemployment rate
Macao welcomed 34.9 million visitors last year 23.8 percent than the previous year, and the hotels received more than 14.4 million guests in 2024, establishing a new historical record.
The economic crisis created by the pandemic led the unemployment rate to reach 4 percent in the third quarter of 2022, the highest since 2006. But, despite the increase in the number of non-resident workers, the unemployment rate has been seven for Months in a row at 1.7 percent, equaling the historical minimum reached before the start of the pandemic.
Macao's economy grew 11.5 percent in the first three quarters of 2024, compared to the same period of the previous year, thanks to the resumption of the game, according to official data. Gross Domestic Product (GDP) represented 86.3 percent of the amount recorded in the same period of 2019, before the start of the pandemic.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:47:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Personal Data | Yang Chongwei keeps leadership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/dados-pessoais-yang-chongwei-mantem-lideranca/</link><description>Yang Chongwei's appointment as director of the Directorate of Personal Data Protection Services (DSPDP) was renewed by Sam Hou Fai for a period of one year, until the end of January 2026.
The information is contained in an order published yesterday in the official bulletin. According to the document, the decision took into account the fact that Yang "has appropriate experience and professional ability to perform their duties." Yang Chongwei has been in office since 2017, when the service management was just a cabinet.
Yang Chongweei joined the public administration in 1999, having held the positions of higher technician at the Institute of Social Action (IAS); IAS Family Action Office Coordinator; Superior technician, functional chief and assistant coordinator of the cabinet for personal data protection. He is a degree in Social Sciences (Public Administration) from the University of Macao, has a master's degree in Social Work from the University of Hong Kong and is a doctoral student in International Relations from the Macao University of Science and Technology.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:40:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Encounter | Sam Hou Fai received table</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/encontro-sam-hou-fai-recebeu-mesa-da-al/</link><description>Executive Chief Sam Hou Fai received at the Government headquarters the President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), Kou Hoi In, and the other members of the AL, the deputies Chui Sai Cheong, vice president, Ho Lon Sang, First secretary, and Si Ka Lon, according to secretary.
According to the official version of the meeting, the two parts “exchanged impressions of mutual support between the executive and legislative bodies” and addressed the “creation of a more effective communication mechanism”.
In addition, there was an agreement for the creation of a “legislative coordination between the executive and legislative bodies”, whose molds were not elaborated. At the meeting were also attended by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong Weng Chon, the chief executive's chief of staff Chan Kak, the chief executive's office advisor Chen Licheng.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:38:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Buses | Almost the whole fleet powered by electricity</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/autocarros-quase-toda-a-frota-movida-a-electricidade/</link><description>In late January, more than 92 percent of public buses were moved to “new energies”, while more than 86 percent of taxis are electric hybrid vehicles. Deputy Lo Choi in suggests subsidies to renew fleets of Takeaway companies with electric scooters
 
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) yesterday indicated that at the end of last January the Transmac and TCM fleets were composed of over 92 percent buses powered by new energies. The percentage had already been advanced by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), but was updated yesterday with the increase of nearly 30 additional electric buses for a total of 929 buses.
The proportion fulfills the goals set by the 2021-2025 environmental protection planning, which was significantly three years ago set the goal of over 90 percent of the fleet of buses in the territory being "moved with new energies" by 2025. According to Panorama Traced in Environmental Protection Planning 2021-2025, the government indicated that by 2020 only 8 percent buses in the territory were moved with new energies.
The update was made on the Macau Forum Program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, where it was also revealed that only about 3 percent of public buses do not fulfill the environmental protection standards provided for in the Euro 4 standard, which came into force in 2005.
Moving silence
Regarding taxi fleets, they operate in Macau 210 “purely electric” vehicles, which represents a proportion of almost 12 percent of all taxis, while the hybrid taxis is 1,526, about 86.2 percent.
DSPA also stated that it continues to follow the evolution of the transport sector and promote the use of newer new energy buses through the two bus companies and encourage the taxis sector to use more electric vehicles or new energy vehicles.
However, Deputy Lo Choi In would like to see the widening of environmental use of environmental energies to all transport, including motorcycles of Take-Away companies and other commercial vehicles. "The government can subsidize Take-Away distributors to promote the use of electrical motorcycles," the deputy told the public broadcaster's microphones.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:32:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lunar New Year | Cheung Kin Chung praises tourism performance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/ano-novo-lunar-cheung-kin-chung-elogia-desempenho-do-turismo/</link><description>The president of the Board of the Macao Tourism Agencies Association and the Macao Hoteleiros Association, Cheung Kin Chung, considered that local tourism performed “good” during the days of the Lunar New Year.
In statements cited by the newspaper or Mun, the appointed deputy justified the good performance of the sector with the increase in the number of excursions to visit the territory and the occupancy rate of the hotel rooms above 90 percent.
The deputy's statements arise in a context in which the average visitors along the holidays of the Lunar New Year is being below the expectations of the Tourism Services Directorate. In late January, Helena de Senna Fernandes had predicted a daily average of 185,000 tourists during the days of the Lunar New Year. By the end of the seventh day of the festivities had entered Macau 1,172,355 people, which represented a daily average of 167.5 thousand tourists.
As part of the positive balance of tourism performance, the deputy and entrepreneur indicated that prices were only slightly more expensive than last year, but told that one cannot speak of excessive prices, taking into account the offer of hotels. At the same time, he pointed out that there were no problems or complaints about the services provided.
Cheung Kin Chung also stated, according to the newspaper or Mun, that the "quality" of tourists has increased because they visit more cultural, historical places and experience different types of food.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:02:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Sport | Au Kam San Critica Estoril Pool Closing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/desporto-au-kam-san-critica-encerramento-da-piscina-estoril/</link><description>Former deputy Au Kam San criticized the closing of the Estoril pool, due to the construction works of the new central library. The criticism was published in an online comment.
With a closing time that can range from three to five years, depending on the completion of the project, Au considered that the administration must have opted for a different solution that kept the facilities open. The former deputy also argued that it was incomprehensible that the only pool in the most central area of ​​the territory was closed over such a long period.
On the other hand, it also left the possibility that the closing decision was avoided if the facilities were explored by a private individual, rather than being managed by the Sports Institute. “Let's imagine that it was a trader who explored the pool and that next to it a building was built. Had this government ever suggested to this merchant the suspension of the operation of the pool? How would the merchant answer? ”He asked.
Au Kam San opined that closing was not the only solution available and that the pool could be working as long as safety measures were taken.
The former deputy also stated that the decision results from the development of a bureaucratic culture in the administration to make the slightest effort to avoid taking responsibility if errors occur. “The most important thing is not to take responsibility, no matter what people have to stop swimming or the facilities are abandoned. Closing should only have been weighted as a last resort solution, ”reads the publication.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 00:59:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao in the year of the serpent and mass tourism</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/macau-no-ano-da-serpente-e-o-turismo-de-massas/</link><description>“Today's Tourist in the Longer Pays Attention to Consolidated Elements - Heritage, Cultural, etc. - Which have traditionally benated in what has come to be called the tourist bubble, but flex from it in search of what he or she considers authentic. ”
Constructing The Tourist Bubble
Dennis R. Judd
Macau, a region known for its rich mix of Portuguese and Chinese cultures, has become a global tourist attraction point, especially in recent decades. Macao has a complex history influenced by various cultural exchanges. Originally a fishing village became a Portuguese colony in the sixteenth century, establishing commercial routes that connected Asia to Europe. Over time, Macau began to serve as a gateway to western traders looking for Asian products. The transfer of sovereignty to China in 1999 marked a new era, with the transition from colonial management to special administrative status under Chinese governance.
In the early 2000s, Macau learned of a significant development of his tourist infrastructure due to economic policies favorable to liberalization. The government encouraged foreign investments, which led to an increase in infrastructure for casinos and luxury hotels. This development has significantly diversified the economy, creating employment and stimulating rapid urbanization. As a result, Macao emerged as a reference destination not only for the game, but also to leisure and entertainment, attracting millions of tourists every year.
The year of the serpent, which occurs from twelve to twelve years and was found on February 10, 2013, and repeats this year can symbolize significant transformation and growth. During this period, Macao will record a tribute of tourists, mainly from mainland China, contributing to the local economy. The mass tourism model provided economic benefits, including increased GDP and job opportunities. However, the strong dependence on tourism, especially the game, puts risks to the economic sustainability of Macau. As the tourism industry grows, concerns are beginning to emerge as to potential long -term economic repercussions. The growth of the tourism sector leads to an increase in cost of living, which can create friction between residents and visitors. Inflation in housing and essential services affects local communities, which face the threat of being marginalized in their own territory.
Macau had long been to have implemented an urban planning on tourist activity and gastronomic script in the city's historic center with the closing of São João's sidewalk and Rua de S. Domingos from the corner with Travessa do Bispo to Rua de Pedro Nolasco da Silva or Rua do Campo and rehabilitating Travessa da Sé that offers visitors and residents a degrading environment with establishments that sell Chinese fast food food without any food quality control and hygiene with people sharing in banks and Squakes on the street the food containers, as well as the implementation of a plan of all since tours where bacteria and viruses proliferate
Rua da Palha is invaded by piles from establishments that sell all kinds of Fast Food Chinese where less and less artisanal almond biscuits predominate and the famous Nata Pastels (which invaded Macao and Asia and which the Wikipedia encyclopedia mention and we played https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/egg_tart#cite_Note-7 “In 1989, British Pharmacist Andrew Stow and Hist Margaret Wong Opened Lord Stow's Bakery In Colaane .
[7] This variation is a Portuguese Tart (葡撻; poùh tāat).
[8] [9] In 1999, Wong Sold the Recipe to KFC, Which Then introduced the macau-star pastel by Nata to other parts of Asia, including Singapore and Taiwan.
[3] [10] ” - There must be a reflection on public consultation to classify the Pastel de Nata as part of Macao's intangible cultural heritage by the Cultural Institute. In 2011, the Belém Pastel in North Portugal known as Pastel de Nata was elected one of the 7 Wonders of the Gastronomy of Portugal, so the Portuguese Consulate General was also pronouncing this icon of Portuguese cuisine), for pharmacies, etc. (where the lace of the few available stores are at millionaire prices and that there is little or nothing in the revenues of stores that are compatible with sales and hence the constant opening and closing dance of establishments.
Does this market law of wild and unmistralled capitalism interest Macao and that Milton Friedman so well describes in “Free to Choose” about Hong Kong? Even in the absence of established price regime, it is nonetheless speculation and lead to the creation of real estate bubbles that we all know the consequences.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:36:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Refreshing vulvar and shame</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/refrescantes-vulvares-e-a-vergonha/</link><description>Recently, a celebrity in Portugal has launched a product that has given to talk, generated numerous posts and even made some paint. It is an intimate bruma, suggestively called Pipy, available by 29.90 euros. The goal? Refresh and somehow empower women to feel good with their bodies.
I always suspect the media of certain products. This was undoubtedly created "to ask them." The usual criticism followed: feminists with the customs of the custom-many of which I subscribe to soul and heart-supported by health professionals. These are recurring discourses, because reality persists: there is a whole industry that thrives at the expense of female insecurity. Society insists on generating a feeling of dedequation in relation to normal body processes. If you want to refresh your vulva, wash it with water-the effect will probably be the same.
In addition, products like this, created from an artificial need, can bring more problems than solutions. The vagina has a sophisticated cleaning system and doesn't need new formulas to “clean yourself better”. Interfering with this balance can cause pH imbalances, making the intimate zone more susceptible to infections such as candidiasis and bacterial vaginosis. And then, yes, smell and discomfort become a clinical problem.
 What bothers me is the discursive dance around these themes. On the one hand, there are those who see the existence of a product as an act of empowerment; On the other, there are those who, tirelessly, try to educate for a healthier relationship with the body. Now one thinks that there is a product is to empower the vulves, while others try to educate for happy vulvas. And we stayed like this. The latter preach for the deaf, and the first preach stupidity.
What is the discursive opportunity of these vaginal refreshing, what pedagogical opportunities are we waste? A sincere conversation about people's badness. Why do people feel the need to buy products to hide the natural smell of their private parts? Although manufactured, insecurity and discomfort are still real, touching a sensitive point of existence: the shame.
Shame is a complex emotional system, based on beliefs that have been blaming the vulves because they are as they are. Also based on millennial discursive traditions. In ancient Greece they explained that men had a less poignant smell than women, and so they needed more delicate perfumes, and women perfumes that best covered their natural aroma.
Dealing with shame is not easy - it requires delicacy. Explain that this is a manufactured shame does not make it disappear by magic. Continuous experiences of understanding are needed so that shame dissolves and becomes a true state of empowerment. Pipy is pseudo-popping because it works like a fast, temporary relief for deeper insecurity. The discussions that we have watched also perpetuate ideological chapels, easy to predict, without great emotional and empathic depth.
This will be only one of many articles written about Pipy, but perhaps the only one with the modest purpose of claiming that shame is being seen and understood. We were taught to be ashamed of the vulva. To unlearn, to achieve real empowerment, we have to look at this shame with affection and understanding. This recognition would be a first step to collective liberation. Only then will we leave the vulves finally at peace.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Australia interdicts social networks to children under 16 (i)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/04/australia-interdita-redes-sociais-a-menores-de-16-anos-i/</link><description>The Australian Senate approved on November 28, 2024 the change to the “Internet Security Law (minimum age for access to social networks), banning children under 16 to use most social networks. The new law does not provide for exceptions for users under 16. Therefore, as soon as changes enter into force, under 16 years should immediately stop using social networks, otherwise they will be infringing the law. This prohibition extends to young people who are allowed by parents to use networks.
The new law also requires social networking companies to take measures to prevent children under 16 from accessing their platforms, and prohibits them to oblige children to present identification documents for age verification. The maximum fine for companies that violate the new law is $ 50 million Australian (approximately RMB $ 250 million or HK $ 235 million). It is expected that the new law be tested by 2025 and fully implemented by 2026.
Although the new law does not specify which companies will be regulated, the Australian press advances that companies like Facebook, Instagram and X will be very affected.
The purpose of the new law is clear. Children can have access to all kinds of scientific and technological knowledge through social networks, allowing them to open horizons and make friends everywhere. However, there are also many disadvantages, such as being easily exposed to misinformation, contacting strangers and endangering. If young people are annoyed and eager for spending too much time on the internet, or even avoiding social life, the consequences will be even more serious. Since children are still developing mentally and physically, any negative effects of the use of the internet should be avoided.
The content of the new law is simple, but from the point of view of its effective functioning, there are many issues that deserve to be discussed.
First, Australia is not the first country to enact legislation in this matter. In Europe, many countries have already restricted children's access to social networks. For example, in France, children under 15 need their parents' consent to create social networks, children under 11 are prohibited from using mobile phones and children under 13 cannot use mobile phones with access to Internet. Norway has established 15 years as the minimum age for young people to use social networks. Below the age of 15, parental consent is necessary.
In Germany and Belgium children's access to social networks is only allowed after 13 years, and in Italy after 14. Germany and Italy also established parental consent, but Belgium not.
In Asia, on January 20, 2025, Indonesia announced that it would follow Australia and would prepare legislation to restrict the use of social networks to children from 13 to 17, while parents of children aged 13 to 15 can control the social networking accounts of children. As mobile phones become more popular, the issue of children's access to the internet and social networks has attracted more and more attention. Probably more countries and regions will legislate in this area.
Secondly, the new law sets the minimum age of 16 to access the internet, which is not the strictest standard. In Florida, the age limit established by the legislation is 14 years. It is not surprising for different countries to establish different ages to allow access to social networks. However, Florida's law restricts the use of social networks to children under 13, having been accused of limiting freedom of expression, which triggered a judicial process. After the new law is implemented in Australia, will there be similar processes to those of Florida ?? This is the risk that the Australian government may have to run after the introduction of the new law.
Next week, we will continue this analysis.

Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the School of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Blog: http://blog.xuite.net/legalpublications/hkblog
Email: LegalpublicationSreaders@yahoo.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 01:15:46</pubDate></item><item><title>It was just the first</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/03/foi-so-o-primeiro/</link><description>Those who decide to be a politician have to be compensated that they have to be serious, competent, incorruptible and serve the people with honesty. Not complying with this desiderate becomes just another person who does not comply with what he swore in a possession ceremony. It becomes a disregarded and fragile citizen before the Portuguese to continue to perform his role as minister, secretary of state, deputy or mayor.
Last week, after several “cases and houses”, identical to what the PSD accused the government of António Costa, such as what happened in INEM and in certain cases of AD mayors who now resigned, this government of Luís Montenegro was confronted with the first resignation of one of its members in just one year in office.
The Secretary of State for Local Administration and Planning of Territory, Hernani Dias, filed the resignation. Allegedly being suspected of old and recent fraud. It has happened that this gentleman has long been investigated by the European Attorney's Office for alleged irregularities committed during his term as Mayor of Bragança, including suspicions of receipt of improper counterparts. Not complying with the severity of the situation agreed to be ruler with the pelro that recently defined the new soil law.
Hernani Dias, Chico-Esperto, has rushed to create two real estate and real estate construction companies. So, the ruler becoming aware of which rustic land through the interior of the country was to found two companies that could compete for land that would be transformed into real estate construction? Great vision of “statesman”… Hernâni Dias asked for the resignation and the Prime Minister immediately accepted. The people say that there is no smoke without fire and in fact the installed controversy is reason to be because the incompatibility in question is blatant.
Hernani Dias has denied any illegality, ensuring that he has always acted “with total transparency” and is willing to collaborate with ongoing investigations. "In political life it is necessary to have the manner of making decisions," he said, stressing that his continuity in office could harm the government's work. These statements give us only want to laugh. Transparency? Much, if we meet the investigation of the European Attorney and the creation of two companies as a ruler related to properties possible to be built in places that Hernani Dias himself became aware of the new soil law.
Irony is still greater when it claims that it is necessary to have “manage to make decisions”. Decisions? That we knew their decisions were to have received counterparts as a mayor and create real estate companies after knowing the content of the new soil law. Its decision to resign only arises following news that indicates for a possible conflict of interest due to the alleged creation of companies that could benefit from the legislative changes promoted by its ministry. Clear, like water. The Secretary of State has resigned because he knows he is under suspicion and to be investigated. The rest are bullshit.
The country cannot be governed by greedy. By individuals who put their interests above the interests of the people and who only serve the state positions for cambalachos who illegally enrich them. For decades we have seen such cases and do not end the options for the irregular function of state server.
The sad lark becomes more substantial when Hernâni Dias justified Lusa that his departure was a “act of responsibility” to ensure the stability of the government and preserve the image of the Prime Minister… Act of responsibility? We will call the act a obligation to go out the back door full of shame. As an aggravating factor, the former secretary of state still had the disappointment of throwing himself against the media claiming that a campaign of “misinformation” has been underway… misinformation? So what happens in the European Attorney's Office is misinformation? Are real estate companies created by themselves, as ruler, are misinformation? Indeed, journalists are a roguish who publicize each truth…
And we are right that this dismissal was only the first in a government where health and internal administration ministers have long had to resign the positions, by indecent and bad figure. In a government where a lawyer linked to the real estate business is that he was hired as a legal consultant in the elaboration of the new soil law…
In addition, credible sources said that because it was RTP to disclose the case of the companies created by the ruler, that RTP will be the target of privatization faster than planned. If so, we are facing another case of revenge served coldly, because with a privatized RTP we cannot think that freedom of information will continue…
The same RTP also advanced that one of the real estate societies was constituted in conjunction with the ruler's wife and children in question, while the second company has as a minor a minor… all “transparent”, as the former governor said. And this is how this Portugal of ours continues to be governed, always with the cover of possible suspicions, accusations, trials and appeals behind judicial appeals. Ai, Portugal, Portugal…</description><pubDate>2025-02-03 02:59:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Museum in honor of Cristiano Ronaldo opens in July</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/hong-kong-museu-em-homenagem-a-cristiano-ronaldo-abre-em-julho/</link><description>Asia's first Cristiano Ronaldo Life (CR7) museum will be inaugurated in July 2025 at the K11 Museea mall in Tsim Sha Tsui, Hong Kong, according to organizers on Tuesday.
With state -of -the -art interactive exhibitions, rare memorabilia and reports of the various milestones in the career of the footballer, the museum offers visitors an engaging tribute around the football legend, the people's diary indicates.
Tickets were set for sale yesterday, coinciding with Ronaldo's birthday, providing fans around the world the opportunity to be part of the historic inauguration. The organization estimates that the space is expected to attract more than 12 million visitors to Hong Kong over a year.
The opening day of CR7 Life Museum will be attended by several international celebrities, in honor of Cristiano Ronaldo's career. Between March and April, two stores with autographed products in Tsim Sha Tsui and Hong Kong Island will be opened.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:46:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative Macau | Henry MA presents works in paint from China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/creative-macau-henry-ma-apresenta-obras-em-tinta-da-china/</link><description>Henry MA has been making a career in the arts area, not only in the government but in the gym, and returns, starting next Tuesday, with a new exhibition of ink works from China at Creative Macau. “Searching” is the name of the show that can be seen for free until mid -March
 
Creative Macao presents, from next Tuesday and until March 11, the exhibition “Searching”, with works by Henry Ma, a highlighted name within local arts and also higher education.
This is a show facing the pieces made of ink from China by the creative and teacher who graduated in Fine Arts in Canada, then made a master's degree in History at the University of Jinan, China, and a doctorate in archeology and museology by Beijing University.
A note from Creative Macau cites the author's own words about the exposure of his own. “It has been almost 40 years since I licensed at the Faculty of Fine Arts of Canada. After returning to Macao in the early 1980s, I started working for the government and was responsible for the exhibitions of Fine Arts. Since then, I have organized exhibitions only for others and, occasionally, I participate in joint exhibitions to show one or two of my own works, which does not reflect the scope of my artistic creation, ”he says.
Thus, according to Henry MA, “Searching” is made up of 30 pieces of his sketches made with paint from China, being drawings made on various landscapes and outdoor places in recent years. "Although they cannot be considered as great works of art, they should be considered as a review of my research and development phases." For the artist and creative, “there are still many flaws that need to be improved,” he assumes.
Return and Career
According to the artist, he recalls that when he returned to Macao, he tried to “apply western painting techniques in Chinese art”, as well as “incorporate Chinese handwriting as a means of expression”.
However, success did not always accompany him. “I tried in many ways, but the effect was not significant, so I returned to the starting point with outdoor sketches. At first, he drew with handmade paper fiber pens and then moved to China's ink on rice paper. In the early stages, I could not deal with the reaction between ink and water, but after years of practice, I gradually understood the interrelationship between these two means. ”
Still, the artist assumes that he continues to "think and constantly seek the way he expresses me in my own works of art."
Henry MA was a member of the Executive Committee of the Institute for Macao Municipal Affairs by 2020 and is director and member of the Executive Committee of the Macao Radio and Television station since 2021, the Macao teledifusion.
MA has also taught in institutions such as the University of Beijing and the University of Science and Technology of Macau, having published a book entitled “A Research on Blue and White Porcelain Wares of the Ming Dynasty Unearthed in Macau”, along with articles edited in several magazines academic. His art, which includes paintings, photographs and Chinese calligraphy, was exhibited in Canada, Continental China and Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:21:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Exhibition of writer Charles Dickens in London at his house-museum addresses social concern</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/exposicao-do-escritor-charles-dickens-em-londres-na-sua-casa-museu-aborda-preocupacao-social/</link><description>The Writer Charles Dickens' Museum House will celebrate a century of existence with an exhibition that includes objects never seen or recently acquired, such as a portrait considered lost and letters that reflect social concern.
On display for the first time there will be a letter in which it seems to recognize the homosexuality of one of its characters, Miss Wade in “Little Dorrit”, and another massive where he asks a teenager about to enter a refuge for homeless women who helped found.
Museum officials believe that the first missive, in response to a suggestion of similarities between Miss Wade and one of author Amelia Opie's characters, contains a reference to the LGBTQ+community. In "Little Dorrit", Miss Wade forms a strong friendship with Harriet Beadle and his relationship can be considered romantic, contrary to the laws and social restrictions of the time.
“I watched Miss Wade in real life (as I dare to say that you have observed her gentleman) and I know the character is true in every respect,” Dickens tells the interlocutor, suggesting that she was aware of the situation.
The author's biographer and tetranet, Lucinda Dickens Hawksley, admits that the comment is quite indirect, “due to the type of laws and social customs of the time, but it seems to us that they are talking about a LGBTQ+character, and that Dickens ensures that Your character is real. ”
“One thing I think is fascinating in Dickens' work, and the reason why it continues to be so appreciated today is that he shows [in his work] people from all quadrants, characters from different social classes, and Dickens was Clearly aware of the LGBT+world, even if it did not express it in this way and were a little circumspect because of the customs of the time, ”he told Lusa.
Letters as proof
In another unheard of letter, Dickens asks the director for clothes for a 16-year-old girl who was about to join Urania Cottage, a refuge for shelter women, including prostitutes, who founded with philanthropist Angela Burdett-Coutts in 1847.
Both letters reflect the character of social activist, who wrote or often spoke in support of causes and institutions such as the hospital for sick children or legislation that intended to ban leisure activities on Sunday, affecting the poorest above all.
The letters, acquired in 2019, contribute to “confirming things we thought already needed, but for which we might not have much evidence,” said Hawksley.
Among the 100 pieces symbolically chosen for this exhibition, which will remain until June 29, is also a delicate portrait of Dickens while writing “a Christmas tale” covered with mold in the settlement of a house in South Africa in 2017, after being lost for 174 years.
The little painting, by Margaret Gillies, had been missing since 1886 and was resumed six years after a background campaign. The Museum House, located at 48 Doughty Street Street, was where the writer (1812-1870) lived in London from 1837 to 1839, during which she ended “Pickwick notebooks” and wrote “Nicholas Nickleby” and “ Oliver Twist ”.
Given the literary success and growth of the family, Dickens moved, but in 1923, after the author's death, the property was acquired by a group of admirers and reopened in 1925 as a museum.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 18:19:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Death | Writer Maria Teresa Horta dies at 87</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/obito-escritora-maria-teresa-horta-morre-aos-87-anos/</link><description>The writer Maria Teresa Horta, the last of the “Three Marys”, died yesterday, at the age of 87, in Lisbon, announced the publisher Don Quixote.
“A loss of incalculable dimensions for Portuguese literature, poetry, journalism, and feminism, to whom Maria Teresa Horta has proudly dedicated much of her life,” reads the editor to Lusa.
In the same text, Don Quixote regrets “the disappearance of one of the most notable and admirable personalities” of Portuguese literature, “recognized defender of women's rights and freedom, at a time when it was not always easy to assume it, author of a work that will be forever in the memory of several generations of readers. ”
In December, Maria Teresa Horta was included in a list prepared by the British BBC public station of 100 most influential and inspiring women from around the world, which included artists, activists, lawyers or scientists.
In 2022, in the 50th anniversary of the work “New Portuguese Letters”, written with Maria Isabel Barreno and Maria Velho da Costa, Maria Teresa Horta stated, in an interview with Lusa, that the book was always disregarded in Portugal and was confessed “perplexa” with the interest raised five decades after publication.
“New Portuguese Letters”, written by Maria Isabel Barreno, Maria Teresa Horta and Maria Velho da Costa, from the love letters addressed to a French officer by Mariana Alcoforado, constituted a libel against the pre-pre-ideology in the pre-period April 25, which denounced the colonial war, the oppressions to which women were subject, a persecutory judicial system, emigration and fascist violence.
It began to be written in May 1971 and was published in April 1972, having been banned by the dictatorship and its authors taken to trial.
Until the end, the three refused to reveal and no one knows the authorship of each text individually, as Lusa Maria Teresa Horta, who contested a something widespread idea that most would be Maria Velho da Costa. “They were written by the three. No one will say [who wrote each text]. They are already dead and I neither killed nor live who wrote, because we made a vow, ”he said in 2022.
Active life
Born in Lisbon in 1937, Maria Teresa Horta attended the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon, was leader of ABC Cine-Clube, activated militant in the movements of female emancipation, journalist of the newspaper A Capital and leader of Women magazine.
As a writer, she made her debut in the field of poetry in 1960, but built a literary course also composed of novels and short stories. With books edited in Brazil, in France and Italy, Maria Teresa Horta was the first woman to perform driving functions in Cineclubism in Portugal and is considered one of the exponents of Lusophony feminism.
It has been widely awarded throughout its literary career, highlighting, in recent years, the Authors 2017 Award, in the Best Poetry Book category, for “Annunciations”, the Cultural Merit Medal with which the Ministry of Culture distinguished it in 2020, the Póvoa Casino Literary Prize, which won in 2021 for the work “Strangeness”, and the decoration in 2022, with the degree of great officer of the Order of Liberty by the President of the Republic.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:33:50</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT | Macao Retalia and suspends orders from the USA</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/ctt-macau-retalia-e-suspende-encomendas-dos-eua/</link><description>The CTT of Macao temporarily suspended order services between the territory and the United States of America (USA). According to a statement issued yesterday by CTT, postcards such as letters, document sending and air mail were not included. The suspension applies to orders and packages delivery services by maritime and express mail.
The president of the Macao International Logistics and Transport Association, Kuok Fai Law, believes that the local logistics sector will avoid the negative effects of the blockade yesterday by the United States Postal Service (USPS).
Speaking to Radio Macau's Chinese channel, the association's leader acknowledged that some companies with American capital, such as game -related companies, need to regularly send equipment to be maintained in the United States. However, law indicated that the volume of these orders is “little”.
Kuok Fai Law also pointed out that the sector began to ponder other means to send these materials to the US, or, as an alternative, who may also choose to maintain equipment in factories in Singapore or Australia.
On the impacts on the maintenance of aircraft in Macau, Kuok Fai Law devalued the subject, because most aircraft in Macau are from the Airbus brand, indicating that for these devices there are several parts of parts not only in the interior, but also in Southeast Asia .
Morning shocks
News about the “temporary” blockade by USPS to orders from interior and Hong Kong were released yesterday morning, and appear in the latest trade war between the US and China. The duration of the block was not disclosed, but by decision of US President Donald Trump, products imported from China are subject to a new rate of 10 percent.
In a statement, USPS clarified that the measure will not affect “the flow of cards and normal mail”, but only low -value products that previously benefited from exemption from fees.
The USPS measurement can block or delay orders made through Chinese shein, and stared out of low prices, but also from the American Amazon, given that many products come from interior, but also from the American prices. or by Hong Kong.
According to the numbers cited by the Lusa Agency, the exemption from rates in the purchase of low value articles has greatly benefited from the two Chinese platforms and Amazon: the number of fees -free shipments has increased by 600 percent over the past ten years, reaching 1, 36 billion orders last year, against almost 140 million in 2015.
After all there was another
In a last minute turnaround, USPS has announced that it will now accept postal order services from China and Hong Kong, totally contradicting what it had announced. With the announcement arriving at the time of the closing of this edition it was not possible to assess any reaction of the Chinese and local CTT services.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:38:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | Elderly stable after the fan is connected</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/gripe-idosa-estavel-apos-estar-ligada-a-ventilador/</link><description>A 69-year-old woman recovered from a complicated clinical influenza A, who forced respiratory aid and in the second no longer needed a fan, being currently considered stable, health services indicated yesterday.
The patient went to the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center on January 14 where he was diagnosed with bacterial pneumonia and submitted to hospitalization.
About two weeks later, symptoms got worse with fever and shortness of breath. On February 1, it would eventually be diagnosed with flu and pneumonia, which forced the medical team to resort to the mechanical fan. Authorities added that the patient was not vaccinated against seasonal flu this year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:16:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Banking | Profits with lower value in the last 14 years</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/banca-lucros-com-valor-mais-baixo-dos-ultimos-14-anos/</link><description>Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas last year, as it represented a 21.3 percent reduction compared to 2023. The data were released by the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM)
 
Macao banks made a profit of 4.01 billion patacas by 2024, a drop of 21.3 percent and the lowest value since 2010.
According to official data from the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM), the main reason for decreasing profits was a fall of 18.3 percent, to 16.1 billion patacas, on the interest margin, the difference between loans and deposit expenses.
This after AMCM approved three descents of the main reference interest rate in the last three months of 2024, the last of which a 0.25 percentage points, introduced on December 19, following the US Federal Reserve.
The loans, the main source of revenue of the banking worldwide, decreased 7.2 percent compared to the end of December 2023, setting at 1.01 billion of patacas. On the contrary, deposits with Macau banks increased 4 percent to 1.27 billion of patacas in late 2024, AMCM said on Monday.
The bank had ended 2023 with a profit of 6.14 billion patacas, 53.5 percent than the previous year. Macao has two currency broadcasters: the local Chinese state bank branch Banco da China and the National Bank Overseas (BNU), which belongs to the Caixa Geral de Depósitos group.
BNU with profits
BNU announced in November net profits of 444.2 million patacas in the first three quarters of the year, a 3.4 percent homologous decrease, in part due to the “prevailing environment of interest rates”.
Malpated credit increased by 30.3 percent by 2024 to 56.1 billion patacas, the highest value since AMCM began compiling this data in 1990, still during the Portuguese administration of the territory.
Overdue loans represented 5.5 percent of Macao banks loans, 1.6 more percentage points than at the end of 2023. A percentage that reaches 6.9 percent in the case of credit to institutions or individuals outside the Chinese region .
The European banking authority, the EU regulatory agency, for example, considers that banks with at least 5 percent of poorly misplaced loans have “high exposure” at risk and should establish a strategy to solve the problem.
Still, the percentage of bank credit overdue in Macau is far from the 25.3 percent record reached in mid -2001, in the middle of the world economic crisis caused by the buzzing of the speculative bubble of companies linked to the internet.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:15:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Suspicious transactions broke record in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/jogo-transaccoes-suspeitas-bateram-recorde-em-2024/</link><description>Over last year, suspicious financial transactions related to the game sector increased by 11.8 percent compared to 2023, with a total of 3,837 reports presented to the authorities in 2024, according to data provided by the Financial Information Office (GIF) to GGR Asia Portal. The authorities justified the increase with the economic recovery of the territory and the “significant increase” of the number of tourists who visited Macau.
In addition to the socioeconomic context, GIF states that the increase in suspicious financial transactions is also related to the continuous investment in resources to identify suspicious movements in the game industry.
Last year's number of suspicious transactions has hit the annual record as long as this type of registration is made, ie since 2006. This year, the most common type of gif radar activities includes conversion of game sheets with few or without Betting, exchange of game sheets on behalf of third parties, currency exchange and currency conversion.
In general, the GIF received a total of 5,245 appearances, with 73.2 percent from the casino dealers, while 20.9 percent arrived from banks and insurers and 5.9 percent of other institutions and entities.
The referenced sectors, including pledge, jewelery, real estate and auction houses, are required to communicate to the authorities any transaction equal to or greater than 500,000 patacas. Of the total of 5,245 appearances, the GIF last year 142 suspected transactions to the prosecutor for investigation, 26 more than 2023.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:02:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Lunar New Year | Number of tourists below expectations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/ano-novo-lunar-numero-de-turistas-aquem-das-expectativas/</link><description>During New Year's Festivities almost 1.31 million people visited Macau, however, an average of 163,700 tourists per day was below government expectations. In January, the game's recipes also did not correspond to the analysts' predictions
 
Almost 1.31 million people visited Macau during the so -called Golden Week of the Lunar New Year, less 3.5 percent than in the same period of 2024 holidays, it was announced yesterday.
According to data from the Macao Public Security Police (PSP), between January 28 and February 4, more than 163,700 tourists per day entered the territory. On January 17, Macau's Director of Tourism Services (STD), Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, said she expected a daily average of 185,000 visitors during the 'Golden Week'.
The Lunar New Year, the largest mass movement in the world, is the main traditional party of Chinese families and takes place in January or February, depending on the lunar calendar, and the number of days depends on the decision of the State Council. This year, the first day of the year was celebrated on January 28, a Tuesday.
According to PSP data that also cover the previous weekend, Macau received almost 1.7 million visitors over a period of 11 days, between January 25 and February 4. The data released by the PSP did not indicate the origin of tourists, but reported that 38.8 percent entered through the doors of the siege, the main border with the interior.
Alternative Paths
Another 23.2 percent, arrived in the territory by the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge (29.8 percent), a 55.5 kilometers infrastructure that connects Macau and the adjacent Chinese city, Zhuhai, to the neighboring region of Hong Kong.
In fact, the bridge inaugurated in October 2018 recorded on Friday the passage of more than 156 thousand people at the Zhuhai terminal, a new maximum record, according to the state newspaper China Daily. The Lunar New Year is one of the three tall times for tourism and the Macao casinos, along with the 'golden weeks' of Labor Day (May 1) and China National Day (October 1).
The game's revenues in the game fell 5.6 percent in January, compared to the same month of 2024, to less than 18.3 billion patacas, below analyst expectations. Macau received last year 34.9 million visitors, 23.8 percent than the previous year, but still far from the 39.4 million record set in 2019, before the pandemic.
The number exceeded the initial STD forecasts, which were 33 million, as well as the magazine forecast on December 4: 34 million.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 00:52:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Flu | One death and two patients in critical condition</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/gripe-uma-morte-e-dois-doentes-em-estado-critico/</link><description>Over last month, health services recorded five serious influenza cases, which resulted in a death and two patients still needing fan. Authorities expect to increase patients to resort to emergencies this week
 
With the peak of the time of the flu to continue until the end of February, health authorities expect an increase in patients at hospital emergency and health centers throughout this week. Speaking yesterday to the media the head of the Preta Sand Health Center, Chou Mei Fong, said that during the last week, with the holidays of the Lunar New Year, the number of patients who sought medical treatment descended slightly to about 1,200, compared to the previous week.
During January, health services recorded five severe influenza cases that forced the use of fan, four of which with a clinical history of chronic diseases and a smokers.
Of these five cases, two remain in serious condition still requiring respiratory aid through fan and there was a record of a dead man, an 86-year-old who died on Monday. Among the five patients, three were not vaccinated.
After a week marked by many trips, gatherings and crowds, the authorities warned the population to pay attention to flu, continue to wear mask and not neglect personal hygiene. If symptoms, such as breathing difficulties and fever, if health services get worse, recommend immediate resource to hospital emergency.
Authorities have warned again to the special attention of people who belong to risk groups, such as children, the elderly and chronic patients, as they risk more severe symptoms.
Picas and Hong Kong
The head of the Preta Sand Health Center, Chou Mei Fong, also indicated that the government bought 214,000 doses of the influenza vaccine for the time of flu 2024/2025. Until yesterday, more than 186,000 doses of the vaccine had been administered, which represents a growth of about 13 percent over the same period last year.
With the influenza situation within Macao control in Hong Kong health authorities face a different panorama.
The neighboring region's health protection center released last week alarming data. One week, between January 19 and 25, 46 people died and in two days (January 26 and 27) died 10 more people. From January 9 until the end of this month, 88 people have died in Hong Kong following flu complications, the worst record of the last five years.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:11:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Cost per square meter falls 17 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/habitacao-custo-por-metro-quadrado-cai-17-por-cento/</link><description>For the first time, since September 2024, the average cost of housing was below 70 thousand patacas per square meter. Prices at Taipa exceeded those practiced in Coloane
 
In the first half of January, the average price of housing transactions was a reduction of 17 percent compared to the previous year, according to the latest data towards Finance Services (DSF).
According to official information, in early January the average price of housing purchase and sale was 69,882 patacas per square meter, a reduction of 17 percent, compared to the price of the first half of January 2024. Average square meter reached 84,325 patacas.
For the first time, since September last year, the average housing price per square meter was below 70,000 patacas.
Compared to the prices of the first half of December last year, when the square meter was marketed to an average of 82,383 patacas, January represents a reduction of 15.17 percent of the value of houses.
In the first half of January this year, the average price perhaps was registered in the mud, with an average of 79,474 patacas per square meter. In Coloane, the place where the price is traditionally reaches the highest values, the average value did not go beyond 72,252 per square meter. In the Macao Peninsula, the average price was 66,753 patacas per square meter.
Reduced increase
At the same time that real estate prices were cheaper, more housing transactions were recorded. In the first half of this year, there were 125 purchases and sales, which represented an increase of 20 transactions, or 19.05 percent, compared to the same period, when 105 purchases and housing sales had been counted.
When the comparison is made taking into account the first half of December 2024, there were 31 more transactions, since during this period there had been a total of 94 purchases and housing sales.
In terms of transactions, the largest number of housing purchases and sales occurred on the Macao Peninsula, with 96 transactions, followed by the mud where 20 businesses took place. Finally, in Coloane there were nine transactions. The beginning of January confirmed the trends of late December, when also on the peninsula had the largest number of transactions, with 53 purchases and sales, followed by Taipa, with 37 transactions, and Coloane, where there were six operations.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:06:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us around the house, pies us his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on violations in Ukraine in this “special operation”), an act that he forced us to watch, and then we tell him: High There we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You haven't said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - Madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails about sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is managed to seek a reason for Things abroad to us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicidou -If and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ that had not entered the story. »
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when you announced the Nobel Prize in this year's literature, I couldn't help but remember this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, compared to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large newspaper Daily National Wrote wrote Five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize of Literature was awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete unknown. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners - I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example - but that only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone is He knows and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from him.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I also preferred that in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have been awarded. Les années ”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday an article came out in Maputo's morning “News”, to realize that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho Award Coast.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but to be highlighted simply that we "we do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funeral trips for countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - which starts still awaits us, that secret spells we will still have to overcome, what horrors will be erected before our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our strenuous mind to diminish a response, so we feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart fired in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the mountain of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most undevailed ambitions, if they are fortunately fortunate to glimpse a fuxi, it is true that the fields will be triggered soon and the fields will be triggered by it Cultivated, it will be beheaded the meek animals, by it will be sacrificed the best young men of two generations and destroyed the pride of countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the midst of Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneousness and frankness were coarcet in relationships in relations Human, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a "essence", therefore declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, "one and absolute". Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as António Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter My Dear Friend: You are a pure, excellent and very noble poet, but one Also victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I malice.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people, who always seems the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters At eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Evidently, they are the two 'Bigger Than Life', but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my rank of hatter at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and Treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Deepseek | Launched recruitment campaign with high salaries to respond to search</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/deepseek-lancada-campanha-de-recrutamento-com-altos-salarios-para-responder-a-procura/</link><description>The Chinese Artificial Intelligence Platform (IA) Deepseek announced yesterday a recruitment campaign with offers exceeding $ 150,000 a year after achieving worldwide success at its launch.
The company has published at least 37 employment offers for various advanced technology positions, the best paid of which is the deep learning researcher, with an annual salary of about 1.12 million yuan (148,000 euros), according to the Business Journal Securities Times.
Deepseek currently has 150 employees, against about 1,700 from OpenAi, the main American competitor and the most used AI model to date.
According to the newspaper, the company intends to recruit the best talents finished leaving the Chinese universities, for which also launched an offer of scholarships in the main domains of AI, with daily financial compensation far superior to the usual internship and lunch And even dinner are subsidized.
With staff reinforcement, the technology company seeks to respond to the exponential growth of users since launch and improve and stabilize the service, which has suffered interruptions and technical failures allegedly due to the influx of consultation, even more intense due to the Lunar New Year, period in which much of the Chinese population was on vacation.
DeepSeek caused a major excitement in the global AI industry after the launch a few weeks ago from its V3 model, which will have only taken two months to develop and cost less than six million dollars.
On January 20, he released the latest version, called R1. Launched in 2023 by the Chinese investment fund High-Flyer Quant, DeepSeek is open source and offers 95 percent services cheaper than OpenAi's O1 model.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:43:50</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE | Beijing against rates imposed by Washington</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/mne-pequim-contra-taxas-impostas-por-washington/</link><description>China said yesterday that it resolutely opposed to increasing customs imposed by the United States about its products and appealed to dialogue after revealing a series of retaliation measures on Tuesday.
"China expresses its profound dissatisfaction and is resolutely opposed to US measures," Chinese Foreign Foreign Ministry spokesman at a press conference said. "What we need now is not a unilateral increase in rates, but a dialogue and discussions based on mutual respect," he added.
Target of additional customs of 10 percent customs on all its exports to the United States, Beijing immediately retaliated on Tuesday, promising to increase customs barriers on a series of US products, from crude oil to agricultural machinery.
Beijing also announced new restrictions on critical metal exports used in sectors ranging from mining to aerospace industry. "The measures taken by China are a necessary action to defend their legitimate rights and interests," said the Chinese spokesman.
United States President Donald Trump said on Monday that a call with his Chinese counterpart, Xi Jinping, could take place soon, giving the impression that a quick turnaround was possible. But he later denied the statement, saying that "I was not in a hurry" to talk to Xi.
Asked about a possible future conversation between the two leaders, Chinese diplomacy spokesman did not give details.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:32:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Toyota | New battery and electric vehicle unit in Shanghai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/toyota-nova-unidade-de-baterias-e-veiculos-electricos-em-xangai/</link><description>Toyota Motor announced yesterday that it will create a company detained 100 percent by the Japanese car manufacturer in Shanghai, to develop and produce electric vehicles and batteries for its Lexus brand, which should be operational by 2027.
The new company will be headquartered in the Jinshan district, southwest of the Chinese city of Shanghai, with an initial production capacity of about 100,000 units per year, and is expected to create about 1,000 jobs in the starting stage.
“Due to this partnership with the Shanghai Municipal Government, Toyota hopes to contribute to the Chinese government's goal of achieving carbonic neutrality by 2060 in domains such as hydrogen energy, automated driving technology and recycling and reuse of batteries.” , the company said in a statement.
Before establishing his own company in China, the Japanese manufacturer had already worked with local partners such as China Faw Group and Guangzhou Automobile Group.
The announcement comes the same day that the company released the results of the first nine months of fiscal year (April-Decro), during which it registered a net profit of 4.1 billion yen (25.77 billion euros), An increase of 3.9 percent, thanks to the climb of sales, driven by hybrid models and the weakening of the Japanese currency, the yen.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Company shares operating ports in Panama Caem</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/hong-kong-accoes-de-empresa-que-opera-portos-no-panama-caem/</link><description>The actions of the Hong Kong CK Hutchison conglomerate, a mother company of the company that explores the Panamian ports Balboa and Cristobal, fell 1.8 percent yesterday, due to the intention of the US president to resume control of the Panama Canal.
CK Hutchison, owned by Li Ka-Shing-the richest man in Hong Kong and the richest eighth in Asia-has been holding Panama Ports Company (PPC), which operates the Porto de Balboa in Pacific, the second port of the busiest containers in the country, and the Port of Cristobal, in the Atlantic, the fifth of the list.
On several occasions, Donald Trump threatened to "make" the Panama channel and criticized former President Jimmy Carter's decision to negotiate treaties that allowed the channel transfer to Panama, a process that was completed in 1999. Earlier this month. At a press conference before his inauguration as president, Trump did not rule out the use of military force to recover the control of the channel.
China's growing economic weight in Latin America has been a source of concern for years in Washington, which fears that the region, rich in natural resources and part of its sphere of influence, is leaning to Beijing.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:28:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | China rejects Trump's proposal to expel inhabitants</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/06/gaza-china-rejeita-proposta-de-trump-de-expulsar-habitantes/</link><description>Beijing defended the solution of two states in the medium and vehemently opposed Donald Trump's intention to assume control of the region and expel the Palestinians from his land
 
China yesterday expressed its opposition to the proposal of US President Donald Trump to expel the inhabitants of the Gaza Strip and reiterated their defense of the solution of two states to the Israelo-Palestinian issue.
“We oppose the forced displacement of residents of the Gaza Strip. China expects all parties to accept ceasefire and return to a two-state political solution, ”Lin Jian Ministry spokesman said at a press conference.
Trump said on Tuesday that Palestinians have no choice but to leave the Gaza Strip because the place is uninhabitable, and insisted that it wants Jordan and Egpito to welcome them.
The Chinese spokesman added that the parties involved should "put the Palestinian question on the right track." "This means an agreement based on the" two -state solution "that aims at lasting peace in the Middle East," he warned.
Beijing has repeatedly affirmed that Palestine should be “fully” recognized as a state in the United Nations and will insist on solving two states to ensure “peaceful coexistence” between Israelites and Palestinians.
China also expressed its support for the “fair cause of the Palestinian people to restore their rights and legitimate interests”, and their employees held several meetings with representatives of Arab and Muslim countries to reaffirm this position or to try to advance the conversations of peace.
Occupation and destruction
Trump stated that in the Palestinian enclave "everything is demolished" and that the inhabitants of Gaza "would be happy" to leave, if they had the opportunity to do so in a "pleasant place with pleasant borders."
Since 1967, Israel has built about 160 illegal colonates that host more than 700,000 Jews in the occupied West Bank and East Jerusalem. The Israeli state also claims the sovereignty of the whole city of Jerusalem, whose eastern side was captured in the 1967 war, occupied militarily and unilaterally annexed in 1980.</description><pubDate>2025-02-06 01:23:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul | Openai and Kakao Messaging Service announce a new partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/seul-openai-e-servico-de-mensagens-kakao-anunciam-nova-parceria/</link><description>The American technology company OpenAi and the leading messaging service in South Korea, Kakao, announced yesterday a new collaboration project to incorporate Artificial Intelligence (AI) on this South Korean platform.
The purpose of the partnership is to incorporate the chatgpt language model in Kakao, they announced the two companies after a Seoul meeting between Kakao executive director Chung Shin-A, and OpenAi official Sam Altman. "I am pleased to share our partnership with OpenAi as part of our ambition to reach new innovation and a leap in front through AI in 2025," Chung Shin-A told press.
According to explained, the two companies will work together to apply the technology of the US company to Kakao services and also develop AI joint products, while the South Korean company plans to launch the new AI Integrated brand, Kanana, until end of 2025.
"ChatgPT technologies will be integrated into our services, including Kanana, and the partnership includes technology sharing and the joint development of AI products for Kakao's 50 million users," Chung added.
Kakao is South Korea's main information technology company and operates the largest application of mobile conversation, Kakaotalk, with over 50 million users, a number that almost equals the country's population.
The announcement of OpenAi and Kakao comes weeks after the launch of DeepSeek, the latest Chinese AI development alternative, which is at the top of the free transfers tables from the App Store mobile application store, both in China and the US, surpassing the chatgpt itself.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:37:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Nissan Motor | Court confirms a conviction of former director</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/nissan-motor-tribunal-confirma-condenacao-de-ex-director/</link><description>American Greg Kelly, former director of Nissan Motor, was yesterday again convicted in Japan for collaborating on the financial irregularities committed by former President Carlos Ghosn, run away from Japanese justice.
The Supreme Court of Tokyo upheld the decision made in March 2022 by another court in the capital, which was the subject of appeal by the defendant, after receiving a suspended sentence of six months in prison.
Kelly, once Ghosn's right arm, was considered guilty of conspiring with the former president of the company not to declare future compensation agreed between Nissan and the maximum leader of the automotive manufacturer.
The suspended imprisonment meant that Kelly had not to serve a prison sentence as long as she was not involved in any criminal activity over three years, and in practice allowed her to return to the United States.
Kelly alleged in the appeal the acquittal of all accusations that he was considered guilty. The prosecution requested up to two years in prison for the US executive, detained in Japan in November 2018, at the same time as Ghosn's detention.
The American jurist worked at Nissan as a representative director, one of the highest positions at the top of the company, and turned out to be the only Nissan executive to be tried after other Japanese officials have reached court agreements.
The sentence of 2022, confirmed yesterday, was the first in the 2018 process against Ghosn, which shook the automotive industry, because it is one of the most respected executives among the largest car manufacturers in the world.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:35:08</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Trump creates sovereign background that can buy Tiktok</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/eua-trump-cria-fundo-soberano-que-pode-vir-a-comprar-a-tiktok/</link><description>Donald Trump signed an executive order on Monday that determines that the Treasury and Commerce departments create a “sovereign background,” stating that it may acquire the Tiktok social network.
“I believe Scott and I will create an amazing sovereign background. Other much smaller countries already have them and are not the US. We have incredible potential in this country, ”he said, alluding to his nominee to Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent in statements made at the White House.
Speaking about this background, Trump advanced Tiktok's example, opening the door to his acquisition. “Let's do something. Maybe with Tiktok or maybe not. We can put it in the sovereign background, ”he said, adding that there are“ a lot of things ”that can be included in the background.
This platform continues to work in the US, thanks to the 75 -day extension signed by Trump on 21 January a day after being sworn in president. Trump's decree ordered the Attorney General and the Justice Department that they did not apply sanctions or a law of the previous president, Joe Biden, in the next 75 days.
Biden's law forced this video platform to separate from its Chinese holding, Bytedance, and finding a buyer of a country that was not considered “an adversary” before 19 January.
Although the Supreme Court approved the law, the platform did not change company. From what it stopped working for a day until Trump signed the order. Wee weeks ago, Trump wrote on his social network, alluding to the future of Tiktok, that "I would like the US to have 50 percent of a joint company." In this way, he wrote, "we save Tiktok, put it in good hands and allow him to continue to grow."</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:25:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Silk Route | Beijing considers “unfortunate” withdrawal from Panama</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/rota-da-seda-pequim-considera-lamentavel-retirada-do-panama/</link><description>China considered on Monday "unfortunate" the removal of Panama from the Seda Route initiative, which classified as an economic cooperation platform for "global south" countries, rejecting any "political agenda" in this initiative.
“I think it's a unfortunate decision, because, first of all, (…) it's an economic initiative. The aim is to build a platform for countries, especially from the global south, to have economic cooperation with each other. It is not related to any political agenda, ”said China's ambassador with the United Nations (UN), Fu Cong, at a press conference in New York.
According to the diplomat, the economic cooperation in question "is mutually beneficial," admitting to expect Panama to "see it rightly." "Any defamation campaign that is launched by the United States and some other Western countries" about the silk route initiative "is totally unfounded," he said.
At the same time, US Secretary of State, Marco Rubio, considered on Monday that Panama took "a big step" by not renewing the commercial cooperation agreement with China about the Silk Route initiative.
“The announcement made yesterday [Sunday] by President José Raúl Mulino that Panama will let his participation in the initiative of the waist and the Route of the CCP [Communist Party of China] is a big step forward to relations between the US and Panama and for a free Panama channel, ”said Rubio on social network X.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 01:23:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Ricardo Clara Couto, author of the documentary about Francisco de Pina | The weight of the guilt that persists</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/05/ricardo-clara-couto-autor-do-documentario-sobre-francisco-de-pina-o-peso-da-culpa-que-persiste/</link><description>“Francisco de Pina - The Portuguese who wrote the future of Vietname” tells the story of Father Jesuit, born in Guarda in 1586, who made the romanization of the Vietnamese alphabet. The documentary, by Ricardo Clara Couto was funded by RTP2 and aired at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
How did you come across this character in Portuguese history in the East?
My brother, named Filipe Pires, traveled for Vietnam for a while and when he arrived from the trip he told me that he had to know the incredible history of the Jesuit Francis of Pina who had made the romanization of the Vietnamese alphabet, providing freedom and cultural independence tremendous. I was a little skeptical at first, because I found it strange no one to know this in Portugal, but I started my research on the subject and discovered a university study of a Franco-Vietnamese teacher who teaches in Madeira. I then confirmed that the idea that my brother had brought from Vietname was correct. From there, I tried to discover the origin of this priest, the work he had done, and realize why there was so little knowledge about Francisco de Pina in Portugal.
In addition to being a Jesuit missionary, can you highlight some biographical points that help you understand your legacy?
In the documentary I did not have the time to be able to take a more exhaustive biographical approach. I focused on the part where he arrives at Vietname. We talk about a man with an incredible culture and a desire to acculturate and be acculturated. A man who was a musician and was easier, thus learning the Vietnamese, which is a six -tone language. Deep down, despite being a Jesuit priest, he had the first of course culture and not so much religion. This, for me, is a reason for huge admiration. For him the essential objective of evangelization was secondary, because, for him, if we could not understand the culture of Vietname, we could not teach the Vietnamese people. It was more important to deepen local culture and language, making it possible to be able to explore the most religious part. It was also a man who had a hard time when he arrived at Vietname.
Why?
There were some internal wars before some local gentlemen of the regions who did not agree with the mission of the priests. This is not explored in the documentary, but in fact Francisco de Pina even made some steps [for the Jesuit mission], as the priests were not totally accepted everywhere. He eventually took refuge in a Japanese neighborhood and, from there, built his base.
Francisco de Pina, like what happened to many Jesuits at the time, was training in Macau, at the College of S. Paulo. How was it influenced by this period spent in the territory?
There is not much information about this time. It is known that it was indeed formed in this college, as was the case with many Jesuit priests at the time, but then went to Japan. Only then go to Vietname. So far, there was nothing of great relief in the life of Francisco de Pina, who followed the normal way. Japan was already expelling the Jesuit priests and it is in this context that goes to Vietname. The only most prominent thing about this period is that the 14 ships that left Portugal to arrive in Macau this year remained only three, and the ship where I was Pina Francisco was one of those who survived the storm.
Do you consider that your great legacy was the romanization of Vietnamese? What are the great contributions of this process in linguistic terms?
It is a giant contribution. If we think that even in the romanization of the language, Vietname was very dependent on the Chinese alphabet, and could not have cultural, linguistic and economic independence as well. After the romanization of the alphabet it was possible for Vietname to grow in these domains and have her own identity. The country has grown a lot to this day, because without writing a tongue passes only to the new generations of mouth in mouth, and the legacy of Francisco de Pina also remains today. The Vietnamese people are very grateful to this, and the proof is that two years ago a delegation of the Vietnammemesse Language Foundation Foundation came to Portugal and offered a monument to Guarda City Council (see Caixa) in honor of Francisco de Pina. However, I was surprised by the fact that the Vietnamese, and we talked about full -sided academics, know the story, the figure of Francisco de Pina, existing in the country several references. But in Portugal it is a little known figure.
How do you explain this?
I think this will have to do with the need Portugal has to make its catharsis about this period of history. Portugal was a completely different country from Africa to the East, and completely different from Africa to the Americas. But, however, there is this weight of guilt. Portugal cannot talk about this period of time, despite having a rich history between Africa and the East, but this time is not very approached because the country has not taken over what happened and, therefore, cannot talk about this period. Therefore, so much of the rich history of Portugal is unknown to the Portuguese.
How was the research process for the documentary?
I quickly arrived at the study of Professor Minh Ha Nguyen Lo Cicero of the University of Madeira, and with her we went to the roots of the Vietnamese language. When I discovered it was amazing, because it is part of the Vietnamese alphabet romanization triangle, as it is Franco-Vietnamese. Until recently, the official version that existed was that Alexandre de Rhodes, French Jesuit, had romanized the alphabet, later registering it in the Vatican and saying that it was a work in honor of his master, Francisco de Pina. However, the name of Francisco de Pina disappeared. From here we passed to the nationalist French official narrative that the romanization of the alphabet had been made by French because Vietname was a French colony. Then I also arrived at Professor António Morgado. The remaining contacts were made at Vietname, linguists, university professors and language specialists, especially in writing, who later joined the documentary.
How would you describe the Vietname of the time of Francisco de Pina?
It was very fragmented. They have a very their own culture that existed through a writing with Chinese hieroglyphics, but deals with Vietnamese, which led only 1 to 3 percent of the population to read and write. With the romanization this percentage increased exponentially, and with this the culture developed with the populations, united them more around common writing. I think this has made Vietname more modern and prepared to integrate into the rest of the world by having a more affordable language.
Do you feel you will help unravel this part of the history of Portugal, as well as the history of the Jesuit mission itself?
I hope so. Portugal seems to have a certain fear and shame to talk about this time, and proof of this is that this Vietnamese people came to Guard to offer a monument and practically did not come out of the subject. In addition, the representatives of the Vietname delegation were a little admired for not being received at an official level, except for the mayor of Guarda. I, who was invited by them to be present, felt a little shame of others, because Vietname came to Portugal to offer a monument and this is viewed as a secondary event, which is not. It would be important to make known this priest and this made to the country and the world, because Portugal and Vietnam have a very close and rich cultural history, as with Japan and China. But this is a little known aspect of the Portuguese people and [this documentary] can be a good opportunity for the country to make their catharsis.
Vietnamese artist sculpture resembles Francisco de Pina at Guarda
In November 2023, the Vietnamese Language Foundation offered the city of Guarda the sculpture “Nova Estela” by Vietnamese artist Nguyen Huy Anh. The work can be seen in the Garden of the Eduardo Lourenço Municipal Library. According to news from the agency Ecclesia, the event took place within the scope of the 824th anniversary of the Foral Assignment by King D. Sancho I to the city. “This is a posthumous tribute to Father Francisco de Pina, a Guarda-born Jesuit priest in 1586, whose religious path underwent a mission in Vietname, where he lived nine years of intense missionary activity, linguistics and of interculturality, ”said the Diocese of the Guard, in a statement.
According to the same note, missionary Francisco de Pina was responsible for the introduction of the Latin alphabet and diacritical signs in the transcription of the sounds and tones of the Vietnamese language, which used in writing Chinese characters.
The priest embarked for over 400 years at the Nau de Nossa Senhora do Mount of Carmo, having completed the training at the São Paulo College in Macau and received the priestly ordination in Malaca. It was then called to the newly created Mission of the Jesuit Cchinchina, a zone that corresponds to the central part of the current Vietname. “He never came to the city where he was born and now returned in a bronze -carved boat by Vietnamese artists brought by the distant Vietname sea. From now on, Father Francisco de Pina will be in the historical memory of the guard and its inhabitants, materialized in this boat that brought him back to his city, leaving the name of the guard far, also written in Bronze letters ” , concluded the diocese.</description><pubDate>2025-02-05 00:46:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Francisco Leandro, author and professor at the University of Macao: “Support from the country reinforces the role of Macao platform”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2024/12/16/francisco-leandro-autor-e-professor-na-universidade-de-macau-apoio-do-pais-reforca-o-papel-de-plataforma-de-macau/</link><description>Gang Wen interview with China Daily newspaper
Francisco Leandro, an associate professor at the Faculty of Social Sciences at the University of Macao, states that the nation's support has allowed the MSA to serve as the Center for Commerce, Investment and Cultural Interactions between China and Portuguese -speaking communities.
 
 
How do you see Macau's development since your return to the homeland? Among the city's achievements, which ones impressed him most? What about its sector, has there been an important progress in the last 25 years?
The 25th anniversary of Macau's return to the homeland and the creation of the Macao Special Administrative Region is a significant milestone in the history of the region, reflecting a successful diplomatic process and demonstrating its current political and economic stability. Currently, RAE de Macao enjoys political stability and is deeply integrated into national development plans. The governance of the city under the beginning of “a country, two systems” allowed him to maintain a high degree of autonomy, while aligning himself with national policies. This integration facilitated Macao's economic growth, making it a vital part of the country's broader economic strategy.
Macao's socioeconomic development strategy is consecrated in the policy “a center, a platform, a base”. This picture aims to position MSA as a world center of tourism and leisure, reinforcing its attraction as a global tourist destination. In addition, MSAR acts as a platform for economic and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, promoting international trade and cultural exchange. Rae de Macao is also becoming a base of exchange and cultural cooperation, promoting cultural interactions and the conservation of heritage. This multifaceted approach supports Macao's integration into national development plans and reinforces its global presence. The unique position of MSA as a bridge between China, in particular the great Guangdong-Hong Kong-Macau Bay, and Portuguese-speaking countries underline their strategic importance.
The concept of “a platform, three centers” enhances Macao's role in promoting economic and cultural exchange. This platform allowed the city to serve as a platform for trade, investment and cultural interactions, reinforcing the ties between China and the Lusophone world.
Macau's development as a tourism and leisure center, along with the promotion of four main industries - conventions and exhibitions, cultural and creative industries, traditional Chinese medicine and modern financial services - diversified its economy. These initiatives not only boosted economic activity, but also reinforced the global attraction of Macau as a tourist destination.
The central government adopted a series of policies for Macao. Is there any specific measure that has benefited your sector? As?
The interior of China and the Macao Economic Economic Partnership Agreement (Cepa) play a crucial role in the great bay and the promotion of ties with Portuguese -speaking countries. By promoting commercial and economic cooperation, the strain reinforces the position of MSA as a bridge between China and Lusophone countries. This agreement facilitates access to the market, investment and cultural exchange, promoting Macao as an international business center. In addition, the strain supports the integration of Macao in the Great Bay area, contributing to regional development and economic diversification. This strategic role underlines the importance of Macau in the broader economic and diplomatic initiatives in the country.
The promotion of higher education in RAE de Macao also played a crucial role in its development. In investing in education and research, Macau contributed to the objectives of national development and was positioned as a center of academic excellence. This bet on education has allowed to create a skilled labor, essential to sustain economic growth and innovation. The University of Macao is highly considered in global academic rankings. It was classified in 180th place at the World University Rankings 2025 by Times Higher Education, and 245th at QS World University Rankings 2025. In addition, the University of Macao is ranked 262nd in the best global universities by US News &amp; World Report. These classifications reflect the university's commitment to excellence in teaching and research, particularly in areas such as Artificial Intelligence, Engineering and Social Sciences. The university's strong international collaboration and innovative investigation contribute significantly to their estimated global position.
This year is the third anniversary of the creation of the Guangdong-Macau in-depth cooperation zone in Hengqin. In your opinion, how should Macau continue to take advantage of the advantages of the zone to develop himself and the education sector?
Hengqin's cooperation zone is one of the main objectives of Macao's modernization efforts. This zone has been fundamental to boosting innovation and economic diversification, providing a space for new industries and promoting a narrower integration with the continent. The area exemplifies Macau's commitment to modernization and its strategic role in regional development.
Macao is a unique mix of Chinese and Portuguese cultures. In your opinion, how can this merger help the nation to reinforce communication with the international community and tell the good stories of China?
Macao is a fascinating mix of cultures, where the East meets the West in a unique and harmonious way. His linguistic landscape is a testimony of his multicultural heritage. The Chinese is the official language and the Portuguese language can be used for official purposes, reflecting the historical ties of Macao with Portugal and its Chinese roots. English is also widely spoken, especially in business and tourism, which makes Macau a truly multilingual society.
The legal system of MSAR is another domain in which this cultural mixture is evident. Based on the Portuguese Civil Law System, it was adapted to the local context under the “one country, two systems” principle. This double legal system allows a unique mix of Chinese and Western legal traditions, ensuring that Macau's legal environment is familiar to its residents and accessible to international companies.
Macao's approach to the extrajudicial resolution of commercial conflicts further enhances its multicultural policy. The city offers various arbitration and mediation services that serve both local and international parts, promoting the efficient and friendly resolution of disputes. Macao's open city policy and multicultural attitude are the key to its success as a global center. The city welcomes people from around the world, promoting a diverse and inclusive community. This opening is reflected in its festivals, its gastronomy and their daily lives, where different cultures coexist and enrich each other. Essentially, the mix of language, legal systems and multicultural attitudes of Macau makes it a unique and dynamic place that establishes bridges between cultures and promotes global bonds.
What achievements would you like to see by Macau in the next 25 years?
In short, Macao's future is brilliant, with greater integration with mainland China, its central role in international trade, diversified economic growth and a strong global presence. These elements will ensure Macao's continuous success and development at the world scene. The 25th anniversary of Macao's return to the Fatherland celebrates not only a successful diplomatic achievement, but also the continuous contributions of the region to national and world development. Macao's strategic initiatives and their integration in national plans underline their importance as a dynamic region and facing the future.</description><pubDate>2024-12-16 02:20:12</pubDate></item><item><title>António Antunes, cartoonist: “Sometimes I consider myself an artist”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2024/12/12/antonio-antunes-cartoonista-as-vezes-considero-me-um-artista/</link><description>It's called Antonio Antunes, but signs her cartoons simply as Antonio. For 50 years it has characterized today using drawing and humor, most of them in the Express. In an interview, the cartoonist, who designed the days of the April 25, regrets that today young cartoonists do not have so many opportunities to sing in their career
This 50 -year adventure is already long dedicated to Cartoon. Have you ever thought you were going to do this for so many years?
No. Things were happening, and the result is this. There were not even perspectives to have a plan. Portugal has not been a country that greatly favors this type of activities.
He did training at António Arroio school during the Estado Novo period. What was it like to learn arts at a time when the country [Portugal] was so gray, with limits to creativity?
We mainly learned techniques, work or composition. Now creativity is something else. Not only was she very limited, but it's not something to sell either. There are no courses to take artists, there are courses that give us notions about painting composition or techniques, or colors. But that alone is not enough. Then there needs to be anything beyond what is academic. In the arts there is always anything that escapes even if you learn everything. Creativity is a strange thing because there is no rule.
Is Antonio considered an artist?
(Hesitates) Sometimes I consider.
He has had many controversial cartoons, namely Pope John Paul II with the condom in his nose. What were the cartoons that forced you to make the biggest waist play or deal with more pressures?
Maybe it's my happiness, but my problems are never a priori, but to posteriori. So far I have not been very limited in what I can do in the newspaper [Expresso]. Now, when things go out, sometimes have consequences. In Portugal it was the issue of condom in the Pope, internationally other things. This cartoon continues to move.
What was it like to deal with all this controversy?
This cartoon [Pope John Paul II] was controversial because they wanted to be so. That went very well and did not generate any ranks. Then there was a conservative movement within the church that wanted to make it a controversy, three weeks began to excite that, to make a petition. The man who led the Catholic forces said he expected a million signatures, but fortunately he got only 29,000, and the difference made the mountain not a mouse Parisse. It was even discussed at the Assembly [of the Republic]. It is a controversy a lot of little, even more, 30 years later, when the church itself is changing its point of view on this matter, namely with this Pope [Francis], fortunately. In the face of what led me to do this cartoon, I did it again. The Pope's statements at the time were public, they were not even hidden, inside walls, and spoke to the whole world, so also to me. I felt injured, that it made no sense. I think the Pope's attitude at that moment was criminal at the Pico da Aida and in Africa. It was of huge insensitivity and foolishness.
Is Cartoon a throwing weapon, a form of expression?
Throw of throwing is a hard expression of too much, but the cartoon is, in fact, the way I express myself. There are my colleagues who make articles, but I make drawings.
What other cartoons highlights, for what they brought you?
The first one that sensitized me was the one who made me win the world's largest salon in the world [major prize of the XX Salon International of Cartoon, Montreal, 1983], from this corner that is Portugal. A hall that had over a thousand participants, and gaining it was very good. I was safer, confident, because from then on they could continue to do things. This first cartoon also gave controversy, the “Warsaw Ghetto in Shatila”, in which I use the known photograph of the ghetto, a Jewish kid raised, harassed by Nazi soldiers, and in the cartoon the kid is Palestinian and Israeli soldiers. [The controversy was] with all the voices of the Jews, who are experts in this, making a lot of noise, with a certain tone of victimization, even if they are attacking. A hall director said he tried to change the vote, such is the weight of Jewish lobby, but failed.
This cartoon could be drawn today again.
I already published it again. Unfortunately it is not out of date.
But do you feel that much of what you designed about today is repeated, in a sign that the story is cyclical?
There is a resistance to change. One of the merits of the cartoonist is to be able to see ahead of time, or over time if you want. I have the invasion of Crimea made in 2014, and I assume that vision. It was above, and others did it later. There are other examples.
It begins to do cartoon after April 25, 1974, there a little there in the aftermath of the revolution. Do you feel that, in a way, has inaugurated the discipline of the Political Cartoon in Portugal?
Perhaps. But I'm not very clear about it, because before me there was a great designer, João Abel Manta, a fantastic chart, which had a huge difference from us, because we were kids and he already had a culture that allowed him that. But there is a less good side, because he did political propaganda. He was a man of the Portuguese Communist Party (PCP), and made this advertisement to where the revolution allowed it. Then when things stabilized, he went out and went to do other things. This does not remove the quality, but it is not my notion of Cartoon. I respond to the various stimuli of events otherwise. Cartoon allows me to express opinions, but be able to do so in different meanings of life, perspectives, without being a prisoner, as he became a prisoner of the PCP, was something that helped me a lot.
Did you ever feel any pressure from the newspapers where you collaborated?
(Hesitates). Some things, but they are not important. One thing I got, without much effort, was to make people think I have a bad damn shape, and it was better not to get me. It helped because they thought twice before talking to me. Once in Expresso, a type of sport commissioned me a cover, and began to give tips on how I should make the design. Until I asked you if I ever told you how to write news. This must have been in memory for many years, and must have reverberated this conversation in other people. I did not go to the Express, I was always in my corner and did not wear out with everyday life, with friendships and enmities.
Do you usually draw here, in the studio?
Here. But this [the image of bad shape] really helped me. And there is also the story of me having another profession. I often say that I really had two professions, because I was a cartoonist and graphic designer, and then I had my customers who were also of the Express, namely the tobacha. He was a friend of the commercial director, a comfortable type, who was staring to negotiate contracts with the newspaper in the name of A Tabaqueira. Therefore, I conveyed an effective image of power that actually did not have. If you add a type that has bad shape to a type that apparently has power, it is a boring (laughs).
When I ask you about the pressures, I think in the period right after April 25, 1974-1975, when everything was politicized. Were there bigger?
I managed to deal with it. During this period of the Prec (ongoing revolutionary process) it even had a cartoon over the need that lasted two years. It was a kind of escape forward. There was a great confusion, and I think it was interested in my newspaper [express], although that was never said. It gave an idea of ​​freshness of the newspaper about a complex period, but they never told me that. I have the idea of ​​this use of Cartoon, it was the way of consolidating the newspaper's independence regarding events, even when sometimes there was no such independence.
Are we today in a politically correct era, where everything seems to offend?
I don't feel, because I don't want to feel. I came to a phase of my life where if they didn't want to put up with me, they don't work. It's easy. Everything that was a struggle to impose a name and a point of view, a career, has already been made. It can be improved and consolidated, but if not, it is not. If I become very inconvenient for the newspaper where I work, and I want to believe this does not happen…
But in general terms, to the news, comments on social networks, do you feel that there is the politically correct?
Of course there is. My situation is of exception. The younger ones in the world of Cartoon have no opportunities at all. They have less than when I started. For various chances of life I have a position that has solidified, but this is not exemplary to what goes on. The new cartonists are full of trouble, there is no room for them, there is no means of payment. They are pushed to get out of the newspapers, not to enter.
Doesn't Cartoon have no place on social networks?
(Hesitates) It may appear, but it doesn't seem to me… Journalism is said to die and we cartoonists are going first. I think this is the trend. Journalism has been losing power in the face of social networks, with an anonymous opinion, which cannot be scrutinated, is very bad and mediocre. And that will grow.
What about Artificial Intelligence (AI)? Can replace the cartoonist.
This one I don't even speak because I do not know the limits, but I am intended to be terrible. It can indeed replace the cartoonist, but there is a subverting creativity.
Is there any public figure who particularly likes to portray in Cartoon?
The other day he said that, in relation to Trump, he had two antagonistic feelings: as a citizen, I find man detestable; But as a cartoonist is my raw material. Putin is also good. All men with many narratives and much power are likely to give good things from the point of view of analyzing a cartoonist. They are politicians with a very clear speech about what they want and what they want, and this can be good for Cartoon.
How do you feel to go to Macau again?
The exhibition [at the Military Club] will be different from the others, with 160 works. It's still a lot. It is a trip for these years, for Portuguese and international politics as well. I'm full of curiosity, promoting the show, seeing what they ask me, but this is part of the game.
The press of Macao does not have a great presence of Cartoon, except for Rodrigo [Rodrigo de Matos].
I know him, I get along with him. But I must say that the phenomenon is similar to Portugal. What do we have here? I, in the Express; Cristina Sampaio in the public; André Carrilho left the Diário de Notícias; António Maia in Correio da Manhã and little more. This is a general trend. Sometimes, and I think this happened to me, there are times when a cartoonist can represent a more value for the newspaper, but it's just a few moments when it can happen. In my most complicated period in Expresso, in the late 1970s, a reference newspaper that was in a country in convulsion, with some “irresponsibility” I could go ahead, and I have the perception that I helped the newspaper to detangle of these limitations. But this happens in very specific periods. In this phase [after April 25], I even made drawings at night that were already out of date.
Do you really have a bad shape or is it just to disguise?
I am shy, but I've been treating myself. (laughs) It was never something that had blocked me, I speak well in public. I'm a type I don't like to take stupid risks. I have been in this building for several years and I know only the gate because it has to be, and I do not want to have the risk of having an antipatic person to whom I confident. I do this with the greatest naturalness.
Military Club Exhibition
After the lecture at the Rui Cunha Foundation, this Wednesday, António will be today at the University of São José to talk to students at the “Cartoon Drawing: Ideas” workshop. This Friday follows the inauguration of the exhibition at the Military Club, which will be evident until January 2.</description><pubDate>2024-12-12 00:58:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Ben Lee, a game analyst, about the new concessions: “We need something grand”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2024/12/03/ben-lee-analista-de-jogo-sobre-as-novas-concessoes-precisamos-de-algo-grandioso/</link><description>The game analyst and consultant Ben Lee believes that it is necessary to do much more to diversify the economy of Macau beyond the game, especially given the type of events organized under the new concessions. The analyst thinks that Macau could look at two resorts in Vietnam as examples to follow international tourists
 
What balance do you do the two years of new game concessions?
There is still a lot of work to do. From what we could see so far, dealers have focused on lighter projects, such as local art galleries, cultural events, concerts and small rehabilitation of cultural neighborhoods. Large projects, such as the high -tech amusement park, the conservatory or new hotels have not yet been seen. Since two of the ten years have passed [concession], and given that the construction of some of these projects should take several years, it seems that it will be necessary to add them. The non-game segment revenues, in a percentage of gross revenue obtained by the dealers, seem to be higher than 2019, but have diminished in the last two years. It is possible to return to the next two years to be between the 10.5 and 11 percent verified in 2019.
Recently, Ho Iat SENG thanked the concessionaires to comply with contracts and collaboration in the development of the non-game segment, reiterating that they were able to make some profits during the pandemic. Do you think it was fair in your words?
Casinos are making efforts to develop the non-game segment, but once again most of these efforts are focused on lower, lower-level events. We don't see great ideas like the $ 2.3 billion investment sphere we see in Las Vegas, for example. If that happened, it would easily fit the $ 15 billion commitments promised by the concessionaires [when signing the new contracts]. We could also talk about the idea of ​​making a Formula 1 competition on the street, as seen in Singapore and recently in Las Vegas.
How do you analyze the recovery of operators in terms of game revenue in recent months?
The recovery of the game in Macao has been extremely good, and the sector is expected to recover to about 78 or 79 percent of the levels recorded in 2019.
The Macao Games Society (SJM), for example, was one of the game operators with the greatest difficulty in terms of cash flow during the pandemic. Do you consider that your recovery, compared to the other five, was positive?
The SJM had difficulties at first, but it seems to be finally making some progress. But there will still be some challenges to reposition your hardware [facilities and other enterprises] in the future.
What can we expect from the new government of Sam Hou Fai for the game area?
The chief executive elected seems to be trying to ensure that operators honor their commitments. Your two terms will probably cover the next eight years of the new concessions. I think that, ultimately, everything will be known to know if he can motivate the various government appliances to perform his vision and mission.
In the context of new contracts, how do you see the global evolution of the game sector?
In 2019, the percentage of non-game segment revenues compared to the game's recipes reached 10.5 percent. This percentage rose to 22 percent during COVID-19, and has since gradually fallen to 13.5 percent, according to the third quarter of this year. This percentage will continue to decrease as game recipes continue to grow. In recent times we have seen residents of Macau and Hong Kong go to the north [China] to save money. The question that arises is why the inhabitants of the continent would go down and do the reverse? The solution, as provided by the authorities, is that Macau needs to diversify the market [of tourists and players] that comes from the continent. This makes perfect sense in terms of logic, but the reality is that our efforts seem to be regressing. Visitors from outside the Greater China represented 7.8 percent of the total visitors from Macao, but decreased to 6.5 percent by the end of September this year. This refers to the lightweight events that have been organized that, by far and largely, are really oriented to the Chinese who, after all, constitute most of our source of recipes.
How can you get around this scenario?
Returning to the beginning, I think we really need something large, iconic, similar to the sphere in Las Vegas or even something like the “Golden Bridge” project in Da Nang, worthy of appearing on Instagram, or “Bridge From the kiss ”, in Phu Quoc, both in Vietname. The fact that these projects were built by a local group linked to the hotel sector, without any connection to profits from the game, demonstrates long -term creativity and perspective in terms of planning.
Class struggle
Ben Lee warns of the mass market danger of “running away” from Macau
The conversation with Ben Lee comes in the context of a lecture that recently starred in the two years of new game concessions. Promoted by the France-Macau Chamber of Commerce, the session was named “Macau New Gaming Landscape: Two Years Into Concessions, What Now?”, Having Igamix Management &amp; Consulting, according to Asian Gaming Brief, according to the portal Gaming Brief (AgBrief), that the VIP game did not end completely, thus being the target of a new classification.
According to Agbrief, citing words by Ben Lee, "the mass game incorporated the same [players] level that was so openly criticized by the government," but that operators "are changing their focus to accommodating it."
The analyst highlighted the "recent focus on the transformation of older and older hotel rooms into luxury options, with all operators understanding the need to get quality rather than quantity."
However, he argued that “the focus on the luxury segment continues to create an impasse” because “Macau has long focused on increasing the number of visitors to increase revenues”, but the business model “goes against the need to increase expenses per person ”.
Ben Lee also warned that many tourists could, in fact, start choosing other more affordable destinations. The analyst argued that mass players "cannot be ignored" as they remain "the main engine" of the sector. "Exorbitant prices from hotel rooms can be a" dam "for the increase of visitors," as, as suggested, "gamblers can go to other vacation places, such as Thailand, if the price is not good." This Asian country “is growing and is expected to exceed Singapore in terms of gross revenues” at a time when Thai work in the new legislation on the game.
“They hope to pass your game law in May next year. Starting from the principle this happens three to five years to build an integrated resort or enterprise. They may be working considerably before the opening of Japan, ”said Ben Lee.
Still in relation to the game market in Asia, the analyst pointed out that Asian gamblers will focus on the future game markets of Thailand and Japan "while enjoying the current offers in Macau, Singapore and Philippines," wrote Agbrief.</description><pubDate>2024-12-03 00:08:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion expropriated from any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death , systematically carried out to this day (still in 2011 the Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the county).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. In fact, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and masquerade/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hate speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tennis | Nuno Borges will play in front of Alcaraz in the Australia Open</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/16/tenis-nuno-borges-vai-jogar-frente-a-alcaraz-no-open-da-australia/</link><description>Nuno Borges surpassed the nervousness to defeat Australian Jordan Thompson in three sets in the second round of Australia Open, and will now face 'Carlitos' Alcaraz without pressure, admitted the Portuguese tennis player to Lusa agency.
“I feel it was a good game on my part. Undoubtedly it was better than the first round, the sensations were there, ”he began by analyzing national number, in statements to Lusa, after moving to the third round of the first Grand Slam of the season.
The 27-year-old Maiato contradicted Wednesday the favoritism of the 'local' Jordan Thompson, 27th standard head, imposed on 6-3, 6-2 and 6-4 partials in one hour and 47 minutes, in a John Cain Arena - the third most important court by Melbourne Park - crowded.
"It was very nervous, it was a big stadium, not every day [that happens], so I think within that I could make a very good game and I really am very happy for the result," he said.
Follow to Alcaraz
Semifinalist in Auckland at the start of the year, Borges has now extended his good moment, setting a meeting in the third round with Spanish Carlos Alcaraz, the third world player.
“Now, against 'Carlitos', there is not much to say. Everyone knows what he is capable of and everything he has done, [is] quite famous around the world, there is not much to highlight, ”he said about his opponent who, in Australia, seeks to become the younger Tennis player (is 21 years old) to complete the career Grand Slam.
In front of Spanish, the 33rd ATP ranking will try to do its best and "make it the most uncomfortable possible." "I will play without pressure, try not to put high expectations in my head to see if I can bring my best tennis," he concluded.
Last year, Nuno Borges, who will still start his walk in the pairs alongside Francisco Cabral, became the first Portuguese tennis player to reach the round of 16 at the Australia Open.</description><pubDate>2025-01-16 22:38:03</pubDate></item><item><title>After “very positive meeting”, Borges “looking forward to playing at a stadium” with Thompson</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/14/apos-encontro-muito-positivo-borges-ansioso-por-jogar-num-estadio-com-thompson/</link><description>Portuguese tennis player Nuno Borges debuted yesterday, the 13th, in the 113rd edition of Open of Australia, first major of the time, with a “very positive meeting” against Frenchman Alexandre Muller in Melbourne Park, where he will face the Australian now Jordan Thompson.
“I am very happy. It was a very positive meeting. I think, in general, I served very well, at least I managed to put the ball on the places where I wanted and have a good percentage (69%). I felt that I kept quite constant except in the tie-break of the first set, which I didn't play very well. I always kept looking for and very consistent during a meeting and this turned out to be the key to the result, ”he said in statements to Lusa.
The world's national and 33rd number one needed two hours and 55 minutes to get the best of the Gaul opponent, recently champion of the Hong Kong ATP 250, in four sets, by the 6-7 (2-7) partials (2-7) , 6-3, 6-2 and 7-5, but believes it has deserved the triumph, in the return to Melbourne, where a year ago became in the first Portuguese tennis player to reach the round of 16.
“I feel like I deserved to win in four sets, I was slightly higher from the first set and I'm very happy. The first rounds are never easy in terms of sensations. Tennis does not flow the same way, is trying to gain pace, but fortunately meetings at the best of five sets give more time to find this rhythm. I feel that I ended up the meeting quite well, although exhausting too, ”he explained.
After the inaugural round victory, Nuno Borges will “take the opportunity to rest and recover tomorrow to play possibly Wednesday” with a home player, Jordan Thompson (27th ATP), who today surpassed at Margaret Court Arena O 'Qualifier' German Dominik Koepfer also in four partials, 7-6 (7-3), 6-4, 4-6 and 6-3.
“I hope it's a good opportunity to play at a stadium possibly, I'm looking forward to it. We have played a long time ago [Estoril Open of 2021]. In 2024, he made a great season, quite impressive and I know that he, here in Australia, competes very well, always available to play five sets. I know I'll have to play my best tennis and I'm waiting for another big challenge, maybe even more challenging than today, ”said Borges, winner of the only duel with Thompson.</description><pubDate>2025-01-14 16:15:44</pubDate></item><item><title>GT Cup | Great Bay Race gains impulse from the interior</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/27/taca-gt-corrida-da-grande-baia-ganha-impulso-do-interior/</link><description>The GT Cup-Great Bay Race will be part of this year, the newly created Sro GT Cup, the latest GT competition launched in the interior of China, inspired by the GT4 class vehicles of the Macau Grand Prix
 
On the eve of last Christmas, Sro Motorsport Group, the entity responsible for organizing numerous events and championships, including the GT World Challenge Asia and, as the official partner of the FIA, the co-coordination of the FIA ​​GT World Cup in Macau , announced the creation of a competition for GT4 vehicles, consisting of four events in China. At the time of the announcement, only the inaugural event in Shanghai and the end in Beijing had been confirmed as part of the calendar.
Almost 30 cars, representing an impressive total of ten automotive builders, participated in the GT Cup - Great Bay Race of 2024, a race that has become an important milestone over the weekend of the Macao Grand Prix in recent years. Indeed, no other GT4 event in Asia brings together such quantity and diversity of cars. The Balance of Performance (BOP), responsible for balancing the performance of the various participating cars, was, at the time, managed by SRO.
In a statement, Benjamin Frannasovici, managing director of Sro Motorsports Asia, said:
“We are enchanted, proud and privileged for adding the GT Cup - Great Bay Race to the inaugural calendar of Sro GT Cup, which begins and ends with the two largest motorized sports events in China. We already have a strong working relationship with the GT Cup - Great Bay Race, which has become the most significant race for GT4 cars in Asia. Its inclusion in the 2025 calendar of the SRO underlines the size of our ambition for this new national series. ”
High interest
The SRO GT Cup debut season starts in March at China's Formula 1 Grand Prix in Shanghai, before moving to the Zhuhai International Circuit - a place previously visited by SRO in BPR times and the FIA ​​GT Championship - where two 30 minutes races are planned. This is followed by the new Citadine Circuit of Beijing, which will host the GT World Challenge Asia on the same weekend, before the big end of the Sro GT Cup season, scheduled for a month later at the Guide Circuit in Macao.
The enthusiasm surrounding this competition is evident. As Benjamin Franassovici said, “This is reflected in the number of consultations and registration for the full season we have received since the release of the championship, just before Christmas. The demand has exceeded our expectations. ”
Up to 28 cars will be able to compete in the season end event on the streets of Macau, with places to be assigned based on the classification after the second round of the championship, which is scheduled for the Zhuhai Permanent Circuit. All pilots with “bronze” or “silver” classifications attributed by the FIA ​​are eligible to compete in this competition, as long as they use approved cars from the GT4 class.
To attract brands, the results of SRO GT Cup races will tell the SRO GT4 builders ranking, a title attributed to the brand with better performance in the GT4 category at the end of each season. SRO GT CUP joins its Asian equivalent, Japan Cup, in a list that also includes continental and national competitions in Europe, America and Australia.</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 11:13:41</pubDate></item><item><title>MOTOR EMBALISM | Rui Valente is not due</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/21/automobilismo-rui-valente-nao-se-da-por-vencido/</link><description>Rui Valente will return this year for another season in motorsport in the region. The Macao pilot has been in the active for the same time and will play the Macau Roadsport Challenge, the tourist cars competition organized by the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), as well as the 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix , in November
 
With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive, in the 2025 season, a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit last November in the Macao Roadsport Challenge race. In the event held at the event of the territory, the Portuguese pilot finished sixth place, after losing some positions in the start, where he descended to tenth. The result was not even better because the rain -played race ended prematurely due to an opponent's accident.
In the competition for local pilots, which currently combines starting grids with more than half a hundred cars, all of them Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8), Rui Valente admitted to HM that “not being overcome”, revealing still who is “missing the podium, both in China and Macau…”.
Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the bet for this year will be in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
"At this time, I just wanted to increase the diameter of the front wheels and widen the gauge to improve the car's behavior," he confided to HM, also reporting that he intends to "optimize weight transmission during the curve and its. exit". These improvements, along with updates in the brake system, should increase the competitiveness of the Japanese machine in a fierce grid, consisting of Macau, Hong Kong pilots and China interior, with constantly evolving cars.
Undefined calendar
The AAMC -organized car competition calendar has not yet been revealed. In 2024, Macao Roadsport Challenge debuted at the Zhuzhou International Circuit in East of Hunan Province, but Rui Valente would rather the competition returned to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC) in Zhaoqing.
“I was very fond of returning to Gic, because I have everything there,” says the Portuguese pilot, defender of the track located in the neighboring province. “When you go to a qualification test, for those who make four races and then Macau, if you are on a track you already know, such as GIC, where you are seven or more years, each time you get on the track and try to do better than which last means you are improving and improving your driving. So you know you soon that you are stronger that year to Macau. ”
On the other hand, for the experienced pilot of the territory, “if you go to a new track, like the Zhuzhou circuit, besides floors there to learn the new layout and improve your time, you will never know if you are really stronger For Macao, as you know when you run in the gic. ”
Like what happened in past seasons, the Macau Roadsport Challenge calendar is expected to be composed of two weekends, with two races each, which also serve as an investigation for the Grand Prix.</description><pubDate>2025-01-21 23:47:48</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Luca Engstler still recovers from the accident</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/12/gp-macau-luca-engstler-ainda-recupera-do-acidente/</link><description>Although every year the Macau Grand Prix Organizing Committee puts a lot of resources and a lot of energy in the driver's safety, the Guide Circuit Continates, and will continue to be one of the most dangerous and risky in the world. This year, the young German Luca Engstler, who first participated in a GT3 car, felt the old maxim of this circuit in the skin: “The mistakes pay dearly”
 
After eight weeks after the most severe accident of his career, the 24 -year -old is still recovering from the apparent misfortune at the Cup of GT World Cup of the 71st Macao Grand Prix. On Friday afternoon, with the chronometer counting and when trying to improve his brand, Luca Engstler lost control of his Lamborghini Huracán GT3 Evo in the dreaded Mandarin curve, beating over 230 km/h in protective barriers. The car inscribed by the Liqui Moly Team Engstler, but prepared and placed by Grasser Racing Team, was completely destroyed and the German pilot even became unconscious after the impact.
“This is a unique event, Lamborghini's progress was not very good and to be ahead we had to risk more than the others. Basically, I was completely thoroughly and was unsuccessful, ”said Luca Engstler, at the time, the accident she suffered. Two months after what was “the most horrible day of my life to this day,” former German Touring Champion (TCR) is still in the recovery process.
“It was really a big impact,” said Luca Engstler, in conversation with the specialized portal motorsport-total.com, who needed a wheelchair after the accident. “The big problem was that my right ankle suffered a lot. I tore the lateral ligaments and had a lot of hemorrhages in tibia and fibula, which caused some concern, ”he recalled.
Returning to walk normally was also a big challenge for the young Lamborghini pilot, who in the 2024 season impressively won two DTM races and first participated in a GT3 car in Macao. "It took me a long time to be able to walk," he recalled. “In the first two or three days, I was really a wheelchair, because I just couldn't do anything and all the bones hurt me,” Engstler described to the publication of his country, saying that “he had bruises everywhere and everything was difficult ”.
Recover
Still, Lucas Engstler, at the end of the day of the accident, already at the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, made a publication on social networks to say that everything was fine. The pilot, who was in Macao accompanied by his father, Franz Engstler - also a pilot and a well -known figure of Asian motorsport - wanted to reassure the closest. Two days after the accident, appeared on the GT da Fia World Cup starting grid on Sunday, without crutches, only slightly supported by an umbrella.
"What was important to me was not wanting to make a big sink about this," he explained to the Germanic portal. "In the end, the accident seemed very serious, but that only shows how safe the cars are," he said.
The pilot continues to recover from the sequelae of the strong impact. He took advantage of the winter break to take a trip from Autocaravana to Sweden with his best friend. "Everything is going well," he said, clarifying that he can run. "I would say I'm 95 percent and I have no permanent damage."
After the accident, the German worked on their recovery in the Allgäu region, in their homeland, “with some acquaintances, who are physiotherapists and doctors. I received excellent assistance. ”
Return
Luca Engstler admits that she has become impatient during the recovery process. "I was told that I could only do sports again in early February, but of course this could not accept," recognizing that he started training earlier than recommended.
Fortunately to Luca Engstler, DTM only starts on the last weekend of April. In the coming times, the pilot plans to sit back behind the wheel, possibly in a rental kart to start. The aim is to be in shape for the beginning of the preseason and the preparation tests of the popular German championship, scheduled for mid-February and early March.
As for the Macao Grand Prix, two days after the accident, Luca Engstler was quite clear: “I told everyone that my goal is to return and try to fight for victory in this great race.”</description><pubDate>2025-01-12 23:43:24</pubDate></item><item><title>GP Macau | Maro Engel clarified GT World Cup episode</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/01/10/gp-macau-maro-engel-esclareceu-episodio-da-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>Maro Engel won, in an inappropriate race for heart, the FIA ​​GT World Cup in Macao's 71st Grand Prix. However, German's fourth victory among us was anything but peaceful. Maro Engel took advantage of an interview with the German magazine Motorsport Aktuell to explain what happened on the streets of the territory and earned him so many criticism
 
The Germanic pilot, who will turn 40 this year, had a 2024 season full of hits: he won the GT World Challenge Europe, was the best of Mercedes-AMG representatives in the TMD and won a fourth triumph in the Grand Prix of Macao. However, Maro Engel prefers not to highlight a single feat in his 2024 dream season, having referred to his country's expert magazine that “in terms of prestige, the victory in Macao has to be highlighted. But honestly, I don't want to highlight a single moment like the great achievement of this amazing year. I worked hard to reach all these successes. ”
In the since, the triumph of the Bavarian pilot was offered on a tray when the first two ranked ranks, Antonio Foco (Ferrari) and Raffaele Marciello (BMW), fell out in the lock for the Lisbon curve two turns from the end. However, Maro Engel had already been involved in another incident, when, at the beginning of the race, his loneliness, his Mercedes-AMG GT3 gave a subtle touch to the rear of the Vanthoor dries BMW, which followed in front of him in the third position. The young Belgian was projected against the barriers, eventually abandoning due to damage to the suspension of the M4 GT3, while Maro Engel would see the flag axad said first, with an advantage of 11 seconds.
Already at the end of the race, the College of Sports Commissioners decided that the aforementioned touch deserved a penalty of 5 seconds, which had no impact on the final result, leading BMW Motorsport, Andreas Roos, to tell the press that the incident “ It was not adequately penalized. ” Dries Vanthoor, who was also a candidate for victory, went further and said at the time that when “pushing another car out of track, he should not be able to win the race.”

It was not on purpose
Maro Engel's aggressive style was criticized at the time, but the pilot, who debuted to win in Macau in 2014, prefers to point out that “does everything within the boundaries of Fair Play” and thinks it is “hard to accuse a pilot not to try everything to win there (in Macau). ” In the situation in question, Maro Engel wanted to clarify that “I was clearly faster. At the wide part of the circuit at the bottom, I had no chance of attacking, so I tried at the top. It ended up running badly, and that was not my intention. I apologized to the dries later. In general, I run to win. The day you no longer give it all for that, I hang my helmet. I definitely not here to make new friends. ”
Despite the “chair dance” among the car builders involved in the GT3 class in this preseason, Maro Engel will continue to defend the colors of Mercedes-AMG, something that has been doing since 2008, and of course will be one of the stupid brand choices to The World Cup in November, at the Guide Circuit. The natural pilot of Munich is not being removed from the tracks anytime soon, because “I have not reached my peak yet and I still find pleasure in the races.”
In his curriculum, in events held in Macau, Maro Engel has two wins in the GT Macau Cup - FIA GT World Cup (2015 and 2024) and two in the GT Macau Cup (2014 and 2022), but promises not to stay here.</description><pubDate>2025-01-10 06:21:42</pubDate></item></channel></rss>