<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Borders | Thai and Cambodian soldiers in confrontation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/fronteiras-soldados-tailandeses-e-cambojanos-em-confronto/</link><description>Soldiers from Thailand and Cambodia yesterday exchanged shots in a disputed border zone, the armies of both countries reported.
According to a statement from the Thai part, the Cambodian soldiers entered the disputed area and the Thai approached to negotiate. However, due to a misunderstanding, the Cambodian side opened fire and the Thai soldiers retaliated. Cambodia Army spokesman Mao Phalla said the country's troops were performing a routine patrol along the border when the other side opened fire.
The confrontation lasted about ten minutes until local commanders communicated and ordered a ceasefire. The Thai army stated that both parties were negotiating and that the confrontation did not make victims.
The Phnom Penh representative noted that there is no information on any victims so far. Thai Defense Minister Phumtham Wechayachai said the situation is resolved and that the two parts did not intend to make the shots. Thailand and Cambodia, neighboring countries, have a long history of territorial disputes. The incident was recorded on video and became viral on social networks.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:10:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Investment and Development | Tam chi neng appointed president</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/macau-investimento-e-desenvolvimento-tam-chi-neng-nomeado-presidente/</link><description>"It is appointed, under the accumulation of functions, Tam Chi Neng, as Chairman of the Board of Directors of Macau Investment and Development, S.A., for a period of one year."
This is how the Chief Executive officialized Tam Chi Neng's rise to the top of the Macau Investment and Development hierarchy, through an order published yesterday in the official bulletin.
Macau Investment and Development aims to design, manage and exploit spaces for companies and non -business entities, such as the traditional Chinese medical park in Hengqin or the Macao Industry Incubator in Zhongshan.
The entity had been without leadership since the dismissal of Wu Jianfeng from the chairman of the Board of Directors, after the publication of an order signed by Sam Hou Fai at the beginning of last February.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:51:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade Balance | Deficit of 9.4 billion in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/balanca-comercial-defice-de-94-mil-milhoes-em-abril/</link><description>In April, the trade balance deficit was 9.4 billion patacas, according to data published yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). For this amount, contributed exports of goods of 1.12 billion patacas and imports of goods of 10.53 billion patacas.
These numbers mean that, compared to April last year, exports fell 7.7 percent and 4 percent. Regarding April, the value of the re -export descended 7.8 percent to 1.01 billion patacas. The value of jewelery re -exportation decreased 48.9 percent, although the value of alcoholic beverages and beauty, make -up and skin care products has grown 58.8 percent and 46.6 percent.
Regarding the first four months of the year, the trade balance deficit was 36.16 billion patacas, less 2.42 billion patacas, compared to the same period, when the balance deficit was 38.58 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:37:38</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC welcomes debate “challenges of being macanese today!”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/frc-acolhe-debate-desafios-de-ser-macaense-hoje/</link><description>Today, from 6.30 pm, the first session of a new cycle of conferences about the Maca community. The session is called “Challenges of being Macaense today!” and is part of the cycle of lectures “Being Macaense in the 21st century-culture, tradition, identity, challenges”.
Today's lecture is attended by José Luís de Sales Marques, chairman of the Macanese Council of Communities, Elisabela Larrea, researcher, founder and president of Macra - Macanese Culture Research Association; António Monteiro, President of AJM - Association of Young Macanese; Rachel Antonia Handley, Young Member of the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong; and Miguel Silva (via Zoom), affiliate of the Macao House in Portugal and the nephew of the last poet of Patuá, Adé dos Santos Ferreira.
According to a press release, the event aims to address “the way of life of the macanese, the community or the communities in Macao and the diaspora, and their daily challenges to maintain the being and feel of the Macanese reality”. Thus, “the purpose of the conference, and the next in this cycle, is a constructive discussion to look at the present and the future, without forgetting the tradition and the distinctive identity milestones, especially the gastronomy and the theater in Patuá, both intangible heritage of MSAR and RPC”.
The appreciation of the Chinese
At HM, José Sales Marques said that this cycle of debates that begins today is coordinated by itself and seeks to “bring to the table a wide range of personal contributions and, in a way, renew the debate about what it is to be and feel macanese in the 21st century”.
For the person in charge, "challenges are always new, because time is always new, it doesn't go back," there is a "complex current that acts as an accelerator, where things turn to unimaginable speeds."
"We are always discovering and learning, especially with the younger ones. The challenge of identity dilution is not only here in Macao through integration and miscegenation. It happens everywhere. Therefore, we have to understand the pulse of reality and the open mind to recognize that the being macanese can also change with times, maintaining some constant elements," he said.
António Monteiro, on the other hand, said that “Macaense's biggest challenge has always been adapting to several times, moments and conjuncture over the 500 years of Macao”, and today the challenges of belonging to this ethnicity, and preserve it, are “different, especially for the younger ones”.
"Bases were created in Macaense Associativism, many of Portuguese matrix, in the civil society of Macao. We watched a height of" witness pass "or the emergence of new faces in the Macaense community. Dilution will only exist if the Macaense community does not take over as Macaense, culturally or idlely, and is not physically present in Macau," he defended.
The president of AJM recalled that "the Chinese community recognizes and values ​​the macanese and its culture, even in intangible heritage."</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:05:20</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP | MP wants severe penalty for agent aggressor</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/cpsp-mp-quer-pena-severa-para-agressor-de-agente/</link><description>The driver who attacked with a metal bar a police, after being warned for an illegal parking situation, is subject to periodic presentations, prohibition of leaving the territory and had to pay a security
 
The driver who assaulted an agent of the Public Security Police (CPSP) with a metal bar is obliged to present himself periodically before the authorities, forbidden to leave the territory and still had to provide a security. These were the coercion measures applied to man detained on Sunday, according to a statement from the Public Prosecution Service (MP).
"Given the nature, Modus Operandi, the unlawfulness of the facts and the severity of the guilt, the Criminal Instruction Judge, under the promotion of the Public Prosecution Service, applied him the measures of coercion of security, periodic presentation and prohibition of absence," was reported.
On the basis of these measures was the fact that the judge considered to have “strong evidence of the crime of aggravated injury, the crime of damage, resistance and coercion, and the crime of unjustified detention of weapons and other instruments”.
In the statement, the MP warns the population that will always promote “severe penalties” for any citizen who use violence against police officers. "For any kind of crimes involving violence, the Public Prosecution Service not only promotes, under the law, the application of severe punishments, which may still be aggravated under the criminal law, when serious circumstances related to acts of violence against authority agents, but also strive to rigorously investigate the legal responsibilities of infrastructors, defending the dignity and security of the agents." indicated. "The Public Prosecution Service calls on citizens from now on to observe the law, to have a good discipline, to respect and actively cooperate with the work of agents of authority in order to preserve together the good social order of Macao," he was added.
Profanity and aggression
In a statement, the MP indicates that the driver “used profanity to insult the agent […] and brave a metal hydraulic stick” while still inside the vehicle. Then, later, he left the vehicle, "with the stick in his hand, brave her towards the police officer and immediately walked away by car twice."
To the third, says the MP, when the driver was intercepted "descended from the vehicle to assault the police officer with the Court, causing him injuries to his body." "During the detention process, damage to police equipment was also caused," he was completed.
The crime of aggravated injury provides for a 4.5 -month arrest penalty or a fine of 180 days, the crime of 3 -year arrest damage, the crime of resistance and coercion may reach 5 years in prison and the crime of unjustified arrest and other two -year or 240 -day instruments.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:30:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Moody’s keeps rating, but admits negative perspective</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/economia-moodys-mantem-rating-mas-admite-perspectiva-negativa/</link><description>Macao's monetary authority issued a statement to mention the assessment of the good situation of territory finances. However, it left out that the notation was attributed with a negative perspective
 
Financial notation agency Moody’s maintained Macau rating at AA3 level, the highest fourth on the scale, but admits that the prospect for the future is negative. The most recent report, published on Tuesday, indicates that if the territory issues debt to finance itself, it is considered a good investment, although there is a risk that the note is reduced in the near future.
As part of the justification for the notation to be kept at AA3 level, Moody's indicated the strong capacity of the territory to cope with any debts due to the high level of gross per capita domestic product, as well as the fact that the MGRAM has not issued any debt.
Financial reserves are also taken as a good pillow to “absorb” any shocks that result from the “structural slowdown of the Chinese economy”, which is the main Macao market. After Moody’s revealed the maintenance of the rating, the monetary and currency authority of Macao (AMCM) issued a statement that left out of negative perspectives and direct references to the risks associated with the economic situation across the border.
"Moody's maintained the" AA3 "notation, positioned at the fourth higher level, attributed to the MSAR, based on the stable situation of public finances and external payments of the MSAR," was indicated. "In addition, the absence of charges with debt by the Government of MSAR continues to give a strong capacity for resistance to potential external shocks," he was added.
AMCM also highlighted the fact that the economy in 2025 was 85.2 percent of 2019 levels: “Despite the complex challenges and multiple uncertainties that the global economy is currently faced, the economy of MSAR has demonstrated a solid recovery trend. In the first quarter of 2025, the dimension of the local economy reached 85.2 percent of the same period registered at the same period 2019 ”, was highlighted.
Beijing's hand
AMCM has linked the role of the central government in Macao's economic diversification plans: “In addition, with the support of the central government, the government of MSAR is ordered, in an orderly manner, the development of the proper diversification of the economy and regional cooperation, further reinforcing the sustainability of mashed economic growth,” was reported.
The financial notation of different agencies serves as a reference for investors when they make decisions about the debts they buy. The better the assessment, the lower the risk of not being able to pay debts, which leads to the interest paid by the issuers to be lower.
However, as Macau does not issue debt, unlike the interior of China, the notation has not truly impacting, and is an opinion of an external entity on local public finances.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:27:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro | Profit of 17.43 million despite subsidies cuts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/metro-lucro-de-1743-milhoes-apesar-de-cortes-nos-subsidios/</link><description>Without the Budget subsidies of the MSAR, the company that explores the light meter would have presented losses of 660.67 million patacas. However, ticket sales revenues are improving
 
Last year, the profits of the Macao Light Metro Society recorded a reduction of 16.7 million patacas, falling to 17.43 million patacas. The numbers were published yesterday, through the Portal of the Directorate of Services of Supervision and Management of Public Assets (DSSGAP), and the difference can be explained with the reduction of public subsidies.
The result represents a break of 48.9 percent compared to the profit of 34.13 million patacas presented in 2023. For this difference, the government subsidies contributed to the company, and without which the results would always be negative.
In 2023, the government delivered subsidies to the company that explores the 705.47 million Patacas meter. Last year this number had a cut of 48.9 million patacas, falling to 678.10 million patacas.
However, without the support of the MSAR, the company would have lost 660.67 million Patacas last year, which represents an improvement compared to 2023, when without government support the losses would have been 671.34 million patacas. However, companies' revenues show signs of improvement, especially at the level of ticket sales.
Ticket sales revenues rose to 27.06 million patacas, when the previous year had been 13.21 million patacas, which means that within one year more than doubled. This increase was explained by the company with the opening of the Seac Pai line goes in November last year and with the opening of the Hengqin line in December.
Other sources
Also the revenues with the parking lot registered an increase of 596 thousand patacas to 1.3 million patacas. In addition, the sale of cards to use Metro saw the recipes rise from 344 thousand patacas to 676 thousand patacas.
At the same time, “other revenues” were 6.76 million patacas, an increase compared to 4.53 million patacas from the previous year. While interest rates were 52.0 million patacas, when the previous year had been 47.45 million patacas. However, operating expenses grew more than 12 million patacas to 746.77 million patacas by 2024, when the previous year had been 734.15 million patacas.
The highest expenses involved costs with staff that reached 299.70 million Patacas the operation and maintenance of the subway lines that represented expenses of 229.75 million patacas and other expenses that reached 89.68 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:54:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Checks | Traditional associations remove conversion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/cheques-associacoes-tradicionais-afastam-conversao/</link><description>After Pereira Coutinho and Ron Lam if they expressed the conversion of the pecuniary check to a consumer card, deputies of traditional associations joined the opposition. One of them was Lo Choi In, who saw yesterday the citizen newspaper apologize for an article written by AI in which deputy defended the replacement of the supports
 
The controversy regarding the conversion of the form of attribution of the pecuniary check to a consumer card, which restricts where to spend the support and assumes the form of discounts, knew yesterday new contours, with the “choir” of voices of deputies to increase in volume.
The idea returned to the order order after two government-organized meetings with association representatives, about two weeks ago, to hear suggestions on the reform of the monetary reimbursement. In the end, the Executive revealed that someone suggested changing the way they attribute pecuniary checks, converting them into consumption cards to support trade and restoration in community neighborhoods.
Deputy Pereira Coutinho began by criticizing the replacement of support and stated that he would try to know the position of the other deputies elected by direct suffrage, whose associations to which they belong were at meetings with the government. After Ron Lam and Nick Lei, deputies of traditional associations came to join the displeased voices with the idea.
Wong Kit Cheng, deputy from the General Association of Macao Women, Deputy Ngan Iek Hang of the Macao residents 'General Union (Ugamm), and Leong Sun IOK, from the Macao Workers' Associations (Faom), took positions against the change in the way the monetary checks are attributed.
Technological failures
The most caricatured opposition to the change of the form of the pecuniary check came yesterday, with an errata and apology of the citizen newspaper regarding the summary of article written with the appeal to Artificial Intelligence (IA), where it was indicated that LO Choi In, deputy of the association linked to the community of Jiangmen, was favorable to controversial conversion.
The article was published on January 16 this year, but due to the controversy on the subject, resurfaced on social networks where much criticism of the deputy's position reflected in the citizen's article was added.
The summary of the article stated that “the deputy suggests that part of the pecuniary check should be converted to a consumption card” and that the authorities must adjust the allocation of flexibility resources. However, what the deputy actually defended was the application of the amount spared by the exit of the resident program that live outside Macao on a consumption card to encourage consumption in community neighborhoods.
For this reason, the newspaper published a statement yesterday apologizing to Lo Choi In. “Due to AI technical problems, the article appeared with misleading statements, which misunderstanding the original intention of Mrs Lo Choi in about the pecuniary check plan.”
The deputy responded on social networks, sharing the apology of the citizen newspaper, and called on to the public to read the articles with complete content and not to be written with AI software written.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:48:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | “Illicit game” with an increase of more than 900 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/criminalidade-jogo-ilicito-com-aumento-superior-a-900-por-cento/</link><description>The changes to the “Law on Combating Unlawful Game Crimes”, which added the crime of illegal exchange, led to more occurrences. Only in a year was there an increase of 906.3 percent of crimes associated with the “illicit game”. The data are related to the first quarter of this year and were released yesterday by Secretary Wong Sio Chak
 
The law has changed and the crime increased. It was like this with the illegal exchange rate in casinos, as the activity began to be criminalized by the change to the “law to combat illicit gaming crimes” last year.
According to the balance of crime made yesterday, the crimes associated with the illicit game rose 906.3 percent, with 161 cases in the first quarter of this year compared to last year, growth enhanced by illegal exchange cases. The legislative change in question “led to a large increase of this type of crime, especially with regard to illegal exchange,” was mentioned.
In adding the crime of “illicit exchange exchange for game”, it was thus adjusted “the scope of coverage of some related crimes, resulting in the increase in crimes related to the illicit game”, it was added.
At yesterday's press conference, Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, said that police authorities will continue to “reinforce the work of prevention and execution of the law”, and follow “and analyze the development of crime”.
Exchanges and Baldrocas
In general terms, the game -associated crimes also increased, with 567 inquiries, 216 compared to the first quarter of 2024, representing an increase of 61.5 percent.
According to a press release of Wong Sio Chak's office, "it is believed that the main cause of this increase is related to the criminalization of" illegal money "," the dismantling of several relevant criminal networks in joint operations, as well as uncertain factors in society resulting from increased tourist. "
In the overview of the crime, the police instituted, in total, 3,289 criminal investigations, which represents a decrease of 260 cases and translates a decide of 7.3 percent for the same period of the year 2024.
Taxis | More than 700 offenses in three months
Data released yesterday by the executive show how taxi drivers committed to increasing. In the first quarter of this year alone, 773 offenses were registered, with 660 being detected by agents of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP).
According to the authorities, "more than half were situations in which taxi drivers did not wait for the order of customers in taxi squares." Police say they have "dealt with cases in accordance with the law and appealed to offenders not to break the law again."</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:47:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Borders | Thai and Cambodian soldiers in confrontation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/fronteiras-soldados-tailandeses-e-cambojanos-em-confronto/</link><description>Soldiers from Thailand and Cambodia yesterday exchanged shots in a disputed border zone, the armies of both countries reported.
According to a statement from the Thai part, the Cambodian soldiers entered the disputed area and the Thai approached to negotiate. However, due to a misunderstanding, the Cambodian side opened fire and the Thai soldiers retaliated. Cambodia Army spokesman Mao Phalla said the country's troops were performing a routine patrol along the border when the other side opened fire.
The confrontation lasted about ten minutes until local commanders communicated and ordered a ceasefire. The Thai army stated that both parties were negotiating and that the confrontation did not make victims.
The Phnom Penh representative noted that there is no information on any victims so far. Thai Defense Minister Phumtham Wechayachai said the situation is resolved and that the two parts did not intend to make the shots. Thailand and Cambodia, neighboring countries, have a long history of territorial disputes. The incident was recorded on video and became viral on social networks.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:10:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Investment and Development | Tam chi neng appointed president</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/macau-investimento-e-desenvolvimento-tam-chi-neng-nomeado-presidente/</link><description>"It is appointed, under the accumulation of functions, Tam Chi Neng, as Chairman of the Board of Directors of Macau Investment and Development, S.A., for a period of one year."
This is how the Chief Executive officialized Tam Chi Neng's rise to the top of the Macau Investment and Development hierarchy, through an order published yesterday in the official bulletin.
Macau Investment and Development aims to design, manage and exploit spaces for companies and non -business entities, such as the traditional Chinese medical park in Hengqin or the Macao Industry Incubator in Zhongshan.
The entity had been without leadership since the dismissal of Wu Jianfeng from the chairman of the Board of Directors, after the publication of an order signed by Sam Hou Fai at the beginning of last February.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:51:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade Balance | Deficit of 9.4 billion in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/balanca-comercial-defice-de-94-mil-milhoes-em-abril/</link><description>In April, the trade balance deficit was 9.4 billion patacas, according to data published yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). For this amount, contributed exports of goods of 1.12 billion patacas and imports of goods of 10.53 billion patacas.
These numbers mean that, compared to April last year, exports fell 7.7 percent and 4 percent. Regarding April, the value of the re -export descended 7.8 percent to 1.01 billion patacas. The value of jewelery re -exportation decreased 48.9 percent, although the value of alcoholic beverages and beauty, make -up and skin care products has grown 58.8 percent and 46.6 percent.
Regarding the first four months of the year, the trade balance deficit was 36.16 billion patacas, less 2.42 billion patacas, compared to the same period, when the balance deficit was 38.58 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:37:38</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC welcomes debate “challenges of being macanese today!”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/frc-acolhe-debate-desafios-de-ser-macaense-hoje/</link><description>Today, from 6.30 pm, the first session of a new cycle of conferences about the Maca community. The session is called “Challenges of being Macaense today!” and is part of the cycle of lectures “Being Macaense in the 21st century-culture, tradition, identity, challenges”.
Today's lecture is attended by José Luís de Sales Marques, chairman of the Macanese Council of Communities, Elisabela Larrea, researcher, founder and president of Macra - Macanese Culture Research Association; António Monteiro, President of AJM - Association of Young Macanese; Rachel Antonia Handley, Young Member of the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong; and Miguel Silva (via Zoom), affiliate of the Macao House in Portugal and the nephew of the last poet of Patuá, Adé dos Santos Ferreira.
According to a press release, the event aims to address “the way of life of the macanese, the community or the communities in Macao and the diaspora, and their daily challenges to maintain the being and feel of the Macanese reality”. Thus, “the purpose of the conference, and the next in this cycle, is a constructive discussion to look at the present and the future, without forgetting the tradition and the distinctive identity milestones, especially the gastronomy and the theater in Patuá, both intangible heritage of MSAR and RPC”.
The appreciation of the Chinese
At HM, José Sales Marques said that this cycle of debates that begins today is coordinated by itself and seeks to “bring to the table a wide range of personal contributions and, in a way, renew the debate about what it is to be and feel macanese in the 21st century”.
For the person in charge, "challenges are always new, because time is always new, it doesn't go back," there is a "complex current that acts as an accelerator, where things turn to unimaginable speeds."
"We are always discovering and learning, especially with the younger ones. The challenge of identity dilution is not only here in Macao through integration and miscegenation. It happens everywhere. Therefore, we have to understand the pulse of reality and the open mind to recognize that the being macanese can also change with times, maintaining some constant elements," he said.
António Monteiro, on the other hand, said that “Macaense's biggest challenge has always been adapting to several times, moments and conjuncture over the 500 years of Macao”, and today the challenges of belonging to this ethnicity, and preserve it, are “different, especially for the younger ones”.
"Bases were created in Macaense Associativism, many of Portuguese matrix, in the civil society of Macao. We watched a height of" witness pass "or the emergence of new faces in the Macaense community. Dilution will only exist if the Macaense community does not take over as Macaense, culturally or idlely, and is not physically present in Macau," he defended.
The president of AJM recalled that "the Chinese community recognizes and values ​​the macanese and its culture, even in intangible heritage."</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:05:20</pubDate></item><item><title>GARDEN House | Frank Law Exhibition Brand reopening of space</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/casa-garden-exposicao-de-frank-lei-marca-reabertura-do-espaco/</link><description>After being closed for five months for restoration work, Casa Garden, headquarters of the Oriente Foundation in Macau, is preparing to receive the one that is the largest retrospective exhibition of the work of Frank Law, local artist. With the support of the Artistry of Wind Box Community Development Association, it presents, from June 3, “when the island launches its shadows: a retrospective of Frank Law”
 
Local artist Frank Law has won, in recent times, highlight in the local artistic landscape. After the inauguration of the show “Frank Law: Cuba 92”, on the 7th, at the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association, here that Casa Garden now welcomes a new exhibition with works by the deceased artist, with the support of the Artistry of Wind Box Community Development Association.
This is the largest retrospective exhibition of Frank Law's work, entitled “When the Island launches its shadows: a retrospective of Frank Law”, and opens to the public on June 3. According to a note from the organization, this initiative “marks the first big show since the death of artist Frank Lei and presents the most extensive selection of his works to date”, and the audience can view “more than 60 selected photographic pieces”.
These works include “the photographs of law since their studies in France in the 1990s and their subsequent artistic projects after their return to Macao”.
According to the same note, Frank Law is considered a “pioneer of contemporary photography and experimental art in Macao”, and his works “explore not only the aesthetics of photography, but also offer deep criticism and reflections on social realities”. “Through photography, installations and interdisciplinary practices, he challenges the boundaries of art, capturing metaphors and poetry inherent to urban development,” says the organization.
Influences and looks
The show dedicated to Frank Law reveals itself at Casa Garden, headquarters of the Oriente Foundation in Macau, in three rooms that exploit the artist's artistic style and reveal “their aesthetic and cultural influences, interdisciplinary experiences and social and pedagogical practices”.
Also noteworthy is the organization of two parallel exhibitions, entitled “Errante Look: A Margin”, carried out in eight places outside the exhibition space, and “Artist Bookshelf - Frank Law: through the pages at Dialect Photo Library”. It is also expected to perform a series of additional activities, with pop-up tea stands, street photography guided tours and experimental photography workshops for families.
In addition to being a retrospective of Frank Lei's work, this show also takes the opportunity to provide “a deep reflection on the role of contemporary art in society”, and “art enthusiasts and the public are invited to visit and interact with the urban landscape that he once observed, raising reflections on social and local culture”.
According to a note from the Artistry of Wind Box Community Development Association, Frank Law was a “pioneer of contemporary photography and experimental art in Macao”, also making a connection with “the social reality” of Macao. “Through photography, installation and experimentation in various media, it went beyond the limits of art, capturing metaphors and poetics of urban development in Macau - an island defined by contradictions and transformations.”
The curatorship is by Jane Law, Lam Sio Man and Cho Ian Leong. The show ends on June 29. The opening ceremony takes place a few days later at the opening of doors to the public, on June 17, at 18:30.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:04:19</pubDate></item><item><title>UN criticizes new model of food help distribution in Gaza</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/onu-critica-novo-modelo-de-distribuicao-de-ajuda-alimentar-em-gaza/</link><description>UN Chief Agency for Refugees (Unrwa), Philippe Lazzarini, defended yesterday that the new model of food distribution in Gaza, supported by Washington, is a “waste of resources and a distraction from atrocities”.
"I believe it is a waste of resources and a distraction of atrocities. We already have a proper help distribution system. The humanitarian community in Gaza, including Unrwa, is ready. We have the experience and knowledge necessary to reach the needy people," said Lazzarini.
The official added that the time to avoid hunger "is running out" and that humanitarian employees "need to be allowed to make their work save lives now." The new US Humanitarian Foundation (GHF), supported by the US, began its operations on Tuesday at a southern gaza's aid distribution center. According to journalists from France Presse, there were moments of chaos when thousands of people ran from this new center to the center in Rafah.
Chaos installed
Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu acknowledged on Tuesday that there was a "temporary loss of control" in a new Gaza's aid distribution center.
"We have developed a plan with our American friends to control the distribution sites where an American company would distribute food to Palestinian families," Netanyahu said during a speech in Jerusalem, adding that "there was a temporary loss of control" when the Palestinians hosted an open center in Rafah [southern Gaza]. "
The incident occurred at the moment Israel, which in mid -May intensified the offensive in the hungry Palestinian territory, devastated for 19 months of war, is applying a new help distribution system, contested by the humanitarian community.
United Nations agencies have argued that the flow of aid to Palestinian territory is insufficient and limited by restrictions such as crossing of insecure areas due to combat, risk of looting and delays because of coordination with Israelite military.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:08:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospitality | More workers, but wages without increases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/hotelaria-mais-trabalhadores-mas-salarios-sem-aumentos/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), related to the first quarter of this year and out of the inquiry to labor needs and remuneration point to an increase of 7.2 percent in the number of workers in hotels, a total of 60,482 people, compared to the same period of 2024.
However, in salary, the average remuneration of full -time workers in the hotel was 20,090 patacas, 1.9 percent, while in the restoration sector a worker earned an average of 10,540 patacas, less 0.7 percent than 2024.
At the end of the quarter under analysis, the rate of hospitality vacancy lowered only 1.1 percent compared to the first quarter of last year due to the fact that "the vacancies of this branch were filled and the demand for labor to gradually stabilize." Thus, the number of vacancies in that quarter, in the hotels, was 839.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:36:26</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Luo Ping (1733-1799), the unclassifiable Yangzhou painter, at the end of his already widowed life, Buddhist and aged monk, was portrayed by holding a white flower in a lotto. At that time living in a monastery, he would already sign paintings with the name Huazhisi Seng, "The Monk of the Temple of Flowers." And of all the flowers was the white lot, Bailian who accompanied him as if it were a vehicle that opened the ability to move with the beauty of the things of the world, with people.
Because Bailian was the name of a brush of the woman with whom she had married her nineteen. Zhu Shuzhen, the twelve -century century poet writing about the tragic story of Concubine Yang Guifei, spoke of this illuminated look at the beauty that is a crack for the Spirit: “Flutes and stringed instruments made it raise from his skirt of drills,/ his full body and lightly revealed his legs ready to fly. This day,/ the barbarians would not have been able to kill Yang Guifei. »
An enlightened look was what Fang Wanyi (1732-1779), with his name Bailian, will have given Luo Ping, which was seen in his bold paintings. She was, like him, poet and painter and the two made many paintings in common.
Nas pinturas que ela fez sozinha destacava-se como motivo preferido a flor meihua, da árvore prunus mume traduzida habitualmente como ameixieira que, porque florescem ainda no fim do Inverno, era um exemplo de longanimidade. Moreover, the whole family, the couple and the three children were dedicated to the painting of this other white flower.
Fang Wanyi and her husband Luo Ping participated in the usual social encounters among painters, poets and writers with rich Yangzhou salt merchants. This was the case of a party that took place in the spring of 1775 on the property of the merchant Ye Yongting. The name chosen for his Shuizhuang residence, "The Quinta de Só someone," had the character of a question and an allusion to Buddhist doctrine.
As the owner writes in an autobiographical note, he wanted to highlight the constancy of the farm space with the impermanence of his occupant. From this meeting would be made a written memory that resulted in two albums with twenty paintings and thirty -eight caligraffes of several guests and including Luo Ping and Fang Wanyi (paint and paper, 19 x 24.5 cm each, sold on the Bonhams platform).
Some of those who wrote, reinforcing the idea of ​​transience expressed by the host, used the expression Canghai Sangtian, "Blue Sea becoming a field of mulberry", the proverb that alludes to the great changes that occur over time. Perhaps it was what remains in the time that led Luo Ping to hold a white lot flower in his hand or it was he who wanted to distinguish the word that briefly illuminated his gaze.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Luo Ping (1733-1799), the unclassifiable Yangzhou painter, at the end of his already widowed life, Buddhist and aged monk, was portrayed by holding a white flower in a lotto. At that time living in a monastery, he would already sign paintings with the name Huazhisi Seng, "The Monk of the Temple of Flowers." And of all the flowers was the white lot, Bailian who accompanied him as if it were a vehicle that opened the ability to move with the beauty of the things of the world, with people.
Because Bailian was the name of a brush of the woman with whom she had married her nineteen. Zhu Shuzhen, the twelve -century century poet writing about the tragic story of Concubine Yang Guifei, spoke of this illuminated look at the beauty that is a crack for the Spirit: “Flutes and stringed instruments made it raise from his skirt of drills,/ his full body and lightly revealed his legs ready to fly. This day,/ the barbarians would not have been able to kill Yang Guifei. »
An enlightened look was what Fang Wanyi (1732-1779), with his name Bailian, will have given Luo Ping, which was seen in his bold paintings. She was, like him, poet and painter and the two made many paintings in common.
In the paintings she made alone, she highlighted the favorite reason for the Meihua flower, from the Prunus Mume tree commonly translated as a shoe that, because they flourish in late winter, was an example of long-term. Moreover, the whole family, the couple and the three children were dedicated to the painting of this other white flower.
Fang Wanyi and her husband Luo Ping participated in the usual social encounters among painters, poets and writers with rich Yangzhou salt merchants. This was the case of a party that took place in the spring of 1775 on the property of the merchant Ye Yongting. The name chosen for his Shuizhuang residence, "The Quinta de Só someone," had the character of a question and an allusion to Buddhist doctrine.
As the owner writes in an autobiographical note, he wanted to highlight the constancy of the farm space with the impermanence of his occupant. From this meeting would be made a written memory that resulted in two albums with twenty paintings and thirty -eight caligraffes of several guests and including Luo Ping and Fang Wanyi (paint and paper, 19 x 24.5 cm each, sold on the Bonhams platform).
Some of those who wrote, reinforcing the idea of ​​transience expressed by the host, used the expression Canghai Sangtian, "Blue Sea becoming a field of mulberry", the proverb that alludes to the great changes that occur over time. Perhaps it was what remains in the time that led Luo Ping to hold a white lot flower in his hand or it was he who wanted to distinguish the word that briefly illuminated his gaze.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>In April, the trade balance deficit was 9.4 billion patacas, according to data published yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). For this amount, contributed exports of goods of 1.12 billion patacas and imports of goods of 10.53 billion patacas.
These numbers mean that, compared to April last year, exports fell 7.7 percent and 4 percent. Regarding April, the value of the re -export descended 7.8 percent to 1.01 billion patacas. The value of jewelery re -exportation decreased 48.9 percent, although the value of alcoholic beverages and beauty, make -up and skin care products has grown 58.8 percent and 46.6 percent.
Regarding the first four months of the year, the trade balance deficit was 36.16 billion patacas, less 2.42 billion patacas, compared to the same period, when the balance deficit was 38.58 billion.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>In April, the trade balance deficit was 9.4 billion patacas, according to data published yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). For this amount, contributed exports of goods of 1.12 billion patacas and imports of goods of 10.53 billion patacas.
These numbers mean that, compared to April last year, exports fell 7.7 percent and 4 percent. Regarding April, the value of the re -export descended 7.8 percent to 1.01 billion patacas. The value of jewelery re -exportation decreased 48.9 percent, although the value of alcoholic beverages and beauty, make -up and skin care products has grown 58.8 percent and 46.6 percent.
Regarding the first four months of the year, the trade balance deficit was 36.16 billion patacas, less 2.42 billion patacas, compared to the same period, when the balance deficit was 38.58 billion.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 2025
In Chinese proverbial lessons I discovered great affinities between spontaneous Chinese popular philosophy, which runs from mouth to mouth, and the Christian proverbial wisdom, also made so that believers, in every corner of the globe, could memorize, repeat and disseminate.
Nothing like the other's knowledge to bring and dispel prejudice, being one of the most usual that Chinese are extremely pragmatic and cold. But when we come across proverbs such as “love others as yourself,” in a direct translation and faithful to the original “爱人如己” (ài Rú Rú Jǐ), such leads us to think twice, it seems not to be here just a matter of respect, uncharged and formal, but rather a strong feeling for the other, not any, only a deep affection, of those we understand well that we are good, we will be well, we will be well, we will be well, we will be better. Then he runs a love of the Christian way for China without Christ ever been. Such finding can lead us to the assumption of the existence of universal structures, not only logical, including as regards affections, therefore sentimental. After all, selfishness may not be a dominant tendency, there is everything: selfish, aggressive and competitive people, as others will be naturally altruistic, compassionate and cooperatives, ready to recognize the universality of the feeling of love, which crosses borders rather than erecting them, bringing people closer to the most diverse social classes, ethnic groups, geographies, as in "love has no borders", in a direct translation "" (Àiqíng wú jiējí zhī fēn), here is particularly emphasized social borders.
The content of the message gains full sense when one realizes that love to oneself takes place in a culture that many consider wrong and prejudiced only to focus on the whole, in the community.  Attention to the person, the particular and the style and feeling of each, lives, in philosophies such as Taoist for centuries with the valorization of the collectivity, this ultimate tendency manifestly inculcated and worked by Confucianism.  Love to itself, care for the individual body and mind, is emphasized in the so -called Proverbial “well -understood love and virtue must begin with us”, which has the following correspondence in Chinese “爱德从己起” (to Cong Jǐ qǐ).
Anyone who imagines that in proverbial wisdom there is only place to praise and sing relational love, since the Chinese do not have any religious philosophy that chants spiritual love above all, in the Christian way of St. Augustine, will be surprised to find the following proverb "where there is no other gentleman", that in a direct translation of the Chinese is "the love above all" 爱情至上 爱情至上 爱情至上ZHì Shàng).
If in doubt, there is another saying of complementary meaning and in which the idea of ​​the integrity and unity of this powerful affection, which moves mountains in the Christian sense, when it reads 爱情专一 （（（（iqíng zhuān yī）, in a possible translation "love cannot be broken", "one person cannot have a heart in two parts at the same time."
From a psychological point of view, the acceptance of the other in loving terms will have to be complete, so their tastes, affections, relationships, and objects cannot be rejected, as is clear from the lesson "Who loves Beltrão, loves their dog", in a relative correspondence for "爱屋及乌" (ài wū jí wū), which in a literal translation would be "love the house and the crums."
As is well known, proverbs are susceptible to various interpretations, so they say polysemic, but if they are perspective as a whole, and only then as pieces of a puzzle, there seems to be many doubts with regard to the proverb philosophy and psychology of Chinese love, which is echoed in the country's scholarly philosophies.
In Chapter 67 of the Book of the road and virtue (《道德经》), also known by the name of the Patriarch of Taoism, Lazi (老子), is the first of the three guiding virtues of the Wise Way, love, as you can read in the translation of Claudia Ribeiro (2004, 139):
I have three treasures
What entesouro and retains:
The first is love (CI),
The second frugality,
The third is not daring to be the vanguard of the world.
(…)
For love,
In combat, it triumphs,
And in defense it is firm.
The sky will come to aid
And, with love, will protect
(我有三寶/寶而持之/一曰慈/二曰儉/三曰不敢為天下先 (……) 夫慈以戰則勝//以守則固/以慈衛之 1)
It is noted that while in proverbial philosophy the synogram used for love is 爱/愛 2 (AI), in the scholarly philosophy of the Patriarch of Taoism the term employment is 慈 (CI), that is, love with a strong relational and spiritual burden; Although they are different words, both refer to love, the first concerns the most physical and concrete feeling, centered on the heart of the person and the clutches that hold it;  The second to that most relational and general indicates that love comes from inside the heart (内心 nèixīn), where it has the roots, emerging like any plant. However, the truth is that both terms focus on people, or rather in their hearts, affectionate connection with others, such a strong connection that draws the attention of heaven (天 tiān), maximum impersonal power, it ensures victory on all battle fronts, whether in the forefront or rear, when fighting and defended itself for love.
Already the patriarch of Confucianism, Confucius (孔子), in the Chapter Twelve, later entitled the deep face, of the Analects (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 22) defines the main virtue of the school, benevolence or humanity, (仁 Rén) as an act of love to others, maintaining the term of the traditional vernacular 爱 (AI): “Fan Chi asked what was the benevolence was what answered, "love people". " (樊遲問仁 ， 子曰 「愛人 3。 ”) It is in this context of love of neighbor, that one of the main maxims of Confucian philosophy must be understood, which arises in the same chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 2)“ Do not make the others what they do not want for you ”(己所不欲勿施於人 jǐ suǒ bù yù shunk yú rén).
The essentials in Confucian philosophy will then guarantee love of others in terms of respect or humanity towards others, in order to ensure the normal functioning of society, without extreme sacrifices or exaggerated explorations, given to the proverb containment of confusion in relation to feelings, they are important and useful but should not extravate the boundaries of rationality, that is, even the best of them, will have to be measured, controlled and ritualized in the name of harmony collective. Therefore, the love that moves friendships, especially intellectuals, is the most praised, as we remembered at the end of this chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 24):
Zeng Zi stated: “A gentleman resorts to knowing to make friends and friends to cultivate benevolence4” (曾子曰：君以文會友 ， 以友輔仁。)
Finally, also the Buddhist philosophy, especially from the Chan (禅 Chán) or Zen meditation line, praises the love of humanity, but indirectly, drawing attention to the heart and the identification of Buddha with the heart, the way of the Daoxin Patriarch (道信) and its maximum proverbially known “the heart is Buddha and Buddha is the heart” (非心不问佛 ， 问佛不非心 fēi xīn bùwèn fu, wèn fi bù fēi xīn). Here you come to love indirectly, only an enlightened heart can love the Buddha, as it is not surprising in the picture of this philosophy, after all what is Buddha but the very love that expresses itself not in a selfish, sick, self -centered heart, but in a heart capable of establishing relationships, healthy, altruistic and without empty, but not indifferent to the other?  This confirms it the social and humanitarian actions of Via Mahayana Buddhism, which was accepted in China and unfolds in collective works such as the construction of educational institutions, hospitals, centers of social solidarity, in a proselytist action at all similar to the history of the Christian Church and its missionaries around the world.
Bibliographic references
Lansheng, Jiang (Comp.) 1997. 100 Excerpts from Zen Buddhist Texts. Hong Hong Kong: Commercial Press.
NGAN, António André. 1998. SINE-SHORE CONGRELLANCE OF PROVERBS AND IDIOMATIC PHRASES. 中葡對照成語集. Macau: Macao Adult Association.
RIBEIRO, Claudia (Trad). 2004. 《道德經》 The Book of Road and Power. Bilingual edition. Mem-Martins: European American Publications.
Xin Guanjie (辛冠洁) (org. And trad.) 1994. 《論語》 .Tradument for contemporary Chinese falls xiqin (蔡希勤) and English translation of Lai Bo (赖波) and Xia Yuhe (夏玉和). Beijing: Sinolingue.
References:
Text in classic Chinese.
Love in simplified and traditional Chinese.
Text in classic Chinese.
A gentleman in ancient Chinese times was a gentleman and a potential ruler.
“This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors” https://www.cccm.gov.pt</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Literature | Must bets on Camões translation project to Chinese</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/literatura-must-aposta-em-projecto-de-traducao-de-camoes-para-chines/</link><description>The University of Science and Technology of Macau is betting on Luís de Camões translation projects. At a time when they celebrate the 500th anniversary of the birth of the poet, Filipe de Saavedra, Academic of the Local University, speaks of the initiative and the Middle Middle Congress of the Birth of Luís de Camões, in Mozambique
 
Last year, 500 years were completed from the birth of the one who is considered the greatest Portuguese poet of all time. Luís de Camões, author of the epic “Os Lusíadas”, was born in 1524, sailed the seas and traveled lands where the Portuguese walked, namely Mozambique, Goa and Macao, among others, and on them left poems and writings in letters. Its importance is mirrored in the celebrations of June 10 - Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese Communities.
All the literary manifestations that Camões has left written will now be translated into Chinese thanks to a project that has been developed by the University of Science and Technology of Macao (Must, English acronym). Filipe de Saavedra, specialist in the life and work of Luís de Camões, professor and researcher at this University and PhD in Portuguese Studies, spoke to HM about the project.
“Our translations will come out of a project ongoing at UCTM [Must in the Acronym in English] where the full translation of Chinese of all lyrical genres and letters of Camões is foreseen. Students have been exposed to the poet from the first year of the degree in Portuguese studies to the master's degree, and their response is enthusiastic. Macao '. We had already had the same success with the Indonesian students.
"The most ambitious project is that of the critical edition of the work, which we are starting with letters and odes. It will combine the accumulated efforts of various generations of scholars with our new readings of the manuscripts, and new interpretations. It will be the most lasting and most necessary contribution by these celebrations," added the Camonist.
Must also have the theater studio project in which “students represent Camões”, and this year in this year's poetry contest, students chose to recite Camões, demonstrating great sensitivity to his poetry ”. For Filipe de Saavedra, "the seed is launched, and from there will come the translators and camons of the future."
Given Macau's strong connection in the life of Luís de Camões, the territory welcomed the “I Congress of Middle Millennium”, representing academics from various countries with studies around the figure, work and life of Luís de Camões.
The balance made by Filipe de Saavedra is quite positive. “We have already brought three times the master-transtor Zhang Weimin, always with the support of the Oriente Foundation, which gave several master classes on how to translate Camões into Mandarin to UCTM's most advanced courses.”
In this context, Must has established "protocols with foreign universities where there are Camonian centers for common initiatives." One of the most recent was with Eduardo Mondlane University in Mozambique to hold the second edition of the same Congress next June, Maputo and the Island.
Camões in Mozambique
According to Philip de Saavedra, "Congress takes place on special days for Camões, and in places he dwelt: February 25, the most likely date of his birth and March 12, the date of the publication of the epic; and now June 10, the poet's death day in Lisbon."
"As Camões lived two years on the island of Mozambique, late or early we would go. Congresses had already been held about Camões in Portugal and Brazil, but this is the first that gathers throughout Africa, and in Asia we also did two, one in Indonesia and one in Macao, the first on this continent," he explained.
In Mozambique, the professor will talk about “about Africans in general [present] in the work of Camões”, and other academics will “take care of his relationship with Mozambique, with other people who have passed through the time he was there, of translation issues that are always primal, and the teaching of Camões in schools”. According to the Academic, this Congress has the support of the Portuguese National Commission for the celebrations of the V Centenary of Camões.
Filipe de Saavedra is also part of the “Camões Network in Asia &amp; Africa”, which brings together several experts in Camões and has organized the Middle Millennium Congresses. "The chamonism network we have implemented in Asia will be true to its translating meeting point matrix with exegetes. It is characterized by a global and plural perspective, centered on texts, but anchoring equally on the vital experience of the poet, specifically in his Asian and African experiences. This is a different point of view from that of Portugal."
The III Middle Millennium Congress will take place next year in Goa, in partnership with the University of Goa. "We will deepen the relations of Camões with India of that time, and not only with Portuguese India. We are offering co-inmates to Indian students of Master and PhD who want to work Camões, as well as bibliographic assistance. We will also invest in the search for new translators of Camões poetry for the various Indian languages," he said.
Missing writings
Asked what the poet's work is to be analyzed and investigated, the Must researcher highlights the few advances at the level of the work, and more in the biographical aspect. “In the twentieth century, and in what goes from the 21st, it has advanced above all in the knowledge of Camões's life. But as for the work, progress has been slower. Despite the fundamental contributions provided by Portuguese and foreign scholars, it can be said that no lyric editions are still up to its whole as definitive, and the same as those of theater.
Philip de Saavedra points out that "a lot is done and a lot is to do," but as far as the poet's hectic life is concerned, "there are many aspects of Camões's life where we even know too much, on matters that he might have not liked to know so much."
"Even the study of the lyric would already be an abuse for him, since he did not want to gather or publish, when he could easily have done it after the success of" Os Lusíadas ". It was a renegade part of his work, not to mention the private letters, some very private. Therefore all this excess of knowledge, this one knows almost everything about life and about the work of Camões, represents for us a miracle, and for him," he added.
For Philip de Saavedra, "the distressing dilemma between respecting the will and privacy of an author, and pending to the intimate recesses his earthly existence, even probing his most intimate thoughts." "Here we are forced to weigh the interest of the individual on the one hand, ideally assistance, and the interest of culture and history by the other, which is greater and sovereign. It wins the second, and that Camões forgive us," he concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 22:56:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | As Bachará and businessman Yip Hon helped cement STDM</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/jogo-como-o-bacara-e-o-empresario-yip-hon-ajudaram-a-cimentar-a-stdm/</link><description>Jorge Godinho, a jurist and expert in the history of the Macao game, published an article that highlights the legacy of Stanley Ho and how Bachará and businessman Yip Hon were essential in the construction of the Empire of the Macao Tourism Society. Yesterday five years were completed of the death of the king of the game of Macao
 
The magazine “Gaming Law Review” has just been published, an analysis article by academic Jorge Godinho who portrays the essential pieces that helped build the EMTDM Empire - Macao's Tourism and Amusement Society and the legacy that Stanley Ho has left in the game industries and entertainment of the territory. The founders of STDM were Yip Hon, Teddy Yip, Henry Fok and Stanley Ho.
In “The Place of Stanley Ho (1921-2020) In Macao Casino Gaming History” [The Place of Stanley Ho (1921-2020) in the history of the Casino game in Macao], it is concluded that given the little knowledge and mastery of the functioning of the Fortune Games and unlucky by the Hong Kong tycoon, it turned out to be Yip Hon the great stratega of STD in this area. And that, in the early years, Bachará was the game that gave fortune to the pockets of STDM managers.
“Yip Hon was behind the main changes of 1975-1976: the turn to the baccará and the use of a game promoters network. Stanley Ho was a very intelligent entrepreneur, with an extremely attentive look at business opportunities. It was decisive in taking the opportunity offered by reforms and the 1961-1962 public contest and creating STDM. However, this is not necessarily the same as having experience in game In general and in Bachará in particular, ”wrote Jorge Godinho at the conclusion.
The visiting professor at the University of Macao and teacher at Ismat - Instituto Superior Manuel Teixeira Gomes cites a dialogue between Stanley Ho and CNN journalist Lorraine Hahn, in an interview of 2004, in which she assumes her weak knowledge of the intricacies of the game's functioning.
“I don't realize anything about gambling, I still don't play. I got this concession because it was a challenge for myself, because I can't see why Hong Kong was so prosperous and Macau was a dying city, just 40 miles away. So, once again, I love challenges, I presented a proposal and won the concession. Stanley Ho, adding that he was only interested in sport. “Well, I like that name [King of the Game], but to be very frank I don't deserve this 'king of the casino', I don't play, how can I be the king of the casino?” Stanley Ho asked in response to the journalist.
Jorge Godinho's article points out that “in the early years, and during the period when the great turn to Bachará, the driving force of the game on STDM was Yip Hon (1904-1997), the true expert of the STDM game”, whose importance was recognized by Stanley Ho himself.
"Due to the time I spent in Macau, I knew everyone there and, in 1961, when there was a contest for the game concession, I joined some friends and made a proposal for the casino-and we won the franchise. I was working with Mr. Henry Fok, my brother-in-law Teddy Yip and Yip Hon, who was a professional player." Magnata, quoted in the article.
Yip Hon was "the only shareholder of STDM game expert", and in the early years of the company, Bachará gradually assumed more importance, gaining prominence against games such as Blackjack and Roulette, "both in the mass market and in the segment of the big bets."
Data cited by Jorge Godinho, from the direction of inspection services and games coordination, at the time with the name inspection of game contracts, show a “obvious” rise of Bachará, which was the biggest game in 1977, with 37 percent of market share, and 65 percent quota in 1984. “On the other hand, all other games decreased their relative weight,” adds the author of the article.
Divide the cake
The STDM monopoly in Macao lasted exactly 40 years and three months-from January 1, 1962 to March 31, 2002, when authorities decided to liberalize the market, bringing to the US concessionaires territory.
The article is referred to in Stanley Ho's public position regarding the arrival of new operators and the style of company that brought news to what was going on in Macao, with more international event events. "They want to imitate Las Vegas, create large spaces focused on family entertainment. This is good for Macau. As for our usual customers, they come to play as soon as they enter the casino. They have no time to see other things," said the Magnata.
From the STDM was born the Macau Game Society (SJM) that ran for the public tender for the assignment of new concessions and which won one, but for Jorge Godinho there may have been a poor analysis of future competition, which partly affected the operator's position.
"SJM may have forgotten its own past and may have repeated some of the mistakes made by TAI Heng in the 1961 public tender, starting with overconfidence. SJM may have understood that, as one of the concessions would always be attributed, it would not be worth making 'excessive' commitments. This approach turned out to be incorrect," he reads.
The study refers to 1961, when the previous concessionaire to STDM, Tai Heng Ltd, faced this contest “too optimistic and may have underestimated potential competition in a competition process in which the decision is essentially based on a very simple and direct base: the amount of the offered income”. "Tai Heng may have expected that there was no competition, given the amount of the necessary investment," said Jorge Godinho.
Competition
In 2001, Macao had left behind the Portuguese administration and was already mashed. The analyzes of the future of the game without monopoly were therefore prudent. "Although in 2001 it was believed that there was the potential to grow and transform the market through the introduction of competition, at the time expectations were not very high. In a somewhat conservative, careful or incremental movement, the decision was made (only) three concessions. In fact, in 2001, no one could have predicted the huge development that actually occurred in the following years."
The crime marked by sects in the late 1990s was "very fresh" and "the decision makers were very prudent." "There were questions about whether large international companies would be present in the 2001 public tender. There was also the perception that many years would be needed for new operators to effectively generate some kind of significant competition for the old STDM monopoly."
According to Jorge Godinho, "with the benefit of the retrospective, it is quite clear that these perceptions were not in accordance with what happened," because "the years that followed 2001 were characterized by historical growth and qualitative transformations."
Jorge Godinho recalls that although it was “widely expected that one of the concessions was attributed to SJM”, the truth is that the company “was classified in third place - which is not an excellent position”. "Perhaps because pre-concessioned investment projects were not seen as the best for what was intended to be a future dominated by mass tourism in Macau and with increasing diversification. SJM will have estimated that the new competition would not remove it too much market share, especially in the VIP sector," he added.
The place today
At the time of the development of the first projects of great wingspan in Cotai, Jorge Godinho highlights how the “driving force was Venetian, led by Sheldon Adelson”, who brought to the territory the largest casino in the world, the Venetian. It was “a very strong bet in Macau, which gave good results,” said the author of the study, who points out that SJM quickly lost ground in the market.
"The lead role in these projects [at Cotai] was not played by SJM. The loss of SJM market share began in 2004 and was relatively rapid. In 2009, SJM continued to lead, 31 percent of quota, but market leadership was lost in 2014 and never returned. Godinho.
The study also brings data on the current position of SJM after the hard years of the pandemic, and already in the context of the attribution of new gambling licenses, totaling six.
“SJM was the last operator to open a large resort integrated in the Cotai area”, it reads, following that, from the third quarter of 2023, the market share by GGR [Gross Gaming Revenue-Gross Revenue] was 26.9 percent for Venetian, 18 percent for Galaxy, 14.6 percent for MGM, 14.5 percent For Melco, 13.4 percent for Wynn and 12.1 percent for SJM.
Thus, what has occurred in recent years was “the inevitable loss of importance of SJM” taking into account “intense competition since the end of the monopoly in 2001”. “SJM is currently in the last position. SJM Resorts is the main casino operator in Macao only in a specific metric: the number of casinos (13). This is mainly due to its long history and the legacy of 'satellite casinos'. 2022, the SJM was classified in sixth position - the last among historical operators ”, stresses Jorge Godinho.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 23:00:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Nanfang Media | Guangdong Group creates platform with Portugal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/nanfang-media-grupo-de-guangdong-cria-plataforma-com-portugal/</link><description>On Friday, a media cooperation platform was launched, promoted by the Nanfang Media group, based in Guangdong and offices in Macau. The “Chinese-Portuguese Platform of Media Contents to the Great Bay” aims to “reform media cooperation and facilitate the exchange of cultural news and content between China and Portuguese-speaking countries”
 
A new platform has just been created to exchange news and cultural content between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. The project is from Nanfang Media Group, based in Guangdong Province and offices in Macau, and calls it "Greater Bay Area Chinese-Sports Media Content Platform." This is an integrated project in the internationalization and expansion of the Chinese group and which was launched last Friday in Lisbon, integrated at the Chinese-Portuguese Culture Festival “Chinese Styles, Portuguese Flavors” [Chinese styles, Portuguese flavors], which took place at Quinta da Marmeleira headquarters in Lisbon.
Nanfang Media Group, which has titles such as GD Today, in English, now wants to reach the Portuguese language universe and a “global audience of about 300 million Portuguese speakers,” wrote this publication. Also there is also describing that the great purpose of this new platform is to “reinforce media cooperation and facilitate the exchange of news and cultural content between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
In his speech, Zhao Yang, chief of wording of the “International South” portal, linked to the Nanfang group, presented the main objectives of this platform, namely “strengthening collaboration with Portuguese media," Think Tanks "and other institutions and presenting, more affordablely, stories about China's business environment, large bay and guangdong."
It is also aiming to show the economic and social modernization that China has known in recent years, as well as showing “sino-Portuguese pragmatic cooperation and friendship between the two peoples”.
Thus, this contact platform also aims to “take advantage of the potential of artificial intelligence in order to promote our media in the digital age”. “I hope this initiative can contribute, with the force of the media, to the dialogue between civilizations and deepening a comprehensive cooperation between China and Portugal,” said Zhao Yang.
The official also explained that "in the last two years, and through the use of journalistic advantages in Macao, South has reinforced collaboration with the Sino-Portuguese platform, Lusa agency or other Portuguese-speaking communication bodies, widely spreading stories about Portuguese to live and work in the great country [China], Hong Kong and economic cooperation between Guangdong and Portugal." It should be noted that the Nanfang group, chaired by Liu Qiyu, currently holds the Portuguese radio Iris FM, based in Samora Correia and Lisbon.
President Words
Liu Qiyu, president of Nanfang Media Group, highlighted the fact that this platform is launched at a time when the 500th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations between China and Europe are celebrated, as well as “the 20th anniversary of establishing a comprehensive strategic partnership between China and Portugal”.
Referring to the group he leads, which has “wide national and international influence and is rooted at China's main economic province in Guangdong,” Liu Qiyu spoke of the idea of ​​internationalizing the group, “striving to build international bridges and promoting dialogue between civilizations”.
"We want to reinforce cooperation with the media around the world in order to promote a global understanding between peoples," he said. The official said he hoped the new platform "can gather the wisdom and strength of the media of both countries to tell stories of the Lusophone world and the stories of Guangdong, the Great Bay and China, and also to take stories from Portugal and Europe to China, especially to Guangdong."
The president of the Nanfang group did not forget the role of Macau in connection with the Hengqin zone, at a time when “the role of the region as an economic and commercial service platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Camões and Ronaldo
Zhao Bentang, China's ambassador in Lisbon, was present at the event, noting that "Chinese and Portuguese civilizations are valued, learn and coexist harmoniously, which benefits people on both sides, also making important contributions to peace and world development."
"Linguistic and cultural cooperation between China and Portugal has suffered a rapid process," he said, noting that in recent years Chinese culture has increasingly popular abroad, while Portugal "was one of the first European countries to communicate with China." It is a story “over 500 years”, having created “a solid basis for common development” and greater cultural exchange, he said.
Zhao Bentang did not forget the highlight that football and literature in Portuguese have had in China. "Cristiano Ronaldo is a well -known name in China, and the excellent works of Portuguese writers such as Camões, Fernando Pessoa or José Saramago can be found in all Chinese bookstores," he recalled.
The Sino-Portuguese Cultural Festival where the launch of this new media platform was part of Chinese cuisine and also macanese and Portuguese dishes, signed by Michael Franco, Macaense Hong Kong that recently opened a new restaurant in Lisbon, Dragon Inn.
Moreover, the event, supported by several entities, such as the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry (CCILC), had wine tamings and demonstrations of Chinese culture, with handwriting and wearing traditional robes.
Bernardo Mendia, Secretary-General of CilC, stressed that China created, 71 years ago, the idea of ​​“mutual respect and peaceful coexistence between nations, the celebrated five principles of peaceful coexistence, which are no more than a manifestation of respect for third party culture, without the pretense of changes or impositions, as if some cultures were superior to others”.
The official stressed that, in economic links, "culture is an essential and even previous element as a way to enhance the good bilateral relationship and mutually beneficial business realization."
In this sense, Bernardo added, "respect for culture is non -negotiable," because it is "an intangible good, because it is composed of values, beliefs, customs and traditions, transmitted from generation to generation through practices, rituals and expressions that result in the very identity of a people or community."
According to GD Today, Bernardo Mendia said "that media can help us break barriers and facilitate communication", and the new platform could have "huge meaning in the connection between Portugal and China."
Referring to the debate that currently exists in Portugal, about the end of bullfighting, Bernardo Mendia pointed out that “the races of Portuguese bumps” are part of culture, something “prior to the power of the state itself, which is legitimized by the respect of the culture of its people and communities”. Thus, in this context, the Secretary General of Cilc lamented that the state tries to “impose a culture-a phenomenon called the 'state culture'”. In such cases, “chaos is installed, as we recently witnessed in the western world with the attempt to impose Woke culture by some states,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 00:18:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | “Illicit game” with an increase of more than 900 percent</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/criminalidade-jogo-ilicito-com-aumento-superior-a-900-por-cento/</link><description>The changes to the “Law on Combating Unlawful Game Crimes”, which added the crime of illegal exchange, led to more occurrences. Only in a year was there an increase of 906.3 percent of crimes associated with the “illicit game”. The data are related to the first quarter of this year and were released yesterday by Secretary Wong Sio Chak
 
The law has changed and the crime increased. It was like this with the illegal exchange rate in casinos, as the activity began to be criminalized by the change to the “law to combat illicit gaming crimes” last year.
According to the balance of crime made yesterday, the crimes associated with the illicit game rose 906.3 percent, with 161 cases in the first quarter of this year compared to last year, growth enhanced by illegal exchange cases. The legislative change in question “led to a large increase of this type of crime, especially with regard to illegal exchange,” was mentioned.
In adding the crime of “illicit exchange exchange for game”, it was thus adjusted “the scope of coverage of some related crimes, resulting in the increase in crimes related to the illicit game”, it was added.
At yesterday's press conference, Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, said that police authorities will continue to “reinforce the work of prevention and execution of the law”, and follow “and analyze the development of crime”.
Exchanges and Baldrocas
In general terms, the game -associated crimes also increased, with 567 inquiries, 216 compared to the first quarter of 2024, representing an increase of 61.5 percent.
According to a press release of Wong Sio Chak's office, "it is believed that the main cause of this increase is related to the criminalization of" illegal money "," the dismantling of several relevant criminal networks in joint operations, as well as uncertain factors in society resulting from increased tourist. "
In the overview of the crime, the police instituted, in total, 3,289 criminal investigations, which represents a decrease of 260 cases and translates a decide of 7.3 percent for the same period of the year 2024.
Taxis | More than 700 offenses in three months
Data released yesterday by the executive show how taxi drivers committed to increasing. In the first quarter of this year alone, 773 offenses were registered, with 660 being detected by agents of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP).
According to the authorities, "more than half were situations in which taxi drivers did not wait for the order of customers in taxi squares." Police say they have "dealt with cases in accordance with the law and appealed to offenders not to break the law again."</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:47:15</pubDate></item><item><title>CCCM | Launched bilingual edition of book on human science</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/23/cccm-lancada-edicao-bilingue-de-livro-sobre-ciencia-humana/</link><description>Human science, which aims to “integrate all areas of human knowledge”, was the subject of a book by Maria Burguete and Lui Lam released in 2015. Now the bilingual edition of “Science Matters - Human Science, a unified perspective on humanities and sciences”, edited with the support of the University of Macau. The work was presented on Wednesday at the Scientific and Cultural Center of Macau
 
There was a time when philosophy was the basis of knowledge before other areas of knowledge emerge. However, the exact sciences from the humanities, the art of philosophy, as completely different areas, are now separated. Maria Burguete, scientist and president of the Science Matters Association, established in Portugal, launched on Wednesday the book Bilingual “Science Matters-Human Science, a unified perspective on humanities and sciences”, written with Chinese scientist Lui Lam. The work seeks to demonstrate how all areas of knowledge can live and live together, in a kind of complementarity, without forgetting philosophy.
The book was presented at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) and was supported by various entities, namely the University of Macau and the Rocha Cabral Institute.
First launched in 2015, the work is now edited in a bilingual version, in Portuguese and Chinese, in order to gather the work that has been developed by Maria Burguete, a doctorate in science stories in Germany and with biochemistry base formation, and scientist Lui Lam. It is at the Science Matters Association, which has been linked, since 2018, the Center Science Matters, that Maria Burguete gives courses on the concept of “human science”, while Lui Lam is dedicated to the same work in China.
At Wednesday's session, Maria Burguete explained that human science, Portuguese translation of the concept “Science Matters”, aims to “integrate all areas of human knowledge, including natural, social and human sciences, under the scientific paradigm”. Thus, "the idea is that all aspects related to humans can be scientifically studied, breaking with the traditional divisions between the natural and human sciences", promoting "the unification of all the knowledge produced by the human species in a single multidiscipline." Therefore, the areas of humanities and the arts with the social sciences, or the humanities with the medical sciences, are included.
According to the author, human science brings a “unifying vision of knowledge”, being “a new multidiscipline that is like a new 21st century philosophy”. It is a “new approach to knowledge, where common patterns are recognized” to all areas, he explained.
Maria Burguete says she had contact with the concept from the ideas of English nuclear physicist Charles Percy Snow, who in a Cambridge lecture in 1959 presented the idea of ​​the “two cultures”, a separation between the exact sciences and the humanities, as two opposite poles.
“My basic formation is biochemistry and chemical engineering. Therefore, I am very linked to the natural sciences. And there was a time when C.P. Snow, when I was a teacher in Cambridge, gave a conference where he spoke of the existence of two cultures. This was a scandal at the time, because it seemed that there was scientific culture and all who were not within this scientific culture. of the rest, and that has to end. ”
For Maria Burguete, “it makes no sense to create barriers” because “all areas complement each other”. "All areas, one way or another, are subject to a very similar paradigm of knowledge. How do you form, where they come from and where they go? They all go through these steps. Of course, the approaches are different, as is literature, arts or chemistry, but they remain areas of knowledge development," he added.
The Role of Philosophy
Maria Burguete's contact with Lui Lam was at the time of the 20th World Congress of the History of Science, which took place in Beijing in 2005. “Then I presented a new epistemology, and my physical colleague, who is physically, was enchanted and came to me, proposing a new multidiscipline, because I said, how I know is transverse,” he said to HM.
Moreover, this bilingual work is born from a six -volume editorial project, and this edition is only the first volume. The conferences promoted by Maria Burguete and Lui Lam related to the theme of human science scored in 2007 and several editions took place in 2009, 2011, 2013, 2015, 2017 and 2019. What was said in these conferences was compiled in English, editing now, in the book presented on Wednesday.
The academic believes that “everything came up with philosophy”, referring to the period of classical antiquity. "Philosophy was the main milestone of knowledge, and only then did the areas of knowledge begin to diverge."
Álvaro Rosa, Macaense and professor at ISCTE - University Institute of Lisbon, left some of the themes that can be found on the work, namely the history of science in China. "For those interested in China's problems, this book helps us understand how China faces and sees the history of sciences, and how science communication is done," he said.
"China is not exactly the same as the West, it has its characteristics, and this book helps us understand how China sees this and other issues. It is a book that is worth reading, made for open minds, so that one can discuss knowledge without a vocabulary or approach too technical," added Álvaro Rosa.
Álvaro Rosa launched the refers to the CCCM audience with the example of how the beauty or the ugliness of something is viewed. “We often say that tastes are not discussed. The scientist begins by classifying which things are beautiful and ugly and then performs an inquiry, starting to observe whether or not there is ugliness, putting everything in categories. There is a completely different approach from the humanist. Therefore, the idea of ​​Maria Burguete is to cover all the themes related to humanity within what we call, in the sense of what we can, in the same way as we can put, in the same way as we can put, in the same way as we can put, what we can put, in the same way as we can put, in the same way as we can put, what we can put, in the sense of what we can put, in the same way as we can put, in the same way as we can put, in the sense of what we can put, in the same way we can put it in the same way as we can Hat, the study of all topics and their interpretation. I find it very interesting, ”said Álvaro Rosa.
“An integrated perspective”
Ana Cristina Alves, coordinator of the CCCM Educational Service and formed in the area of ​​Chinese philosophy and culture, argued that the book of Maria Burguete and Lui Lam presents “a holistic and integrated perspective” of knowledge.
"Western philosophy looks at Chinese philosophy as not being philosophy, staring at it as poorly scientific, because it does not start and does not end in logic," he said, speaking of the example of integrating existing knowledge in traditional Chinese medicine.
"Traditional Chinese medicine is all supported by philosophy, its substrate is philosophy. When there is no integrated and holistic philosophical perspective, what is done in medicine is to receive patients in five minutes and ready. And what is important for a good diagnosis is to realize the ills that afflict the patient. This is only possible from an integrated perspective," he said.
In this sense, Maria Burguete argued that a doctor should not end her formation without "having at least three years of philosophy, because treating people is not only to treat the body physically, but also to realize the person in front of him."</description><pubDate>2025-05-23 06:18:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Foreign language students increasingly use AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/19/estudo-alunos-de-linguas-estrangeiras-usam-cada-vez-mais-a-ia/</link><description>A study by academics at Macao Polytechnic University concludes that 80 percent of a sample of 25 Portuguese students “regularly uses” artificial intelligence as a study tool. The authors of the study warn of the need for combination with traditional teaching and teacher education methods
 
To what extent is Artificial Intelligence (AI) being used by Chinese students to learn foreign languages, and how is this use done? A study developed by academics and teachers at Macao Polytechnic University (UPM) Vanessa Amaro and Manuel Pires concludes that the use is growing.
The work, entitled “Artificial and Natural: Interconnections and Balances in Ple”, published in the scientific journal “Millenium - Journal of Education, Technologies and Health”, concludes that, from a sample of 25 undergraduate students in UPM, “80 percent uses the AI. Lusophone ”.
Students concerned attend the third and fourth year of the course and were chosen because they have “a more advanced level of dominance of the Portuguese language and greater experience with different pedagogical approaches, including the use of technologies in teaching”.
In addition, "most participants were aged between 21 and 24 years, from various provinces in the interior of China (about 70 percent) and Macao", and "had prior experience in the use of AI tools for linguistic learning."
In general terms, the work points out that AI is increasingly important “in the learning of PLE [Portuguese as a foreign language]”, and that “the analysis of student interactions with AI for foreign languages ​​is critical to ensuring that technological solutions are worked based on their needs and expectations”.
It also states that the 25 students interviewed assume "a positive attitude towards the integration of AI in the learning of Portuguese, recognizing both significant advantages and its limitations." "A recurring theme was the need to maintain the balance between the use of AI and human interaction, highlighting the desire for language teaching open to new technologies, but without compromising the benefits of interpersonal relationships," the authors point out.
Tongue
If 80 percent of the students often resort to AI, what are the purposes of this use? The study points out that AI can support “the training of pronunciation, especially in the context of autonomous learning”. "Many have highlighted the neutrality of generated voices, which avoids regional influences, as an effective resource for developing correct habits in oral production." One student referred to the authors of the study that "the AI ​​voice is adjusted, there is no accent of any region and, therefore, it is good for students to train oral understanding with various types of texts beyond the materials given by the teacher in class."
In addition to pronunciation training, AI tools are also widely used for information research on Portuguese -speaking countries. “Students have recognized that these tools save time and allow more direct access to relevant content,” says the work, which highlights a student's response: “Help me to look for information about current trends in Brazil or Portugal, because books and information on the internet are dispersed and require many more time and much more time.”
However, it is stressed, based on the experience of both teachers, "that excessive use of AI tools has contributed to the significant reduction in the development of critical skills between students."
“More and more work, both written and oral, lack analytical depth, presenting advanced lexical and grammatical structures that do not correspond to the actual level of student proficiency. This disadvantage suggests a superficial relationship with study materials, where reflective effort and autonomous thinking are often replaced by the AMA automatically generated answers,” he concludes.
Complementarity is needed
According to Vanessa Amaro and Manuel Pires, the study allows us to conclude that “the integration of AI in foreign language teaching is an irreversible trend, but it requires a structured and careful pedagogical approach”.
"Most students [interviewed] recognized the importance of adapting language teaching into current technological reality, stressing the need to incorporate the AI ​​in a planned way. The balance between traditional methods and the use of new technologies is critical to ensuring effective learning," is concluded.
One of the students even defended that it is necessary to have a balance between AI and traditional methods, ”because“ language learning can be better and more interesting through AI, but it lacks the ability to create ideas and imagination, as well as the intercultural aspects of language learning ”.
Thus, for the students inquired, “the presence of the teacher, as a mediator of knowledge, is seen as essential, especially in the specific context of Macau, where there is no linguistic immersion during the learning process of Portuguese”.
Human interaction is, in addition to the “transmission of linguistic content, the ability to interpret cultural, social and emotional aspects, something that was going, despite its technical efficiency, cannot replicate”.
Vanessa Amaro and Manuel Pires also highlight the fact that “AI ethical and pedagogical challenges in teaching are complex and multifaceted”. This is because "data privacy is a central concern, as many AI tools collect personal information that can be used for purposes that users are unaware of." Moreover, “the risk of algorithmic bias can be a pertinent issue, because if the algorithms produce results that are systematically incorrect, biased or unfair, it can accentuate difficulties and inequalities in learning and require extra care in its use and regulation,” is indicated.
The authors also consider that "the excessive dependence of AI can compromise human interaction, essential for the development of social and cultural skills present in educational processes."
Given that "in the teaching of foreign languages ​​there seems to be several speeds in the integration of AI, with higher education institutions that do so gradually and even with enough reservations, as well as those that are most developed and proactive in the way they embrace these technologies", it is necessary to "foster dialogue and cooperation between the various teaching agents to understand the potential of AI".</description><pubDate>2025-05-19 02:27:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Leo XIV offers Vatican mediation to “silence the weapons”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/leao-xiv-oferece-mediacao-do-vaticano-para-silenciar-as-armas/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday exhorted world leaders to sit down and negotiate to “silence the weapons” and offered the Vatican's mediation to all belligerent parts. "The Holy See is available for enemies to meet and look in their eyes," Leo XIV told Vatican to speak at the representatives of the 23 Catholic churches of the East.
The Pope said it is necessary that "peoples can rediscover the hope and dignity to which they are entitled," the dignity of peace. "The people want peace and I, with my heart, say to the leaders of the people: We find, we speak, negotiate! War is never inevitable, weapons can and should be silenced, because they do not solve problems, but increase them," he said.
The US Pope's appeal appears on the eve of possible negotiations in the Turkish city of Istanbul about the Russian War against Ukraine. It is also unknown if today's conversations can include a meeting between Russian presidents, Vladimir Putin, and Ukrainian, Volodymyr Zelensky. Other wars have caused suffering in other latitudes, such as the Middle East, Africa or Asia.
First-hand
Leo XIV said in the Paul VI room, before thousands of people who moved to the jubilee of countries such as Syria, Ukraine, Lebanon and Iraq, which the oriental churches know "firsthand the horrors of war."
"To the point that Pope Francis has called martyrs to your churches," he said, quoted by the Spanish news agency Efe. "It is true: from the Holy Land to Ukraine, from Lebanon to Syria, from the Middle East to Tigray [Ethiopia] and to the Caucasus, so much violence," he lamented.
The Pope, applauded by the hearing, said the horror of war and "of the massacres of so many young lives" should cause indignation, "because in the name of military conquest people die."
He asked him to pray for peace, which he described as "reconciliation, forgiveness, courage to turn the page and start over." “For this peace to differ, I will do everything within my reach,” he promised. "The church will not get tired of repeating:" May weapons shut up, "he said.
Leo XIV said that others are not enemies, but human beings, "they are not bad people to hate, but people to dialogue." The Pope has asked to escape "from the typical manichaeist visions of violent narratives, which divide the world between good and bad."
Leo XIV prayed for the oriental and Latin Christians, who, especially in the Middle East, "resist their lands, stronger than the temptation to abandon them." He also launched a new appeal to be given to Christians the opportunity to remain where they live "with all the rights necessary for a safe existence."
Robert Prevost, 69, born in the United States, but with double American and Peruvian nationality, leads the Catholic Church since May 8, under the name of Leo XIV. It succeeded the Argentine Pope Francis, who died on April 21, 88 years old.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:21:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Investment and Development | Tam chi neng appointed president</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/macau-investimento-e-desenvolvimento-tam-chi-neng-nomeado-presidente/</link><description>"It is appointed, under the accumulation of functions, Tam Chi Neng, as Chairman of the Board of Directors of Macau Investment and Development, S.A., for a period of one year."
This is how the Chief Executive officialized Tam Chi Neng's rise to the top of the Macau Investment and Development hierarchy, through an order published yesterday in the official bulletin.
Macau Investment and Development aims to design, manage and exploit spaces for companies and non -business entities, such as the traditional Chinese medical park in Hengqin or the Macao Industry Incubator in Zhongshan.
The entity had been without leadership since the dismissal of Wu Jianfeng from the chairman of the Board of Directors, after the publication of an order signed by Sam Hou Fai at the beginning of last February.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:51:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Health | Sam Hou Fai gathers with National Commission leader</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/saude-sam-hou-fai-reune-com-dirigente-de-comissao-nacional/</link><description>The chief executive received on Tuesday at the government's headquarters the sub-director of the National Health Commission, Cao Xuetao, with whom he exchanged impressions on the development of Big Health industry and the training of health professionals.
Sam Hou Fai stressed that the government will continue to “cooperate with the National Health Commission, in order to reinforce clinical practice for Macau health students, intensify medical education and the exchange of qualified frameworks and raise the level of Macao health services”. The ruler stated that the MSAR is concentrated in the development of the Big Health industry and will deepen the synergy of the Great Bay in this domain.
According to the Social Communication Office (GCS), the Chief Executive said that the entry into operation of the Islands Hospital reflects “the attention and importance of the country to the well-being of the people of Masters”. The GCS did not advance any comment or statement made by the head of the National Health Commission at the meeting with the Chief Executive.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:50:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Checks | Traditional associations remove conversion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/cheques-associacoes-tradicionais-afastam-conversao/</link><description>After Pereira Coutinho and Ron Lam if they expressed the conversion of the pecuniary check to a consumer card, deputies of traditional associations joined the opposition. One of them was Lo Choi In, who saw yesterday the citizen newspaper apologize for an article written by AI in which deputy defended the replacement of the supports
 
The controversy regarding the conversion of the form of attribution of the pecuniary check to a consumer card, which restricts where to spend the support and assumes the form of discounts, knew yesterday new contours, with the “choir” of voices of deputies to increase in volume.
The idea returned to the order order after two government-organized meetings with association representatives, about two weeks ago, to hear suggestions on the reform of the monetary reimbursement. In the end, the Executive revealed that someone suggested changing the way they attribute pecuniary checks, converting them into consumption cards to support trade and restoration in community neighborhoods.
Deputy Pereira Coutinho began by criticizing the replacement of support and stated that he would try to know the position of the other deputies elected by direct suffrage, whose associations to which they belong were at meetings with the government. After Ron Lam and Nick Lei, deputies of traditional associations came to join the displeased voices with the idea.
Wong Kit Cheng, deputy from the General Association of Macao Women, Deputy Ngan Iek Hang of the Macao residents 'General Union (Ugamm), and Leong Sun IOK, from the Macao Workers' Associations (Faom), took positions against the change in the way the monetary checks are attributed.
Technological failures
The most caricatured opposition to the change of the form of the pecuniary check came yesterday, with an errata and apology of the citizen newspaper regarding the summary of article written with the appeal to Artificial Intelligence (IA), where it was indicated that LO Choi In, deputy of the association linked to the community of Jiangmen, was favorable to controversial conversion.
The article was published on January 16 this year, but due to the controversy on the subject, resurfaced on social networks where much criticism of the deputy's position reflected in the citizen's article was added.
The summary of the article stated that “the deputy suggests that part of the pecuniary check should be converted to a consumption card” and that the authorities must adjust the allocation of flexibility resources. However, what the deputy actually defended was the application of the amount spared by the exit of the resident program that live outside Macao on a consumption card to encourage consumption in community neighborhoods.
For this reason, the newspaper published a statement yesterday apologizing to Lo Choi In. “Due to AI technical problems, the article appeared with misleading statements, which misunderstanding the original intention of Mrs Lo Choi in about the pecuniary check plan.”
The deputy responded on social networks, sharing the apology of the citizen newspaper, and called on to the public to read the articles with complete content and not to be written with AI software written.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:48:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Right of manifestation | State security risk, says secretary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/direito-de-manifestacao-risco-para-seguranca-do-estado-diz-secretario/</link><description>The government said yesterday that demonstrations may threaten China's security, but denied that the police pressured an association to cancel a protest on Labor Day. "The demonstrations can bring conflicts to society, state security," said the secretary for security. "This has to do with the well-being of our country. We cannot, due to a person's interest, harm our people," said Wong Sio Chak.
During the pandemic, security forces refused to approve the course of any protest, invoking reasons for “order and safety” or public health.
Authorities raised antipandemic restrictions at the end of 2023, but the protests did not return to the city streets. Wong Sio Chak reiterated the respect of the government of masters for the right to manifestation, but stressed that "it cannot impact society." "We have a negotiation of public order, as earlier, because a demonstration has to occupy public space and can also have many people to participate," said the secretary.
Wong Sio Chak also gave as an example an alleged police decision in Spain, which was confirmed by the court, to prohibit a demonstration "involving two religious groups that could lead to conflict and disorder."
Asked if the Macao police had reason to fear that the Labor Day protest could lead to physical clashes, the secretary did not respond directly. However, Wong stressed that "all police are afraid of conflict, aggression."</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Violation | Cases decrease, government refers to “drunkenness” from victims</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/violacao-casos-diminuem-governo-refere-embriaguez-das-vitimas/</link><description>In the first quarter of this year ten violations were registered, four less compared to the same period last year, representing 28.6 percent. However, the authorities highlight the fact that, in the case of local victims, the vast majority are drunk at the time of the crime.
"In cases where the victims were residents, most occurred after alcohol consumption in bars, just as most victims were in a state of deep drunkenness," was referred to in the presentation of the data, while in the case of natural victims in the interior of China, which represent "half of the victims", the crimes occurred in hotel rooms.
"In some of the cases there were monetary conflicts between the victims and the suspects, and it is not possible to rule out the hypothesis that the cases occurred in a context of sexual transactions," ie prostitution. Police authorities say they carry out prevention platforms such as the “community policing connection mechanism” and the “Friends of Criminal Prevention for Women” project.
Domestic Violence | Only four occurrences considered a crime
In the first quarter of this year only four cases of crime of domestic violence were recorded, two more than in the same period last year. However, and according to investigations carried out by the 12th of this month, of the 26 occurrences preliminarily faced as domestic violence, only four cases even received this criminal classification, while 12 were considered offense crimes to physical integrity and two as other types of crimes.
There are even eight occurrences to be investigated. Regarding the crime of sexual abuse of children, five cases were recorded by the authorities in the first quarter of the year, another occurrence compared to the first quarter of 2024, an increase of 25 percent.
It has been said that the cases involved "especially the practice of voluntary acts between people of the same age and the diffusion of photographs and pornographic images."</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:44:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Computer crime decreases, but there are more and more burlas with</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/crime-informatico-diminui-mas-ha-cada-vez-mais-burlas-com-ia/</link><description>Police authorities registered, on April 24 this year, the “First Case of Macao in Macao related to Artificial Intelligence Technology (IA), Deepfake, in which“ criminals produced a video and, with face and voice mutation, personified a celebrity from Macao to attract the audience to access a fraudulent virtual investment platform ”.
According to the presentation yesterday by the government of crime data in the first quarter, there were no allegations of victims of this burla scheme, but the authorities highlight that there are increasingly crimes of AI, which "have originated a huge variety of" modes of performance].
Also noteworthy is for the beginning of the trend of breach of computer crime. The authorities mentioned yesterday that “computer crimes also began to record a decrease trend”, something demonstrated by the data: in the first quarter of this year there were 186 but 26 compared to the same period last year, which represents a 14 percent break compared to the first trimester of 2024.
Relief time
Regarding online buns or using telecommunications, in the first quarter of the year there were 74 cases of telephone mockery, a decrease of 22 cases compared to the same period of 2024.
According to yesterday's presentation, “about 40 percent of cases concerns the 'simulation of calling by public services'”, representing “a descent” in the form of acting of the burns. In turn, the cases of burla with the “guess who I” method rose about 20 percent in annual terms.
In the first three months of the year there have been 145 cases of cyber circumvents, an annual break of 47 cases, and "throws through online ticket sales and purchases were the most frequent forms of the practice of this type of crimes."
About nude chat situations, with nudity images associated with money extortion schemes, there were 14 cases in the first quarter, seven compared to the same period of 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:42:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Requested measures to diversify the origin of visitors</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/turismo-pedidas-medidas-para-diversificar-origem-dos-visitantes/</link><description>Samuel Tong, president of the Macao Management Institute, argued that the government should launch more measures to attract tourists from other Chinese provinces in addition to Guangdong, considering that the number of visitors from the rest of the country in the first four months of this year has a rise of just 4 percent in terms annually. According to the newspaper or Mun, the academic recalled that the measure of adding eight more cities to the "individual visa" policy to travel to Macau and Hong Kong has been in place for a year.
Thus, Samuel Tong pointed out that tourists with “individual visa” from other cities and provinces besides Guangdong have a drop for falling, highlighting the case of northern and east China cities where two to three hours take to travel to Japan or South Korea, the same time spent on a trip to Macau or Hong Kong, but more attractive destinations.
Samuel Tong suggests the creation of more direct flights between the cities of the most distant country and the two special administrative regions.
In turn, the president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association, Andy Wu, argued that the significant increase in Guangdong tourists makes the growth of visitors from other provinces slower. This also argues that the number of direct flights does not have a great positive effect to the number of tourists, as they can take advantage of Zhuhai's airports to move to Macao.
At the same newspaper, Andy Wu concluded that the biggest problem with the tourist sector in Macao is the fall in consumption capacity, and it is necessary to think of strategies to take tourists to consume in community neighborhoods outside the zones with the highest attractions.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 23:11:02</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great America (IV)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/a-grande-america-iv-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the May 22 edition)
Why is Putin not having a free hand to Ukraine? And when it threatens to tear Granelândia, one way or another, to the Atlantic Denmark (or themselves), in terms that could theoretically trigger a relief to those harmed through Article 5 of the Washington Treaty, will not bury NATO, Russia's existential objective? And at the same time, mark the vacuity of the anti-chinese quadrilateral and similar alignments, always intended to be revoked? We depart from the principle that we do not have any document paraphrased by Trump, Putin or another. On the contrary, we are certain that we could never do better than writer Leonardo Scascia, since among gentlemen the paramilitary understandings are filed with a virtual hand grip.
But what if we did it? We would have a report of the great confrontation with the following content. Title: “For a new order of chaos”. Parentheses attributable to Minuteman. First. We share a common interest in perpetuating the existence of each other's empires, as well as our own. (Accomplices smiles.) Second. We noticed that a war between us would not have winners. All losers. (Mutual congratulations.)
Third. In common, we will have a hidden enemy tomorrow who is now our supreme asset, the AI. Let us fear that it seizes our command and eliminate us to all, along with the rest of humanity. (The last five words seem unmofited.) Fourth. We have established a common red line to be extended to the rest of the states and imposed, if necessary, by force (here Putin resembles Trump the five Roosevelt policies, gently) how to prohibit the development of AI beyond the threshold that would not allow us to control it. (evokes Fausto, reading from the cave in disgraced adolescence. Trump's fingers hit impatience.) Fifth and last. Any change to the great confrontation requires unanimity. (The three largest world leaders cross the six hands in fervent approval.) Apparently cleaning the conference table, the lucky scribe found playing cards scattered representing Ukraine, Canada, Gronelândia, Panama, the moon and Mars. Among others.
Mexico cartels are not forgotten because they are very powerful criminal organizations, not only in their own territory, but also in many other parts of the world, including Europe. The term “cartel” was first used by Florida prosecutors in the early 1980s, during a lawsuit against the Colombian drug trafficking group of Medellin led by Pablo Escobar. This word aims to translate, simplifying, relationships between criminal groups often in conflict. It is part of an organized coexistence between clans, police, military and politicians. In the meshes of this well oil network, powerful interests that go far beyond a fentanil or methamphetamine tablet flourish. Currently, the two most powerful organizations are the Synaloa Cartel and the Jalisco Nueva Generación cartel, which, to abbreviate, uses the acronym (CJG).
These transnational criminal structures are involved in drug production and trafficking, the purchase and sale of weapons, the bleaching of capital, the smuggling of migrants, the exploitation of prostitution and corruption and extortion. Not least, the black market for oil and fuels and minerals such as gold and silver. In the first nine months of 2022, the Mexican state company of oil and gas Pemex lost seven hundred and thirty million dollars due to oil theft through the insertion of illegal taps into the pipelines. The near future also seems quite dark due to the impact of the new and certainly deadly commercial tariffs against Mexico announced by Trump.
In the state of Tabasco, Pemex is developing a bill of $ 1 billion for a new oil and gas field, recently discovered in the Bakté zone, which is expected to be operational this year. It is no coincidence that there are strong tensions among criminal clans in Tabasco. In 2024, this state occupied second place in Mexico in terms of homicides. The Mexican hydrocarbon industry is in crisis due to the exhaustion of important deposits such as Cantarell and Ku-Maloob-Zaap. Recent discoveries are limited and the decline in oil and gas production can lead to serious geopolitical imbalances inside and illegal rows. The Sinaloa clan operates in forty -seven countries. Twenty -five years dedicated to the methamphetamine market and, for thirteen years, also to that of Fentanil.
The cartel matters from Asia from chemical precursors for fentanil production and manufactures tablets in their own laboratories, located in places where it is easier to control the territory. Sinaloa currently lives an internal fracture. The families Zambada and Guzmán (El Chapo) vie for the leadership of the entire cartel. Conflicts and guerrillas are spread over several Mexican states under the control of the same group. In the city of Caborca, in the middle of the Sonora Desert, a war between the Guzmán (Los Chapitos) and the Caborca ​​cartel for control of this key zone for Arizona has been locked. The most profitable markets for methamphetamine are in Asia and Oceania, led by Thailand, Japan, Australia and New Zealand. Profits can be a hundred times higher than those obtained with sales in the United States.
Trade with China is also important, extended by Mexicans to a fish, Totoaba, mainly fish in the Gulf of Mexico, from which the dry bladder is extracted, very important in traditional Chinese medicine. Links between China and Mexico are ensured by various ports, including Mazatlán, entirely under the control of the Sinalo Cartel, which also gives the use of port of scale to other criminal organizations for payment. Equally important is the Port of Manzanillo, in the state of Colima, where they operate several cartels, including the Sinaloa cartel, although the surrounding territory is not under its control. However, most of the drug and fentanyl movement from Asia is performed by land or air. The Arizona border is almost fully under the control of the Syinal Cartel. The border posts of San Luis, Rio Colorado and Nogales are functional for drug trafficking, but also key centers for fentanyl smuggling in brand tablets especially intended to spray the Los Angeles zone.
San Ysidro's bustling border post is an open intersection for the Synaloa cartel. A vast network of tunnels facilitates crossing the border between the United States and Mexico. Underground tunnels exploit sewage and water systems from border cities. Sometimes calls between houses in Mexico and US companies are excavated so that goods can be unloaded and charged without being seen. The use of drones or the launch of catapults are rare events, but highlighted in the press because they are scenic. The CJNG cartel expanded as a franchising business. Its leaders are linked to each other by marriage or direct blood ties. After the Sinaloa cartel, he is the second largest drug distributor in the United States. The main markets are Japan and Australia.
The “Great America” is the prosperous United States and with few income and wealth disparities, where poverty is minimal. Essential basic needs, such as health care, are a right and not a privilege and are universally available to everyone. A nation with justice and true as the proverbial lady with blindfolded eyes holding a set of scales, where the recovery is administered equally, not just appearance.
A nation that the world admires for the defense of universal democracy and human rights, respecting others. At the same time, infrastructors will be quickly treated by the world community, reinforced by their very effective military capabilities. A nation that promotes and develops cutting -edge technology to improve life everywhere. A nation that is universally respected by its efforts to live in optimal and clean environmental conditions, but does not give in to climate change extremists. And lastly, but not least a nation with military capabilities with which no nation would dream of wanting to get involved. Possible but absolutely unenforceable with Trump.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:07:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The hot bed</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/a-cama-quente/</link><description>The text what is Neo Abjectism was first published in 1967, in local texts and, later, in 1971, in style exercises. But as early as 1963, he had been read by Mario Cesariny in the press house.  What is most important is not so much Luiz Pacheco to make it clear, in this performance-confession that he asked without returning-who asked knowing that he was not going back-but that he tried to be free alone and failed. He needed the other, even if it was to ask him alms. In fact, what was at question in the hand that asks alms is precisely the need to have another. I think Luiz Pacheco's writing goes a lot to this other, it's like this bed already sweaty where we have to lie down.
And how to be free being poor?, Here's the question. He says he can, that he is "intensely free, free until he is libertine, which is a real and body form of freedom; free to abjection, which is the result of wanting to be free in Portuguese." And what interests us, us and our beautiful salaries of Macao, who still insist on resisting? In 2025, Portugal is preparing to ask Luiz Pacheco that, in return, give us without having to return him.
If I were a bad chronicler, I would say that this NATO on May 7, 1925 was the Encount Terrible of the Portuguese Letters, a man who chose to live on the banks of society, or any other parvo. The project “Luiz Pacheco walks throughout the paper”, outlined about his centenary, promises to live up to the honoree, without falling into similar clichés. There will be no public pedies or many people sleeping in the same bed (the famous hot macao beds?), As in the unforgettable community. We are not interested in whether or not Pacheco would be against this academic apparatus, which actually goes far beyond academic, because it has a strong dimension of cultural intervention, things that together are rarely, and on top of the entire national territory. As I would say, "A corpse will never be right, even if it had had it before." We can only look at the eyes of the living, with the eyes of the gifts. We will never be able to look with the eyes of the dead.
The project “Luiz Pacheco walks throughout the paper” is the central axis of these celebrations, bringing together academic and cultural institutions in a coordinated effort to make more present and Luiz Pacheco. Organized by the Center for Lusophone and European Literature and Cultures (Clepul) of the University of Lisbon Faculty of Letters, the program extends until 2026. The Organizing Committee, coordinated by Rui Sousa, prepared a program that aims to cover the multiple facets of life and work of the author, editor and critic.
Through the counterpoint publisher, founded in 1950, Luiz Pacheco was responsible for the publication of names that became essential in Portuguese letters, such as Mario Cesariny, António Maria Lisboa, Natália Correia, Herberto Helder and Vergílio Ferreira. As an author, Pacheco created a work that has autobiographical and critical dimension, in texts such as “The Libertine walks through Braga”, “Community”, “The Valentine” and “Theodolito”. Having to be a writer, critic, reviewer, editor, even censor, all at the same time, is not a grace given by talent, it is the mandatory path of a Ulysses that crosses the bas-fond of fascism, now the reappearing visas.
The celebrations include international congresses (two!), Exhibitions, theatrical performances and the publication of their complete works. Cities such as Lisbon, Setúbal, Palmela and Braga - places where the Libertino walked - will be the scene of various events. The highlight of the celebrations will be the “Luiz Pacheco International Congress”, on October 22 and 23 in Setúbal and Palmela, which will be accompanied by the inauguration of an exhibition from the author's estate, in possession of the son Paulo Pacheco, the Paulocas of the community, on the 23rd, and by a reading of texts, in Setúbal, 24.
From 2026, Luiz Pacheco will also walk beyond borders, with a traveling exhibition that, after having passed through the cities of his intimate map, will also be in different countries, from Brazil and Colombia to Italy, Spain and Poland. In Sertã, in early July, the readings marathon will be dedicated to him. And at Casa da Liberdade Mario Cesariny and Perve Galeria, in Lisbon, is, by the end of the year, an exhibition of its material and unpublished materials. Also with the support of the Santarém Polytechnic Institute, an exhibition will be evident at the BrancaAmp Freire Library.
The text “What is neo-abjectism”-we are back because it is the key to a work-seeking, precisely by the idea of ​​freedom, to transform a radical choice certain circumstances, first and more of a circumstance of 48 years, of course, and that everyone knows what it is. It is not easy. Only those who have an ugly face of people get. And the libertine, does not come for a walk through Fai Chi Kei?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Princess Mononoke 520 (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/princess-mononoke-520-ii/</link><description>Last week, we analyzed the points of view of patent love in the work "Princess Mononoke" ("幽灵公主") of Japanese master of manga Hayao Miyazaki and also in the recent Chinese television series "the story of my best friend" ("流金歲月"). We are saddened and sincerely wish to the beloved person. Secondly, true love is free. True lovers do not kidnap or restrict the other in the name of love, because this kind of love is not true, but the manifestation of a kind of control for personal satisfaction. my."
If in a marriage there is a lack of companionship, care and attachment, there is no love and the marriage certificate is just a servitude contract. The couple lives in a kind of cage, unable to escape, but having to live with each other.
Since in a relationship what is necessary is to exist love, there is not much difference whether there is a marriage certificate or not, right? The answer is "not quite". A couple buys a house together to reside there. After getting married, they have a baby. The husband's parents call the baby "grandson" as well as the wife's parents. Two families who did not know each other have been linked because of a marriage certificate. From that moment on, the man has the responsibility to take care of his wife's parents and the wife has the responsibility to take care of her husband's parents. The couple also have to raise their children together. This example talks about taking care of parents and children, the custody of ancestors and descendants and the inheritance of goods. There are both practical and legal issues that can only be protected by law if the couple's relationship is confirmed by a marriage certificate. If we want to connect to the other person conveniently, then the companionship, the care and attachment we mentioned above do not arrive. How can we talk about “aging together, take care of children and parents and succession rights”? How are we going to live in the future?
Of course the love between two people is the center of everything. The center should be stable before considering questions such as “aging together, taking care of children and parents and succession rights.” These questions may affect the love between the couple, but are also affected by the conditions of each duo. Suppose a man in the house of 50 asks the hand of a 38 -year -old divorced woman with a daughter and she accepts. For this couple, the core of love - companionship, care and attachment - is still valid, but is it still important to take care of parents? The answer is, not necessarily. Since the man is already in the 50s, parents may have been leaving for a long time, so the responsibility to take care of their parents is very small, and the issue of family integration is relatively simple. As the woman already has a daughter, they decided to have no more children and focus on the one that already exists. Therefore, the impact of these issues in a marriage can be more limited or more complex.
If you ask me if I agree with Princess Mononoke's views on love, I tell you I want to ask my love what you think. I may not accept everyone, but I don't deny everyone definitive either. I respect my beloved and I want to be with her. Issues such as taking care of parents, succession rights and family integration are not important to any of us, but questions such as companionship, care, attachment and aging together imply a two -way commitment, not something to be done alone.
I love you, Princess Mononoke, you can come to see me when you miss me. Perhaps this wants to say, "When you think of me, you still love me as deeply as you loved me yesterday." If you do not want to stop, if you do not want to stay in a place, then my way of loving you is "walking with you," you go where you are, whether at the end of the world or in a sea nook, or beyond hundreds of rivers and mountains, I will continue to walk with you, because I want to hold your hand tightly as it walks beside me.
If I can whisper to your ear every night, "I miss you every day," and I also hope that "it is summer or winter, I will love you more and more." I will write you an article and declare my love for you every year on May 20. If we reach the top of the world, we can no longer move on, please fly with me and I will always be with you.
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 23:38:46</pubDate></item><item><title>The gravedigge of democracy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/26/o-coveiro-da-democracia/</link><description>Here he is! Of hand on the chest and neck. To faint. With the televisions all covering all day the route of the ambulances that carried it. Appearing in the Lisbon Square of Ligasure in the Fist and Penses in his arms, pretending to cry in a good pocket and tricky way.
This is, the poor thing, who deserved the illiterate vote of politics, or rather all those who did not think if not in a messiah who will save Portugal from the corrupt, immigrants and Gypsies. From his name André Ventura, he managed to capture the disgruntled to the parties of governance in 51 years of democracy and obtain an unbelievable vote that no polls ever alviped. Ventura is in the largest. On the gravedigge path of democracy.
The arrival will certainly be as the main opposition party, as it seems that the votes of emigrants in Europe and outside Europe will offer two deputies to AD and two at the arrival. The elections have effectively showed everything we have written here over the years: the discontent of the middle class, the low wages, the pensions of misery, the schools with rain entering, the young people without home and emigrates, the poorly paid doctors and nurses, the more likely, the elderly without dignified homes, the poor non -power to buy their medicines. Ruled, transportation to crack and with expensive passes, IRS increasing, income subsidies to be removed to more than 80,000 poor, pregnant women to have their children in ambulances, consultations and surgeries to delay months and, a few years, the absence of social housing or affordable income, domestic violence to be increased and the prevarickers to be sent in freedom. All of these facts have been highlighted in these chronicles and all of these reasons have led to the increase in vote in a neo -fascist party. How was it possible for the always socialist and communist algarve possible to stop at the hands of the arrival? For the discontent that is raising in the Portuguese population.
The arrival even won in Algueirão-Mem Martins, on the outskirts of Lisbon, where the vast majority of residents are made up of maids and lower hierarchical civil servants who get up every day at five o'clock to catch a train for work when there is no strike. It was this phenomenon of discontent with the rulers of the PSD and PS that took many people who are not racist, not xenophobic, not pedophile, does not steal bags, to vote for the arrival. They voted voters who previously put the cross on the PSD, the PS, the PCP and even in the Left Block. A friend of ours of the BE conveyed to me that he voted for arrival because he will never forgive Mariana Mortágua had failed party employees who were pregnant. And therefore, we watched the huge fall of the BE that is deadly in Parliament and symptoms of upcoming elections disappear from the hemiciclo.
As for the “Hecatombo” of the Socialist Party was already expected. A party that chose to forget the young people, who has become an anti António Costa feud, who has more than six factions inside to swallow themselves, obviously it would have to fall into disgrace. With more or less reflection, with a new secretary general, it will take many years to get up from the ground, if it does not happen to him the same as the French Socialist Party. Socialist vows with family members living with difficulties went to the arrival. Votes Socialist Anti Pedro Nuno Santos went to the free.
As for AD, who was taken to the lap for televisions, is singing a great victory. Which victory? The number of votes has increased a little and can not even have normal stability to govern. Of the two, one. Either it combines with the arrival, or awaits the small socialist parliamentary group to take advantage of the government program and the state budget. The voices have already been sadly listened to the pepêdist hosts. Hugo Soares and Paulo Rangel have already given the motto that in many proposals there will be a coexistence with the arrival.
The Portuguese did not think twice. They got intoxicated with the promises of Ventura that he could never fulfill, in the face of Portugal, they had no money so that their desiderates were forward and voted for a creature that already had the disappointment of saying that “they have not seen anything” and “I will be the future Prime Minister”.
Ventura is undemocratic, just wants to alter the Constitution, remove the word “socialism” from the Constitution, want to remove all subsidies and houses from the Gypsy communities, to remove, to Laia de Passos Coelho, the vacation and Christmas allowance, to prohibit that in schools there are sexual education, that the police are preferably black because it is a pure racist and, essentially, that the immigrants who are to “hold” to "who are" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are to" who are to be "who are to" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are to" who are to be "who are" who are to be "who are to" who are to "to be" to be "who are to" who are to "to" to be "to" Social Security are expelled from Portugal, in a good trumpper way.
Portuguese democracy is in danger. Not now. But in the next legislative elections, if democratic parties are not convinced that they have to come together to defend a regime won with much struggle, arrests and deportations of anti -fascist men. Ventura only has in mind to change the regime and be the gravedigger of democracy, so that it can continue to receive the congratulations from all the far right of Europe and the US. Ventura -If the Portuguese do not open their eyes well and if the rulers do not start solving the survival problems of the majority -will go to the executive head and the neo -fascist tragedy will be a reality in Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-05-26 01:04:36</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC welcomes debate “challenges of being macanese today!”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/frc-acolhe-debate-desafios-de-ser-macaense-hoje/</link><description>Today, from 6.30 pm, the first session of a new cycle of conferences about the Maca community. The session is called “Challenges of being Macaense today!” and is part of the cycle of lectures “Being Macaense in the 21st century-culture, tradition, identity, challenges”.
Today's lecture is attended by José Luís de Sales Marques, chairman of the Macanese Council of Communities, Elisabela Larrea, researcher, founder and president of Macra - Macanese Culture Research Association; António Monteiro, President of AJM - Association of Young Macanese; Rachel Antonia Handley, Young Member of the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong; and Miguel Silva (via Zoom), affiliate of the Macao House in Portugal and the nephew of the last poet of Patuá, Adé dos Santos Ferreira.
According to a press release, the event aims to address “the way of life of the macanese, the community or the communities in Macao and the diaspora, and their daily challenges to maintain the being and feel of the Macanese reality”. Thus, “the purpose of the conference, and the next in this cycle, is a constructive discussion to look at the present and the future, without forgetting the tradition and the distinctive identity milestones, especially the gastronomy and the theater in Patuá, both intangible heritage of MSAR and RPC”.
The appreciation of the Chinese
At HM, José Sales Marques said that this cycle of debates that begins today is coordinated by itself and seeks to “bring to the table a wide range of personal contributions and, in a way, renew the debate about what it is to be and feel macanese in the 21st century”.
For the person in charge, "challenges are always new, because time is always new, it doesn't go back," there is a "complex current that acts as an accelerator, where things turn to unimaginable speeds."
"We are always discovering and learning, especially with the younger ones. The challenge of identity dilution is not only here in Macao through integration and miscegenation. It happens everywhere. Therefore, we have to understand the pulse of reality and the open mind to recognize that the being macanese can also change with times, maintaining some constant elements," he said.
António Monteiro, on the other hand, said that “Macaense's biggest challenge has always been adapting to several times, moments and conjuncture over the 500 years of Macao”, and today the challenges of belonging to this ethnicity, and preserve it, are “different, especially for the younger ones”.
"Bases were created in Macaense Associativism, many of Portuguese matrix, in the civil society of Macao. We watched a height of" witness pass "or the emergence of new faces in the Macaense community. Dilution will only exist if the Macaense community does not take over as Macaense, culturally or idlely, and is not physically present in Macau," he defended.
The president of AJM recalled that "the Chinese community recognizes and values ​​the macanese and its culture, even in intangible heritage."</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:05:20</pubDate></item><item><title>GARDEN House | Frank Law Exhibition Brand reopening of space</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/casa-garden-exposicao-de-frank-lei-marca-reabertura-do-espaco/</link><description>After being closed for five months for restoration work, Casa Garden, headquarters of the Oriente Foundation in Macau, is preparing to receive the one that is the largest retrospective exhibition of the work of Frank Law, local artist. With the support of the Artistry of Wind Box Community Development Association, it presents, from June 3, “when the island launches its shadows: a retrospective of Frank Law”
 
Local artist Frank Law has won, in recent times, highlight in the local artistic landscape. After the inauguration of the show “Frank Law: Cuba 92”, on the 7th, at the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association, here that Casa Garden now welcomes a new exhibition with works by the deceased artist, with the support of the Artistry of Wind Box Community Development Association.
This is the largest retrospective exhibition of Frank Law's work, entitled “When the Island launches its shadows: a retrospective of Frank Law”, and opens to the public on June 3. According to a note from the organization, this initiative “marks the first big show since the death of artist Frank Lei and presents the most extensive selection of his works to date”, and the audience can view “more than 60 selected photographic pieces”.
These works include “the photographs of law since their studies in France in the 1990s and their subsequent artistic projects after their return to Macao”.
According to the same note, Frank Law is considered a “pioneer of contemporary photography and experimental art in Macao”, and his works “explore not only the aesthetics of photography, but also offer deep criticism and reflections on social realities”. “Through photography, installations and interdisciplinary practices, he challenges the boundaries of art, capturing metaphors and poetry inherent to urban development,” says the organization.
Influences and looks
The show dedicated to Frank Law reveals itself at Casa Garden, headquarters of the Oriente Foundation in Macau, in three rooms that exploit the artist's artistic style and reveal “their aesthetic and cultural influences, interdisciplinary experiences and social and pedagogical practices”.
Also noteworthy is the organization of two parallel exhibitions, entitled “Errante Look: A Margin”, carried out in eight places outside the exhibition space, and “Artist Bookshelf - Frank Law: through the pages at Dialect Photo Library”. It is also expected to perform a series of additional activities, with pop-up tea stands, street photography guided tours and experimental photography workshops for families.
In addition to being a retrospective of Frank Lei's work, this show also takes the opportunity to provide “a deep reflection on the role of contemporary art in society”, and “art enthusiasts and the public are invited to visit and interact with the urban landscape that he once observed, raising reflections on social and local culture”.
According to a note from the Artistry of Wind Box Community Development Association, Frank Law was a “pioneer of contemporary photography and experimental art in Macao”, also making a connection with “the social reality” of Macao. “Through photography, installation and experimentation in various media, it went beyond the limits of art, capturing metaphors and poetics of urban development in Macau - an island defined by contradictions and transformations.”
The curatorship is by Jane Law, Lam Sio Man and Cho Ian Leong. The show ends on June 29. The opening ceremony takes place a few days later at the opening of doors to the public, on June 17, at 18:30.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:04:19</pubDate></item><item><title>Graça Morais and Júlio Pomar at Gallery Amagao from Thursday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/graca-morais-e-julio-pomar-na-galeria-amagao-partir-de-quinta-feira/</link><description>It's called “Creativity Dialogues” and it is the name of the new show promoted by the Gallery Amagao and which opens to the public this Thursday, from 18:30. According to a gallery note, it presents “an exceptional selection of contemporary Portuguese artists”, and each brings a “unique and innovative perspective on the current artistic panorama”.
In all, 24 artists are in all, some of which have already exposed their work in Macau. “Creativity Dialogues” integrates a total of 50 works. From the list of artists prominent to the great names of contemporary Portuguese painting, as is the case of Graça Morais and Júlio Pomar. Following are names like Abílio Febra, sculptor and artist; Alfredo Luz, Ana Cristina Dias, Ana Pimentel, André Pedro, Cunha Nery, Fernando Law, Francisco Geraldo, João Paulo, Jorge Francisco, Joseph Luis Tinoco, Lara Roseiro, Luís Jesus, Luzia Lage, Madalena Pequito, Maria Dulce Martins, Maria João Franco, Maria Leal da Costa, Numbered, Pedro Proença, Raquel Grail and Susana Bravo.
PAINTING FROM
The painter Graça Morais, with full name Maria da Graça Pinto de Almeida Morais, was born on March 17, 1948 in Trá-os-Montes. He completed the Higher Painting Course at the Porto School of Fine Arts (Esbap) in 1971. From 1976 to 1979 lived in Paris as a fellow of the Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation. Currently resides and has its studio in Trás-os-Montes and Lisbon.
Since 1974 he has held and participated in more than a hundred individual and collective exhibitions in Portugal and abroad. The representation of Portugal stands out at the XVII São Paulo Biennial (1983) and individual exhibitions at the São Paulo Museum of Modern Art (1984) and the Rio de Janeiro Museum of Modern Art (1985).
Already Júlio Pomar, another great name of Portuguese painting, was born in Lisbon, on January 10, 1926, and died on May 22, 2018 in the same city. He settled in Paris in 1963. He attended the António Arroio School of Decorative Arts and the Lisbon Fine Arts (1942-44) and Porto (1944-46) schools, which he abandoned after a disciplinary suspension by student activities.
From 1946, from the Central Commission of the Youth Democratic Unit Movement (MUD), with resistance to the Estado Novo in Portugal, was part of the Central Commission, and was an activity by which he was arrested the following year and convicted in court. In 1949, on the occasion of participation in the presidential candidacy of Norton de Matos, from whom he designed a widely publicized portrait, was removed from the place of design teacher in technical education.
He first exposed in 1942 in Lisbon, in a group show in his studio, and held the first solo exhibition in 1947, in Porto, in the Portuguese Gallery, featuring drawings that would be the following year edited in an album prefaced by Mário Dionísio.
At the beginning of his career, he was one of the animators of the Neo-Realist movement, developing a large critical intervention in newspapers and magazines: “The Afternoon” (diary published in Porto, where he coordinated the weekly page “Art”, in 1945), “Literary World”, “Seara Nova”, “Horizon”, “Portucale”, etc. Participated in the Organization of Independent Exhibitions, in 1944-45, in Porto, and then at the exhibition of Spring (Porto, Commercial Athenaeus, 1946), being one of the main organizers of the General Exhibitions of Fine Arts (National Society of Fine Arts, Lisbon, 1946/1956). In 1956, he was one of the founders and first members of the board of the “engraving” cooperative. Pomar dedicated himself especially to painting, but also carried out drawing, engraving, sculpture and “assembly”, illustration, ceramics and glass, tapestry, theater scenography and tile mural decoration.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 22:51:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Artm | Shows about the 25th anniversary of the Ka-Hó Association</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/artm-mostra-sobre-os-25-anos-da-associacao-em-ka-ho/</link><description>It is already this Sunday that the Gallery "Hold on To Hope", a project of the Macao Toxicode Pexicodes Rehabilitation Association in the village of Ka-Hó, hosts a new exhibition. It is the result of the creative projects developed by users in the context of recovery and rehabilitation. The show is called “Ageing Gracefully” and also aims to sensitize the community to the therapeutic effect of art
 
He calls himself “Ageing Gracefully” and is the new exhibition patent in the Hold on To Hope Gallery, managed by the Macao Toxicodeperit Rehabilitation Association (ArtM), with home in the village of Ka-Hó. The inauguration takes place on June 1, at 16h.
“Ageing Gracefully” arrives precisely to celebrate the 25th anniversary of ArtM, founded in 1993, and continues to support people with toxicodependence problems, also providing rehabilitation and social integration programs.
According to a note by the ArtM, the works of art and handicrafts integrated in this show are born of these activities with the users, being “vital elements of daily life in the therapeutic community of the artm”.
“Through various methods and tools, participants can express their feelings through their creations, developing their practical skills and creativity, while exploiting their perceptions about the world around them. These activities have shown to improve physical functioning and produce very positive results,” he reads.
In the same note, the ArtM says it expects the exposure to “increase awareness between organizations and related departments on the current situations of special cases”. In addition, the show allows artm users to "present their creations to the public, with the aim of strengthening their trust and understanding and acceptance of the community."
ArtM also aims to “encourage the positive impact of creativity and the arts”, “promote the engagement and positivity of participants” and “strengthen the understanding of special cases between organizations and departments”.
The Community Effect
The association describes, in the same note, that since its foundation it has developed a model of “therapeutic community”, seeking to “meet the special needs of each client in rehab” and using “a bio-psychosocial perspective”.
The association says that "the period of treatment lasts at least one year and includes various components, such as community life, development of responsibility skills, peer counseling, bio-psychosocial counseling, therapy groups, educational seminars, vocational training, community activities, recreational activities, development of interests and family support groups."
With these actions, the artm seeks to “deepen individuals' understanding of their dependence and personal issues, promote personal growth, rebuild family relationships and assist them in reintegrating society with a new healthy lifestyle”, “in recent years, they have welcomed several special cases”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 22:45:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade Balance | Deficit of 9.4 billion in April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/balanca-comercial-defice-de-94-mil-milhoes-em-abril/</link><description>In April, the trade balance deficit was 9.4 billion patacas, according to data published yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). For this amount, contributed exports of goods of 1.12 billion patacas and imports of goods of 10.53 billion patacas.
These numbers mean that, compared to April last year, exports fell 7.7 percent and 4 percent. Regarding April, the value of the re -export descended 7.8 percent to 1.01 billion patacas. The value of jewelery re -exportation decreased 48.9 percent, although the value of alcoholic beverages and beauty, make -up and skin care products has grown 58.8 percent and 46.6 percent.
Regarding the first four months of the year, the trade balance deficit was 36.16 billion patacas, less 2.42 billion patacas, compared to the same period, when the balance deficit was 38.58 billion.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:37:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Hospitality | More workers, but wages without increases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/hotelaria-mais-trabalhadores-mas-salarios-sem-aumentos/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), related to the first quarter of this year and out of the inquiry to labor needs and remuneration point to an increase of 7.2 percent in the number of workers in hotels, a total of 60,482 people, compared to the same period of 2024.
However, in salary, the average remuneration of full -time workers in the hotel was 20,090 patacas, 1.9 percent, while in the restoration sector a worker earned an average of 10,540 patacas, less 0.7 percent than 2024.
At the end of the quarter under analysis, the rate of hospitality vacancy lowered only 1.1 percent compared to the first quarter of last year due to the fact that "the vacancies of this branch were filled and the demand for labor to gradually stabilize." Thus, the number of vacancies in that quarter, in the hotels, was 839.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:36:26</pubDate></item><item><title>TALHAN | Macao authorities praise nuclear central security</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/taishan-autoridades-de-macau-elogiam-seguranca-de-central-nuclear/</link><description>Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, led a delegation of mashed service representatives at a meeting with Taishan Nuclear Central, which is about 70 kilometers from Macao last Friday. According to a statement issued yesterday by the Unit Police Services (SPU), Commander General Leong Man Cheong highlighted “the sense of responsibility of Guangdong in the nuclear emergencies response work and the scientific and rigorous attitude in safety-based work”.
Leong Man Cheong also indicated to expect the exchange with the exchange with the authorities of Taishan, namely with visits "to nuclear centers, vocational training courses and thematic lectures", to "raise awareness of nuclear risk prevention and the nuclear emergency treatment capacity of macao's competent services."
The MSar entourage visited the Taishan Nuclear Center to find out the “operation of the cooling source, control room and emergency command center.”
The SPU adds that Guangdong and Macau will reinforce the exchange and cooperation “in the public opinion response on this matter”, will “cautiously” information and communication with the public, to “create a good social atmosphere and jointly safeguard the socioeconomic stability of the great bay”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:35:11</pubDate></item><item><title>CPSP | MP wants severe penalty for agent aggressor</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/cpsp-mp-quer-pena-severa-para-agressor-de-agente/</link><description>The driver who attacked with a metal bar a police, after being warned for an illegal parking situation, is subject to periodic presentations, prohibition of leaving the territory and had to pay a security
 
The driver who assaulted an agent of the Public Security Police (CPSP) with a metal bar is obliged to present himself periodically before the authorities, forbidden to leave the territory and still had to provide a security. These were the coercion measures applied to man detained on Sunday, according to a statement from the Public Prosecution Service (MP).
"Given the nature, Modus Operandi, the unlawfulness of the facts and the severity of the guilt, the Criminal Instruction Judge, under the promotion of the Public Prosecution Service, applied him the measures of coercion of security, periodic presentation and prohibition of absence," was reported.
On the basis of these measures was the fact that the judge considered to have “strong evidence of the crime of aggravated injury, the crime of damage, resistance and coercion, and the crime of unjustified detention of weapons and other instruments”.
In the statement, the MP warns the population that will always promote “severe penalties” for any citizen who use violence against police officers. "For any kind of crimes involving violence, the Public Prosecution Service not only promotes, under the law, the application of severe punishments, which may still be aggravated under the criminal law, when serious circumstances related to acts of violence against authority agents, but also strive to rigorously investigate the legal responsibilities of infrastructors, defending the dignity and security of the agents." indicated. "The Public Prosecution Service calls on citizens from now on to observe the law, to have a good discipline, to respect and actively cooperate with the work of agents of authority in order to preserve together the good social order of Macao," he was added.
Profanity and aggression
In a statement, the MP indicates that the driver “used profanity to insult the agent […] and brave a metal hydraulic stick” while still inside the vehicle. Then, later, he left the vehicle, "with the stick in his hand, brave her towards the police officer and immediately walked away by car twice."
To the third, says the MP, when the driver was intercepted "descended from the vehicle to assault the police officer with the Court, causing him injuries to his body." "During the detention process, damage to police equipment was also caused," he was completed.
The crime of aggravated injury provides for a 4.5 -month arrest penalty or a fine of 180 days, the crime of 3 -year arrest damage, the crime of resistance and coercion may reach 5 years in prison and the crime of unjustified arrest and other two -year or 240 -day instruments.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:30:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Moody’s keeps rating, but admits negative perspective</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/economia-moodys-mantem-rating-mas-admite-perspectiva-negativa/</link><description>Macao's monetary authority issued a statement to mention the assessment of the good situation of territory finances. However, it left out that the notation was attributed with a negative perspective
 
Financial notation agency Moody’s maintained Macau rating at AA3 level, the highest fourth on the scale, but admits that the prospect for the future is negative. The most recent report, published on Tuesday, indicates that if the territory issues debt to finance itself, it is considered a good investment, although there is a risk that the note is reduced in the near future.
As part of the justification for the notation to be kept at AA3 level, Moody's indicated the strong capacity of the territory to cope with any debts due to the high level of gross per capita domestic product, as well as the fact that the MGRAM has not issued any debt.
Financial reserves are also taken as a good pillow to “absorb” any shocks that result from the “structural slowdown of the Chinese economy”, which is the main Macao market. After Moody’s revealed the maintenance of the rating, the monetary and currency authority of Macao (AMCM) issued a statement that left out of negative perspectives and direct references to the risks associated with the economic situation across the border.
"Moody's maintained the" AA3 "notation, positioned at the fourth higher level, attributed to the MSAR, based on the stable situation of public finances and external payments of the MSAR," was indicated. "In addition, the absence of charges with debt by the Government of MSAR continues to give a strong capacity for resistance to potential external shocks," he was added.
AMCM also highlighted the fact that the economy in 2025 was 85.2 percent of 2019 levels: “Despite the complex challenges and multiple uncertainties that the global economy is currently faced, the economy of MSAR has demonstrated a solid recovery trend. In the first quarter of 2025, the dimension of the local economy reached 85.2 percent of the same period registered at the same period 2019 ”, was highlighted.
Beijing's hand
AMCM has linked the role of the central government in Macao's economic diversification plans: “In addition, with the support of the central government, the government of MSAR is ordered, in an orderly manner, the development of the proper diversification of the economy and regional cooperation, further reinforcing the sustainability of mashed economic growth,” was reported.
The financial notation of different agencies serves as a reference for investors when they make decisions about the debts they buy. The better the assessment, the lower the risk of not being able to pay debts, which leads to the interest paid by the issuers to be lower.
However, as Macau does not issue debt, unlike the interior of China, the notation has not truly impacting, and is an opinion of an external entity on local public finances.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:27:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Bela Vista Road | Hundred with land for substation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/estrada-da-bela-vista-cem-com-terreno-para-subestacao/</link><description>Six plots of land near the Bela Vista Road, on the Macao Peninsula, joined the State Public Domain, according to an order signed by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam Vai Man, published yesterday in the official bulletin.
Of the six land recovered, four lots with a total area of ​​2,425 square meters will be added and granted, “by private use and with dismissal of public tender”, to the Macao Electricity Company (CEM).
According to the order signed by Raymond Tam, the lot will be destined to build a substation and support facilities, in a single property with five floors, one of them in a basement. The granting of private use for one hundred will be valid for 15 years, and may be renewed upon request submitted between one year and six months from the end of the concession period.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:55:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro | Profit of 17.43 million despite subsidies cuts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/metro-lucro-de-1743-milhoes-apesar-de-cortes-nos-subsidios/</link><description>Without the Budget subsidies of the MSAR, the company that explores the light meter would have presented losses of 660.67 million patacas. However, ticket sales revenues are improving
 
Last year, the profits of the Macao Light Metro Society recorded a reduction of 16.7 million patacas, falling to 17.43 million patacas. The numbers were published yesterday, through the Portal of the Directorate of Services of Supervision and Management of Public Assets (DSSGAP), and the difference can be explained with the reduction of public subsidies.
The result represents a break of 48.9 percent compared to the profit of 34.13 million patacas presented in 2023. For this difference, the government subsidies contributed to the company, and without which the results would always be negative.
In 2023, the government delivered subsidies to the company that explores the 705.47 million Patacas meter. Last year this number had a cut of 48.9 million patacas, falling to 678.10 million patacas.
However, without the support of the MSAR, the company would have lost 660.67 million Patacas last year, which represents an improvement compared to 2023, when without government support the losses would have been 671.34 million patacas. However, companies' revenues show signs of improvement, especially at the level of ticket sales.
Ticket sales revenues rose to 27.06 million patacas, when the previous year had been 13.21 million patacas, which means that within one year more than doubled. This increase was explained by the company with the opening of the Seac Pai line goes in November last year and with the opening of the Hengqin line in December.
Other sources
Also the revenues with the parking lot registered an increase of 596 thousand patacas to 1.3 million patacas. In addition, the sale of cards to use Metro saw the recipes rise from 344 thousand patacas to 676 thousand patacas.
At the same time, “other revenues” were 6.76 million patacas, an increase compared to 4.53 million patacas from the previous year. While interest rates were 52.0 million patacas, when the previous year had been 47.45 million patacas. However, operating expenses grew more than 12 million patacas to 746.77 million patacas by 2024, when the previous year had been 734.15 million patacas.
The highest expenses involved costs with staff that reached 299.70 million Patacas the operation and maintenance of the subway lines that represented expenses of 229.75 million patacas and other expenses that reached 89.68 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:54:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed with scholastic rigor stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I do not always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification as to their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funeral trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells will we have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Borders | Thai and Cambodian soldiers in confrontation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/fronteiras-soldados-tailandeses-e-cambojanos-em-confronto/</link><description>Soldiers from Thailand and Cambodia yesterday exchanged shots in a disputed border zone, the armies of both countries reported.
According to a statement from the Thai part, the Cambodian soldiers entered the disputed area and the Thai approached to negotiate. However, due to a misunderstanding, the Cambodian side opened fire and the Thai soldiers retaliated. Cambodia Army spokesman Mao Phalla said the country's troops were performing a routine patrol along the border when the other side opened fire.
The confrontation lasted about ten minutes until local commanders communicated and ordered a ceasefire. The Thai army stated that both parties were negotiating and that the confrontation did not make victims.
The Phnom Penh representative noted that there is no information on any victims so far. Thai Defense Minister Phumtham Wechayachai said the situation is resolved and that the two parts did not intend to make the shots. Thailand and Cambodia, neighboring countries, have a long history of territorial disputes. The incident was recorded on video and became viral on social networks.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:10:15</pubDate></item><item><title>UN criticizes new model of food help distribution in Gaza</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/onu-critica-novo-modelo-de-distribuicao-de-ajuda-alimentar-em-gaza/</link><description>UN Chief Agency for Refugees (Unrwa), Philippe Lazzarini, defended yesterday that the new model of food distribution in Gaza, supported by Washington, is a “waste of resources and a distraction from atrocities”.
"I believe it is a waste of resources and a distraction of atrocities. We already have a proper help distribution system. The humanitarian community in Gaza, including Unrwa, is ready. We have the experience and knowledge necessary to reach the needy people," said Lazzarini.
The official added that the time to avoid hunger "is running out" and that humanitarian employees "need to be allowed to make their work save lives now." The new US Humanitarian Foundation (GHF), supported by the US, began its operations on Tuesday at a southern gaza's aid distribution center. According to journalists from France Presse, there were moments of chaos when thousands of people ran from this new center to the center in Rafah.
Chaos installed
Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu acknowledged on Tuesday that there was a "temporary loss of control" in a new Gaza's aid distribution center.
"We have developed a plan with our American friends to control the distribution sites where an American company would distribute food to Palestinian families," Netanyahu said during a speech in Jerusalem, adding that "there was a temporary loss of control" when the Palestinians hosted an open center in Rafah [southern Gaza]. "
The incident occurred at the moment Israel, which in mid -May intensified the offensive in the hungry Palestinian territory, devastated for 19 months of war, is applying a new help distribution system, contested by the humanitarian community.
United Nations agencies have argued that the flow of aid to Palestinian territory is insufficient and limited by restrictions such as crossing of insecure areas due to combat, risk of looting and delays because of coordination with Israelite military.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:08:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Accident | Six missing people after factory explosion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/acidente-seis-pessoas-desaparecidas-apos-explosao-em-fabrica/</link><description>Six people are still missing following an explosion in an eastern chemical factory in East China, which resulted in the deaths of five people and wounded another 19. Tuesday's explosion in a weifang industrial park in the province of Shandong, toppled nearby building windows and launched a thick cloud of white smoke, according to shared social networks.
It was not immediately clear what caused the explosion, which occurred in a factory belonging to Gaomi Youdao CO., a producer of pesticides and chemicals for medical use with more than 500 employees, according to the company's records. Local firefighters sent more than 230 staff to the scene, according to state television CCTV.
A student from a school located about a mile from the factory told local press that he heard an explosion and saw dirty yellow smoke out of the factory. The young man also stated that there was a strange smell and that respiratory protection masks were given to all students.
An employee of the local environmental office told The Paper that a team was sent to the scene to control potential pollution, but has not yet presented any report.
Last year, the chemical factory was cited by “safety risks” at least twice, but in September was praised by Weifang's Emergency Management Office for relying on Communist Party members to effectively manage risks in the workplace. Specifically, party members in Gaomi Youdao identified more than 800 safety risks in the first eight months of 2024 and rectified us to all, the office said.
Workplace safety has been improving over the years in China, but it remains a persistent problem. The National Ministry of Emergency Management recorded 21,800 incidents and 19,600 deaths in 2024.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Tariffs | China points to the immense demand from the US market after 90 day truce</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/tarifas-china-aponta-para-imensa-procura-do-mercado-dos-eua-apos-tregua-de-90-dias/</link><description>China yesterday highlighted the increase in sending containers to the United States, since the two countries agreed a 90 -day commercial truce, which demonstrates "immense demand" and that the economic ties "benefit both".
"This shows that cooperation between the world's two largest economies has brought tangible benefits to companies and consumers from both countries," China's Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokeswoman Mao Ning said.
Mao added that following the agreement reached in Switzerland to lower customs rates for three months -the US from 145 percent to 30 percent and China from 125 percent to 10 percent -"US orders have increased," showing "huge demand." "Protectionism takes nowhere," said Hand. Beijing "welcomes the US and other countries to cooperate and do business" in China, he said.
Suspension of rates ends on August 10 and some analysts are optimistic about the possibility of a longer lasting trade agreement to help reduce the risk of disorders in the supply chain before the end of the year.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:01:15</pubDate></item><item><title>European companies reduce investments against economic slowdown</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/29/empresas-europeias-reduzem-investimentos-face-a-abrandamento-economico/</link><description>European companies are cutting costs and reducing investment plans in China as the economy slows down and fierce competition drops prices, according to an annual survey released yesterday.
"Many companies continue to reassess their involvement with the Chinese market, with a large number to cut costs, reduce expansion plans, transfer investments to other regions and take steps to isolate their supply chains in China and the rest of the world," reads the results of the European Union Trade Chamber in China.
"Confronted with a series of challenges-including the persistence of regulatory barriers and market access, increased geopolitical tensions, price deflation, low internal consumption and margin reduction-the optimism of chamber members in relation to short and medium term perspectives is now historically low level," he added.
The challenges faced by European companies reflect broader problems of the world's second largest economy, affected by a prolonged real estate crisis, which has contained consumer spending.
Other wars
Beijing also faces protectionist measures from the United States and Europe, in response to China's persistent commercial surpluses. "The scenario has deteriorated in many key indicators," the European Union Chamber of Commerce in China said, in the introduction of its business confidence survey 2025.
The same forces that are boosting Chinese exports are penalizing business in the domestic market. Chinese companies, often supported by state subsidies, have intensively invested in specific sectors, such as electric vehicles, leading to the installed capacity of factories to overcome demand widely.
This excess of capacity has given rise to fierce price wars, which reduced profits and led companies to drain the excess production abroad, raising accusations of 'dumping' - a sale below production cost.
In Europe, this situation has generated fears that Chinese imports could harm local industries and their workers. Last year, the European Union has increased customs rates on electric vehicles from China, claiming that the country unfairly subsidized the sector.
"I think there is a clear perception that the benefits of bilateral trade and investment relationships are not being distributed equitably," said the EU Mayor in China, Jens Eskelund, during the presentation of the survey.
Pros and cons
Eskelund greeted China's efforts to stimulate consumption, but argued that the government should also take steps to ensure that the growth of supply does not exceed demand. Inquiry results indicate that the downward pressure on profits has increased over the past year and that the drop in business confidence has not yet reached its lowest point, he said.
About 500 associated companies responded to the inquiry between mid -January and mid -February. "It's very difficult for everyone at this time, in a decline margin environment," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-05-29 00:00:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | China, Asean and Gulf States promise economic solidarity</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/28/tarifas-china-asean-e-estados-do-golfo-prometem-solidariedade-economica/</link><description>In addition to the commitments made to combat the economic war launched by Donald Trump, the countries represented in the tripartite summit in Malaysia also expressed profound concern about the situation in Gaza
 
China, Southeast Asian countries and six Gulf states pledged to promote narrow cooperation yesterday, with a strong emphasis on economic integration and energy collaboration, in a context of the trade war launched by Washington.
In a joint statement, the leaders of the Southeast Asian Nations Association (Asean), the Gulf Cooperation Council (CCG) and China reaffirmed their commitment to a multilateral commercial system based on rules and economic globalization, manifesting simultaneously “serious concerns” with the situation in Gaza.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang considered the tripartite summit, which took place in Kuala Lumpur, “an innovative initiative” in transregional cooperation, in an international “volatile” and weak global growth. Malaysian Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim praised the joint statement issued at the end of the meeting, considering it “detailed and elaborate” and a strong message of solidarity and trilateral cooperation.
Based on an Asean summit with the CCG in 2023, the meeting was seen as an effort to diversify commercial bonds and counteract the tariffs launched by US President Donald Trump. The declaration of 4,200 words did not directly mention the United States, nor touched sensitive issues such as territorial disputes in the Southern Sea of ​​China or the deepening of the crisis in Myanmar (former Burma).
Malaysia is Asean's current rotary president, which also includes Brunei, Cambodia, Indonesia, Laos, Myanmar, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam. The CCG includes the Barorian oil producing nations, Kuwait, Saudi Arabia, Oman, Qatar and United Arab Emirates.
Chisel
In their joint statement, the parties recognized the “fundamental role of China in the promotion of peace, stability, prosperity and sustainable development at regional and world level”, as well as the centrality of ASEAN in regional affairs and the “central role” of the CCG in the Middle East.
Highlighting mutual respect, international law, multilateralism, and its common commitment to regional stability, economic integration and sustainable development, the declaration outlined a broad trilateral cooperation framework, in close consonance with the Chinese track and route initiative and its impulse to expand world economic ties.
The parties said they have recognized the need to reinforce trust in a rules -based multilateral commercial system, with the World Trade Organization at its core, and reaffirmed its determination to make economic globalization more open, inclusive, balanced and beneficial to their peoples and future generations.
Full conviction
With regard to the Middle East, the leaders of China, the CCG and the Asean expressed "serious concerns" and condemned all attacks against civilians, simultaneously appealing to a lasting ceasefire in Gaza and the "most effective and affordable distribution of humanitarian aid."
The support for the implementation of the “two -state solution” was also reiterated, recognizing the international mediation efforts developed by China, Qatar and Saudi Arabia. Participants also pledged to seek narrow cooperation to prevent and combat transnational crime, cybercriminality, terrorism and extremism.
In his opening speech by the Trilateral summit on Tuesday, I read Qiang to "firmly take this historical opportunity to enrich trilateral cooperation."
China and Asean are the main trading partners with each other, while the CCG provides more than one third of China's gross oil imports. ASEAN, CCG and China have a joint GDP of almost 25 billion dollars and a market of over 2 billion people.</description><pubDate>2025-05-28 23:58:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Japan promises humanitarian aid</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/gaza-japao-promete-ajuda-humanitaria/</link><description>Japanese Prime Minister Shigero Ishiba promised the Nations Agency for Palestinian refugees (Unrwa) that Japan will contribute to the arrival of humanitarian aid in the Gaza Strip.
"Japan aims to work to ensure the maintenance of a sustainable environment in which humanitarian assistance activities can be performed," Ishiba told UNRWA Director-General Philippe Lazzarini during a meeting in Tokyo, according to a statement from the Japanese Foreign Ministry.
Lazzarini made a courtesy visit of about 20 minutes to the Japanese president, who expressed his respect for the international organization and his condolences to employees who died during the conflict with Israel in the Gaza Strip.
The Unrwa Director-General expressed his gratitude for the assistance provided by Japan to date and explained the current humanitarian situation in the Gaza Strip, as well as the conditions facing Unrwa and his efforts to improve his management, after the temporary help of certain countries, including Japan, due to the alleged calls of some of his employees with the Islamita Hamas group.
Ishiba and Lazzarini confirmed that they will continue to collaborate to support Palestinian refugees facing "a serious crisis," the ministry added.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 22:52:55</pubDate></item><item><title>China / EU | Commerce responsible again meet in June</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/china-ue-responsaveis-pelo-comercio-voltam-a-reunir-se-em-junho/</link><description>Those responsible for trade in China and the European Union (EU) will meet again in June, the Chinese official press yesterday, in a period of rapprochement, against the trade war launched by Washington.
The Global Times newspaper said that Chinese trade minister Wang Wenta will meet with the European Commissioner for Economic Trade and Security, Slovaco Maros Sefcovic, as part of a World Trade Organization (WTO) ministerial summit in Paris.
After Sefcovic's visit to China in late March, the two commercial representatives “have been in close communication, maintaining extensive and in -depth discussions on issues related to economic and commercial cooperation between China and EU”, according to Global Times.
And, in a videochamada held in early April, the two parties agreed to start consultations on market access issues and immediately start negotiations on Brussels imposed on electric cars imported from China.
An expert quoted by Global Times framed the increase in contacts between Beijing and Brussels in a context of “growing protectionism and unilateralism of some Western countries”, in a clear reference to the United States.
The EU Chamber of Commerce in China recently revealed that the Chinese government has extended the “red carpet” to European companies operating in the country, although they continue to complain about inequalities in market access and also the favorable treatment Beijing gives their state companies.
The news of the meeting comes after US President Donald Trump has agreed to extend the deadline to negotiate a trade agreement with the EU until July 9, to avoid 50 percent rates. Since mid -month, the US and China have been in a 90 -day truce that reduced the additional rates that had applied to each other during the tariff of previous weeks.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 22:43:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Ukraine | China reiterates that it has not provided weapons to Russia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/27/ucrania-china-reitera-que-nao-forneceu-armas-a-russia/</link><description>China reiterated yesterday that it never provided lethal weapons “to either part of the parties” in the war in Ukraine, after Kiev said again that Beijing provides military materials and equipment to the Russian weaponry industry.
"We never provide lethal weapons to either party involved in the conflict and rigorously control the double-use civil and military articles. Ukraine knows it very well," the Ministry of Foreign Ministry spokesman Mao Ning said yesterday at a press conference.
The spokesman added that China opposes “unfounded accusations” and “political manipulation” in response to the head of the Ukrainian external information service, Oleh Ivasshchenko, who told Ukrainian press on Monday that “Kiev can confirm that Beijing provides important materials and equipment to 20 Russian military factories”.
Last month, Ukraine had already accused China of providing direct military assistance to the Russian weaponry industry. According to Ivashchenko, your country has data that confirms that "China provides machines, special chemicals, gunpowder and components specific to the Russian defense industries."
Aposi at dialogue
Since the beginning of the war in Ukraine, China has kept an ambiguous position on conflict, appealing to respect for the “territorial integrity of all countries,” including Ukraine, and attention to the “legitimate concerns of all” states in reference to Russia.
Beijing opposed “unilateral” sanctions against Moscow and called for a “political solution” to the conflict. The West accused China of supporting the Russian military campaign, which he has always denied, and to provide Russian leader Vladimir Putin, essential components for weapons production.
European countries have also repeatedly appealed to Chinese leader Xi Jinping to use their influence on Putin to end conflict, although some argue that China has given priority to reinforce its relations with Russia, which has imported low -cost oil and gas.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 22:20:56</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the appropriate place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
What other projects are in this book?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Yes. The idea of ​​publication, with Barcelona's Actar Books, has to do with putting the work, and more than that, its message, which is very specific to Macau and our way of working in the international and architects community, and this goes a lot through the Biennial. It was also in Europe that a consensus was built on the level of descriptions [in architecture] for a few centuries, and where there is a discussion, national and international, around the issues of the profession. We want our work to be present, either through the book and through acting Books, in this international community, to be part of the world.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through the space narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and see as soon as I was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the guide circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of copies produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos also underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitano Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major goal will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name in Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao's historicals get a GP clearance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/20/historicos-de-macau-conseguem-apuramento-para-gp/</link><description>The Guangdong International Circuit welcomed, last weekend, the second and decisive double journey of Macao - Macau Road Sport Challenge cars, proof of finding for the most important motor racing of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. In a journey with few celebration reasons for the colors of the sinters, the veterans Jerónimo Badaraco and Rui Valente managed to ensure the qualification.
With a list of 68 subscribers, the grill was divided into two groups, A and B, with all the pilots competing with Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) models. This year, with only one race scheduled for the Grand Prix Program - due to the inclusion of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup - the number of riders was reduced to 36, which placed a supplementary pressure for both missing races. To complicate, the rain came, changing the turns to teams and riders.
In Group A, where Rui Valente faced a complicated weekend on the track around Zhaoqing, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão failed to qualify, in a series dominated by Hong Kong pilots. In Saturday's race, the podium consisted of Wong Chuck Pan, Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping. On Sunday, these three repeated the feat, but with a new order: Lo Pak Yu, Chan Ka Ping and Wong Chuck Pan.
In difficult atmospheric conditions on Saturday, Rui Valente ended only 25th, due to an error in tuning, improving to 15th on Sunday, with the track dry. A penalty after the second race fired him to the 27th place. Still, the 7th place obtained on the first round was enough to secure a place in the Macao Grand Prix.
On the contrary, Maximiano Mannão, behind the wheel of a Toyota with the colors of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended on 26th and 14th, a result below the finding, but it turns out to be positive given that it was Jove Pilot's debut in these wanderings. Célio Alves Dias, with difficulties in his car since the first race, was 24th and 28th, far from the usual level of this experienced Macaense pilot.
Badaraco with final sprint '
On a weekend, where the lively races were broadcast on live streaming in Group B, Hong Kong riders stood out again. On Sunday, Adrian Chung won, with Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin completing the podium. In the second confrontation, Cheang Kin Sang reached a deserved victory, followed again by Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin.
Jerónimo Badaraco came to this challenging weekend without the assured clearance. A modest qualification and 11th Saturday place maintained the open outcome. However, a solid race on Sunday and an excellent 4th place assured veteran Macanese the much desired place on the grid of the Macao Grand Prix, along with countrymen Cheng Kin San, Leong Keng Hei, Lou Check In and Carson Tang.
Also outside the Grand Prix was Dionísio Albino Pereira, who finished 23rd in Saturday's race, but closed the time more forcefully, cutting the line of goal in 13th place in the second race.
At the end of the races, competitors provisionally calculated had an extra technical verification, being forced to open engines and gearbox, to verify the legality of these two decisive organs of their vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-05-20 01:57:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Motorial Council approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and a MSAR test enthusiast, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The growth and development potential in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into details, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula Cup last year, says that “this big step will benefit undoubtedly local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSAR VICTORY AND TOP-10 to Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite the safety car entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet beginning, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, third in the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item></channel></rss>