<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Jiangyou | Protests require severe sanctions after aggression to the lowest</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/jiangyou-protestos-exigem-sancoes-severas-apos-agressao-a-menor/</link><description>Hundreds of people have manifested themselves in the Chinese city of Jiangyou to demand more severe punishments from minors involved in aggression to a 14-year-old colleague, in a case filmed and disclosed online that generated widespread indignation on social networks.
The protests included posters with the image of the victim, nicknamed Lai, and songs to ask for a "fair investigation." Videos shared on social network X show confrontations with police and punctual arrests.
The popular revolt intensified after the announcement by the police authorities that the perpetrators would only be the target of “administrative measures” and sent to a correctional educational center. The decision was made twelve days after the complaint was filed, an excessive interval by many netizens.
Before that, a widely shared photograph on the networks showed family members of Lai kneeling before a local official, asking for justice, which further increased social pressure.
The aggression, filmed in the vicinity of a teaching establishment, shows Lai to be slapped by at least two colleagues, from nicknames Liu and Peng. In one of the videos, one of the aggressors boast of having been "more than ten times" in a squad without "never being more than twenty minutes."
On the same day of aggression, on July 22, Lai went with his father to the police to file a complaint. After a preliminary medical examination, he returned later to make statements.
According to the local newspaper The Paper, between July 24 and August 3, the police interrogated all witnesses and requested a forensic report, according to national body damage assessment standards, which recommend examining the victim between one and two weeks after stabilization of the injuries.
On 3 August, doctors ruled out hidden fractures and classified the injuries as slight. The next day, the authorities ended the case with the application of administrative sanctions.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:14:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Medical Error | Leong Sun IOK suggests revision of the legislation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/erro-medico-leong-sun-iok-sugere-revisao-da-legislacao/</link><description>Deputy Leong Sun IOK argues, in a video released on social networks, that the legislation on medical error must be reviewed taking into account the amounts charged to the compulsory insurance provided for in the regime. For the deputy, the values are not reasonable and the regime needs to be reviewed, considering that it has entered into force eight years ago.
The deputy said he had received complaints from doctors and responsible for private clinics, which is why he felt the need to intervene. The complainants will have said that daily treat simple diseases that do not involve high -risk medical operations or acts, and that compulsory insurance is a heavy load.
Leong Sun Iok explained that the price of insurance is almost the same for all doctors who can only purchase insurance in Macao in a monopolistic market. For this reason, the deputy cites opinions of the medical class that it should be allowed to buy insurances to his choice, and there is the possibility of reducing the value of the benefit taking into account the number of care and associated compensations.
According to the deputy, the sector also wants the opening of a liability insurance system that encompasses the cities that are part of the great bay as an alternative, asking the Macao government to create a fund for this new insurance and compensation schemes to support the medical sector.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:37:34</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Three detainees for credit cards</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/pj-tres-detidos-por-burlas-com-cartoes-de-credito/</link><description>The Judiciary Police (PJ) announced the detention of three people due to the theft of bank payment card data, which were then used to make online shopping. In total, the authorities estimate that the criminal network has made improper purchases and payments of 1.18 million patacas.
According to the contours of the case, in May, September and October last year PJ received reports from two banks on the existence of suspicious transactions in Macao using data from cards issued abroad. In total 2,611 transactions were performed that resulted in a movement of 3.5 million patacas. Transactions involved online payments or use of terminals for credit card purchases. Among these, 771 transactions, which represented 1.18 million patacas are challenged by banks as illegitimate and without permission of card owners.
The transactions were made at local shops. However, police investigation concluded that the amounts traded during the dates in question do not make sense in the light of the normal business volume investigated. It was also concluded that the amount of sales is not consistent with the type of products available.
Cards whose data were used were issued in the United States, Belarus, France, Indonesia, South Africa, Middle East and Taiwan.
The detainees are three residents of Macao, including a 39 -year -old man who owns a car sales stand. Another 34 -year -old man was arrested on his own, and a 38 -year -old woman, a beauty product seller.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:50:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinematheque | Fantastic cycle to see in the coming weeks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/cinemateca-ciclo-fantastico-para-ver-nas-proximas-semanas/</link><description>Cinemateca Paixão presents this month a new movie cycle, entitled “Daydreams &amp; Labirintos - Fantastic Film Festival”. Among the selected titles, highlighting “Dangerous Animals” and the frightening “Massacre in Texas”, without forgetting the musical touch brought with the documentary about the blur
 
Cinema has the gift of revealing us other life forms and stories, but when these stories have a hint of horror or fantastic, the attraction to the movie you will see can differentiate yourself, for the better or worse. For those who love horror movies or fantastic genre stories, this is a good month to go to Cinematheque Paixão, which features the cycle “Daydreams &amp; Labyrinths - Fantastic Cinema Festival”. A total of 17 films integrates this poster, which extends until September.
And one of the highlights goes to "Dangerous Animals", aired on 16 August and then on September 6th.
This is a story that refers to the unlucky of Zephyr, a cunning and free -spirited surfer who is kidnapped by a serial killer obsessed with sharks and held a prisoner in his boat.
The woman will have to find a way to escape before this killer gives her to eat to the sharks that swim under the site where Zephyr is. Only Moses realize that she has disappeared, being a person for whom she has a loving interest.
Also noteworthy is the exhibition of the restored copy of “Massacre in Texas”, a 1974 film that celebrated 50 years of existence last year, and is still current and with a wave of fans.
Performed by Tobe Hooper, "Massacre in Texas" remains a reference for the subgenre of horror films entitled "Slasher". It was filmed in a short time, with a limited budget and actors completely unknown to the general public.
"There is no corner of the world where you can go and say the title" Texas Chainsaw Massacre "and no one knows what is talking about, whether you have seen the movie or not," France Presse (AFP) Chase Andersen of Exurbia Films, which holds the rights of the saga.
The story focuses on a carefree group of young people who come across an isolated house occupied by a masked lunatic that begins to cut them with sharp things, Leatherface. At Cinemateca Passion the film will be screened on Saturday, August 30.
Faces of happiness
“Different Man” [a different man] is not just about a man who has a strange disease that deforms his face, making him a monster in the shape of people. It is also a story about the meaning and conception of happiness, and how it depends on one's life and choices.
The protagonist, Oswald, is played by Adam Pearson, an actor who has always fought against neurofibromatosis that changed his face forms. Oswald had everything to be an unfortunate and shy man, hiding from humanity, but the opposite happens: he can be popular and a person perfectly integrated into society. The same does not happen to an actor with whom he intersects. “Different Man” will be aired on August 19th and 29th.
On August 16, “The Dream of Alexandria” will be shown, which refers to the 1920 Los Angeles, when in Hollywood still dominates silent cinema. In these times an immigrant girl appears hospitalized in a hospital after a fall, and who is friends with an adherence man, also paralyzed due to an accident during a footage. He enchants her with a fantastic story that carries her beyond the hospital's monotony, towards the exotic landscapes of her own imagination. This version displayed at this festival is also a 4K -restored version with additional scenes compared to the 2006 version, having been filmed in 24 countries.
THE HISTORY OF THE BLUR
“Blur: To the End” [Blur: Until the end] is a 2024 documentary scheduled for screening on August 17 and September 7, and where the history of friendship and companionship of the Blur members, British band of Britpop and Alternative Rock formed in the 1980s, which marked an entire generation in the 1990s.
This documentary was filmed in 2023, when the band met to record new songs and to prepare for the first shows at Wembley Stadium in London, which were exhausted. The film features interpretations of the most iconic and fans -cherished themes, including images of the band in the studio and on the road.
In a very different record is “the girl with the needle”, aired on August 22 and September 7, in which the story of Karoline, a manufacturing worker who fights to survive in the city of Copenhagen, in the years after World War II. When he finds himself unemployed, abandoned and pregnant, he intersects with Dagmar, a charismatic woman who generates a clandestine adoption agency, helping mothers to find homes of reception for unwanted children. With no alternative, Karoline accepts the role of milk loves. Between the two women is born a strong connection, but Karoline's world collapses when discovering the shocking truth behind her work, describes the synopsis of the film.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:01:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Medical Residences | Registration for 79 vacancies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/residencias-medicas-abertas-inscricoes-para-79-vagas/</link><description>Today open registration for medical residency exams for 33 specialties. Of the 79 vacancies available, 29 will be to form clinical paintings of the Conde de São Januário Hospital and 28 to the Ilhas Hospital. Specialties include cardiology, psychiatry, internal medicine, family medicine and geriatrics
 
The government officially announced yesterday the opening of the contest to evaluate “medical integrated skills, for admission to the medical residency” of 79 professionals who will reinforce the clinical staff of hospitals in the territory. The parameters of the contest were released yesterday in the official bulletin, in a publication signed by the director of Alvis Lo health services.
Registration opens today and interested parties can apply until August 18 to the competition of the liability of the Medical Academy.
Qualified candidates admitted to the Residency Program will receive six years of systematic training in the workplace in public, private and community health institutions in Macao, consisting of two years of basic training and four years of advanced training.
The 79 vacancies for medical residences will be divided into 33 specialties, including 10 surgeons, but also cardiology, psychiatry, internal medicine, family medicine and geriatrics. Among the nearly eight dozen vacancies, only three are for psychiatry doctors (all for the hospital Conde de São Januário)
The two poles
Among the vacancies that will open to medical residences, 29 will reinforce the clinical condition of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, 28 at the Island Health Care Complex, seven at Kiang Wu Hospital, two in public health at the Disease Prevention and Control Center and 13 in family medicine in the Community Health Care Department.
According to a statement published yesterday by health services, the contest for medical residences resulted from the work of the Macao Medical Academy Specialty Council, which took office in March.
The body led by Alvis Lo promises that he will continue to develop "access to medical residency in order to prepare the reserve of talents from different specialties and raise the overall level of Macao medical services."
The government is also committed to deepening cooperation with training institutions, and optimizing the allocation of training resources and increasing vacancies for more trainees, with the aim of creating a “broader professional development platform for young doctors in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:42:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Chikungunya fever | Critical phase of prevention and control</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/febre-de-chikungunya-fase-critica-de-prevencao-e-controlo/</link><description>With a total of eight cases registered in Macao, two of them local, health services point out that the territory is in the critical phase of prevention and control of chikungunya fever. The subject was approached yesterday on the Macau Forum Morning Program, from the Chinese channel of Radio Macau
 
In a disease propagated by mosquitoes, prevention is everything. And Macao is currently in the early and critical prevention and control of chikungunya fever prevention and control, the head of the Center for Prevention and Control of Health Services (SS), Chan Choi Wan, said yesterday. The statements were made on the morning program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the Macao Forum.
The official said he hoped that the population can apply stagnant water zones cleaning measures in order to avoid the spread of mosquitoes that can cause this disease. These zones can be stagnant water puddles or water spaces with water, having been recommended to wear long clothes to avoid mosquito bites, or even the use of mosquito nets.
"Chikungunya fever and dengue fever are transmitted through mosquitoes of ade mosquitoes, not being transmitted diseases among humans. These are transmitted but controllable diseases and whose prevention is possible," he said in the radio program.
However, Chan Choi Wan pointed out that, although there is no community transmission, the risk of transmission in Macau remains high due to the importation of cases.
Asked about scientific criteria for the establishment of mosquito elimination zones, Chan Choi Wan said that after the epidemiological analysis of each case of infection is performed the elimination of mosquitoes in the risk zone. A circular radius is also calculated taking into account the approximate distance from the mosquito flight.
The substitute chief of the Environmental Hygiene Division of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), Pang Sao Hun, recalled that since July, more mosquito elimination actions have been carried out.
"Regarding the hygiene of private places or unoccupied land, if it is verified of an urgent or risk or risk situation for public health, and if we cannot contact the owners, AMI seeks to coordinate to remove stagnant water spaces and waste, in order to avoid the spread of mosquitoes and thus reduce the risk of disease transmission," he said.
Light symptoms
Macao currently has eight cases of chikungunya fever, of which six are imported and two locations. Public health doctor at the Ieong Chon Kit disease prevention and control center revealed that the two patients relating to local cases are still being treated at the hospital with light symptoms.
On Tuesday, the Zhuhai market regulation administration has published a warning of chikungunya fever control in pharmacies, noting that pharmacies need to record data from the users who buy analgesic medications or have symptoms of this fever, or have been chopped by mosquitoes. Authorities also asked pharmacies to disclose information on the prevention and control measures of these two types of fever.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Kiang Wu Association | Land used for parking was recovered</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/associacao-kiang-wu-terreno-usado-para-estacionamento-foi-recuperado/</link><description>It was to be used as a park of Keang Peng school, but at least since 1996 it was no longer this end. 30 years after, the executive decided to recover the land because he considered that the free concession contract had been violated
 
The government recovered land that had been freely assigned to the Kiang Wu Hospital Beneficency Association to function as a park of a school. At issue is the fact that the lot has been used as a parking lot, violating the terms established in the concession. The information was released yesterday, through an order signed by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam Vai Man.
According to the version published in the official bulletin, the land had been granted free of charge on October 23, 1981 to the Macao Most Popular Private Hospital Association. The concession aimed to create a park to complement the facilities of the Kiang Wu Peng Man Luen Hap School. Years later the name of the educational institution was changed to Keang Peng School, which currently still exists and offers primary and secondary school classes in two different campuses.
However, the school ceased to work at that place in July 1996, almost 30 years ago, so the terrain was no longer useful for which it had been assigned and was used for car parking.
The recovery thus arises following a 147.4 square meter inspection, located on the Macau Peninsula, next to Rua do Barão. "There is the change of purpose of the concession and the end for which the land was granted is not being continued, which is a violation of the duty to use the land in accordance with the purposes assigned in the concession title," was considered by the government.
Silently
Confronted by the executive with the possibility of losing the granting of the land, the Kiang Wu Hospital Benefice Association, led in recent years by businessman Liu Chak Wan, remained silent: “The concessionaire has not commented, in written hearing, about the meaning of declaring the termination of the concession,” was nominated.
Raymond Tam's order also defines that any improvements made on the ground during the concession period go to “the Special Administrative Region of Macao, without any compensation by the Kiang Wu Hospital Beneficency Association”.
Despite not having a defense before the order, the document points out that the Kiang Wu Hospital Beneficency Association may try to challenge the decision of the secretary of recovery of the current parking with the Second Instance Court.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:36:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Hong Kong companies for hengqin</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/cooperacao-convidadas-empresas-de-hong-kong-para-hengqin/</link><description>Hong Kong's chief executive visited Macao and "traded impressions in depth" with Sam Hou Fai to "further reinforce cooperation." The ruler of the mandate reiterated John Lee the importance of Hengqin in the Great Bay project and invited Hong Kong companies to the deepened cooperation zone
 
An entourage of the Hong Kong government, led by executive head John Lee Ka-Chiu, visited Macao and Hengqin on Tuesday afternoon and had a meeting with a team of representatives of the MSAR executive. According to the Social Communication Office (GCS), Sam Hou Fai and John Lee “exchanged impressions in depthly further reinforcing cooperation between the two regions”, in areas such as tourism, “high quality development of the large bay” and “new opportunities” in Hengqin.
The Macao government leader took John Lee and members of his executive on a visit to Hengqin, who identified as an “important platform for Macau's participation in the integrated development of the great bay and the promotion of the proper diversification of the economy”. In this respect, Sam Hou Fai “underlined the participation of more Hong Kong companies” in Hengqin, so as to “grab new opportunities in the second phase of the cooperation zone, to share the benefits of high quality development”.
If you say it
In separate communications, both governments have pointed out that Hong Kong and Macau are also special administrative regions of China which, over the years, have fully used the unique advantages of "one country, two systems," which the Executive of the MSAR states to have "achieved success in worldly remarkable development."
Sam Hou Fai also indicated that Hong Kong and Macau are also central cities of the Great Bay and nuclear engines of regional development.
In tourist terms, the ruler of MSA has suggested that the two regions should take advantage of the experience of national games and hold more sporting events together to "attract more and different tourists to visit Hong Kong, Macao and the entire great bay."
In this area, Sam Hou Fai argued that the two regions should “continue to reinforce the connectivity of the transport network to provide greater facilities to residents and tourists circulating between the two territories”, and bet on promoting “multi-desert” itineraries.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:30:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Economic Report Highlights Startup “Historical Record”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/hong-kong-relatorio-economico-destaca-recorde-historico-de-startups/</link><description>"Hong Kong's startups are on the rise." This is how the executive in the neighboring region describes the business environment in the region, where they were created in 2024 about 4,700 startups, plus 10 percent of 2023. In the "Report of Hong Kong's Business Environment 2025" it is read that the territory is far from losing economic competitiveness
 
The Hong Kong government released last July 30 the latest report on the neighboring region's economic scene. And one of the highlights is given to the scenario of growth of entrepreneurship.
In the “Report of Hong Kong’s Business Environment 2025” [Hong Kong 2025 Business Environment Report] it is noteworthy that “Startups in Hong Kong are on the rise”, given that last year there were “about 4,700 startups in the city, a historic record and an increase of 10 percent from the previous year”.
The document explains that "more than a quarter of these startups has founders from outside Hong Kong," it is companies that operate in a "broad spectrum of sectors, including Fintech [High Technology], Electronic Trade and Information, Informatics and Technology", having hired more than 17,000 people. This number of human resources also represents an increase of seven percent compared to 2023. "All this is proof of Hong Kong's strong appeal for startup entrepreneurs," the authorities highlight.
But it is not only startups that record growth, with the report to point out that the current government, led by executive head John Lee, "achieved remarkable results in attracting companies, investments and talents."
"For example, in 2024, the number of companies in Hong Kong with headquarters outside the territory increased significantly by about 10 percent, reaching almost 10,000." The “Office for the attraction of strategic companies, created more than two years ago, attracted 84 strategic companies to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, including companies with market capitalization or valuation of over $ 10 billion, involving cutting -edge technology”, it is added.
The report also points out that between January 2023 and the first half of this year, Invest Hong Kong, linked to the Raehk government's direct foreign investment department, "helped over 1300 foreign and continent companies establishing or expanding their business in Hong Kong, bringing investments of over $ 160 billion."
Still with regard to Invest Hong Kong, the entity helped "539 companies from the continent or foreign to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, which represents an annual growth of over 40 percent."
At the end of June this year, Hong Kong had 1.5 million local companies, while the total number of companies not registered in Hong Kong reached 15 509. "Both numbers represent historical records," it reads, and for the government of the neighboring territory the data "demonstrate the great confidence that continent and abroad companies have in the future of Hong Kong."
Given that Hong Kong also has a talent capture program, the Hong Kong Talent Engage, reads in the report that by June this year "were received about 500,000 candidates in the shelter of various talent admission programs, of which about 330,000 were approved." Of these numbers, Hong Kong actually arrived to work 220,000 qualified frames.
Good scholarship scenario
Quoted on an official press release, a government spokesman stated that "in a complex and volatile external environment, Hong Kong is undergoing a phase of economic update and transformation, but there are more opportunities than challenges."
Given that the territory has always positioned itself as a strong financial market worldwide, this scenario seems to have recorded a recovery in recent years.
“This year Hong Kong's financial market performance has been constantly improving. The Hang SENG Index has a 18 percent increase last year and an increase of more than 25 percent this year so far. The average daily business volume in the first half of the year was about $ 240 billion, with an increase of about 120 percent.”
Authorities highlight the maintenance of the economic competitiveness of the territory, pointing out that "over the years Hong Kong has been constantly classified as a global leader in economic freedom and competitiveness."
Attention to the trade war
In conclusion, Raehk's government clarifies that territory seems to maintain economic stability in times of constant commercial conflicts, with Donald Trump threatening and imposing tariffs on a number of countries.
“As volatile and turbulent as the world may be, we remain firmly committed to the rules -based multilateral commercial system, with the WTO [World Trade Organization] as a nucleus, while actively participating and supporting regional economic cooperation.”
The “numerous advantages of Hong Kong” are referred to, with its “highly internationalized business environment, a flexible and solid financial system, a simple and secure tax regime with low tax rates and a robust and independent legal system”.
Porém, no documento é também salientado que a “guerra tarifária provocou uma realocação global de capital”, sendo que Hong Kong quer apostar na atracção de “empresas e capital estrangeiros” para a região.
O relatório dá também conta de que “as organizações internacionais e as câmaras de comércio estrangeiras em Hong Kong estão confiantes nas perspectivas futuras” do território, e que para as autoridades “não há motivo para preocupação com alguns sentimentos excessivamente pessimistas”.
“Na verdade, o Governo da RAEHK está a criar um novo impulso e a expandir a capacidade para sustentar o crescimento económico de Hong Kong, aumentando assim a sua competitividade geral e alcançando um desenvolvimento de alta qualidade”, é ainda acrescentado.
O porta-voz do Executivo estabeleceu ainda um paralelismo entre a boa situação económica e a estabilidade política. "In recent years, the implementation of the National Security Law has restored a stable social environment in Hong Kong. This not only protected the rights and freedoms of the general public, but also made Hong Kong a safe haven to attract international capital and investment," he concluded. O relatório foi apresentado pelo Secretário para as Finanças de Hong Kong, Paul Chan.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Jiangyou | Protests require severe sanctions after aggression to the lowest</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/jiangyou-protestos-exigem-sancoes-severas-apos-agressao-a-menor/</link><description>Hundreds of people have manifested themselves in the Chinese city of Jiangyou to demand more severe punishments from minors involved in aggression to a 14-year-old colleague, in a case filmed and disclosed online that generated widespread indignation on social networks.
The protests included posters with the image of the victim, nicknamed Lai, and songs to ask for a "fair investigation." Videos shared on social network X show confrontations with police and punctual arrests.
The popular revolt intensified after the announcement by the police authorities that the perpetrators would only be the target of “administrative measures” and sent to a correctional educational center. The decision was made twelve days after the complaint was filed, an excessive interval by many netizens.
Before that, a widely shared photograph on the networks showed family members of Lai kneeling before a local official, asking for justice, which further increased social pressure.
The aggression, filmed in the vicinity of a teaching establishment, shows Lai to be slapped by at least two colleagues, from nicknames Liu and Peng. In one of the videos, one of the aggressors boast of having been "more than ten times" in a squad without "never being more than twenty minutes."
On the same day of aggression, on July 22, Lai went with his father to the police to file a complaint. After a preliminary medical examination, he returned later to make statements.
According to the local newspaper The Paper, between July 24 and August 3, the police interrogated all witnesses and requested a forensic report, according to national body damage assessment standards, which recommend examining the victim between one and two weeks after stabilization of the injuries.
On 3 August, doctors ruled out hidden fractures and classified the injuries as slight. The next day, the authorities ended the case with the application of administrative sanctions.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:14:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Medical Error | Leong Sun IOK suggests revision of the legislation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/erro-medico-leong-sun-iok-sugere-revisao-da-legislacao/</link><description>Deputy Leong Sun IOK argues, in a video released on social networks, that the legislation on medical error must be reviewed taking into account the amounts charged to the compulsory insurance provided for in the regime. For the deputy, the values are not reasonable and the regime needs to be reviewed, considering that it has entered into force eight years ago.
The deputy said he had received complaints from doctors and responsible for private clinics, which is why he felt the need to intervene. The complainants will have said that daily treat simple diseases that do not involve high -risk medical operations or acts, and that compulsory insurance is a heavy load.
Leong Sun Iok explained that the price of insurance is almost the same for all doctors who can only purchase insurance in Macao in a monopolistic market. For this reason, the deputy cites opinions of the medical class that it should be allowed to buy insurances to his choice, and there is the possibility of reducing the value of the benefit taking into account the number of care and associated compensations.
According to the deputy, the sector also wants the opening of a liability insurance system that encompasses the cities that are part of the great bay as an alternative, asking the Macao government to create a fund for this new insurance and compensation schemes to support the medical sector.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:37:34</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Three detainees for credit cards</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/pj-tres-detidos-por-burlas-com-cartoes-de-credito/</link><description>The Judiciary Police (PJ) announced the detention of three people due to the theft of bank payment card data, which were then used to make online shopping. In total, the authorities estimate that the criminal network has made improper purchases and payments of 1.18 million patacas.
According to the contours of the case, in May, September and October last year PJ received reports from two banks on the existence of suspicious transactions in Macao using data from cards issued abroad. In total 2,611 transactions were performed that resulted in a movement of 3.5 million patacas. Transactions involved online payments or use of terminals for credit card purchases. Among these, 771 transactions, which represented 1.18 million patacas are challenged by banks as illegitimate and without permission of card owners.
The transactions were made at local shops. However, police investigation concluded that the amounts traded during the dates in question do not make sense in the light of the normal business volume investigated. It was also concluded that the amount of sales is not consistent with the type of products available.
Cards whose data were used were issued in the United States, Belarus, France, Indonesia, South Africa, Middle East and Taiwan.
The detainees are three residents of Macao, including a 39 -year -old man who owns a car sales stand. Another 34 -year -old man was arrested on his own, and a 38 -year -old woman, a beauty product seller.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:50:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinematheque | Fantastic cycle to see in the coming weeks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/cinemateca-ciclo-fantastico-para-ver-nas-proximas-semanas/</link><description>Cinemateca Paixão presents this month a new movie cycle, entitled “Daydreams &amp; Labirintos - Fantastic Film Festival”. Among the selected titles, highlighting “Dangerous Animals” and the frightening “Massacre in Texas”, without forgetting the musical touch brought with the documentary about the blur
 
Cinema has the gift of revealing us other life forms and stories, but when these stories have a hint of horror or fantastic, the attraction to the movie you will see can differentiate yourself, for the better or worse. For those who love horror movies or fantastic genre stories, this is a good month to go to Cinematheque Paixão, which features the cycle “Daydreams &amp; Labyrinths - Fantastic Cinema Festival”. A total of 17 films integrates this poster, which extends until September.
And one of the highlights goes to "Dangerous Animals", aired on 16 August and then on September 6th.
This is a story that refers to the unlucky of Zephyr, a cunning and free -spirited surfer who is kidnapped by a serial killer obsessed with sharks and held a prisoner in his boat.
The woman will have to find a way to escape before this killer gives her to eat to the sharks that swim under the site where Zephyr is. Only Moses realize that she has disappeared, being a person for whom she has a loving interest.
Also noteworthy is the exhibition of the restored copy of “Massacre in Texas”, a 1974 film that celebrated 50 years of existence last year, and is still current and with a wave of fans.
Performed by Tobe Hooper, "Massacre in Texas" remains a reference for the subgenre of horror films entitled "Slasher". It was filmed in a short time, with a limited budget and actors completely unknown to the general public.
"There is no corner of the world where you can go and say the title" Texas Chainsaw Massacre "and no one knows what is talking about, whether you have seen the movie or not," France Presse (AFP) Chase Andersen of Exurbia Films, which holds the rights of the saga.
The story focuses on a carefree group of young people who come across an isolated house occupied by a masked lunatic that begins to cut them with sharp things, Leatherface. At Cinemateca Passion the film will be screened on Saturday, August 30.
Faces of happiness
“Different Man” [a different man] is not just about a man who has a strange disease that deforms his face, making him a monster in the shape of people. It is also a story about the meaning and conception of happiness, and how it depends on one's life and choices.
The protagonist, Oswald, is played by Adam Pearson, an actor who has always fought against neurofibromatosis that changed his face forms. Oswald had everything to be an unfortunate and shy man, hiding from humanity, but the opposite happens: he can be popular and a person perfectly integrated into society. The same does not happen to an actor with whom he intersects. “Different Man” will be aired on August 19th and 29th.
On August 16, “The Dream of Alexandria” will be shown, which refers to the 1920 Los Angeles, when in Hollywood still dominates silent cinema. In these times an immigrant girl appears hospitalized in a hospital after a fall, and who is friends with an adherence man, also paralyzed due to an accident during a footage. He enchants her with a fantastic story that carries her beyond the hospital's monotony, towards the exotic landscapes of her own imagination. This version displayed at this festival is also a 4K -restored version with additional scenes compared to the 2006 version, having been filmed in 24 countries.
THE HISTORY OF THE BLUR
“Blur: To the End” [Blur: Until the end] is a 2024 documentary scheduled for screening on August 17 and September 7, and where the history of friendship and companionship of the Blur members, British band of Britpop and Alternative Rock formed in the 1980s, which marked an entire generation in the 1990s.
This documentary was filmed in 2023, when the band met to record new songs and to prepare for the first shows at Wembley Stadium in London, which were exhausted. The film features interpretations of the most iconic and fans -cherished themes, including images of the band in the studio and on the road.
In a very different record is “the girl with the needle”, aired on August 22 and September 7, in which the story of Karoline, a manufacturing worker who fights to survive in the city of Copenhagen, in the years after World War II. When he finds himself unemployed, abandoned and pregnant, he intersects with Dagmar, a charismatic woman who generates a clandestine adoption agency, helping mothers to find homes of reception for unwanted children. With no alternative, Karoline accepts the role of milk loves. Between the two women is born a strong connection, but Karoline's world collapses when discovering the shocking truth behind her work, describes the synopsis of the film.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:01:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Dirks Theater | NON -VERBAL THEATER WITH LINKS TO SARAMAGO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/dirks-theatre-teatro-nao-verbal-com-ligacoes-a-saramago/</link><description>It's called “Echoes in Dreams” and is the new nonverbal play of the local company Dirks Theater. Scheduled for September, this show mixes the compositions of Argentine José Luís Merlin, with body performances inspired by the Psychology and the tale “O Centauro”, by José Saramago
 
Macao Dirks Theater's theatrical company features, between September 19th and 21st, the show “Echoes in Dreams”, which constitutes a performance in which bodies wanders to the sound of the classic guitar, with sounds of Argentine José Luís Merlin, and expressions of nonverbal theater.
The play is presented in the northern zone of the peninsula, namely in the space “Hiukok Laboratory, in number 408 of Rua dos Fishermen, specifically in the industrial building Nam Fong.
According to information provided by the company, it mixes a “classic guitar, six strings, and three souls and bodies”, being a show that “will lead the public to observe human behavior from a perspective in the third person, plunging into themes such as physical and subconscious conflict, exploring the very understanding of 'identity'”.
In this play there is also no shortage of influences from Portuguese literature, namely the Nobel Prize for literature José Saramago, with the tale “O Centauro”.
It is a text that begins this way: “The horse stopped. The horseshoe-free hulls were signed in the round stones and slips that covered the almost dry bottom of the river. The man poured his hands, cautiously, the thorny branches that covered his vision to the side of the plain.
“The centaur, an immortal prehistoric creature, half a man, half horse, feels blame for his race has been annihilated by humans while he could do nothing to prevent him. This hybrid creature has been wandered around the world since then, becoming a night figure just to stay away from all human species. last time.
Jung is present
In addition to the reference to Saramago, “Echoes in Dreams” will also seek inspiration from psychology, namely the work “Memories, Dreams, Reflections” by Swiss psychologist Carl Gustav Jung. On stage, Macao guitarist Bruce Chi Man Pun plays the compositions of José Luís Merlin, while actor Ka Man IP and dancer Chloe Wong "have a visual and emotionally evocative performance."
"Echoes in Dreams" is about concepts such as "nostalgia", "contrast", "exile" and "happiness", narrating the inner world of "someone who lives in a certain city." It is also made, in the play, a reflection on the themes of “exile” and “belonging” in the contemporary global context.
Tickets are on sale on the Dart Ticketing platform and cost 240 patacas, with discounts for those who buy tickets in advance and also for students and retired. “Echoes in Dreams” has already climbed the stage once, with another format. According to the company, what the public will see in September is a "small retrospective of the first" Echoes in Dreams "race."
“It will not be the same as we did in 2023. The world has changed and we all move. Let's dance once again,” is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:14:57</pubDate></item><item><title>HIMALAIAS | At least five dead and 100 missing in a sudden flood</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/himalaias-pelo-menos-cinco-mortos-e-100-desaparecidos-em-inundacao-repentina/</link><description>At least five people have died and more than 100 remain missing in a land allocation caused by torrential rainfall in the Indian state of Uttarakhand in Himalayas, a source of the rescue team announced yesterday.
The disaster took place around 1:30 pm on Tuesday in the village of Dharali, in the district of Uttarkashi, when a sudden flood caused a large water drop from the mountains and devastated the village, dragging everything to his passage, including dozens of people. “About 150 people were taken to a safe place.”
According to available information, four people have been found dead and more than 100 are missing. We are still awaiting confirmation from the local administration, ”said the Assistant Response Force (NDRF) Assistant Inspector General, Mohsen Shahedi, who sent three teams to the affected area.
Hours later, the Press Trust of India State News Agency (PTI) reported the recovery of a fifth body of the rubble in Dharali, while search and rescue efforts continue.
Images released by the authorities and the media show the Kheerganga River to suddenly overflow and completely submerge the area, now covered by thick and debris mud, making it difficult to assist authorities.
Uttarakhand chief minister Pushkar Singh Dhami arrived at the disaster scene this morning to coordinate the response at the scene.
"There are great rescue efforts, involving more than 160 police," said Dhami, adding that food packages have been prepared for distribution and a medical team has been mobilized to deal with the injured. Dharali, a popular summer tourist destination, now remains practically isolated after several access roads have been destroyed or blocked by land allings.
Red alert
Authorities have asked residents to remain away from rivers due to the risk of new floods. This disaster happens at a time when a red alert was issued by the Meteorological Institute of India due to the risk of “extremely strong” rainfall in various areas of the state in the coming days.
Uttarakhand, a mountainous and ecologically fragile region, has recorded uninterrupted rainfall during the current monsoon station and numerous land and flooding. The so -called “cloud explosions”, extremely localized phenomena that cause torrential rain in just a few minutes, are especially dangerous in areas such as Himalayas, where the soil cannot absorb water.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:06:48</pubDate></item><item><title>STD | More than 10 million followers in the 28 accounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/dst-mais-de-10-milhoes-de-seguidores-nas-28-contas/</link><description>Last month, the 28 official accounts of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) exceeded 10 million followers on various social networks.
According to a statement released yesterday by the body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes, the promotional strategy on social networks has conveyed “visitors around the world, in an innovative and interactive way, the latest tourist information, festivities, events and typical experiences of Macao”.
Given the Internet habits of different visitor issues, STD has opened accounts on social networks such as Twitter, Facebook, Youtube, Instagram, Tiktok, Kakao Talk, Line, Wechat, Weibo, Red Note, Douyin (Chinese Tiktok), depending on the region or country.
STD also bet on the invitation to digital influencers from the interior of China and Hong Kong to publicize Macau on their platforms through broad broadcasts, images or short videos. Investment in digital influencers promotions, coupled with toy brands campaigns such as pop Mart, focuses on attracting generation Z visitors.
Recently, the STD account in Tiktok has launched a series of short dramas in Indonesian, filmed in Macao and directed to the young audience, which accumulated about 100 million views.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values “the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's World Heritage Site, has a "high to extreme" prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees Celsius above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the most extensive and severe bleaching that there is registration to date”, read in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot recover sufficiently quickly between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values “the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's World Heritage Site, has a "high to extreme" prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees Celsius above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the most extensive and severe bleaching that there is registration to date”, read in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot recover sufficiently quickly between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values “the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's World Heritage Site, has a "high to extreme" prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees Celsius above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the most extensive and severe bleaching that there is registration to date”, read in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot recover sufficiently quickly between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Zhao Gou (1107-1187), Emperor Gaozong (R.1127-62), lived the difficult time of recreation of the Song dynasty, when in 1127 his members were forced by the Jurchen nomades to abandon the capital Bianjing (current Kaifeng) towards the southern.
Of these unsettling times with which the South Song (1127-1279) was started the escape itinerary made them pass through Nanjing, where they went to the current Shangqiu, then Yangzhou until they set a new capital in Linan (current Hangzhou) in 1129.
Xiansheng Cilie (1115-1197), the Emperor's wife, or simply Song's Empress Wu who was, like he lover of the brush arts, recalled with bitterness in a brief poem: “Here beautiful plums are early and peach-winged by the wind,/ In the light of dusk, the Jade album in the vicent Celeste./ In Yangzhou I met the soft face of the spring breeze,/ comparing all the flowers, in general, nothing resembles the others.
Everything, by the way, would be a little different. In the influence of neo-confutic philosophy, the reform of the society from the bottom up was now sought. Seeing painters' works, there will be a tendency to reduce the size of the paintings, abandoning the great scenarios with the large mountain visually dominating other smaller ones suggesting a order from above, and a closer form of representation emerges from more intimate scenes linked to everyday life.
An example of this change is seen in the works of Su Hanchen (1094-1172), a painter of the Imperial Academy, sponsored by Gaozong's father, the inspired Emperor Huizong (1082-1135). In a painting made in a round range (Tuanshan) is a lady sitting in front of a parker in a garden (paint, color and gold on silk, 25.2 x 26.7 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts of Boston). Seen from her back, her face appears in the mirror she holds in her right hand, stressing the fact that we are admiring a private moment.
Su Hanchen would, however, be more recognized by two themes that would become genres within figurative painting. The scenes of children playing, Yingxi Tu, shown in different environments and bucket salespeople, Huolang Tu, transporting a huge paraphernalia of objects, usually cheap articles accessible to all. Both figures capable of provoking an unconstant joy.
In two paintings that are at the National Palace Museum in Taipei (one of them, a vertical roller, ink and silk color, 181.5 x 267.3 cm) joins both themes, showing the street vendor welcomed by children from rich families. In a foreboding of what would come next. After all, with a smaller territory, the dynasty resumed in the south by Gaozong would be even more prosperous than in the north.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values “the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's World Heritage Site, has a "high to extreme" prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees Celsius above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the most extensive and severe bleaching that there is registration to date”, read in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot recover sufficiently quickly between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>CCCM | Fusion with Foundation for Science and Technology creates new agency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/04/cccm-fusao-com-fundacao-para-a-ciencia-e-tecnologia-cria-nova-agencia/</link><description>Operating since 1999, the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center will merge with the Foundation for Science and Technology and the National Innovation Agency, creating a new institution. The practical consequences for the CCCM that aims to promote studies on Macao, China and Asia in Portugal are unknown. The president of the center says it is early to make comments
 
It is not known whether it will maintain its name, the number of scholarships for studies on China, Macao and Asia, or whether to change staff, but what is certain is that the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) will merge with the Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT) and the National Innovation Agency. Of these three entities will be born the new agency for research and innovation.
The process is linked to the desire to reform the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology by the Portuguese government led by Luís Montenegro, and the changes were announced on Thursday.
However, there is still no great information about the consequences of this merger to the CCCM. At HM, Carmen Amado Mendes, its president, chose to refer to clarification for the future operation of the center, considering that it is "premature" to give answers about something "that is not yet defined."
On Thursday, Minister Fernando Alexandre announced the reform of the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation with the extinction of several entities, including FCT that has been the main financier of PhD and other research projects in Portugal.
The reform of the ministry was approved by the Council of Ministers and, at a press conference at the end of the meeting, Fernando Alexandre justified the restructuring by describing his ministry as an “anacronic structure”, with fragmented organizations, disintegrated information systems and disarticulated governance.
With 18 entities and 27 higher leaders between the services of the non -higher education system and higher education, science and innovation, the ministry will have only seven entities and 27 higher leaders, with the integration of extinguished entities into new entities.
Regarding the extinction of the FCT, the minister assured that the financing of science will be preserved, with funding for four years that guarantees stability, predictability and “the protection of the financing of the most basic fundamental investigation”.
“When we started thinking about this reform, we do it with a vision: to ensure equal opportunities to access quality education,” said Fernando Alexandre, also underlining the reinforcement of the education system.
Marcelo can veto
The extinction of FCT has generated some less good reactions in Portugal because it fears a reduction in investment in science and research. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, president of the Portuguese Republic, said he had “the sensation” that the foundation was replaced “with an agency in which he was integrated, and had other functions beyond those of FCT.”
Marcelo acknowledged that the Foundation was a “very old structure” and that “it had many aspects that deserved to be rethought”, but said: “Just seeing what the new agency will do can I answer if this extinction is a good or bad idea.”
As for the eventual 'green light' from Belém, Marcelo said that if he thinks this extinction is "good", promulgates the diploma "without anguish." "If you have doubts about a point that is this diploma that is very important I ask the government to rethink. It has happened. I may not veto soon. If the government insists, I can come to veto, if it is until the end of my mandate," he also admitted.
A history of the transition
The CCCM was born in 1995 during the administration of Vasco Rocha Vieira, the last Portuguese governor of Macao, intending to be “a place of excellence for the dissemination of Macau, its history, its culture and its economy”, reads in the memories of Rocha Vieira, “to all the ports I arrived”.
This entity, operating in the Alcântara area, in Lisbon, was inaugurated in November 1999 by the then President of the Republic, Jorge Sampaio, and had as first president Alexandra Costa Gomes.
On the CCCM website it is read that the institution is endowed with administrative autonomy and its own heritage, being a public institute integrated in the indirect administration of the state and under the tutelage of the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation.
In the objective booklet, it is read that the CCCM “has as its mission to produce, promote and disseminate knowledge about Macao as a platform between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China, as well as between Europe and Asia”, also presenting itself as “a space dedicated to the study and teaching of Chinese language, culture and history”. The center has also been established as "a center for scientific research and continuous and advanced training on the relations between Portugal and China, as well as between Europe and Asia."
After the long presidency of Luís Filipe Barreto, academic at the University of Lisbon, the CCCM began to be chaired, from February 2020, by Carmen Amado Mendes. The leader recently saw her service committee renewed by 2030.
A few months after taking office as president, Carmen Amado Mendes presented, on September 18, 2020, the new “Strategic Development Plan of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center 2020-2030”.
Since then, the CCCM has awarded dozens of doctoral scholarships for the studies of Macao, China and Asia, and the “Spring Conferences”, which bring together academic performances around the same themes every year. Also noteworthy that the CCCM opened, in December last year, the “Gallery of Governors”, with 41 paintings of the former Portuguese governors of Macao. A new building that houses the file and library was also inaugurated.
This plan sets objectives by 2030, "the reinforcement of scientific and cultural cooperation in the domain of past understanding, present and future trends of relations between Europe and Asia."
With regard to archives, it is intended to “modernize and dynamization within a network of documentation centers and international reference file on euro-seatic themes, with emphasis on the various files in Lisbon, but also in Portugal and Europe”.
Given that the CCCM houses, in its facilities, the Macao Museum, the board points to the “insertion and appreciation in the museum network at the level of Lisbon and National”.
The central idea of the plan was to develop, by 2030, “CCCM facilities as a pole of streamlining scientific, cultural and economic relations between Portugal and China, including the installation of entities such as the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry, the Erasmus+Youth Entrepreneurs Association, as well as research nuclei in eurical studies”. It remains to be seen if, with the merger, all these initiatives will continue their initial course.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 07:39:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs: Seven agreements since Trump arrived at the White House</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/29/tarifas-sete-acordos-desde-que-trump-chegou-a-casa-branca/</link><description>The United States have reached seven bilateral trade agreements since Donald Trump returned to the White House in January and the latest, signed on Sunday with the European Union (EU), is the largest in terms of business volume.
In addition to the EU agreement, the US government has agreed new commercial terms with the United Kingdom, China, Vietnam, Japan, Philippines and Indonesia, while negotiations continue with dozens from other countries, US authorities.
Here is the data from the list of the seven bilateral trade agreements that Trump was able to obtain since January, when he returned to the White House for a second presidential term.
+++ United Kingdom +++
Signed on May 8, it was the first bilateral agreement signed by Trump since the US government announced a new tariff plan.
This agreement establishes the reduction of tariffs on British cars from 25% to 10% - up to 100,000 vehicles per year - and the elimination of steel and aluminum tariffs; Reciprocal permissions for export of beef and agricultural products, as well as reduction of non -tariff barriers and simplification of customs procedures.
+++ China +++
On June 26, after reciprocal threats of tariffs up to 115%, the United States and China have reached an agreement of principle that is still being developed.
Although it keeps high rates-55% for exporting certain Chinese products to the United States-facilitates the export of rare land in China, eliminates mutual retaliation measures and softens controls on Chinese products to the US market.
+++ Vietnam +++
The US and Vietnam agreed on July 2 to increase the vietnamese exports to the US to 20% (with a 40% rate on the products suspected of being Chinese origin). Trump's previous threat was to establish tariffs in the 46%.

++ Japan ++
Japan agrees with a 15% rate on all its exports to the United States compared to the 25% rate with which Trump had threatened. The country was committed to investing $ 550 billion (about 470 billion euros) in the US and opening its markets to sectors such as car, rice and agricultural products.
++ Philippines ++
The US now imposing a 19% rate on Philippine products, less a percentage point than the 20% that had threatened, in exchange for the exemption of tariffs on US products that enter the Philippines. The announcement was made on July 22, after the visit of Filipino President Ferdinand Marcos Jr., to the White House.
++ Indonesia ++
On the same date, July 22, and with almost identical content, Trump's agreement with Indonesia establishes 19% rates on exports to the United States and, in parallel, includes aircraft purchase commitments, US agricultural and energy products.
++ European Union ++
On Sunday, July 27, the trade agreement between the United States and the EU was announced, which states that most European exports will be subject to 15% fees - Trump had threatened with 30% - but included tariff exemptions for certain products.
In the agreement, the EU is committed to buying $ 750 billion (about 650 billion euros) in the United States, investing $ 600 billion (about 510 billion euros) in the country and increasing its US military equipment purchases.</description><pubDate>2025-07-29 02:33:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Forum | Former advisor to Rocha Vieira enhances complementarity</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/24/forum-macau-antigo-assessor-de-rocha-vieira-realca-complementaridade/</link><description>The role of the Macao Forum should be compromised in a complementary way to other existing cooperation. The idea was defended by Tiago Vasconcelos, advisor to Rocha Vieira, at a symposium promoted by the City of Macau. The Major General also agrees with the extent of the forum to Spanish-speaking countries
 
On Tuesday at the City of Macau (UCM), a symposium centered on cooperation in areas of scientific research and higher education between Macau, China and Portuguese-speaking countries, which served to present various academic projects that are being developed at MSAR.
The event was attended by Major-General Tiago Vasconcelos, who was an advisor to General Rocha Vieira in the last years of the Portuguese administration of the territory, and who defended a broader look at the role that the Macao Forum can take.
In its presentation, which HM had access, it is read that "the importance of the creation of the Macau Forum cannot be underestimated, both from a symbolic and practical point of view," but "it is necessary to be realistic as to what one can expected from such an organization."
Thus, for Tiago Vasconcelos, “the Macao Forum must find its place among other forms of diplomacy”, such as “bilateral relations, in some cases 'strategic partnerships' bilateral, such as Brazil and Portugal”, or “belonging to other forums” or “multilateral organizations such as G20 or BRICS, of which both China and Brazil are members, or the ASEAN Regional Forum, of which Timor-Leste as China are participants. ”
It is for the person responsible for a "variable geometry", where "the belongings of countries to various forums simultaneously can offer opportunities for the" Macao Platform "to broaden its scope."
And here the former advisor of the last Portuguese governor of Macau highlights the importance of the extent of the MSA platform to Spanish -speaking countries, something that has also been defended by the local executive.
Thus, the MSAR can, with the multiplicity of roles and partnerships of the Macao Forum, “reach other Latin-speaking countries, especially Spanish-speaking, given the similarities between Portuguese and Spanish languages, and existing dialogue platforms, such as the Ibero-American conference, which connects Portugal, Spain and most Latin American countries”.
In general terms, the official understands that one should “understand the proper role played by the Macau Forum among the various personalized bilateral and multilateral cooperation formats, as well as the lessons learned from the more than 20 years of history of the Forum”. This “is of paramount importance to ensure the proper level of ambition and the effectiveness of any new forms of cooperation in which Macau can act as a useful platform,” he said.
A promising land
In conclusion, Tiago Vasconcelos said that since the arrival of the early Portuguese to the territory, in the mid -16th century, that "Macao has played a traditional role as a platform between mainland China and the outside world", playing "part of the" Portuguese world "for almost 450 years, naturally integrating its network."
Thus, ties with Portuguese -speaking countries are "a legacy of their history," which "helps Macao to preserve some of their distinctive characteristics, but also play a useful role in supporting Chinese diplomacy, further facilitating China's relations with Portuguese -speaking countries."
For Tiago Vasconcelos, “Macau's prospects are quite promising to continue to play its traditional and very distinctive role as a connecting platform between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries”, taking into account that it begins half of the 50-year transition period present in the Sino-Portuguese joint statement of 1987.
Still in the area of higher education, the Major General pointed out that "despite its dimension, Macau is becoming, if it is no longer, a center of excellence for higher education in China." "Even worldwide, the same can be said about some specific sectors, making Macau a highly attractive destination for very talented students," he added. The official highlighted the role of the four key laboratories of the existing state, namely VLSI (large-scale integrated circuits) analog and mixed signal at the University of Macao (one); The Quality Research Laboratory in Chinese Medicine, between one and the University of Science and Technology of Macao; The Internet of Things Laboratory to Smart Cities, at UM; and also the laboratory for the Lunar and Planetary sciences, of Must.
The seminar where Tiago Vasconcelos participated, entitled “Scientific and Technological Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”, also attended representatives of the central government's connection office on the Macau forum, among other academic and business personalities.
According to a press release on the event sent to HM, José Paulo Esperança, vice-rector of the UCM Faculty of Economics, spoke of the importance of financing academic investigations by the Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT) in Portugal, highlighting “FCT's efforts to promote international cooperation and resolution of common challenges”.
IP KUAI PENG, Vice-Rector of UCM and Director of the Institute of Studies of Portuguese Speaking Countries of the same educational institution, argued that Macau “should be based on cooperation with Portuguese-speaking countries”, as well as “actively expanding exchange in various areas with Spanish-speaking countries, building a deep, and sustainable cooperation ecosystem, continuing to expand the circle of international friends and international friends and draw a new plan for modernization ”in the format followed by China.
In addition, the official believes that the “remains an important high-level outside opening window for the country” should continue to create “an international cooperation model in areas such as high technology, digital economy and standardization of traditional Chinese medicine, contributing to the construction of a technological power of the country and, at the same time, achieving diverse and moderate economic development”.
Think-Tank to Spanish
The UCM Vice Rector believes it can be created in Macao “an interregional Think Tank with the best universities in Portuguese and Spanish countries, focusing on areas such as green energy, biomedicine and digital technology, promoting transf by technological means and helping developing countries to overcome digital gap”.
Among the participating researchers in the seminar, highlighting Marta Filipa Simões, from the Macao University of Science and Technology, which presented the Sino-Portuguese Cooperation Project in Fungi and Astrobiology Research. The academic suggested “the conduct of various research projects through cooperation between Macau and scientific research institutions in Angola, Brazil, Cape Verde, Mozambique and Portugal, in order to promote interregional scientific innovation”.
Already André Antunes, from the University of São José, stressed that, currently, "Macao plays an important role as a point of contact in the network of Portuguese-speaking countries", with a very centered cooperation "in the economic area", although, he defended, "the scientific area will become in a new strong point."</description><pubDate>2025-07-24 05:04:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Economic Report Highlights Startup “Historical Record”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/hong-kong-relatorio-economico-destaca-recorde-historico-de-startups/</link><description>"Hong Kong's startups are on the rise." This is how the executive in the neighboring region describes the business environment in the region, where they were created in 2024 about 4,700 startups, plus 10 percent of 2023. In the "Report of Hong Kong's Business Environment 2025" it is read that the territory is far from losing economic competitiveness
 
The Hong Kong government released last July 30 the latest report on the neighboring region's economic scene. And one of the highlights is given to the scenario of growth of entrepreneurship.
In the “Report of Hong Kong’s Business Environment 2025” [Hong Kong 2025 Business Environment Report] it is noteworthy that “Startups in Hong Kong are on the rise”, given that last year there were “about 4,700 startups in the city, a historic record and an increase of 10 percent from the previous year”.
The document explains that "more than a quarter of these startups has founders from outside Hong Kong," it is companies that operate in a "broad spectrum of sectors, including Fintech [High Technology], Electronic Trade and Information, Informatics and Technology", having hired more than 17,000 people. This number of human resources also represents an increase of seven percent compared to 2023. "All this is proof of Hong Kong's strong appeal for startup entrepreneurs," the authorities highlight.
But it is not only startups that record growth, with the report to point out that the current government, led by executive head John Lee, "achieved remarkable results in attracting companies, investments and talents."
"For example, in 2024, the number of companies in Hong Kong with headquarters outside the territory increased significantly by about 10 percent, reaching almost 10,000." The “Office for the attraction of strategic companies, created more than two years ago, attracted 84 strategic companies to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, including companies with market capitalization or valuation of over $ 10 billion, involving cutting -edge technology”, it is added.
The report also points out that between January 2023 and the first half of this year, Invest Hong Kong, linked to the Raehk government's direct foreign investment department, "helped over 1300 foreign and continent companies establishing or expanding their business in Hong Kong, bringing investments of over $ 160 billion."
Still with regard to Invest Hong Kong, the entity helped "539 companies from the continent or foreign to establish or expand their business in Hong Kong, which represents an annual growth of over 40 percent."
At the end of June this year, Hong Kong had 1.5 million local companies, while the total number of companies not registered in Hong Kong reached 15 509. "Both numbers represent historical records," it reads, and for the government of the neighboring territory the data "demonstrate the great confidence that continent and abroad companies have in the future of Hong Kong."
Given that Hong Kong also has a talent capture program, the Hong Kong Talent Engage, reads in the report that by June this year "were received about 500,000 candidates in the shelter of various talent admission programs, of which about 330,000 were approved." Of these numbers, Hong Kong actually arrived to work 220,000 qualified frames.
Good scholarship scenario
Quoted on an official press release, a government spokesman stated that "in a complex and volatile external environment, Hong Kong is undergoing a phase of economic update and transformation, but there are more opportunities than challenges."
Given that the territory has always positioned itself as a strong financial market worldwide, this scenario seems to have recorded a recovery in recent years.
“This year Hong Kong's financial market performance has been constantly improving. The Hang SENG Index has a 18 percent increase last year and an increase of more than 25 percent this year so far. The average daily business volume in the first half of the year was about $ 240 billion, with an increase of about 120 percent.”
Authorities highlight the maintenance of the economic competitiveness of the territory, pointing out that "over the years Hong Kong has been constantly classified as a global leader in economic freedom and competitiveness."
Attention to the trade war
In conclusion, Raehk's government clarifies that territory seems to maintain economic stability in times of constant commercial conflicts, with Donald Trump threatening and imposing tariffs on a number of countries.
“As volatile and turbulent as the world may be, we remain firmly committed to the rules -based multilateral commercial system, with the WTO [World Trade Organization] as a nucleus, while actively participating and supporting regional economic cooperation.”
The “numerous advantages of Hong Kong” are referred to, with its “highly internationalized business environment, a flexible and solid financial system, a simple and secure tax regime with low tax rates and a robust and independent legal system”.
However, in the document it is also stressed that the “tariff war caused a global reallocation of capital”, and Hong Kong wants to bet on the attraction of “foreign companies and capital” to the region.
The report also tells that "international organizations and foreign trade chambers in Hong Kong are confident in the future perspectives" of the territory, and that for the authorities "there is no reason to worry about some excessively pessimistic feelings."
"In fact, the Raehk government is creating a new momentum and expanding the ability to support Hong Kong's economic growth, thus increasing its overall competitiveness and achieving high quality development," is still added.
The executive spokesman also established a parallelism between good economic situation and political stability. "In recent years, the implementation of the National Security Law has restored a stable social environment in Hong Kong. This not only protected the rights and freedoms of the general public, but also made Hong Kong a safe haven to attract international capital and investment," he concluded. The report was presented by the secretary for Hong Kong finances, Paul Chan.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Rain | HK alerts and more than 80,000 residents of Beijing removed from home</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/chuva-alertas-em-hk-e-mais-de-80-mil-residentes-de-pequim-retirados-de-casa/</link><description>China and Hong Kong have faced periods of heavy rainfall in recent days that have forced extra care and residents' travel. In the Chinese capital 82,000 people had to leave their homes, while in Hong Kong streets and a hospital suffered floods and some subway stations were closed
 
Strong rains continue not to give respite, not only in Macau (see page 7), but in Hong Kong and in the interior of the country. In the case of China, Beijing authorities moved more than 82,000 people from home due to torrential rain, a week after deadly floods that led those responsible for recognizing failures in the response, the official news agency Xinhua said yesterday.
Thus, tens of thousands of residents were removed from the most affected areas by rain until 9 pm on Monday, local time, according to the Municipal Flood Response Center. The center warned of the high risk of floods in the districts of Miyun (northwest), Fangshan (southwest), lied (west) and Huairou (north).
The Chinese capital kept in force the red alert-the highest-until yesterday morning, before predictions of heavy rain between Monday and the morning of Tuesday.
Last week, these same rural districts north of Beijing were the most affected by the weather that caused 44 dead and nine missing, according to official data. Most of the deadly victims were registered in a home of elderly in Miyun.
New measures in agriculture
The severity of the catastrophe led municipal authorities to recognize “gaps” in the preparation of emergency services. Natural disasters are frequent in China during summer, with some regions subject to torrential rainfall and others to severe droughts.
However, the Chinese authorities reinforced the device to respond to the adverse effects of intense rainfall and heat waves on agricultural cultures in various regions of the country, at a crucial time for autumn harvesting.
Since the beginning of the rainy season, east and northern China areas have recorded episodes of extreme precipitation, while provinces such as Henan (Center) and Anhui (East) face prolonged periods of drought and high temperatures.
This combination of meteorological phenomena represents a challenge for farmers, especially when about two months left to harvest the main autumn cereals, yesterday pointed out the Xinhua official news agency.
In the province of Shaanxi (Center), where precipitation recently exceeded 100 millimeters in less than 24 hours, local authorities adopted preventive measures such as channel cleaning and reinforcement of dikes, which allowed much of the cultivated lands.
However, Henan agricultural cooperatives affected by drought opted for gout watering systems and localized application of fertilizers to conserve moisture and minimize losses.
Authorities have given priority to the rehabilitation of water infrastructure and the dissemination of efficient water management techniques in the absence of precipitation in some areas. The fall campaign represents a fundamental component of China's annual cereal production.
In a statement issued yesterday, the Ministry of Agriculture and Rural Affairs warned that weather conditions in the coming weeks will be determining and appealed to "all efforts to protect harvesting and strong support for the country's food security."
Chinese President Xi Jinping said in 2023 that, although “1,400 million Chinese eat well” currently, “the food issue should not be careless”, stressing that the supply of food “is not an insignificant issue”.
China has less than nine percent of the planet's aurable land, although it represents about 18 percent of the world's population. In the last summers, weather disasters have caused significant damage in the country: the 2023 scirred months were marked by flooding in Beijing, which caused more than 30 dead, while by 2022 several extreme and dried heat waves hit the center and east of China.
Hong Kong on Alert
With regard to the panorama of heavy rains in neighboring territory, they have not given respite either. According to public broadcaster RTHK, some hong Kong stations were closed yesterday due to the risk of flooding, given that the Hong Kong Observatory kept the black signal of storm [Black Rainestorm Warning Signal] until around 17 hours.
Winds of about 110 kilometers per hour were recorded in some areas of the territory, and thunderstorms were also registered. The rthk channel also reveals that more than 10,800 lightnings were counted in the territory between midnight and 10 am yesterday, half of them occurred on Lantau Island.
Until 11 am yesterday, the authorities responsible for the drainage systems recorded 21 episodes of flooding, and 180 emergency responses were made in 240 different locations.
Highlight for the occurrence of an episode at Queen Mary Hospital this Tuesday, namely “on some roads” hospital access in Pok Fu Lam, and patients were displaced by firefighters to Ruttonjee Hospital in the Wanchai area. In some zones of the hospital the water reached the knees, and sand bags were placed to stop the flow of the rains. At about 11 am yesterday this scenario was resolved, with the normal one returning to the Queen Mary Hospital near noon.
The rains also led to the large increase in water level in the Lower Shing Mun reservoir in the Shaan area, which led to the notification of nearby housing complexes, such as Mei Lam Estate, May Shing Court, Mei Chung Court and Granville Garden.
Despite the heavy rains, some people went to work normally doing alternative routes. This was the case of Mak, a woman who, to the RTHK channel, said she had to make a deviation to get to the office. “I couldn't go straight to there and had to make a longer route. The metro [mtr] made some warnings [about the storm and closing], but I would like them to do them also inside the carriages, because I only realized that access was closed when I arrived on the way out,” he described.
The sun
Information provided by the Hong Kong Observatory speaks of the passage of an active "southwest monsoon and high altitude disturbances that are bringing heavy rainfall and violent thunderstorms to the southern coast of China and the northern part of the southern China Sea."
Yesterday the highest daily precipitation record was broken to August since 1884, when 355.7 millimeters of precipitation at the Observatory's headquarters were registered.
For today time should stay unstable in Hong Kong, with “heavy rains at the beginning” of the day. However, these "should gradually decrease" tomorrow, expected "a lot of heat with sunny periods in the next two days."
Also the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) leave a heavy rain alert to this day with “frequent, sometimes intense, thunderstorm”. The sun is expected to start appearing at the MSAR from tomorrow, still with some clouds, extending this weather scenario until next Monday. Temperatures should reach 33 degrees.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:29:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Iam | Cats captured due to complaints from the University of Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/05/iam-gatos-capturados-devido-a-queixas-da-universidade-de-macau/</link><description>The collection of cats from the land of the University of Macao resulted from “university complaints about the large amount of cats in its campus,” the institute for municipal affairs told HM. The public body removes, for now, the scenario of slaughtering animals, feared by the students
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) clarifies that the collection of 15 cats between July 22 and 25 of the University of Macao campus (one) emerged in response to complaints from the institution of higher education in relation to hygiene problems in the campus generated by the presence of animals.
"AMI has constantly receiving complaints from one about the large amount of cats on its campus and food waste that is not removed in time and affecting environmental hygiene," was referred to in the response sent to HM.
UM UM Campus Cats led to a wave of students' indignation, who say Temer the slaughter of animals after the period of complaint and adoption. AMI will move away, this scenario.
"Regarding cats captured, if they are not claimed by the owner after the period of complaint, AMI will implement the policy of" open capture, sterilization and adoption "(TNA), prioritizing finding appropriate adopters for cats. It should be noted that AMI does not set a deadline for retention of the adopted animals."
In the same answer it is said that during the waiting period for host families, AMI “will continue to provide clinical care and daily care to animals, never existing their slaughtering situation due to the term of retention period”.
In this sense, it is explained that AMI veterinarians “are performing a series of medical care that include body examination, vaccine administration and microchips.” In addition, “cats can only be available for adoption after being sterilized,” Iam said.
“Lack of sensitivity”
The warnings for the adoption of these animals continue on social networks, and in a note sent to HM and signed by “a member of the UMERS - UMM groups”, is questioned the “worrying situation” that occurred during the summer vacation and therefore the absence of most students.

“These cats, considered an integral part of the university community, survived the sign of signal 10, but unfortunately they could not escape these AMI capture operations in recent days. For many students and teachers, these cats were like 'veterans' of campus, following them during significant moments of academic life and providing comfort and joy in the university environment.”
The note explains that "UMERS" members cannot adopt cats "due to various circumstances," such as family allergies, possession of other animals, or "additional restrictions" for students in the interior of China.
The alerts on social networks aim to “sensitize the public for this situation and encourage people with adequate conditions to adopt these cats in the municipal Kennel of Macau.
On the Red Note platform there is even the group “A CatStories”, where the stories of cats captured by AMI are shared, and only one publication generated 460 tastes and 160 comments. A group was also created on Facebook, “Macao Cats II”, and there is also publications on Threads, with a total of 500 tastes and 500 shares, including the ten thousand views.
One of the profiles of the "a catstories" concerns a "slight little cat," described as "a" unnamed "file, just created on the computer: still blank, slowly exploring the world and trying to type loose fragments to write" his own story.
“Hurryned to a corner, I watch the people who pass, evaluating who can become an important character of my plot. So far, few people have been written in my story, and I have also left few brands in someone's life. Before leaving the campus maybe this" unnamed "file is only 5kb, recording some shy explorations and a soft desire for human warmth," reads the adoption.
The HM questioned one on this subject, given that the animals were being cherished by the students, but until the closing of the edition did not receive an answer. "UMERS" members also question how one can one, "an institution that seeks academic excellence and better classifications in the world rankings, demonstrate such a lack of sensitivity, allowing the capture of these animals without any alternative solution."
Aborted association
In the same grade it is said that students considered creating an association to “organize the sterilization of campus cats, but the university did not approve the creation of such a student association”.
UMERS members enhance “contrast with renowned universities in the interior of China, such as the University of Beijing, where there is a student association dedicated to the care of university campus cats, and at the University of Zhejiang, where UM UM Rector Song Yonghua has previously worked an association to protect university campus animals since 2005”.
Regarding animal collection and treatment actions, AMI says that "TNA policies correspond to the guiding principles of the World Animal Health Organization (WOAH), which contribute to reducing the possibility of stray animals being exposed to disease and facing unfavorable environmental factors."
Such policies also contribute to the reduction of the number of animals "and their excessive long -term reproduction." It is also noted that "TNA policies still take into account the state of survival and welfare of animals, in order to find adopting families for animals with conditions, dedicating themselves to helping them to obtain permanent and stable proper care."
The AMI also says it has "constantly optimized the municipal kennels", and in recent years, "complementary facilities and equipment have been perfected." In addition, there is also cooperation “with animal protection associations”, and joint projects in schools and community neighborhoods for animal adoption and care.
Official data available on the AMI website indicates that in the first quarter of this year 264 animals were captured without microchip, which increased to 280 in the second quarter. The numbers are similar to the first two quarters of 2024: the first were caught 266 animals without microchip, followed by 327 animals in the second quarter. In the third and fourth quarters of last year 258 and 203 animals were caught, respectively.
Regarding sterilization actions, in the first quarter of this year 289 were made, followed by 211 actions of this kind in the second quarter. In the first quarter of this year were claimed, or adopted, 102 cats and 29 dogs, and in the following quarter, 93 cats and 49 dogs were adopted.
As for the number of animals slaughtered, in the first quarter of this year alone 32 cats and 69 dogs were killed. If in cats this number reduced in the second quarter to 11, the same did not happen with the dogs: 101 were slaughtered.</description><pubDate>2025-08-05 01:24:52</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia | Great Coral Barrier has been declining since there is a record</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/australia-grande-barreira-de-coral-sofre-maior-declinio-desde-que-ha-registo/</link><description>The Great Barrier of Choir, with 2,300 kilometers long, off the Australian East, has been suffering the largest coral decline since registrations began in 1986, a yesterday report published.
The Australian Institute of Marine Sciences, of the government, documented the condition of 124 reefs between August 2024 and May 2025 to determine the widespread coral lanchament in the three sections of the Greater Barrier.
The impact is higher in the northern areas (Cape York to Cooktown), with a 24.8 percent decline compared to the 2024, and southern levels (proserpine to gladstone), with 30.6 percent, representing these two values “the largest annual decline in coral cover” in 39 years.
In the central region (cooktown to proserpine), the decline recorded is 13.9 percent compared to last year. The last episode of bleaching on site, declared UNESCO's World Heritage Site, has a "high to extreme" prevalence in all three areas, scientists find in the report.
“Individual reefs registered a decline of corals of up to 70.8 percent” near Lizard Island in the North Zone, it refers to the study. The death of the corals, manifested by its bleaching, is caused by the impact of water heating - temperatures were recorded one to 2.5 degrees Celsius above average during the southern summer of 2025 - associated with the climate crisis.
The large coral barrier “experienced unprecedented levels of thermal stress, resulting in the most extensive and severe bleaching that there is registration to date”, read in the document, in reference to the phenomenon that occurred in 2024 and continued during the first months of this year.
The Australian agency warns that the habitat can reach “a point of non -return”, where the choir cannot recover sufficiently quickly between catastrophic events.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:22:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Medical Error | Leong Sun IOK suggests revision of the legislation</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/erro-medico-leong-sun-iok-sugere-revisao-da-legislacao/</link><description>Deputy Leong Sun IOK argues, in a video released on social networks, that the legislation on medical error must be reviewed taking into account the amounts charged to the compulsory insurance provided for in the regime. For the deputy, the values are not reasonable and the regime needs to be reviewed, considering that it has entered into force eight years ago.
The deputy said he had received complaints from doctors and responsible for private clinics, which is why he felt the need to intervene. The complainants will have said that daily treat simple diseases that do not involve high -risk medical operations or acts, and that compulsory insurance is a heavy load.
Leong Sun Iok explained that the price of insurance is almost the same for all doctors who can only purchase insurance in Macao in a monopolistic market. For this reason, the deputy cites opinions of the medical class that it should be allowed to buy insurances to his choice, and there is the possibility of reducing the value of the benefit taking into account the number of care and associated compensations.
According to the deputy, the sector also wants the opening of a liability insurance system that encompasses the cities that are part of the great bay as an alternative, asking the Macao government to create a fund for this new insurance and compensation schemes to support the medical sector.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:37:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Kiang Wu Association | Land used for parking was recovered</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/associacao-kiang-wu-terreno-usado-para-estacionamento-foi-recuperado/</link><description>It was to be used as a park of Keang Peng school, but at least since 1996 it was no longer this end. 30 years after, the executive decided to recover the land because he considered that the free concession contract had been violated
 
The government recovered land that had been freely assigned to the Kiang Wu Hospital Beneficency Association to function as a park of a school. At issue is the fact that the lot has been used as a parking lot, violating the terms established in the concession. The information was released yesterday, through an order signed by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam Vai Man.
According to the version published in the official bulletin, the land had been granted free of charge on October 23, 1981 to the Macao Most Popular Private Hospital Association. The concession aimed to create a park to complement the facilities of the Kiang Wu Peng Man Luen Hap School. Years later the name of the educational institution was changed to Keang Peng School, which currently still exists and offers primary and secondary school classes in two different campuses.
However, the school ceased to work at that place in July 1996, almost 30 years ago, so the terrain was no longer useful for which it had been assigned and was used for car parking.
The recovery thus arises following a 147.4 square meter inspection, located on the Macau Peninsula, next to Rua do Barão. "There is the change of purpose of the concession and the end for which the land was granted is not being continued, which is a violation of the duty to use the land in accordance with the purposes assigned in the concession title," was considered by the government.
Silently
Confronted by the executive with the possibility of losing the granting of the land, the Kiang Wu Hospital Benefice Association, led in recent years by businessman Liu Chak Wan, remained silent: “The concessionaire has not commented, in written hearing, about the meaning of declaring the termination of the concession,” was nominated.
Raymond Tam's order also defines that any improvements made on the ground during the concession period go to “the Special Administrative Region of Macao, without any compensation by the Kiang Wu Hospital Beneficency Association”.
Despite not having a defense before the order, the document points out that the Kiang Wu Hospital Beneficency Association may try to challenge the decision of the secretary of recovery of the current parking with the Second Instance Court.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:36:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Most lucrative macao investment where singonese is spoken</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/investimento-de-macau-mais-lucrativo-onde-se-fala-cantones/</link><description>Macao and Hong Kong's investment in the countryside tends to be more profitable when the companies they invest are in the singing zone where Cantonese is spoken. The conclusion is part of a study by the University of Jinan's academic MA Sen, with the title “Cultural Ties, External Direct Investment and Companies Performance: Proof of Investment in China originating in Hong Kong and Macau” published in the Journal of Economics The World Economy.
Given the companies in the interior whose capital belongs to more than 50 percent to people or companies from Macau or Hong Kong, the study found that on average companies in the singing zone where Cantonese speaks have profits about seven percent higher than companies with administrative regions in the other interior areas.
In analyzing the facts that contribute to this difference, the author indicates that the hypotheses studied point to greater cultural proximity, which is translated into greater effectiveness of business exploitation. The author even denies that the difference is due to any kind of favoritism because there is cultural proximity: “the profitability gain that benefits culturally linked companies is mainly obtained by reducing transaction costs and not through a favoritism -based selection,” was bound.
More employees
Another of the standards identified by researcher MA without, points out that the companies in Macau and Hong Kong in the interior also have a higher proportion of employees when they are located within the region where singer is spoken.
According to the study, companies in Macau and Hong Kong within this region are about 14 percent more jobs than companies outside. This difference is justified with greater cultural proximity and the positive impact on the desire to invest inside by entrepreneurs and companies from Macau and Hong Kong.
Cultural connections also have an impact on interest -paid by the companies of Macau and Hong Kong in the interior. According to the study data, companies within the area that speaks Cantonese pay on average 1.5 percent lower than companies with this nature outside this area.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:34:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Hong Kong companies for hengqin</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/cooperacao-convidadas-empresas-de-hong-kong-para-hengqin/</link><description>Hong Kong's chief executive visited Macao and "traded impressions in depth" with Sam Hou Fai to "further reinforce cooperation." The ruler of the mandate reiterated John Lee the importance of Hengqin in the Great Bay project and invited Hong Kong companies to the deepened cooperation zone
 
An entourage of the Hong Kong government, led by executive head John Lee Ka-Chiu, visited Macao and Hengqin on Tuesday afternoon and had a meeting with a team of representatives of the MSAR executive. According to the Social Communication Office (GCS), Sam Hou Fai and John Lee “exchanged impressions in depthly further reinforcing cooperation between the two regions”, in areas such as tourism, “high quality development of the large bay” and “new opportunities” in Hengqin.
The Macao government leader took John Lee and members of his executive on a visit to Hengqin, who identified as an “important platform for Macau's participation in the integrated development of the great bay and the promotion of the proper diversification of the economy”. In this respect, Sam Hou Fai “underlined the participation of more Hong Kong companies” in Hengqin, so as to “grab new opportunities in the second phase of the cooperation zone, to share the benefits of high quality development”.
If you say it
In separate communications, both governments have pointed out that Hong Kong and Macau are also special administrative regions of China which, over the years, have fully used the unique advantages of "one country, two systems," which the Executive of the MSAR states to have "achieved success in worldly remarkable development."
Sam Hou Fai also indicated that Hong Kong and Macau are also central cities of the Great Bay and nuclear engines of regional development.
In tourist terms, the ruler of MSA has suggested that the two regions should take advantage of the experience of national games and hold more sporting events together to "attract more and different tourists to visit Hong Kong, Macao and the entire great bay."
In this area, Sam Hou Fai argued that the two regions should “continue to reinforce the connectivity of the transport network to provide greater facilities to residents and tourists circulating between the two territories”, and bet on promoting “multi-desert” itineraries.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:30:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Traffic | Counselor asks for prudence in the circulation to the north</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/transito-conselheiro-pede-prudencia-na-circulacao-para-o-norte/</link><description>After the Hong Kong executive announced that, from September, he will eliminate the appointment requirement to Raehk drivers to take the car to Guangdong, IP Wai Keong, a member of the Traffic Advisory Board, asked the Government of the Raem to consider a similar measure.
The counselor argued, in statements to the newspaper Exmooo, that there is a contradiction between the economy of residential neighborhoods and the demand for consumption of residents. Despite the recovery of Gross Domestic Product for levels around 90 percent of the verified before the pandemic, if it is even easier for Macao residents to cross the car border, the local economy will suffer even more, especially in the northern area of the peninsula, also at the level of employment.
In addition, IP Wai Keong has expressed doubts that the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge Border Post has the ability to respond to the increase in traffic produced by exempting the need for marking to cross the border in private cars.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:48:33</pubDate></item><item><title>Replicas of voting assemblies for residents to “try to vote”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/replicas-de-assembleias-de-voto-para-residentes-experimentarem-votar/</link><description>The Macao Electoral Commission will make two replicas of voting assemblies available for residents to “try to vote” and know “how they can vote correctly” on September 14, it was announced yesterday.
The two replicas - one more than in the legislatures of 2021 - will allow residents to “try to vote” and “deepen the knowledge of the vote and also the election work,” the chairman of the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee (Caeal), after a meeting of the body, told journalists yesterday.
"We hope that the public, through the visit to the replica of the voting Assembly, can know more about the functioning of the Assembly and, through simulation, can also know how it can vote correctly and also [about] the confidentiality of the vote," he said.
Also according to the official, schools will bring students to these two enclosures - installed at the Tap Seac multipurpose pavilion and at the facilities of the Macao Forum, from 6 to 12 September - "in the sense of reinforcing the civic consciousness of students," to be "prepared to be voters in the future."
For visually impaired people, Seng Ioi Man added, they are still available on site Braille voting reports.
Vote tradition
Asked by Lusa about whether the installation of these replicas is a sign that the population of the territory still has little knowledge about the act of going to the polls, without responding directly, Seng Ioi Man has noticed that this “is a tradition” in Macao and that they are addressed to future voters, “who cannot yet vote and [which] may feel the vote procedure” and those who now debut in scrutiny. But not only. "For those who had already voted, former voters can also - spending so many years - experimenting [the act of voting]," he added.
Yesterday also take stock of the electoral process and asked if Caeal has received reactions from the population, Seng said only that "there are increasingly voters or citizens" to accompany the work and the information released by Caeal, "allowing those people who do not have enough information can participate in the electoral act. The election campaign starts on August 30 and ends on September 12.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:47:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Academic one speaks at the end of contraction</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/economia-academico-da-um-fala-em-fim-da-contraccao/</link><description>Henry Law considers that the economic crisis has come to an end and that gross domestic product should no longer suffer any contraction by the end of the year. At the real estate market, Law believes that good news can arrive if there is a reduction in the interest rate
 
The Associate Chief of the Department of Finance and Business Economics of the University of Macao (UM), Henry Lei Chun Kwok, considers that the economy of the territory is going through a recovery phase and that the decline of the first three months of the year is outdated. This is how the academic reacted to the growth of gross domestic product (GDP) of 5.1 percent in real terms in the second semester, compared to the same period.
Speaking to the newspaper or Mun, Henry Law pointed out that growth is justified mainly with increasing external demand. However, and despite the improvements, the academic warned of the need to track the possible risks for private consumption, investment and the impact of the devaluation of the real estate market.
However, in relation to the price of real estate, Henry Lei acknowledged that there are possibilities that next month there are positive news, if the federal US bank chooses to reduce interest rates. Given that Pataca is indexed indirectly to the US dollar, the US interest rate will lead to the most capital available in Macau to invest and buy housing.
Henry Lei also explained that a recovery of the real estate market is positive, as indirectly can promote activity in other sectors, such as new loans with banks, new housing remodeling works, and greater private consumption.
Better distribution
Alongside economic recovery, Henry Law warned the executive to the need to ensure better distribution of economic growth. Currently, law explained, growth gains are concentrated on what the leading industries claimed, as with game dealers. However, law pointed out that greater cooperation between the government, commercial associations and companies, which lead tourists to visit community neighborhoods and generate the growth of other businesses that are not directly linked to the game.
For its part, the director of the UM UM Game Industry Institute, Davis Fong, trusts that game's revenues in the second half of the year will be over 20 billion patacas per month.
The former deputy recalled that the revenues of the game have always been over 20 billion Patacas in the last three months, so the government should be questioned about what “did well in the last three months” and continue on this path.
Regarding the closure of satellite casinos, Davis Fong predicts that the market will absorb the changes gradually. In addition, the academic has devalued the closing of satellite casinos because their weight in the game market has been decreasing in recent years, although recipes are growing.
Fong also defended the closure of the satellite casinos indicating that it will contribute to consolidate the position of the dealers, lowering operating costs and increasing profits.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:43:35</pubDate></item><item><title>COP30 - A challenge for Brazil</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/cop30-um-desafio-para-o-brasil/</link><description>The last two conferences of the United Nations Convention in the United Nations Convention on Climate Change took place in 2023 and 2024, respectively in the United Arab Emirates (COP28) and Azerbaijan (COP29), which, as oil producing countries, should not be very interested in energy transition.
Now it is up to Brazil to organize CPO30, from November 10 to 25, 2025, in Belém, Pará. This is not the first time this country has been predisposed to organize such a conference. He had already been invited, and accepted the invitation to organize COP25. However, the government headed by Bolsonaro, a convinced negotiation such as his American mentor Donald Trump, "Roi the rope," said it as a said, claiming that the problem of climate change would be just a commercial game.
Chile was then tasked with being the new host, but the great disorders that occurred in this country before the scheduled dates, made the conference to Madrid, between December 2 and 13, 2019. It was an opportunity that was lost to project Brazil as one of the leading countries of the fight against climate change.
It turns out that Brazil is among the ten largest producers of gross oil and there are those who doubt that the Brazilian government is greatly interested in the energy transition. Undoubtedly, Lula da Silva's governments have taken into consideration, to some extent, the preservation of the Amazon and the well-being of indigenous populations, and have been committed in oil exploration in areas that may affect them. However, the great commercial value of oil makes it often subaltern the fact that fossil fuels are proven to be the main factor in increasing greenhouse gas concentration in the atmosphere and, consequently, global warming. There was even someone1 in Brazil who even said that oil exploration would contribute to funding the energy transition.
There is no doubt that COP30 in Belém will contribute to Brazil has an increasingly important role in the context of the problem inherent in climate change. It will be necessary, however, much skill on the part of the Brazilian government to convince the international community about its intentions to the commitment made when the Paris Agreement signed, in which the need to limit global warming up, until the end of the 21st century, to a maximum of 2 ° C, preferably to values less than 1.5 ° C. In this context, the Brazilian official policy seems not to be very coherent, especially since it has already been approved by the House of Representatives and the Senate, the infamous project-Law No. 2159 of 2021, nicknamed “PL of devastation”, because it opens the way to potentially serious ventures to the environment, such as the much discussed “offshore” oil exploration near the Amazon River mouth. This project, also called “equatorial margin”, may, in the face of the risk of oil spill, affect indigenous communities and biodiversity in the vicinity of the exploration zone. In case of such happening, it would not be the first time in Brazil, meeting that, in 2001, a platform operated by Petrobras suffered several explosions, which caused its sinking with about 1,500 tons of gross oil and the death of 11 people.
Incidents of this type in ocean facilities where perforation is not rare. Examples can be mentioned recurring strokes in the nineties of the last century in the North Sea on Shell-operated platforms, with serious consequences for the maritime environment. More recently there was a stroke in the Gulf of Mexico in 2010, where the damage of a security valve on a BP platform caused an explosion that caused the death of 8 workers and a stroke of about 780 million liters of oil, causing irreparable damage to maritime fauna. Incidents of this type may also affect ecosystems that mangais are part, causing damage to the transition zones between the coast and the sea, resulting in the destruction of ecosystems and the increase of erosion caused by the associated waves, or not, to storm tides.
Aware of these inconvenient potentials, the Brazilian Institute of Environment and Renewable Natural Resources (Ibama), has been denied licenses for oil exploration several times in the vicinity of the mouth of the Amazon River. According to the “PL of devastation”, “special environmental licenses” may occur for projects considered strategic, which, after submission to the entity responsible for licensing and in the absence of response within one year, would automatically be licensed. Considering that Ibama is characterized by staff scarcity, there will be the risk of projects submitted to be approved, after this period.
Given that the president can completely or partially veto the project-law, within 15 days after his submission by Congress2, it is now liable for Lula da Silva to take this attitude. There are only a few days to do so, because the deadline will in principle end on August 8.
Throughout this process, President Lula da Silva, unlike the minister of the “Environment and Climate Change”, Marina Silva, has shown a certain passivity, which causes some fear about her attitude regarding the promulgation of the decree. According to the most progressive means in Brazil, Lula da Silva should not have been silent after the approval by Congress, but staying firm vetoing the project “PL of devastation” and other potentially disastrous and attentive projects of forests and populations. In case of veto, it needs to be explained by invoking legal or political reasons, such as unconstitutionality or not convenience or opportunity.
In the meantime, an international campaign of Avaaz “Brazil: Stop the Devastation Bill” is underway, with about one million supporters.
But not everything is in the hands of Lula, as, in case of veto, the project-Law returns to Congress, which may impose the promulgation of the respective law, if the veto is overthrown by the absolute majority of the votes of the deputies and senators. The last word is, therefore, from Congress. However, there is a great expectation of what will be the attitude of Lula da Silva.
It is a tremendous challenge about the balance between environmental protection and economic development.
(Meteorologist)
References:
Jean Paul Prates - President of Petrobras from January 26, 2023 to May 14, 2024
National Congress - maximum body of the Legislative Power, composed by the Chamber of Deputies and the Federal Senate.
AVAAZ - Global scale movement that seeks to give voice to civil society in the areas of democracy, human rights and sustainability of the land.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:04:54</pubDate></item><item><title>The American Pope (II)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/o-papa-americano-ii-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the July 24th edition)
Ergo, Christianity is also pagan because, in history, while willing to welcome its end. Newman's proposal to open the doors of the Church to the laity combines with a very broad theological view. Perhaps one can see an unconscious trace of this in the expensive appeal to Leo XIII, not only nominal prevost reference, which invites to "get out of the sacred statue" in the spirit of his encyclical rerum Novarum (1891), today much mentioned. And it is reflected in the impulse of the innovators who would like to compensate for the tremendous vocations crisis recruiting lay people from both sexes for the Pope's divisions. The reworking of the mystery of the sun and the moon is echoed in the contemporary era (1958) in the then Archbishop of Milan (Papa Paulo VI), last (so far) governor of Peter's Chair, unsusceptible to movement because “the church is compared to the moon, whose phases of decrease and growth reflect the alternating history of the church that decay and recovers, and it never failed, because it is failed, because it Ecclesia Non Suo Sed Christi Lumine, shines not with her own light, but with that of Christ.
The ontological proof of Roman-Christian ecstasy, the shiver of communion with almighty God in its historical intimacy with Aeternitas Augusti (Augusto's immortality), seal of the Roman Empire, is in the abside of the Basilica of Santa Pudencian. Maybe Peter's house. It stands out the oldest mosaic of Rome, dated from the early fourth century. In the center, Christ in the skin of Imperator Orbis Terrarum, Lord of heaven and the world. Behind him, the Constantinian gemaged cross, over a blue sunset background scratched by reddish pale. Beside their side, the apostles Peter and Paul, dressed as Roman senators, symbolize the concord between the Jewish ecclesia ex eccisione and the ecclesia ex Gentibus pagan or non -Jewish. East cast with West. Incarnate in Rome. So much so that the leaders Pedro and Paul will sometimes be assimilated to Romulus and Remo.
In the first three centuries of the Christian era, the sennarial aristocracy continues to claim the preservation of pagan rites. For the followers of Jesus, the city remains Babylon. Between the imperium (temporal or political power) and the priestium (spiritual or religious power) a longtime rivalry is established, never resolved. Only after Constantine, on the Throne from 306 to 337, the imperial-paral headquarters leans into the second horn of power, the nascent ecclesiastical, divine and secular, intercept and accompanies the decline (eternal empire) imperium sine fine, designed to reproduce by gemulation in the Germanic, Byzantine, Moscovite and Frenchman. Caput Mundi (capital of the world) becomes apostolic thirst. In the narrative of Jesuit historian Karl Schatz states that “the two currents were confused in one and the unique character of ancient Rome was communicated to Ecclesiastical Rome, papal, refounding its primacy. The Roman nobility brought as its way of thinking, the charisma of his leadership, his talent for reconciling opposites, his practical sense sober as power. Thus, everything that had made Rome capable of dominating the world.
Catholic universalism is from Roman root. It is good to remember the stigma, when the exhaustion of the local line on the throne of Peter exposes the particularisms that weaken the clergy and the people of God. Here, a few steps from Francisco's tomb in Santa Maria Maggiore, the worldly footprints of the Christian's relationship with the earthly city, in the active waiting of the City of God, between the already and not yet. Among the apocalypse of John, who sees in the state the beast that arises from the abyss (13,1 and following), and the letter to the Romans (always 13,1 and following for some unknown reason), in which Civil Romanus Paul orders that “all must submit to the constituted authorities. In fact, there is no authority but of God, for those who exist are established by God. Therefore, who opposes authority opposes the order established by God. In tune with Jesus, who addressing Pilate determines: "You would have no power over me if it had not been given to you from above" (John, 19:11). Among these two poles, which in extreme cases can lead to the asceticism or worldienization of the ecclesiastical institution, runs the universal history of the church, from the golgota to this day, at the same time cheerful and dark.
What forces us to reassemble Christ «Caesaris Caesari, I gave Deo there (Caesar what is from Caesar, and to God what is of God)” (Matthew, 22:21). Four words of Jesus inaugurate centuries of disputes on the relationship between Christianity and political power, treated in millions of pages. Registered in the double citizenship of the Christian, on the land and in the city of God. Hence hermeneutic wars not only virtual, schisms, convictions and papal rehabilitation. Rivers of paint or bits in its symbolic binary value of state/church dualism, but also of spilled blood to trace the right way in the central question of ecclesiastical geopolitics. Permanent tension. Radicalized with the rise of Leo XIV to the rare throne, if not unique, coincidence between national identity and papal mission, both related to the maximum power in the countryside, whether worldly or religious. What owes the Pope, not only American, to the United States, what would the “number one” like his ecumenical citizen?
Jesus is crucified because the Romans identify him as a zelot who self -proclaims king of the Jews. Adherent, like other apostles, among whom Simon, perhaps Judas and Pedro himself, to the armed movement of the zelotes, guerrillas (terrorists, would correct a Caiaphas of today) in struggle to free the Palestine from the yoke of Rome. Christ sympathizes with the zelot cause, but rejects violence, much less aims to terrestrial thrones. Establishes French Lutheran historian and theologian Oscar Cullmann in his classic "God and Caesar" stating "Jesus' position lies beyond both an uncritical acceptance of the Roman state and political resistance to this state." Since he "seeks the future polis". Is there anything pilatesco in this interpretation? Much, I would say blasphemous. The dualism between powerful and Christian is translated into the tension between present and future, would replicate the practical.
To resolve the dispute, another Jesuit, Francesco Occhetta, author of the preface to the Cullmann rehearsal that says that "certainly, for a Christian, is in heaven, but the terrestrial is also good, even if it is a pagan state, as long as its tasks remain within the limits attributed by divine will."</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:02:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Financial Management II</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/05/gestao-financeira-ii/</link><description>Recently, a publication that circulated on the internet in Macao triggered heated debates. The person who published it (we called him Mary) said he was 32 years old, a savings of 2 million patacas and asked Internet users what this value represented exactly.
Of course there is no single answer to this question. Some answered it was little, while others said it was too much. But some gave an interesting answer, saying it would have been better if the two million were US dollars. Some netizens pointed out that several students from mainland China lost 9 million RMB in a case of telephone fraud. Others asked him how long he led to gather the 2 million patacas.
Before we analyze if 2 million patacas is a small or high amount, let's first realize what savings are. From the point of view of ordinary people, savings are what is left after we deduce expenses to revenues. But those who perceive finances know that this definition is not correct. When we manage our money we must be a certain amount to cover the expenses. Expenses can be divided into two categories: daily expenses and emergency expenses. Daily expenses must be lower than the monthly salary, otherwise the money we receive is not enough.
Financial experts usually recommend that we should have an emergency fund of three to six wages. Therefore, if we have a bank account equivalent to six salaries, it means that the amount of one salary is applied to cover monthly expenses and the remaining five salaries will go to the emergency fund. From this point of view, how can the value of six salaries deposited in the bank be considered a savings?
The question raised by netizens is very reasonable. How long did Mary get 2 million patacas? If you can save 10,000 patacas per month, it takes 200 months, or about 17 years. In these 17 years, if money is not raised from the account, the result will be achieved. In this calculation, we did not consider the interest generated by the deposit; This is because uncertainty about interest rate is high and the method of calculation without considering them is easier to understand.
From this method, we can see that to gather 2 million patacas we must take into account four factors: the amount of monthly savings, the time it reaches the goal, the impossibility of removing money from the account and the fact that the interest is not taken in line.
The amount of monthly savings varies according to revenue. The higher the revenue, the greater the savings if the expenses do not change. If the money the person receives only comes from salary, we are facing a single source of revenue. If you provide a property, dividends of actions, or copyright, we are facing revenues of a completely different nature. In these cases, there is first a good, well that then generates a return. Therefore, the more goods you have, the greater the performance and the greater the “ability to generate money”.
In the article last week, we mentioned that the average monthly income in Macao is about 20,000 patacas. If half of this amount is used to cover expenses and the other half is applied in savings, 17 years are required to gather 2 million patacas. Quoting Chai Jiu's famous phrase (柴九), the protagonist of the series “Rosy Business” (巾幗梟雄), from Hong Kong TVB, “How many decades have in our lives” (人生有幾多個十年), we can understand that 17 years is not a short period.
From the point of view of financial management, it is necessary to save 2 million patacas in ten years. How do you need money to buy houses and actions without initial capital, how can they be used to generate more income? Based on this premise, 2 million patacas should be a goal for several steps.
Savings must be the objective of a life that should not be interrupted after achieving a particular goal. After we spend a lot of time saving, we have to be careful not to be slaves to the money or “greedy”; That is, we cannot only save and not spend. Therefore, when we can gather 2 million, we need first to stop, reward ourselves for our effort and self-discipline, spoil ourselves, and then throw ourselves into a next goal of savings.
In this life we need to make money and save, but we also need to be happy. Without pleasure, there is no life. The satisfaction of our pleasures requires some money, which will come out of savings. How to compensate for these expenses? The answer is that we should increase sources of performance, ie the greater our “ability to make money”, the more easily we will pay off spending.
The income that depends on our work and our abilities is the "money of the people." Income, dividends and copyright are the income obtained through tools that generate money, ie "money that generates money." The more tools that generate money we have, the more income we will have. When income increases and expenses remain equal, savings also increase. Money generates money and looking for pleasure consumes some. Since we know how to find balance, money and happiness are our wealth.
People with a rich life experience understand that money and pleasures are just part of our wealth in this world. In addition to them there are also family affections, marital love, friendship social recognition, our health, etc. These are all important elements that constitute our wealth. For our lives to be very rich, all these elements must grow and we cannot focus only on income and savings.
Instead of asking if 2 million is too or little, why not gradually join this amount to ensure our health, family affections, love, friendship and other elements that enrich our lives?
Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-08-05 02:17:16</pubDate></item><item><title>There they are</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/04/ai-estao-eles/</link><description>Portugal has been in iron and fire for over a week. There they are, the fireworks. The fireworks of innovation, demagogy, sloppiness, incompetence, altruism, corruption, criminal incendays, self -interested loggers and absurd legislation. Arouca, Barca Bridge, Gondomar, Nisa, Santarém, Penafiel, Paiva Castle, Cinfães and dozens of villages are the stage for uncontrolled flames, the despair of populations, burning houses, exhausted heroic firefighters, falling aircraft, trying to erase more than 10 meters with some buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets or buckets some blades. There are 131 municipalities at maximum risk. The burning area is already triple 2024. About 30 suspects of fire is already arrested for the excellent work of the Judicial Police. Most of the time paid by loggers who are interested in burnt wood to quickly sell and get income from these crimes. One night one saw a car pass by a forest, after five minutes a huge fire began that still draws in the Ponte da Barca area. Fireworks are initiated by criminal incendays, which most of the time the courts send them free.
We kept contact with a prestigious geologist who told us that there is absurd legislation regarding the cleaning of land around the houses. Legislation that requires cleaning a surrounding area of houses with 50 meters. The geologist explained that 30 meters would be enough and that the 50 -meter cleaning obligation is very expensive for people who live from the little they have. Result: Few people clean the land and the fuel there is waiting for the incendays. The same geologist pointed out that the land in Portugal contains an amount of biomass that will lead to fires for at least another decade. The government appeared with a new internal administration minister who may know how to sew socks, but fires is a right zero. He has not even addressed the huge problem of continuing to postpone the purchase of new helicopters that are so lacking.
This year, like other years, we have had injured firefighters, evacuated villages, elderly, women and children sleeping on the ground in multipurpose pavilions, falling aircraft and several burnt houses. By the way of houses, a striking criticism for emigrants who build three -story villas, spending hundreds of thousands of euros in the middle of the forest and then want firefighters everywhere where flames endangers these villas. The situation is tragic for thousands of Portuguese, but every year is the same thing: they allow eucalyptus and pine to plant everywhere, when there should be a global planning with land appropriate to the ordered plantation of pines, oaks, eucalyptus, cork oaks and other trees. The lack of said geological and demographic planning leads to the misfortune we assist. Last Saturday, the day I wrote these words, already more than 20 residents had gone to the hospital and 10 firefighters received hospital treatment. For over a decade we have heard that something has to do anything. Obviously there are solutions, but most projects are in government drawers. And as no one tells him, we emphasize the risky and professional action of reporters who have risked day and night life at a temperature that has been around 45 degrees, running away from the flames, sleeping and eating poorly. I leave you blunt images of this drama that Portugal is living with another global fire scenario.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 08:00:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Cinematheque | Fantastic cycle to see in the coming weeks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/cinemateca-ciclo-fantastico-para-ver-nas-proximas-semanas/</link><description>Cinemateca Paixão presents this month a new movie cycle, entitled “Daydreams &amp; Labirintos - Fantastic Film Festival”. Among the selected titles, highlighting “Dangerous Animals” and the frightening “Massacre in Texas”, without forgetting the musical touch brought with the documentary about the blur
 
Cinema has the gift of revealing us other life forms and stories, but when these stories have a hint of horror or fantastic, the attraction to the movie you will see can differentiate yourself, for the better or worse. For those who love horror movies or fantastic genre stories, this is a good month to go to Cinematheque Paixão, which features the cycle “Daydreams &amp; Labyrinths - Fantastic Cinema Festival”. A total of 17 films integrates this poster, which extends until September.
And one of the highlights goes to "Dangerous Animals", aired on 16 August and then on September 6th.
This is a story that refers to the unlucky of Zephyr, a cunning and free -spirited surfer who is kidnapped by a serial killer obsessed with sharks and held a prisoner in his boat.
The woman will have to find a way to escape before this killer gives her to eat to the sharks that swim under the site where Zephyr is. Only Moses realize that she has disappeared, being a person for whom she has a loving interest.
Also noteworthy is the exhibition of the restored copy of “Massacre in Texas”, a 1974 film that celebrated 50 years of existence last year, and is still current and with a wave of fans.
Performed by Tobe Hooper, "Massacre in Texas" remains a reference for the subgenre of horror films entitled "Slasher". It was filmed in a short time, with a limited budget and actors completely unknown to the general public.
"There is no corner of the world where you can go and say the title" Texas Chainsaw Massacre "and no one knows what is talking about, whether you have seen the movie or not," France Presse (AFP) Chase Andersen of Exurbia Films, which holds the rights of the saga.
The story focuses on a carefree group of young people who come across an isolated house occupied by a masked lunatic that begins to cut them with sharp things, Leatherface. At Cinemateca Passion the film will be screened on Saturday, August 30.
Faces of happiness
“Different Man” [a different man] is not just about a man who has a strange disease that deforms his face, making him a monster in the shape of people. It is also a story about the meaning and conception of happiness, and how it depends on one's life and choices.
The protagonist, Oswald, is played by Adam Pearson, an actor who has always fought against neurofibromatosis that changed his face forms. Oswald had everything to be an unfortunate and shy man, hiding from humanity, but the opposite happens: he can be popular and a person perfectly integrated into society. The same does not happen to an actor with whom he intersects. “Different Man” will be aired on August 19th and 29th.
On August 16, “The Dream of Alexandria” will be shown, which refers to the 1920 Los Angeles, when in Hollywood still dominates silent cinema. In these times an immigrant girl appears hospitalized in a hospital after a fall, and who is friends with an adherence man, also paralyzed due to an accident during a footage. He enchants her with a fantastic story that carries her beyond the hospital's monotony, towards the exotic landscapes of her own imagination. This version displayed at this festival is also a 4K -restored version with additional scenes compared to the 2006 version, having been filmed in 24 countries.
THE HISTORY OF THE BLUR
“Blur: To the End” [Blur: Until the end] is a 2024 documentary scheduled for screening on August 17 and September 7, and where the history of friendship and companionship of the Blur members, British band of Britpop and Alternative Rock formed in the 1980s, which marked an entire generation in the 1990s.
This documentary was filmed in 2023, when the band met to record new songs and to prepare for the first shows at Wembley Stadium in London, which were exhausted. The film features interpretations of the most iconic and fans -cherished themes, including images of the band in the studio and on the road.
In a very different record is “the girl with the needle”, aired on August 22 and September 7, in which the story of Karoline, a manufacturing worker who fights to survive in the city of Copenhagen, in the years after World War II. When he finds himself unemployed, abandoned and pregnant, he intersects with Dagmar, a charismatic woman who generates a clandestine adoption agency, helping mothers to find homes of reception for unwanted children. With no alternative, Karoline accepts the role of milk loves. Between the two women is born a strong connection, but Karoline's world collapses when discovering the shocking truth behind her work, describes the synopsis of the film.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:01:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Dirks Theater | NON -VERBAL THEATER WITH LINKS TO SARAMAGO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/dirks-theatre-teatro-nao-verbal-com-ligacoes-a-saramago/</link><description>It's called “Echoes in Dreams” and is the new nonverbal play of the local company Dirks Theater. Scheduled for September, this show mixes the compositions of Argentine José Luís Merlin, with body performances inspired by the Psychology and the tale “O Centauro”, by José Saramago
 
Macao Dirks Theater's theatrical company features, between September 19th and 21st, the show “Echoes in Dreams”, which constitutes a performance in which bodies wanders to the sound of the classic guitar, with sounds of Argentine José Luís Merlin, and expressions of nonverbal theater.
The play is presented in the northern zone of the peninsula, namely in the space “Hiukok Laboratory, in number 408 of Rua dos Fishermen, specifically in the industrial building Nam Fong.
According to information provided by the company, it mixes a “classic guitar, six strings, and three souls and bodies”, being a show that “will lead the public to observe human behavior from a perspective in the third person, plunging into themes such as physical and subconscious conflict, exploring the very understanding of 'identity'”.
In this play there is also no shortage of influences from Portuguese literature, namely the Nobel Prize for literature José Saramago, with the tale “O Centauro”.
It is a text that begins this way: “The horse stopped. The horseshoe-free hulls were signed in the round stones and slips that covered the almost dry bottom of the river. The man poured his hands, cautiously, the thorny branches that covered his vision to the side of the plain.
“The centaur, an immortal prehistoric creature, half a man, half horse, feels blame for his race has been annihilated by humans while he could do nothing to prevent him. This hybrid creature has been wandered around the world since then, becoming a night figure just to stay away from all human species. last time.
Jung is present
In addition to the reference to Saramago, “Echoes in Dreams” will also seek inspiration from psychology, namely the work “Memories, Dreams, Reflections” by Swiss psychologist Carl Gustav Jung. On stage, Macao guitarist Bruce Chi Man Pun plays the compositions of José Luís Merlin, while actor Ka Man IP and dancer Chloe Wong "have a visual and emotionally evocative performance."
"Echoes in Dreams" is about concepts such as "nostalgia", "contrast", "exile" and "happiness", narrating the inner world of "someone who lives in a certain city." It is also made, in the play, a reflection on the themes of “exile” and “belonging” in the contemporary global context.
Tickets are on sale on the Dart Ticketing platform and cost 240 patacas, with discounts for those who buy tickets in advance and also for students and retired. “Echoes in Dreams” has already climbed the stage once, with another format. According to the company, what the public will see in September is a "small retrospective of the first" Echoes in Dreams "race."
“It will not be the same as we did in 2023. The world has changed and we all move. Let's dance once again,” is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:14:57</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC | Prominent handwriting on the show “Go ahead, the future shines”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/05/frc-caligrafia-em-destaque-na-mostra-vai-em-frente-o-futuro-brilha/</link><description>A new exhibition is inaugurated today at the Rui Cunha Foundation, which will be evident for a short time, until this Saturday. It is “go ahead, the future shines”, a show of handwriting whose protagonists are the students of the art and literature courses at the Fo Guang Shan Buddhist Center. This is a tribute to Master Hsing Yun
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) hosts, between today and Saturday, a new exhibition of handwriting. This is the show “Keep Going, The Future Is Bright” [goes ahead, the future shines], with the organization of the teacher and students of the Fo Guang Shan Buddhist Center and Literature courses, and is presented as a tribute to the “Venerable Master” Hsing Yun.
The show features about 50 works of calligraphy and Chinese painting “that seek to continue the spirit of Master Hsing Yun, founder of the Buddhist Center, whose vision problems would get worse in recent years,” describes a FRC note. The same master developed and used the "eye of the heart" and the "eye of the dharma" to write his unique handwriting of "a trace", hoping to convey compassion, wisdom, peace and light through his creations.
Dharma is a multifaceted concept that largely refers to the principle of cosmic order, of the rectitude, duty and the way to a meaning with meaning, which in Buddhism encompasses the moral obligations of the individual, ethical conduct and the natural laws that govern the universe.
Works with Messages
The project includes the work of Professor Hok-Lon Yim's art and literature students, a “young and influential Caligraph and Painter of Macau” who was invited by the Fo Guang Shan Buddhist Center to guide the teaching of handwriting and painting to all enthusiasts, with greater or lesser experience, using brush and paint to transmit blessings and bring joy to people.
The founding of the Macau Buddhist Center dates back to early 1989, when Master Hsing Yun preached Dharma in public places in Hong Kong, gathering devotees from the neighboring territory and also spontaneous group formations from Macao to attend the lectures. The invitation was then released to Master Hsing Yun to send her disciples to Macau to preach Dharma, and her own came here countless, between 1991 and 2014, giving emotional lectures, always with crowded auditoriums.
In 1996, the center was officially recorded as a non -profit charity organization by the government, starting its mission to spread Dharma in Macau, following the principle of "promoting humanist Buddhism and building a pure land." This is a branch of Fo Guang Shan Regional and Macao's largest urban Buddhist center.</description><pubDate>2025-08-05 02:02:57</pubDate></item><item><title>Joaquim Surumali helps preserve Timorense cultural heritage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/04/joaquim-surumali-ajuda-a-preservar-patrimonio-cultural-timorense/</link><description>It is in his workshop in Tasi Tolu, Dili, that Joaquim Surumali preserves the cultural heritage of Timor-Leste by replicating in jewelry, for daily use, pieces used in sacred houses and in traditional ceremonies and dances.
In his hands, Kaebauk, an ornament with buffalo horns, which represents the sun, strength, safety, protection and power, traditionally used in the head and on the roofs of sacred houses, gains the form of earrings and pending to be used in a necklace.
Already the “Belak”, a bronze disc that symbolizes the moon and is used to the chest and inside the sacred houses, can also be bought in earrings.
In Joaquim Sumali's workshop, neither does necklaces, called “Morten”, are normally listed with the orange color, which bring luck and prosperity and push the evil spirits and negative energies.
“I want to do this job. My father also worked with jewelry, shaped Belak and Kaebauk since the time of the Portuguese, and so far my brothers and sisters sometimes still make jewelry like Kaebauk and Belak in Dili,” Lusa Joaquim Surumali told.
The 34 -year -old jeweler stressed that his art is a family tradition, which continues to this day. “I learned to make jewelry with my father and my brothers. But our work comes from our own blood, from our father and the elders who also made jewelry like the ones that are done today,” explained Joaquim Surumali.
Other materials
Joaquim Surumali makes the jewelry in gold, silver or bronze, depending on the preference and money of customers. The material, according to the jeweler, is bought in Timor-Leste, but most come from Indonesia or Singapore, because resources in the country are scarce.
"As people buy in gold to put in holy houses, it is no longer available. So we try to buy abroad. Most of the time, customers are the ones who bring gold and we only charge for our labor," said the jeweler.
Asked about jewelry prices, the craftsman explained that a pure gold "Belak" can cost $ 600 and a $ 100 "death". "Many Timorese buy these jewelry, but also many Portuguese, especially teachers," he said.
Joaquim explained that the Portuguese appreciate these pieces because they see in them something unique and traditional of Timor-Leste. The Timorenses buy them to put them in the sacred houses of families and can be seen in all municipalities of the country. The most bought articles are, above all, the “Belak” of gold.
About the monthly yield of jewelry production, Joaquim Surumali said it can reach the monthly $ 500, but it depends on the number of customers and visits.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 07:57:41</pubDate></item><item><title>PJ | Three detainees for credit cards</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/pj-tres-detidos-por-burlas-com-cartoes-de-credito/</link><description>The Judiciary Police (PJ) announced the detention of three people due to the theft of bank payment card data, which were then used to make online shopping. In total, the authorities estimate that the criminal network has made improper purchases and payments of 1.18 million patacas.
According to the contours of the case, in May, September and October last year PJ received reports from two banks on the existence of suspicious transactions in Macao using data from cards issued abroad. In total 2,611 transactions were performed that resulted in a movement of 3.5 million patacas. Transactions involved online payments or use of terminals for credit card purchases. Among these, 771 transactions, which represented 1.18 million patacas are challenged by banks as illegitimate and without permission of card owners.
The transactions were made at local shops. However, police investigation concluded that the amounts traded during the dates in question do not make sense in the light of the normal business volume investigated. It was also concluded that the amount of sales is not consistent with the type of products available.
Cards whose data were used were issued in the United States, Belarus, France, Indonesia, South Africa, Middle East and Taiwan.
The detainees are three residents of Macao, including a 39 -year -old man who owns a car sales stand. Another 34 -year -old man was arrested on his own, and a 38 -year -old woman, a beauty product seller.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:50:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Medical Residences | Registration for 79 vacancies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/residencias-medicas-abertas-inscricoes-para-79-vagas/</link><description>Today open registration for medical residency exams for 33 specialties. Of the 79 vacancies available, 29 will be to form clinical paintings of the Conde de São Januário Hospital and 28 to the Ilhas Hospital. Specialties include cardiology, psychiatry, internal medicine, family medicine and geriatrics
 
The government officially announced yesterday the opening of the contest to evaluate “medical integrated skills, for admission to the medical residency” of 79 professionals who will reinforce the clinical staff of hospitals in the territory. The parameters of the contest were released yesterday in the official bulletin, in a publication signed by the director of Alvis Lo health services.
Registration opens today and interested parties can apply until August 18 to the competition of the liability of the Medical Academy.
Qualified candidates admitted to the Residency Program will receive six years of systematic training in the workplace in public, private and community health institutions in Macao, consisting of two years of basic training and four years of advanced training.
The 79 vacancies for medical residences will be divided into 33 specialties, including 10 surgeons, but also cardiology, psychiatry, internal medicine, family medicine and geriatrics. Among the nearly eight dozen vacancies, only three are for psychiatry doctors (all for the hospital Conde de São Januário)
The two poles
Among the vacancies that will open to medical residences, 29 will reinforce the clinical condition of the Conde de São Januário Hospital Center, 28 in the Island Health Care Complex, seven at Kiang Wu Hospital, two in public health at the Center for Disease Prevention and Control and 13 in Family Medicine in the Community Health Care Department.
According to a statement published yesterday by health services, the contest for medical residences resulted from the work of the Macao Medical Academy Specialty Council, which took office in March.
The body led by Alvis Lo promises that he will continue to develop "access to medical residency in order to prepare the reserve of talents from different specialties and raise the overall level of Macao medical services."
The government is also committed to deepening cooperation with training institutions, and optimizing the allocation of training resources and increasing vacancies for more trainees, with the aim of creating a “broader professional development platform for young doctors in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:42:54</pubDate></item><item><title>STD | More than 10 million followers in the 28 accounts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/dst-mais-de-10-milhoes-de-seguidores-nas-28-contas/</link><description>Last month, the 28 official accounts of the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) exceeded 10 million followers on various social networks.
According to a statement released yesterday by the body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes, the promotional strategy on social networks has conveyed “visitors around the world, in an innovative and interactive way, the latest tourist information, festivities, events and typical experiences of Macao”.
Given the Internet habits of different visitor issues, STD has opened accounts on social networks such as Twitter, Facebook, Youtube, Instagram, Tiktok, Kakao Talk, Line, Wechat, Weibo, Red Note, Douyin (Chinese Tiktok), depending on the region or country.
STD also bet on the invitation to digital influencers from the interior of China and Hong Kong to publicize Macau on their platforms through broad broadcasts, images or short videos. Investment in digital influencers promotions, coupled with toy brands campaigns such as pop Mart, focuses on attracting generation Z visitors.
Recently, the STD account in Tiktok has launched a series of short dramas in Indonesian, filmed in Macao and directed to the young audience, which accumulated about 100 million views.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Chikungunya fever | Critical phase of prevention and control</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/febre-de-chikungunya-fase-critica-de-prevencao-e-controlo/</link><description>With a total of eight cases registered in Macao, two of them local, health services point out that the territory is in the critical phase of prevention and control of chikungunya fever. The subject was approached yesterday on the Macau Forum Morning Program, from the Chinese channel of Radio Macau
 
In a disease propagated by mosquitoes, prevention is everything. And Macao is currently in the early and critical prevention and control of chikungunya fever prevention and control, the head of the Center for Prevention and Control of Health Services (SS), Chan Choi Wan, said yesterday. The statements were made on the morning program of the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the Macao Forum.
The official said he hoped that the population can apply stagnant water zones cleaning measures in order to avoid the spread of mosquitoes that can cause this disease. These zones can be stagnant water puddles or water spaces with water, having been recommended to wear long clothes to avoid mosquito bites, or even the use of mosquito nets.
"Chikungunya fever and dengue fever are transmitted through mosquitoes of ade mosquitoes, not being transmitted diseases among humans. These are transmitted but controllable diseases and whose prevention is possible," he said in the radio program.
However, Chan Choi Wan pointed out that, although there is no community transmission, the risk of transmission in Macau remains high due to the importation of cases.
Asked about scientific criteria for the establishment of mosquito elimination zones, Chan Choi Wan said that after the epidemiological analysis of each case of infection is performed the elimination of mosquitoes in the risk zone. A circular radius is also calculated taking into account the approximate distance from the mosquito flight.
The substitute chief of the Environmental Hygiene Division of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI), Pang Sao Hun, recalled that since July, more mosquito elimination actions have been carried out.
"Regarding the hygiene of private places or unoccupied land, if it is verified of an urgent or risk or risk situation for public health, and if we cannot contact the owners, AMI seeks to coordinate to remove stagnant water spaces and waste, in order to avoid the spread of mosquitoes and thus reduce the risk of disease transmission," he said.
Light symptoms
Macao currently has eight cases of chikungunya fever, of which six are imported and two locations. Public health doctor at the Ieong Chon Kit disease prevention and control center revealed that the two patients relating to local cases are still being treated at the hospital with light symptoms.
On Tuesday, the Zhuhai market regulation administration has published a warning of chikungunya fever control in pharmacies, noting that pharmacies need to record data from the users who buy analgesic medications or have symptoms of this fever, or have been chopped by mosquitoes. Authorities also asked pharmacies to disclose information on the prevention and control measures of these two types of fever.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Accident | Player of the football selection among the deadly victims</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/acidente-jogador-da-seleccao-de-futebol-entre-as-vitimas-mortais/</link><description>The extreme right of Macao's football team, Leon NG Lai Teng, just 20, died on Monday in a car accident, according to the club where he played, Cheng Fung, who expressed regret and condolences. Leong was the fourth deadly victim to be confirmed by the authorities.
"On behalf of all players and employees [at Cheng Fung], we would like to express our most sincere condolences to Leon NG Lai Teng's family," the club said on Facebook, manifesting available to do the "best to provide all the assistance and support needed for the family."
The accident occurred around 6 am on Monday morning, when a vehicle of five passengers carrying seven people, driven by a 20-year-old, displeased and clashed against concrete barriers on the roadside.
The three of the occupants who survived the tragic accident continued hospitalized yesterday, according to police. "As we learned of this tragic news, everyone in the club was taken for infinite sadness and deep regret," Cheng Fung said on social networks.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:01:32</pubDate></item><item><title>SMG | Rain will extend today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/smg-chuva-vai-prolongar-se-durante-o-dia-de-hoje/</link><description>For the first time, this year, the black sign of heavy rain was issued and it is expected that precipitation will not continue to give respite in this day. Yesterday, the most intense rains registered at Dr. Sun Yat Sen Municipal Park and Coloane Village
 
Thunderstorms, sweeteners and unstable time. This was the forecast left by the Directorate of Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) for this day, after a morning with intense and quite thunder, which led to the emission of the first black signal of intense rain of the year.
“Due to the combined influence of a southwest air stream and high altitude disturbances, time is expected to be unstable between Tuesday and the beginning of Wednesday (August 5-6), with frequent, sometimes intense, thunderstorm,” was explained on the SMG portal. "It is appealed to the population to pay attention to information and weather warnings, adjust their travel properly and pay attention to the possibility of flooding in low areas during heavy rain in a short time," he was added.
Yesterday was marked by the most intense rain of the year, which was felt mainly in the morning. In some zones of the territory, the largest water loads felt between 5am and 6 am, especially in the northern part of the city, such as black sand, but rain has extended practically all day.
As a consequence of bad weather, and water accumulation, the heaviest rainfall signal, the highest of the scale, was lifted around 8:18 am, with the forecast of floods in the low zones of the territory. This signal is issued when it is expected that in one hour precipitation reaches 80 millimeters of rain, ie the equivalent of 80 liters of water per square meter.
Suspended classes
The intense rain alert led any secondary school classes to be suspended in the morning, according to a statement from the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ). In the same vein, children's, primary and special teachings were suspended throughout the day.
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) revealed that during the most intense rainy season there was a need to assist a driver whose car suffered a malfunction on the Macao bridge.
Around noon and a half, and at a time when the rain signs had been raised, the area to record the highest precipitation accumulation was the coloane village, with 118.6mms of rain from midnight. This zone recorded the largest rain around 8am, when it accumulated almost 60 millimeters of rain.
According to SMG data, Dr. Sun Yat Sen Municipal Park, near the doors of the siege, was another one of the most affected places with 118.2 mm of rain. In this place, the most intense rain occurred at 6am. The Monte Fortress (109.2mm), the black sand (104.4mm) and Ka-Hó (104.4mm) were other areas where in 12 hours the accumulated rain exceeded 100 millimeters.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:56:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Heritage | Requested action to the government in building buildings</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/patrimonio-pedida-accao-ao-governo-na-gestao-de-edificios/</link><description>Following the damage caused by Typhoon Whipa, the former Iam Chan Pou Sam counselor understands that the government should take a strong position in the management and maintenance of old buildings or historical interest. The official argues that the Kaiping model is followed in Macau in the Patio do Espinho
 
The passage of the first typhoon that led to the issuance of Alert Signal 10, Whipa led the honorary president of the Macao population and welfare promotion association, Chan Pou Sam, to warn of the need to change laws and regulations to ensure the integrity of the city's buildings, especially of the oldest and of equity interest.
Speaking to the citizen newspaper, the former member of the Advisory Board of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) gave the damage to facades of buildings, such as the new and luxurious Nova Grand, in the mud, but also the collapse of a wall in an old house in the courtyard of Espinho.
The official considers that the government should improve the regulations governing private buildings, clarify the legal status of owners, oblige inspections and reparations of buildings and increase subsidies for the maintenance of buildings and boost a proactive attitude in the defense of the integrity of buildings.
Chan Pou Sam states that many owners have an advanced age, are not instruction and do not comprise the laws and regulations on the maintenance of older buildings. The situation is aggravated in buildings where property rights are not clear, and that do not have associations of owners or any organization that deals with the maintenance of the building. As such, the leader considers essential that the executive assumes a more interventional role in defending the integrity of the city's urban park.
Thorn
According to official data, there are approximately 4,800 buildings in Macao over 30 years old, and more than 3,500 of these buildings are less than seven floors and are located in old neighborhoods. From this last sample, about 1,700 have aged structures, poor -wedy doors and windows, lack of fire protection, pipeline and ancient electric networks and precarious sanitation.
In addition to the buildings that constitute a risk to public safety, Chan Pou Sam emphasizes the degradation of the homes of the Patio do Espinho (in the rear of the ruins of São Paulo), a place with a history of over 400 years, which deserves to be preserved for constituting a physical memory of Macao's “roots and soul”.
Once the properties and management of real estate remains unchanged, the official thinks that the government should take responsibility for the conservation and revitalization of homes in the Patio do Espinho, following the example of the model adopted in the villages of Kaiping and Diaolou in Jiangmen.
It should be noted that Chan Pou Sam has assumed positions of management in associations linked to the Jiangmen community and was the AMI counselor who suggested a public consultation to remove the “colonialist names” from the streets of Macao. At the time, the executive led by Chui Sai On, at the end of his second term, did not access the suggestion.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 00:51:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us his wife and daughter (cf. Recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: High there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad for us, in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts him a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people, which always seems the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Jiangyou | Protests require severe sanctions after aggression to the lowest</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/jiangyou-protestos-exigem-sancoes-severas-apos-agressao-a-menor/</link><description>Hundreds of people have manifested themselves in the Chinese city of Jiangyou to demand more severe punishments from minors involved in aggression to a 14-year-old colleague, in a case filmed and disclosed online that generated widespread indignation on social networks.
The protests included posters with the image of the victim, nicknamed Lai, and songs to ask for a "fair investigation." Videos shared on social network X show confrontations with police and punctual arrests.
The popular revolt intensified after the announcement by the police authorities that the perpetrators would only be the target of “administrative measures” and sent to a correctional educational center. The decision was made twelve days after the complaint was filed, an excessive interval by many netizens.
Before that, a widely shared photograph on the networks showed family members of Lai kneeling before a local official, asking for justice, which further increased social pressure.
The aggression, filmed in the vicinity of a teaching establishment, shows Lai to be slapped by at least two colleagues, from nicknames Liu and Peng. In one of the videos, one of the aggressors boast of having been "more than ten times" in a squad without "never being more than twenty minutes."
On the same day of aggression, on July 22, Lai went with his father to the police to file a complaint. After a preliminary medical examination, he returned later to make statements.
According to the local newspaper The Paper, between July 24 and August 3, the police interrogated all witnesses and requested a forensic report, according to national body damage assessment standards, which recommend examining the victim between one and two weeks after the injury stabilization.
On 3 August, doctors ruled out hidden fractures and classified the injuries as slight. The next day, the authorities ended the case with the application of administrative sanctions.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:14:16</pubDate></item><item><title>HIMALAIAS | At least five dead and 100 missing in a sudden flood</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/07/himalaias-pelo-menos-cinco-mortos-e-100-desaparecidos-em-inundacao-repentina/</link><description>At least five people have died and more than 100 remain missing in a land allocation caused by torrential rainfall in the Indian state of Uttarakhand in Himalayas, a source of the rescue team announced yesterday.
The disaster took place around 1:30 pm on Tuesday in the village of Dharali, in the district of Uttarkashi, when a sudden flood caused a large water drop from the mountains and devastated the village, dragging everything to his passage, including dozens of people. “About 150 people were taken to a safe place.”
According to available information, four people have been found dead and more than 100 are missing. We are still awaiting confirmation from the local administration, ”said the Assistant Response Force (NDRF) Assistant Inspector General, Mohsen Shahedi, who sent three teams to the affected area.
Hours later, the Press Trust of India State News Agency (PTI) reported the recovery of a fifth body of the rubble in Dharali, while search and rescue efforts continue.
Images released by the authorities and the media show the Kheerganga River to suddenly overflow and completely submerge the area, now covered by thick and debris mud, making it difficult to assist authorities.
Uttarakhand chief minister Pushkar Singh Dhami arrived at the disaster scene this morning to coordinate the response at the scene.
"There are great rescue efforts, involving more than 160 police," said Dhami, adding that food packages have been prepared for distribution and a medical team has been mobilized to deal with the injured. Dharali, a popular summer tourist destination, now remains practically isolated after several access roads have been destroyed or blocked by land allings.
Red alert
Authorities have asked residents to remain away from rivers due to the risk of new floods. This disaster happens at a time when a red alert was issued by the Meteorological Institute of India due to the risk of “extremely strong” rainfall in various areas of the state in the coming days.
Uttarakhand, a mountainous and ecologically fragile region, has recorded uninterrupted rainfall during the current monsoon station and numerous land and flooding. The so -called “cloud explosions”, extremely localized phenomena that cause torrential rain in just a few minutes, are especially dangerous in areas such as Himalayas, where the soil cannot absorb water.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:06:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Shanghai | Tesla's 'megafábrica' deliveries in the face of competition from Chinese brands</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/xangai-entregas-da-megafabrica-da-tesla-caem-face-a-concorrencia-de-marcas-chinesas/</link><description>Tesla MegaFábrica deliveries in Xangai, east of China, decreased in July, resuming the negative trend interrupted in June, at the time totaling eight consecutive months of falls due to competition from local brands, the Chinese press said.
According to the Hong Kong South China Morning Post newspaper, which is based on data from the CPCA employer association, the factory - the largest Tesla in the field of world assembly - delivered about 68,000 vehicles to customers in China and abroad, which represents a 5.2 percent drop compared to June and 8.4 percent, in homologous terms.
“Premium models are losing appeal among Chinese consumers because they want to save money. They are choosing cheaper and developed electric models in China,” explained Yiyou Auto Service sales manager Tian Maowei.
In accumulated of the year, including sales in China and exports, the megafábrica established in the East Chinese megalopolis has delivered more than 432,000 cars, a 13.7 percent drop in homologous terms.
The number contrasts with the 35 percent increase of tramful sales in China, to about 7.6 million units, in the first seven months of 2025, according to CPCA data. These two opposing trends made Tesla's market share on the Chinese electric vehicle market dropped from 6.9 percent a year to 3.8 percent. In 2020, when he opened the factory in Shanghai, the quota of the brand led by Elon Musk was 16 percent.
Given the competition of local companies such as Xpeng, Leapmotor or Li Auto and a pricing war that led to government intervention, Tesla is trying to recover ground with new more spacious or more autonomy versions of its most successful vehicles, such as Model 3 or Model Y.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:58:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Philippines | Beijing rejects criticism for falling rocket wreckage</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/filipinas-pequim-rejeita-criticas-por-queda-de-destrocos-de-foguetao/</link><description>A China rejeitou as críticas das Filipinas pela queda de destroços de um foguetão perto da ilha de Palawan, garantindo que os fragmentos caíram em águas internacionais previamente notificadas, segundo fontes citadas pelo jornal oficial Global Times.
The launch took place “according to the mission plan” and the reentry zones were previously notified to neighboring countries “in accordance with international practice”, indicate the sources cited by the newspaper
The same sources considered that Manila's statements reveal a "unfair stance" and a deliberate effort to "harm the image of China."
The Larga March-12 rocket was launched on Monday from the Commercial Space Center located on Hainan's Chinese Island, with the aim of orbit a group of internet satellites from the company Galaxyspace.
On the same day, the Filipine Space Agency warned of the possible drop in non -fuel wreckage in water near Palawan and recommended to the population to inform the authorities in case of sighting. On Tuesday, the National Philippine National Security Counselor, Eduardo Año, classified the launch as a “irresponsible” race that “alarmed the population” and “put the inhabitants at risk” of that island.
The conviction of the Filipino Security Council has aggravated the tension between Manila and Beijing, which vie for the sovereignty of various territories in the Southern Sea of China.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:57:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Chikungunya | More combat measures after thousands of infections in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/chikungunya-mais-medidas-de-combate-apos-milhares-de-infeccoes-na-china/</link><description>The fight against chikungunya fever in China intensifies with the authorities to resort to all weapons to contain the outbreak that already has 7,000 cases, most in Foshan
 
An outbreak of the Chikungunya virus in China led authorities to implement strict preventive measures, including use of mosquitoes, drones and disinfectant, with threats of fines and electricity cuts for those who do not eliminate standing waters.
More than 7,000 cases were reported until yesterday, concentrated mainly in the industrial city of Foshan. Authorities indicated a slight reduction trend in new contagion. Transmitted by mosquitoes, chikungunya causes fever and joint pain, with symptoms similar to dengue, affecting children, older people, elderly and people with pre-existing diseases.
Chinese state television has displayed images of teams to spray disinfectant in streets, residential areas, construction shipyards and other places where transmitting mosquitoes can be reproduced in stagnant waters.
In some office buildings, spraying was made before employee entry into a reminiscent approach to restrictive tactics applied during the Covid-19 pandemic.
Local authorities threaten to apply fines up to 10,000 yuan and electricity cuts to residents that do not eliminate external containers with water such as bottles or vessels.
The United States issued a warning advice to travel to the Chinese province of Guangdong - where Foshan, Dongguan and other industrial centers - as well as countries such as Bolivia, Brazil, and the Indian Ocean nations, also affected by the virus.
It's not easy
Intense rainfall and high temperatures aggravated the situation in China, where Chikungunya, common in tropical areas, came up with unusual force this year. Since the outbreak of Sars in 2003, China has resorted to coercive measures considered excessive by many countries.
In Foshan, those infected are required to stay in the hospital for at least one week. Authorities even imposed two -week home quarantines, however suspended that the virus is not transmitted between humans.
According to reports, fish that feed on larvae and even larger mosquitoes have been used to hunt the vectors of the virus. Meetings and defined national protocols were held, in a demonstration of Chinese determination to contain the outbreak and avoid internal and international criticism.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:54:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Hiroshima marks 80 years of the atomic bomb in a context of conflict</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/hiroshima-assinala-80-anos-da-bomba-atomica-num-contexto-de-conflitos/</link><description>Japan will mark on Wednesday the 80th anniversary of the launch of the atomic bomb over Hiroshima in a context of appeals to abandon nuclear weapons and wars in Ukraine and the Middle East.
On August 6, 1945, at 8:15 am, the United States launched an atomic bomb over the city of Hiroshima, killing about 140,000 people. Three days later, an identical bomb hit Nagasaki and killed 74,000 more people, according to France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
The two attacks, which precipitated the end of World War II (1939-1945), are the only cases in history in which nuclear weapons were used in war time. Representatives from 120 countries and regions, as well as from the European Union, are expected to attend the ceremony in Hiroshima tomorrow, a record number, according to the authorities of the city of southwest Japan.
The main states with nuclear weapons, such as Russia, China and Pakistan, will not be present, while Iran, accused of trying to purchase the bomb, will be represented. Contrary to usual practice, Japan said it did not choose the guests for the ceremony, but notified all countries and regions of the event.
"The existence of [politicians] leaders who want to reinforce military power to resolve conflict, including the possession of atomic weapons, makes the establishment of world peace difficult," Hiroshima Chamber of Hiroshi, Kazumi Matsui, said, referring to wars in Ukraine and the Middle East.
Matsui invited last month the president of the United States to visit Hiroshima, when Donald Trump compared recent air attacks against Iran to atomic bombing of 1945.
"It seems to me that he [Trump] does not quite understand the reality of atomic bombing, which, if used, cost many innocent citizens, friends or enemies, and threaten the survival of humanity," he said at the time.
The war continues
Hiroshima is currently a prosperous metropolis with 1.2 million inhabitants, but the ruins of a building topped by the metal skeleton of a summit remain in the city center as a recall of the horror of the attack.
"It is important that many people gather in this city hit by the atomic bomb because the wars continue" in the world, said Toshiyuki Mimaki, co -president of the Nihon Hidankyo organization, formed by pump survivors and a 2024 Nobel Peace Prize winner.
Nihon Hidankyo wants governments to take action to eliminate nuclear weapons, based on the testimonies of the survivors of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, known as 'Hibakusha'. “I want foreign representatives to visit the Memorial Peace Museum and understand what happened” under the atomic cloud in the form of mushroom, Mimaki said.
"I believe the global trend to a world without nuclear weapons will continue. The younger generation is working hard to achieve it," said 80 -year -old Kunihiko Sakuma, who was 9 months old in 1945 and was three kilometers from the point of impact.
Sakuma, who is expected to meet Japanese Prime Minister Shigeru Ishiba, after the ceremony, intends to appeal to Tokyo to add to the UN treaty about the prohibition of nuclear weapons, signed in 2017. Tokyo refused to sign the treaty, claiming that the objective is unattainable without the help of states with nuclear weapons.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:16:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Financial support for 16 foreign activists prohibited</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/hong-kong-proibido-apoio-financeiro-a-16-activistas-estrangeiros/</link><description>Sixteen Activists of Hong Kong, resident abroad, were yesterday targeted by sanctions from Hong Kong authorities, including cancellation of passports and banning access to financial support on suspicion of threat to national security.
Yesterday's activistivists are part of a group of 19 people, targeted by July warrants, reported the Associated Press news agency.
Hong Kong Security Secretary in China, Chris Tang, has banned funds or economic resources to 16 activists, including Victor Ho, Keung Ka-Wai, Australian student Chongyi Feng and US citizen Gong Sasha, according to Hong Kong government statement.
The travel documents were canceled to 12 of the 16 Hong Kong passport holders. The Hong Kong government has also banned access to lease to 16 indicted, as well as commercial or business activity, stressing that any violation of orders is subject to a penalty of up to seven years in prison.
The 16 activists are out of Hong Kong, and are accused of remaining involved in activities that endanger national security. The accusation also covers incitement to hatred against Beijing and Hong Kong, on the grounds of defamation and slander. The measures now adopted, according to the statement of the Hong Kong authorities, were taken "to have a significant impact."</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:10:37</pubDate></item><item><title>China requires greater control of technology in training models with AI algorithms</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/china-exige-maior-controlo-das-tecnologicas-no-treino-de-modelos-com-algoritmos-de-ia/</link><description>Chinese authorities warned yesterday with the risks associated with the so -called “data contamination” in Artificial Intelligence Systems (AI) and instituted technology companies to reinforce the control of the information used in the training of their models.
In a statement published on the Wechat social network, the State Ministry of Security warned that the proliferation of texts, images and videos generated by IA is increasing the likelihood of “falsified, skewed or repetitive” contents to integrate new training data sets, which may result in judgment errors, “wrong automatic decisions” or “public opinion handling”.
Authorities cite studies that one in 10,000 samples would be false to make the number of harmful responses from a model to increase in a significant way. This “waterfall effect”, where artificially generated contents generated new systems, is a matter of concern for sensitive sectors such as health, finance or public safety, where decisions based on inaccurate data would have a direct impact on the population.
To mitigate these risks, the ministry has recalled that since January, a regulation that obliges the Generative AI platforms to perform security audits, clearly identify the contents produced by artificial intelligence, and periodically eliminate data that violates the rules in force.
The body had already warned, in July, that the use of AI could represent a threat to “social stability”, sensitive data protection and national security if technology falls into the hands of “hostile forces to China”.
General distrust
Since 2023, AI services in the country have been obliged to follow the “fundamental socialist values” and prohibited from “generating content that undermines national security, territorial unity and social stability”.
Despite the launch of chatbots by large Chinese technological groups such as Alibaba, Deepseek, Tencent or Bytedance, doubts about AI development persist.
Since 2023, the State Ministry of Security has published regularly in its official accounting account of alleged spying and recommends to the population to be suspicious of job offers or requests for information from abroad.
At the same time, the ministry calls for a “mobilization of the whole society” to “prevent and combat espionage” and “reinforce national defense”, warning of the risks of sending sensitive data over the internet.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:09:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Tariffs | Beijing opens market to Brazilian coffee in response to US rates</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/tarifas-pequim-abre-mercado-a-cafe-brasileiro-em-resposta-a-taxas-dos-eua/</link><description>The tariff war imposed by the US administration continues to lead to the adoption of against measures. Given the imposition of 50% rates on Brazil for political reasons, China opens the doors to Brazilian coffee
 
China has authorized 183 Brazilian companies to export coffee to its domestic market, yesterday advanced local press, days after the United States imposed 50 percent rates on coffee from Brazil.
The measure, valid for five years, was released a few days after the announcement of the new US tariff, which comes into force tomorrow, and caused alarm among Brazilian producers and exporters, now forced to look for alternative markets.
According to industry data, about 85 percent of Brazilian Arabica production in 2025 - the most exported variety for the US - has already been harvested. This type of coffee plays a central role in the US market, where it is often mixed with softer grains from other Latin American producers to suit the local taste. Brazil is responsible for 44 percent of world arabica production, which makes the country a difficult to replace in the short term.
The United States is the largest consumer of coffee and imported 3.3 million Brazilian coffee bags in the first half of the year, almost 23 percent of the total exported by Brazil during this period. Already China imported 530 thousand bags in the same interval. Although the Chinese market is even smaller, it has been gaining importance as Brazilian access to the US market faces new barriers.
Last November, Apexbrasil, the Brazilian Export Promotion Agency, signed an agreement with Luckin Coffee, China's largest coffee chain, to supply 240,000 tons of Brazilian coffee between 2025 and 2029. The contract is valued at $ 2.5 billion and succeeds a previous agreement of mid -2024, worth $ tons.
Growing
Founded in 2017, Luckin Coffee currently operates over 22,000 stores throughout the Chinese territory and serves over 300 million customers. Although tea remains the dominant traditional drink, coffee consumption has been growing rapidly in the Asian country, especially among young urban professionals. The per capita consumption doubled in five years, from eight to 16 cups a year - still well below the global average of 240 cups and more than 400 registered in the US.
At the time of the agreement, Luckin Coffee executive director Jinyi Guo praised Brazilian coffee and described the contract as “the beginning” of a long -term collaboration. "In the future, we want to further expand this partnership," he said.
Since 2009, China is the main commercial partner in Brazil, with bilateral trade from nine billion dollars in 2004 to 188 billion in 2024. Brazil plays, in particular, an important role in China's food security, composing more than 20 percent of the Asian's agricultural and livestock imports.
The second world's second largest economy feeds nearly 19 percent of humanity with only 8.5 percent of the planet's arable lands. By comparison, the Latin American country has almost 7 percent of the arable land to 2.7 percent of the world's population.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 01:07:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Anabela Santiago, Academic: “China is a reformist and moderate”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/anabela-santiago-academica-a-china-e-reformista-e-moderada/</link><description>Anabela Santiago has just defended at the University of Aveiro the doctoral thesis that analyzes how China has been positioned in recent decades as an important actor in the “global health governance”. Today, Beijing seeks “alternative mechanisms” of cooperation in the “global south” and tries to build an alternative model to the World Health Organization
 
 
Let's start with the concept of Global Health Governance (GGS). Is this a more contemporary concept or relating to the post-war period and the Foundation of the World Health Organization (WHO)? What have been the main actors of this governance until China's growth?
GGS is a concept whose prominence and relevance have grown significantly in the 21st century, largely driven by economic globalization and worldwide interconnection. Although global health has always transcended national borders, demanding multidisciplinary approaches and international cooperation, only from the 1990s it was made greater awareness of it. Historically, GGS has been predominantly influenced by western powers and neoliberal values. The main actors of this governance, until China's growth, were historically marked by interventions of entities such as WHO and non-governmental, predominantly American and European organizations.
One of the findings of its doctoral thesis is that China has been progressively positioning itself in this leadership. This position started specifically when and why?
Yes, China has been progressively positioned as a relief actor in the evolution of the GG system. Although it is not possible to point out an exact start date, China has evolved from a relatively isolated country to a main actor in global political, economic and technological arenas. Its growing economic and political influence also represents a change in GGS's historical dynamics, and in the 1960s China tried to play a humanitarian health care role in neighboring countries and Africa. The thesis points out that China's experience can be seen as an example of what is achievable when a state chooses its own way rather than a pre-established model, aligning itself with the 21st century prediction as the "century of Asia."
Did the pandemic years influence this position? How?
Covid-19 pandemic highlighted the need for global health cooperation, as well as the potential consequences of the failure to prioritize global health. The thesis explores the evolution of the Health Silk Route before and after the pandemic, indicating that the pandemic years allowed greater awareness of the need for instruments such as the Health Silk Route as the most effective cooperation platforms among nations. Although not detailed in this specific section, it is implicit that the pandemic intensified China's performance in health diplomacy and health development assistance.
Looking at the internal reforms that China has carried out in the health area, which highlights as the most important?
I approach, in the thesis, the reforms of the China Health System and I point out that the Chinese governance model is a unique combination of state -oriented economic reforms and development by the state, incorporating elements of neoliberalism and authoritarianism into political issues in general, and the health sector is nothing different from the rest. One of China's mentioned contributions, recognized by WHO, is its primary health care model based on the recognized good practice of “barefoot doctors” (barefoot doctors). In addition, the thesis analyzes the main reform policies and their progress and challenges in the period 2009-2018, which comprise the reforms of primary health care, hospital and pharmaceutical reform. The “Healthy China 2030” program is also an important and ambitious reference of China's domestic reforms in health, also encompassing social determinants.
Is Beijing's intention to create an alternative entity to WHO, or simply create an alternative movement that can coexist with WHO, in the context of the relationship with the global south? How could this work?
The thesis suggests that China adopts a "dual approach": while integrating in existing global structures, forging simultaneously alternative paths, particularly through regional alliances such as BRICS and partnerships with Global South. This indicates an intention to create an alternative movement that can coexist and complement the role of WHO, rather than a direct alternative entity. China demonstrates a clear commitment to align the objectives of the “Belt and Road” initiative with the united nations sustainable development objectives, showing their willingness to present these initiatives as complements to the existing cooperation mechanisms in the international liberal order. President Xi Jinping's view of a “future community shared for humanity”, which includes the notion of a “global health community for all”, also points to a new perspective in international cooperation.
Traditional Chinese Masks, Vaccines and Medicine (MTC): What are China's products or instruments to position itself as an increasingly global actor in GGS?
The thesis points out that China is an indispensable provider of global public health, essential for the product supply chain, such as masks and vaccines. The MTC is also mentioned as one of China's great contributions to global health governance, with its chinese herbal treatments, some of which already recognized by WHO in 2017. In addition, Chinese medical assistance and medical teams sent to other regions of the globe are important instruments of Chinese health diplomacy.
In creating an alternative movement or reality to WHO, China may be taking advantage of the lack of full representativeness in the same WHO, or gaps in its operation?
The thesis does not address directly whether China is taking advantage of a lack of full representativeness in WHO or gaps in its operation. However, it emphasizes that the work aims to fill a gap in scientific knowledge in relation to the paradigm of health governance from a non-western and liberal perspective, emphasizing China as an actor of the global south. This suggests that China seeks to strengthen alternative models that can offer more personalized health challenges, different from those defended by Western countries, positioning itself as a moderate reformist actor.
How has the European Union (EU) foreign policy in relation to China affecting or influenced this position of the country in global health governance?
In the thesis, the fourth publication, entitled "Challenges on the European Union-China Cooperation in Higher Education from" People-To-People Dialogue ’Perspective: The Case of Health-Related Joint Projects," explores cooperation in higher education, in particular that includes health-related projects. Therefore, despite the strategic and economic dialogue, the deterioration of UE-china bilateral relations intensified, with the commission to assume a decline of enthusiasm due to “China's countermeasures to EU human rights sanctions, economic coercion and commercial measures against the single market, and the positioning of China in the war in Ukraine”. Although challenges and tensions are recognized, cooperation in higher education, including health projects, is seen as part of a broader picture of strategic partnership between EU and China. However, it is evident that there is no long tradition of health cooperation between EU and China in higher education, and that there are few joint projects compared to the general panorama. It is suggested that both EU and China should make more efforts to align medical study curricula and promote more joint research in areas related to health, infectious diseases, among others.
In the Trump 2.0 era, and without pandemic, what could be China's role in global health governance?
Although the thesis is published this year, it focuses on the preceding period and includes the pandemic, where it does not speculate directly on a future scenario of “Trump 2.0” without pandemic. However, the thesis argues that China is not just a participant, but a moderate reformist force in the formation of global health standards. Regardless of future political scenarios, their growing economic and political influence, strategic health diplomacy, internal reforms and initiatives such as the Health Silk Route will continue to shape their role in global health governance. The view of a “global health community for all” also remains a guiding principle for China's efforts.
Does this power of China in GGS verify more with bilateral or multilateral agreements?
The thesis suggests that China's power in global health governance manifests itself through both bilateral and multilateral agreements, but with a growing emphasis on certain forms of cooperation that strengthen their role in the global south and through alternative mechanisms. Although the thesis does not explicitly quantify the predominance between bilateral and multilateral, the focus on regional alliances (BRICS) and partnerships with the Global South (which often involve bilateral agreements and group cooperation initiatives) and the Health Silk Route indicate a hybrid approach.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 23:46:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Forum | Secretary-General says it has never discussed widening to Hispanic countries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/30/forum-macau-secretario-geral-diz-que-nunca-se-discutiu-alargamento/</link><description>In an interview with Lusa agency, the secretary general of the Macau Forum, Ji Xianzheng, assured that “never discussed” the widening of action to Hispanic countries, but that to realize the will already stated by the government of Sam Hou Fai will have to be the authorities to decide a new direction to the cooperation strategy
 
The Secretary-General of the Macau Forum stated that the institution “never discussed” the creation of an entity to extend to Hispanic countries to promote economic cooperation similar to those that provide the connection between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
“Within the Macao Forum, we have never discussed this topic,” said the Forum Secretary-General for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries Ji Xianzheng.
The official acknowledged that, "in society, there were some conversations to discuss or address the possibility of promoting more contact and cooperation with Spanish -language countries, but at the Forum level we have never addressed this theme."
The Macao executive announced in mid -April the intention of creating a center to promote economic services between China and the Portuguese and Spanish languages in the neighboring special Economic Zone of Hengqin.
The idea is to provide companies in Hispanic countries services in the “linguistic, legal, fiscal, verification of compliance with norms, formation, arbitration and mediation”, according to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong.
Days earlier, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, had also announced the intention of “promoting exchange and cooperation” through Macao between China and the universe of Spanish -speaking countries.
Although Macau wants to widen focus to Castilian -speaking countries, “the forum will remain the forum for China and Lusophony countries,” said Ji Xianzheng. The secretary general clarified that the institution that directs "can contribute contributions to the greater opening of Macao in international cooperation", as is the intention announced by the new government of MSAR.
Complementary forum
Personally, the secretary general has ensured that he had “pleasing to work with all parties,” but stressed that this is a “decision that is up to central governments to make” and that the forum was never contacted in this regard.
"Yes, I worked in Latin America, Spain, nine years in Madrid and Caracas. But this is not a decision of personal interest, it is up to politicians to make the decision," he said, explaining that the idea will be to promote the relationship between Macao and Brazil and then to other Latin American countries, as well as expanding the relationship with Portugal to Spain.
"There is no limit. The Macao Forum is complementary. It does not restrict any promotion of the cooperation of the other parts," he said.
According to the Macao Government Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai admitted on June 21 that he postponed a trip to Portugal, scheduled for July, and should also pass through Spain and the European Union headquarters in Brussels.
Bad interpretations
In the same interview with Lusa, the secretary general of the Macao Forum imputed to national governments the responsibility for conducting economic development and cooperation policies, stressing that the institution “has no investment projects”.
Ji Xianzheng attributes criticism to the Macao Forum to an wrong interpretation regarding the body's mission. "The forum is a mechanism of cooperation between central governments. Many people think it is to the secretariat that it is up to the execution of policies, but we have a limited number of people," added Ji.
"The secretariat has no investment projects, is a mechanism for preparing the ministerial conference, connecting with governments, is not a promotion agency. It has not been thought of, connects with the promotion agencies. We are four people sent by China and one delegate for each country," he said.
At the last ministerial conference, in April 2024, then Portuguese Economy Minister Pedro Reis argued that the Portuguese Language China-Parais Cooperation and Development Fund should bet more on small and medium enterprises (SMEs).
The Cooperation Fund was created in 2013 by the China Development Bank and the Macao Industrial and Commercial Development Fund, with a thousand million dollars, of which about 60 percent have already been invested, according to the secretary general.
Action plans
Ji Xianzheng has admitted that SMEs are "a difficult theme for any government" and that "international cooperation for the promotion of development and cooperation of small and medium enterprises is even more difficult. It is a topic that is being debated daily worldwide." But admitted, "here, little."
"But it is stipulated in the action plan [2024-2026]. It is up to central governments and commerce chambers, promotion agents, to work together to do this. The secretariat assumes responsibility as authorized by the central governments, specifically, in the activities program," he said.
Politicians from various countries, including Portugal, Angola and Mozambique, have appealed to a change in the rules of the fund's candidacy. Current rules require, for example, that candidate projects have a minimum investment of five million dollars, and the fund only covers 20 percent of total investment, referring the rest to governments or companies.
Ji Xianzheng said the new fund's new direction "is committed to promoting a broader investment, with better coverage for all forum countries, [relatively] to projects that have a strategic or significant impact on the socioeconomic development of participating countries."
According to the secretary general, "the terms of application [of the rules of access to the background] will be more flexible and the forms of application will also be more diverse." “Instead of being just direct investment, they are also studying ways to apply the fund, in cooperation with other funds or with other financial institutions,” he gave as an example.
"This fund has an operation according to market rules. It is not a humanitarian aid fund. Therefore, it has to guarantee the minimum return of benefit. But, on that, they are very open to study, in this case, the conditions of each project," added Ji Xianzheng, but to give examples of "flexibilization of the rules."
Regarding the approximation of the China universe and countries of the Iberian Peninsula, already cemented in official speeches, economist Maria Fernanda Ilhéu, president of the Seda's New Route Association, told HM, earlier this month, that this intention is “very objective and pragmatic and can be summarized to the Macao economy diversification project, for which companies and investors are not only in Macao, but also from Macao, but also from Macao, but also from countries, but countries Portuguese Language ”.
"But the fact is that companies and institutions from Portuguese-speaking countries are not being effective in responding to this need for Macao. Therefore, widening companies and Spanish institutions this invitation to cooperation seems logical to me," the economist said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Isabel Rio Novo, author of the biography of Luís de Camões: “Time in Macau was of tranquility”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/26/isabel-rio-novo-autora-da-biografia-de-luis-de-camoes-tempo-em-macau-foi-de-tranquilidade/</link><description>It will be launched tomorrow, at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, the biography of Luís de Camões, by Isabel Rio Novo. In an interview with HM, the author unravels some secrets about the poet's life in Macau, a period of relative calm in the middle of a almost always turbulent life
 
Why did you decide to get in the writing of another biography of Camões?
It is true that Luis Vaz de Camões has been biographed many times over 500 years. However, 50 years ago there was no biography about him. From my point of view and the editor, Camões deserved a more current biography that revised all kinds of prejudices, seeking known sources, the uncovered information research and where the rereading of all previous works were rereading. This biography is not only a summary, but also the reinterpretation of what has been known, but which had rarely been related. The book also brings some new data with some documentation that was discovered.
How was your relationship with the writing of Camões born?
I fell in love and went to those young readers who was not tormented with Camões. On the contrary, I liked it soon and let myself be seduced by Camões Lyric. I am from the areas of comparative literature and history, and in this sense I always understood the dimension and importance of the work of Camões.
And what are they?
It is a work and an author of its time and its time, which was extraordinary, with the Renaissance, Humanism and the travels of navigation. But at the same time, it is a work that is the product of an outstanding literary genius, one that we can tell a handful in the history of universal literature.
What camões we find in this biography?
I tried to go to the bottom, remove layers of the meaning that these 500 years were adding to Camões, in the sense that each season read its Camões and produced its interpretation. I wanted to discover the substrate, the man of flesh and bone he lived and wrote 500 years ago.
He was a man suffered, with many financial difficulties.
He was a man with a complex and difficult relationship with reality, not only of his time, but also with reality [itself]. The theme of the time, the disconcerting of the world, how society seems to work instead of what should work, being a literary topic of the Renaissance, it was something Camões felt personal and genuinely.
How?
He lived a series of disagreements, of extreme experiences. Suffice it to say that you have been stuck several times and for various reasons. He made great trips at a time when these were absolutely risky, long, and complicated enterprises. Camões was involved in military expeditions, and almost all his life was soldered. But this set of experiences allowed him to be almost everything someone could be at the time he lived.
He was one of the most traveled authors of the time, having been in Brazil, Goa…
Yes. Even the connection to Macau, which is contested by some scholars, but not by me… I am persuaded, given the existing documentation and indirect testimonies, which Camões passed through China with the position of Dead and Missing Provider. When this happened, albeit very incipiently, the Portuguese establishment in China, which was already Macao. It is not known whether Camões held this position assigned to him by Viceroy D. Francisco Coutinho, if he was exactly assigned to be a provider during the trip, or a provider at Macao's establishment. But what he knew from China was surely this little warehouse that Portugal had achieved, at a lot of cost, with great difficulty and after many attempts to obtain in China.
What did a deceased provider?
Whenever a Portuguese died in the East, a soldier or merchant, it was necessary to ensure the rights of the heirs, the families who were normally in Portugal. The provider had to identify the deceased, his naturalness, origin and make the heirs known. He also had to keep the deceased's assets before they were stolen, auction them, keep the coins that would result in, and then take it all to Lisbon. It was a process that, if it went well, took many months, because it was necessary to send this money to the authorities of Goa who later sent him in the career from India to Lisbon.
Can we talk about a period of stability in Camões's life in Macau?
Yes. Until this appointment as a deceased provider, everything Camões knew from the East had been as a soldier. As soon as Goa [1553] arrives weeks later in a first military expedition. We know why: Not because I had some war appeal, but because only participating in expeditions earned your welding. Although everyone said that the soldiers lived very poorly, the welding was what Camões had to survive. The time lived in Macao, when he was free from soldier obligations, was a time of tranquility regarding subsistence, which was assured. He had some time and calm to continue the work with "the Lusíadas." More than that, as much as the sources allow to deduce, Camões met in Macau a phase of balance in terms of personal and loving life, as, on the return trip, he brought with him, according to the testimony of Diogo do Couto, a Chinese girl.
Dinamene.
This was the term used by the chronicler. We don't know if it would be a Chinese or Asian girl. This girl with whom Camões lived maritally was someone who liked it very much, according to the testimony of Diogo do Couto. But Dinamene would certainly not be her name, as it was a mythological name that, by the way, Camões used in her lyric, even before she boarded the East. Chinese girls with whom soldiers and merchants in Macao lived amanced were baptized and received a Christian name. Therefore, Dinamene would even have a Christian and Portuguese name. But as we do not know her name, and if we are aware that we use a kind of metaphor, we can call it Dinamene.
She dies later on a trip and makes Camões very shaken.
On Macao's return trip to Goa, probably at the end of his mandate as a provider, Camões suffers the celebrated wreck, in which he loses the personal assets he had ease, including the assets of the deceased that he was guardian, and this will bring him complications. It also suffers the loss of dynamine. The wreck went with some in the seas of China, probably by the mouth of the Mekong River.
Considers unlikely to have lost part of "the Lusíadas."
The first biographers say Camões was saved from this wreck with a board. It is not unreasonable that he managed to save the manuscript of the Lusíadas on this board. But it is also no excluding that Camões knew his poem by heart. The memory of people in the sixteenth century was different. They were very used to keeping things from memory. And we know, because the proof is obtained in the work of Camões, that it had an extraordinary memory. I have a way to prove it, of course, that Camões is one of the rare authors who knew his poem by heart.
Do you think Camões had a lower life to his true talent?
Undoubtedly. According to a too extensive set of concordant testimonies, he dies poor, even in miserable conditions, and according to an eyewitness, without having a blanket with which he covered himself. On the other hand, Camões was known to follow the publication of the Lusíadas, who were commented and read [in the poet's life time]. We have the testimony of Faria de Sousa, one of the first biographers of Camões, which says that when he passed the streets, people stop and pointed. Camões also had a figure that stood out, with a leaked eye and using a pale. By then, I would be quite sick, using crutches. But there is a set of poets, which is very unreliable that they did not know Camões, who never refer to them. There are, on the other hand, other humanists, such as Pedro Magalhães Gândavo, who from the outset praises him as the prince of Portuguese poets.
But the king gives him a tendency for deeds provided and the publication of "The Lusíadas."
This famous tendency, which should not be a big deal, because all ancient biographers say it was derisive, is attributed to him as a kind of military reform, because of the 17 years of service in the East, and not as a reward for the publication of "The Lusíadas." D. Sebastião's mercy letter, which attributes him the title of nobleman knight, had no repercussion in practice, but gave him 15 thousand reais. [The publication of “the Lusíadas”] was an additional argument [for the letter] and not the main argument. This leads us to believe that D. Sebastião will not even have read or heard “the Lusíadas”, will have received indirect information, favorable about the poem.
How did the process of editing “Os Lusíadas” occurred?
It was an event, because both the press and the books that were published a year were a very small amount. In the year in which “the Lusíadas” are published were the only work of non -religious caress [to be edited]. To fund the edition, it is more than likely that Camões had the support of a patron, probably D. Manuel de Portugal, from the Condes do Vimioso family. Getting the work was a press was a mere and complicated process, as it had to go through the prior examination of the civil authorities, the royal authority and the censorship of the Inquisition. The resident of the Holy Office does not only let the book pass, but to make an amount of almost unprecedented compliments in the license that authorizes the publication of the work. If we go to the opinions emitted by the same rear, there is no other work on which he is as compliments as it was with the epic of Camões.
In Indonesia, he befriended a slave on the island of Java.
Camões was, at least once, on the island of Ternate, Indonesia, in the archipelago of molucas, at a time when there were conflicts motivated by an extremely cruel Portuguese captain towards the king or sultan of Ternate, which originated a kind of war between the Portuguese and the places. Camões has a song that describes the island of Ternate. We do not know if it was at this time, or in another passage to the Far East, that Camões turned on to a Jaú, or Javanese, but could not be exactly from the Far East, but a freed slave who had been linked by friendship to Camões. And this is because in one of the first biographies of Camões it reads that Jaú, with the Christian name António, asked for alms at night. This freedom of movements of a slave indicates that he would probably be a freed slave. He asked for alms to Camões, for himself and the mother of Camões, with whom Camões will have lived in recent years of life.</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 23:30:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. He even received an inscription on Chinese, and even a Chinese pavilion was built on his sanctuary. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even He showed a marked tendency to moralize, and epitomously his thinking in masterful sentences.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the appropriate place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
What do you talk about is economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | FIA has already defined what the F4 World Cup will be like</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/25/gp-fia-ja-definiu-como-sera-a-taca-do-mundo-de-f4/</link><description>The Macao Grand Prix hosts the first edition of the FIA Formula 4 World Cup, between November 13 and 16 this year. The International Automobile Federation has published the Sports Regulation, which reveals some details about what will be the latest cup in the world integrated into the 72nd Macau Grand Program
 
Registration for the Formula 4 Macao Race - Formula 4 World Cup of the International Automobile Federation (FIA) is open until July 30, and FIA is the selection of the pilots who will participate. FIA responsible will have been pre-selected by the best Formula 4 national championship riders, also encouraging all the pilots interested in directly contacting the FIA and providing details of their sports history to be considered.
The final list of twenty pilots will be confirmed through an official invitation letter, taking into account the current classification of the pilots in the respective championships. The final selection should only be made public in mid -October, as is tradition in the guide circuit test.
At a time when behind the scenes, it is spoken of the possibility of increasing the minimum age of formula 4 to 16 years, the sports regulation stipulates that all pilots must be at least 15 years old, and the birthday is binding. An inscribed pilot may not have participated in more than two races of a championship with any type of monolugar that has been conceived and/or built to achieve a power-to-weight ratio of less than 3.0 kg/hp, which prevents participation in this riders running regional formula seasons or Formula 3.
The sports regulation does not specify technical details, but in previous communications, the FIA had already confirmed that Mintimes - organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship - will be the “unique operator” of the race, together with FFSA (Fédération Française Du Sport Automobile (FFSA), responsible for the world's cup technical support. In practice, all competitors will use Mygale M21-F4 singlesules, recently re-baptized as Ligier JS F422.
These formulas, equipped with 1.3 -liter Turbo Renault engines, will be rented to teams from the interior of China and operated by a single technical team - the same that organizes the French F4 Championship. Pirelli will be the exclusive tire supplier, as is the case with the Macao Grand Prix of Regional Formula and the FIA GT World Cup.
Although the official time of the event has not yet been released, it is known that the World Cup will feature a qualification race played over 8 laps, or at most 60 minutes, most likely on Saturday. The main race will be held on Sunday, with 10 laps or, equally, a maximum of 60 minutes. Prior to that, a 40 -minute free training session will take place, followed by a qualification session with the same duration.
PATACA AND POINTS
About 350,000 patacas in monetary awards will be distributed to the competitors present in this first cup of the world, with the winner of the main race to raise eight thousand US dollars. As a curiosity, all participants will receive three hundred dollars of participation-the same value attributed to the pole-position of Saturday's qualification race and the rider who reaches the highest tip speed during the event.
More important than the monetary awards, the FIA Formula 4 World Cup winner on the streets of Macau will win two points for the super license - points that may be decisive to access the restricted Formula 1 world. The winner will also be forced to attend the FIA awards ceremony, which will take place on December 12 in Tashkentão, USBekistan.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 05:01:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Lamborghini | Charles Leong returns to the Academy of Young Pilots</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/20/lamborghini-charles-leong-regressa-a-academia-de-jovens-pilotos/</link><description>The Lamborghini Squadra Corso, the Automobili Lamborghini competition division, will give Macau pilot a new opportunity for Macao Charles Leong Hon Chio, who was again selected to join the Italian -brand prestigious youth academy, the “Young Driver Program”
 
Charles Leong, who participates for the second year in a row in the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia, by SJM team Theodore Racing, currently leads the Pro category, with four wins in six races already played. This weekend, the territory pilot travels to South Korea to compete in the fourth race of the Sant'Agata Bolognese builder's Asian competition season, a small locality in the Emilia-Romanha region in northern Italy, between Modena and Bologna.
In a statement, the transalpina brand made known that, in all, selodes were pre-selected pilots of the various Super Trofeo championships and five of the various international GT3 championships, including Portuguese Rodrigo Testa, for the annual Lamborghini Squadra Corso program, which focuses on both track and outside performance. The twenty -one pilots will be accompanied and evaluated throughout the season, with specific analysis of their progression, consistency, experience, professionalism and ability to provide technical feedback. In addition, five additional pilots are part of Lamborghini's young professional pilots, receiving direct support from the factory in Sant'Agata Bolognese and Scola Federale ACI Sport, an entity managed by the Italian Federation.
The big news for the 2025 edition of the Young Driver Program is the selection process: it failed to settle only in age criteria, focusing on the most impressive pilots of the first two rounds of the year, based on a classification coefficient covering the three continental championships. The pilots were evaluated by Scoola Federale ACI-Sport chief instructor Niki Cadei, in collaboration with YDP consultants and official Lamborghini drivers Andrea Caldarelli (North America), who has already competed at the Macao Grand Prix, and Marco Mapelli (Europe and Asia), taking into account several performance indicators.
The results of qualification training and racing are thoroughly analyzed, such as track conduct, the pilot's post-end reports and the technical feedback provided to engineers and Squadra corse's technical team. The average score determines the final list of pilots selected for the decisive phase. A group of these young pilots will participate in a dedicated training camp at Lamborghini headquarters in Sant'Agata Bolognese, as well as at the final selection session in Misano. The best of the session will then receive support from Lamborghini Squadra Corso for the 2026 season.
Future is played in Italy
Among Super Trofeo Junior pilots, ten compete in the European series, while the rest come from the American and Asian championships. In addition to Macao's 24 -year -old pilot in Asian representation, Lamborghini also chose Singapore's Ethan Brown and Ireland's Alex Denning, which this year shares the steering wheel with Charles Leong to join this program.
Charles Leong will be evaluated throughout the season, and the final selection - whether or not to integrate Lamborghini's youth professional riders program - will be made in November at the Italian circuit of Misano, after the traditional closing of the Season of the various Super Trofeo, during the Lamborghini world endings. It is recalled that the winner of the Macao Formula 4 Grand Prix in 2020 and 2021 was part of this program last year, but was not selected. At the time, the final assessment took place at the Jerez circuit in Spain - an unknown layout, unlike his opponents.</description><pubDate>2025-07-20 15:23:35</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FR World Cup will have a new car in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/06/gp-taca-do-mundo-de-fr-tera-novo-carro-em-2026/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) has recently revealed some details about the future of the Regional Formula (FR), the discipline that currently gives body to the Macao Grand Prix and which, from 2026, will finally have a new monolugar - faster and more safe
 
Initially baptized by FIA as F3 Regional, the now designated regional formula (FR) is above the Formula 4 Formula 4 National Competitions and FIA Championship, which, in turn, supports the FIA Formula 2 Championship and Formula 1. Last year, the FIA decided that this category was the one that best filed the Guide Circuit, thus ending four decades of Formula 3 Macao Award.
Last week, the regulator of world motorsport and the Italian national sports association has jointly presented the future monoligue that will compete in the European regional FIA (FREC in English) regional formula championship and will succeed the current freka. The fact that the acronym has lost the letter “A” is due to the exit of the Alpine brand as a partner and engine supplier to the championship. FRECA premiered in 2019, succeeding the Formula Renault Eurocup. In recent seasons, more than 160 pilots, representing 44 nationalities and 22 teams, participated in the championship. This category has gained importance in the FIA monologene pyramid, having as old pilots former champion Andrea Kimi Antonelli, Isack Hadjar, Gabriel Bortoleto and Franco Colapinto-all of them now militate in Formula 1.
The competition will have the FIA support seal and should be the largest supplier of teams and pilots for the FR World Cup of the Macao Grand Prix from next year. FIA involvement in the competition is intended to generate more revenues for it, something that may have reflexes on the price scale. The FR championships in the Americas and Japan, as well as the FIA -certified trophies in the Middle East and Oceania will continue, and progressively will introduce the new car produced in Italy.
FIA President Mohammed Ben Suulayem believes this project "will create a stronger and more support for young pilots. With the full support of the FIA regions and a clear progression vision, we are taking an important step to ensure the future of junior monoliga pyramid." Former Ralis pilot and today maximum leader of automobile sports, who was recently in the territory for the FIA general assembly, said that “accessibility, international credibility and cost efficiency are at the center of this initiative.”
New car promises more
The new Tatuus T-326, the second-generation FR monolugar, is equipped with a 3-cylinder and 1.6 liter Toyota engine, which debits 270 horsepower and 360 Nm of torque, specially adapted and prepared by ATM-Autotechnic Motori. The T-326 represents a natural evolution of the T-318 model, the Tatuus monolugar that defined most FR championships worldwide and says goodbye to the big stages next November, during the weekend of the Macao Grand Prix. The second edition of FR's FR World Cup will continue to use the Tatuus T-318 Monolugar, motorized by a 1.75-liter Turbo Alpha Romeo block, also prepared by ATM-Autotechnic Motori, but the Italian brand has failed to manufacture.
The future car, which will use a new special tire built by Pirelli, will have a fully redesigned aerodynamic profile, shaped by the new FIA technical regulations for the category and inspired by the latest trends in the top categories of single -molding. The result is a general increase in performance, better aerodynamic efficiency and reduction of turbulence effect, which will facilitate overtaking.
Main improvements include weight reduction, optimized direction rack and magazine suspension, offering greater lightness and ease of driving. Security remains a key pillar in all Italian tatus projects, and this car is no exception. Chassis further increased its impact resistance. Crucial elements such as front and rear impact absorption structures, anti-intrusion panels and roll bar have been updated to meet the latest safety standards. In addition to safety, the cockpit is designed to maximize pilot's comfort and ergonomics, welcoming both men and women in a wider range of heights, ensuring the best conditions to compete on track.</description><pubDate>2025-08-06 23:59:42</pubDate></item><item><title>Nürburgring Nordschleife is a new favorite stage of Chinese brands</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/08/01/nurburgring-nordschleife-e-novo-palco-predilecto-das-marcas-chinesas/</link><description>In the middle of the Eifel forest - in German, Eifelwald - Two cars with Chinese enrollment are parked in front of a hotel unit. The scenario appears to be intriguing at first glance, but it is not.
Nürburgring Nordschleife, in Rhineland-Palatinado, already close to the Belgium and Luxembourg border, has become the favorite stage of new Chinese automobile builders to show the world that they can also measure forces with their European, American and Asian rivals with regard to high performance vehicles.
Chinese automotive industry bet is strongly concentrated in NEVs - “New Energy Vehicles” - as part of the strategy for reducing pollution, reducing dependence on fossil fuels and boosting innovation in the automotive industry. China represented almost two thirds of global electric vehicle sales in 2024, and their builders, all relatively new, discuss Taco the Taco with the large traditional builders a piece of this appetizing market.
It is undisputed that the growth of sales of this type of vehicles in the world has not been accompanied at the same speed by the evolution of technology applicable to automobile sport, especially with regard to electric vehicles (EVs).
The World Formula World Championship and is the only truly global competition for electric vehicles, after the fiasco and the premature death of the FIA - FIA etcouring world cup. With no alternatives to affirm their everyday products on the tracks, Chinese brands headed in weight to Nürburgring Nordschleife, known to be one of the favorite places of European car manufacturers to test high performance cars.
The “green hell”, a name given by the legendary pilot Jackie Stewart due to its difficulty and the density of the surrounding forest, is a circuit with over 20 kilometers and 170 curves, combining fast lines, technical sections and sharp unenforcement. Many return records are measured here for sports and super -sports car cars, making Nordschleife an unavoidable reference to car performance.
Chapters for History
In 2017, Nio became known to the western world when it established a record with its EP9 electric supercar. The vehicle completed a circuit of 20.8 km in 6 minutes and 45.90 seconds, becoming the fastest production car at the time to travel the famous Germanic layout.
This feat has evidenced the ability of Nio and Chinese industry to compete with brands established in the high performance cars segment. Two years later, Lynk &amp; Co, the first Chinese brand to win a race in the guide circuit, with model 03 Cyan Concept, a high performance version of the Sedan 03, reached a time back in 7 minutes and 20,143 seconds, setting a new record for four -door cars.
Brands such as Zeekr, MG and Lotus passed the old stage of the Formula 1 German Grand Prix, until, in 2024, Xiaomi arrived with a crash. With a production version of the SU7 Ultra, it registered a time of 7 minutes and 4.957 seconds, surpassing rivals such as Porsche Taycan Turbo GT and Rimac Snowra. To keep up with the sales success of your car, the electronic technology brand was even further: Last month, the Su7 Ultra Prototype, built in partnership with Prodrive, reached an impressive 6-minute and 22.091 seconds, becoming the third fastest car of all time on the circuit, behind only the Porsche 919 Hybrid and Volkswagen ID.R.R.
These results from Xiaomi had a significant impact, both in the western and home press, as well as proof of the international affirmation of an industry that wants to be an undisputed leader with regard to Nev vehicles. On the other hand, Xiaomi took the opportunity to “surf the wave” and launched in the market a special limited edition of Su7 -all -how.
More will come
Nürburgring Nordschleife is part of the Chinese auto industry vocabulary and the trend is for an even stronger presence of Chinese brands in the coming years on the German track.
"I believe it was the decision of Xiaomi that brought greater attention to the definition of records back in Nürburgring," explained Chinese journalist Bruno Qi to HM. “With a huge media influence in China and a high profile CEO like Jun Law, Xiaomi attracted a significant focus on this scenario. After Nio's success, this was another strong performance of a Nürburgring high -performance electric vehicle.”
Xiaomi, which already names a bend of the German circuit, may want to improve its time back, while other Chinese brands seek to follow the trend - even to show off on a respected and good memories.
"Brands like Yangwang (BYD's luxury brand) have also sent their models for time attempts around," says Chinese publication journalist Bec Motorsport. “I think Chinese auto builders have now found a relevant opportunity to demonstrate the capabilities of their high performance electrical platforms, and this strategy is already helping to boost sales.” Also, at the end of the day, what weighs is what is sold.</description><pubDate>2025-08-01 01:14:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Great Bay Race learned more pilots for the GP</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/11/corrida-da-grande-baia-apurou-mais-pilotos-para-o-gp/</link><description>The GT Cup Races - Great Bay Race, integrated at the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix, ended with a double journey at the Pingtan Speed Festival last weekend of June. Of the twenty -eight vacancies assigned by the first two GT Cup races, only one Macao pilot got a direct entrance at the great sports event of November.
Following the success of the two races played under the China Formula 1 Grand Prix, both 30 -minute races of the GT4 Chinese Championship had a total of 21 participants at the event held at the International Circuit of Lago Ruyi in Pingtan. This picturesque track, located in Fujian province, replaced the Zhuhai International Circuit, initially included in the provisional calendar released in January, but did not confirm the holding of his event.
In Pingtan's semiurban layout, Chinese pilot Han Lichao won both races behind his Toyota GR Supra GT4 EVO2. In two very lively races, Kevin Leong Ian Veng (BMW M4 GT4) was the only Macau pilot scoring, having reached a sixth and eighth place, respectively.
Although only one Pilot of the Misrem has guaranteed the direct determination, it is possible that more riders in the territory will align on the GT - Great Bay Race, integrated in the Macao Grand Prix. This is because only 21 pilots scored in these four races, which means that even if all these pilots are signed up for the guide circuit race, seven vacancies will still be filled.
In addition to Kevin Leong, seven other pilots from Macau - Miguel Law, Wong Cheng Tou, Fok Wai Ming, Lao Kim Hou, IP Un Hous, Wong Wai Hong and Law Kit Meng - participated in at least one of the two qualification events and may be repaired for local test if the sports committee's sports committee of the Macau Grand Prix so.
Among the riders are some known names of the region's motorsport, such as Darryl O'Young, double winner of the Macau GT Cup; Chen Weian, 12 -hour separate winner; Liu Kaishun, Chinese F4 runner-up; Daniel Lu, former Champion of the Porsche Carrera Asia Cup; or Luo Kailuo, winner of the GT Cup - Great Bay Race at Macao's 70th Grand Prix.
It's not over yet
This debut season, Sro GT Cup still has two more pointed events, the last, naturally, played in the iconic Guide Circuit. The competition, which has the support of the Macao General Automobile Association - China (AAMC), has reached its intermediate point, and the struggle for the title is in the red. Prior to the mandatory visit to Macau, from 17 to 19 October, the GT4 category cars will compete at the first event held on the streets of Yizhuang, in Beijing.
Beijing's Citadino Circuit is one of the most anticipated auto events in the Popular Republic of China and represents an excellent opportunity for Macao GT4 riders - and not only to prepare for the big challenge that are the curves and countercurns of the territory layout.</description><pubDate>2025-07-11 00:45:06</pubDate></item><item><title>TCR China | André Couto participated in the Zhejiang race</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/07/01/tcr-china-andre-couto-participou-na-prova-de-zhejiang/</link><description>Over the weekend, André Couto had an unexpected return to the TCR China Championship, in what was his first race of this season. The rider of the sgas showed that "who knows, never forgets", despite having had a troubled passage through the Zhejiang International Circuit
The Portuguese pilot residing in Macao, who has not competed since November last year-when he played the World Lamborghini Super Trofeo World Finals, having won the title in the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia Pro-AM category-received a last-minute invitation from MacPro Racing Team to conduct one of the Honda Civic Fl5 TCR Team in the third race of the Chinese Championship. TCR.
Without any prior training, André Couto came back to sit in a car he already knew, also with a technical structure that was familiar to him. By 2023, the territory pilot had already played some TCR China events with this set, then at the service of the official team Dongfeng Honda Racing Team, showing a progress right from the beginning.
"Free training did not go wrong, but in qualification a less attentive pilot hit me on my first departure lap to the track. He hit me from behind and did not realize why. Damaged me the rear, dislocated the convergence and the car was crooked. Hm. "Still, I qualified myself in fourth in Q1, five tenths of the first, which, with the car in the conditions it was, was not bad. The car had potential."
In Q2, due to the damage, the Japanese car “became much harder to guide” and Couto ended in tenth. However, this ended up having a positive effect: “With the reversal of the starting grid, the tenth place of Q2 allowed me to start first to the second race.”
The first race, played on Saturday on the shaoxing track, did not go as well as the pilot wanted, not being able to follow the official links, nor the best Honda and Hyundai. "I ended up eighth. The car was not as good as expected and we found that there was a damaged damper, still from the crash in the qualification, which was exchanged for the Sunday race."
Inglorius Sunday
In the 20 Sunday round race, André Couto had everything to shine as he departed from pole-position and Honda finally seemed in a position to fight for the first places. "On the way back, the car was good. I didn't feel strange anymore and I was optimistic."
The idea was to get well to distance themselves from the fastest competitors in the first laps and then manage the race with new tires. However, it all faded quickly when it was wrapped by Wu Yi Fan right in the brake for the first curve.
“That was my mission, but I couldn't,” acknowledged the winner of the 2000 Macao Grand Prix. “He hit me on the first curve and the car was damaged. Sports commissioners, but that does not change the fact that I have given up. ”
Com a direcção danificada do Honda, André Couto não teve outra opção senão abandonar. “Fiquei um bocado desiludido porque tinha esperanças de conseguir um bom resultado para a MacPro Racing Team que me tinha dado um bom carro. Íamos arrancar em primeiro… mas as corridas são assim.”</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:26:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>