<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>India requires surveillance of the weapons of Pakistan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/111705/</link><description>India demanded yesterday that Pakistan nuclear weapons be placed “under surveillance” from the International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA), days after the most serious confrontation between the two armies of the last two decades.
"The nuclear arsenal of Pakistan should be placed under the supervision of the AIEA. I mean this very clearly," said Indian Defense Minister Rajnath Singh, quoted by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
During a visit to the Armed Forces Headquarters in Srinagar, the main city of Caxemira Indiana, the minister wondered whether nuclear weapons will be safe "in the hands of an uncontrollable and irresponsible nation." Pakistan did not react immediately. The two countries with nuclear weapons were involved last week at the deadliest military confrontation since the 1999 war.
On the night from May 6th to 7th, India fired missiles at places in Pakistan which, according to Nova Delh, housed members of the 'jihadist' group suspected of the attack that killed 26 people on April 22 at Caxemira Indiana.
Pakistan, which denied any responsibility for the attack, immediately retaliated. For four days, the two armies exchanged artillery shots and missile attacks and drones, feeding serious fears of a large -scale conflict. To a general surprise, US President Donald Trump announced an immediate ceasefire on Saturday, which was immediately confirmed by both parties.
No thanks
The group of old personalities known as the "Elders" defended yesterday in Tokyo Nuclear Non-Proliferation. Former United Nations Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon released the warning to southern Asia.
"There is a possibility that the international security system will be completely destroyed if India or Pakistan use nuclear weapons," he warned. Former Colombian President Juan Manuel Santos questioned where the UN was led by Portuguese António Guterres during the conflict.
The truce have been respected on the border between the two countries, but rhetoric remains very aggressive. "India will not tolerate the nuclear blackmail," said Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi on Monday night.
India categorically denied news of an attack on a Pakistani nuclear installation about 200 kilometers from the various cities recently hit by Indian missiles. Indian Foreign Ministry spokesman Randhir Jaiswal secured on Tuesday that India's military operation remained conventional. Throughout the crisis, Pakistan repeated that the nuclear option was never considered. "It would be inconceivable and stupid because it would endanger 1.6 billion people," army spokesman General Ahmed Chaudhry said.
Death accounts
India has atomic weapons since the 1990s, transported by Missiles Earth-Terra in the intermediate range. Pakistan has Nuclear Land and Short and Medium Air Range, and performed the first tests in 1998.
The Pakistani army said the Indian attacks killed 40 civilians and lost 13 soldiers. Already Nova Deli, he reported the death of 16 civilians and five soldiers in Indian territory. Despite the unfolding on the ground, India and Pakistan are adamant and claim that they will not lower the guard. "If another terrorist attack targets India, we will respond firmly," Modi warned.
In a telephone conversation with Guterres on Wednesday, Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif said he was "concerned about the provocative and inflammatory statements of India."
India and Pakistan compete for Caxemira's sovereignty since the bloody division when independence in 1947. The fate of the territory of Himalayas, a village mostly by Muslims, gave rise to several wars between the two countries. Since 1989, the Indian side has been the scene of a separatist insurrection that has already caused tens of thousands of dead.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>CCAC | Promised Righteous and Stable Business Environment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/ccac-prometido-ambiente-empresarial-integro-e-estavel/</link><description>The commissioner against corruption, Ieong Seong, has ensured that the institution will contribute to “a righteous, fair, stable and predictable business environment” to allow “companies to invest and develop without worries”. This is how the Commissioner reacted to the visit to Macao de Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao Working Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office with the Council of State.
The Commissioner, through a statement, stated that the speech of director Xia Baolong presented "clear demands on the future development of Macao and the contribution to the construction of the country and that at the same time had a guiding meaning for the work of CCAC."
According to Ao Ieong Seong's report, Xia Baolong left as expectations for the business sector to promote the "spirit of fighting" and "Union of the Homeland, Hong Kong and Macau". In addition, Xia has indicated entrepreneurs that she has to "maintain a firm confidence in development, consolidating and expanding business in Hong Kong and Macau", while expected to enjoy "their own advantages to overcome the challenges and widen the opening abroad and to affirm themselves in the international panorama."
According to Ieong Seong, the interior ruler also expects local entrepreneurs to tell "the world the story of Hong Kong, Macau and China, with a firm position."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:16:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Job fairs offer 77 vacancies in stores and hospitality</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/dsal-feiras-de-emprego-oferecem-77-vagas-em-lojas-e-hotelaria/</link><description>Today open the registration for three sessions of employment fairs, which will be held on May 22 and 23 for the sectors of the retail hotel and trade, according to information released yesterday by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). Interested parties can apply until noon next Wednesday and apply for the 77 job vacancies.
The first session, scheduled for the morning of May 22, will provide 11 jobs for “Hotel W Macau - Studio City”, for the positions of Customer Customer Contact Center, Customer Service Agent, Guest, Elementary Level cook and spa receptionist.
In the afternoon of the same day, it is the turn of the luxury retail sales sector, with 16 vacancies for the “Giorgio Armani Macau Limited” and “Gucci” for the positions of store assistant, store supervisor, sales consultant and warehouse employee.
On the morning of May 23, 50 vacancies will be offered for store employees, warehouse employee and customer service employee at “Isa Boutique Limited” and “Isport Sporting Goods” stores.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:24:27</pubDate></item><item><title>"Flashmobs" this weekend in community neighborhoods</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/flashmobs-este-fim-de-semana-nos-bairros-comunitarios/</link><description>This weekend will take place the initiative “Culture to Your Door”, with 16 flashmobs in 12 local community neighborhoods, an event organized by the Cultural Institute (IC).
According to a note from the IC, flashmobs have five themes, namely theater, Cantonense Opera, martial arts, cinema and reading, intending to “bring rich cultural resources to community neighborhoods, nourishing culturally residents in their daily lives and reinforcing their sense of happiness”.
In the area of ​​theater, with the theme “Theater in More Local”, he presents himself “a magic trip to the stage”, in which the audience is intended to explore “different spaces of action, such as the Greek Ancient Amphitheater, the traditional Bambu de Macao Theater and modern theaters, through the format of interactive theater”.
With the theme “Cantonense Opera in Most Local” it is intended that “residents experience this precious art of intangible cultural heritage”, while with “more places in more local”, the “classic movements of Wing Chun on site are presented, where residents can also experience the basic movements under the guidance of instructors and understand the concepts of Chinese marial culture”.
Cinema and Reading
Already with "cinema in more local", "Flashmob" will "turn the community into an outdoor movie theater, where the public will be able to enjoy the documentary about the sector of Macao's" interpretation of images "cinematic exhibition, know the centenary history of industry and the development of cinema."
In turn, through the theme “Read in More Local”, the activity “Exchange one book for another” is carried out, which is also part of the “joint reading month throughout the city of Macau 2025”. Residents will be able to carry books that comply with the rules on site, selecting their favorites and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books, performing the circulation and sharing of reading resources in the community neighborhoods.
The “Culture at Your Door” activity takes place in several mornings and afternoon tomorrow and Sunday, in community or local neighborhoods such as the S. Lourenço Activities Center-Ajardinado Terrace, Taipa Central Park, Iao Da Orchid Square Terrace Leisure Zone, IP PAI VAN VAN VAN-LOUS GARDEN, Rotunda de Carlos da Maia, leisure zone of the Praceta de Venceslau de Morais, Urban of Areia Preta Park, leisure zone contiguous to edif. Wang Hoi and Wang Kin, leisure zone in the social neighborhood of Tamagnini Barbosa and Edf's leisure zone. Lok Yeong Fa Yuen.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:38:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Predicted stability in the second quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/economia-prevista-estabilidade-no-segundo-trimestre/</link><description>Macao's economic prosperity rate for the second quarter points to stability, but has imbalances in some indicators, such as the low confidence of Chinese consumers and the low value of game concessionaires actions
 
According to the latest predictions of Macao's economic prosperity rate, the local economy will remain stable in the second quarter, a prospect that Macao Economic Association analysts risk just risking to a short-term period.
The report released on Wednesday continues to reveal asymmetries in the evolution of the various indicators evaluated. Following the trends of the latest reports, the decrease in the purchasing power of Chinese tourists visiting Macao and the poor confidence of consumers from the interior of China continues to make black clouds over the economic perspectives of MSc. Another negative indicator, highlighted by the Macao Economic Association, is the continuation of the value of the game dealerships “curing at the low level for a long time”.
The prosperity rate also points out the weak demand for credit in the local economy. The macao banking resident loan ratio/deposits fell from 62.4 percent to 51.1 percent between the end of 2022 and last March, is indicated.
Analysts conclude that the smallest will of residents and companies by contracting loans "reflects a cautious attitude towards the current situation and economic perspectives." Although the MSar banking system has “widely liquidity”, funds were not actually converted into support for credit in the real economy, which indicates a lack of efficiency in capital affectation and confidence in investment.
The association led by former Deputy Joey Lao Vinca also the cooling in recent years in real estate and large-scale investment projects, as well as the high values ​​of Malparado credit, factors that further reduced the demand for bank loans.
Both sides
The association also indicates, on the other hand, that the volume of monetary mass broke a new historical record, exceeding the first time 810 billion patacas, an annual increase 8.8 percent in annual terms.
Another positive indicator concerns the number of visitors and hotels in hotels that remain at a “hot” level. Having warned of the impact of the trade war launched by Donald Trump, the analysts of the Macao Economic Association again enhanced the external environment as a destabilizing factor.
"In a context of weak search, insufficient dynamic economic growth and a restrictive financial environment and risks related to geopolitical and tariff disputes, Macao, as a micro-export-oriented economy, must be very aware of potential risk of falling their economic trends in the short and medium term," is indicated.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:23:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Budget Execution | Public revenues with a reduction of 5%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/execucao-orcamental-receitas-publicas-com-reducao-de-5/</link><description>In the first four months of the year, there was a 0.06 percent drop, to 29.8 billion patacas, from tax revenues on the game. In addition, there was an expense of 874.7 million patacas in “actions and other participation”
 
The current revenue of the MSAR budget presented a 4.95 percent reduction in the first four months of the year, compared to the same period of 2024, especially due to a drop in financial revenues, it was announced yesterday.
Current revenue between January and April was 34 billion Patacas, according to published "online" data by the Territory Finance Services Directorate (DSF). The main reason for the decrease was financial revenues, which went from billion in the first four months of 2024 to only six thousand patacas this year.
This heading corresponds to the results of the Macao monetary authority, the region's financial regulator, and includes investment and interest and dividend revenues. In addition, the data also reveal a drop of 0.06 percent, to 29.8 billion patacas in tax revenues, which still represented 84.7 percent of the total.
The six city game operators pay a 35 percent direct tax on the game's revenues, 2.4 percent for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development, and 1.6 percent delivered to the Macao, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic Foundation.
Expenses for explaining
Taxes on the game fell, although the Macau casinos registered total revenues of 76.5 billion patacas in the first four months of the year, more 0.8 percent than in the same period of 2024. Between January and April, Macau collected 30.2 percent of current revenue projected for 2025 in the region's budget, which is 112.6 billion.
On the contrary, public expense rose 2.6 percent in the first four months to 24 billion patacas, due to an expense of 874.7 million patacas in “actions and other appearances”. Lusa has asked DSF more information about this heading, but has not received any response so far.
On April 15, the new government leader, Sam Hou Fai, admitted to fear a budget deficit in 2025, due to the slowdown in the game's recipes. Macao ended April with a surplus in public accounts of 10.3 billion patacas, 18.5 percent less than in the same period last year.
Still, this value is already higher than the government's forecast for the year 2025: 6.83 billion patacas. Macao closed 2024 with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the one recorded the previous year.
The last exercise was the first since 2020, at the beginning of the pandemic, in which the territory was able to keep the accounts on positive land, something required by the basic law, without transfers from the financial reserve.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:18:55</pubDate></item><item><title>National Security | Alert for US -related risks and “western countries”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/seguranca-nacional-alerta-para-riscos-ligados-a-eua-e-paises-ocidentais/</link><description>The Secretary for Security has warned the population that the defense of national security is an obligation of all, and that it is necessary to maintain attention to “hegemonic acts” and defamations from the United States of America and Western countries
 
Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, considers that the population has to maintain the "spirit of struggle" and "not giving", in view of what "hegemonic acts" and defamations from the United States of America and Western countries. The message was left on Wednesday, on the secretary's portal, and appears following the visit to Macao de Xia Baolong, director of Hong Kong's work office and Macau of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Cabinet Director for Hong Kong and Macau affairs to the Council of State.
"Currently, given the accelerated evolution of centenary changes in the world and the most intense strategic competition between China and the United States of America, the risks that affect Macao's national security and social stability become increasingly serious," was written on the secretary's portal.
The message identifies the risks such as the “hegemonic acts of the US and Western countries” as well as “words and actions that destroy, defame and disturb Macao”, considering that “Macao society must identify the situation, maintain position firmly, cultivate the spirit of struggle, and cannot give in”.
Wong Sio Chak also warns that all residents are expected to act as national security guardians. "The defense of national security is the responsibility of all. All residents of Macao are the beneficiaries and guardians of national security, no one is left out," is bound. “The Society of Macao must remain united, have a firm confidence, convey the good tradition of love for the homeland and Macau, to enhance their own advantages, contribute to the construction of a strong country and the revitalization of the Chinese nation, and tell the story of 'one country, two systems',” he was added.
Hostile and criminals
At the same time, the ruler highlights the need to act in peacetime against “hostile and criminals” because it is more worth preventing. “We must predict possible dangers in peacetime, as it is better to prevent remedy,” he was written. "The Society of Macao should value the current favorable situation of stability and prosperity more, should be aware of the crises, give high importance to the problems we face in the scope of Macao's development and security, support the government government to reinforce system development, properly resolve the risks, to resolutely prevent the interference and destruction of hostile and criminals," has been added.
The text also points out that Macao's safety protection will fulfill the "demands made by" Xi Jinping and "dynamically fulfill the sacred mission to safeguard national security, creating high level security to ensure high quality development."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:14:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin | Leader fires after investigation for corruption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/hengqin-dirigente-demite-se-apos-investigacao-por-corrupcao/</link><description>The Government of MSAR has announced that a deputy director of the executive committee of the in-depth cooperation zone has resigned "for personal reasons." The statement does not mention that Su Kun resigned hours after a corruption investigation was released to a state company responsible for the development of Hengqin
 
Lame
"At the request of Su Kun, his duties as advisor to the Secretary's Office for the Economy and Finance and Deputy Chief of the Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone ceases from May 15, 2025, for personal reasons." Thus, in just one sentence, that the Government of MSAR reacted, through the Secretary's Office for Economics and Finance, to a statement issued hours earlier by the Guangdong Province Anti -Corruption Commission to announce the investigation into a corruption case involving a state company responsible for the development of Hengqin.
Su Kun is one of the six deputy coordinators of the executive committee of the in-depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau. According to the Macao Government Portal, this commission “assumes the functions of promoting international dissemination, business and investment capture, industry introduction, land exploitation, construction of specific projects and management of subjects concerning the life of the population”.
Things of Life
Su Kun's resignation happens hours after the Guangdong Neighboring Neighborhood Anti -Corruption Commission announced the beginning of an investigation to the former president of the state company responsible for the development of the Hengqin Special Zone.
In a statement, Guangdong's Provincial Disciplinary Inspection Commission said the former president of Hengqin's Zhuhai Group, Hu Jia, “is suspected of serious disciplinary violations,” a phrase that usually refers to corruption.
The note, also with only one sentence, says Hu is being the subject of “disciplinary review and investigation” by Zhuhai's Municipal Inspection and Disciplinary Supervision Commission.
The Zhuhai Group of Hengqin was created in 2009 by the Municipality of Zhuhai for the construction and development of the Special Economic Zone of Hengqin and is responsible for investment, financing, construction, operation and infrastructure management.
In the business group website it is indicated that Hu Jia has been the president of Heng Qin Investment since December 2013, and was director general from May 2012 to December 2013. It is also said that HU has held “management positions in a series of public companies, has profound financial knowledge and a vast experience in business operation and management”. In addition, “he has unique knowledge regarding the innovation of business finance models, urban design concepts, business group management and business talent introduction”.
It is necessary to integrate
Lusa asked the Macao government yesterday if Su Kun's resignation is related to corruption investigation against Hu Jia, but until the closing of this edition received no response.
Sam Hou Fai, who took office in December as chief executive, has defended a greater bet on integration with Hengqin. The development of the neighboring island “is our main task,” said the leader of the Government of Masters to journalists on Tuesday.
Sam was speaking at a Six -day visit to Macao from the Chinese Communist Party's leading Macao for the affairs of the two semi -autonomous regions, Xia Baolong. On Monday, the director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office, under the tutelage of the Council of State, said that "the construction of hengqin should be treated as a priority of Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:06:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account] to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
What other projects are in this book?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Yes. The idea of ​​publication, with Barcelona's Actar Books, has to do with putting the work, and more than that, its message, which is very specific to Macau and our way of working in the international and architects community, and this goes a lot through the Biennial. It was also in Europe that a consensus was built on the level of descriptions [in architecture] for a few centuries, and where there is a discussion, national and international, around the issues of the profession. We want our work to be present, either through the book and through acting Books, in this international community, to be part of the world.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through spatial narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>India requires surveillance of the weapons of Pakistan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/111705/</link><description>India demanded yesterday that Pakistan nuclear weapons be placed “under surveillance” from the International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA), days after the most serious confrontation between the two armies of the last two decades.
"The nuclear arsenal of Pakistan should be placed under the supervision of the AIEA. I mean this very clearly," said Indian Defense Minister Rajnath Singh, quoted by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
During a visit to the Armed Forces Headquarters in Srinagar, the main city of Caxemira Indiana, the minister wondered whether nuclear weapons will be safe "in the hands of an uncontrollable and irresponsible nation." Pakistan did not react immediately. The two countries with nuclear weapons were involved last week at the deadliest military confrontation since the 1999 war.
On the night from May 6th to 7th, India fired missiles at places in Pakistan which, according to Nova Delh, housed members of the 'jihadist' group suspected of the attack that killed 26 people on April 22 at Caxemira Indiana.
Pakistan, which denied any responsibility for the attack, immediately retaliated. For four days, the two armies exchanged artillery shots and missile attacks and drones, feeding serious fears of a large -scale conflict. To a general surprise, US President Donald Trump announced an immediate ceasefire on Saturday, which was immediately confirmed by both parties.
No thanks
The group of old personalities known as the "Elders" defended yesterday in Tokyo Nuclear Non-Proliferation. Former United Nations Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon released the warning to southern Asia.
"There is a possibility that the international security system will be completely destroyed if India or Pakistan use nuclear weapons," he warned. Former Colombian President Juan Manuel Santos questioned where the UN was led by Portuguese António Guterres during the conflict.
The truce have been respected on the border between the two countries, but rhetoric remains very aggressive. "India will not tolerate the nuclear blackmail," said Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi on Monday night.
India categorically denied news of an attack on a Pakistani nuclear installation about 200 kilometers from the various cities recently hit by Indian missiles. Indian Foreign Ministry spokesman Randhir Jaiswal secured on Tuesday that India's military operation remained conventional. Throughout the crisis, Pakistan repeated that the nuclear option was never considered. "It would be inconceivable and stupid because it would endanger 1.6 billion people," army spokesman General Ahmed Chaudhry said.
Death accounts
India has atomic weapons since the 1990s, transported by Missiles Earth-Terra in the intermediate range. Pakistan has Nuclear Land and Short and Medium Air Range, and performed the first tests in 1998.
The Pakistani army said the Indian attacks killed 40 civilians and lost 13 soldiers. Already Nova Deli, he reported the death of 16 civilians and five soldiers in Indian territory. Despite the unfolding on the ground, India and Pakistan are adamant and claim that they will not lower the guard. "If another terrorist attack targets India, we will respond firmly," Modi warned.
In a telephone conversation with Guterres on Wednesday, Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif said he was "concerned about the provocative and inflammatory statements of India."
India and Pakistan compete for Caxemira's sovereignty since the bloody division when independence in 1947. The fate of the territory of Himalayas, a village mostly by Muslims, gave rise to several wars between the two countries. Since 1989, the Indian side has been the scene of a separatist insurrection that has already caused tens of thousands of dead.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>CCAC | Promised Righteous and Stable Business Environment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/ccac-prometido-ambiente-empresarial-integro-e-estavel/</link><description>The commissioner against corruption, Ieong Seong, has ensured that the institution will contribute to “a righteous, fair, stable and predictable business environment” to allow “companies to invest and develop without worries”. This is how the Commissioner reacted to the visit to Macao de Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao Working Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office with the Council of State.
The Commissioner, through a statement, stated that the speech of director Xia Baolong presented "clear demands on the future development of Macao and the contribution to the construction of the country and that at the same time had a guiding meaning for the work of CCAC."
According to Ao Ieong Seong's report, Xia Baolong left as expectations for the business sector to promote the "spirit of fighting" and "Union of the Homeland, Hong Kong and Macau". In addition, Xia has indicated entrepreneurs that she has to "maintain a firm confidence in development, consolidating and expanding business in Hong Kong and Macau", while expected to enjoy "their own advantages to overcome the challenges and widen the opening abroad and to affirm themselves in the international panorama."
According to Ieong Seong, the interior ruler also expects local entrepreneurs to tell "the world the story of Hong Kong, Macau and China, with a firm position."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:16:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Job fairs offer 77 vacancies in stores and hospitality</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/dsal-feiras-de-emprego-oferecem-77-vagas-em-lojas-e-hotelaria/</link><description>Today open the registration for three sessions of employment fairs, which will be held on May 22 and 23 for the sectors of the retail hotel and trade, according to information released yesterday by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). Interested parties can apply until noon next Wednesday and apply for the 77 job vacancies.
The first session, scheduled for the morning of May 22, will provide 11 jobs for “Hotel W Macau - Studio City”, for the positions of Customer Customer Contact Center, Customer Service Agent, Guest, Elementary Level cook and spa receptionist.
In the afternoon of the same day, it is the turn of the luxury retail sales sector, with 16 vacancies for the “Giorgio Armani Macau Limited” and “Gucci” for the positions of store assistant, store supervisor, sales consultant and warehouse employee.
On the morning of May 23, 50 vacancies will be offered for store employees, warehouse employee and customer service employee at “Isa Boutique Limited” and “Isport Sporting Goods” stores.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:24:27</pubDate></item><item><title>"Flashmobs" this weekend in community neighborhoods</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/flashmobs-este-fim-de-semana-nos-bairros-comunitarios/</link><description>This weekend will take place the initiative “Culture to Your Door”, with 16 flashmobs in 12 local community neighborhoods, an event organized by the Cultural Institute (IC).
According to a note from the IC, flashmobs have five themes, namely theater, Cantonense Opera, martial arts, cinema and reading, intending to “bring rich cultural resources to community neighborhoods, nourishing culturally residents in their daily lives and reinforcing their sense of happiness”.
In the area of ​​theater, with the theme “Theater in More Local”, he presents himself “a magic trip to the stage”, in which the audience is intended to explore “different spaces of action, such as the Greek Ancient Amphitheater, the traditional Bambu de Macao Theater and modern theaters, through the format of interactive theater”.
With the theme “Cantonense Opera in Most Local” it is intended that “residents experience this precious art of intangible cultural heritage”, while with “more places in more local”, the “classic movements of Wing Chun on site are presented, where residents can also experience the basic movements under the guidance of instructors and understand the concepts of Chinese marial culture”.
Cinema and Reading
Already with "cinema in more local", "Flashmob" will "turn the community into an outdoor movie theater, where the public will be able to enjoy the documentary about the sector of Macao's" interpretation of images "cinematic exhibition, know the centenary history of industry and the development of cinema."
In turn, through the theme “Read in More Local”, the activity “Exchange one book for another” is carried out, which is also part of the “joint reading month throughout the city of Macau 2025”. Residents will be able to carry books that comply with the rules on site, selecting their favorites and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books, performing the circulation and sharing of reading resources in the community neighborhoods.
The “Culture at Your Door” activity takes place in several mornings and afternoon tomorrow and Sunday, in community or local neighborhoods such as the S. Lourenço Activities Center-Ajardinado Terrace, Taipa Central Park, Iao Da Orchid Square Terrace Leisure Zone, IP PAI VAN VAN VAN-LOUS GARDEN, Rotunda de Carlos da Maia, leisure zone of the Praceta de Venceslau de Morais, Urban of Areia Preta Park, leisure zone contiguous to edif. Wang Hoi and Wang Kin, leisure zone in the social neighborhood of Tamagnini Barbosa and Edf's leisure zone. Lok Yeong Fa Yuen.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:38:03</pubDate></item><item><title>CLOCKENFLAP | Festival features Franz Ferdinand and Beth Gibbons former Portishead singer</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/clockenflap-festival-traz-franz-ferdinand-e-beth-gibbons-ex-vocalista-dos-portishead/</link><description>There is more poster of Clokenflap, a festival that for three days brings a lot of music to Hong Kong, to Central Harbourfront. The first presences are already known and include names like Franz Ferdinand or Beth Gibbons, former Portishead singer. The musical offer is also composed with Rich Brian, Jacob Collier and Yoga Lin, among many others
 
For those who want to enjoy a huge musical variety in that which is considered the monthly birth month, the Clockenflap festival in Hong Kong is back this year for a new edition between December 5 and 7 instead of custom, Central Harbourfront. Tickets began to be sold this week and are already known some names that take the stage: Rich Brian, Jacob Collier, Franz Ferdinand, Yoga Lin, Panther Chan, and Beth Gibbons, former Portishead singer, the Scots that revolutionized the musical world with their 2004 homonymous album and with success like "Take Me Out" or success "This Fire".
The poster also includes Rich Brian, known as “The Indonesian Rap Star”, which acts on Saturday, December 6, Yoga Lin, the great “Pop Mandarin Star”, scheduled for Sunday, 7, and Panther Chan, known local singer and songwriter, scheduled for the first day of the festival, December 5.
Also on Friday, the performances of British singer and songwriter Passenger take place, as well as a DJ set with Germans Digitalism. Also noteworthy is the presence in Hong Kong of Soccer Mommy, "the favorite of the American Alt-Indie," or the Chilli Beans, the "Japanese Indie-Pops." Still in the Indie kingdom, the festival organization features phum viphurit, "dear Thai indie", or the TV girl, considered the "indie Californian heroes."
From Japan, also arrives at Clockenflap the singer and composer Akasaki, who acts on the 6th, or DJ Riria, who was born in Japan, but is living in the United Kingdom. With regard to the talents of local music, Clockenflap brings the Bitter Tea of ​​General Yeng again, "return after a long hiatus." These are considered "mythical post-punk legends of Hong Kong."
Mixture art
There are still many months to close the Clockenflap poster and many surprises can still appear. The organization highlights the iconic space where the festival takes place, “with the spectacular outdoor scenario between the imposing Central skyscrapers and the epic views of the iconic Hong Kong Porto”, presenting again this year “the complete experience of a world class festival that made the event an unmissable occasion for music fans across the city and not alone”.
In addition to music, the festival also includes "a series of eye -stuffing artistic installations, workshops and shows for the whole family and a selection of food and drink to make mouth water, including unique snacks of some of the city's most appreciated restaurants."
One of the artistic news that the festival brings to this edition is the project “Minimax - Mobile &amp; Modular Theatical Experience”, understood by the organization as “a new concept for all art lovers”, currently in the recruitment phase of “local talents”.
The early sale of tickets takes place only until May 23, with discounts, and from that date the tickets become a higher price. Early purchase for the three days for general admission is $ 1,790 from Hong Kong (HKD), while early one day tickets in general admission cost 1,150 HKD.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:35:24</pubDate></item><item><title>APEC foresees trade stoppage and drastic softening in the region</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/apec-preve-paralisacao-do-comercio-e-abrandamento-drastico-na-regiao/</link><description>The Organization for Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) provides for a virtual stagnation of trade and a drastic economic slowdown in the region by 2025 due to tariff climbing, according to forecasts released yesterday.
APEC brings together 21 economies (Australia, Vietnam, Thailand, Japan, the United States, Canada, Mexico, etc.), including Asian countries that depend on commerce and which were harshly hit by the Customs War launched by Washington.
Economists in the organization provide for exports in the Asia-Pacific region to grow only 0.4 percent by 2025 compared to a 5.7 percent record last year. Imports must stagnate (+0.1 percent).
Consequently, APEC countries are expected to record Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth of only 2.6 percent by 2025, an estimate compared to 3.3 percent in the previous forecast of the organization. For 2026, there is now a growth of 2.7 percent, well below the expected performance for the rest of the world (+3.3 percent).
General losses
Although the organization covers a wide range of economies, they are all suffering: the climbing of customs retaliation “is leading to a loss of confidence from investors and a weakening of demand,” APEC's Department of Public Policy Department, cited by France Presse, told the France Presse, in the margin of a meeting of the organization of the organization, which began yesterday in South Korea.
In addition to 25 percent tariffs on cars and steel, President Donald Trump's US administration announced, in early April, prohibitive “reciprocal” customs surcharge, currently suspended until July.
The highest customs rights will penalize the supply chains, will increase production costs, which will be transferred to the end consumer, and therefore will reduce the search for goods, ”Kuriyama explained. In the economist's opinion, uncertainty is the worst risk:“ It is essential to ensure that policies are stable and, if there are changes, that are permanent and not temporary, ”he suggested.
Starting points
This week's APEC meeting is an occasion for a series of bilateral discussions between the US commercial representative, Jamieson Greer, who is in South Korea, and representatives of US partners, including Chinese commercial representative, Li Chenggang.
Beijing and Washington recently selated a partial break in the heavy clusters of reciprocal customs. "This is positive, but it doesn't take us back to the point where we were before April," said Carlos Kuriyama.
Within APEC, "many governments are trying to apply measures to facilitate trade in order to compensate for the negative effect of US measures," he added, however, that these initiatives will have a limited impact because "the United States are the largest economy in the world."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:32:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Bridge | Radars installed to control speed</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/ponte-macau-instalados-radares-para-controlar-velocidade/</link><description>From tomorrow, 22 speed detection fixed systems and four average speed detection systems will begin to work on the Macau bridge. The measure aims to “combat speeding offenses”.
These systems allow not only to detect instant speed, but also make the average time the vehicles took time to go through the bridge, and if below a certain number, there will be a fine for speeding.
According to the statement from the Public Security Police (CPSP) and the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the radars will be installed on the sides of Macau and the Main Bridge mud, in the nearby paci ramps and the main bridge and the exclusive motorcycle and moped corridor.
The Macau Bridge has as full speed limits of 80 km/h, 60 km/h and 40 km/h, depending on the sections. In some access ramps, and on the exclusive corridor tunnels for motorcycles and mopeds, the maximum limit is 40 km/h.
Drivers who violate the speed limits on the Macau bridge incur a fine of 600 patacas at 20,000 patacas and may still be without driving, in case of recurrence or severe excess speed.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:20:51</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Liu Yuxi (772-842), Luoyang's poet (Henan), contemplating the heavens noticed in certain birds who liked to dwell with families and indicated a permanence within the constant change of stations. Observing the habits of the swallows and the decay of the high classes in Jinling, he wrote in the last two verses of the poem to Rua das Mansions of Black Village:
Under the eaves of the powerful Wang and Xie
before they were swallows,
Now flying, they seek so many times
our humble dwellings.
This proximity that speaks, for example, the founding legend of the first dynasty that there are written records and that is the origin of the Shang lineage (c. 1500-1050 A. C.) it was long recognized with the first.
Then, according to historian Sima Qian, a woman named Jiandi would have eaten a swallow egg (Yan), previously called simply Xuanniao, "black bird", then giving birth to a man named Xie, who was the ancestor of the founders of the dynasty. Over time, in various arts such as architecture, painting or poetry, repeated references were unfolded to this relationship of perceived friendship with black birds.
In times of uneasiness, such as those who followed the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition in which painters identified with the losers and belonging to the previous reigning family, such as Zhu da (1626-1705) known as Bada Shanren, found new, expressive forms of the fluidity of the caleigraphic brush trace along the Tang and Song Dynasties and Song and Song Qichang would make an ideal.
In the epitome of its speed, this trait was designated Feiba, the "flying white", which left only the traces of the brush passage. A painter from Xinghua (Yangzhou, Jiangsu) admirer of Bada Shanren showed in several paintings the same independent attitude of canons that would lead to one of the Yangzhou Baguai, "the eight eccentrics of Yangzhou."
Li Shan (1686- C.1756) who would use the stage name Futang, which can be translated as a "recovery of family relationships", in the vertical roll swallows (paint and color on paper, 134.9 x 33 cm, metmuseum) painted slowly, carefully two swallows in a branch made with the spontaneity of the speed of the trace used to write with the pinl.
And as in many paintings by Bada Shanren, the words in Him are written in harmony with the figuration, and just like the swallows in the branch depend on each other. In this roll Li Shan wrote: «As soon as the fall does salguels begin to wither cruelly wither,/ how do they compare to the spring brisa and the corner of the swallows?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>India demanded yesterday that Pakistan nuclear weapons be placed “under surveillance” from the International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA), days after the most serious confrontation between the two armies of the last two decades.
"The nuclear arsenal of Pakistan should be placed under the supervision of the AIEA. I mean this very clearly," said Indian Defense Minister Rajnath Singh, quoted by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
During a visit to the Armed Forces Headquarters in Srinagar, the main city of Caxemira Indiana, the minister wondered whether nuclear weapons will be safe "in the hands of an uncontrollable and irresponsible nation." Pakistan did not react immediately. The two countries with nuclear weapons were involved last week at the deadliest military confrontation since the 1999 war.
On the night from May 6th to 7th, India fired missiles at places in Pakistan which, according to Nova Delh, housed members of the 'jihadist' group suspected of the attack that killed 26 people on April 22 at Caxemira Indiana.
Pakistan, which denied any responsibility for the attack, immediately retaliated. For four days, the two armies exchanged artillery shots and missile attacks and drones, feeding serious fears of a large -scale conflict. To a general surprise, US President Donald Trump announced an immediate ceasefire on Saturday, which was immediately confirmed by both parties.
No thanks
The group of old personalities known as the "Elders" defended yesterday in Tokyo Nuclear Non-Proliferation. Former United Nations Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon released the warning to southern Asia.
"There is a possibility that the international security system will be completely destroyed if India or Pakistan use nuclear weapons," he warned. Former Colombian President Juan Manuel Santos questioned where the UN was led by Portuguese António Guterres during the conflict.
The truce have been respected on the border between the two countries, but rhetoric remains very aggressive. "India will not tolerate the nuclear blackmail," said Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi on Monday night.
India categorically denied news of an attack on a Pakistani nuclear installation about 200 kilometers from the various cities recently hit by Indian missiles. Indian Foreign Ministry spokesman Randhir Jaiswal secured on Tuesday that India's military operation remained conventional. Throughout the crisis, Pakistan repeated that the nuclear option was never considered. "It would be inconceivable and stupid because it would endanger 1.6 billion people," army spokesman General Ahmed Chaudhry said.
Death accounts
India has atomic weapons since the 1990s, transported by Missiles Earth-Terra in the intermediate range. Pakistan has Nuclear Land and Short and Medium Air Range, and performed the first tests in 1998.
The Pakistani army said the Indian attacks killed 40 civilians and lost 13 soldiers. Already Nova Deli, he reported the death of 16 civilians and five soldiers in Indian territory. Despite the unfolding on the ground, India and Pakistan are adamant and claim that they will not lower the guard. "If another terrorist attack targets India, we will respond firmly," Modi warned.
In a telephone conversation with Guterres on Wednesday, Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif said he was "concerned about the provocative and inflammatory statements of India."
India and Pakistan compete for Caxemira's sovereignty since the bloody division when independence in 1947. The fate of the territory of Himalayas, a village mostly by Muslims, gave rise to several wars between the two countries. Since 1989, the Indian side has been the scene of a separatist insurrection that has already caused tens of thousands of dead.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>India demanded yesterday that Pakistan nuclear weapons be placed “under surveillance” from the International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA), days after the most serious confrontation between the two armies of the last two decades.
"The nuclear arsenal of Pakistan should be placed under the supervision of the AIEA. I mean this very clearly," said Indian Defense Minister Rajnath Singh, quoted by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
During a visit to the Armed Forces Headquarters in Srinagar, the main city of Caxemira Indiana, the minister wondered whether nuclear weapons will be safe "in the hands of an uncontrollable and irresponsible nation." Pakistan did not react immediately. The two countries with nuclear weapons were involved last week at the deadliest military confrontation since the 1999 war.
On the night from May 6th to 7th, India fired missiles at places in Pakistan which, according to Nova Delh, housed members of the 'jihadist' group suspected of the attack that killed 26 people on April 22 at Caxemira Indiana.
Pakistan, which denied any responsibility for the attack, immediately retaliated. For four days, the two armies exchanged artillery shots and missile attacks and drones, feeding serious fears of a large -scale conflict. To a general surprise, US President Donald Trump announced an immediate ceasefire on Saturday, which was immediately confirmed by both parties.
No thanks
The group of old personalities known as the "Elders" defended yesterday in Tokyo Nuclear Non-Proliferation. Former United Nations Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon released the warning to southern Asia.
"There is a possibility that the international security system will be completely destroyed if India or Pakistan use nuclear weapons," he warned. Former Colombian President Juan Manuel Santos questioned where the UN was led by Portuguese António Guterres during the conflict.
The truce have been respected on the border between the two countries, but rhetoric remains very aggressive. "India will not tolerate the nuclear blackmail," said Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi on Monday night.
India categorically denied news of an attack on a Pakistani nuclear installation about 200 kilometers from the various cities recently hit by Indian missiles. Indian Foreign Ministry spokesman Randhir Jaiswal secured on Tuesday that India's military operation remained conventional. Throughout the crisis, Pakistan repeated that the nuclear option was never considered. "It would be inconceivable and stupid because it would endanger 1.6 billion people," army spokesman General Ahmed Chaudhry said.
Death accounts
India has atomic weapons since the 1990s, transported by Missiles Earth-Terra in the intermediate range. Pakistan has Nuclear Land and Short and Medium Air Range, and performed the first tests in 1998.
The Pakistani army said the Indian attacks killed 40 civilians and lost 13 soldiers. Already Nova Deli, he reported the death of 16 civilians and five soldiers in Indian territory. Despite the unfolding on the ground, India and Pakistan are adamant and claim that they will not lower the guard. "If another terrorist attack targets India, we will respond firmly," Modi warned.
In a telephone conversation with Guterres on Wednesday, Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif said he was "concerned about the provocative and inflammatory statements of India."
India and Pakistan compete for Caxemira's sovereignty since the bloody division when independence in 1947. The fate of the territory of Himalayas, a village mostly by Muslims, gave rise to several wars between the two countries. Since 1989, the Indian side has been the scene of a separatist insurrection that has already caused tens of thousands of dead.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 2025
In Chinese proverbial lessons I discovered great affinities between spontaneous Chinese popular philosophy, which runs from mouth to mouth, and the Christian proverbial wisdom, also made so that believers, in every corner of the globe, could memorize, repeat and disseminate.
Nothing like the other's knowledge to bring and dispel prejudice, being one of the most usual that Chinese are extremely pragmatic and cold. But when we come across proverbs such as “love others as yourself,” in a direct translation and faithful to the original “爱人如己” (ài Rú Rú Jǐ), such leads us to think twice, it seems not to be here just a matter of respect, uncharged and formal, but rather a strong feeling for the other, not any, only a deep affection, of those we understand well that we are good, we will be well, we will be well, we will be well, we will be better. Then he runs a love of the Christian way for China without Christ ever been. Such finding can lead us to the assumption of the existence of universal structures, not only logical, including as regards affections, therefore sentimental. After all, selfishness may not be a dominant tendency, there is everything: selfish, aggressive and competitive people, as others will be naturally altruistic, compassionate and cooperatives, ready to recognize the universality of the feeling of love, which crosses borders rather than erecting them, bringing people closer to the most diverse social classes, ethnic groups, geographies, as in "love has no borders", in a direct translation "" (Àiqíng wú jiējí zhī fēn), here is particularly emphasized social borders.
The content of the message gains full sense when one realizes that love to oneself takes place in a culture that many consider wrong and prejudiced only to focus on the whole, in the community.  Attention to the person, the particular and the style and feeling of each, lives, in philosophies such as Taoist for centuries with the valorization of the collectivity, this ultimate tendency manifestly inculcated and worked by Confucianism.  Love to itself, care for the individual body and mind, is emphasized in the so -called Proverbial “well -understood love and virtue must begin with us”, which has the following correspondence in Chinese “爱德从己起” (to Cong Jǐ qǐ).
Anyone who imagines that in proverbial wisdom there is only place to praise and sing relational love, since the Chinese do not have any religious philosophy that chants spiritual love above all, in the Christian way of St. Augustine, will be surprised to find the following proverb "where there is no other gentleman", that in a direct translation of the Chinese is "the love above all" 爱情至上 爱情至上 爱情至上ZHì Shàng).
If in doubt, there is another saying of complementary meaning and in which the idea of ​​the integrity and unity of this powerful affection, which moves mountains in the Christian sense, when it reads 爱情专一 （（（（iqíng zhuān yī）, in a possible translation "love cannot be broken", "one person cannot have a heart in two parts at the same time."
From a psychological point of view, the acceptance of the other in loving terms will have to be complete, so their tastes, affections, relationships, and objects cannot be rejected, as is clear from the lesson "Who loves Beltrão, loves their dog", in a relative correspondence for "爱屋及乌" (ài wū jí wū), which in a literal translation would be "love the house and the crums."
As is well known, proverbs are susceptible to various interpretations, so they say polysemic, but if they are perspective as a whole, and only then as pieces of a puzzle, there seems to be many doubts with regard to the proverb philosophy and psychology of Chinese love, which is echoed in the country's scholarly philosophies.
In Chapter 67 of the Book of the road and virtue (《道德经》), also known by the name of the Patriarch of Taoism, Lazi (老子), is the first of the three guiding virtues of the Wise Way, love, as you can read in the translation of Claudia Ribeiro (2004, 139):
I have three treasures
What entesouro and retains:
The first is love (CI),
The second frugality,
The third is not daring to be the vanguard of the world.
(…)
For love,
In combat, it triumphs,
And in defense it is firm.
The sky will come to aid
And, with love, will protect
(我有三寶/寶而持之/一曰慈/二曰儉/三曰不敢為天下先 (……) 夫慈以戰則勝//以守則固/以慈衛之 1)
It is noted that while in proverbial philosophy the synogram used for love is 爱/愛 2 (AI), in the scholarly philosophy of the Patriarch of Taoism the term employment is 慈 (CI), that is, love with a strong relational and spiritual burden; Although they are different words, both refer to love, the first concerns the most physical and concrete feeling, centered on the heart of the person and the clutches that hold it;  The second to that most relational and general indicates that love comes from inside the heart (内心 nèixīn), where it has the roots, emerging like any plant. However, the truth is that both terms focus on people, or rather in their hearts, affectionate connection with others, such a strong connection that draws the attention of heaven (天 tiān), maximum impersonal power, it ensures victory on all battle fronts, whether in the forefront or rear, when fighting and defended itself for love.
Already the patriarch of Confucianism, Confucius (孔子), in the Chapter Twelve, later entitled the deep face, of the Analects (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 22) defines the main virtue of the school, benevolence or humanity, (仁 Rén) as an act of love to others, maintaining the term of the traditional vernacular 爱 (AI): “Fan Chi asked what was the benevolence was what answered, "love people". " (樊遲問仁 ， 子曰 「愛人 3。 ”) It is in this context of love of neighbor, that one of the main maxims of Confucian philosophy must be understood, which arises in the same chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 2)“ Do not make the others what they do not want for you ”(己所不欲勿施於人 jǐ suǒ bù yù shunk yú rén).
The essentials in Confucian philosophy will then guarantee love of others in terms of respect or humanity towards others, in order to ensure the normal functioning of society, without extreme sacrifices or exaggerated explorations, given to the proverb containment of confusion in relation to feelings, they are important and useful but should not extravate the boundaries of rationality, that is, even the best of them, will have to be measured, controlled and ritualized in the name of harmony collective. Therefore, the love that moves friendships, especially intellectuals, is the most praised, as we remembered at the end of this chapter (論語 • 颜渊第十二 ， 24):
Zeng Zi stated: “A gentleman resorts to knowing to make friends and friends to cultivate benevolence4” (曾子曰：君以文會友 ， 以友輔仁。)
Finally, also the Buddhist philosophy, especially from the Chan (禅 Chán) or Zen meditation line, praises the love of humanity, but indirectly, drawing attention to the heart and the identification of Buddha with the heart, the way of the Daoxin Patriarch (道信) and its maximum proverbially known “the heart is Buddha and Buddha is the heart” (非心不问佛 ， 问佛不非心 fēi xīn bùwèn fu, wèn fi bù fēi xīn). Here you come to love indirectly, only an enlightened heart can love the Buddha, as it is not surprising in the picture of this philosophy, after all what is Buddha but the very love that expresses itself not in a selfish, sick, self -centered heart, but in a heart capable of establishing relationships, healthy, altruistic and without empty, but not indifferent to the other?  This confirms it the social and humanitarian actions of Via Mahayana Buddhism, which was accepted in China and unfolds in collective works such as the construction of educational institutions, hospitals, centers of social solidarity, in a proselytist action at all similar to the history of the Christian Church and its missionaries around the world.
Bibliographic references
Lansheng, Jiang (Comp.) 1997. 100 Excerpts from Zen Buddhist Texts. Hong Hong Kong: Commercial Press.
NGAN, António André. 1998. SINE-SHORE CONGRELLANCE OF PROVERBS AND IDIOMATIC PHRASES. 中葡對照成語集. Macau: Macao Adult Association.
RIBEIRO, Claudia (Trad). 2004. 《道德經》 The Book of Road and Power. Bilingual edition. Mem-Martins: European American Publications.
Xin Guanjie (辛冠洁) (org. And trad.) 1994. 《論語》 .Tradument for contemporary Chinese falls xiqin (蔡希勤) and English translation of Lai Bo (赖波) and Xia Yuhe (夏玉和). Beijing: Sinolingue.
References:
Text in classic Chinese.
Love in simplified and traditional Chinese.
Text in classic Chinese.
A gentleman in ancient Chinese times was a gentleman and a potential ruler.
“This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors” https://www.cccm.gov.pt</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Liu Yuxi (772-842), Luoyang's poet (Henan), contemplating the heavens noticed in certain birds who liked to dwell with families and indicated a permanence within the constant change of stations. Observing the habits of the swallows and the decay of the high classes in Jinling, he wrote in the last two verses of the poem to Rua das Mansions of Black Village:
Under the eaves of the powerful Wang and Xie
before they were swallows,
Now flying, they seek so many times
our humble dwellings.
This proximity that speaks, for example, the founding legend of the first dynasty that there are written records and that is the origin of the Shang lineage (c. 1500-1050 A. C.) it was long recognized with the first.
Then, according to historian Sima Qian, a woman named Jiandi would have eaten a swallow egg (Yan), previously called simply Xuanniao, "black bird", then giving birth to a man named Xie, who was the ancestor of the founders of the dynasty. Over time, in various arts such as architecture, painting or poetry, repeated references were unfolded to this relationship of perceived friendship with black birds.
In times of uneasiness, such as those who followed the Ming-Qing Dynastic Transition in which painters identified with the losers and belonging to the previous reigning family, such as Zhu da (1626-1705) known as Bada Shanren, found new, expressive forms of the fluidity of the caleigraphic brush trace along the Tang and Song Dynasties and Song and Song Qichang would make an ideal.
In the epitome of its speed, this trait was designated Feiba, the "flying white", which left only the traces of the brush passage. A painter from Xinghua (Yangzhou, Jiangsu) admirer of Bada Shanren showed in several paintings the same independent attitude of canons that would lead to one of the Yangzhou Baguai, "the eight eccentrics of Yangzhou."
Li Shan (1686- C.1756) who would use the stage name Futang, which can be translated as a "recovery of family relationships", in the vertical roll swallows (paint and color on paper, 134.9 x 33 cm, metmuseum) painted slowly, carefully two swallows in a branch made with the spontaneity of the speed of the trace used to write with the pinl.
And as in many paintings by Bada Shanren, the words in Him are written in harmony with the figuration, and just like the swallows in the branch depend on each other. In this roll Li Shan wrote: «As soon as the fall does salguels begin to wither cruelly wither,/ how do they compare to the spring brisa and the corner of the swallows?</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Church | Victims of sexual abuse want Leo XIV to assume theme</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/igreja-vitimas-de-abuso-sexual-querem-que-leao-xiv-assuma-tema/</link><description>One of the movement spokesmen that represents victims of sexual abuse in the Catholic Church yesterday asked Pope Leo XIV to put the theme as a priority and defines global rules to deal with cases.
"Now that we have a new Latin American Pope should be given an example in all Latin American episcopades that, by decision and by the Pope, there can be no double standard" among the various Catholic hierarchies around the world, "said Argentine Sebastián Cuattromo, from the adult collective for the rights of the child.
On the day the Pope made the first Sunday greeting in St. Peter's Square, praying Regina Caeli, a group of victims joined the square to ask the Vatican to impose common rules on the whole church.
Cuattromo, 42, set an example of what is happening "in the first world societies and Latin America that acts as a Vatican backyard, where the same [repair] demands are not felt, such as they are felt before European public opinion."
"As a survivor of childhood sexual abuse within the Catholic Church, with other companions survivors of this crime, we hope that the Pope will make an explicit mention of this question and an explicit reference to what he intends to do about it to pay off very large debts that, in our opinion, the Catholic Church still has to the victims," ​​said Cuattromo.
“We victims broke the taboo, silence, denial, concealment, with our struggles, with a huge sacrifice, and reached a level of visibility in public opinion,” which forced the church to face the problem.
Therefore, the global group of victims subscribed to a petition already delivered, in which they require “a true zero tolerance law that is established as canonical law”, which would “imply the immediate expulsion of the religious life of anyone involved in these acts”.
Moreover, they propose a “Truth Commission that should not be directed by the Vatican, but by international human rights organizations with the United Nations standards and with which the Vatican would have to fully cooperate, freeing all the archives he has on the subject”.
Finally, the victims intend a “justice process for the victims, where, among other things, there are concrete actions of reparation and justice for survivors around the world”, with the costs supported by the Church's own goods.

In the first person
In his particular case, Sebastian Cuattromo filed an action against a religious from a Catholic school of Buenos Aires for sexual abuse and won the process in 2012, even before the election to the Pope of then Cardinal Bergoglio, archbishop of the Argentine capital. "Then the city's Catholic hierarchy was against the victims and supported the school, which intended to silence the victims of this offense through a private economic agreement," he recalled.
"They made us feel a profound underestimation of the severity of the crime we were talking about," because, at that moment, "I was a young man who was fighting in solitude, with many doubts, with a lot less, with much anguish and felt an absolute lack of empathy and, instead, deep arrogance," he explained.
After Francis' election, "I invited him publicly and privately to meet with the victims of his country, especially those who had bad experiences," but the Pope "never had the courage or sensitivity of calling us."
For the new Pope, who is also accused of having ignored abuse complaints when he was a prior of the Augustinhos, Cuattromo expects Leo XIV to “assume this theme personally” and to be willing to “go to the last consequences”. Cardinal Robert Francis Prevost, 69, was elected Pope on Thursday after two days of Conclave, in the Vatican City, and took the name of Leo XIV.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Osaka 2025 | Japanese architect Kengo Kuma considers it to be friendly with architecture</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/12/osaka-2025-arquitecto-japones-kengo-kuma-considera-ia-amiga-da-arquitectura/</link><description>Japanese architect Kengo Kuma states in an interview with Lusa that she wanted to show the uniqueness between Portugal and Japan in the Portuguese Pavilion project at Expo 2025 Osaka and considers AI (artificial intelligence) friendly to architecture.
Asked if Artificial Intelligence (AI) is a friend or enemy of architecture, Kengo Kuma opts for the first option. "Yes, it's a friend", because in fact in the design process "we are working with AI".
Artificial intelligence “is a very strong team between us” and “we like to work” with this technology, he says. “We wanted to show the relationship with the ocean in Portugal,” says Kengo Kuma, when asked what was the project's inspiration. Portugal participates in Expo Osaka with the theme “Ocean, Blue Dialogue” and is located in the “Empowering Lives” zone, in a lot with 1,836.75 square meters, being close to the Japan Pavilion.
The Kuma Kuma project expresses the dynamics of the ocean moment, using 9,972 suspended cables weighing more than 60 tons, and recycled networks to create a perennial effect and exposed to natural elements such as sun and wind, according to the organization.
Sea connections
The life of Portugal and Japan is “very linked to the ocean”, in the sense that “we eat fish, we travel a lot through the oceans and history and life are closely linked to the ocean,” adds the architect. There is this “uniqueness of Portugal and Japan and we want to show” this similarity between the two countries.
The volume of the Portugal Pavilion is characterized by a scenic facility that symbolizes the upper square suspended as a wave.
"This design is very, very new to the history of art. We have long tried to use lines as a resource for navigation. With these lines, we try to show the beauty of natural phenomena," in the sea "we see natural light and breeze," he explains.
“We tried to bring this kind of natural phenomenon to the Expo, perhaps the first attempt in the history of the expo to bring its own nature to the pavilion,” says the architect. About what will happen to the pavilion after finishing the Expo, the architect says he wants to bring the diversity of the project (which includes cables of various diameters and lengths) to different places.
“I want to bring this diversity to different places” and “now we are planning to work with some artists” about it. Kengo Kuma said that the Slaughterhouse Project in Porto is completing and has two more projects in Portugal.
The architect says he loves the side of the big cities in Portugal, but also the mountainous side and the ocean of the country. “We want to enjoy the diversity of Portugal,” he says.
Create Memories
Asked how can the more sustainable architecture currently become, Kengo Kuma considers that "the most important for sustainability is to leave the memory of architecture forever." That is, "architecture, life, basically, are not so permanent."
However, “we can leave the memory of architecture forever, which is the connection between architecture and humanity” and this “is the most important for sustainability,” he says. Used to comment on the controversy around his choice to project the Portuguese pavilion, the architect points out that he has an international office working in Portugal.
"Maybe that's why we were invited," he concludes. Regarding the challenges that architecture currently faces, Kengo Kuma states that its cost is increasing “dramatically” and that everyone wants to reduce it.
"But at the same time, people want to create a new monument" for this pillar. "And the cost and monumentality must walk together" today. Expo 2025 runs since April 13 and runs until October 13 on the artificial island of Yumeshima, located on the edge of Osaka, Kansai, Japan.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 04:03:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Startups | Portugal interested in the SINO-LUSOPHONE TECHNOLOGY FUND</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/startups-portugal-interessado-no-fundo-sino-lusofono-de-tecnologia/</link><description>A delegation from Macao, with government representatives and local startups, is in Portugal to meet with leaders of Portuguese companies and participate in the SIM conference, which ends today in Porto. During the visit, a protocol was signed that signs the Portuguese interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund, managed by Heng Qin Group's state-owned company Zhuhai
 
Several macao startups are represented on a trip to Portugal this week, and whose delegation also includes representatives of the Directorate of Economics and Tourism Development Services (DSEDT) and the Macao, China and Portuguese -speaking countries Association (AEIMCP). The objective is to strengthen ties with the entrepreneurship ecosystems of Lisbon and Porto and reinforce Portugal's interest in the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund designed to support startups, which will be managed by Heng Qin Group's Zhuhai state company.
In this sense, a protocol between AEIMCP and the nascent Value, “Portuguese company with extensive investor capture” and also “accelerating small business growth (SME) and startups in Portugal and Portuguese-speaking countries, focused on innovation and cutting-edge technology”, is signed on Monday, in Lisbon, in Lisbon, in Lisbon.
The protocol signed on Monday signs the highest Portuguese access to the new Sino-Lusophone Technology Fund. The document was signed as part of a visit from the Macau Group to Lispolis - Lisbon Technological Pole.
The nascent Value thus becomes a “exclusive agent for investor capture services in Portugal, focusing on the involvement of investors in the background” SINO-LUSOPHONE, whose official name is “from Heng Qin Sino-Maluso Technology and Innovation Investment LPF”. This “promotes investments in high quality science and technology innovation companies in Portuguese -speaking countries”, explains the same note.
Thus, this protocol will allow AEIMCP, as a connecting entity between Portugal and the Fund via Macau, and the nascent Value, “reinforce its commitment to support startups, promote transfronhoring investment and create new opportunities for collaboration between Macau, Portugal and other Portuguese -speaking countries”.
Quoted by the same note, AEIMCP's Marco Duarte Rizzolio, said this new agreement shows how the entity, which also organizes the “929 Challenge” contest, is committed to “creating bridges for the global startup growth, facilitating the entry of Portuguese startups into the Chinese market through Macao, as well as the expansion of Chinese startups to Portugal and Europe”.
In turn, Rui Ferreira said that “the signing of this protocol is an important milestone for connecting innovation ecosystems and promoting synergies between macao startups and Portuguese investors”. "We are confident that this partnership will bring significant results for both sides," he added.
At HM, Rui Ferreira explained that the signature of the protocol represents the culmination of a work of about a year.
“We want to promote a model of welcoming startups and companies from Macao that want to enter Europe through Portugal, as well as in Portuguese-expression countries, and vice versa, that is, to place, through Macau, companies of these territories, but always through Portugal, in the East, in order to obtain easier connections with the Chinese market.”
Thousand Visits
Macao's group visited several essential points of the Portuguese entrepreneurship sector. In addition to the visit to Lispolis, considered the “key moment to foster dialogues between Deep Tech startups and potential investors, consolidating Macau's vision as an innovation and entrepreneurship hub with global range”, the entourage passed through the unicorns factory in Lisbon, and the PWC consultant.
Marco Duarte Rizzolio explained to HM the benefits to Macao from the journey through Portugal. “In addition to the interest in the Sino-Lusophone Fund and its preparation, as it will be released soon, our focus has also been the startups. On the visit to Lispolis macao startups made a pitch [attempted investment tarning], presented their products and had a networking session with other startups. Immersion in the Entrepreneurship Ecosystem in Portugal. ”
According to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, Macao's entourage only took to Portugal to startups with a more advanced business phase, namely Zence Object, founded by Calvin Sio and obtained a $ 2.5 million financing from the Alibaba Group entrepreneurs to the Great Bay area. Zence Object uses patented technology to transform organic waste, namely tea leaves, into alternative plastic and paper products. The idea is that these recycled and transformed products can be used on a daily basis, such as home or decorating utensils.
"There are startups in Macau who are very advanced in terms of business and we have brought to Portugal. We want to explore new opportunities for internationalization, so that they explore other markets, as these startups already have some development. We want to create partnerships, so that these representatives realize what the market is like and explore possible customers," said the representative of AEIMCP.
By unbeaten paths
Macau's entourage is today in Porto to participate in “SIM Conference” [Startups &amp; Investment Matching], where “it will have its own stand to present projects and connect with investors and possible customers”. This event was organized by the Entity Startup Portugal, which invited to be present.
Also today will be signed another protocol, this time between the association that organizes the contest “929 Challenge” and Startup Portugal. The idea is, according to Marco Duarte Rizzolio, “stimulate the connection of the Portugal ecosystem with Macau and help in the process of internationalization of the startups on both sides, both the Portuguese who are intended for the great bay, through Macau, both the macao startups that go to Portugal”.
The official has no doubt that what is lacking in knowledge is left in interest. “There is a great interest in China, but at the same time there is a great ignorance. The startup ecosystem in Portugal is much more linked to Europe. When we talk to the unicorns factory, it has been told that there was a great interest in the Macao and China market, but that these visits to Portugal were lacking. It is growing a lot in technology and artificial intelligence, with the launch of DeepSeek, for example. ”
According to Rui Ferreira, the presence of the delegation of Macao in “Yes Conference” will allow access to “privileged and wider contacts”, as it is a national event. "With this visit we have been able to do two things: starting the relationship with AEIMCP more formally and helping Macao companies know of partners and investors. We also want to bet on the work for the future Sino-Musso fund, to prepare companies with investment potential," he said.
For Rui Ferreira, the Macao market has the potential “to be used as a business exchange platform, thanks to linguistic connection, and there is conditions in the territory to establish all the part of reception, support and exchange with China entities and create an ecosystem”. In addition, “it will be interesting Macao to make a specialized innovation hub in strategic areas”, which in this case is technology. Highlight for the fact that the visit also had the organization of the Macao Sino-Lusophone Platform Association for sustainable development.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Leo XIV offers Vatican mediation to “silence the weapons”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/leao-xiv-oferece-mediacao-do-vaticano-para-silenciar-as-armas/</link><description>Pope Leo XIV yesterday exhorted world leaders to sit down and negotiate to “silence the weapons” and offered the Vatican's mediation to all belligerent parts. "The Holy See is available for enemies to meet and look in their eyes," Leo XIV told Vatican to speak at the representatives of the 23 Catholic churches of the East.
The Pope said it is necessary that "peoples can rediscover the hope and dignity to which they are entitled," the dignity of peace. "The people want peace and I, with my heart, say to the leaders of the people: We find, we speak, negotiate! War is never inevitable, weapons can and should be silenced, because they do not solve problems, but increase them," he said.
The US Pope's appeal appears on the eve of possible negotiations in the Turkish city of Istanbul about the Russian War against Ukraine. It is also unknown if today's conversations can include a meeting between Russian presidents, Vladimir Putin, and Ukrainian, Volodymyr Zelensky. Other wars have caused suffering in other latitudes, such as the Middle East, Africa or Asia.
First-hand
Leo XIV said in the Paul VI room, before thousands of people who moved to the jubilee of countries such as Syria, Ukraine, Lebanon and Iraq, which the oriental churches know "firsthand the horrors of war."
"To the point that Pope Francis has called martyrs to your churches," he said, quoted by the Spanish news agency Efe. "It is true: from the Holy Land to Ukraine, from Lebanon to Syria, from the Middle East to Tigray [Ethiopia] and to the Caucasus, so much violence," he lamented.
The Pope, applauded by the hearing, said the horror of war and "of the massacres of so many young lives" should cause indignation, "because in the name of military conquest people die."
He asked him to pray for peace, which he described as "reconciliation, forgiveness, courage to turn the page and start over." “For this peace to differ, I will do everything within my reach,” he promised. "The church will not get tired of repeating:" May weapons shut up, "he said.
Leo XIV said that others are not enemies, but human beings, "they are not bad people to hate, but people to dialogue." The Pope has asked to escape "from the typical manichaeist visions of violent narratives, which divide the world between good and bad."
Leo XIV prayed for the oriental and Latin Christians, who, especially in the Middle East, "resist their lands, stronger than the temptation to abandon them." He also launched a new appeal to be given to Christians the opportunity to remain where they live "with all the rights necessary for a safe existence."
Robert Prevost, 69, born in the United States, but with double American and Peruvian nationality, leads the Catholic Church since May 8, under the name of Leo XIV. It succeeded the Argentine Pope Francis, who died on April 21, 88 years old.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:21:34</pubDate></item><item><title>Literature | The interest of linguist Hugo Schuchardt in Patuá de Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/07/literatura-o-interesse-do-linguista-hugo-schuchardt-no-patua-de-macau/</link><description>Hugo Schuchardt had a genuine interest in Luso-Asian Creole languages, with particular emphasis on Patuá, spoken by the Macaense community. The linguist, who was born in 1842, was the subject of a lecture conducted by researcher Hugo Cardoso, linked to the University of Lisbon
 
Porto, 1883. José Leite de Vasconcelos writes a letter to the German linguist Hugo Schuchardt who had been developing studies, albeit at a distance, about the languages ​​spoken in Asia originated in Portuguese, the so -called Creoles. The letter, written according to the spell agreement of the time, however digitized and today to keep the Archive of the University of Graz, Austria, comes in the context of Schuchardt's own requests to Vasconcelos Milk on the Creole that was then spoken in Macao, known as Patuá.
“My respectable friend: I can only respond to you today. Here in Porto there are no books that say, but I wrote to Lisbon to my friend Vianna and he replied that the Balsmanha does not appear, and that in Macao's story there comes nothing about the dialect port. From Macau. Usual.
I have already asked for information about the Creoles, but I have not yet got anything; This study also interests me about regarding Portuguese. I look forward to the 2 new booklets that promises me. (…) Without anymore I am a friend, J. Vasconcelos Leite, Porto, S. Victor, 25 ”.
Hugo Schuchardt's interest in Luso-Asian Creole has been studied by Hugo Cardoso, a researcher and professor at the Faculty of Letters of the University of Lisbon (FLUL), a Creole specialist who developed investigation at the University of Macao.
The academic recently led a lecture at the National Library in Lisbon over the linguist born in Gotha, Germany, in 1842 and died in Graz, Austria, in 1927, being considered one of the most important linguists of the late nineteenth and early twentieth century. The session was called “Hugo Schuchardt and the search for the Luso-Asian Creole”.
Despite Schuchardt's interest on Macao's Creole, he did not publish any academic work on the subject, as he told HM Hugo Cardoso. "Schuchardt did not publish any work on Macau. However, when he covered his correspondence, it is clear that Macau was also on his radar, since he discusses the Macao Creole with several of his correspondents, including Vasconcelos milk and Gonçalves Viana," he said.
After the German linguist, Hugo Cardoso highlights, “there were actually several people who leaned over Macau Creole, including Danilo Barreiros, José dos Santos Ferreira (Adé), Graciete Batalha, Ana Maria Amaro and, more recently, Prof. Raúl Gaião and Prof. Mário Pinharanda Nunes”. Also noteworthy is the study of Marie Arana-ward "about the Creole spoken by the descendants of Macanese in Hong Kong."
This is another change of correspondence with Vasconcelos milk, dated December 28, 1889, in which books and dictionaries are mentioned about Portuguese and Chinese. “Exmo. Friend: I hurried to respond to your ticket, since you are in a hurry. What I know from China-Portuguese is as follows: J. A. Gonçalves,-Portuguese Dictionary and China-Portuguese. Macau 1831;-China art, Alphabeto and Grammatica. (…) I estimate you to have good shoes. Friend thanks, José Leite de Vasconcellos ”.
The role of rabbit
Hugo Cardoso, whose doctoral thesis is called “The Indo-Portuguese Language of Diu”, former territory of the so-called Portuguese India along with Goa and Damão, spoke at the National Library of Hugo Schuchardt's Studies around this Creole and also the language of Batávia/Tugu in Indonesia.
For the professor at FLUL, pioneering in the study of the Creoles is an expression that rhymes with Schuchardt. The German linguist was "absolutely pioneering in this domain, not only in the study of the Luso-Sasitive Creole or even the Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles globally, but in the study of Creole languages ​​in general" and, for this reason, is "a larger figure in the history of linguistics."
Hugo Cardoso also points out that "as regards the Portuguese lexical base creoles, before him, there had been some activity, especially by Adolfo Coelho, who, in 1881, had published" The Romanesque or Neo-Latin dialects in Africa, Asia and America, "in which he was a caught in several Portuguese-based Creole." However, in this work, Adolfo Coelho refers only to three Luso-Asiatic Creole: “Ceylon's (at Sri Lanka), Malaca and Macau's-giving some examples that he could get from previous publications (such as Macau's Ta-Ss-Yang-Kuo magazine)”.
The academic has no doubt that “Hugo Schuchardt was surely inspired by Rabbit's work, but his efforts to obtain primary data from many other Asian places greatly expanded the cartography of the Luso-Asian Creole and resulted in the first published news and the first grammatical descriptions of many of them (such as Diu, Cananor, Mahé, Mangolor, Mangar, Mangar etc.) ”.
Future inspirations
According to Hugo Cardoso, the German linguist left works that inspired future academics and many materials from the personal archive. "One effect of his work was to inspire other agents to develop similar work: there stands out the figure of Sebastião Rodolfo Dalgado, who led his own research and made his own publications about the Indo-Portuguese Creoles that Schuchardt had not approached, about Damão, Bombaim, Ceylon and Negapath."
In the case of José de Leite Vasconcelos, who wrote the letter cited at the beginning of this text, "it also corresponded with Schuchardt and reveals, in his linguistic studies, the impact of Schuchardt's work."
Asked by HM about the possible interconnections between the Creole of IUD, Batávia and Macao, Hugo Cardoso states that there are "continuities between the various Luso-Asian Creole, but also many differences." "The Batávia/Tugu Creole is the one that most resembles Creole de Macao, for example, at the Lexicon level. But this is understandable because it has already shown that Macao Creole has an important historical connection with the Creole that developed in Southeast Asia, in particular Malaca."
According to an academic article by Hugo Cardoso himself written in partnership with Tjerk Hagemeijer and Nélia Alexandre, entitled “Portuguese Lexical Base Creoles”, these “were, in most cases, oral languages ​​to the nineteenth century, when the first collections of oral traditions, texts and translations began to emerge, being linked“ to maritime expansion in Africa and Asia, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact, the result of the contact between the contact. Portuguese and different African and Asian languages ​​”.
Also according to the same article, "some of these Crioulos, namely in Asia, were extinguished, having only recorded from the transition from the nineteenth century to the twentieth century. With the exception of the Creole of Alta Guinea, the vitality of the living Portuguese Creole is generally decreasing."
In the case of Creoles of Portuguese origin in the southern Asia area, they emerged from the arrival of Vasco da Gama to Calecute, India, in 1498, especially from the phase in which the entire base of the Portuguese empire the East focuses on Goa. According to the same academic article, several Creole were developed, the so-called “Indo-Portuguese” in coastal areas of India, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh and Burma. "Currently, its presence is much reduced: they survive those of IUD, Damão, Korlai, Cananor and Sri Lanka (Ceylon) - which, despite having, has once been used all over the island, is currently restricted to the cities of Batticaloa and Trinchomalee," is highlighted in the article. The author draws attention to the extinction in 2010 of the Vaipim Creole, in Cochim, due to the "death of what seems to have been the last fluent speaker in this region." There are then the Southeast Asia and East Asia Creole, which includes Macao. Patuá is currently “spoken with native fluency only by some people in Macau and the Macanese diaspora”, is mentioned.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 01:19:43</pubDate></item><item><title>PME | Events promoted by Melco generated $ 1 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/pme-eventos-promovidos-pela-melco-geraram-1-milhao-de-dolares/</link><description>Melco Resorts claims to have generated about $ 1 million for small and medium -sized local businesses through events promoted last year. In the 2024 sustainability report, the game operator also highlights the results in terms of waste management and energy spending
 
The Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment Sustainability Report has just been published last year, which highlights the gains obtained by small and medium -sized (SMEs) with the events promoted by the operator. With regard to the “community engagement and investment” part, it is read that “more than $ 1.02 million for local companies and [NGO] non-governmental organizations in Macao through 21 SME events, with 603 SME and NGO participants” were generated. In addition, in the volunteering area, Melco points out that "about 3,600 participants offered their time and effort in more than 359 volunteering initiatives," "more than $ 17.42 million that were donated to decent causes in our communities."
Quoted by the report, Lawrence Ho, Melco's president and executive director, says that "21 Heart of House initiatives and community events have generated more than $ 1 million for local companies in Macao, providing 603 SMEs and NGO opportunities to connect, expand and grow." According to the official, last year were "in -depth partnerships with PME and NGO".
Regarding the relationship with local SMEs, Melco also highlights the connection with the supply chain, because “86 percent of acquisitions arose from local companies in Macao”, and of this total, “59 percent were local SME acquisitions”. Similar scenario occurred in the other operators that Melco holds in Cyprus and Manila, with local acquisitions around 40 and 76 percent, respectively.
Regarding the company's training actions, Melco says it has invested on average "582 US dollars per full -time worker in learning and development activities, which is equivalent to an average of 38 hours of training." In this context, “100 percent of colleagues participated in training actions”, can be read. In addition, "over 758,000 participants have attended more than 1,400 courses offered by" Melco Learning Academy ", which is equivalent to over 870,000 hours of learning." Also noteworthy is that, in all Melco projects, "women represent 23 percent of the boards of business and 32 percent of the higher paintings."
The report also tells that “63 percent of positions at the vice-presidency level, or above this post, were filled from local communities, increasing to 70 percent in Macao”, can read.
All for the environment
Another of the areas highlighted in Melco's sustainability report concerns environmental policies. One of the areas that is “in progress” is the energy consumption, in order to obtain more reasonableness of consumption. "In 2024, despite an increase of 39 percent in terms of the number of visitors and the rise of 19 percent in the occupation rate of the hotel rooms, along with the addition of a property and a new resort integrated into our portfolio, the energy intensity increased by 10 percent from 2023, but was 19 percent lower than our year of reference 2019."
One of the “achieved” objectives is the energy efficiency measures, which “since 2018 has resulted in an annualized savings of more than 62.5 million kWh, an increase of 9 percent compared to 2023”. Another "achieved" goal concerns the installation of "over 25,000 photovoltaic panels on all properties in Macau, Manila and Cyprus, generating about 10,000 kWh annually." Thus, in the properties of Melco "the electricity consumption from renewable sources increased by 72 percent compared to 2023".
Regarding the group's means of transportation, “buses, electric and hybrid vehicles represent 55 percent of our combined fleet, with loading stations, an increase of 25 percent compared to 2023”.
In terms of materials and waste management, Melco says it has avoided plastic spending in the order of 13.2 million bottles, thanks to the installation of “the Nordaq water filtering system that serves almost every hotel rooms in Melco Integrated Resorts”.
In addition, the example of the City of Dreams venture in Manila is presented where “a circular economy system was established in which food waste is decomposed on site, and the excess donated to a local fifth to cultivate some of the vegetables served to guests”.
In terms of water consumption, the report indicates that “despite the increase in the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate”, “total water consumption and water intensity increased only 6 and 2 percent compared to 2023, respectively, and were 6 and 30 percent lower, respectively, to the 2019 reference year”. However, this is a goal that, according to the company, is still "in progress".
Another objective highlighted in the report was the “annual economy of over 510,820 cubic meters of water through water efficiency measures, an increase of 10 percent compared to 2023.
"As we invest in people and communities, we continue to develop environmental efforts with the same determination. (…) The intensity of energy and water consumption, as well as greenhouse gas emissions, remained significantly below our 2019 base line, even adding a new property and an integrated resort," says Lawrence Ho.
The entrepreneur also referred to the increase "of the amount of valuable materials diverted through recycling and composting in global operations - 58 percent over last year." “In our restoration spaces we also fight food waste, with the 'clean dish challenge' to contribute to a 9 percent reduction in waste in the Macao and Manila restoration areas.”
“Mentality change”
For Lawrence Ho, greater sustainability in Melco requires "a change of mindset" verified in "small actions that, on scale, can have a significant impact."
Regarding the supply chain of the group's integrated hotels and resorts, good results are also highlighted. "Although the numbers do not always show exponential heels, our focus on responsible supply remains unwavering, 18 percent of all seafood bought by weight to be sustainable sources, and 100 percent of our food and drink points in Macao and Manila to serve eggs of outdoor chickens," he reads.
There is thus "an effort that reflects a deeper ambition to incorporate sustainability into acquisitions," said Lawrence Ho, who added that "more than one service, hospitality has to do with the experience it creates, the people it supports and the impact it leaves."
“Every year, Melco challenges himself to go further, believing that luxury and responsibility are not opposite forces, but partners in progress, which is reflected in the way we defend strong governance, we manage our environmental impact, we support our people and communities and lead the responsible game. This commitment to progress shaped our approach in 2024, as a year of recalibration in which we continue to strengthen operations, operations, rekindle the impetus and ensure that our integrated resorts remain at the forefront of excellence, ”he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:08:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Seismos | Macau will have a monitoring station in national partnership</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/sismos-macau-vai-ter-estacao-de-monitorizacao-em-parceria-nacional/</link><description>The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, presented on Wednesday the report of the 2025 government lines for his tutelage, and said to the deputies that a seismo monitoring station will be created in partnership with interior authorities from China will be created.
 
The Macao government announced on Wednesday the creation, together with the interior authorities of China, of a seismic monitoring station, as part of the authorities' plans to reinforce disaster prevention. “The meteorological and seismic monitoring network will be optimized, and is foreseen, in collaboration with the competent services of the interior of China, the construction of a seismic monitoring station,” said the secretary for public works and transport, by presenting, in the Legislative Assembly (AL), the lines of government action (LAG) for the guardianship, for 2025.
Raymond Tam will justified the new station with the intention of "increasing the capacity for analysis and evaluation in the scope of natural disasters." The space has realized in the direction of the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG), will be located in Hengqin.
"Macao's earthly area is small and population density is very high, so it is difficult to find space for the creation of monitoring stations and now with the favorable policies with Guangdong province, we have been able to build a joint monitoring station in the cooperation zone [deepened between Guangdong and Macau]," SMG director Leong Weng Kun said. The official noted that the space should contribute to "increasing prevention capacity and public knowledge about weather information."
Agree
Macao and Zhuhai signed the “comprehensive and deepened cooperation project in the context of meteorology” to reinforce the cooperation and sharing of meteorological detection equipment, computer programs and data sharing, according to a statement released by SMG at that time.
Cooperation is also expected to reinforce the “joint prevention of weather catastrophs alert systems, promote scientific and technological research and the development of artificial intelligence applied to weather activity”.
Macau is often affected between May and November by the passage of Tuffons, being July to September the period in which the highest incidence of tropical storms is recorded. This year, the territory is expected to be affected by between five to eight tropical storms, SMG announced in March.
Light Metro | Secretary admits operating gaps
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam said on Wednesday that the light meter is still short of the expectations of the population. "I have to confess that the services of the Light Metro, namely the electronic payment services, are still short of the expectations of the population of Macao," he said, promising measures for the means of transport to improve "gradually".
Environment | Policies planning will be studied this year
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works Raymond Tam announced on Wednesday that this year will be "Study for the Next Planning of Environmental Protection", to support new "environmental policies based on a scientific and prospective view." Still in the area of ​​the environment, the ruler promised measures to achieve the national objective of the “double carbon goal”. As such, concrete emission reduction shares will be driven, including legislative elaboration for the control of emissions from non -road mobile sources, the slaughter of highly polluting vehicles, the improvement of the electric vehicle charging network, the exploitation of the potential application of photovoltaic energy in public spaces and the optimization of the energy structure ”, concluded the report.
Housing | Government admits to review the whole policy
With the reduction of demand for economic housing, the government admits to review all housing policy. "We are reviewing our policy at this time, taking into account the changes recorded. We will evaluate if there is a need to review the policy of five housing classes, but it is a subject that is still being studied," said Raymond Tam, Secretary for Transport and Public Works in the debate on the government lines for this year. The ruler said that "public housing policies will be reviewed and perfected, promoting the construction of social and economic housing and ensuring rational availability, in order to satisfy the housing needs of residents with different levels of income." Lots of zone A of new landfills should be completed between 2026 and 2028.</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:08:32</pubDate></item><item><title>CCAC | Promised Righteous and Stable Business Environment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/ccac-prometido-ambiente-empresarial-integro-e-estavel/</link><description>The commissioner against corruption, Ieong Seong, has ensured that the institution will contribute to “a righteous, fair, stable and predictable business environment” to allow “companies to invest and develop without worries”. This is how the Commissioner reacted to the visit to Macao de Xia Baolong, director of the Hong Kong and Macao Working Office of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office with the Council of State.
The Commissioner, through a statement, stated that the speech of director Xia Baolong presented "clear demands on the future development of Macao and the contribution to the construction of the country and that at the same time had a guiding meaning for the work of CCAC."
According to Ao Ieong Seong's report, Xia Baolong left as expectations for the business sector to promote the "spirit of fighting" and "Union of the Homeland, Hong Kong and Macau". In addition, Xia has indicated entrepreneurs that she has to "maintain a firm confidence in development, consolidating and expanding business in Hong Kong and Macau", while expected to enjoy "their own advantages to overcome the challenges and widen the opening abroad and to affirm themselves in the international panorama."
According to Ieong Seong, the interior ruler also expects local entrepreneurs to tell "the world the story of Hong Kong, Macau and China, with a firm position."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:16:01</pubDate></item><item><title>National Security | Alert for US -related risks and “western countries”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/seguranca-nacional-alerta-para-riscos-ligados-a-eua-e-paises-ocidentais/</link><description>The Secretary for Security has warned the population that the defense of national security is an obligation of all, and that it is necessary to maintain attention to “hegemonic acts” and defamations from the United States of America and Western countries
 
Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, considers that the population has to maintain the "spirit of struggle" and "not giving", in view of what "hegemonic acts" and defamations from the United States of America and Western countries. The message was left on Wednesday, on the secretary's portal, and appears following the visit to Macao de Xia Baolong, director of Hong Kong's work office and Macau of the China Communist Party Central Committee and Cabinet Director for Hong Kong and Macau affairs to the Council of State.
"Currently, given the accelerated evolution of centenary changes in the world and the most intense strategic competition between China and the United States of America, the risks that affect Macao's national security and social stability become increasingly serious," was written on the secretary's portal.
The message identifies the risks such as the “hegemonic acts of the US and Western countries” as well as “words and actions that destroy, defame and disturb Macao”, considering that “Macao society must identify the situation, maintain position firmly, cultivate the spirit of struggle, and cannot give in”.
Wong Sio Chak also warns that all residents are expected to act as national security guardians. "The defense of national security is the responsibility of all. All residents of Macao are the beneficiaries and guardians of national security, no one is left out," is bound. “The Society of Macao must remain united, have a firm confidence, convey the good tradition of love for the homeland and Macau, to enhance their own advantages, contribute to the construction of a strong country and the revitalization of the Chinese nation, and tell the story of 'one country, two systems',” he was added.
Hostile and criminals
At the same time, the ruler highlights the need to act in peacetime against “hostile and criminals” because it is more worth preventing. “We must predict possible dangers in peacetime, as it is better to prevent remedy,” he was written. "The Society of Macao should value the current favorable situation of stability and prosperity more, should be aware of the crises, give high importance to the problems we face in the scope of Macao's development and security, support the government government to reinforce system development, properly resolve the risks, to resolutely prevent the interference and destruction of hostile and criminals," has been added.
The text also points out that Macao's safety protection will fulfill the "demands made by" Xi Jinping and "dynamically fulfill the sacred mission to safeguard national security, creating high level security to ensure high quality development."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:14:18</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin | Leader fires after investigation for corruption</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/hengqin-dirigente-demite-se-apos-investigacao-por-corrupcao/</link><description>The Government of MSAR has announced that a deputy director of the executive committee of the in-depth cooperation zone has resigned "for personal reasons." The statement does not mention that Su Kun resigned hours after a corruption investigation was released to a state company responsible for the development of Hengqin
 
Lame
"At the request of Su Kun, his duties as advisor to the Secretary's Office for the Economy and Finance and Deputy Chief of the Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone ceases from May 15, 2025, for personal reasons." Thus, in just one sentence, that the Government of MSAR reacted, through the Secretary's Office for Economics and Finance, to a statement issued hours earlier by the Guangdong Province Anti -Corruption Commission to announce the investigation into a corruption case involving a state company responsible for the development of Hengqin.
Su Kun is one of the six deputy coordinators of the executive committee of the in-depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau. According to the Macao Government Portal, this commission “assumes the functions of promoting international dissemination, business and investment capture, industry introduction, land exploitation, construction of specific projects and management of subjects concerning the life of the population”.
Things of Life
Su Kun's resignation happens hours after the Guangdong Neighboring Neighborhood Anti -Corruption Commission announced the beginning of an investigation to the former president of the state company responsible for the development of the Hengqin Special Zone.
In a statement, Guangdong's Provincial Disciplinary Inspection Commission said the former president of Hengqin's Zhuhai Group, Hu Jia, “is suspected of serious disciplinary violations,” a phrase that usually refers to corruption.
The note, also with only one sentence, says Hu is being the subject of “disciplinary review and investigation” by Zhuhai's Municipal Inspection and Disciplinary Supervision Commission.
The Zhuhai Group of Hengqin was created in 2009 by the Municipality of Zhuhai for the construction and development of the Special Economic Zone of Hengqin and is responsible for investment, financing, construction, operation and infrastructure management.
In the business group website it is indicated that Hu Jia has been the president of Heng Qin Investment since December 2013, and was director general from May 2012 to December 2013. It is also said that HU has held “management positions in a series of public companies, has profound financial knowledge and a vast experience in business operation and management”. In addition, “he has unique knowledge regarding the innovation of business finance models, urban design concepts, business group management and business talent introduction”.
It is necessary to integrate
Lusa asked the Macao government yesterday if Su Kun's resignation is related to corruption investigation against Hu Jia, but until the closing of this edition received no response.
Sam Hou Fai, who took office in December as chief executive, has defended a greater bet on integration with Hengqin. The development of the neighboring island “is our main task,” said the leader of the Government of Masters to journalists on Tuesday.
Sam was speaking at a Six -day visit to Macao from the Chinese Communist Party's leading Macao for the affairs of the two semi -autonomous regions, Xia Baolong. On Monday, the director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office, under the tutelage of the Council of State, said that "the construction of hengqin should be treated as a priority of Macao."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:06:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Consulate | Sea Policy Director in Macau and HK</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/consulado-directora-da-politica-do-mar-em-macau-e-hk/</link><description>Marisa Lameiras da Silva, Director-General of the Directorate-General of Sea Policy, an entity linked to the Portuguese Government Ministry of Economy, will be in Macau and Hong Kong today and tomorrow for a series of activities and meetings with rulers. Today, the Portuguese government representative brings together, at 4:30 pm, with the secretary for the transport and logistics of the Hong Kong executive, Mable Chan.
Tomorrow, it is the turn to take place meetings with MSAR rulers, namely Susana Wong, director of maritime and water services, as well as IP Kuong Lam, director of environmental protection services.
Also tomorrow, from 11:40 am, the “Oceans - Future” forum will take place at the Portuguese School of Macao, which also has Marisa da Silva, Consul, Alexandre Leitão, and Hidy Yu, president and founder of Bling Ocean Foundation of Hong Kong, Hidy Yu. The Macao International Institute hosts tomorrow, from 3 pm, the “Blue Talk” debate on “Sustainable Blue Economy - an Ocean of Opportunities”, with the Consul, and the academics Cristina Calheiros, Yanan Song and Jorge Rangel, president of IIM.
The “Blue Talks” initiative was born from the will of the consulate general of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong of “resuming the concept and launching the cycle” of debates by joining the two territories, and tomorrow begins.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:22:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao prepares digital currency for trade between China and Lusophone countries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/macau-prepara-moeda-digital-para-comercio-entre-china-e-paises-lusofonos/</link><description>Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, revealed that he intends to finalize the Pataca Digital system in 2025 and use it as a commercial settlement instrument for transactions between China and Portuguese-speaking countries
"We hope that Digital Pataca can be used as one of the digitized transaction instruments for Portuguese-speaking countries, commercial transactions, and sino-Portuguese transactions," said Anton Tai Kin IP.
In response to deputies' questions during the Legislative Assembly session, the secretary confirmed that the central digital currency system should be finalized by the end of 2025, following a series of technical tests. "The first phase of implementation will focus on retail transactions before expanding to gross applications," said Tai. "We then intend to leave Macau to connect with the Portuguese Language platform," he added.
It is recalled that a delegation led by Tai Kin IP was in Lisbon in early March, having met with leaders of Banco de Portugal, including administrator Luís Morais Sarmento.
At the end of March, the secretary's office announced in a statement that the various meetings served to “negotiate the consolidation and deepening of cooperation between Macao and Portugal in the areas of science, technology, economy and commerce”.
Tai Kin IP told deputies on Tuesday that he would continue to visit more Portuguese-speaking countries in the future to seek support for the use of Digital Pataca.
The secretary promised to take advantage of Digital Pataca as a currency whose circulation will be free through the borders of Macao, an economy open to the flow of capital. On the contrary, the Chinese currency, Renmimbi, is not entirely convertable in other currencies, and Beijing authorities impose a strict control on the flow of capital, especially out of the country.
Digital seeds
Trading between Portuguese -speaking countries and China reached $ 225.2 billion last year, 2 percent more than in 2023, according to data from China customs services.
The prototype of the Macao Digital Pataca System (e-Mop) was launched on December 12, eight days before the end of the term of the previous government leader, Ho Iat Seng.
In September, the then financial regulator of the region said that Pataca Digital could “serve as an example for Portuguese -speaking countries”. Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM) President Benjamin Chan Sa San spoke during the second conference of the central banks and financial banks governors between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries, which took place in Macao.
At the opening of the event, Ho Iat Seng said E-Mop's development was supported by the Government and Central Bank of China, which was the world's first major economy to launch a digital currency, the Digital Renmimbi or E-CNY in August 2020.
In September, AMCM explained that, before the official launch of Pataca Digital, it would take tests to identify risks and “establish laws and regulations”. The regulator stressed that, unlike private cryptocurrencies (the best known to Bitcoin), E-MOP will be “a currency with legal course”, with the same legal status and monetary value as Pataca currencies and physical notes.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Metro | People's Covenant defends acceleration of connection to China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/metro-alianca-do-povo-defende-aceleramento-de-ligacao-a-china/</link><description>The covenant of the people wants the planning of the Light Metro Network to take into account the links to Zhuhai and the National Railway Network. A guardian linked to the Fujian community argues that the light meter should be the main transport in Macao, with buses playing a complementary role
 
The slight meter should be the main means of public transport in Macao, while buses move to a secondary and complementary role. The position was taken by Tong Ho Laam, vowel of the executive board of the Povo's covenant of Macao, the official name, in statements to the newspaper or Mun.
Given the expected increase in demand and pressure on the public transport network and traffic in the city, the official indicated that the government should actively promote the strategy of making the meter light the main means of transportation in the city to relieve road pressure. Tong Ho Laam understands that when the lightweight metro stations network is extended, it will increase the overall effectiveness of public transport and ensure better experiences to residents and tourists. One of the improvements that can be implemented in the short-term is the ability to use electronic payments and harmonize the connection with buses.
In addition, the People's Covenant leader argues that the planning of Light Metro stations should be done in articulation with the Regional Industrial Development Strategy. An essential point is to ensure the connection with the national rail network through Zhuhai, a work that should be accelerated to reinforce Macao's position in the Great Bay.
The vowel believes that the connection to China, namely Hengqin, can bring a new impetus to the local industrial sector to pursue emerging areas at the Traditional Chinese Technological Innovation and Mountain Medicine poles.
Cure for all ills
Given the energy challenges resulting from the fight against climate change, the associative leader argues that the development of the light meter should be thought of from a long-term perspective, taking into account environmental protection. To this end, the MSar should reserve land for green energy production facilities to feed the slight meter. Tong Ho Laam pointed out this objective as a way for the Mand to stand out in environmental terms in the Great Bay area, adopting leadership in the goal of carbonic neutrality, while promoting economic diversification.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:39:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching | IA contents transmitted to local students</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/ensino-conteudos-sobre-ia-transmitidos-a-alunos-locais/</link><description>The Macao government says it is preparing students, teaching system and teachers for artificial intelligence, providing didactic materials in schools, classes and organizing training actions. Deputies also want initiatives on artificial intelligence outside schools
 
Schools and teachers are preparing for the reality of Artificial Intelligence (IA). According to the secretary's explanations for Social Affairs and Culture, the LAM, the Directorate of Services for Youth Education and Development (DSEDJ) “intends to provide AI content or related to science and technology, with an average duration of 10 hours per year, computer teachers and 6 hours to teachers of other subjects”, was referred to yesterday in response to an oral interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai. The first actions already took place in the current school year.
In addition, the secretary confirmed that schools can adhere to manuals that include AI teachings. "Several reference materials on the interior of China were introduced for adoption in schools," said Lam.
Last year, DSEDJ joined South China Normal University to "establish a new basis for learning and exchange focusing on AI teaching." In this context, “didactic materials of this institution on the AI” are made available, and invitations are foreseen to “interior experts and academics to provide training and support for teaching staff in the development of AI teaching activities”.
At the legislative level, the executive says he made the necessary changes to “the program and teaching of AI become part of the curricula of primary and secondary schools”, and it is intended that “AI contents can be integrated into the curriculum guidelines of information technology classes”. The government intends to make the “interleavement evaluation of the planning of non-higher education in Macao, to build an innovative technological support system”, taking into account the “general lines of planning for the construction of a large educational power (2024-2035)”.
LAM indicated that, through the financing of the Educational Fund, it is intended to “optimize facilities and school equipment” to improve science teaching and create the “AI” classrooms project.
In this context, DSEDJ launched this year the pilot project of “Intelligent Teaching” to which 25 schools joined. "The established goal is to make the platform available to all secondary schools in Macao in the school year 2026/2027," the secretary said yesterday.
I was going to everyone
One of the interveners in yesterday's debate was Deputy Zheng Anting, who defended the partnership with playing operators for the creation of “AI classes” in hotels, in conjunction with tourists who pass through these spaces or even in community neighborhoods, “for populations to have greater contact with AI”. "We can develop actions in partnership with the six dealers, because they already have visitors," he added.
Regarding the AI ​​relationship with the population and the promotion of literacy in this area for adults, a representative of the Macau Science Center said this space can be “an open classroom so that, outside schools, new knowledge and learning scenarios of AI can be provided”.
"We will collaborate with more technology companies, because we want to have more technological resources to support this scientific background. The Science Center will create different measures to improve the digital literacy of the population by introducing AI, and so we can generalize education for AI for the whole society. The evolution of AI has been fast and we will invite experts to share the most advanced techniques and employment trends in this area, in order to create an AI training platform.
The official said that "shift workers could access this type of resources." LAM has ensured that the future goes through the "generalization of AI education for residents" and, for this, the government will "dialogue with associations so that these measures have a greater effect."</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:36:13</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great America (III)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/a-grande-america-iii-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the May 15th edition)
And then they said, too many times, that Europe is in the laws of history, but who knows these laws of history? And who has ever prevented men, especially the great men, from going against the laws of history? We were in 1966. Sumantra Maitra is right when asking them "what happened to you? To exhort them, with some emphasis, to the role of a" key western country. "
His thesis crosses the geopolitics of the maritime periphery of forty -end memory, updated for current crises, such as the tensions between Turks, Greeks and French, the attcluded allies of fact aligned with themselves. What happens if a conflict bursts? Italy could focus on creating local devices in some key areas, assuming the task of providing logistical and structural support.
Italians have a well -structured navy. This is a domain in which they could make a considerable contribution, dealing with training and safety in the southern and north back. Trump and the Pentagon are correct, as we the Europeans provide logistics, along with secret services, cybernetics and anything useful. But it is the Italians who put their boots on the ground.
An idea that they rejected when Trump 1.0 invited them to recover Libya. It was not a matter of imitating the failed landing conceived by the then Chairman of the Council of Ministers Giovanni Giolitti (1903-1914) in Tripoli, in 1911, the World War I Spark, the coup for the communities of North Africa and Italian Levantinas they need so much.
The question was whether they should admit a strong degree of Turkish control over Tripolitania, then Russian control over Cyrenaica, or taking care of its own backyard. Refused. An error that should serve as a lesson for the future. The stigma of our time is the awareness that man can end the world. A privilege so far reserved for God for Christians, who has the last word about how and when. A secret that opposes Christ, at least according to Matthew that “heaven and earth will pass, but my words do not.
As for that day and that hour, no one knows, neither the angels of heaven, nor the son, but only the Father ”(24,35-36).“ If the owner of the house knew what the time the thief comes, he would watch and not let his house be broken into. Therefore, you are also prepared, because the Son of man will come to the time when you least expect it ”(24: 43-44). If this gospel applies, we are sure that the thief is away from home, for never before man has thought in the end.
It remains for us to expect the mysterious “Katechon” of Paul's second letter to the Thessalonians, the supposed containment force that prevails over chaos, delayed the apocalypse and the coming of Jesus. If philosophers and theologians argue about “Katechon” it is because we live the apocalypse as a gift, not as a future. Immersed in chaos, disfigured by the wicked anomos that the Lord will crush “with the breath of his mouth” (2,8).
Is it a sign of the times that the Catholic Church, for centuries committed to inflicting ourselves "Mori", has softened this litany after Hiroshima? Perhaps you fear losing the latest mystery monopoly, secularized in coffee conversation. We don't get in the passionate diatribe of whose, what, how is the "katechon". Unattainable hermeneutics. What matters is to observe how the perception of living within the apocalypse, living death, exacerbates the despair of the chaos that paralyzes us. It deceives us to think that we can escape the constraints of politics, the way of reason, the art of the symposium. A temptation that generates terrible simplifiers of all kinds.
Anomie producers who want to perform with the breath of their mouth. Is Trump the power that slows or speeds up the American crisis? A very European question. For an American, the question does not arise. Those who are convinced that they belong, by grace of divine mandate, to the benevolent supreme entity, super sorted to the rest of humans, tend to imagine their trajectory as a sequence of cycles in constant ascending evolution. Drawing endless circles, just starting. In the lower stages, the American believer pushes to the top because the best is yet to come.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:41:51</pubDate></item><item><title>The Great America (III)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/a-grande-america-iii/</link><description>“We Are Going Through a Bad Stage in the Cold War-All Wars have ther Bad Stages. But in All Wars When one is gouing thound a Bad Stage One Should Concentrate First and Foomos on the Core of the Problem;
Weaknesses of Western Society
Pietro Quaroni
In recent years, we have been watching an unprecedented interest from Americans in Europe. Initially it was "what do you want from us?" A mixture of condescension and sympathetic contempt, which raises embarrassing answers or simply silence, since we are not used to establishing what we can want. Then the sudden turn to "what would they do in our place?" Until Trump's counterattack. With it there are no questions, only pre-placed or improvised agreements. All extremely informal on the basis that "we want this, they can help us like this, in return they receive that other. Good luck." Of course, firepower is totally disproportionate. Deadly is retaliation in case of insubordination. The example may be that if we make state -of -the -art trade with Chinese technologies, we must at least expect reprisals on customs rights and visa regime over the table, with steps accompanied underneath.
Which forces us to know beforehand what we can want from the leader and at what price. Nothing extraordinary. Tactical variants of a strategy. This should be based on our geostrategic income, which we not only neglect but even undermine. The southern continent is Mediterranean first, European in second. But this privilege is lived as a shame. They did not take advantage of the advantage of the mid-oceanic turning point they enjoyed since the opening of Suez, which today risks closing disastrously due to the Red Sea crisis. His sea gaze sees his inner waters as a limit and not as a source that pushes them to the world and the world to them.
Among the harmful inheritances of their Europeanism and the inferiority complex associated with continental nations, hydrophobia is the most harmful. The secret figure of their strategy escapes them because they are Western because they are medium-oceanic, not because they are European. Its continental neighbors, starting with the Germans, are by anti-medium-ocean vocation. Since time immemorial. As the “School of Annales” states, the concept of Europe was born against Rome, when the Islamic tide broke the Mare Nostrum in two, between the 18th and eighth centuries. A fracture that continues to resolve and to get worse. The Italians remain the passive center, at best reactive hypotheses of the middle ocean, after their decisive pivot.
Ridiculous disguise themselves with pivots. It is urgent to make sense of its western advanced geography in the middle of the ocean. And that this counts more on Germany and France, which are directly facing the world ocean, while they have to defend with nails and teeth the exit through Suez and Bab-El-Mandeb (the Bab-El-Mandeb Strait in Arabic, “gateway” is the epicenter of the vast maritime region that extends from the Red Sea to the Indian Ocean Officer, Also encompassing the Gulf of Aden and part of the Arabic Sea. This strangulation, which is only twenty-seven kilometers wide at its narrower point, near the island of Perim, separates the horn from Africa from the Middle East and serves as an antechamber to the Suez Canal, the artificial passage that, since the second half of the nineteenth century, connects the Indo-Pacific Limits to the Atlantic system through the Mediterranean).
Together with those who will be willing to treat them as partners in the middle of the ocean. First, and certainly not only, the United States. They feel here in debt to the great Italian diplomat Pietro Quaroni (their thoughts and actions are described in “Pietro Quaroni, Italian Diplomacy and the Libyan Issue (1945-1949)” by Luciano Monzali) who belonged to this race of state servants who understood this privilege as a contribution to foreign policy. Even contrary to intellectual fashion, resisting the temptation of bureaucracy and politicking. Its golden pamphlet on the “Atlantic Pact and Freedom Security”, published sixty years ago, is of a fulminating current. Pietro Quaroni suggested that they "fit into an peripheral American policy" within NATO, evolving from a "sea power" into a "maritime power." The Thalassocratic Theater distinguishes them from their continental partners and gives them greater freedom of movement than France and Germany.
Expressed in the “peripheral defense based on the outer waist of Europe, England, Iberian Peninsula, Italy and Greece”. Not being a naval power, it is capital to revive them bilateral understanding with America as the first Mediterranean power, as happened with England while still dominating the waves. While their foreign policy remained firm in the beginning that they could take all freedoms except to turn against England, any foolishness they had done had serious consequences; The day they forgot this principle, the consequences would be such that they would still remember them. Today, instead of England, are the United States, and it is the first need for Italian politics to understand with the United States as Giorgia Meloni intends. They should not be dragged on behalf of a alleged Europe for a European policy that is in fact-the-American.
(Continues)</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:19:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Seagull</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/gaivota/</link><description>Those who watched the beginning of the conclave certainly noticed in the seagull that stopped by the chimney where at this time the smoke should be visible in the face of expectant eyes of thousands of people and media, but in such an unexpected presence this moment became an almost prophetic signal. We all remember the radius that fell into the Vatican to when the abdication of Benedict XVI and the strange impression caused, a man who came from the end of the world after the succeeding one would sit in Peter's chair like a seagull, all in white, hovering papal purple with a little spending Argentine shoes remembering the fisherman's sandals.
The signs walk everywhere, sometimes emphatic and rude as it was the case with the image of Trump as Pope, this funestal desecration that can be subliminal and nauseating effect as measure for all things, calling, perhaps, attention to subjects concretely manufactured for a final resolution: but if we compare it to this one, we will know the differences, to look at the speech, to look at the speech, to look at the speech, to look at the speech, to look at essential. Superb-laden vestments have never dressed into anyone and still left their dresses, but a chance can put ourselves forever with something we did not know, that in this very short space of time we loose “robes” essences with wings in the promontory of temporal inheritance.
Yeats tell us about white birds believing that all poets love birds, speak to them and interpret them (each certainly in their own way) that always this ethereal nature is their pleasing being part of a wonderful conscience that insists on not lowering for bars, and that's what was there, that lonely seagull coming from the most beautiful soul corner: deleted, and did not disappear; And the light of the blue star, suspended in the twilight by the sake of the sky/… «in-white birds»
There are unexpected things, and this is good- sudden events- that life will not be this true big dazzle where all things communicate differently being those that maintain their essence the most contemplated? Continuity is a wing, a straight to eternity, a rhythm, a cross, or a work, and whatever we look at will be through the eyes of this soul that formed us on the way, but the vision of things is now insinuated in a very blind world that does not have the gift of true invisuals.
No one is irreplaceable and we all have faults, but there are the seagulls, the chimneys, the rays, the stone and the creative wedding that in this May live. Times are harsh but we still do not feel what may mean such an expression, that feeling is not probative of anything until some other than rescues and transcends it. Francisco left his white mobile pope for Palestine to make him an emergency room, and this is seagull.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 22:59:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Queen's College's cadabulas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/os-cabulas-do-hong-kong-queens-college/</link><description>Last April, during the Unified History Test of China at the Hong Kong Queen's College, several students from one of the classes copied. They shouted the answers to each other, consulted the books and the iPads. The vigilante tried several times to stop them, but failed. The board of the college said that it will only punish prevariculars students according to internal rules.
The college also notified parents about this incident, saying that as only a month left for final exams and, to avoid unnecessary pressures about the students, the test will not be repeated. The results of the China Unified History Test of this class will be canceled and the classification to this discipline will depend on the final exam. For the other classes, the classification of China's History discipline will take into account the results of the unified test and the final exam.
Students often happen to copy the tests. With new technologies, the tools that allow them to “make cheats” change every day. From traditional paper rackets to intelligent devices, the evolution of these tools reflects the erosion of academic integrity through the abuse of technology. In the past, the students wrote the answers to pieces of paper, commonly known to rabids, and took them to the exam room; Or asked to go to the bathroom and so they consulted the materials. With the popularization of intelligent clocks, real -time concerted communication functions allow remotely online cabular. If the vigilante is not aware, students can use smart watches for this purpose while sitting in their places. Real -time -time translation functions have recently appeared that can directly convert English to Chinese texts. The constant evolution of these tools makes the work of vigilantes increasingly difficult.
To get a thief, we need evidence. To get a gussy student, you also have to have tests. However, for vigilantes, it is always very difficult to obtain these evidence; If they can't prove that the student copied, it is complicated to accuse him. In the case of the "Cada on paper", the student can swallow or hide it as they are being exposed, or argue with the vigilante and refuse to deliver the rabula. Teachers are not police officers and are not entitled to review students, so several "jams" escape unpunished for lack of tests and naturally cannot be accused. These cases, to some extent, lead other students to risk.
There is certainly no lack of diligent students, scholars and workers in an exam room. When these students discover the colleagues' strokes, they can choose to report them, but if they do the most likely it is to be ostracized and subject to intimidation. In addition, the highly stressful exam environment makes most students focus on their own answers, and have no time or energy to observe others. Therefore, the reports of colleagues represent a small percentage and the exposure of these cases depends on the vigilantes to be committed and want to discover the offenders.
Copy, use fake certificates and plagiarize are all academic violations of the same nature - dishonesty and bad practices. In recent years, it is not difficult to find these cases in the news. Having this incident in one of Hong Kong's oldest elite colleges, reflects not only the moral deviation of the students, but also the distortion of learning values. The more students make glow, the greater the change of values ​​and the less they will study hard.
The “elite” group created by false achievements may seem knowledgeable, but in fact is devoid of value and will eventually expose their lack of knowledge in their areas in the future. Just think: Can a doctor without skills treat a patient? Can a lawyer defend the client without knowing the law? This hidden danger is like a clock pump. Its destructive power continues to manifest in the next decade or even later, and finally the whole society will pay its price. We have to stop this problem.
Schools have to take proper measures, prescribe the right medicine, improve situations that give it azo and cultivate the correct values ​​in students. Containing the jar requires multi-dimensional efforts.
Firstly, students who copy should be severely punished and this behavior cannot be tolerated. Schools must have rules for dealing with unusual behaviors. For example, if at least two vigilantes see a student swallowing papers, it should be disqualified from the exam. After the punishment must be re -educated. Schools must have subjects that deal with academic integrity and compulsory courses that shape the values ​​of learning.
It is necessary to make students understand that a grade of 60 is not shameful, but it is vital that they realize that a false 100 has to be punished. Since this pedagogical idea becomes consensual, society will no longer judge heroes by their grades, students will be able to maintain their moral values ​​and the entrepreneurial spirit of “knowing shame and then learning to be brave” will reappear. Only after stressing the importance of identifying the “real value” of students can education return to its original purpose of “teaching and sharing knowledge”, the reasons that lead to glow can decrease and the promotion of talented people will no longer be a game that compares large and small number.

Legal Consultant of the Association for the Promotion of Jazz in Macau
Associate Professor at the Faculty of Management Sciences, Macau Polytechnic University
Email: cbchan@mpu.edu.mo</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 05:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>"Flashmobs" this weekend in community neighborhoods</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/flashmobs-este-fim-de-semana-nos-bairros-comunitarios/</link><description>This weekend will take place the initiative “Culture to Your Door”, with 16 flashmobs in 12 local community neighborhoods, an event organized by the Cultural Institute (IC).
According to a note from the IC, flashmobs have five themes, namely theater, Cantonense Opera, martial arts, cinema and reading, intending to “bring rich cultural resources to community neighborhoods, nourishing culturally residents in their daily lives and reinforcing their sense of happiness”.
In the area of ​​theater, with the theme “Theater in More Local”, he presents himself “a magic trip to the stage”, in which the audience is intended to explore “different spaces of action, such as the Greek Ancient Amphitheater, the traditional Bambu de Macao Theater and modern theaters, through the format of interactive theater”.
With the theme “Cantonense Opera in Most Local” it is intended that “residents experience this precious art of intangible cultural heritage”, while with “more places in more local”, the “classic movements of Wing Chun on site are presented, where residents can also experience the basic movements under the guidance of instructors and understand the concepts of Chinese marial culture”.
Cinema and Reading
Already with "cinema in more local", "Flashmob" will "turn the community into an outdoor movie theater, where the public will be able to enjoy the documentary about the sector of Macao's" interpretation of images "cinematic exhibition, know the centenary history of industry and the development of cinema."
In turn, through the theme “Read in More Local”, the activity “Exchange one book for another” is carried out, which is also part of the “joint reading month throughout the city of Macau 2025”. Residents will be able to carry books that comply with the rules on site, selecting their favorites and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books, performing the circulation and sharing of reading resources in the community neighborhoods.
The “Culture at Your Door” activity takes place in several mornings and afternoon tomorrow and Sunday, in community or local neighborhoods such as the S. Lourenço Activities Center-Ajardinado Terrace, Taipa Central Park, Iao Da Orchid Square Terrace Leisure Zone, IP PAI VAN VAN VAN-LOUS GARDEN, Rotunda de Carlos da Maia, leisure zone of the Praceta de Venceslau de Morais, Urban of Areia Preta Park, leisure zone contiguous to edif. Wang Hoi and Wang Kin, leisure zone in the social neighborhood of Tamagnini Barbosa and Edf's leisure zone. Lok Yeong Fa Yuen.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:38:03</pubDate></item><item><title>CLOCKENFLAP | Festival features Franz Ferdinand and Beth Gibbons former Portishead singer</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/clockenflap-festival-traz-franz-ferdinand-e-beth-gibbons-ex-vocalista-dos-portishead/</link><description>There is more poster of Clokenflap, a festival that for three days brings a lot of music to Hong Kong, to Central Harbourfront. The first presences are already known and include names like Franz Ferdinand or Beth Gibbons, former Portishead singer. The musical offer is also composed with Rich Brian, Jacob Collier and Yoga Lin, among many others
 
For those who want to enjoy a huge musical variety in that which is considered the monthly birth month, the Clockenflap festival in Hong Kong is back this year for a new edition between December 5 and 7 instead of custom, Central Harbourfront. Tickets began to be sold this week and are already known some names that take the stage: Rich Brian, Jacob Collier, Franz Ferdinand, Yoga Lin, Panther Chan, and Beth Gibbons, former Portishead singer, the Scots that revolutionized the musical world with their 2004 homonymous album and with success like "Take Me Out" or success "This Fire".
The poster also includes Rich Brian, known as “The Indonesian Rap Star”, which acts on Saturday, December 6, Yoga Lin, the great “Pop Mandarin Star”, scheduled for Sunday, 7, and Panther Chan, known local singer and songwriter, scheduled for the first day of the festival, December 5.
Also on Friday, the performances of British singer and songwriter Passenger take place, as well as a DJ set with Germans Digitalism. Also noteworthy is the presence in Hong Kong of Soccer Mommy, "the favorite of the American Alt-Indie," or the Chilli Beans, the "Japanese Indie-Pops." Still in the Indie kingdom, the festival organization features phum viphurit, "dear Thai indie", or the TV girl, considered the "indie Californian heroes."
From Japan, also arrives at Clockenflap the singer and composer Akasaki, who acts on the 6th, or DJ Riria, who was born in Japan, but is living in the United Kingdom. With regard to the talents of local music, Clockenflap brings the Bitter Tea of ​​General Yeng again, "return after a long hiatus." These are considered "mythical post-punk legends of Hong Kong."
Mixture art
There are still many months to close the Clockenflap poster and many surprises can still appear. The organization highlights the iconic space where the festival takes place, “with the spectacular outdoor scenario between the imposing Central skyscrapers and the epic views of the iconic Hong Kong Porto”, presenting again this year “the complete experience of a world class festival that made the event an unmissable occasion for music fans across the city and not alone”.
In addition to music, the festival also includes "a series of eye -stuffing artistic installations, workshops and shows for the whole family and a selection of food and drink to make mouth water, including unique snacks of some of the city's most appreciated restaurants."
One of the artistic news that the festival brings to this edition is the project “Minimax - Mobile &amp; Modular Theatical Experience”, understood by the organization as “a new concept for all art lovers”, currently in the recruitment phase of “local talents”.
The early sale of tickets takes place only until May 23, with discounts, and from that date the tickets become a higher price. Early purchase for the three days for general admission is $ 1,790 from Hong Kong (HKD), while early one day tickets in general admission cost 1,150 HKD.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:35:24</pubDate></item><item><title>FRC welcomes debate today with Sandro Mendonça</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/frc-acolhe-hoje-debate-com-sandro-mendonca/</link><description>Today, from 6.30 pm, the “Roda de Ideias - Creative Environments” session at the Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC), which is attended by Sandro Mendonça, Associate Professor of Economics at ISCTE - University Institute of Lisbon and Professor at the City of Macau. The session, more specifically, addresses the theme “Steering the Evolving Sandbox Economy 'from the Greater Bay to the Portuguese-Speaking Geographies”, focusing on the economies of the great bay in connection with Portuguese-speaking countries.
Thus, it is intended to “explore the concept of experimental innovation zones, the so-called 'sand boxes', such as children's recreational spaces, which allow future advances through the creation of controlled and secure test areas to test, replicate, evaluate, adopt, implement and launch new products, devices, technologies or systems, within a conditioned and provisional structure”.
With these “experimental” environmental processes associated with the economy, effective means of evaluating the development of innovative ideas and projects without ruptures in the normal functioning of business or institutional structures ”. "Greater freedom within these parallel systems [sand boxes] with more dynamic and flexible regulation can be promoted."
Sandro Mendonça focuses on concrete in the Greater Bay region, as it covers “a set of cities that form a techno-institutional innovation center, even Portuguese-speaking countries that begin to use these experimental models, namely in the sectors of telecommunications and energy”.
Long career
This is the third time Sandro Mendonça has a session at the FRC. The first was in 2023, with the lecture “The Change in Communications: from 5G to AI through digital platforms”, and then starred in 2024, the “The Future of Bigtech” session, where he described the balance of forces among the world giants, which include American companies Apple, Amazon, Google (Alphabet), and Microsoft, and Microsoft, and Microsoft, and Microsoft, and Microsoft, and Microsoft Chinese Alibaba and Tencent.
Sandro Mendonça is a full professor in Portugal, Italy and Macau, and also taught in Doctoral Programs in Chengdu (UESTC) and Guangzhou (SMU), China. Its main focus is on innovation and sectoral dynamics.
He received several recognitions in his career, including the German Marshall Fund member of the United States (GMF) and a young European leader from Friends of Europe Foundation. In 2024, he coordinated the report “The Futures of Big Tech in Europe” for the European Commission and was on the list of the world's leading scientists at Stanford University. He is currently advisor to the president of the European Patent Institute (EPO).</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:17:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisboeta Macau welcomes photographs of Hiroshi Sugimoto</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/lisboeta-macau-acolhe-fotografias-de-hiroshi-sugimoto/</link><description>It takes place until June 30 the show “Eternal Imaging’: photography exhibition of Hiroshi Sugimoto ”, patent at the HWA's gallery, in the“ Art H853 ”space in the Lisbon Macao venture.
According to a note from the organization, the public can see “Limited Publications of the renowned Publisher Kyoto Shoin Co., Ltd, Koyanagi Gallery, Tokyo, and Mori Art Museum, also in Tokyo”, and are presented “great -shaped color photographs of the Opticks series, released for the first time in the Kyoto City Kyocera Museum of Arte's commemorative exhibition”.
In the case of the “Seascape” series, created in 1980, the Japanese photographer “records an elementary scene, the sky and the sea”, in a “ancient one that connects today's people to ancient times and that thus reflects eternity”. In turn, in the series of works entitled "Theater", comes "an over-exposed screen that compresses a two-hour movie in a white beam of light, encompassing both our consciousness and our subconscious perceptions."
In the case of the "Opticks" series, "the red, blue and green tones, presenting small colored particles under the lens, show the multifaceted nature of light through the prism." The organizers of the exhibition intend to "awaken the collective memories that are dormant in the images, related to the old, ephemeral and eternity."
The place of philosophy
Born in 1948 in Tokyo, Hiroshi Sugimoto continues to work in this city, but also in New York. Considered a "of photographers with greater philosophical depth in contemporary art," with a work that "explores time, memory, history and the essence of existence through minimalist formats."
Sugimoto is also considered “excellent in using photography as a 'time container', condensing abstract concepts in eternal images that evoke the contemplation of life and cosmos through their serene stillness”.
Since 2023, he has been a member of the Japanese Academy of Arts, having received the National Arts Club photography medal in New York in 2018. The Japanese photographer also belongs to the Real Academy of Belgium, having an honorary doctorate attributed by the prestigious Parsons School of Design, also located in New York, USA. Has works in selected museum collections such as the Modern Museum of Art (MoMA), in New York, or or Metropolitan Museum, in the same city; As well as Tate in London and Getty Museum in Los Angeles, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:15:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Job fairs offer 77 vacancies in stores and hospitality</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/dsal-feiras-de-emprego-oferecem-77-vagas-em-lojas-e-hotelaria/</link><description>Today open the registration for three sessions of employment fairs, which will be held on May 22 and 23 for the sectors of the retail hotel and trade, according to information released yesterday by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). Interested parties can apply until noon next Wednesday and apply for the 77 job vacancies.
The first session, scheduled for the morning of May 22, will provide 11 jobs for “Hotel W Macau - Studio City”, for the positions of Customer Customer Contact Center, Customer Service Agent, Guest, Elementary Level cook and spa receptionist.
In the afternoon of the same day, it is the turn of the luxury retail sales sector, with 16 vacancies for the “Giorgio Armani Macau Limited” and “Gucci” for the positions of store assistant, store supervisor, sales consultant and warehouse employee.
On the morning of May 23, 50 vacancies will be offered for store employees, warehouse employee and customer service employee at “Isa Boutique Limited” and “Isport Sporting Goods” stores.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:24:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Predicted stability in the second quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/economia-prevista-estabilidade-no-segundo-trimestre/</link><description>Macao's economic prosperity rate for the second quarter points to stability, but has imbalances in some indicators, such as the low confidence of Chinese consumers and the low value of game concessionaires actions
 
According to the latest predictions of Macao's economic prosperity rate, the local economy will remain stable in the second quarter, a prospect that Macao Economic Association analysts risk just risking to a short-term period.
The report released on Wednesday continues to reveal asymmetries in the evolution of the various indicators evaluated. Following the trends of the latest reports, the decrease in the purchasing power of Chinese tourists visiting Macao and the poor confidence of consumers from the interior of China continues to make black clouds over the economic perspectives of MSc. Another negative indicator, highlighted by the Macao Economic Association, is the continuation of the value of the game dealerships “curing at the low level for a long time”.
The prosperity rate also points out the weak demand for credit in the local economy. The macao banking resident loan ratio/deposits fell from 62.4 percent to 51.1 percent between the end of 2022 and last March, is indicated.
Analysts conclude that the smallest will of residents and companies by contracting loans "reflects a cautious attitude towards the current situation and economic perspectives." Although the MSar banking system has “widely liquidity”, funds were not actually converted into support for credit in the real economy, which indicates a lack of efficiency in capital affectation and confidence in investment.
The association led by former Deputy Joey Lao Vinca also the cooling in recent years in real estate and large-scale investment projects, as well as the high values ​​of Malparado credit, factors that further reduced the demand for bank loans.
Both sides
The association also indicates, on the other hand, that the volume of monetary mass broke a new historical record, exceeding the first time 810 billion patacas, an annual increase 8.8 percent in annual terms.
Another positive indicator concerns the number of visitors and hotels in hotels that remain at a “hot” level. Having warned of the impact of the trade war launched by Donald Trump, the analysts of the Macao Economic Association again enhanced the external environment as a destabilizing factor.
"In a context of weak search, insufficient dynamic economic growth and a restrictive financial environment and risks related to geopolitical and tariff disputes, Macao, as a micro-export-oriented economy, must be very aware of potential risk of falling their economic trends in the short and medium term," is indicated.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:23:09</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Bridge | Radars installed to control speed</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/ponte-macau-instalados-radares-para-controlar-velocidade/</link><description>From tomorrow, 22 speed detection fixed systems and four average speed detection systems will begin to work on the Macau bridge. The measure aims to “combat speeding offenses”.
These systems allow not only to detect instant speed, but also make the average time the vehicles took time to go through the bridge, and if below a certain number, there will be a fine for speeding.
According to the statement from the Public Security Police (CPSP) and the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT), the radars will be installed on the sides of Macau and the Main Bridge mud, in the nearby paci ramps and the main bridge and the exclusive motorcycle and moped corridor.
The Macau Bridge has as full speed limits of 80 km/h, 60 km/h and 40 km/h, depending on the sections. In some access ramps, and on the exclusive corridor tunnels for motorcycles and mopeds, the maximum limit is 40 km/h.
Drivers who violate the speed limits on the Macau bridge incur a fine of 600 patacas at 20,000 patacas and may still be without driving, in case of recurrence or severe excess speed.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:20:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Budget Execution | Public revenues with a reduction of 5%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/execucao-orcamental-receitas-publicas-com-reducao-de-5/</link><description>In the first four months of the year, there was a 0.06 percent drop, to 29.8 billion patacas, from tax revenues on the game. In addition, there was an expense of 874.7 million patacas in “actions and other participation”
 
The current revenue of the MSAR budget presented a 4.95 percent reduction in the first four months of the year, compared to the same period of 2024, especially due to a drop in financial revenues, it was announced yesterday.
Current revenue between January and April was 34 billion Patacas, according to published "online" data by the Territory Finance Services Directorate (DSF). The main reason for the decrease was financial revenues, which went from billion in the first four months of 2024 to only six thousand patacas this year.
This heading corresponds to the results of the Macao monetary authority, the region's financial regulator, and includes investment and interest and dividend revenues. In addition, the data also reveal a drop of 0.06 percent, to 29.8 billion patacas in tax revenues, which still represented 84.7 percent of the total.
The six city game operators pay a 35 percent direct tax on the game's revenues, 2.4 percent for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development, and 1.6 percent delivered to the Macao, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic Foundation.
Expenses for explaining
Taxes on the game fell, although the Macau casinos registered total revenues of 76.5 billion patacas in the first four months of the year, more 0.8 percent than in the same period of 2024. Between January and April, Macau collected 30.2 percent of current revenue projected for 2025 in the region's budget, which is 112.6 billion.
On the contrary, public expense rose 2.6 percent in the first four months to 24 billion patacas, due to an expense of 874.7 million patacas in “actions and other appearances”. Lusa has asked DSF more information about this heading, but has not received any response so far.
On April 15, the new government leader, Sam Hou Fai, admitted to fear a budget deficit in 2025, due to the slowdown in the game's recipes. Macao ended April with a surplus in public accounts of 10.3 billion patacas, 18.5 percent less than in the same period last year.
Still, this value is already higher than the government's forecast for the year 2025: 6.83 billion patacas. Macao closed 2024 with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the one recorded the previous year.
The last exercise was the first since 2020, at the beginning of the pandemic, in which the territory was able to keep the accounts on positive land, something required by the basic law, without transfers from the financial reserve.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:18:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Vocational Training | End of the pandemic leads to the breach of courses and students</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/formacao-profissional-fim-da-pandemia-leva-a-quebra-de-cursos-e-alunos/</link><description>Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) reveal that last year there were fewer people attending vocational training courses compared to 2023. The break was registered in the number of courses, 1,777, less 7.2 percent in annual terms.
In relation to the trainees, the break was 21.8 percent, reaching a total of 76,385 participants. According to DSEC, this break was due to the fact that "some temporary training plans, implemented in response to the pandemic, ended."
In addition, the number of courses for the public was 896, less 12.5 percent, and here also the number of graduates fell 30.6 percent, to a total of 35,140 people. In turn, the number of formations for companies or institutions was 881, 1.1 percent less than 2023, and also in this segment the number of graduates fell 12.3 percent in annual terms, with 41,245 registrations.
The most sought after courses were “Trade and Administration”, with 17,898 students, representing 23.4 percent of all graduates; and the “Health” course, with 10,343 students, having the 13.5 percent share of the total number of trainees.
In global terms, last year there were 67 institutions to conduct vocational training courses, just one more compared to 2023, and in 2024 there were 51 more employees, a total of 1,885 people. Of these, 1,138 were teachers, with an increase of 54 teachers full or partial.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:09:39</pubDate></item><item><title>COVID-19 | Macau exceeded peak infections</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/covid-19-macau-ultrapassou-pico-de-infeccoes/</link><description>Covid-19 infections have been progressively decreased since half of March, when the peak has been reached, but health services warn that coronavirus is still active in the territory. Authorities add that this year there were no deaths resulting from Covid-19
 
While in the neighboring regions of Macao, COVID-19 infection cases continue to increase, here infection rates have been gradually descended since half of March, health services indicated in a statement released on Tuesday night.
Authorities add that although the Mand has surpassed the most critical point of covid-19 infections, coronavirus remains active in the territory. As such, they appeal to the care and adoption of preventive attitudes, especially between risk groups, such as elderly, chronic diseases and people with weakened immune system, namely taking complete vaccination against the JN.1 variant.
Regarding the evolution of infection rates in Macao and neighboring regions, the entity led by Alvis Lo explains that Macau entered the infectious peak before the surrounding areas.
According to laboratory monitoring data, the positivity rate of the new coronaviruses detected in patients with flu symptoms in Macau began to increase in late February this year, reaching the peak in mid -March. In March 16 and 22, the authorities record a positivity rate of 44.3 percent, which was decreasing from there.
In the last three weeks, the positivity rate has come down to 12 percent, rose to 17 percent and then went back to 11 percent, "which indicates a slight recovery," the health services concluded.
Walk there
With regard to collective infections that result in flu symptoms, between the beginning of the year and this week 111 cases were recorded, of which 26 were from COVID-19, detected mainly in elderly homes. In these cases, the authorities ensure that they have adequate medical services to the elderly homes, prescribing antiviral medications.
Throughout this year, so far, Macao has not registered any critical or fatal case caused by Covid-19 infection, is indicated. The prevalent coronavirus variant in Macao is currently the XDV variant related to DN.1, which is basically the same that circulates in the surrounding areas. The latest data do not show that XDV causes more serious illnesses than JN.1, XBB and its descendant strains.
As such, health services ensure that the JN.1 variant vaccine remains effective in reducing “risk of infection and developing serious diseases caused by the currently prevalent variant.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:03:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Incomes increase 0.4% in the first quarter</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/habitacao-rendas-aumentam-04-no-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>In the first three months of the year, housing incomes registered an increase of 0.4 percent, compared to the period between October and December, according to “lace statistics for the first quarter of 2025”, released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
The largest increases occurred in the bass of the mud, where there was a growth of 1.1 percent, for an average lace per square meter of 140 patacas, in the parts of the outdoor port (Zape), with the rents to grow 0.8 percent, to 120 patacas per square meter, and in the Nape and landfills of Praia Grande Bay, where the lace rose 0.7 percent average 144 Patacas per square meter.
With the exception of housing rents, DSEC points out that all other spaces had reductions between the fourth quarter of last year and the first of 2025.
Regarding store rents, the latest data show a 0.9 percent reduction for a monthly income of 485 patacas per square meter. The average income of the spaces used as offices had a decrease of 1.3 percent to 290 patacas per square meter. Finally, the average incomes of industrial buildings fell about 0.2 percent to an average price of 123 patacas per square meter.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:54:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification as to their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained the guts to the dogmas of the "modern". For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my rank of hatter at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>India requires surveillance of the weapons of Pakistan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/111705/</link><description>India demanded yesterday that Pakistan nuclear weapons be placed “under surveillance” from the International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA), days after the most serious confrontation between the two armies of the last two decades.
"The nuclear arsenal of Pakistan should be placed under the supervision of the AIEA. I mean this very clearly," said Indian Defense Minister Rajnath Singh, quoted by the France-Presse (AFP) news agency.
During a visit to the Armed Forces Headquarters in Srinagar, the main city of Caxemira Indiana, the minister wondered whether nuclear weapons will be safe "in the hands of an uncontrollable and irresponsible nation." Pakistan did not react immediately. The two countries with nuclear weapons were involved last week at the deadliest military confrontation since the 1999 war.
On the night from May 6th to 7th, India fired missiles at places in Pakistan which, according to Nova Delh, housed members of the 'jihadist' group suspected of the attack that killed 26 people on April 22 at Caxemira Indiana.
Pakistan, which denied any responsibility for the attack, immediately retaliated. For four days, the two armies exchanged artillery shots and missile attacks and drones, feeding serious fears of a large -scale conflict. To a general surprise, US President Donald Trump announced an immediate ceasefire on Saturday, which was immediately confirmed by both parties.
No thanks
The group of old personalities known as the "Elders" defended yesterday in Tokyo Nuclear Non-Proliferation. Former United Nations Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon released the warning to southern Asia.
"There is a possibility that the international security system will be completely destroyed if India or Pakistan use nuclear weapons," he warned. Former Colombian President Juan Manuel Santos questioned where the UN was led by Portuguese António Guterres during the conflict.
The truce have been respected on the border between the two countries, but rhetoric remains very aggressive. "India will not tolerate the nuclear blackmail," said Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi on Monday night.
India categorically denied news of an attack on a Pakistani nuclear installation about 200 kilometers from the various cities recently hit by Indian missiles. Indian Foreign Ministry spokesman Randhir Jaiswal secured on Tuesday that India's military operation remained conventional. Throughout the crisis, Pakistan repeated that the nuclear option was never considered. "It would be inconceivable and stupid because it would endanger 1.6 billion people," army spokesman General Ahmed Chaudhry said.
Death accounts
India has atomic weapons since the 1990s, transported by Missiles Earth-Terra in the intermediate range. Pakistan has Nuclear Land and Short and Medium Air Range, and performed the first tests in 1998.
The Pakistani army said the Indian attacks killed 40 civilians and lost 13 soldiers. Already Nova Deli, he reported the death of 16 civilians and five soldiers in Indian territory. Despite the unfolding on the ground, India and Pakistan are adamant and claim that they will not lower the guard. "If another terrorist attack targets India, we will respond firmly," Modi warned.
In a telephone conversation with Guterres on Wednesday, Pakistani Prime Minister Shehbaz Sharif said he was "concerned about the provocative and inflammatory statements of India."
India and Pakistan compete for Caxemira's sovereignty since the bloody division when independence in 1947. The fate of the territory of Himalayas, a village mostly by Muslims, gave rise to several wars between the two countries. Since 1989, the Indian side has been the scene of a separatist insurrection that has already caused tens of thousands of dead.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>APEC foresees trade stoppage and drastic softening in the region</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/apec-preve-paralisacao-do-comercio-e-abrandamento-drastico-na-regiao/</link><description>The Organization for Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation (APEC) provides for a virtual stagnation of trade and a drastic economic slowdown in the region by 2025 due to tariff climbing, according to forecasts released yesterday.
APEC brings together 21 economies (Australia, Vietnam, Thailand, Japan, the United States, Canada, Mexico, etc.), including Asian countries that depend on commerce and which were harshly hit by the Customs War launched by Washington.
Economists in the organization provide for exports in the Asia-Pacific region to grow only 0.4 percent by 2025 compared to a 5.7 percent record last year. Imports must stagnate (+0.1 percent).
Consequently, APEC countries are expected to record Gross Domestic Product (GDP) growth of only 2.6 percent by 2025, an estimate compared to 3.3 percent in the previous forecast of the organization. For 2026, there is now a growth of 2.7 percent, well below the expected performance for the rest of the world (+3.3 percent).
General losses
Although the organization covers a wide range of economies, they are all suffering: the climbing of customs retaliation “is leading to a loss of confidence from investors and a weakening of demand,” APEC's Department of Public Policy Department, cited by France Presse, told the France Presse, in the margin of a meeting of the organization of the organization, which began yesterday in South Korea.
In addition to 25 percent tariffs on cars and steel, President Donald Trump's US administration announced, in early April, prohibitive “reciprocal” customs surcharge, currently suspended until July.
The highest customs rights will penalize the supply chains, will increase production costs, which will be transferred to the end consumer, and therefore will reduce the search for goods, ”Kuriyama explained. In the economist's opinion, uncertainty is the worst risk:“ It is essential to ensure that policies are stable and, if there are changes, that are permanent and not temporary, ”he suggested.
Starting points
This week's APEC meeting is an occasion for a series of bilateral discussions between the US commercial representative, Jamieson Greer, who is in South Korea, and representatives of US partners, including Chinese commercial representative, Li Chenggang.
Beijing and Washington recently selated a partial break in the heavy clusters of reciprocal customs. "This is positive, but it doesn't take us back to the point where we were before April," said Carlos Kuriyama.
Within APEC, "many governments are trying to apply measures to facilitate trade in order to compensate for the negative effect of US measures," he added, however, that these initiatives will have a limited impact because "the United States are the largest economy in the world."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:32:48</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE | Brazil and four Latin American countries exempt from entry visa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/mne-brasil-e-quatro-paises-latino-americanos-isentos-de-visto-de-entrada/</link><description>China said yesterday that, from June 1, citizens of Brazil, Argentina, Chile, Peru and Uruguay can enter China without visa for stay up to 30 days.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian confirmed yesterday the details of the measure, announced by President, XI Jinping, during the recent China-Community Ministerial Summit of Latin American and Caribbean states (Celac).
According to Lin, the policy will be in force until May 31, 2026 and will allow common passport holders to travel to China for tourism, business, family visits, cultural exchanges or traffic.
The goal is to "further facilitate exchanges between people and promote friendly cooperation." Lin assured that China will “continue to expand its opening policy” and welcome more Latin American citizens to “visit, explore and experience the country's vitality and diversity”.
The initiative is part of a series of measures that Beijing has been taking since 2023 to revive tourism and international ties after the prolonged end of borders due to the Covid-19 pandemic. China had already extended the period of visa exemption to countries such as Portugal and Spain from 15 to 30 days and signed reciprocal exemption agreements with 20 other states.
China is currently the main commercial partner of countries such as Brazil, Chile and Peru, increasing its presence in Latin America through infrastructure and trade projects linked to its new silk routes.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:31:04</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | Chinese military personnel willing to expand calls with Russia</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/cooperacao-militares-chineses-dispostos-a-expandir-ligacoes-com-a-russia/</link><description>China yesterday indicated that it wants to expand pragmatic cooperation with the Russian military after President Xi Jinping's recent visit to Moscow for celebrations of the 80th anniversary of World War II victory last week.
"Chinese military personnel are willing to work with the Russian side to further increase strategic mutual trust, intensify strategic communication and expand practical cooperation," Chinese Ministry spokesman Jiang Bin said in a statement without directly referring to war in Ukraine.
China and its Russian neighbor have reinforced economic, political and military cooperation in the last decade. This trend accelerated further after the invasion of the Ukrainian territory by Moscow in 2022. Xi Jinping watched the 80th anniversary of the victory in World War II in the Red Square of Moscow last week.
Asked about Xi's visit to Moscow, the Chinese Ministry of Defense said yesterday, in a statement that bilateral military relations are at one high level in recent years.
China has claimed to be a neutral part in the Russian-Ucranian conflict and has offered its services as a mediator, although regularly accused by the West of Moscow, crucial and political support to perform its military operation.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:28:57</pubDate></item><item><title>HK / Bag | Largest Chinese pharmacist launches public offering</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/hk-bolsa-maior-farmaceutica-chinesa-lanca-oferta-publica/</link><description>Jiangsu Hengrui Pharmaceuticals wants to achieve investments of over a billion euros designed to finance research and developmental actions in the area of ​​the pharmacy area
 
China's largest pharmacist, Jiangsu Hengrui Pharmaceuticals, launched an initial public offering on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange to attract up to 1.13 billion euros in investment.
In a statement sent to the Chinese semi -autonomous scholarship, Hengrui said it intends to sell 224.5 million actions, for a value that could reach 9.89 billion dollars from Hong Kong. The document explains that most of this money would go to research and development projects and the construction of new pharmaceutical production and research units in both China and abroad.
Hengrui, based in Jiangsu Province (East), was created in 1970 as a state -owned company of generic medicines. After being privatized in the 1990s, the group devoted itself to the development of new medicines.
Seven institutional investors, including Singapore Gic Sovereign Fund and United States Investment Company Invesco Advisers, had already committed to investing US $ 533 million in the offer. Hengrui, which is already quoted on the Shanghai Stock Exchange, considered China's financial capital, is expected to be listed on the Hong Kong Stock Exchange on May 23.
Sum and follow
Hengrui's initial public offering comes two days after the world's largest electric vehicle battery manufacturer, contemporary amperex technology (CATL), having done the same. The CATL, already listed in the scholarship of the neighboring city of Shenzhen, aims to raise at least $ 31 billion from Hong Kong in its Hong Kong debut, which is scheduled for May 20.
The company said 90 percent of the raised funds will be used to finance the expansion of CATL operations in Hungary, as well as Germany, Spain and Indonesia.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:26:22</pubDate></item><item><title>“Golden Dragon” | China and Cambodia begin the largest joint military exercises of their history</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/dragao-de-ouro-china-e-camboja-iniciam-os-maiores-exercicios-militares-conjuntos-da-sua-historia/</link><description>China and Cambodia began yesterday the largest joint military maneuvers ever between the two countries, involving state -of -the -art Chinese military equipment, including artillery, war ships and robotic combat dogs.
About 900 Chinese soldiers and more than 1,300 Cambojan soldiers participate in the exercises, which will extend until May 28, according to a statement from the Khmer Royal Forces (RCAF, Cambodia).
According to the statement, will be presented state -of -the -art Chinese military equipment, including armored vehicles, helicopters, war ships, recognition drones and robotic combat dogs. The objective is to “develop narrower ties and cooperation” between the two armies.
"The exercises are larger than last year in terms of personnel and equipment," RCAF spokesman Thong Solimo told AFP, adding that a Chinese war ship, Chanbai Shan, attracted Ream Cambodian naval base with the equipment. The ream base in southwest of Cambodia was renewed by China and inaugurated on April 2 by Prime Minister Cambodian Hun Manet and a Chinese military delegation.
“China wants to show its muscles” and send the message that “it is a superpower”, through these exercises, nicknamed “Golden Dragon,” argued or Virak, a Cambodian political expert, quoted by the French news agency.
In addition to this demonstration of strength, China must also “give confidence to its partners, telling them that China is growing, developing and becoming stronger, both in terms of dimension and technological progress and military power,” he added or Virak.
Cambodia should also receive two China war ships. The first joint military exercises, called “Golden Dragon”, took place in 2016 and, in early 2017, Cambodia ended the “Angkor Sentinel”, a similar joint exercise that had been organized in the previous seven years with US forces.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:10:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Range and Route | Colombia confirms adherence to the Chinese initiative</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/15/faixa-e-rota-colombia-confirma-adesao-a-iniciativa-chinesa/</link><description>In the Chinese capital to participate in the China-Celac Forum (Latin American and Caribbean Community), Colombian President Gustavo Petro signed a memorandum to join the Track and Route International Trade Initiative
 
China and Colombia signed yesterday in Beijing a cooperation plan for the Latin American country to join the Chinese track and route initiative, confirmed the Colombian presidency through the social network X. The Memorandum, signed in Beijing by the leaders of both countries, Xi Jinping and Gustavo Petro, brings together Colombia to an initiative with which the Asian giant intends to generate an international trade network and Extend its influence worldwide through the construction of infrastructure, and to which more than twenty countries in Latin America and Caribbean have joined.
“Under this meeting, Colombia has signed an important economic cooperation agreement for the adhesion of our country to the [initiative] track and route,” says the Colombian presidency. Xi and Petro gathered yesterday to reinforce bilateral ties by signing new agreements, including this, among all the most emblematic.
Before traveling to China, Petro revealed that on his previous voyage to the Asian country in October 2023, he intended to sign this memorandum, but at the time it was not possible due to an alleged mistake of his previous Foreign Minister, Álvaro Leyva.
"This is what I am going to do now, an agreement of intent; future governments will see if the intention comes true, and must come true," the Colombian president said. Petro was with Xi on Tuesday at the opening of the China-Celac Forum (Latin American and Caribbean Community) in the Chinese capital, where he appealed to a dialogue between civilizations “free from authoritarianism and imperialism”.
The trade scale between Colombia and China is particularly unfavorable to the Latin American country, whose annual deficit is about $ 14 billion. By 2024, Colombia exported $ 2.38 billion from goods to China and imported $ 15.9 billion from Chinese products.
In addition, between 1994 and 2023, China invested $ 813.3 million in Colombia -yet a value far lower than the United States and Spain -concentrated in sectors such as infrastructure, mining exploration, energy and transport.
Other ties
In addition to trade, Colombia is trying to reinforce technological cooperation with China. On Tuesday, Petro visited the headquarters of the Huawei 'giant' in Beijing telecommunications, where, according to Colombian Minister of Information and Communications Technology, Julián Molina, eventual initiatives for cooperation in the domains of artificial intelligence, data infrastructure and connectivity were discussed.
Petro's government's interest in strengthening commercial ties with China during the visit has caused internal controversy, due to the fear of any negative repercussions on the relationship with the United States, Colombia's largest commercial partner.</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 01:05:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Fentanil | China asks the US to stop blaming Beijing for the epidemic</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/fentanil-china-pede-aos-eua-que-parem-de-culpar-pequim-pela-epidemia/</link><description>China yesterday asked the United States to blame the Chinese for the fentanyl epidemic in the country and criticized the “irrational” customs imposed by Washington.
"If the United States wants to sincerely cooperate with China, they should stop defaming and blaming China and get involved in a dialogue based on equality, respect and mutual benefit," said China's Foreign Ministry spokesman Lin Jian at a press conference.
The US has been responsible for China because it is the country of manufacture of most of the chemicals that come in the United States. Fentanil is a powerful synthetic opioid that has become a public health problem in the United States in recent years, being responsible for tens of thousands of deaths annually.
On Monday, US representative for trade, Jamieson Greer, revealed that the Fentanil crisis had been first approached in commercial talks between the United States and China.
Contacts between the two countries have taken place since the weekend in Geneva. The issue of Fentanil has been one of the main points of the tariff confrontation between the two powers, with Washington asking Beijing to suppress the illegal production and export of chemicals that allow the manufacture of the substance.
Asked yesterday about the perspectives of dialogue on the subject, Lin Jian said China was proactive, but was not responsible for the crisis. "The United States ignored China's goodwill and imposed irrational tariffs on Fentanil. This seriously impairs dialogue and cooperation between China and US in the fight against drugs and severely undermines China's interests," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 22:58:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing puts an end to the prohibition of Chinese companies to receive Boeing planes</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/13/pequim-poe-fim-a-proibicao-das-companhias-chinesas-receberem-avioes-da-boeing/</link><description>China raised a ban that prevented Chinese airlines a month ago from receiving Boeing aircraft after commercial negotiations with the United States, which temporarily reduced the customs rights of each party.
Beijing authorities have begun to inform domestic carriers and government agencies this week that aircraft deliveries in the United States may be resumed, according to Chinese sources in statements to Bloomberg on anonymity, because the information is confidential.
Airlines were given freedom to organize deliveries in their own deadlines and conditions, one of the sources added. The resumption of deliveries to China is an immediate boost for Boeing.
Defrosting occurs when the world's two largest economies agreed to a tariff truce, with the United States to reduce to 30 percent for 90 days their combined rates of 145 percent over most Chinese imports.
China has agreed to reduce its 125 percent customs rights to US products to 10 percent and to eliminate other counterfeit against the United States since April 2.
How long?
Still, the restoration of aircraft deliveries may be short -term if the tariff war is not resolved during the three months of suspension.
In this scenario, the American aeronautical giant based in Arlington, Virginia, will be able to see the price of its aircraft increase compared to its two main competitors, European Airbus and Commercial Aircraft Corporation of China (Comac), which seeks to gain land in the domestic market with state support.
Boeing was spared the rates during the last episode of the trade war during the first presidency of Trump (2017-2021), but their sales to the Asian giant have been falling since 2019. In 2022, the expectation was that 25 percent of Boeing's international deliveries would go to China, but by 2023 the number dropped to 9 percent.
On the other hand, experts believe that if the trade war is not stuck, the dispute will make US companies of all sectors higher prices for parts and raw materials that buy to China, which means they will face the double challenge of relocating part of their production and losing competitiveness in the Chinese market.</description><pubDate>2025-05-13 22:56:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account] to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
What other projects are in this book?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Yes. The idea of ​​publication, with Barcelona's Actar Books, has to do with putting the work, and more than that, its message, which is very specific to Macau and our way of working in the international and architects community, and this goes a lot through the Biennial. It was also in Europe that a consensus was built on the level of descriptions [in architecture] for a few centuries, and where there is a discussion, national and international, around the issues of the profession. We want our work to be present, either through the book and through acting Books, in this international community, to be part of the world.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through spatial narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and I see soon that AI was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had to do research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>João Romão, academic: “Macau is in a highly privileged position”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/02/joao-romao-academico-macau-esta-numa-posicao-altamente-privilegiada/</link><description>Professor at Yasuda Women’s University in Japan, João Romão prepares to launch in June a book entitled “Economic Geography of Tourism”. Speaking to HM, the academic enhances the interconnection between tourism, economy and geography, and lists its possibilities, limitations and effects, including Macau
 
 
In this book it speaks of the concept of “spatial economy”, in connection with tourism and geography. How is this connection?
Economic geography combines the geographical context with economic processes, being studied the spatial distribution of economic activities. The economy of tourism is particularly sensitive to these geographical constraints, as they are the characteristics of each place that enhances the development of certain products or services. These characteristics widely exceed the physical aspects of the territory and also include culture, history, ways of life or even institutions and legal frameworks. The case of casino, something particularly important in Macao, is a good example of the importance of legal aspects to develop certain types of tourism. Economic geography has a wider scope than the spatial economy, more focused on strictly economic aspects. Being evident in tourism this relationship between economics and geography, this book establishes a double approach that systematizes the interdependence of these three aspects it refers. First explores how the concepts and theories of economic geography can apply to tourism. In the second half it makes the opposite route, discussing how the analysis of relevant problems of contemporary tourism justifies the use of economic geography. Examples are the degradation of local resources, environmental impacts, contribution to climate change, acceleration of gentrification processes or disturbance of community modes of life.
Can having an excessively -dependent economy of tourism constitute a problem or salvation?
The two things, and are both cases that economic geography can help to understand. The industrialization of economies is linked to the agglomeration processes of activities that reinforce each other when they reach a certain scale. This allows the massification of production and consumption, with reasonable costs. Contemporary industries, more associated with the integration of digital technologies and creative processes, are less clustered in specialized industrial development zones, but tend to focus on large cities and metropolitan areas. It also follows that rural areas, islands, or sites that have not followed industrialization processes, have more difficulty mobilizing investments, technologies or qualified people to innovate and develop new industries. In such cases, tourism often appears as the possible solution as it can be developed with incorporation of technology and relatively low knowledge. On the other hand, tourism consumption, not being essential to human life, is very sensitive to income fluctuations.
Can you give examples?
This was visible, for example, with the 2007/2009 international crisis. Tourism is also very vulnerable to safety problems or international epidemics, such as COVID-19 has demonstrated to the extreme. Economies too specialized in tourism are very vulnerable to external shocks and less resilient to crises. It is also visible that, being the tourist development often supported by intensive and weak labor services, the specialization in tourism can cause, in the long run, embarrassment in terms of population qualifications, the ability to innovate and integrate technology or to add value to the regional economy.
The book also speaks of “intelligent tourism” and “co-creation of experiences”, using the megados and IA. Is tourism definitely becoming more digital?
Social networks are fundamental instruments for new generations. However, they began to generalize the tools for planning or promotion of travel supported by artificial intelligence. The so-called “intelligent tourism” more generally designates the use of digital technologies to intensify information flows, consolidate the formation of networks and promote more informed and shared decision making, eventually contributing to the so-called “co-creation of experiences”. Tourism digitization has its origins in service distribution systems originally developed by airlines since the 1960s, but it would be the internet to accelerate and globalize digitization.
And social networks.
The emergence of social networks promoted the creation of a more interactive universe, potentially in real time and involving wide numbers of users and various types of supports. The generalization of the use of mobile phones permanently connected to the Internet, even on foreign travel, has further increased this potential for intensive and interactive use of data and information. This "co-creation", however, hides obvious imbalances of power.
Such as?
With regard to tourists, or consumer in general, it is usually the role of providing information, for example through social networks. This information is obtained, accumulated and marketed, sometimes without consent or even without knowledge, to eventually translate into the creation, adaptation or promotion of products and services. This process is particularly important in the case of tourism, because there is usually a long period between the decision to travel and the trip itself. This period of travel exploration and planning is used by tourist marketing companies to try to influence choices. This type of interaction also introduces a difference in the “spatiality” of the provision of tourist services, which are usually produced and consumed at the same time and in the same place, in a direct relationship between producer and consumer. The digitization of tourism anticipates most of these interactions and information flows and transfers them to large technological companies or marketing and distribution.
In a world where more and more travel, the routes are shorter and access to information is immense, how can countries and regions be competitive in the tourist offer?
Contemporary tourism lives in a highly competitive international environment. But just as there is a wide variety of destinations and offerings, there is also a wide range of preferences and consumption, what is called “hyper-personalization”, the result of such abundance of information and opportunity for interaction. The challenge that is placed on destinations is to identify the resources, products and services that can be adjusted to a particular group of consumers, to communicate effectively. This competitiveness greatly goes beyond the strict scope of tourist services because it also requires mobility and transportation services, varied infrastructure, safety, medical support, or easy communication. Anywhere you want to develop your tourist industry have to intervene about all these factors.
The book also addresses how “social processes” shape the development of tourism. In the case of China, for example, do you believe we are watching a change, which will have consequences for Macau?
It seems to me that Macau is in a highly privileged position to develop other forms of tourism. China is the largest issuing market in the world, the widespread rise of income in recent decades allows many million people to explore the opportunity to travel. Macao is a very close and distinct destination, with its historical and cultural particularities. For the Chinese population it was not easy to visit Macau and there is certainly a great interest.
How does the Great Bay project come in this?
The strategy that is being followed by integrating the Great Bay allows you to develop a cosmopolitan and diverse offer that can certainly attract Chinese tourists and other parts of the world. Moreover, these three areas have excellent hotel and tourism schools, which guarantee qualified personnel for tourism management and planning. The element of differentiation that Portuguese culture introduces in this context can certainly contribute to the success of the transition from a casinos focused on other forms that value culture and heritage more.
Is it possible to have sustainable tourism?
The problems and difficulties of tourism sustainability are more visible than in other sectors. This “spatiality” of tourism (where the consumer is obliged to move to the place of consumption) implies that the consequences of this consumption become more evident. These effects are less obvious when it comes to the unsustainability of industrial units or intensive forms of agriculture in relatively isolated areas. As mass reduction and investment reduction strategies also apply to tourism, the consequences of the environment or the quality of life of residents in destinations can be devastating. Sustainability implies a long -term perspective based on the idea that today's decisions do not imply future negative consequences. Sustainable practices depend on the control of the impacts that accumulate over time by individual and independent economic agents.
How can this control be done?
When a hotel or airline defines what ability to install on their services they may eventually estimate the impact that consumers will have on the local environment or economy. They will have more difficulties in anticipating that impacts will be generated in the next 10, 15 or 20 years to investment. And surely it will be impossible to measure how this impact accumulates the impacts caused by other service providers, now or in the future. In other words, although the idea of ​​sustainability is widespread accepted, economic agents do not have mechanisms or instruments in practice. Regulating the use of resources and territories by public entities with a more comprehensive and future perspective can contribute to the sustainability more effectively than the regulation associated with market dynamics, which in many cases has been revealed highly predatory. The Chinese economy is one of these examples and may eventually benefit from it.
And in the concrete case of Macau?
Macao has historically known problems: ultra-urbanized and polluted areas, with large energy consumption and waste production; Great concentration of tourists in a relatively small area of ​​great historical and cultural interest; Great dependence on the game, with the resulting imbalances in the appropriation of tourism benefits. The ongoing transition to new forms of tourism should better solve these problems and state regulation will certainly have better results than based on market dynamics.</description><pubDate>2025-04-02 23:28:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is it for them to be denied this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the guide circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of copies produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos also underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitano Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major goal will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name in Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Tourism finding races took place in Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/21/gp-corridas-de-apuramento-de-turismo-decorreram-em-zhaoqing/</link><description>The 2025 edition of the Macao-Macau Road Sport Challenge-Macao Touring Championship-began at the Guangdong International Circuit, with 67 cars divided into two groups, A and B, disputing a total of four races over the weekend. Hong Kong riders again showed their superiority, but there were positive results among Macau pilots
 
In addition to the titles at stake, the competition organized by the Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), which is divided into two events, also serves to assign the thirty-six vacancies available to the most important race of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. As such, this first journey on the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing was particularly tense, with very disputed races between the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), all equipped this year with the new DMC compound pirelli tires.
In the group it aligned three well -known pilots of the Lusophone community: Rui Valente, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão. However, a less achieved qualification left the three in the final part of the starting grid, forcing them to redoubled work in the first race, played on Saturday afternoon. This same race was eventually interrupted with a red flag a few turns from the end, due to an oil stroke on the track. Damon Chan, winner of the competition in 2024, triumphed, followed by Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping, in a podium entirely composed of Hong Kong pilots. The experienced Rui Valente starred in an excellent recovery race, rising from 29th to 14th position. Maximiano Mannão won three places and finished 22nd, while Célio Alves Dias climbed eight positions, ending at 25th.
In the second race, Rui Valente again printed a strong progress, spinning 5th, but the degradation of the tires prevented him from maintaining the position, ending in 7th. With a scoring system that privileges the top ten classifieds, this result may be decisive for their qualification for the Great Award. In his weekend debuts to the commands of a Maximian Maão Tourism car, whose Toyota boasts the colors and the logo of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended in 15th. Célio Alves Dias, on a complicated weekend, was only 23rd and knows that there is a lot to do if you want to qualify next month. The victory was up to Lo Pak Yu, pressured closely by Wong Chuk Pan and Leong Keng Hei. The best representative in the territory was Lou Check In with a 4th place.
MSAR VICTORY AND TOP-10 to Badaraco
Group B races were also marked by uncertainty and great animation inside the track. Chung Kwok Hei, winner in 2023, led the race until a hole forced him to leave. Cheng Kin Sang, representative of MSAR, took the opportunity and took the lead. Bayern Yip Wai Hei has released several attacks, all effectively defended by Cheng. However, an apparent accident on the main line, near the end, caused a new red flag interruption. Cheng Kin Sang won, ending ahead of Bayern Yip and Lam Tou.
In the second race, Bayern Yip exceeded Cheng Kin Sang on the second round and took command. Despite Safety Car's entrance twice, Bayern Yip kept his calm and secured the victory, winning a first and second place in the weekend. Rao Long, who left the eighth position, showed excellent pace and climbed to the 2nd place in the last two laps. Cheng Kin Sang concluded in 3rd place, adding two podiums on the opening day.
Jerónimo Badaraco, the last winner of the ACP Cup, in 1999, had a discreet start, ending in 19th Saturday's race. On Sunday, “Noni” showed that he still has a lot to give local motorsport, reaching a precious 10th place. Already Dionísio Albino Pereira completed the first race in 29th position and did not aligned in the second.
The next, final and decisive journey is scheduled for May 16-18, again at the Guangdong International Circuit.</description><pubDate>2025-04-21 23:40:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Council of Motorsport approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and a MSAR test enthusiast, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The growth and development potential in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into details, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula Cup last year, says that “this big step will benefit undoubtedly local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis | Jieni Shao eliminated in the group phase of the World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/17/tenis-de-mesa-jieni-shao-eliminada-na-fase-de-grupos-da-taca-do-mundo/</link><description>The Portuguese Jieni Shao was eliminated yesterday from the Table Tennis World Cup in Macao, losing with Chinese Wang Yidi, the third of the world ranking, in the last game of the group stage.
The two players came to the last match to need a victory to be first in Group 3, the only position that guaranteed the passage to the qualifiers. This after, on Tuesday, the favorite Wang was surprised by the 39-year-old French veteran Yuan Jia Nan, who won three partials to one.
On Monday, at the premiere of the competition, Shao, current 52nd of the world ranking and the only Portuguese representative in the tournament, had tied two partials with Yuan, 44th in the world. In addition to winning the meeting, which lasted 27 minutes, for four partials to zero, the third in the world secured access to the qualifiers.
The World Cup will take place until Doming in Macao for the second year in a row, after a four-year break due to the Covid-19 pandemic. The tournament will distribute total awards worth one million dollars. The competition has 48 players in each of the categories, male and female, including the ranking number one, Chinese Lin Shidong, and world champion, also Chinese Sun Yingsha.</description><pubDate>2025-04-17 00:53:34</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Touring cars finding begins with greater presence Macaense</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/16/gp-apuramento-dos-carros-de-turismo-comeca-com-maior-presenca-macaense/</link><description>The Macao-Macao Road Sport Challenge Touring Car Championship will start this weekend at the Guangdong International Circuit in the city of Zhaoqing, 200 kilometers northwest of the ride. For this race, which will serve as qualification for the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, will be on the starting grid a dozen Macau pilots, including five Portuguese names
 
Among the sixty subscribers, all equipped with two types of vehicles - Toyota GR86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) - are well -known guys from Macau's motor racing. With the same enthusiasm recognized for decades, Rui Valente will again drive a Subaru BRZ, the same car with which he competed in the Guide Circuit in November last year. Premium Racing Team driver had, in the last Macao Grand Prix, one of the fastest in terms of tip speed in the platoon of his race. Therefore, the focus on pre-season has been in other technical aspects of the car that go beyond the engine.
Also back is Célio Alves Dias, after a difficult year in 2024, far short of his expectations. For this, the pilot Macaense bet on changing the chassis of his Toyota Gr86. This year, its objective is to account for the twenty -fifth participation in the largest annual sports event of MSAR, so all the details are important.
Back is also Jerónimo Badaraco (Toyota Gr86), a pilot who, in the Macao Grand Prix last year, reached second place at Macao Road Sport Challenge. After having been modest in the finding events, “Noni” was very strong in the city streets, where he was the best Macaense pilot, in a race won by law Kit Meng.
In debut this year will be Maximian Mannão. Bringing with him a nickname with a huge tradition in Macao's motorsport, the young Maximiano, who competed for several years in the local Karting events and, in 2022, participated in a Formula 4 Chinese Championship race, will make his debut at Macau Road Sport Challenge with a Toyota GR86.
The Macanese presence will be reinforced by Dionísio Albino Pereira, a pilot regularly seen in the coloane Karting events, which will conduct a Toyota GR86 from LW World Racing Team. In 2013, he competed in the Macao - Macau Touring Car Series Tourism Championship, then driving a Honda Integra DC5 from the Pas Macau Racing Team team.
The representation of the territory in these findings will also feature Chi Wang, Carson Tang, IP Tok Meng, Chan Chi Ha, Lo Kai Tin and Lou Check In.
It will be to hurt
In 2024, the Macao-China General Automotive Association (AAMC) was able to place all the drivers of the Macau Tourism Championship in the end of the Grand Prix. This year, it seems that the scenario of organizing two races for local pilots will be impossible. As such, these qualifying races will have a much higher impact, and only half of those now registered will have entry ticket for the largest annual sports event of MSAR.
Another novelty for this year is that all cars will be equipped with tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, as had already happened in the Grand Prix. However, this year there will be a new compound, the same for everyone, which may shuffle the favorite accounts. Centralins will continue to be drawn, as in the past.
Since the number of participants is high, AAMC will divide the pilots into groups A and B, not two but four races in total. Each race will have 15 laps, two of which will be played on Saturday and two on Sunday.</description><pubDate /></item></channel></rss>