<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>War | Thailand accused Cambodia of violating airspace with 250 drones</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/guerra-tailandia-acusou-camboja-de-violar-espaco-aereo-com-250-drones/</link><description>Thailand yesterday accused Cambodia of violating the current ceasefire agreement by sending 250 unmanned aerial devices (drones) over Thai territory.
The Thai Army indicated that more than 250 drones were detected entering the country in the border area. For the Thai Armed Forces, Cambodia's action constituted a provocation and a violation of measures “aimed at reducing tensions” between Bangkok and Phnom Penh. At the time of writing, the Cambodian authorities had not commented on Thailand's accusation regarding the airspace violation.
The two countries reached a ceasefire on Saturday after three weeks of clashes along their 800-kilometre common border, following two days of negotiations in China. The ceasefire agreement provides for an end to weeks of fighting along the disputed border, which has left more than 100 people dead and more than half a million displaced in both countries. Thai Foreign Minister Sihasak Phuangketkeow and his Cambodian counterpart Prak Sokhonn met in southwest China's Yunnan province for talks mediated by his Chinese counterpart Wang Yi.
The head of Chinese diplomacy stated that Beijing “does not want to see Thailand and Cambodia on battlefields”. During a meeting with his Thai counterpart, Sihasak Phuangketkeow, on Sunday, Wang Yi expressed China's “deep concern” about the “tense situation on the border” and argued that, once the fighting stops, “diplomacy must take the lead”.
“Rebuilding peace is the desire of the people and the expectation of all parties,” said the head of Chinese diplomacy, adding that Beijing’s mediation efforts “never impose themselves on others, nor go beyond limits” and aim to create “a relaxed platform for dialogue.”
A fatal history
US President Donald Trump, who threatened to suspend trade privileges if Thailand and Cambodia did not agree to a ceasefire in July, suggested yesterday that fighting between Thailand and Cambodia “will momentarily cease” and stated that the United States “has become the true United Nations”. The territorial limits have been disputed for decades and were inherited from the French colonial period.
According to official figures, recognized by the United Nations, the latest clashes caused 47 deaths: 26 on the Thai side and 21 on the Cambodian side. In July, the first phase of clashes left 43 dead in five days, before a ceasefire was agreed.
Another agreement was subsequently signed on October 26 in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, in the presence of the President of the United States, but was suspended by Thailand after several Bangkok soldiers were injured in the explosion of a military land mine in the border area.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:53:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Weddings | Si Ka Lon wants Macau to be like Las Vegas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/casamentos-si-ka-lon-quer-que-macau-seja-como-las-vegas/</link><description>Representative Si Ka Lon argues that Macau should invest in the wedding industry for tourism purposes, similar to what happens in Las Vegas.
In an oral question presented to the Government, which will be answered in the Chamber next week, the deputy argues that “‘destination weddings’ is one of the directions for the development of the tourism industry”. Si Ka Lon asks whether local authorities will “take as a reference the successful experiences of Las Vegas or Hong Kong, allowing marriage registration in Macau, regardless of the place of residence or nationality of the bride and groom, with a view to exploring the 'wedding tourism' market”.
In the deputy's view, the Executive can “take advantage of Macau's advantages and singularities”, investing in the promotion of “plans for outdoor wedding ceremonies, in order to increase the competitiveness of Macau's wedding tourism products and create a new business card for the city”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:35:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Money exchange | Raid targets 60 million Hong Kong dollar deal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/troca-de-dinheiro-rusga-visa-negocio-de-60-milhoes-de-dolares-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Judiciary Police (PJ) announced the arrest of two women for allegedly being involved in illegal exchanges of money for gambling at a casino in Cotai. According to police estimates, the business operating in a jewelry store had a turnover of more than 60 million Hong Kong dollars, with profits being 1 million Hong Kong dollars.
The detainees are a 36-year-old local resident and a 27-year-old woman from Mainland China. Both performed sales roles in the commercial space. At yesterday's press conference in which the case was presented, PJ representatives admitted that they were currently investigating the whereabouts of the owner of the commercial space.
In addition to the arrests, around 500 thousand Hong Kong dollars in cash were seized. A cell phone was also seized, which was allegedly used to arrange money exchanges. The investigation was based on anonymous complaints that alerted authorities to the possibility that illegal money exchanges were taking place inside the store.
The arrests took place after the agents spent a day monitoring what was happening in the commercial space, having decided to act after seeing three customers with “suspicious behavior”. The store had been operating in the casino, which was not identified, since 2019, and the two employees confessed to exchanging money. The prisoners received salaries of 13 thousand patacas and 15 thousand patacas, which included overtime pay.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:40:43</pubDate></item><item><title>New Year's Eve | Street parties and concerts to end 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/passagem-de-ano-festas-na-rua-e-concertos-para-encerrar-2025/</link><description>Macau and Hong Kong will be in full swing tonight with celebrations that will welcome 2026. From free concerts next to Praça do Lago Sai Van and at the Taipa Houses-Museum, to shows at Cotai and Mariza's performance at the Macau Cultural Center, there is no shortage of options for all tastes
The end of 2025 is here, and if some opt for a more homely celebration, there will be many people willing to go out and have fun in the company of friends and with lots of music in the mix. With paid and free options, Macau and Hong Kong offer a range of options for various tastes.
One of the initiatives comes from the Cultural Institute (IC) and is already a tradition. The end of 2025 is celebrated next to Praça do Lago Sai Van from 10pm, and from 9pm at the Taipa Houses-Museum, with the “New Year’s Eve Concert – Macau 2025” and the “New Year’s Eve Party – Taipa 2025”.
Various singers and musical groups perform at the concert on the peninsula side, between 10pm and 12:10am, including Hong Kong singer Panther Chan and rock band Dear Jane. There is also a cast of local artists such as Soler, Filipe Tou, KC Ao Ieong, winifai, Jenny, thetiredeyes and Initial B, “who will alternate [performances] to present a diverse range of music to celebrate a dazzling New Year's Eve”, describes the IC.
In the case of this performance at Praça do Lago Sai Van, the stage floor stands out, which will feature “an electronic screen combined with lighting and visual effects, providing a totally new visual experience”. “The entire performance will be presented in a theatrical format adapted to each session, which conveys, through narratives, the wishes for the coming year and reflects the exciting facets of the city”, adds the IC.
Regarding the concerts at the Taipa Houses-Museum, the theme will be “Multicultural Integration”, with the public being able to see performances by FIDA, Tuna Macaense, Bossa Eva and João Gomes &amp; Band and Karen Tong, a singer from Hong Kong.
In addition, there will be performances by the Bollywood Dreams Group, by Victor Kumar, and the Filipino dance groups of the Macau Bisdak Association and Burmese and Vietnamese dance groups from Macau. The poster is completed with magic presentations by magician Jason Fong.
From 8:30 pm and until 11:30 pm, there will be cultural exhibitors from local communities in the Philippines, India, Myanmar and Vietnam, who aim to promote the cuisine and culture of their countries.
Mariza at CCM
Another great highlight to end the year is the performance by fado singer Mariza at the Macau Cultural Center (CCM) from 8pm, alongside the Macau Orchestra. “Mariza, the Queen of Fado and the Macau Orchestra (OM)” is the name given to the concert where the fado singer will perform, “with her deeply emotional voice, a selection of iconic fados, providing the public with a musical experience that transcends genres and spatial and temporal boundaries”.
The Portuguese is described “as one of the biggest international Fado stars, being recognized for her own musical style, which incorporates elements of soul, jazz and gospel”.
Looking at Cotai, gaming operators bet heavily on year-end programs. The Venetian Arena concert hall hosts the third and final in a series of concerts by Jason Zhang, which began on Monday. Tickets range from MOP680 to MOP2,580 for VIP seats.
Jason Zhang Jie was born in 1982 in China and debuted in the “My Show” competition in 2004, becoming the winner, which gave him access to a contract with Universal Music China. At the end of 2023, he already had 15 albums recorded and a total of 87 concerts in his career. Still at the Venetian, as well as at The Parisian Macao and The Londoner, there will be fireworks, with the traditional countdown until 2026. The “Sands New Year’s Eve Countdown Extravaganza” event starts with music at 9:30 pm.
Like Sands China, the gaming operator Galaxy also made its plans to end the year in style, namely in the Andaz Macau, Long Bar and Pony &amp; Plume developments. The party takes place with DJ performances and the promise of unlimited drinks.
For those who want something different and, at the same time, themed, there will be a “La Nuit Rouge Countdown Party” at The Ritz-Carlton Bar and Lounge, with French cabaret and live music.
Air Supply in Hong Kong
Going to Hong Kong to close the year 2025 could also be an option. To begin with, one of the centers of entertainment will be the pedestrian zone on Chater Road, in Central.
On the Hong Kong Tourism Board website, it is stated that the public can enjoy “a new format of live music performances combined with light shows”, namely by the band Air Supply, who will perform “a special performance with their timeless classic hits”. The Australian duo, formed in 1975, already has a 50-year career under their belt and has well-known songs such as “All Out of Love”, “Making Love Out of Nothing at All” and “Lost in Love”.
This year-end night, Hong Kong artists Jay Fung and Cloud Wan will also perform. There will be no shortage of a children's choir and the Hong Kong Police Band to welcome 2026. The performances start at 11:28 pm.
Another countdown is scheduled in the Kowloon area, at WestK Christmas Town 2025. The public can attend concerts by On Chan, Kandy Wong, The Hertz, Nowhere Boys, DJ P-Chef and Hong Kong Arts Without Boundaries Foundation, located at WestK Christmas Lane [Harbourside East Lawn, Art Park], with the Victoria Harbor as a backdrop. The party continues after midnight. Still with remnants of Christmas, the public will be able to see and photograph the tree that is at WestK Christmas Town 2025 and is 12 meters high.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:46:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Morgan Stanley less optimistic about MGM China results</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/jogo-morgan-stanley-menos-optimista-face-a-resultados-da-mgm-china/</link><description>The investment bank predicts that MGM China's new contract with its parent company to use the MGM brand will have a significant impact on the gaming concessionaire's financial results.
The rise in costs for using the MGM brand by the game concessionaire MGM China led investment bank Morgan Stanley to reduce expectations regarding the company's financial results. In a note released to investors, the investment bank now expects the concessionaire's financial results to fall within the market average, whereas previously it expected them to exceed the average.
The change in expectations regarding MGM China takes into account the new contract for using the MGM company's brand. According to details released before Christmas, MGM China will now pay 3.5 percent of consolidated monthly net revenues, up from 1.75 percent. This difference means that MGM China will pay practically double to MGM Resorts International, the parent company.
Based on this change, Morgan Stanley explains that the new payments should cost the dealership about 7 percent of earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) per year.
The recently revealed agreement lasts for 20 years, depending on the renewal of the gaming concession after 2030, and foresees a maximum payment of 188.3 million US dollars (1.5 billion patacas) for 2026. However, financial services company CBRE Equity Research believes that the value of MGM China's profits for next year should result in a payment of around US$166 million (1.3 billion patacas).
Historical values
The payment of around US$166 million for next year contrasts with what has been happening since at least 2023. In that year, the first without movement restrictions after the Covid-19 pandemic, MGM China paid MGM Resorts International around US$55.2 million. The following year, payments rose to US$70.9 million, reflecting the company's improved financial performance.
Payments for the current year are not yet known, but by the end of September they totaled US$56.5 million. Taking into account that this rate of profits is maintained, despite the market having expanded in recent months, payments for this year are expected to be around 75.3 million US dollars.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:38:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Research | Prize created for studies on Sino-Portuguese relations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/investigacao-criado-premio-para-estudos-sobre-relacoes-sino-portuguesas/</link><description>The “Fundação Jorge Álvares-General Vasco Rocha Vieira-Portugal-China Friendship Award” will award 25 thousand euros per year and aims to recognize institutions that promote initiatives to strengthen rapprochement between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities
The Jorge Álvares Foundation launched an annual prize, worth 25 thousand euros, to encourage the study and research of relations between Portugal and China, through Macau, according to the entity's website.
With the “Fundação Jorge Álvares-General Vasco Rocha Vieira-Portugal-China Friendship Award”, it also intends to recognize “institutions that promote relevant initiatives in order to reinforce the rapprochement between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities”, it is stated on the foundation's website. “It aims to honor and contribute to perpetuating the memory of the last governor of Macau, founder of the Jorge Álvares Foundation, its curator and first president, who passed away about a year ago”, the current curator, Tiago Vasconcelos, wrote on social media on Monday.
The prize will be awarded, alternately, to institutions, in even-numbered years and from 2026, and to research work, in odd-numbered years, this being launched in 2027.
In the first case, the award is open to any institution, national or foreign, rewarding “relevant actions that develop or deepen the relationship between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities”, in the fields of Portuguese, Chinese or Patuá culture and languages, science, education, philanthropy, among others.
Open investigation
With regard to research work, the award “is open to anyone without academic restrictions, nationality or otherwise”, and rewards “the quality of studies and written work on a topic, to be indicated for each edition, within the scope of relations between Portugal and China, particularly through Macau”. “From the signing of the joint declaration to the transfer of the Portuguese administration of Macau” is, according to the regulations, the theme for the first edition of the award in the research category.
Vasco Joaquim Rocha Vieira was born on August 16, 1939. He was Chief of the Army General Staff and, inherently, member of the Revolution Council between 1976 and 1978.
He served as minister of the Republic of the Azores (1986-1991) and in 1991 was appointed Governor of Macau by the then
President of the Portuguese Republic, Mário Soares. He was the 138th and last Portuguese governor of Macau, a position he held until 1999, when the territory was transferred to China.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:37:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching | Around 97% of students use AI tools</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/ensino-cerca-de-97-dos-alunos-utiliza-ferramentas-de-ia/</link><description>Around 97 percent of secondary school students admitted to having used Artificial Intelligence as a tool to help with their studies. The conclusion is part of a study carried out by the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau, which compared the development of students at local secondary level with students in the Greater Bay Area.
Based on the opinion of 2,000 students, the results presented by deputy Lam Lon Wai indicate that 97 percent of students recognized using artificial intelligence. Among these, more than 50 percent stated that artificial intelligence contributed to their obtaining better grades.
Half of the respondents also stated that artificial intelligence can generate excessive dependence and that it can affect the development of logical and critical reasoning. Given these results, FAOM recommends that schools customize artificial intelligence tools, to take advantage of the advantages and avoid the negative aspects.
The association also considers that it is necessary to change the mentality of educational establishments, with education less focused on obtaining grades to enter the best universities. According to FAOM, the priority should be teaching students to think and develop skills to solve everyday problems.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:34:10</pubDate></item><item><title>ONE | Southern section of the campus in Hengqin will cost 2.38 billion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/um-seccao-sul-do-campus-em-hengqin-vai-custar-238-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The companies Companhia de Construção e Investimento Predial Ming Shun and Jian Tai Construction, from the Huafa group, were chosen to carry out the work, which is scheduled for completion by November 2028.
Construction work on the Southern Section of the new University of Macau Campus in Hengqin will cost 2.38 billion patacas (2.086 billion renminbis), according to the award contract. The information was shared by the company within the local educational institution, Guangdong Hengqin UM Higher Education Development, through the portal of the Directorate of Public Supervision and Asset Management Services (DSSGAP).
The work was awarded through a public tender and the work will be carried out by the consortium made up of the local company Companhia de Construção e Investimento Predial Ming Shun and Jian Tai Construction, which is based in Zhuhai and is part of the state-owned Huafa group.
Since the campus is located in Mainland China, the competition was held in accordance with Chinese legislation and proposals were submitted in renminbis. The consortium made up of Ming Shun and Jian Tai presented the third cheapest proposal of the seven participants in the competition.
The award was publicly announced yesterday, despite having been decided on November 11th, establishing that construction of all buildings must begin by tomorrow. Furthermore, the competition requires that some lots and buildings must be ready by February 2028, while the rest are scheduled for completion by November 2028.
Participated contest
The public tender for the award of the work only included the participation of state-owned companies from Mainland China, some of the largest construction companies in the world. One of the participants was the China Railway Construction Corporation, which presented a proposal worth 2.71 billion patacas (2.38 billion renminbis), the most expensive of all.
The same group was involved twice, through the subsidiary China Railway First, and in this case presented the cheapest proposal worth 1.70 billion patacas (1.48 billion renminbi).
The tender also included a consortium made up of China Overseas Construction Limited and China State Construction Engineering Corporation, which submitted a proposal of 2.61 billion patacas (2.29 billion renminbi).
Zhejiang No. 1 Construction Investment submitted a proposal of 2.53 billion patacas (2.22 billion renminbi), Jiangsu Huajian 2.34 billion patacas (2.05 billion renminbi), while the Beijing Urban Construction Group asked for 2.00 million patacas (1.75 billion renminbi).</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:32:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Light Rail | Deputy questions management and connection with buses</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/metro-ligeiro-deputada-questiona-gestao-e-conexao-com-autocarros/</link><description>Wong Kit Cheng questioned the Government about the integration of payment methods between the Light Rail and public buses. The deputy also wants to know when the public consultation on the development of the Light Rail network will be launched
The development of the Light Rail is the subject of yet another written question by Wong Kit Cheng. In the document, the deputy questions how the planning of this means of transport will be defined without forgetting the connection with the bus network, whose concession contracts expire at the end of 2026.
"It is important to provide a convenient user experience [to passengers]. Taking into account that the bus contracts expire at the end of next year, has the Government already started negotiations on the contracts with the two bus companies, in order to integrate a benefits system?", begins by asking the deputy.
The question arises within the scope of the promise made by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, regarding the installation of new payment terminals at Light Rail stations that can be connected to buses, in order to allow different payment methods.
More specifically, Wong Kit Cheng would like new bus contracts to include the connection of payment methods taking into account the installation of new terminals.
For the deputy, “there is still a large margin for improvement” in the distribution of passengers between the two means of public transport, highlighting that there was a “significant growth” in passengers on the Light Rail, still falling short of “the more than 600 thousand passengers served daily by buses”.
Thus, “to achieve the objective of the Light Rail as the main means of transport, and buses as a complement”, Wong Kit Cheng considers that “the authorities need to optimize the passenger experience, especially with regard to resolving long-standing problems, such as Light Rail payment methods, greater coordination of transfers and the resolution of faults, in addition to improving the accessibility of lines and stations”.
Ongoing assessments
Still regarding the future of the Light Rail, Wong Kit Cheng asked for a “status” of the mid-term assessment that the Executive is carrying out in relation to the execution of the concession contract. “What is the status of these evaluation works?
Are there already preliminary results or optimization recommendations, particularly with regard to improving the quality and stability of the service?”, he asked.
The deputy also took up another promise made in the last debate on the Lines of Government Action by secretary Raymond Tam, regarding the holding of a public consultation on the study of the Light Rail development strategy. “How will this public consultation be organized”, he asks.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:24:35</pubDate></item><item><title>War | Thailand accused Cambodia of violating airspace with 250 drones</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/guerra-tailandia-acusou-camboja-de-violar-espaco-aereo-com-250-drones/</link><description>Thailand yesterday accused Cambodia of violating the current ceasefire agreement by sending 250 unmanned aerial devices (drones) over Thai territory.
The Thai Army indicated that more than 250 drones were detected entering the country in the border area. For the Thai Armed Forces, Cambodia's action constituted a provocation and a violation of measures “aimed at reducing tensions” between Bangkok and Phnom Penh. At the time of writing, the Cambodian authorities had not commented on Thailand's accusation regarding the airspace violation.
The two countries reached a ceasefire on Saturday after three weeks of clashes along their 800-kilometre common border, following two days of negotiations in China. The ceasefire agreement provides for an end to weeks of fighting along the disputed border, which has left more than 100 people dead and more than half a million displaced in both countries. Thai Foreign Minister Sihasak Phuangketkeow and his Cambodian counterpart Prak Sokhonn met in southwest China's Yunnan province for talks mediated by his Chinese counterpart Wang Yi.
The head of Chinese diplomacy stated that Beijing “does not want to see Thailand and Cambodia on battlefields”. During a meeting with his Thai counterpart, Sihasak Phuangketkeow, on Sunday, Wang Yi expressed China's “deep concern” about the “tense situation on the border” and argued that, once the fighting stops, “diplomacy must take the lead”.
“Rebuilding peace is the desire of the people and the expectation of all parties,” said the head of Chinese diplomacy, adding that Beijing’s mediation efforts “never impose themselves on others, nor go beyond limits” and aim to create “a relaxed platform for dialogue.”
A fatal history
US President Donald Trump, who threatened to suspend trade privileges if Thailand and Cambodia did not agree to a ceasefire in July, suggested yesterday that fighting between Thailand and Cambodia “will momentarily cease” and stated that the United States “has become the true United Nations”. The territorial limits have been disputed for decades and were inherited from the French colonial period.
According to official figures, recognized by the United Nations, the latest clashes caused 47 deaths: 26 on the Thai side and 21 on the Cambodian side. In July, the first phase of clashes left 43 dead in five days, before a ceasefire was agreed.
Another agreement was subsequently signed on October 26 in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, in the presence of the President of the United States, but was suspended by Thailand after several Bangkok soldiers were injured in the explosion of a military land mine in the border area.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:53:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Weddings | Si Ka Lon wants Macau to be like Las Vegas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/casamentos-si-ka-lon-quer-que-macau-seja-como-las-vegas/</link><description>Representative Si Ka Lon argues that Macau should invest in the wedding industry for tourism purposes, similar to what happens in Las Vegas.
In an oral question presented to the Government, which will be answered in the Chamber next week, the deputy argues that “‘destination weddings’ is one of the directions for the development of the tourism industry”. Si Ka Lon asks whether local authorities will “take as a reference the successful experiences of Las Vegas or Hong Kong, allowing marriage registration in Macau, regardless of the place of residence or nationality of the bride and groom, with a view to exploring the 'wedding tourism' market”.
In the deputy's view, the Executive can “take advantage of Macau's advantages and singularities”, investing in the promotion of “plans for outdoor wedding ceremonies, in order to increase the competitiveness of Macau's wedding tourism products and create a new business card for the city”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:35:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Money exchange | Raid targets 60 million Hong Kong dollar deal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/troca-de-dinheiro-rusga-visa-negocio-de-60-milhoes-de-dolares-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Judiciary Police (PJ) announced the arrest of two women for allegedly being involved in illegal exchanges of money for gambling at a casino in Cotai. According to police estimates, the business operating in a jewelry store had a turnover of more than 60 million Hong Kong dollars, with profits being 1 million Hong Kong dollars.
The detainees are a 36-year-old local resident and a 27-year-old woman from Mainland China. Both performed sales roles in the commercial space. At yesterday's press conference in which the case was presented, PJ representatives admitted that they were currently investigating the whereabouts of the owner of the commercial space.
In addition to the arrests, around 500 thousand Hong Kong dollars in cash were seized. A cell phone was also seized, which was allegedly used to arrange money exchanges. The investigation was based on anonymous complaints that alerted authorities to the possibility that illegal money exchanges were taking place inside the store.
The arrests took place after the agents spent a day monitoring what was happening in the commercial space, having decided to act after seeing three customers with “suspicious behavior”. The store had been operating in the casino, which was not identified, since 2019, and the two employees confessed to exchanging money. The prisoners received salaries of 13 thousand patacas and 15 thousand patacas, which included overtime pay.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:40:43</pubDate></item><item><title>New Year's Eve | Street parties and concerts to end 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/passagem-de-ano-festas-na-rua-e-concertos-para-encerrar-2025/</link><description>Macau and Hong Kong will be in full swing tonight with celebrations that will welcome 2026. From free concerts next to Praça do Lago Sai Van and at the Taipa Houses-Museum, to shows at Cotai and Mariza's performance at the Macau Cultural Center, there is no shortage of options for all tastes
The end of 2025 is here, and if some opt for a more homely celebration, there will be many people willing to go out and have fun in the company of friends and with lots of music in the mix. With paid and free options, Macau and Hong Kong offer a range of options for various tastes.
One of the initiatives comes from the Cultural Institute (IC) and is already a tradition. The end of 2025 is celebrated next to Praça do Lago Sai Van from 10pm, and from 9pm at the Taipa Houses-Museum, with the “New Year’s Eve Concert – Macau 2025” and the “New Year’s Eve Party – Taipa 2025”.
Various singers and musical groups perform at the concert on the peninsula side, between 10pm and 12:10am, including Hong Kong singer Panther Chan and rock band Dear Jane. There is also a cast of local artists such as Soler, Filipe Tou, KC Ao Ieong, winifai, Jenny, thetiredeyes and Initial B, “who will alternate [performances] to present a diverse range of music to celebrate a dazzling New Year's Eve”, describes the IC.
In the case of this performance at Praça do Lago Sai Van, the stage floor stands out, which will feature “an electronic screen combined with lighting and visual effects, providing a totally new visual experience”. “The entire performance will be presented in a theatrical format adapted to each session, which conveys, through narratives, the wishes for the coming year and reflects the exciting facets of the city”, adds the IC.
Regarding the concerts at the Taipa Houses-Museum, the theme will be “Multicultural Integration”, with the public being able to see performances by FIDA, Tuna Macaense, Bossa Eva and João Gomes &amp; Band and Karen Tong, a singer from Hong Kong.
In addition, there will be performances by the Bollywood Dreams Group, by Victor Kumar, and the Filipino dance groups of the Macau Bisdak Association and Burmese and Vietnamese dance groups from Macau. The poster is completed with magic presentations by magician Jason Fong.
From 8:30 pm and until 11:30 pm, there will be cultural exhibitors from local communities in the Philippines, India, Myanmar and Vietnam, who aim to promote the cuisine and culture of their countries.
Mariza at CCM
Another great highlight to end the year is the performance by fado singer Mariza at the Macau Cultural Center (CCM) from 8pm, alongside the Macau Orchestra. “Mariza, the Queen of Fado and the Macau Orchestra (OM)” is the name given to the concert where the fado singer will perform, “with her deeply emotional voice, a selection of iconic fados, providing the public with a musical experience that transcends genres and spatial and temporal boundaries”.
The Portuguese is described “as one of the biggest international Fado stars, being recognized for her own musical style, which incorporates elements of soul, jazz and gospel”.
Looking at Cotai, gaming operators bet heavily on year-end programs. The Venetian Arena concert hall hosts the third and final in a series of concerts by Jason Zhang, which began on Monday. Tickets range from MOP680 to MOP2,580 for VIP seats.
Jason Zhang Jie was born in 1982 in China and debuted in the “My Show” competition in 2004, becoming the winner, which gave him access to a contract with Universal Music China. At the end of 2023, he already had 15 albums recorded and a total of 87 concerts in his career. Still at the Venetian, as well as at The Parisian Macao and The Londoner, there will be fireworks, with the traditional countdown until 2026. The “Sands New Year’s Eve Countdown Extravaganza” event starts with music at 9:30 pm.
Like Sands China, the gaming operator Galaxy also made its plans to end the year in style, namely in the Andaz Macau, Long Bar and Pony &amp; Plume developments. The party takes place with DJ performances and the promise of unlimited drinks.
For those who want something different and, at the same time, themed, there will be a “La Nuit Rouge Countdown Party” at The Ritz-Carlton Bar and Lounge, with French cabaret and live music.
Air Supply in Hong Kong
Going to Hong Kong to close the year 2025 could also be an option. To begin with, one of the centers of entertainment will be the pedestrian zone on Chater Road, in Central.
On the Hong Kong Tourism Board website, it is stated that the public can enjoy “a new format of live music performances combined with light shows”, namely by the band Air Supply, who will perform “a special performance with their timeless classic hits”. The Australian duo, formed in 1975, already has a 50-year career under their belt and has well-known songs such as “All Out of Love”, “Making Love Out of Nothing at All” and “Lost in Love”.
This year-end night, Hong Kong artists Jay Fung and Cloud Wan will also perform. There will be no shortage of a children's choir and the Hong Kong Police Band to welcome 2026. The performances start at 11:28 pm.
Another countdown is scheduled in the Kowloon area, at WestK Christmas Town 2025. The public can attend concerts by On Chan, Kandy Wong, The Hertz, Nowhere Boys, DJ P-Chef and Hong Kong Arts Without Boundaries Foundation, located at WestK Christmas Lane [Harbourside East Lawn, Art Park], with the Victoria Harbor as a backdrop. The party continues after midnight. Still with remnants of Christmas, the public will be able to see and photograph the tree that is at WestK Christmas Town 2025 and is 12 meters high.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:46:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong hosts winter festival until Sunday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/hong-kong-acolhe-festival-de-inverno-ate-domingo/</link><description>For those who still want to experience the last moments of the season between Christmas and New Year, the neighboring territory hosts the “Hong Kong Winter Fest”, with two events ending next Sunday. A giant Christmas tree in the city center, lots of lights and spaces that spark the imagination is what you can expect from this initiative.
One of the spaces is the “Christmas City”, located in Central, which has a 20 meter high Christmas tree and various decorations with toys that make reference to the festive days that have just come to an end. The “Christmas Town” began on November 14th and can be visited until this Sunday.
Another attraction of this festival is the “Immersive Light Show”, also in Central. As the name suggests, the public can see a light show, with three-dimensional projections, music and animation, with viewing points in North Square and South Square, Statue Square Gardens. There are shows every 30 minutes between 7:30 am and 11:30 pm.
Here, “eight iconic buildings become a giant screen” for this show, with figures such as snowmen, angels or reindeer dancing “among the buildings and trees, creating a rich and dreamy experience that illuminates the festive nights of Hong Kong”, describes the tourism department of the HKSAR Government.
The buildings where the light show will be projected are the Bank of China Tower, Hong Kong City Hall High Block, Hong Kong Club, the main building of HSBC and Standard Chartered Bank, among others.
Lights until February
There is also a third initiative integrated into this winter festival that runs until February 22nd. This is “Starlight Boulevard”, where Chater Road will be adorned with various lights, including a pedestrian crossing and “an impressive centerpiece above the Chater House”.
“Visitors can continue their journey under a golden canopy of light to reach Noëlia at LANDMARK, an enchanting large-scale interactive installation for more surprises and Christmas charm”, it is further described on the event page. This area of ​​lights can be visited between Chater Road and Central.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:46:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysts estimate that BYD will surpass Tesla in global sales by 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/analistas-estimam-que-byd-supere-tesla-nas-vendas-globais-em-2025/</link><description>BYD's rapid global expansion and Tesla's regulatory difficulties in the United States and other markets should allow the Chinese manufacturer to lead global sales of all-electric vehicles for the first time in 2025, analysts predict. Both groups are expected to release their annual reports soon, but based on the latest data, BYD's accumulated advantage is such that it seems almost impossible that Tesla has managed to regain ground.
By the end of November, BYD had already sold 2,066,002 fully electric vehicles, becoming the first brand to surpass that milestone. Tesla registered 1,217,902 units by the end of September.
The North American manufacturer benefited, in the third quarter, from a shopping rush caused by the end of tax incentives in the USA, which led many consumers to anticipate purchasing their vehicles. Tesla's global deliveries rose 7 percent year-on-year to 497,099 vehicles.
Analysts predicted a rapid contraction in the following quarter. The consensus of analysts at the financial services company FactSet points to 449 thousand units in the fourth quarter (-9.48 percent compared to the previous year) and a total of 1.65 million vehicles for 2025 (-7.66 percent). This is an annual projection well below the level already reached by BYD until November 30th.
German bank Deutsche Bank estimates that Tesla will deliver 405,000 vehicles in the fourth quarter, while analysts at Swiss bank UBS point to 415,000 – both forecasts recently revised downwards.
Deutsche Bank highlighted sales below expectations in North America (-33 percent), Europe (-34 percent) and, to a lesser extent, China (-10 percent).
Glass half full
The TD Cowen bank presents a more optimistic estimate (429 thousand units), but highlights that the quarter was “a little delicate”, due to the end of tax incentives, which made projections difficult, according to analyst Itay Michaeli. “Tesla’s deliveries will show signs of weakness in the fourth quarter,” said the director of Wedbush Securities, Dan Ives. “A total of 420 thousand vehicles would already be enough to show some stability in demand, at a time when the market is focused on the launch of autonomous driving in 2026”, he added.
Tesla's sales have been affected by a slower-than-expected electrical transition, increased competition and US President Donald Trump's decisions since returning to power in January.
The closeness between Elon Musk and Trump, both during the campaign and after taking office, also affected the brand's image, leading to calls for a boycott. Sales fell sharply, especially in Europe.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:50:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Chinese excursionists with a drop of almost 24%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/turismo-excursionistas-chineses-com-quebra-de-quase-24/</link><description>The Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC) revealed yesterday that the number of day trippers recorded an annual drop of 12.5 percent in November, to a total of 191,000.
Noteworthy is the fact that the number of arrivals of visitors on tours from Mainland China, 148,000, fell by 23.7 percent in November, while the number of international visitors on tours, 28,000, grew by 33.8 percent.
At the end of November, Macau had a hotel complex with 147 units, just one more compared to November 2024, which provided 45,000 guest rooms, an increase of 3.5 percent. The occupancy rate that month stood at 90.2 percent, with the occupancy rate of 5-star hotels, at 94 percent, rising 2.5 percentage points, while that of 4-star hotels (84.6 percent) and 3-star hotels (84.3 percent) decreased by 1.2 and 3.1 percentage points, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:39:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yan (464-549), Emperor Wu of Liang (r.502-549) who greatly promoted Buddhism, perplexed by the decision of the wise Tao Hongjing (456-536) to withdraw from the city in 492, at just thirty-six years old, and go to live far away in the middle of the mountains instead of staying at court, where his wisdom and advice would be abundantly recognized and rewarded, sent him a missive asking him why.
According to tradition, the sage, who had dedicated himself to studying the Dao, did not respond to him, but sent him a drawing with two oxen; one free to graze, the other trapped and with a brake. Xiao Yan understood.
The fact that Tao Hongjing chose the corpulent animal, which seems to act without effort or haste, to expose his situation, echoes the understanding of the desire for union with nature that certain Chan followers showed with the figure of Laozi (c.371-477 BC) riding an ox (niu) or a buffalo (shuiniu) walking towards the sunset, moving away from civilization, its useless wars and confrontations.
Years later, during the Southern Song dynasty (1127-1279), painters used the figure of the patient ox several times, taking advantage of its multiple symbolic meaning. The court painter Yan Ciping (act. 1164-1187) was the author of particularly expressive works in which the figure of the buffalo appears associated with young boys.
As in the painting in which the sensation of “docile peace” emerges, as its name ciping implies, and the tactile relationship with the earth, showing two boys sitting, combing each other next to a tree, behind two buffaloes, one large and one small, also sitting, resting (vertical scroll, ink and color on silk, at the Sen-oku Museum, Hakukokan, in Kyoto).
In another, made on a fan mounted on an album sheet, a Boy and a Buffalo in an Autumn Landscape (ink and color on silk, 23 x 21 cm, at the Cleveland Museum of Art) one sees, in the fog, as the time of autumnal transformation unfolds, a young man sitting on a buffalo, leading it by the bridle, expressing in the figure of the buffalo the "true me", the boy being The driver, the most fragile-looking Chan practitioner, abandons the world conditioned by illusions.
Yan Ciping, like others at the Song dynasty court such as the famous Ma Yuan (c.1160-1225), came from a family of painters who refined their own family style. In certain paintings, such as Inn on a Cliff Covered with Pine Trees (fan mounted as an album sheet, ink and color on silk, 21.4 x 23 cm, at the Metmuseum) it is difficult to distinguish which of the two brothers, sons of the painter Yan Zhong, Ciyu or Ciping is the author. In it, a large part of the painting's space is left blank, suggesting the Chan Buddhist conception that matter emerges from emptiness. Looking at the small painting, the viewer could share the feeling of the object's withdrawal from the work.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yan (464-549), Emperor Wu of Liang (r.502-549) who greatly promoted Buddhism, perplexed by the decision of the wise Tao Hongjing (456-536) to withdraw from the city in 492, at just thirty-six years old, and go to live far away in the middle of the mountains instead of staying at court, where his wisdom and advice would be abundantly recognized and rewarded, sent him a missive asking him why.
According to tradition, the sage, who had dedicated himself to studying the Dao, did not respond to him, but sent him a drawing with two oxen; one free to graze, the other trapped and with a brake. Xiao Yan understood.
The fact that Tao Hongjing chose the corpulent animal, which seems to act without effort or haste, to expose his situation, echoes the understanding of the desire for union with nature that certain Chan followers showed with the figure of Laozi (c.371-477 BC) riding an ox (niu) or a buffalo (shuiniu) walking towards the sunset, moving away from civilization, its useless wars and confrontations.
Years later, during the Southern Song dynasty (1127-1279), painters used the figure of the patient ox several times, taking advantage of its multiple symbolic meaning. The court painter Yan Ciping (act. 1164-1187) was the author of particularly expressive works in which the figure of the buffalo appears associated with young boys.
As in the painting in which the sensation of “docile peace” emerges, as its name ciping implies, and the tactile relationship with the earth, showing two boys sitting, combing each other next to a tree, behind two buffaloes, one large and one small, also sitting, resting (vertical scroll, ink and color on silk, at the Sen-oku Museum, Hakukokan, in Kyoto).
In another, made on a fan mounted on an album sheet, a Boy and a Buffalo in an Autumn Landscape (ink and color on silk, 23 x 21 cm, at the Cleveland Museum of Art) one sees, in the fog, as the time of autumnal transformation unfolds, a young man sitting on a buffalo, leading it by the bridle, expressing in the figure of the buffalo the "true me", the boy being The driver, the most fragile-looking Chan practitioner, abandons the world conditioned by illusions.
Yan Ciping, like others at the Song dynasty court such as the famous Ma Yuan (c.1160-1225), came from a family of painters who refined their own family style. In certain paintings, such as Inn on a Cliff Covered with Pine Trees (fan mounted as an album sheet, ink and color on silk, 21.4 x 23 cm, at the Metmuseum) it is difficult to distinguish which of the two brothers, sons of the painter Yan Zhong, Ciyu or Ciping is the author. In it, a large part of the painting's space is left blank, suggesting the Chan Buddhist conception that matter emerges from emptiness. Looking at the small painting, the viewer could share the feeling of the object's withdrawal from the work.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Carlos Morais José</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/carlos-mj/</link><description>Our approach to reality, no matter how disciplined and honest the approach to thought, is always ridden by error, especially when there is no alternative to the use of imagination. Geniuses, the ancient Greeks knew about the Earth's sphericity and that's why they attributed a maximum circle to the planet, which they named Ison. Today we call it Ecuador. However, these Hellene geographers considered these regions to be unreachable and uninhabitable.
Torrid Zone: there, unbearable heat would boil the oceans, preventing the passage to temperate zones, postulated further south of this line that marked the maximum circle of the sphere.
A simple islet, named “das Rolas”, a mere hundred meters from the island of São Tomé, in the Gulf of Guinea, is crossed by this equatorial line. This location of the former Portuguese colony provides it with a type of climate that is only found with such intensity close to the equator: the temperature varies little and, contrary to what the Greeks thought, it does not reach excessive values. Its range is between 20 and 29 degrees Celsius, but the “normal” temperature remains between 23 and 25 degrees. Night, day and throughout the year.
In the permanently cloudy sky, the Sun and Moon are rarely seen. And when this happens, they never fail to appear wrapped in veils of clouds, which gives them an unreal character, invoking ancient magic, witnessing moving skies.
When, towards the end of the afternoon, the rain extends its reign for more than two or three hours, often presented to plants and animals by a thunderstorm, the light dies and a very dark night reigns over the land and sea. The stars fall beyond the clouds that cover everything. On a night like this, there is no moonlight to illuminate or pierce the clouds. A deep pitch falls on the earth, a darkness that is impenetrable to our eyes. And it was like that, at three in the morning, that I woke up. My eyes opened to an abysmal darkness. Nothing, absolutely nothing could be seen. He knew he had the window open, but not a ray of light deigned to enter the room. I reached out, but the lamp didn't work. The electricity was out again. I waited for some time, hoping to get used to the blackness and discover some shapes in it. In vain. He was immersed in a well of black, warm water, he could feel the humidity on his skin, which had just woken up sweaty from a nightmare. I decided to get up and leave the house, looking for some light.
The rain had stopped. Outside, the forest celebrated, hummed, reverberated with sounds. There would be millions of insects, amphibians, vertebrates, all of them nocturnal animals, also immersed in the dark, where they found food, sex and salvation. Life didn't need light. It was heard, deafening.
At the edge of that spontaneous excess of trees and plants, nothing could be seen either. Dark, impenetrable dark. Only the sound prevailed, louder and louder, and suggested movements among the trees. That mixture of buzzing, squealing, buzzing, ringing, rales, loudly surrounded my ears, building a helmet that blocked all other senses, including the one that affects me in space. I was dizzy. And in that half-daziness, I groped my way back to the house, to my bed.
There was nothing he could do. Forget the coffee, eliminate the possibility of reading or consulting a computer. Lying in the dark as if waking up in a coffin.
Our mind cannot handle fear for long. Mostly irrational. As was the case. I can't really talk about fear, fear, but about discomfort, derived from the fragile situation that I attributed to myself. Everything could happen in that dark, and I wouldn't see him. If for some reason you had to leave the room, where would you go, if everything was plunged into darkness? But nothing was happening in the darkness of my room, nor would anything happen that would force me to grope through the pitch black, looking for a light. On the contrary, in that bed I was protected by the dark and if I saw nothing nothing would see me either. This thought provided some comfort. All things considered, that abysmal pitch was strangely comfortable for me. I made it a protective cloak and not a space of threats. And so I remained.
The ancient Chinese say that everyone has an excellent place to stay. A place where you can develop and enjoy who you really are. Maybe this dark package is mine. Perhaps in it I can be for myself what I really am, setting aside what surrounds me, instructs and distracts me. I am undoubtedly alone. Without the possibility of communicating with another person or even acting in my surroundings. I'm left. With me. Alone. Isolated. Here I am not the anthropologist, nor the editor, none of my social titles perform any functions. I am not the husband, the friend or the lover. From the outside I only have the language that inhabits me and my brain rebels in search of meaning. And even this takes second place in daydreams whose material seems to emerge from another place, from knowledge not conditioned to a language — an impression of the world and not its explanation.
I am a consciousness separated from things, which in the dark finds its most intimate relationship with the universe, of almost dissolution, a chamazita, a fiery being, whose interior insists on shining in the dark night. The universe and me. I'm unique. Nothing can divide me without destroying me. I know I am an individual, because I feel it deeply, with an almost painful acuity, even though neurologists tell me about the Self as an evolutionary fiction, structuralists see me as a product of Culture, psychoanalysts as a Family and Marxists as History.
(continued)</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yan (464-549), Emperor Wu of Liang (r.502-549) who greatly promoted Buddhism, perplexed by the decision of the wise Tao Hongjing (456-536) to withdraw from the city in 492, at just thirty-six years old, and go to live far away in the middle of the mountains instead of staying at court, where his wisdom and advice would be abundantly recognized and rewarded, sent him a missive asking him why.
According to tradition, the sage, who had dedicated himself to studying the Dao, did not respond to him, but sent him a drawing with two oxen; one free to graze, the other trapped and with a brake. Xiao Yan understood.
The fact that Tao Hongjing chose the corpulent animal, which seems to act without effort or haste, to expose his situation, echoes the understanding of the desire for union with nature that certain Chan followers showed with the figure of Laozi (c.371-477 BC) riding an ox (niu) or a buffalo (shuiniu) walking towards the sunset, moving away from civilization, its useless wars and confrontations.
Years later, during the Southern Song dynasty (1127-1279), painters used the figure of the patient ox several times, taking advantage of its multiple symbolic meaning. The court painter Yan Ciping (act. 1164-1187) was the author of particularly expressive works in which the figure of the buffalo appears associated with young boys.
As in the painting in which the sensation of “docile peace” emerges, as its name ciping implies, and the tactile relationship with the earth, showing two boys sitting, combing each other next to a tree, behind two buffaloes, one large and one small, also sitting, resting (vertical scroll, ink and color on silk, at the Sen-oku Museum, Hakukokan, in Kyoto).
In another, made on a fan mounted on an album sheet, a Boy and a Buffalo in an Autumn Landscape (ink and color on silk, 23 x 21 cm, at the Cleveland Museum of Art) one sees, in the fog, as the time of autumnal transformation unfolds, a young man sitting on a buffalo, leading it by the bridle, expressing in the figure of the buffalo the "true me", the boy being The driver, the most fragile-looking Chan practitioner, abandons the world conditioned by illusions.
Yan Ciping, like others at the Song dynasty court such as the famous Ma Yuan (c.1160-1225), came from a family of painters who refined their own family style. In certain paintings, such as Inn on a Cliff Covered with Pine Trees (fan mounted as an album sheet, ink and color on silk, 21.4 x 23 cm, at the Metmuseum) it is difficult to distinguish which of the two brothers, sons of the painter Yan Zhong, Ciyu or Ciping is the author. In it, a large part of the painting's space is left blank, suggesting the Chan Buddhist conception that matter emerges from emptiness. Looking at the small painting, the viewer could share the feeling of the object's withdrawal from the work.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Paulo Maia and Carmo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Xiao Yan (464-549), Emperor Wu of Liang (r.502-549) who greatly promoted Buddhism, perplexed by the decision of the wise Tao Hongjing (456-536) to withdraw from the city in 492, at just thirty-six years old, and go to live far away in the middle of the mountains instead of staying at court, where his wisdom and advice would be abundantly recognized and rewarded, sent him a missive asking him why.
According to tradition, the sage, who had dedicated himself to studying the Dao, did not respond to him, but sent him a drawing with two oxen; one free to graze, the other trapped and with a brake. Xiao Yan understood.
The fact that Tao Hongjing chose the corpulent animal, which seems to act without effort or haste, to expose his situation, echoes the understanding of the desire for union with nature that certain Chan followers showed with the figure of Laozi (c.371-477 BC) riding an ox (niu) or a buffalo (shuiniu) walking towards the sunset, moving away from civilization, its useless wars and confrontations.
Years later, during the Southern Song dynasty (1127-1279), painters used the figure of the patient ox several times, taking advantage of its multiple symbolic meaning. The court painter Yan Ciping (act. 1164-1187) was the author of particularly expressive works in which the figure of the buffalo appears associated with young boys.
As in the painting in which the sensation of “docile peace” emerges, as its name ciping implies, and the tactile relationship with the earth, showing two boys sitting, combing each other next to a tree, behind two buffaloes, one large and one small, also sitting, resting (vertical scroll, ink and color on silk, at the Sen-oku Museum, Hakukokan, in Kyoto).
In another, made on a fan mounted on an album sheet, a Boy and a Buffalo in an Autumn Landscape (ink and color on silk, 23 x 21 cm, at the Cleveland Museum of Art) one sees, in the fog, as the time of autumnal transformation unfolds, a young man sitting on a buffalo, leading it by the bridle, expressing in the figure of the buffalo the "true me", the boy being The driver, the most fragile-looking Chan practitioner, abandons the world conditioned by illusions.
Yan Ciping, like others at the Song dynasty court such as the famous Ma Yuan (c.1160-1225), came from a family of painters who refined their own family style. In certain paintings, such as Inn on a Cliff Covered with Pine Trees (fan mounted as an album sheet, ink and color on silk, 21.4 x 23 cm, at the Metmuseum) it is difficult to distinguish which of the two brothers, sons of the painter Yan Zhong, Ciyu or Ciping is the author. In it, a large part of the painting's space is left blank, suggesting the Chan Buddhist conception that matter emerges from emptiness. Looking at the small painting, the viewer could share the feeling of the object's withdrawal from the work.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>UCM | White Paper suggests methods to accelerate economic diversification</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/18/ucm-livro-branco-sugere-metodos-para-acelerar-diversificacao-economica/</link><description>The “White Paper on Scientific and Technological Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”, produced at the City University of Macau, refers to inequalities in the relationship between countries and concludes that “economic diversification has advanced at a slow pace”. Bárbara Morais, main writer of the document, explains the main conclusions of the analysis
On December 3rd, a White Paper was launched that provides a look and analysis of the way in which cooperation in scientific and technological areas between China, Macau and Portuguese-speaking countries has been taking place, outlining some criticisms, not only on this topic, but also on the economic direction that the Macao SAR is taking.
The document, entitled “White Paper on Scientific and Technological Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”, was produced by the City University of Macau (UCM) and had Bárbara Morais, a doctoral student at the institution, as main writer.
In an interview with HM, she describes that, in Macau, “economic diversification has advanced at a slower pace than desired, keeping the economy structurally dependent on gambling and tourism”.
"The central message of the White Paper is clear: Macau needs to accelerate the transition to functions with greater added value. However, the current context offers a renewed window of opportunity. With the support of the Greater Bay Area and, very specifically, the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, Macau now has new structural opportunities to recover lost momentum and reposition itself, not just as a cultural bridge, but as a true platform for innovation", he said.
Still on the territory, but in relation to Forum Macau, the “success in institutionalizing political dialogue” is mentioned, but the White Paper “points the finger at the insufficiency of execution mechanisms”. “To streamline the role of the Forum and transform it into a tool for tangible results, the White Paper advocates a paradigm shift: it is necessary to move from declarations of intent to technicality”, describes Bárbara Morais. The doctoral student suggests “the creation of specialized technical working groups, especially in the technological sphere, and the rigorous definition of performance indicators, such as the number of registered patents, startups created or joint research projects”.
“At the same time, it is suggested to establish a common agenda focused on areas of the future, such as green energy, health, the maritime economy and artificial intelligence, subject to a periodic assessment of progress”, he also said.
The place of arbitration
Taking these meager developments into account, the White Paper suggests that Macau assert itself “as a center for technological arbitration and intellectual property governance”.
HM questioned Bárbara Morais about what should be done in effective terms, taking into account the existence, for several years, of an arbitration center, and the fact that it has been a topic on the territory's political agenda for a long time. The doctoral student highlights that “in order for these ideas, debated for years, to stop being rhetoric and become reality, the Macao SAR needs to create a legal framework specialized in technological disputes aligned with the most demanding international standards”.
"It is essential to attract international experts and arbitrators through competitive incentives and establish an arbitration center that enjoys recognition both in Portuguese-speaking countries and in the Greater Bay Area. The objective is to develop mediation, certification and management services for intellectual property assets, positioning Macau as a 'safe haven', neutral and efficient, for the resolution of international technological disputes", he added.
Unequal cooperation
In global terms, and with regard to cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries (PLP), the White Paper refers to “top planning” by Beijing for cooperation in universities and scientific research. However, planning “does not translate, linearly, into equally effective execution mechanisms on the ground, nor does it guarantee homogeneous results among the nine Portuguese-speaking countries”.
Planning implies “clear guidelines, defined priorities and diplomatic instruments mobilized to guide this cooperation”, with policies such as “Made in China 2025” or the “Digital Silk Road”, which “integrate technological cooperation with the PLP into the very core of Chinese foreign policy and national innovation”, highlights the author.
However, there are “inequalities, which are perhaps the most striking feature of this relationship”, as Bárbara Morais explains. “The current scenario reveals a profound asymmetry, characterized by a ‘bicephaly’ in cooperation. (…) The main scientific capabilities, the robust technological infrastructure and the volume of effective cooperation are overwhelmingly concentrated in Portugal and Brazil”. On the contrary, “Portuguese-speaking African countries (PALOP) and Timor-Leste have a significantly lower participation”.
According to Bárbara Morais, the “disparity does not arise from a lack of political will, but rather from structural funding limitations, a shortage of qualified human resources and the fragility of local research institutions”. Thus, there is “two-speed cooperation, very asymmetrical within the Portuguese-speaking community itself”.
The White Paper highlights the “historic crossroads” in relation to cooperation between China and the PLP, which means “the urgent need to move from potential to implementation” in this matter.
"There are ambitious visions and strategic plans, but practical results remain below what is possible. To resolve this crossroads, the proposed path involves strengthening execution mechanisms, investing massively in talent and technical-scientific education, creating ecosystems of genuine collaborative innovation between China, Macau and the PLP, and, above all, having the courage to measure results and reformulate strategies based on empirical evidence, abandoning the discourse of circumstance in favor of economic and scientific pragmatism."
Gaps in Africa
Another of the conclusions of the White Paper is the “tenuity” of academic links with the African continent, which Bárbara Morais describes as a “fragile scenario”. “There is a triad of factors: the scarcity of installed scientific capacity, the chronic lack of funding and consistent mobility programs”, without forgetting “the absence of stable joint research structures”.
“To bridge this gap and create a lasting critical mass, the White Paper is not limited to diagnosis, suggesting concrete measures such as the robust reinforcement of research grants, the creation of joint doctoral programs, the implementation of collaborative laboratories and the design of academic mobility mechanisms specifically oriented to the African reality”, he adds.
The document also talks about the negative impact of “geopolitical asymmetries”, such as the “technological restrictions of the European Union and NATO on Portugal”. According to Bárbara Morais, “real and restrictive impacts” are at stake. "These limitations condition the participation of Portugal and, by extension, of other Portuguese-speaking actors that cooperate in a network with Lisbon, in high-technology projects that involve China. The impact is particularly sensitive in critical areas such as 5G telecommunications, defense, artificial intelligence and cybersecurity, creating barriers that require complex diplomatic navigation."
New strategies
The White Paper was developed at the UCM Research Institute on Portuguese-Speaking Countries, and written by Bárbara Morais with the participation of academic João Simões. The project is based on a review of academic literature on the topic and also on the results of the “Technological Cooperation Launch Seminar”, held on July 22, 2025 at UCM.
The work analyzes areas such as “strategic evolution”, “institutional mechanisms”, “technological milestones” and “structural challenges”, aiming to “provide evidence-based strategies to transform the potential of the China-PLP partnership into a concrete reality, creating a new model of technological cooperation for the Global South”, says a statement from UCM.</description><pubDate>2025-12-18 00:53:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Australia | Twelve killed in attack during Jewish festival</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/15/australia-doze-mortos-em-ataque-durante-festa-judaica/</link><description>At least twelve people died and many injured were transported to Sydney hospitals yesterday, after a shooting attack on the Australian beach of Bondi, while a Jewish celebration was taking place. “There are two people in police custody on Bondi beach”, reported the New South Wales State Police on its X account, which asks “the public to avoid the area”.
Citing police sources, the AFP news agency reports that the attack caused ten deaths. The New South Wales ambulance service confirmed to ABC television that at least 16 people were transported to six hospital centers in the region.
Several witnesses report that it was a shooting attack carried out by an as yet undetermined number of armed people, but the authorities have not confirmed this information either. A British tourist told French news agency AFP that he saw “two gunmen dressed in black and armed with semi-automatic rifles”.
Australian Prime Minister Anthony Albanese has already issued a statement lamenting the “shocking and distressing scenes” coming from Bondi and confirmed the existence of injuries.
Part of the beach was the scene of a celebration of the Jewish festival of Hanukkah, which began yesterday and, although Australian authorities have not yet made any connection with the incident, the President of Israel, Isaac Herzog, denounced what he classified as a “vile terrorist attack against the Jews who were lighting the first candles” of the religious festival.
"Our heart is with them. The heart of the entire nation of Israel beats strong at this precise moment, as we pray for the recovery of the injured, we pray for them and we pray for those who lost their lives," he said in an official statement.</description><pubDate>2025-12-15 02:14:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Crime | Government does not release data on suicides and attempts</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/15/crime-governo-nao-divulga-dados-sobre-suicidios-e-tentativas/</link><description>After the Health Services, the Security department also stopped publishing data on suicides and attempts, after ten years of publication. The absence was noted in the release of crime data for the months of January to September this year, which show the increase in sexual abuse of minors to almost double
 
The Government stopped publishing data on suicide cases in Macau, as well as attempts. The absence of these numbers was noted by the newspaper Cheng Pou when it released crime data for the months of January and September this year on Friday.
The publication even questions whether “the data on suicide has become ‘the secret that cannot be said’ of the authorities, committed to building a happy Macau”, remembering that this data began to be released in 2015. Highlight is the fact that the Health Services also stopped publishing the statistics, something that was done every three months. In the case of the Security Secretariat, the data was monthly and was broken down by sex, age group and methods used.
The lack of numbers comes after Macau broke records in terms of suicide cases in 2024, registering 90 deaths, 2.27 percent more than in 2023. Compared to 2022, the increase was 12.5 percent. Of the 90 cases, 48 ​​concerned male victims and 42 female victims, aged between 12 and 76 years. The most recent data, for the first half of this year, reveals 41 deaths by suicide and 101 attempts.
In the release of crime statistics, on Friday, only one case of death by suicide appears in relation to an episode of homicide between brothers, which occurred in August this year, in the north zone. Here, the older brother jumped from the balcony, being suspected of having killed his younger brother due to financial disputes.
Break in crime
Looking at the crime panorama in general terms, there is a drop of 7.1 percent in the months under analysis, compared to the same period last year. The territory's authorities highlighted the sharp drop in computer crimes. The Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, said that the drop is due to the “decreasing trend” of “crimes that attract more attention from society”, including serious violent crime, theft, robbery, fraud and computer crimes.
In the first nine months of the year, 187 violent crimes were recorded, which represents a drop of 11 percent compared to the same period in 2024 (210). Thefts, robberies and frauds fell by 7.7, 5.9 and 23.6 percent, respectively. Computer crime, which recorded 770 cases in the first nine months of 2024, showed a decline of 52.1 percent in the period under analysis, with 369 cases.
The decline in cases of fraud using telecommunications, cyber fraud and computer fraud, said Chan Tsz King, “reflects the effectiveness of the prevention and combat work carried out by the police, and the significant increase in public awareness about fraud prevention”, he said.
The Government also highlighted that crime related to illicit gambling increased by 985 percent between January and September this year, with 394 more cases compared to the same period in 2024. The increase is due to the entry into force, in October last year, of the law to combat illicit gambling crimes, which introduced “the new crime of ‘exploitation of illicit exchange for gambling’ and expanded the scope of coverage of some crimes related to illicit gambling”.
For the same reason, said the secretary, gambling-related crimes soared in the first three quarters of 2025 – 1,737 cases, 70.1 percent more than in the same period last year. In the past, the official said, fraud committed by people illegally exchanging money outside casinos “could not be identified as related to gambling”. “However, with the criminalization of ‘illegal money exchange’ and the improvement of legal provisions”, these cases “are now included in gambling crime statistics, thus increasing the number of crimes”, he indicated.
More abuse of minors
Chan Tsz King, who took office in October and presented the crime report for the first time on Friday, also referred to a 6.1 percent increase in crimes against the person, with child sexual abuse increasing by 86.7 percent, from 15 cases in the first nine months of 2024 to 28 cases in the same period this year.
The secretary explained that these are essentially “voluntary sexual acts between people of the same age”, with “transmission of photographs and pornographic images”, without forgetting cases of “less serious sexual harassment”.
“Cases involving people with family relationships were also identified, which deserves the attention of society”, said Chan Tsz King, who released data on awareness-raising actions on this problem: more than 70 activities carried out by the police, which saw the participation of more than 12,000 people, including students, guardians and teaching staff.
Drug trafficking and sale and drug consumption, in turn, registered an increase of 37.1 percent, with 13 more cases, and 72.7 percent, eight more cases, respectively. According to the secretary's presentation, the 48 cases registered in the three quarters and the respective increase are due to “the discovery of several cases of cross-border drug trafficking through the reinforcement of internal and external police cooperation”, highlighting a case that occurred in September, when 31 kilos of cannabis flower worth 31.77 million patacas were seized. Chan Tsz King said that this was “the biggest case of cannabis smuggling seized in the history of Macau”.
Between walls
In the case of the crime of rape, there was a decline in the number of rape crimes, to a total of 24 cases, 40 percent less than in the same period of the previous year.
The Secretary for Security added that “more than 70 percent of the victims were not residents of Macau”, and “the majority of these crimes occurred in hotel rooms”, while “a number of these involved pecuniary conflicts between the victims and the suspects, and it is not possible to rule out the hypothesis that some of the cases occurred in the context of a sexual transaction”.
In this context, the secretary clarified that the police authorities have been “in close communication with the hotel sector”, and “police devices and inspections in peripheral areas of hotels and casinos” have been reinforced. Between January and September, more than 160 police actions were carried out to combat prostitution, with 192 people suspected of engaging in prostitution activity being intercepted.
Furthermore, during the period in question, 17 cases of pimping or exploitation of prostitution were resolved, with the arrest of 26 suspects.
Silence as always
Questioned by Lusa during the press conference about the first case to be investigated in Macau within the scope of national security, the secretary made no comments. “The case (…) is being handled by judicial entities and, due to secrecy, it would not be appropriate for the Secretary of Security to comment”, added Chan Tsz King, who was a Public Prosecutor when former deputy Au Kam San was detained.
At the end of July, the territory's police announced the arrest of Au Kam San, the first under the state security defense law, which came into force in 2009, with the scope being expanded 14 years later. The accusation is not yet known and there is no information about who will defend the former deputy. With Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-12-15 01:25:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Deputies warn of lack of trust and inequalities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/19/economia-deputados-alertam-para-falta-de-confianca-e-desigualdades/</link><description>Despite economic growth throughout this year, Chan Lai Kei and Leong Sun Iok alerted the Government to the problems in community neighborhoods and the need to distribute financial resources more equitably
Deputy Chan Lai Kei called on the Government to focus on promoting economic optimism and consumption, considering that in several neighborhoods in Macau the economic situation is worrying, despite macroeconomic growth. The matter was brought to the Legislative Assembly yesterday, an intervention before the agenda in the Plenary.
According to the deputy linked to the Fujian community, the economy is showing a “stable recovery”. Between January and September “the initial value of GDP grew 4.2 percent compared to the same period last year”. It also indicated that the unemployment rate was 2.3 percent between August and October.
However, Chan warned that “positive macroeconomic data have not completely eliminated negative indicators”, especially with regard to the lives of the population.
Citing a “recent study”, the legislator indicated that there is a weak desire to consume, because “residents’ confidence in increasing income and their satisfaction with their financial situation are still between a low and medium level”.
Chan Lai Kei explained that greater consumption abroad contributes to this wave of pessimism, but also the various closures of small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs): “In view of the stress of consumption abroad, the business environment of SMEs in areas linked to the lives of the population (such as NAPE, Iao Hon and Fai Chi Kei) continues to worsen and the risk of closure remains”, he warned. “These companies generally face the critical challenge of unstable customer sources, high costs and cross-border consumption”, he stressed.
Given the scenario outlined, the deputy asked the Executive to create a consumption incentive mechanism similar to discount vouchers, but with a permanent nature, while the “transformation phase of Macau's economic model” lasts, which “reinforces confidence in business”.
Improve distribution
Deputy Leong Sun Iok also addressed the situation of the economy and pointed out the need to better distribute resources from gambling, the main industry in the territory.
The legislator linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau praised the gaming concessionaires for the greater role they have taken in terms of investment for “urban development, tourism promotion and social security”, especially since 2023.
However, he regretted that resources are being channeled unequally: "It appears that, currently, both the revenues from the game and the gaming concessionaire companies themselves have invested a lot of resources in social development. But, in general, these resources are dispersed and lack a system and interconnection, therefore, they are unable to achieve maximum social benefit", he pointed out.
Leong thus advocated that a greater proportion of the revenue collected by the Administration from gambling be channeled to the Social Security Fund, to pay pensions for the elderly.
The deputy also called for the creation of a fund with money from concessionaires to develop the Macao SAR and to ensure that they “better” fulfill the obligations of the gaming law, such as “worker guarantees”, “support for people with disabilities or those rehabilitated”, support for SMEs and “educational, scientific research, environmental protection, cultural and sporting activities and activities of public interest”.
Leong Sun Iok also asked for a new portal with public information on concessionaires' expenses with non-gambling activities covered by the concessions' obligations and ended the intervention with a request for caution addressed to the Executive. “Society’s resources do not come easily and are the result of the joint efforts of the Government, companies, the various social sectors and the population in general”, he indicated. "The situation is not always good. I hope the Government makes good use of the resources arising from the social responsibilities of gaming companies, to improve the lives of the population", he highlighted.
Minimum Wage | Approved increase of one pataca per hour
The increase of one pataca per hour in the minimum wage, from 34 to 35 patacas, was approved yesterday in the Legislative Assembly. With the changes, starting next year, in weekly terms, the salary will go from 1,632 patacas to 1,680 patacas.
When the monthly calculations are made, the salary increases from 7,072 patacas to 7,280 patacas, an increase of 2.9 percent that will cover 4.4 percent of Macao SAR workers. Domestic workers are excluded, although the approval of the hiring quota, in the case of non-residents, is normally associated with the requirement of a salary between 3,500 and 4,000 patacas.
Budget 2026 | Deputies approve the specialty
The Legislative Assembly yesterday approved the budget for next year, which foresees an increase in gaming revenue of 3.5 percent, to 236 billion patacas. The document, which reflects the Executive's economic choices, estimates revenues of 118.8 billion patacas, while expenses are estimated at 113.5 billion patacas.
Based on these perspectives, the final balance of the regular budget should be positive at 5.3 billion patacas. However, there is a possibility that the scenario is actually better, given that the Government tends to make default estimates with regard to revenue and expenses. The budget also once again provides for exemption from paying professional tax, up to 30 percent of the annual amount, limited to 144 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>EU | New target to reduce 90% of pollutants by 2040</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/11/ue-nova-meta-para-reduzir-90-de-poluentes-ate-2040/</link><description>MEPs and countries from the European Union (EU) yesterday reached an agreement on a target to reduce 90 percent of polluting emissions by 2040, with a view to carbon neutrality in 2050, although new forms of flexibility are foreseen.
“The co-legislators agreed on a target of a 90 percent reduction in greenhouse gas emissions by 2040, compared to 1990 levels, with the aim of achieving climate neutrality in the EU by 2050”, is announced in a statement released in Brussels.
After several hours of negotiations, the European Parliament and the Council thus reached, this morning, a provisional political agreement (which will have to be confirmed by both) on an amendment to the EU Climate Law, establishing a new intermediate and binding target for 2040, that of reducing net greenhouse gas emissions by 90 percent compared to 1990 levels.
Even so, MEPs and countries agreed to introduce new forms of flexibility to meet the 2040 target, “believing that the green transition and European competitiveness must advance hand in hand”, according to the note.
Under review
Specifically, from 2036 onwards, up to five percentage points of emissions reductions (two more than the Commission's initial proposal) could come from high-quality international carbon credits, compatible with the Paris Agreement. In the case of Portugal, for example, this means that sustainable projects in countries such as Portuguese-speaking African Countries (PALOP) can count towards the Portuguese target.
“Thanks to Parliament's insistence, additional safeguards were integrated, including the prohibition of financing projects in partner countries that contradict the Union's strategic interests”, highlights the European assembly. It is up to the European Commission to analyze different options for the role of international credits in future EU climate legislation to reach the 2040 target.
Furthermore, the community executive will assess progress every two years, taking into account the most recent scientific data, technological advances and the EU's international competitiveness.
"The review will analyze the situation of net removals at European level, comparing it with what is necessary to meet the 2040 target, as well as possible implementation difficulties and the potential to strengthen the EU's industrial competitiveness. Trends in energy prices and their impacts on companies and families will also be considered", according to the European Parliament.
This will allow Brussels to modify the 2040 target or take additional measures to strengthen the support framework, for example to protect the EU's competitiveness, prosperity and social stability.
Parliament will now vote on the informal agreement and the Council will also have to approve it, with the text coming into force 20 days after its publication in the Official Journal of the European Union. The European Climate Law makes each country's effort to reduce its polluting emissions legally binding.</description><pubDate>2025-12-11 04:37:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Europe | Merz considers aspects of Trump's geostrategy unacceptable</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/10/europa-merz-considera-inaceitaveis-pontos-da-geostrategia-de-trump/</link><description>The head of the German federal government, Friedrich Merz, declared yesterday that there are certain unacceptable points in the document on Defense and geostrategy of the North American Administration led by Donald Trump, from a European perspective. “I don’t see any need for Americans to want to save Democracy in Europe,” he said, on a visit to Rhineland-Palatinate (a southwestern state), which is home to several United States of America (USA) military bases.
In a strategic document on US national security, released last week, there is a warning about the danger of “civilizational extinction” in Europe if “current trends” continue.
Trump, in the preface, summarizes: “we put America first in everything we do”. “It is more than plausible that, in a few decades at most, the members of NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Organization) will become predominantly non-European”, he wrote, adding that “it is legitimate to question whether they will perceive their place in the World or their alliance with the USA, in the same way as those who signed the organization's charter”.
The White House regrets European decisions that “undermine political freedom and sovereignty, the migration policies that are transforming the continent [Europe] and creating tensions, as well as the censorship of freedom of expression and the repression of political opposition, the drop in birth rates and the loss of national identities (…)”.
Washington expresses the desire for “Europe to remain European, regain its civilizational self-confidence and abandon its fruitless obsession with regulatory suffocation.”</description><pubDate>2025-12-10 03:31:29</pubDate></item><item><title>East Timor | Memories of a man's life reflect the resistance of a people</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/09/timor-leste-recordacoes-da-vida-de-um-homem-reflectem-a-resistencia-de-um-povo/</link><description>The book “Return to Uaidora, the childhood and youth of Domingos Gusmão” recounts the Timorese's testimonies about the years of Timor-Leste's resistance to the Indonesian occupation. The testimony was written in Macau by former resident and university professor Duarte Trigueiros. 50 years after the occupation, the author reminded HM of the work launched in 2022
This year has been marked by the celebrations of the 50th anniversary of the independence of many former Portuguese colonies. Timor-Leste went to one of these territories. However, shortly after the unilateral proclamation of independence, on November 28, 1975, there was a period of confrontation that culminated in the Indonesian occupation, on December 7 of the same year.
This Sunday marks 50 years since the invasion that marked the fate of the young country. In connection with this date, the book “Regresso a Uaidora, the childhood and youth of Domingos Gusmão” was released in 2022, which reveals the story of the Timorese, who was a student in Macau and a student of the author Duarte Trigueiros, former economist and professor at the University of São José. HM spoke to the author about the reflection of the pain and struggle for self-determination of a people that can be seen in the life of a man and his family.
"When I was teaching in Macau, I collected the testimony of this Timorese from Baucau. Domingos Gusmão, knowing that he had taught at the National University of Timor-Leste for several years, told me how he and his family lived through all these terrible events."
This is how the book was born, with Trigueiros merely reporting the testimony, later corrected in partnership with Domingos Gusmão. The work only has an online version, but at the time of launch it had the support of Fundação Oriente in printing some copies. Matebian, East Timor
Duarte Trigueiros, who lived in Macau for several years, came into contact with Domingos Gusmão during the Festa da Lusofonia, in 2015. "I went to the Timor-Leste tent and he told me that he had interesting things to tell me, but that he couldn't speak Portuguese well, and that he would like to leave his testimony in writing. At one point I proposed asking him questions from his childhood, about life in the village, and thus the book was born, with nine chapters.”
The beginning of the work describes, “through the eyes of a child, the day-to-day life of farmers in the Baucau mountains in Timor-Leste, the determination in which they reacted to the invasion of their country in 1975 and the brutal repression that followed”. "The book follows not only his life, but also his family and the few who remained. In the end, there was practically no one left", describes Duarte Trigueiros.
According to the work, Domingos Gusmão was born on November 1, 1969 in the village of Uaidora, belonging to the municipality of Baucau, the son of Julião, a farmer, and Juliana, a maid. "But only the place where I was born is correct. The date of birth is nothing more than a conjecture and the names that appear on the certificate as being my parents, Julião and Juliana, are also not those of my real father and mother, but of relatives who adopted me when I was an orphan. In fact, I am the son of Martinho Gusmão, whose code name was 'Maunoco' and he was the chief of the Uaidora village until his death in 1983; and my mother was Ricardina, Martinho Gusmão’s second wife, the one who gave him offspring.” This is how Domingos’ story begins.
Going to Baucau
The work recounts very difficult years, with thousands of Timorese fleeing into the bush to escape the Indonesians, organizing armed struggle. One of the chapters, highlights Duarte Trigueiros, reports how Domingos and his family "were deported and left without any type of support, without doctors or food. "A huge number of people died at that time, until the beginning of the 80s, and they [Dominicos Gusmão's family], already in the place where they were cultivating the land, began to have fruits from the land, and send children to school. This boy [Domingos Gusmão], during that time, started preparing to go to Baucau to study, something that was not easy, as it was necessary to find a place, and there were many children.” Domingos and Xanana Gusmão
It was there that the family decided to leave the village and go to Baucau, finding jobs “at the service of the troops, judges, nurses and doctors”, which gave them their first contacts with the Timorese resistance.
"He [Domingos Gusmão] began organizing what they called a clandestine front with his colleagues. The book reports all these adventures that clearly reveal how the resistance worked. This boy then felt the desire to continue his studies and applied to a Catholic seminary", recalled Duarte Trigueiros.
The connection to the Catholic religion was not an accident. "The purpose was to go abroad, because the only thing that Indonesians really respected was the Catholic Church, they didn't respect anything else. And he left, spent a number of years training. He was in the Philippines, where he also participated in resistance activities, and returned as a priest, in 2012."
Writing this book was important to Domingos Gusmão because he “wanted to mention the names of the [Timorese] commanders of the first phase, when the Indonesian troops entered through Baucau, towards the interior, and there were a large number of resistance commanders who resisted, almost without weapons, and were killed”. “When he spoke to me about this subject, he was very insistent, he told me ‘Write down the name of that commander.’ Everything so that the names would not be forgotten”, he recalled.
"What he told me is that nowadays, in Timor-Leste, people are compensating the members of the resistance who are alive, but there are many dead who gave their lives for this and are being forgotten. But this book also talks about everything on a personal level, about what happened to the uncle, how the father died at that stage, thrown to the ground, with a gun butt, with kicks, because he refused to accept an order and they threw him to the ground. He was the head of the village and had to accept the order [of the Indonesians], but he refused”, highlighted Duarte Trigueiros.
For the author, the work tells “a truer version” of what the Indonesian occupation was, and very specifically about the experiences of the town of Uaidora and the interior of the country.
In the book, you can read Domingos' testimony about this phase of resistance in Baucau, starting in 1986. “I owe my enlistment in the resistance to the clandestine fronts and also to my colleague Domingos de Oliveira. (…) A few weeks later, on the 16th or 17th of September 1991, the centenary of the Dili cathedral was celebrated and young people were invited to participate. 14 left from Baucau. Buses full of teenagers and I was one of them. The next day, during the return trip, FRETILIN flags appeared and we all sang hymns to independence.
As we passed through Manatuto, the troops ordered us to stop, but then they told us to continue; and at the entrance to Baucau, before the airport, the road was blocked and we were surrounded by a strong military device. There were only three assault cars!”
Gusmão continues his account of this tense moment. "After having cornered us like this, the troops, with the assault vehicles on the right side, occupied the left side. The 14 trucks were lined up with the military device, which had its weapons in position, ready to fire. They were like a very long firing squad. There we stayed, with all those weapons pointed at us, in silence while time passed and nothing happened."
Support from Portuguese
Duarte Trigueiros and Domingos Gusmão kept in touch, but a stroke took away the Timorese's quality of life. "He hardly responds to my emails. Maybe he has a different outlook on life", confesses the author.
Another perspective that the work gives, according to Trigueiros, is the position of the Portuguese authorities during the years of Indonesian occupation, dispelling the idea that there was abandonment after independence. "I simply show what Domingos told me, and he told me that many of the resistance commanders had been Portuguese soldiers and that, therefore, they knew how to use weapons. He also told me that they were extremely patriotic. There is a report that in the 90s they tried to get a satellite phone from Portugal to give to the resistance, and there are references to the support of the Portuguese Embassy in Manila. I think we looked good in the photograph", he concludes.
Duarte Trigueiros taught in Timor between 2004 and 2009, where he found higher education very weak. "The students practically didn't know Portuguese and we had to teach in Portuguese. That alone was a huge effort. In general, the students were weak, they were very poorly prepared. The [educational] preparation of the Indonesians had been of a low level, as there was discrimination against students for being Timorese. The book describes this, how only good students had the right to move up, so to speak, and that didn't even mean going to university."
Even so, Duarte Trigueiros highlights the training of “a good number of people, engineers, law graduates, economists”. “It took a lot of work and that was the great support that Portugal was able to give”, he added.
Today, the former economist says that the Timorese look at the Portuguese with immense gratitude. "It's amazing, because when we go on a street with an Australian, they despise the Australian and don't talk to him, but with the Portuguese they shower him with all kinds of affection. This happens a lot in Timor-Leste", he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 02:47:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Weddings | Si Ka Lon wants Macau to be like Las Vegas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/casamentos-si-ka-lon-quer-que-macau-seja-como-las-vegas/</link><description>Representative Si Ka Lon argues that Macau should invest in the wedding industry for tourism purposes, similar to what happens in Las Vegas.
In an oral question presented to the Government, which will be answered in the Chamber next week, the deputy argues that “‘destination weddings’ is one of the directions for the development of the tourism industry”. Si Ka Lon asks whether local authorities will “take as a reference the successful experiences of Las Vegas or Hong Kong, allowing marriage registration in Macau, regardless of the place of residence or nationality of the bride and groom, with a view to exploring the 'wedding tourism' market”.
In the deputy's view, the Executive can “take advantage of Macau's advantages and singularities”, investing in the promotion of “plans for outdoor wedding ceremonies, in order to increase the competitiveness of Macau's wedding tourism products and create a new business card for the city”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:35:38</pubDate></item><item><title>ONE | Southern section of the campus in Hengqin will cost 2.38 billion</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/um-seccao-sul-do-campus-em-hengqin-vai-custar-238-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The companies Companhia de Construção e Investimento Predial Ming Shun and Jian Tai Construction, from the Huafa group, were chosen to carry out the work, which is scheduled for completion by November 2028.
Construction work on the Southern Section of the new University of Macau Campus in Hengqin will cost 2.38 billion patacas (2.086 billion renminbis), according to the award contract. The information was shared by the company within the local educational institution, Guangdong Hengqin UM Higher Education Development, through the portal of the Directorate of Public Supervision and Asset Management Services (DSSGAP).
The work was awarded through a public tender and the work will be carried out by the consortium made up of the local company Companhia de Construção e Investimento Predial Ming Shun and Jian Tai Construction, which is based in Zhuhai and is part of the state-owned Huafa group.
Since the campus is located in Mainland China, the competition was held in accordance with Chinese legislation and proposals were submitted in renminbis. The consortium made up of Ming Shun and Jian Tai presented the third cheapest proposal of the seven participants in the competition.
The award was publicly announced yesterday, despite having been decided on November 11th, establishing that construction of all buildings must begin by tomorrow. Furthermore, the competition requires that some lots and buildings must be ready by February 2028, while the rest are scheduled for completion by November 2028.
Participated contest
The public tender for the award of the work only included the participation of state-owned companies from Mainland China, some of the largest construction companies in the world. One of the participants was the China Railway Construction Corporation, which presented a proposal worth 2.71 billion patacas (2.38 billion renminbis), the most expensive of all.
The same group was involved twice, through the subsidiary China Railway First, and in this case presented the cheapest proposal worth 1.70 billion patacas (1.48 billion renminbi).
The tender also included a consortium made up of China Overseas Construction Limited and China State Construction Engineering Corporation, which submitted a proposal of 2.61 billion patacas (2.29 billion renminbi).
Zhejiang No. 1 Construction Investment submitted a proposal of 2.53 billion patacas (2.22 billion renminbi), Jiangsu Huajian 2.34 billion patacas (2.05 billion renminbi), while the Beijing Urban Construction Group asked for 2.00 million patacas (1.75 billion renminbi).</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:32:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Land | Coutinho calls for greater transparency</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/terrenos-coutinho-pede-maior-transparencia/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho believes that more transparency is needed in the dissemination of information about land controlled by the Macao SAR. The matter will be addressed in an oral questioning in the Legislative Assembly (AL), between the 6th and 7th of January.
In the interpellation, which was published yesterday on the AL portal, the deputy linked to the Macau Public Service Workers' Association defended greater dissemination of information from Government portals.
Furthermore, the deputy questions what the Executive's plans are to deal with the issue of outstanding land. In 2016, the then Chief Executive, Fernando Chui Sai, admitted that the Government had to allocate more than 88 thousand square meters in land that had been withdrawn from private ownership to be used for public purposes.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:30:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Light Rail | Deputy questions management and connection with buses</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/metro-ligeiro-deputada-questiona-gestao-e-conexao-com-autocarros/</link><description>Wong Kit Cheng questioned the Government about the integration of payment methods between the Light Rail and public buses. The deputy also wants to know when the public consultation on the development of the Light Rail network will be launched
The development of the Light Rail is the subject of yet another written question by Wong Kit Cheng. In the document, the deputy questions how the planning of this means of transport will be defined without forgetting the connection with the bus network, whose concession contracts expire at the end of 2026.
"It is important to provide a convenient user experience [to passengers]. Taking into account that the bus contracts expire at the end of next year, has the Government already started negotiations on the contracts with the two bus companies, in order to integrate a benefits system?", begins by asking the deputy.
The question arises within the scope of the promise made by the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, regarding the installation of new payment terminals at Light Rail stations that can be connected to buses, in order to allow different payment methods.
More specifically, Wong Kit Cheng would like new bus contracts to include the connection of payment methods taking into account the installation of new terminals.
For the deputy, “there is still a large margin for improvement” in the distribution of passengers between the two means of public transport, highlighting that there was a “significant growth” in passengers on the Light Rail, still falling short of “the more than 600 thousand passengers served daily by buses”.
Thus, “to achieve the objective of the Light Rail as the main means of transport, and buses as a complement”, Wong Kit Cheng considers that “the authorities need to optimize the passenger experience, especially with regard to resolving long-standing problems, such as Light Rail payment methods, greater coordination of transfers and the resolution of faults, in addition to improving the accessibility of lines and stations”.
Ongoing assessments
Still regarding the future of the Light Rail, Wong Kit Cheng asked for a “status” of the mid-term assessment that the Executive is carrying out in relation to the execution of the concession contract. “What is the status of these evaluation works?
Are there already preliminary results or optimization recommendations, particularly with regard to improving the quality and stability of the service?”, he asked.
The deputy also took up another promise made in the last debate on the Lines of Government Action by secretary Raymond Tam, regarding the holding of a public consultation on the study of the Light Rail development strategy. “How will this public consultation be organized”, he asks.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:24:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Nam Van | Temporary Landfill will cost almost 12 million patacas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/nam-van-aterro-provisorio-ira-custar-quase-12-milhoes-de-patacas/</link><description>The work is part of a plan presented in August to provisionally use lots A3, A4 and A9 at Lake Nam Van. The plan includes the construction of a new parking zone in the city center
The construction work on the embankment and temporary foundations of lot A4 at Nam Van Lake will cost 11.82 million patacas. The work was awarded to the Tak Fat Kin Ip Construction and Engineering Works Company and aims to allow the provisional use of the land, according to the Public Works Services Directorate (DSOP) portal.
The work was awarded through a consultation procedure by DSOP with some construction companies, which resulted in the presentation of six proposals, with prices varying between 10.68 million patacas and 14.73 million patacas. All of them committed to completing the works within 180 days.
According to DSOP, "currently, lot A4 is an abandoned construction site", despite having an area of ​​1,500 square meters" and being located in a central area of ​​the city. The work required of Tak Fat Kin Ip aims to create the conditions for "the next construction of temporary public spaces", as well as "completely resolve any emerging risks of accumulation of stagnant water" in the existing buildings on lot A4.
Take advantage
The use of the Nam Van Lake plot is part of a broader Government plan, presented in August this year, when the objective was set to “use, in the short term, the three plots of land A3, A4 and A9 at Nam Van Lake for the creation of temporary public spaces”.
The Executive intends to “meet residents' reasonable expectations regarding the optimal use of land and, at the same time, improve the urban landscape of the city center, enriching the experience of Macau as a tourist city”. This option takes into account that the land is located close to some of the city's most popular tourist attractions. Furthermore, the land is located in a commercial area, which means that during holidays the traffic is “very intense” and that during rush hours “crowd control measures are implemented”.
In August, DSOP also committed to carrying out “temporary works that include the construction of a temporary walkway along the lake on lot A9, which will connect with the arcades of the surrounding buildings”. This connection will allow you to walk directly between the Lake View Mansion and Nam Van Peninsula buildings along the lakeshore, without the current need to bypass lot A9.
In lots A3 and A4, between the Hotel Grand Emperor buildings and the FIT Center of Macau, a temporary parking lot will be built.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:33:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Leong Pou OU wants more protection for self-employed workers</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/leong-pou-u-quer-mais-proteccao-para-trabalhadores-independentes/</link><description>Deputy Leong Pou U believes that the Government should create new legislation to guarantee more protection for self-employed workers. The matter appears in an oral interpellation that was released yesterday by the legislator linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau.
According to the deputy, the most recent developments in the productive forces will give rise to “new forms of production relations and labor relations”. However, Leong Pou U warns that the new relationships will be more “flexible” and unstable and that they “differ significantly from traditional models that feature fixed working hours, fixed workplaces and stable employment relationships”.
Despite the new models, the deputy argues that it is necessary to protect “workers' rights in forms of employment and create a legal environment favorable to the development of new quality productive forces”. “Will the authorities carry out a systematic review and amendment of labor laws and regulations in response to the emergence of new forms of employment, thus reinforcing the safeguard of workers’ rights in these new regimes?”, he asks.
Gray areas
Regarding new forms of work, Leong Pou U also indicates that they often take place outside the traditional licenses granted by bodies such as the Institute for Municipal Affairs. Therefore, Leong asks how the authorities will adapt to the change.
The deputy exemplified the new paradigm with the fine imposed on a young man who charged money for photographs near the Ruins of São Paulo. “Recently, a resident who provided paid photography services near the Ruins of São Paulo was fined by the IAM for alleged violations of the street vendor regulations”, he indicates.
“I would like to ask the secretary how the rights and interests of freelancers or people with multiple jobs will be strengthened in the future in order to promote high-quality employment for residents, especially young people,” he asked.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:30:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Aviation | Deputy asks if there will be support for new companies</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/aviacao-deputado-pergunta-se-havera-apoios-para-novas-companhias/</link><description>In February, the new aviation law comes into force, ending Air Macau's monopoly. Lam Lon Wai wants to know how the Government will chart the future development of the civil aviation industry
Deputy Lam Lon Wai asked the Government if there are plans to support airlines to establish themselves in Macau. The matter will be addressed in the Legislative Assembly, in an oral intervention, which was announced yesterday by the legislator.
In the text, Lam Lon Wai begins by regretting that “for many years, Macau only had one local airline” which meant that “the overall size of the market continues to be relatively small”.
The legislator linked to the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau (FAOM) points out that the new law that ends Air Macau's monopoly is causing the aviation market to enter “a new phase of development”.
In this sense, the deputy wants to know how the authorities will “proactively take advantage of new opportunities” to “attract more financially solid aviation companies to establish companies or local branches in Macau”. As part of the strategy, Lam Lon Wai asked whether the Government will launch measures such as “air rights exploitation agreements”, “expansion of airport facilities” or “staff training initiatives” to “boost the Macau aviation market into a new phase of diversification and regional cooperation”.
More companies
The new aviation law will come into force in February next year, and the deputy recalls that “one of the main objectives of the legislation is to allow the creation of local airlines, thus promoting a more autonomous civil aviation system for Macau”.
Lam Lon Wai therefore wants to know whether the entry into force of the new legislation will be seen as an opportunity to reconsider aviation agreements with different jurisdictions. “Will the authorities review all air service agreements signed with various countries and formulate incentive policies to attract foreign carriers, thus reinforcing Macau’s advantages as a transit hub?”, he asked.
The deputy also indicates that Macau can be a hub for regional aviation. “If efforts in the future include greater regional collaboration between airports with the flexible use of air rights, Macau has the potential to evolve and transform into a center for air and logistics connections in the Greater Bay Area”, he pointed out.
However, to implement this strategy, the deputy indicated that it is important that the Hengqin Cargo Terminal for Macau International Airport comes into operation in 2027.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:29:06</pubDate></item><item><title>It’s good for Ukraine</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/29/pra-ucrania-e-que-e-bom/</link><description>I do not discuss the past or the personality of Vladimir Putin. I do not discuss Russia's expansionist policy. I discuss the politics of Portugal and the European Union. In Portugal there are around four million citizens who live on the edge of poverty. There are thousands of Portuguese people with poor pensions. There are elderly people living alone without any medical or social support. There are homes that are human rubbish bins. There are not enough public daycare centers for Portuguese children. There are hundreds of slums. There are hundreds of homeless people, cold and hungry, all over the cities.
There are buildings owned by the Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Lisboa, with more than five floors, completely abandoned and in ruins in a country where there is no social housing for young people, the elderly, the disabled and families who survive by having to choose whether to purchase food or medicine. There are young people who, at the age of 40, still live in their parents' homes because they are unable to rent or buy a house, much less live in a civil union with a partner and have children.
There is a Ministry of Defense that announces the future purchase of war material and aircraft worth billions of euros when public hospitals have closed emergency rooms and future mothers are giving birth at home, in ambulances, in private cars or on the street. There are blind and disabled people who cannot use certain Lisbon Metro stations because there are no elevators or escalators. There are prison establishments where inmates are provided with a type of food that even dogs reject.
There are students who finish secondary school and go to work in a restaurant or in the construction industry because their parents do not have money to pay for tuition fees and university supplies. There are beggars asking for money every day in every city in the country. There are more than 100,000 poor people who have been suspended from a miserable monthly income subsidy of 200 euros.
There are poor people stealing chocolate or bread from a supermarket and are immediately taken to a police station. There are no safe institutes that care for women who are victims of domestic violence. There are political parties that advocate the expulsion from Portugal of immigrants who work and contribute to Social Security. There is an annual increase for retirees of three to five euros.
Politics in Portugal, undeniably, despises the poor, with the argument that the State Budget is not enough for more. And, after all, what happens? That the Portuguese Government has sent billions of euros to Ukraine. For a country, whose
Parliament has a majority of neo-Nazis. A country that has corrupt ministers and head of presidential cabinet at the highest level.
A country where President Zelensky has fired minister after minister for embezzling millions of dollars from the European Union and obviously from Portugal. A country where the people are divided between general elections, even in times of war. A country that six years ago was “exporting” to Portugal one of the largest mafias dedicated to human trafficking, serious robberies of value vans, control of prostitution of Ukrainian women disguised as domestic workers, drug sales and money laundering.
Portugal continues to send millions of euros to Ukraine, when its people live in poverty and misery.
A policy of this kind is not acceptable, where people are already afraid to speak out against decisions related to financial support for Ukraine, because they could run the risk of being accused of supporting the communist Putin. It is not acceptable that the policy of North American interests, led by its president Donald Trump, which supports the most diverse neo-Nazi organizations, including Ukrainian ones, leads Portugal to send millions of euros, who knows what destination, and keeping thousands of its children in poverty.
It is urgent and minimally reasonable that the Portuguese government immediately cease sending millions of euros and war material or aircraft to Ukraine, when this money is so desperately needed by the poor residents of the seaside country. Human solidarity is not this. The Ukrainian people have benefited nothing from the millions from Portugal and other European countries. We have reached the point where military material is being sent to Ukraine and many Ukrainian government officials are selling that same material to Afghanistan and other countries like that. Readers must take a position, within each individual's possibilities, to make the Portuguese authorities aware that the situation described here cannot continue. For the good of the Nation.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 02:01:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Policies for attracting investment, valuation services and inspection of the Science and Technology Park</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/20/politicas-de-captacao-de-investimento-servicos-de-valorizacao-e-fiscalizacao-do-parque-de-ciencias-e-tecnologias/</link><description>The Science and Technology Park is linked to the future of Macau
Deputies Lei Wun Kong and Wong Ka Lon
Macau's economy is overly dependent on gaming revenue, but with the emergence of artificial intelligence in the industry, young people are no longer enthusiastic about offline gaming. With the passage of time, changes in the external situation and other factors, gaming revenues may be unstable and affected. Therefore, the Science and Technology Park project is the key to adequate diversification of the economy.
Question: Create and improve policies for attracting investment and post-investment services and supervision of the said Park
Nowadays, businesspeople are more conservative. To efficiently promote the Park project in question, the Government must take the initiative to attract investments and provide enhancement services. Despite the efforts made by public services, namely the Secretariat for Economy and Finance and its subordinate services, it is necessary to create and improve policies for attracting investment, post-investment services and supervision of the aforementioned Park.
Model: Taking the experiences of model cities in Mainland China as a reference
In recent years, model cities in Mainland China have defined five models for attracting investment. The first is through capital, “funds + industries”, the government creates an industrial fund to promote the implementation of projects, such as the Suzhou biotechnology industry. The second is through a cluster “led by dominant industries”, that is, creating an industrial cluster around dominant companies, for example, in Shenzhen it is Huawei that drives the respective industries. The third is based on “demand-driven supply”, that is, exploring application scenarios to attract technology companies, for example, the company Hangzhou City Brain integrated Alibaba Cloud to develop the application of AI. The fourth is based on “intelligent data matching” to capture digital investments, that is, the creation of big-data to accurately define target companies, such as the “digital investment capture” system in Guangzhou. The fifth is based on “interregional cooperation”, that is, it transcends the delimitation of administrative regions, such as the Shenzhen-Shantou cooperation zone, led by Shenzhen.
Strategy: Develop differentiated policies according to the reality of Macau
Macau, as a micro-economy, in addition to the lack of human resources and land, does not have dominant companies, so it is difficult to create an industrial cluster. Therefore, we must maximize our unique advantages (such as the “one country, two systems” principle, free port, autonomous customs zone, simple tax regime, connection platform with Portuguese-speaking countries and the European legal system, and transform all of this into concrete and attractive points and services for attracting investment), and transform Macau into a platform for interconnection between scientific and technological companies from China and the PLP.
Therefore, we can take the following measures:
1) based on the performance agreement, promote industrial orientation through strategic social participation of the industrial fund, in order to achieve the leverage effect of capital with controlled risk;
2) promote cooperation in attracting inter-regional investment, clearly define the division of labor with Henqin and ensure investment effectiveness;
3) capture local and international talent to attract investments, granting qualified candidates non-permanent resident status;
4) create a large bank to attract investments, etc.
At this time, it is necessary for the Government to implement policies to attract investment through legal incentives aimed at businesspeople who want to enter the park. The investment capture model, operational management and preferential policies, among other key steps, must be clarified. The capture of high-level investments must be ensured and the management process detailed a posteriori, in order to highlight the change in the role of the Government, from manager to service provider, achieving the articulation of these measures with the 15th Five-Year Plan of the Country and the needs and advantages of Macau.
Guarantee: Improvement of value-added services and quantitative supervision
When attracting investments, star cities in Mainland China, in addition to providing value-added services to companies for investment, should facilitate the development of these companies, guiding them towards their continuous growth. Once the process of attracting investments is completed, the phase of monitoring the production value and investment intensity per acre of land follows, which will be used as a basis for determining the value of subsidies and benefits granted by the respective governments.
Although it is difficult for Macau to adopt the quantification model per acre of land, it can carry out an appropriate quantification, taking into account its own needs. For example, taking as quantitative indicators the intensity of employment, the size of investment and possible entry into the capital market. Thus, these values ​​determine the financial support that is granted, as well as tax benefits and other incentive measures. At the same time, as the area of ​​the scientific and technological park and human resources are limited, it is necessary to better define the proportion of each sector, but the blind search for a “large and complete” scope must be avoided. Furthermore, policies should be oriented towards Hengqin-Macao cooperation, cooperation inside and outside the park, and industry-academia-research purposes.
In short, the Government must create an improved system of value-added services and quantitative supervision for attracting investments, in order to achieve advances in several dimensions, namely in “industrial positioning, excellent complementary policies, deep synergy between Macau and Hengqin, the ecosphere of the investment capture process, and the management of business confidence”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-20 04:42:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Is erotic audio storytelling replacing video?</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/19/a-narrativa-erotica-em-audio-esta-a-substituir-o-video/</link><description>Eroticism is gaining a new voice — literally. While video dominated the mainstream sexual imagination for decades, today audio narrative sexual fantasy is experiencing a moment of great popularity: erotic podcasts, apps that tell sensual stories and audiobooks capable of provoking arousal. It is a form of eroticism that appeals to imagination, intimacy and personal experience in a way that visual pornography rarely does.
The audio format works in a radically different way than video. When we watch videos, we receive a ready-made image, a visual script that dictates what should excite us. They are bodies with specific characteristics, many of them with surgical alterations that follow fashions of what is supposed to be sensual or exciting. The audio, on the other hand, works as a suggestion: we are the ones who build the setting, the characters and the chemistry. The narrative comes into play as a kind of trigger — a trigger that allows the imagination to do what it does best: create our own erotic fantasy.
When we listen to an erotic audio story, our brains are not just processing external stimuli; they are actively collaborating with the narrative, filling spaces, generating unique images and sensations. This participation can heighten the erotic response in a way that is different from the more passive experience of watching a screen. These audio stories manage to center the experience on the listener, often placing them in the main role of the fantasy and creating a sense of connection and intimacy that is difficult to replicate on video.
The growing popularity of audio erotica appears to respond to emotional and sexual needs that many people feel are not addressed by traditional forms of pornography. With the narrative, the listener stops being just a consumer and becomes involved in a process of co-creation of the erotic. Apps like Quinn or Dipsea produce narrated stories, often focused on the listener's perspective — with voices, ambient sound and an engaging narrative — rather than explicit images.
It is not only the nature of eroticism that explains this growing popularity, but also the audience for whom these stories are created. Many of these apps and podcasts are designed by women and for women, or for queer people. Pornography, historically associated with the male gaze and desire (with some exceptions), tends to leave out other equally relevant imaginaries. Erotic audio narratives have explored precisely these territories traditionally considered more “feminine”: consent, emotion, vulnerability and female pleasure. Here, the focus on history and anticipation builds a form of eroticism that privileges connection — without ever giving up on excitement.
The success of these apps, podcasts and audio stories suggests that many people are looking for stories that include them and respect their rhythms and desires, especially those who have never recognized themselves in mainstream erotica. The focus on emotional connection, the simple fact that someone whispers sensual words directly into the headphones, creates an intimate and almost confidential experience. This emotional rarity — feeling heard, desired and imagined in the erotic universe — makes audio simultaneously exciting, liberating and safe.
The return to voice can, therefore, be more than a passing fad. It may be a reflection of how we want to experience eroticism today: not as distant spectators, but as active participants in our own erotic co-creation.</description><pubDate>2025-12-19 02:27:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Lessons from 2025 for the Decade</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/18/licoes-de-2025-para-a-decada-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the article published on December 11)
In the security sector, the world will face complex challenges. Terrorism could take on new forms, using digital technologies and artificial intelligence. Cybersecurity will become a priority, with digital attacks on critical systems posing significant risks. It is estimated that by 2030 the global costs of cyber attacks could exceed US$10 billion annually. On a military level, geopolitical tensions between the United States and China could intensify. The Middle East will continue to be a focus of instability. Between 2026 and 2030, social and cultural scenarios will assume a determining role in shaping the global future. International migration will continue to be one of the most striking phenomena, driven by armed conflicts, economic inequalities and climate change.
It is estimated that hundreds of millions of people may be in a situation of international or internal mobility, either in search of better living conditions or out of need for survival. Europe will face migratory pressures from Africa and the Middle East, with hundreds of thousands of people seeking refuge in countries such as Italy, Greece, Spain and Germany. This flow will require more robust integration policies, but it could also generate social and political tensions, fueling populist and nationalist discourses.
In the United States, immigration will continue to be a central issue, with restrictive policies causing social tensions and protests, but also with the need for labor in sectors such as agriculture, construction and services. In Latin America, internal migration will intensify due to extreme climatic phenomena, such as floods and droughts, forcing millions of people to move from rural areas to cities. In Africa, desertification and armed conflicts in the Sahel could displace more than 20 million people, creating large-scale humanitarian crises.
Urbanization will be another central phenomenon. By 2030, more than 65% of the world's population will live in urban areas, with megacities growing rapidly. Cities such as Lagos, Kinshasa, Mumbai, São Paulo and Jakarta could exceed 30 million inhabitants, facing challenges in infrastructure, housing, transport and sanitation. Accelerated urbanization will bring opportunities for economic and cultural dynamism, but also risks of inequality and social exclusion. Cities will need to invest in sustainable solutions, such as efficient public transport, affordable housing and waste management. The digitalization of cities, using smart technologies, can improve the quality of life, but will require inclusion policies to prevent vulnerable populations from being excluded.
Demographic transformations will be equally decisive. Population aging in Europe, Japan and South Korea will require health and long-term care policies, with an impact on pension systems and fiscal sustainability. It is estimated that, by 2030, more than 25% of Europe's population will be over 65 years old, creating productivity and financing challenges for social systems. In contrast, Africa and parts of Asia will have growing young populations, with millions of people entering the job market. This phenomenon could be an opportunity for economic dynamism, but also a risk of instability if sufficient jobs are not created. India, for example, will have more than 1.5 billion inhabitants in 2030, with a young population that could drive growth, but will require massive investments in education and training. China will face the challenge of an aging population, with more than 400 million people over the age of 60 in 2030, which could limit economic dynamism and increase pressure on healthcare and pension systems.
Cultural scenarios will also transform. Digital globalization will continue to spread cultural values ​​and practices, but also generate tensions between local traditions and external influences. Music, cinema and literature will circulate increasingly intensely, creating a hybrid global culture. However, movements asserting identity and valuing local cultures will gain strength, seeking to preserve traditions and resist cultural homogenization. Cultural diversity will be both a wealth and a challenge, requiring policies of inclusion and respect for difference.
Migration, urbanization and demographic transformations will interact with environmental and technological phenomena. Cities will have to adapt to extreme weather phenomena, such as floods and heat waves, which will affect millions of people. Climate migration will become a reality, with entire populations moving due to rising sea levels and desertification. Accelerated urbanization will require technological solutions, such as smart cities and sustainable infrastructure, but also social policies to ensure inclusion. Demographic transformations will create new balances of power, with Africa and Asia gaining demographic and economic weight, while Europe and Japan will face aging challenges.
In summary, the period between 2025 and 2030 can be described as a critical transition phase, in which the events of 2025 acted as catalysts for structural changes that manifested themselves in different dimensions. The global economy entered a cycle of moderate recovery, but with persistent risks. International politics was marked by polarization and geopolitical tensions, with the United States and China competing for technological and industrial leadership, and the Middle East remaining a focus of instability. The environment has revealed the urgency of the energy transition and climate adaptation, with extreme phenomena affecting millions of people. Technology has transformed economies and societies, creating opportunities and risks. Education and health required inclusive and innovative policies. Security has become a priority, with cyberattacks and digital terrorism posing significant risks. The social and cultural scenarios revealed the importance of migration, urbanization and demographic transformations.
The future will depend on the ability to articulate national interests with collective responsibilities, building a balance between competitiveness and solidarity. If countries are able to invest in responsible innovation, inclusive education and energy sustainability, it will be possible to build a fairer, sustainable and inclusive future. Otherwise, the risk of prolonged stagnation and worsening inequalities will remain high. The period between 2025 and 2030 will therefore remain a decisive moment, in which humanity was called to choose between cooperation and fragmentation, between the courage to move forward and the risk of remaining a prisoner of its own contradictions.</description><pubDate>2025-12-18 01:18:06</pubDate></item><item><title>New Year's Eve | Street parties and concerts to end 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/passagem-de-ano-festas-na-rua-e-concertos-para-encerrar-2025/</link><description>Macau and Hong Kong will be in full swing tonight with celebrations that will welcome 2026. From free concerts next to Praça do Lago Sai Van and at the Taipa Houses-Museum, to shows at Cotai and Mariza's performance at the Macau Cultural Center, there is no shortage of options for all tastes
The end of 2025 is here, and if some opt for a more homely celebration, there will be many people willing to go out and have fun in the company of friends and with lots of music in the mix. With paid and free options, Macau and Hong Kong offer a range of options for various tastes.
One of the initiatives comes from the Cultural Institute (IC) and is already a tradition. The end of 2025 is celebrated next to Praça do Lago Sai Van from 10pm, and from 9pm at the Taipa Houses-Museum, with the “New Year’s Eve Concert – Macau 2025” and the “New Year’s Eve Party – Taipa 2025”.
Various singers and musical groups perform at the concert on the peninsula side, between 10pm and 12:10am, including Hong Kong singer Panther Chan and rock band Dear Jane. There is also a cast of local artists such as Soler, Filipe Tou, KC Ao Ieong, winifai, Jenny, thetiredeyes and Initial B, “who will alternate [performances] to present a diverse range of music to celebrate a dazzling New Year's Eve”, describes the IC.
In the case of this performance at Praça do Lago Sai Van, the stage floor stands out, which will feature “an electronic screen combined with lighting and visual effects, providing a totally new visual experience”. “The entire performance will be presented in a theatrical format adapted to each session, which conveys, through narratives, the wishes for the coming year and reflects the exciting facets of the city”, adds the IC.
Regarding the concerts at the Taipa Houses-Museum, the theme will be “Multicultural Integration”, with the public being able to see performances by FIDA, Tuna Macaense, Bossa Eva and João Gomes &amp; Band and Karen Tong, a singer from Hong Kong.
In addition, there will be performances by the Bollywood Dreams Group, by Victor Kumar, and the Filipino dance groups of the Macau Bisdak Association and Burmese and Vietnamese dance groups from Macau. The poster is completed with magic presentations by magician Jason Fong.
From 8:30 pm and until 11:30 pm, there will be cultural exhibitors from local communities in the Philippines, India, Myanmar and Vietnam, who aim to promote the cuisine and culture of their countries.
Mariza at CCM
Another great highlight to end the year is the performance by fado singer Mariza at the Macau Cultural Center (CCM) from 8pm, alongside the Macau Orchestra. “Mariza, the Queen of Fado and the Macau Orchestra (OM)” is the name given to the concert where the fado singer will perform, “with her deeply emotional voice, a selection of iconic fados, providing the public with a musical experience that transcends genres and spatial and temporal boundaries”.
The Portuguese is described “as one of the biggest international Fado stars, being recognized for her own musical style, which incorporates elements of soul, jazz and gospel”.
Looking at Cotai, gaming operators bet heavily on year-end programs. The Venetian Arena concert hall hosts the third and final in a series of concerts by Jason Zhang, which began on Monday. Tickets range from MOP680 to MOP2,580 for VIP seats.
Jason Zhang Jie was born in 1982 in China and debuted in the “My Show” competition in 2004, becoming the winner, which gave him access to a contract with Universal Music China. At the end of 2023, he already had 15 albums recorded and a total of 87 concerts in his career. Still at the Venetian, as well as at The Parisian Macao and The Londoner, there will be fireworks, with the traditional countdown until 2026. The “Sands New Year’s Eve Countdown Extravaganza” event starts with music at 9:30 pm.
Like Sands China, the gaming operator Galaxy also made its plans to end the year in style, namely in the Andaz Macau, Long Bar and Pony &amp; Plume developments. The party takes place with DJ performances and the promise of unlimited drinks.
For those who want something different and, at the same time, themed, there will be a “La Nuit Rouge Countdown Party” at The Ritz-Carlton Bar and Lounge, with French cabaret and live music.
Air Supply in Hong Kong
Going to Hong Kong to close the year 2025 could also be an option. To begin with, one of the centers of entertainment will be the pedestrian zone on Chater Road, in Central.
On the Hong Kong Tourism Board website, it is stated that the public can enjoy “a new format of live music performances combined with light shows”, namely by the band Air Supply, who will perform “a special performance with their timeless classic hits”. The Australian duo, formed in 1975, already has a 50-year career under their belt and has well-known songs such as “All Out of Love”, “Making Love Out of Nothing at All” and “Lost in Love”.
This year-end night, Hong Kong artists Jay Fung and Cloud Wan will also perform. There will be no shortage of a children's choir and the Hong Kong Police Band to welcome 2026. The performances start at 11:28 pm.
Another countdown is scheduled in the Kowloon area, at WestK Christmas Town 2025. The public can attend concerts by On Chan, Kandy Wong, The Hertz, Nowhere Boys, DJ P-Chef and Hong Kong Arts Without Boundaries Foundation, located at WestK Christmas Lane [Harbourside East Lawn, Art Park], with the Victoria Harbor as a backdrop. The party continues after midnight. Still with remnants of Christmas, the public will be able to see and photograph the tree that is at WestK Christmas Town 2025 and is 12 meters high.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:46:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong hosts winter festival until Sunday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/hong-kong-acolhe-festival-de-inverno-ate-domingo/</link><description>For those who still want to experience the last moments of the season between Christmas and New Year, the neighboring territory hosts the “Hong Kong Winter Fest”, with two events ending next Sunday. A giant Christmas tree in the city center, lots of lights and spaces that spark the imagination is what you can expect from this initiative.
One of the spaces is the “Christmas City”, located in Central, which has a 20 meter high Christmas tree and various decorations with toys that make reference to the festive days that have just come to an end. The “Christmas Town” began on November 14th and can be visited until this Sunday.
Another attraction of this festival is the “Immersive Light Show”, also in Central. As the name suggests, the public can see a light show, with three-dimensional projections, music and animation, with viewing points in North Square and South Square, Statue Square Gardens. There are shows every 30 minutes between 7:30 am and 11:30 pm.
Here, “eight iconic buildings become a giant screen” for this show, with figures such as snowmen, angels or reindeer dancing “among the buildings and trees, creating a rich and dreamy experience that illuminates the festive nights of Hong Kong”, describes the tourism department of the HKSAR Government.
The buildings where the light show will be projected are the Bank of China Tower, Hong Kong City Hall High Block, Hong Kong Club, the main building of HSBC and Standard Chartered Bank, among others.
Lights until February
There is also a third initiative integrated into this winter festival that runs until February 22nd. This is “Starlight Boulevard”, where Chater Road will be adorned with various lights, including a pedestrian crossing and “an impressive centerpiece above the Chater House”.
“Visitors can continue their journey under a golden canopy of light to reach Noëlia at LANDMARK, an enchanting large-scale interactive installation for more surprises and Christmas charm”, it is further described on the event page. This area of ​​lights can be visited between Chater Road and Central.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:46:50</pubDate></item><item><title>CCM | “The Journey of a Soloist”, a concert to see and hear today</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/ccm-a-viagem-de-um-solista-um-concerto-para-ver-e-ouvir-hoje/</link><description>Studio II of the Macau Cultural Center today hosts a classical music show led by the Macau Chinese Orchestra. “Chinese Music 360º: The Journey of a Soloist” features Kin Szeto, a young maestro from Hong Kong
A sound experience, immersion of the senses and a way to spend the last days of the year surrounded by music: all the arguments are good for attending today, in Studio II of the Macau Cultural Center (CCM), the concert led by the Macau Chinese Orchestra (OCM).
“Chinese Music 360º: The Journey of a Soloist” starts at 7:45 pm and features the young Hong Kong maestro Kin Szeto.
According to the concert synopsis, this is a show that promises to break “with the traditional concert format, offering a unique and immersive experience”, “a new way of listening to Chinese music: being inside the orchestra”, reads the show poster, whose tickets cost 150 patacas.
“In addition to presenting classic works of Chinese music, the audience is provided with an immersive 360-degree sound effect, allowing them to feel the dialogue and resonance between the instruments through innovative arrangements”, adds the OCM presentation.
The OCM also describes that the public can “be immersed in the vastness of Chinese music”, with the promise that Kin Szeto, “winner of international orchestra conducting competitions, will lead the orchestra with his technical mastery and energetic style, exploring all the richness of Chinese music”.
A long career
Kin Szeto received his doctorate in Musical Arts and orchestral conducting at the University of Cincinnati College-Conservatory of Music, under the supervision of Mark Gibson, and a scholarship that covered his entire studies. Previously, he completed a master's degree in New York, at Ithaca College.
The young man from Hong Kong won the 2022 Orchestra Conductors Competition prize in Romania, having made his European debut with the Brasov Philharmonic Orchestra.
In the United States, Kin Szeto held various musical positions, such as guest and assistant conductor and also musical director. Furthermore, the maestro is a performer of the erhu, a traditional Chinese music instrument. He was a musician at the Hong Kong Chinese Orchestra between 2011 and 2016, and later served as conductor of the orchestra.
More music in January
Also noteworthy is the holding of a concert led by OCM in January, on the 16th, starting at 7:45 pm. It is titled “Dawn Breaks” and features Liao Yuan-Yu as conductor and musicians Lin Jie, performer of ruan, a traditional Chinese instrument; and also Hou Guangyu, who will be on stage playing a dizi.
The program includes compositions such as “Bamboo Reverie”, by Li Jiaying, played by the orchestra together with the dizi; “Formation Break: Contempo”, by JunYi Chow; and also “Macau Impressions”, a work commissioned and composed by Zhao Jiping.
According to the concert synopsis, the OCM maestro will “lead the audience through an exciting artistic journey, from the first flashes of inspiration”.
“The concert will feature Hou Guangyu, renowned bamboo flutist, who will perform the flute concerto ‘Bamboo Reverie’. Lin Jie, head of the Orchestra’s ruan section, will perform, together with the Orchestra, ‘Ode to the Sun’, a work that reveals the strength of joy and encouragement”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:45:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Death | French actress Brigitte Bardot dies aged 91</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/29/obito-actriz-francesa-brigitte-bardot-morre-aos-91-anos/</link><description>Brigitte Bardot, one of the biggest stars in world cinema, passed away yesterday at the age of 91. The actress had been admitted to the hospital in the city of Toulon, in the south of France, since November.
In a statement, the Brigitte Bardot Foundation announced her death with “immense sadness”, describing her as a “world-renowned actress and singer, who chose to abandon her prestigious career to dedicate her life and energy to animal welfare and her foundation”.
Known for her enormous impact on cinema in the 1950s, «BB», as she was widely called in France, was an essential ingredient of French culture and quickly became an icon after her first role in Le Trou Normand (1952). Two more films followed in 1952, when she married director Roger Vadim. A year later, Bardot conquered Hollywood and the United States, and her popularity as one of the sexiest women in the world was firmly established.
Brigitte Bardot continued to act in a total of 28 films over two decades and became a symbol of women's sexual liberation. However, ruthlessly “marketed” as a sexual and hedonistic symbol, Bardot ended up succumbing to the frustration of not being taken seriously as an actress and abandoned her career to dedicate herself to campaigns for animal welfare.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 01:46:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Money exchange | Raid targets 60 million Hong Kong dollar deal</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/troca-de-dinheiro-rusga-visa-negocio-de-60-milhoes-de-dolares-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Judiciary Police (PJ) announced the arrest of two women for allegedly being involved in illegal exchanges of money for gambling at a casino in Cotai. According to police estimates, the business operating in a jewelry store had a turnover of more than 60 million Hong Kong dollars, with profits being 1 million Hong Kong dollars.
The detainees are a 36-year-old local resident and a 27-year-old woman from Mainland China. Both performed sales roles in the commercial space. At yesterday's press conference in which the case was presented, PJ representatives admitted that they were currently investigating the whereabouts of the owner of the commercial space.
In addition to the arrests, around 500 thousand Hong Kong dollars in cash were seized. A cell phone was also seized, which was allegedly used to arrange money exchanges. The investigation was based on anonymous complaints that alerted authorities to the possibility that illegal money exchanges were taking place inside the store.
The arrests took place after the agents spent a day monitoring what was happening in the commercial space, having decided to act after seeing three customers with “suspicious behavior”. The store had been operating in the casino, which was not identified, since 2019, and the two employees confessed to exchanging money. The prisoners received salaries of 13 thousand patacas and 15 thousand patacas, which included overtime pay.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:40:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourism | Chinese excursionists with a drop of almost 24%</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/turismo-excursionistas-chineses-com-quebra-de-quase-24/</link><description>The Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC) revealed yesterday that the number of day trippers recorded an annual drop of 12.5 percent in November, to a total of 191,000.
Noteworthy is the fact that the number of arrivals of visitors on tours from Mainland China, 148,000, fell by 23.7 percent in November, while the number of international visitors on tours, 28,000, grew by 33.8 percent.
At the end of November, Macau had a hotel complex with 147 units, just one more compared to November 2024, which provided 45,000 guest rooms, an increase of 3.5 percent. The occupancy rate that month stood at 90.2 percent, with the occupancy rate of 5-star hotels, at 94 percent, rising 2.5 percentage points, while that of 4-star hotels (84.6 percent) and 3-star hotels (84.3 percent) decreased by 1.2 and 3.1 percentage points, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:39:26</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Morgan Stanley less optimistic about MGM China results</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/jogo-morgan-stanley-menos-optimista-face-a-resultados-da-mgm-china/</link><description>The investment bank predicts that MGM China's new contract with its parent company to use the MGM brand will have a significant impact on the gaming concessionaire's financial results.
The rise in costs for using the MGM brand by the game concessionaire MGM China led investment bank Morgan Stanley to reduce expectations regarding the company's financial results. In a note released to investors, the investment bank now expects the concessionaire's financial results to fall within the market average, whereas previously it expected them to exceed the average.
The change in expectations regarding MGM China takes into account the new contract for using the MGM company's brand. According to details released before Christmas, MGM China will now pay 3.5 percent of consolidated monthly net revenues, up from 1.75 percent. This difference means that MGM China will pay practically double to MGM Resorts International, the parent company.
Based on this change, Morgan Stanley explains that the new payments should cost the dealership about 7 percent of earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization (EBITDA) per year.
The recently revealed agreement lasts for 20 years, depending on the renewal of the gaming concession after 2030, and foresees a maximum payment of 188.3 million US dollars (1.5 billion patacas) for 2026. However, financial services company CBRE Equity Research believes that the value of MGM China's profits for next year should result in a payment of around US$166 million (1.3 billion patacas).
Historical values
The payment of around US$166 million for next year contrasts with what has been happening since at least 2023. In that year, the first without movement restrictions after the Covid-19 pandemic, MGM China paid MGM Resorts International around US$55.2 million. The following year, payments rose to US$70.9 million, reflecting the company's improved financial performance.
Payments for the current year are not yet known, but by the end of September they totaled US$56.5 million. Taking into account that this rate of profits is maintained, despite the market having expanded in recent months, payments for this year are expected to be around 75.3 million US dollars.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:38:20</pubDate></item><item><title>Research | Prize created for studies on Sino-Portuguese relations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/investigacao-criado-premio-para-estudos-sobre-relacoes-sino-portuguesas/</link><description>The “Fundação Jorge Álvares-General Vasco Rocha Vieira-Portugal-China Friendship Award” will award 25 thousand euros per year and aims to recognize institutions that promote initiatives to strengthen rapprochement between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities
The Jorge Álvares Foundation launched an annual prize, worth 25 thousand euros, to encourage the study and research of relations between Portugal and China, through Macau, according to the entity's website.
With the “Fundação Jorge Álvares-General Vasco Rocha Vieira-Portugal-China Friendship Award”, it also intends to recognize “institutions that promote relevant initiatives in order to reinforce the rapprochement between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities”, it is stated on the foundation's website. “It aims to honor and contribute to perpetuating the memory of the last governor of Macau, founder of the Jorge Álvares Foundation, its curator and first president, who passed away about a year ago”, the current curator, Tiago Vasconcelos, wrote on social media on Monday.
The prize will be awarded, alternately, to institutions, in even-numbered years and from 2026, and to research work, in odd-numbered years, this being launched in 2027.
In the first case, the award is open to any institution, national or foreign, rewarding “relevant actions that develop or deepen the relationship between the Portuguese, Chinese and Macanese communities”, in the fields of Portuguese, Chinese or Patuá culture and languages, science, education, philanthropy, among others.
Open investigation
With regard to research work, the award “is open to anyone without academic restrictions, nationality or otherwise”, and rewards “the quality of studies and written work on a topic, to be indicated for each edition, within the scope of relations between Portugal and China, particularly through Macau”. “From the signing of the joint declaration to the transfer of the Portuguese administration of Macau” is, according to the regulations, the theme for the first edition of the award in the research category.
Vasco Joaquim Rocha Vieira was born on August 16, 1939. He was Chief of the Army General Staff and, inherently, member of the Revolution Council between 1976 and 1978.
He served as minister of the Republic of the Azores (1986-1991) and in 1991 was appointed Governor of Macau by the then
President of the Portuguese Republic, Mário Soares. He was the 138th and last Portuguese governor of Macau, a position he held until 1999, when the territory was transferred to China.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:37:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching | Around 97% of students use AI tools</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/ensino-cerca-de-97-dos-alunos-utiliza-ferramentas-de-ia/</link><description>Around 97 percent of secondary school students admitted to having used Artificial Intelligence as a tool to help with their studies. The conclusion is part of a study carried out by the Federation of Workers' Associations of Macau, which compared the development of students at local secondary level with students in the Greater Bay Area.
Based on the opinion of 2,000 students, the results presented by deputy Lam Lon Wai indicate that 97 percent of students recognized using artificial intelligence. Among these, more than 50 percent stated that artificial intelligence contributed to their obtaining better grades.
Half of the respondents also stated that artificial intelligence can generate excessive dependence and that it can affect the development of logical and critical reasoning. Given these results, FAOM recommends that schools customize artificial intelligence tools, to take advantage of the advantages and avoid the negative aspects.
The association also considers that it is necessary to change the mentality of educational establishments, with education less focused on obtaining grades to enter the best universities. According to FAOM, the priority should be teaching students to think and develop skills to solve everyday problems.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:34:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Transport | Proportion of new electric vehicles increases</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/transportes-proporcao-de-novos-veiculos-electricos-aumenta/</link><description>The Statistics and Census Bureau (DSEC) revealed that the number of electric vehicles circulating in Macau has increased. In the first 11 months of 2025, 10,060 vehicles were registered with new registrations, 3,733 of these were electric, representing a share of 37.1 percent of all new registrations. This proportion of electric vehicles shows a growth of 6.3 percent, compared to the first 11 months of 2024.
In relation to cars with new registrations, there was a drop of 15.2 percent compared to the same period in 2024. Even so, at the end of November there were 254,055 vehicles registered in the Macao SAR, 0.5 percent more compared to the end of the same month in 2024.
DSEC data also reveals the occurrence of 1,215 road accidents in November, an annual drop of 14.2 percent, with 395 injuries recorded. But in 11 months, the number of road accidents was 13,578, with four fatalities and 4,983 injuries.
As for the movement of cross-border transport, the number of cars at border posts totaled 958,605 in November this year, 15.1 percent more in annual terms. In the first eleven months of 2025, car movement at border crossings (10,136,209) increased by 21.5 percent in annual terms.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:29:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Buses | Assessment survey scheduled for January</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/31/autocarros-inquerito-de-avaliacao-marcado-para-janeiro/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) will carry out, throughout the month of January, the Quarterly Evaluation Survey of the Public Bus Service for the 4th quarter of 2025.
According to a statement from DSAT, indicators such as “service and management”, “transport and safety means and equipment” and “degree of passenger satisfaction” will be evaluated. In this last indicator, six different means will be made available for collecting opinions, namely interviews with passengers carried out by “workers from an independent third party” or online surveys.
DSAT states that the passenger opinion portion represents 40 percent of the total assessment score for the public bus service.</description><pubDate>2025-12-31 03:28:33</pubDate></item><item><title>ZELENSKY VS ZELENSKY</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A Ukrainian pensioner, with the same name as the president, blames Zelensky for the prolongation of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the villager, who never left his land, is now mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, a villager, represents half the world that recriminates the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters our house, covers his wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on the rapes in Ukraine, in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say to him: hi there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: you still haven't said what name you want to give the children!
A peace that is not dignified is nothing more than a cessation of rights. As serious as the Russophobia that Putin inflicts on his people.
 
10/28/22
At a lunch with several guests, I heard a friend, who declared herself a spiritualist, explaining the particularities of her belief, in a calm and balanced way, I would even say, without a hint of “irrationalism”. He spoke at length and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytism. “Here is someone whose belief has brought thoughtfulness!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at a certain moment a sentence comes out that horrifies me. It says, “there is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, and I glimpse the voracious maws of holism. Because holism has a pathological aspect, like all good things, a shadow side.
Two examples: in Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is just an expression of rigorous karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts he committed in his previous life. In Africa, it is not accepted that death could have been accidental, and many women are accused by the family of the deceased of having caused the death of their husband, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, a huge injustice for the wife — madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism introduced Compassion and Christianity introduced Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a Platonic stage, where we are nothing more than the shadows of something — an inextricable law -, in a determinism that calcifies all singularities, but that strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity was anchored in the conquest of chance and randomness, removing the incidences of a life from this fierce determinism that enclosed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at that moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and its volition were able to emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “there is no such thing as chance, nothing happens by chance!”, which should function as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, however, this phrase is usually used to seek a reason for things outside of us, in others. It's an alibi.
Today there is a holistic temptation in the world, just as there was a satanic temptation in the Middle Ages, without much reflection on its consequences. Because it's not enough to want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even for the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to that cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the fight” took place at the beginning of this century. One of the great mistakes of the 20th century was the false dichotomy between “rationalism and irrationalism”, a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality (the positive side of reason) was confused with rationalism (the pathological aspect of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment, irrationalism was confused with freedom. Almost all 20th century art, with Surrealism at its head, made this mistake. The fallacy still exists despite the emergence of “irrationalism” and the consequent relativist currents that followed it having been consolidated everywhere. Essentially, much of what happened in the 20th century revolved around this clash between two paradigms: Rationalism versus Irationalism.
Now, I see, we must save indeterminacy, chance, randomness from the terrible temptation of the cage of causalities. Holism, in its pathological form, may be reductionism that sets itself up as a new “eschatological narrative”.
Is it “by chance” that holism emerges at a time when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person is besieging everything, all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic awareness has brought a positive impact to greater ecological awareness, but followed with scholastic rigor, it stifles reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than uncomfortable: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that each moment asks of us — but how many will make the distinction, under a Law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will abandon themselves to what is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic awareness, as the Greeks knew, but it also brings agency and the courage of decision. And we cannot give up on this.
Furthermore, as Drummond shows in the poem “Quadrilha”, by Carlos Drummond de Andrade:
«João loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who didn't love anyone./ João went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of a disaster, Maria stayed with her aunt,/ Joaquim committed suicide and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story.»
Real always runs outside the track, completely outside our concepts. That's what matters to us — a J. Pinto Fernandes emerges at the exact moment when we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>From Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
When reading many people's reactions when this year's Nobel Prize for Literature was announced, I couldn't help but remember this comment from Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: «An editor of a large national daily newspaper wrote five lines of indignation at the fact that the Nobel Prize for Literature had been awarded to Thomas Traströmer, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did it not occur to this literary columnist, patented and paid to do his job, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of professional misconduct? Tranströmer had been translated into many languages, it was available in French.»
There is always the chorus of those who wait for the Prize to be announced to complain about not having been invited to be on the jury, there is a subgroup of angry people who profess “I have never read it and I won’t even bother to read it”; It is a less than humble fauna, the one that inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners – I didn't know about the existence of Louise Glück, who I think is a great poet, or Olga Tokarczuk, for example – but this only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows everyone else and the joy of recognizing that the yardstick of the world is not measured with my short measure and that, on the contrary, it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown and learn from it.
And perhaps the most stupid reaction was that of the intelligent man who wrote, But are there still people who read French?; simply confirming that today there is a new type of ignorance that is being raised with abandon: that of those who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda Lê or even Sollers were awarded, or, among the new ones, Mathias Énard, but that does not detract from the dignity of Annie Ernaux's work (and it would have been enough to have written “Les Années”). There are books of hers that I like less, like the vulgar “Uma Paixão Simples”, but that happens with almost all authors, they have pivotal books and others that are like breaks in their itinerary. I recommend reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, “L’écriture comme un couteau”.
11/10/22
Yesterday an article appeared in the morning newspaper “Notícias”, in Maputo, reporting that the Pen Club Narrative Prize had been awarded to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already won the Maria Velho da Costa Prize.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, as it is pathetic, but what is important to highlight is the note of disqualification regarding its “Mozambicanness” when they call it Luso-Mozambican. It's not that it's inaccurate, but, for those who know the context, it's a touch naughty.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, Álvaro Taruma Ronga-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican for writers from the north, etc., etc. Which doesn't appear to happen.
At one point, in the novel, she writes:
«Our color was never the dominant one. In colonial times we were not white, we were dressed in monhés, mugs of washed asses, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goan and Portuguese. In the post-colonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me for Brazilian or Cape Verdean, in France they were lost in thought about where I was from and were surprised when they discovered that I was African. There I had to explain the wanderings of my DNA before settling in Mozambique. It took me a long time to accept that it was like that because yes, and that it was no curse that that was the case; on the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this harlequin cloak that is our genealogy…”
In modern-day Mozambique, it means being white… and that immediately takes precedence over what you do or what you are.
It's sad, but as Naipaul warned, in these parts race is everything and people live as deeply immersed in it as, in other places, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions and who entertained himself by turning his back on the dogmas of the “moderns”, has died. For him, the place, the role of the specialist, was defined more by the perplexity he embodied than by the supposed truth that would sustain him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the goodness of multiculturalism and its equivocal cliché “all different, all equal”, a return to “diplomacy”, given that this, precisely, does not start from the assumption that “we are unified because we share the same nature” but simply highlights that we “still do not share a common world”; It is necessary that we deal head-on with the “abyss of disagreement” that separates us, instead of trying to deceive it.
And about politics he said, boldly:
«If transparency is demanded from politicians, we kill them; if anyone demands fidelity to what the other was or what he says, kill him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, representation is killed. These must therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to bend the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put forward the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years.» (in “Un Monde Pluriel mais Commun”). I believe we will be needed to decipher this frantically complex world that has fallen to us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Fuxi</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these disastrous journeys through countries as old as the stars and the Moon, and as strange as the deepest interior of our wretched souls, what surprises still await us, what secret magics will we still have to overcome, what horrors will arise before our pupils dilated with astonishment and terror?
Increasingly closer to our precarious existences, howls the monster of war, which threatens to merge humanity once and for all with the earth, incessantly traversed by the squalid specter of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pestilences.
Oh damned human, who believes you are superior to Nature itself, but then you reveal yourself, time and time again, incapable of simply ordering your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by fickle anger and are a slave to your own ambition! You are not satisfied with white jade or resplendent gold, there is no treasure that quenches your inextinguishable thirst for command over other men, animals and things; for eternal anguish dwells in you; in you the expelled serpents crawl; for you grows, powerful and impressive, the most fertile ivy of Evil!
This is perhaps why on the Mount they call the White Deer, where one of the eight immortals on a sacred mount soared through the heavens towards Penglai, lives the fuxi, a bird whose shape resembles that of a rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulations, what monstrous embraces, what terrible procedures must have occurred to make the existence of this sinister animal possible? We don't know, but all it takes is for our exhausted mind to dare to come up with an answer, and then we feel our skin covered in horrendous goosebumps and our heart races in parade, like a wild horse whipped by the night whip of fear, unresponsive to reins and containment.
Let men refrain from visiting Monte do Veado, because although there are riches capable of calming the wildest ambitions, if they have the unfortunate luck of catching a glimpse of a fuxi, it is certain that a war will soon break out and the cultivated fields will perish, because of it the tame animals will be beheaded, because of it the best young men of two generations will be sacrificed and the pride of the countries will be destroyed.
The fuxi makes a sound reminiscent of its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, be on your way, because the path you are on is the surest path to misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>While rereading Easter, because of an article I'm preparing, I come across this excerpt, taken from “The Universal Man”:
«Each man, morally, is one and absolute; but he has to live with attenuating his personality. (…) Coexistence is only possible between people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which constantly gives way. Hence, the emptiness of society, an immense ghost made up of countless dead people. A superior man is antisocial or criminal. His destiny is prison and the desert”.
I hesitate to think whether Pascoaes reflects here on the political-social conditions that muzzle, and, worse, in a sad country like Portugal in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relationships were restricted, or if it merely lends to the behavior of (oppressed) men a metaphysical framework, an “essence”, declared in the presumption of each being, in isolation, “one and absolute”. Sometimes, in addition to an excess of Spirituality (or Saudade), Pascoaes lacks the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes Ampoules-of-Great-Ideas and who therefore writes often trapped by a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; It is not uncommon for a glass to be erected between him and reality, the same glass that made him write in O Bailado, from 1921: «Everything is a ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, of afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! And a divine lightning that pierces them, the instantaneous Apparition that appears and throws us to the ground, dazzled!»
Sometimes I felt like reminding him, as António Sérgio did, in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which he dedicated to Pascoaes: «Pascoais, Pascoais my dear friend: you are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: of this horrible isolation that you praise and I curse».
«As a child, he stole two blackbirds», says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, he stole them from a nest, and he felt remorse for that all his life. The Person, few more mischiefs are known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos does a hint of wickedness and obscenity emerge: «Ah, and the ordinary and dirty people, who always look the same,/ Who use swear words as usual words,/ Whose sons steal from grocery store doors/ And whose daughters at the age of eight – and I think this is beautiful and I love it! –/ Decent-looking men masturbate in stairwells.” (Triumphal ode).
Both poets, driven by a certain idea of ​​sanctity, had the same inability to break the siege of their skin with the overflow of someone else's dam, the same curse of sublimating the concrete ferocity of eros with the gentleness of the verses.
Obviously, they are both “bigger than life”, but sometimes it makes me unnerved to watch, from my position as a hatter at the Procrastinators Club, the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of President and Treasurer.
Although Pessoa guessed more things, for example, what he wrote in the lesser-known Ode Martial and which is reflected in the situation we live in today, deferred, with his heart in his hands:
«MARTIAL ODE
(…)
Helahoho! helahoho!
The poor widow's sewing machine who was bayoneted...
She sewed indefinitely in the afternoon…
The table where the old people played,
Everything mixed, everything mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragging horror.
Helahoho! helahoho!
I unearthed the child's tin train pressed into the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet tripped over the sewing machine
[widow who was killed with a bayonet
And that poor instrument of peace stuck a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was the one to blame for everything, I was the soldier for them all
Who killed, raped, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse like a shadow
[misshapen
They travel around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps there are footsteps the size of infinity
And a physical fear of being accountable to God makes me close my eyes.
[eyes suddenly.
(…)
I ordered, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all fathers tied to trees be raped,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And everything scalds and suffocates and I can't move without it
[everything be the same.
God have mercy on me, I didn't have it from anyone!
LÀ-BAS, JE NE SAIS OÙ…”
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment in which Cristiano &amp; Companhia failed in their mission in Braga, and in which the self-sabotage of Russia's gas pipelines reminds us that Putin will be willing to do anything to maintain dominance over the areas endorsed,
is that, bomb for bomb, the “bomb” of the Fifth Empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dears, we were irresolute, a little more on the side of piella than determined, and we procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>War | Thailand accused Cambodia of violating airspace with 250 drones</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/guerra-tailandia-acusou-camboja-de-violar-espaco-aereo-com-250-drones/</link><description>Thailand yesterday accused Cambodia of violating the current ceasefire agreement by sending 250 unmanned aerial devices (drones) over Thai territory.
The Thai Army indicated that more than 250 drones were detected entering the country in the border area. For the Thai Armed Forces, Cambodia's action constituted a provocation and a violation of measures “aimed at reducing tensions” between Bangkok and Phnom Penh. At the time of writing, the Cambodian authorities had not commented on Thailand's accusation regarding the airspace violation.
The two countries reached a ceasefire on Saturday after three weeks of clashes along their 800-kilometre common border, following two days of negotiations in China. The ceasefire agreement provides for an end to weeks of fighting along the disputed border, which has left more than 100 people dead and more than half a million displaced in both countries. Thai Foreign Minister Sihasak Phuangketkeow and his Cambodian counterpart Prak Sokhonn met in southwest China's Yunnan province for talks mediated by his Chinese counterpart Wang Yi.
The head of Chinese diplomacy stated that Beijing “does not want to see Thailand and Cambodia on battlefields”. During a meeting with his Thai counterpart, Sihasak Phuangketkeow, on Sunday, Wang Yi expressed China's “deep concern” about the “tense situation on the border” and argued that, once the fighting stops, “diplomacy must take the lead”.
“Rebuilding peace is the desire of the people and the expectation of all parties,” said the head of Chinese diplomacy, adding that Beijing’s mediation efforts “never impose themselves on others, nor go beyond limits” and aim to create “a relaxed platform for dialogue.”
A fatal history
US President Donald Trump, who threatened to suspend trade privileges if Thailand and Cambodia did not agree to a ceasefire in July, suggested yesterday that fighting between Thailand and Cambodia “will momentarily cease” and stated that the United States “has become the true United Nations”. The territorial limits have been disputed for decades and were inherited from the French colonial period.
According to official figures, recognized by the United Nations, the latest clashes caused 47 deaths: 26 on the Thai side and 21 on the Cambodian side. In July, the first phase of clashes left 43 dead in five days, before a ceasefire was agreed.
Another agreement was subsequently signed on October 26 in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, in the presence of the President of the United States, but was suspended by Thailand after several Bangkok soldiers were injured in the explosion of a military land mine in the border area.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:53:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysts estimate that BYD will surpass Tesla in global sales by 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/analistas-estimam-que-byd-supere-tesla-nas-vendas-globais-em-2025/</link><description>BYD's rapid global expansion and Tesla's regulatory difficulties in the United States and other markets should allow the Chinese manufacturer to lead global sales of all-electric vehicles for the first time in 2025, analysts predict. Both groups are expected to release their annual reports soon, but based on the latest data, BYD's accumulated advantage is such that it seems almost impossible that Tesla has managed to regain ground.
By the end of November, BYD had already sold 2,066,002 fully electric vehicles, becoming the first brand to surpass that milestone. Tesla registered 1,217,902 units by the end of September.
The North American manufacturer benefited, in the third quarter, from a shopping rush caused by the end of tax incentives in the USA, which led many consumers to anticipate purchasing their vehicles. Tesla's global deliveries rose 7 percent year-on-year to 497,099 vehicles.
Analysts predicted a rapid contraction in the following quarter. The consensus of analysts at the financial services company FactSet points to 449 thousand units in the fourth quarter (-9.48 percent compared to the previous year) and a total of 1.65 million vehicles for 2025 (-7.66 percent). This is an annual projection well below the level already reached by BYD until November 30th.
German bank Deutsche Bank estimates that Tesla will deliver 405,000 vehicles in the fourth quarter, while analysts at Swiss bank UBS point to 415,000 – both forecasts recently revised downwards.
Deutsche Bank highlighted sales below expectations in North America (-33 percent), Europe (-34 percent) and, to a lesser extent, China (-10 percent).
Glass half full
The TD Cowen bank presents a more optimistic estimate (429 thousand units), but highlights that the quarter was “a little delicate”, due to the end of tax incentives, which made projections difficult, according to analyst Itay Michaeli. “Tesla’s deliveries will show signs of weakness in the fourth quarter,” said the director of Wedbush Securities, Dan Ives. “A total of 420 thousand vehicles would already be enough to show some stability in demand, at a time when the market is focused on the launch of autonomous driving in 2026”, he added.
Tesla's sales have been affected by a slower-than-expected electrical transition, increased competition and US President Donald Trump's decisions since returning to power in January.
The closeness between Elon Musk and Trump, both during the campaign and after taking office, also affected the brand's image, leading to calls for a boycott. Sales fell sharply, especially in Europe.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:50:53</pubDate></item><item><title>APN | Beijing expels three more generals in anti-corruption campaign</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/30/apn-pequim-expulsa-mais-tres-generais-em-campanha-anticorrupcao/</link><description>Three senior military officials were expelled from China's highest legislative body, part of the anti-corruption campaign that has intensified within the ranks of the People's Liberation Army
According to the South China Morning Post newspaper, the head of the Political and Legal Affairs Committee of the Central Military Commission (CMC), Wang Renhua, the political commissar of the People's Armed Police, Zhang Hongbing, and the director of the CMC training department, Wang Peng, were expelled from the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress (NPC). The decision comes after weeks of speculation about the whereabouts and position of these officers, who have been absent from relevant military events since July, including the anniversary of the Armed Forces and the fourth plenary session of the Central Committee of the Chinese Communist Party, held in October.
Despite their expulsion from the national legislative body, the three continue to appear as members of the Party's Central Committee, the country's highest political decision-making structure.
Wang Renhua, 63, was promoted to admiral less than a year ago by Chinese President Xi Jinping, and led the Army's judicial and disciplinary structures - courts, prosecutors and military prison system - becoming the third main person responsible for military security after the reform of the Armed Forces launched in 2015. Wang's meteoric rise and abrupt fall illustrate the instability in the Chinese military hierarchy and the tightening of the 'zero tolerance' policy towards corruption.
The Chinese Ministry of Defense did not comment directly on the removals, but observers point out that the expulsions reflect a profound shakeup in the command structure and reinforce political control over strategic defense sectors.
The purge continues
The anti-corruption campaign in the Armed Forces has been one of the flagships of Xi Jinping's government and has targeted dozens of senior officials in recent years, including commanders of the Air Force, Navy and nuclear forces.
The United States Department of Defense last week published its annual report on China's military power, in which it highlights that Beijing has expanded the definition of “core interest” to explicitly include Taiwan, as well as territorial claims in the South China Sea. The report, submitted annually to the US Congress since 2000, also mentions China's military sales to Pakistan and Russia, the purge of military leaders for corruption and the technological advancement of the Chinese armed forces, with an emphasis on Artificial Intelligence.
In response, a Chinese defense spokesman said on Thursday that the document misrepresents China's national defense policy and seeks to "mislead the international community" about the country's military strategy.</description><pubDate>2025-12-30 01:49:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Study | Angola and Mozambique exposed to Chinese slowdown</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/29/estudo-angola-e-mocambique-expostos-a-desaceleracao-chinesa/</link><description>The slowdown in the Chinese economy and possible transformation of its growth model could have profound impacts on African countries, including Angola and Mozambique, warns in a report by the Rhodium Group think tank.
“As China's economic model loses steam, African leaders will have to plan growth and economic transformation aware that their largest trading and investment partner could have a very different profile than it has had until now”, reads the analysis carried out by the group, based in New York.
Angola is identified as one of the countries most sensitive to the evolution of the second largest economy in the world. China is one of the main destinations for Angolan crude and the report anticipates that Chinese imports of African oil are expected to stagnate or decline, as Beijing accelerates the energy transition, expands the fleet of electric vehicles and reduces the energy intensity of its economy.
This scenario could put pressure on tax revenues, exports and Luanda's ability to honor its external debt, in a context in which the country already pays more to China in repayments than it receives in new loans.
Mozambique may have a different trajectory. Although also exposed to Chinese demand for raw materials, the report anticipates a structurally robust demand for strategic minerals associated with the energy transition, such as graphite and other critical minerals, sectors in which Mozambique has been gaining relevance.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 01:58:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Foreign trade | Revised law with reinforcement of responses to “external struggles”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/29/comercio-externo-lei-revista-com-reforco-das-resposta-a-lutas-externas/</link><description>China approved on Saturday a revision of the foreign trade law, which strengthens the legal framework for the development of cross-border trade and expands legal tools to respond to “external struggles”.
According to the state agency Xinhua, the Standing Committee of the National People's Congress (APN, legislative body) gave the 'green light' to the new version of the standard, which will come into force on March 1, 2026, after a vote held this Saturday. The revised law incorporates a series of reforms, which until now were applied through regulations or sectoral policies.
These include the system of negative lists for cross-border trade in services, support for new formats and models of external trade, the push for digital trade and the acceleration of the construction of a “green” trade system. The text also establishes provisions for the State to advance in alignment with “high-level international economic and commercial standards” and participate in the formulation of global rules in this field, according to Xinhua.
With the aim of optimizing the environment for foreign trade, the law also reinforces the protection of intellectual property rights linked to international commercial activities. In this sense, it stipulates that the State will improve the level of regulatory compliance of foreign trade operators and their ability to manage risks related to intellectual property.
The standard also introduces a commercial adjustment assistance system, aimed at “stabilizing industrial and supply chains”, an aspect that has gained relevance in recent years in the face of commercial and technological frictions with the United States and other partners.
In time of truce
One of the highlights of the review is the expansion and improvement of the so-called “set of legal tools” for the defense of China's external interests, at a time marked by the trade truce reached with the United States and the persistence of tensions with other actors, such as the European Union.
The reform is approved weeks after Beijing and Washington agreed to a one-year trade truce, which includes tariff reductions and the temporary suspension of some restrictions, although Chinese authorities have insisted, in parallel, on the need to protect national economic security.</description><pubDate>2025-12-29 01:54:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Taipei | At least three people died in subway attack</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/21/taipe-pelo-menos-tres-pessoas-morreram-em-ataque-no-metro/</link><description>At least three people died and five were injured following an attack in the Taipei subway, the Taiwanese capital's fire chief announced Friday, adding that the suspect also died. The attacker wore a mask and was armed with a knife when he threw “five or six Molotov cocktails, or smoke grenades” at Taipei's main metro station, the fire chief explained in statements to the France-Presse news agency.
According to local authorities, the incident began in the underground passage of Taipei Main Station at around 5:30 pm when the suspect threw several smoke bombs as a distraction before heading with a knife along the avenue that connects this station to Zhongshan.
The mayor of Taipei, Chiang Wan-an, told the press that the suspect apparently “committed suicide by jumping from a building to escape his arrest” and that one of the victims died while trying to prevent the attack at Central station, the main subway station in the capital of Taiwan.
One of the victims died from injuries caused by the sharp weapon and a second died from a cardio-respiratory arrest caused by the grenades thrown by the attacker, according to the official CNA news agency.
A previous report showed at least eight injured. The attacker was identified by the CNA agency as a 27-year-old man wanted for ignoring a military recruitment order, according to Spanish news agency Europa Press.</description><pubDate>2025-12-21 01:22:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Gaza | Unicef ​​concerned about possible public health crisis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/21/gaza-unicef-preocupada-com-possivel-crise-de-saude-publica/</link><description>Unicef ​​is concerned about the possibility of a public health crisis in Gaza and children dying from hypothermia, given the catastrophic situation caused by the cold and rain that has been recorded. “The situation in recent days has been really horrible for children here in the Gaza Strip, for several reasons,” said Unicef ​​communications director, Jonathan Crickx, in an interview with the Lusa agency, from the south of the Palestinian enclave.
“There was a storm and there is still very strong rain and winds, which means that all the tents are wet, some of them completely flooded,” he said, adding that the situation affects 750,000 to one million displaced people, most of them people who have already had to move several times and who practically only have what they were wearing when they fled.
“We have many children who only have one or two changes of clothes and are living in makeshift tents, made of plastic or canvas, and the mattresses where they sleep are wet, the clothes are wet, the blankets are wet, the tents are wet”, described Jonathan Crickx.
The situation “is extremely serious”, said the head of Unicef, who is carrying out his fifth aid mission in Gaza. “Children, especially babies, can die from hypothermia”, he highlighted, adding that the temperature at night is around 8º Celsius.
On the other hand, hygiene and sanitation conditions, combined with the fact that many children have suffered from hunger in recent months, make it “very conducive to the spread of water-borne diseases”, he said, admitting that the organization is concerned about the possibility of a public health crisis.
"It's a big concern because families often have to choose between buying soap or buying food. Also because there are not enough bathrooms, not enough toilets, there is a lot of rubbish everywhere because the whole waste management system is not working as efficiently as it used to", explained Jonathan Crickx.
"There are a lot of open sewers, sometimes next to the tents, and, with the water, it floods everything, along with garbage. So, yes, it is very worrying. We are very, very worried about the appearance and spread of water-borne diseases", he reiterated. Although he guarantees that Unicef ​​is working hard to pump out the dirty water and restore the pipes, Jonathan Crickx warned that “there is a lot of work ahead”, because “the level of destruction is immense”.
Given the situation, “a huge effort is needed from the international community”, warned the official. “Even with the ceasefire [in force since October 10], the situation is absolutely dramatic for thousands and thousands of children”, he said, noting that “the ceasefire is far from perfect”.
Insufficient help
Still, Jonathan Crinckx considers that the agreement between Israel and the Islamist group Hamas “brought a little relief to the children” and allowed humanitarian organizations to take more things to the Gaza Strip.
"We managed to bring 250,000 'kits' of warm clothing [each 'kit' consists of a sweater, shoes, a hat and a scarf] to protect children from winter conditions, which is not bad. We also managed to bring tarpaulins, which some people are using to create shelters, in addition to 7,000 tents and around 500,000 to 600,000 blankets", he said.
However, he warned, “this is still not enough because the scale of needs, especially for those families living in tents, is enormous.” On the other hand, there are still items that cannot be taken to Gaza, such as large excavators, heavy machines for removing tons of rubbish and school supplies.
“Notebooks, pencils, rulers and erasers have not been allowed in the Gaza Strip for two years because education is not considered a critical need”, lamented the director of communications at Unicef, noting that education is a latent concern among the population. “I have met many mothers here in Gaza and, as soon as their children's basic needs are met, the first thing they ask is when the schools will reopen,” he reported.
“Education is fundamental and it is very important that children leave the streets and can build a future for themselves”, argued the Unicef ​​official, recalling that “education levels were very good in Gaza before the war”. The Gaza Strip was the target of a polar storm last week that killed at least 11 people, in addition to leaving several others injured and damaging tents and buildings.
The storm caused houses to collapse and damaged dozens of tents used by displaced people. The human rights organization Amnesty International lamented the situation, which it attributed to “Israel's continued restrictions on the entry of essential materials to repair vital infrastructure”, as stated in a statement released this week.</description><pubDate>2025-12-21 01:21:10</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korea | President regretted worsening of the crisis with the North</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/21/coreia-do-sul-presidente-lamentou-agravamento-da-crise-com-o-norte/</link><description>South Korean President Lee Jae-myung defended a patient diplomatic approach to North Korea on Friday, acknowledging that the crisis in relations between the two countries has worsened.
In a meeting with officials from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and the Ministry of Unification, the South Korean president said that in the past Seoul and Pyongyang pretended to be enemies, but that lately, he stressed, they seem to be turning into “real enemies”.
The head of state's statements came three days after South Korean and North American authorities held a series of discussions in Seoul with the aim of reassessing joint policy towards North Korea. On the other hand, the talks generated internal tensions within the South Korean Executive, according to sources from the official Yonhap news agency.
The Ministry of Unification, responsible for affairs between the two Koreas, objected to the talks led by diplomats from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, in a situation that allegedly constituted a question of jurisdiction. “It seems that this entire current situation stems from political ambitions”, criticized the South Korean President.
For Lee Jae-myung, it is necessary to communicate, dialogue, cooperate and fight for coexistence and prosperity, lamenting what he considered a lack of space for consensus capable of resolving internal tensions in Seoul. In the same statement, the South Korean President emphasized the role of the Ministry of Unification as the main negotiator.</description><pubDate>2025-12-21 01:19:44</pubDate></item><item><title>WHO | Indian PM highlights consensus on traditional medicine</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/21/oms-pm-indiano-destaca-consenso-sobre-medicina-tradicional/</link><description>More than 100 countries were represented in New Delhi by politicians, sector professionals and indigenous leaders to discuss the promotion of Traditional Medicine in global health systems. Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi closed the second World Health Organization (WHO) Global Summit on Traditional Medicine on Friday by highlighting the “consensus reached on several important issues”.
Modi considered that this consensus reflects “the strength of global partnerships”, according to a statement from his office cited by the Spanish news agency EFE. The head of the Indian government also highlighted that “boosting research, increasing the use of digital technology in traditional medicine and creating reliable regulatory frameworks at a global level will significantly strengthen” this type of medicine.
The summit, with the theme “Restoring Balance for People and the Planet”, began on Wednesday and brought together policymakers, scientists, professionals and indigenous leaders from more than 100 countries in New Delhi, to debate the integration of traditional medicine (TM) into health systems based on scientific criteria.
Science reinforced
According to the summit's online page, participants committed, in the Delhi Declaration on Traditional Medicine, to strengthening the scientific evidence base of TM, expanding investment in research infrastructures and increasing the number of professionals in the field, as well as promoting the WHO World Library of Traditional Medicine, the first of its kind, which was launched during the summit.
The declaration also includes commitments to support “equitable access to safe and effective products through appropriate regulatory mechanisms”, to guarantee their quality and safety, the integration of “safe and effective” MT into national health systems, respecting biodiversity.
Among the agreed actions, aligned with the objectives of the WHO's global strategy for traditional medicine 2025-2034, is also the promotion of the participation of communities and indigenous peoples.
“Member States and partners will translate the Delhi Declaration into time-bound national actions, supported by enhanced international collaboration, sharing of best practices, reporting and collective accountability.”</description><pubDate>2025-12-21 01:18:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Alfredo Gomes Dias, historian, on Rocha Vieira: “A historical figure, whether he wanted to or not”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/20/alfredo-gomes-dias-historiador-sobre-rocha-vieira-uma-figura-historica-quer-quisesse-ou-nao/</link><description>Launched on Thursday in Porto, with the seal of War and Peace, “Macau: The Last Transition – Vasco Rocha Vieira (1991–1999)” is the result of 20 years of work by historian Alfredo Gomes Dias. The work contains personal testimonies from Rocha Vieira and documented details of the last Portuguese Administration of Macau
Another book has just been released about Rocha Vieira and the last Portuguese administration of Macau. Tell me about the beginning of this project.
This project is more or less 20 years old, and began when I met Rocha Vieira, in 2005, to write a text for the book “Governadores de Macau” [published by Livros do Oriente in 2013]. In the midst of this, I discovered that there was a personal document fund of General Rocha Vieira, while governor. As a historian, I was excited by the idea. I offered to do a project with him, which we called a “report”. All the documents were at his home, in Lagoa, where he was from. They were then deposited in a space provided by Mafra City Council and between 2007 and 2013 I worked on this documentation. It was lonely and long work, because I had to organize 1,700 boxes of documentation and combine it with my work as a teacher. Rocha Vieira kept postponing the project, saying no, but in 2016 he told me to move forward with the “report”, the book. I finished the first version in 2021. It is a committed book, in the sense that it aims to give General Rocha Vieira's vision of what his Government was like. This is not an academic work.
He had complete access to the personal file.
He gave me the green light to consult all the documentation, I had no restrictions. Rocha Vieira told me one story or another in detail, gave me guidelines and revealed to me his concerns during his government. He told me some positions he had and then the different paths they took, and the entire book is built around the many conversations I had with the general, in which I also use documentation. We have a vision of everything that happened between 1991 and 1999 and the governor's actions in the different dimensions of the Administration, at an economic, social and political level, in relations with China and Lisbon, with Hong Kong, and then everything related to the work related to the transformation of the territory, such as the birth of Cotai and the major works that were carried out. There is also talk about the transition phase and the major themes, such as the entry of Chinese troops into Macau, the ceremony and how it was organized. Today we live in an immediate world, and at today's speed it's always strange to say that this book took 20 years to make.
Can we say that this is the first time that we have such a complete testimony of Rocha Vieira's vision of his Government?
The edited biography [Vasco Rocha Vieira – Todos os Portos a que Aguei] already gives many ideas about his concerns. What I ended up doing was not focusing so much on the general's entire life, but only on the years of the Government and developing as much as possible many of the issues that Pedro Vieira raised in this biography.
What subjects are then further developed in this new work?
I describe very well all the processes linked to Macau's transition, such as the issue of laws and localization, the need to translate them into Chinese. This was a gigantic job. Then I discuss the construction of major works, the birth of Cotai. All of this based on the original plans and plans designed for Cotai, where the beginning of the idea for this area is known. Any historian who, in the future, wants to study the transition process must necessarily go through this book. I don't want to say that what's there is definitive, because it never is. But it is important to have this basis and testimony, which is enriched and substantiated by documentation.
I imagine that the controversies of the Rocha Vieira Government are also in the book. The quarrel with Jorge Sampaio, the creation of the Fundação Oriente in Portugal. What is Rocha Vieira’s testimony about these two moments?
He always maintained the same speech compared to what he had already said publicly. There is a specific chapter on Fundação Oriente, where, with the support of documentation, an attempt is made to explain the process and why Rocha Vieira, when he arrived in Macau, felt the need to solve a problem that had been dragging on and which was important to overcome. It describes how he managed to resolve it, as it was an issue that was making dialogue with the Chinese authorities difficult. It explains how Rocha Vieira interacted with the different Governments of the [Portuguese] Republic and the different Presidents, the positions he took in order to guarantee what was his responsibility. While he was at the head of the Government, Rocha Vieira always tried to assert his views, and one of the interesting things is that I had access to copies of minutes of meetings of the State Council, in which Rocha Vieira presented his vision on the situation in Macau. It's an interesting contribution. But he explains that the way he spoke with President Mário Soares was completely different from the way he spoke with Jorge Sampaio. The institutional relationship changed, the way of attending a meeting was also different. This is explained, but without going into the personal side of the dispute.
Did Rocha Vieira leave Macau with a feeling of accomplishment?
I think he left Macau very convinced, and the entire transfer ceremony ends up giving us this image that Portugal left in the best possible way. We also have to think that we are talking about two completely different countries, and that one of them is giant. And that, despite this difference, it was possible to maintain an almost equal dialogue between two States to resolve, in the best way, a specific issue that was Macau. What surprised me most about Rocha Vieira's vision was that he changed the centrality of his vision to Macau.
In what sense?
In general, the Portuguese and the authorities spoke of Macau thinking about guaranteeing the transition process without jeopardizing Portugal's interests. And General Rocha Vieira reverses the terms of the issue, that is, to guarantee Macau's interests, with the idea that guaranteeing Macau's interests would be the same as guaranteeing Portugal's interests. It looks like the same thing, but it's not. This vision, for me, was surprising.
Why?
Because it went against what was the most common discourse among the authorities and people responsible for the Portuguese administration [of Macau]. This central idea ends up changing the way he organizes his Government, how he acts and the type of actions he triggers. They all had to do with this deep conviction, that, in the remaining years, a great development of Macau would be guaranteed, the affirmation of Portuguese culture, supporting institutions, or even with the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM), whose solution ended up not being the one he proposed. It turned out to be a minimalist option.
What, specifically, was Rocha Vieira’s position?
It was to ensure that the old Macau High School was the EPM, which would give the school a completely different dimension compared to [the current location]. It has nothing to do with it. He didn't just want a Portuguese school, but also a space where it was possible to develop cultural activities, create a cultural hub in Macau linked to Portugal, and with a much more dignified option than what was, later, the option of the Ministry of Education, in the figure of Marçal Grilo, who chose [the location] of the old Commercial School. Therefore, the focus has always been to guarantee and develop Macau's interests, its autonomy, and the airport issue was fundamental to guarantee Macau's autonomy. It was also intended that Macau would adhere to international agreements regarding respect for human rights. The idea was that, by managing to guarantee Macau's interests, thinking of the territory as part of China's second system, and that if we invested a lot in Macau, we would, naturally, be defending Portuguese interests and leaving a great legacy.
What was the most complex dossier for Rocha Vieira?
I think he had great regrets about the Ministry of Education's option for Portuguese schools. From the conversations I had with him [that's what it seemed to me]. Then there were the security issues, with the sects, which ended up being resolved. The years 1997 and 1998 were very critical moments in Macau, but as it always had good relations with the Chinese authorities, this led to China realizing the situation, starting to collaborate more with the Portuguese authorities in Macau, in order to control the problem.
About Cotai, how did the idea come about?
It arises in the context of the airport works, when it is realized that it would be relatively easy to mobilize the land that was associated with the airport works, taking advantage of that moment to make a connection and create, essentially, a second urban center in Macau. Cotai's initial plans had to do with urban space, green and industrial spaces. The entire plan was designed to bring together different areas, social spaces, such as schools or health, as if Cotai were a mini-city, so to speak, in the territory.
But who actually had the idea?
It was an idea from Rocha Vieira's Executive, developed with secretaries. The idea came from him, when he was faced with the issue of the works, and was then developed with the team. He was always concerned about developing things with the team, also ensuring continuity with what had been done before. When he talked to me, he was careful to say: “this didn't start with me”, or that this or that secretary had been fundamental for a certain job. He never wanted to take credit that wasn't his, and this is also a great recognition from previous governors.
Therefore, Cotai was not supposed to have so much area dedicated to the game.
From what I analyzed in the documents, there was no idea of ​​giving up such a large space for entertainment, with casinos. I think the initial vision for Cotai was a little more balanced, with housing, schools, health centers, green spaces. It was supposed to be a new urban space that would be created with all the services necessary to function, it wasn't just supposed to be games.
The moments in which Rocha Vieira clutches the flag to his chest, moved, will go down in history. Did he remember those moments with you?
Yes, but despite the historical dimension of his role, Rocha Vieira was not exactly aware of the historical role he was playing. He was there with a clear mission and objectives, without really thinking about the role he could have in the future. Once, when we were having lunch, I told him that we could put our work into perspective, but that he was going to become a historical figure in the history of Portugal, whether he wanted to or not. And the funny thing is that he looked at me with a face like he had never thought of that, with a very surprised look. In fact, it is unthinkable to take away his status as the last Portuguese governor in Macau in hundreds of years of history. On top of that, he was there for a long period [9 years], when most governors were there for three or four years.</description><pubDate>2025-12-20 04:01:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Christian Montag, UM Institute for Collaborative Innovation: “AI cannot imitate the human touch”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/17/christian-montag-instituto-de-inovacao-colaborativa-da-um-a-ia-nao-consegue-imitar-o-toque-humano/</link><description>Can artificial intelligence help combat loneliness? The issue was analyzed in a study by the University of Macau, led by academic Christian Montag. The director of the Institute for Collaborative Innovation emphasizes that AI tools “are not long-term solutions” on a psychological level
How can artificial intelligence (AI) help overcome feelings of loneliness, if social networks cannot achieve this goal?
The “needs and gratifications theory” states that technology can only be successful if its use satisfies human needs, such as, for example, the need for social interaction. With AI companions, whether as stand-alone products or integrated into social media platforms, we have reached a new level, because human beings start talking to an artificial person and not with another human person, as happens on social media. Specific problems arise with these new AI companions, in that there are overly pleasant and charming AI systems that do not challenge a person's biased views of the world. Furthermore, many people around the world have become overly dependent on these products, using them without critical reflection.
One of the conclusions of your study is that AI cannot, on its own, resolve feelings of loneliness. What steps in the investigation were followed to reach this conclusion?
There are well-conducted studies that show that interactions with AI companions can actually reduce feelings of loneliness. We do not doubt these results nor deny the potential that can arise from these interactions between humans and AI, as long as such systems are designed safely and when a human is not available. That said, we believe that these interactions between humans and AI do not represent a long-term solution.
Why?
This is due to the absence of social contact and the real presence of another human being when turning to AI companions based on large-scale language models, especially in moments of desperation. We have reviewed a vast literature that demonstrates that we need to take our evolutionary heritage seriously, with the real need for other human beings, particularly in the age of AI. Our perspective is based on many years of research in the area of ​​affective neuroscience. Still, it is clearly necessary to develop more new empirical studies that directly address interactions with AI and support this vision.
We run the risk of AI causing profound cognitive changes in people. To what extent? Can we change as human beings, especially when it comes to our need for others?
The same discussion arose with the appearance of smartphones. It is important to note that this oldest discussion has not yet been resolved: what happens or happened to our cognitive abilities when we began to permanently outsource the learning of telephone numbers, the guidance from A to B, among other tasks, to a machine? Recent research from MIT [Massachusetts Institute of Technology] suggests that the brain is less activated when using ChatGPT for writing tasks, compared to writing without such support. To me, this is not surprising and should not lead to moral panics. We have other more urgent problems, such as when real difficulties arise when inequalities in society increase, this is because some people use AI and others do not invest in this area.
What are the concrete impacts?
Some people may soon become very, very productive, while those who are not educated to use AI properly will not be able to keep up. Interestingly, we have observed in recent research that people with a deep learning style are more willing to engage with AI to become more productive. As for the question of whether we have changed in relation to our need for others, I highly doubt that, as these evolutionary impulses are genetically anchored in our species and we cannot simply eliminate them. Social needs are an essential part of what it means to be human.
Could these cognitive changes, if they occur, be more significant in young people than in adults, for example?
Interesting question. We know, from some studies on attitudes towards AI, that younger users tend to have more positive views about AI and, therefore, are more likely to adopt it in their daily lives. However, we are currently observing something quite problematic, such as the fact that AI is often eliminating jobs for young people just leaving university. Thus, AI appears to make it more difficult to enter the job market after obtaining a university degree. In other words, a lack of work experience makes things difficult for many young people. In the end, this could also lead to young people's perception of AI becoming more negative soon.
How should governments legislate or adopt policies to promote healthy acceptance and use of AI in society and schools?
We see very different approaches around the world to respond to the AI ​​revolution. I am German and, in Europe, we are seeing strong regulatory efforts with the so-called Artificial Intelligence Regulation (Artificial Intelligence Act). Personally, I am not convinced that the current European regulatory scheme is well planned, as I think it is too strict and, in some points, uses legally undefined terms, although I applaud the aim of promoting reliable AI and trying to reduce harm. I think the current regulation of AI in the European Union could go too far and end up harming the European economy by stifling much-needed innovation. But there are real dangers associated with AI and some regulation is needed.
What dangers?
I'm talking, for example, about the unregulated fusion between biotechnology and AI that could result in harm if people start to “create” new viruses in their backyards. I find Singapore's approach based on lifelong learning as a response to the AI ​​revolution very interesting. The Singapore Government offers its citizens the possibility of obtaining an academic degree in AI from the age of 40, with financial support from the State itself. What I like about this approach is that we need to remind people that it is also their responsibility to acquire new skills throughout their lives. This mentality must be instilled from an early age in schools.
In what areas of our lives can large-scale language models (LLMs) do more good than harm?
There are many routine and repetitive tasks where AI will be really useful to humans. However, we know from scientific literature that humans experience what is called “algorithm aversion”: in some areas of our lives, people do not like AI playing a role. For example, when we talk about couples therapy, people clearly prefer to talk to a human being than an AI system. Perhaps the closer we come to our evolutionary heritage in terms of caring for each other, the more the role of AI must be carefully monitored and reflected upon if we want it to have a place there. Personally, I wouldn't want to see my child being taken care of in kindergarten by an AI-powered robot.
How should psychology adapt to AI, given the growing number of people using it for this purpose?
There are different perspectives on this topic. Firstly, not everyone knows that psychology is a discipline that relies heavily on data. Therefore, psychology students are trained to become excellent data scientists. In this context, it is logical that our discipline adopts AI as a data analysis tool. However, I think it speaks to how psychologists view the increasing use of AI in human relationships. As with many things, this is complex. If AI enables better human communication, such as improving hearing aids for people with hearing problems, that is very welcome. If AI replaces human relationships, from my perspective it will cause problems. As we exposed in our most recent work, AI cannot currently successfully imitate human social touch or the real presence of another person.
At the Center for Cognitive and Brain Science at the University of Macau, what are the main projects developed in this area?
We have unique research opportunities at the University of Macau to study interactions between humans and AI, using neuroscientific techniques. I hope we can publish very interesting discoveries in the near future.
Humanity still lives here
Recently published in the scientific journal “Trends and Cognitive Sciences”, the article “Can AI really help solve the loneliness epidemic?” [Can AI Really Help Solve the Loneliness Epidemic?] counts Christian Montag, associate director of the Institute for Collaborative Innovation at the University of Macau (UM) as lead author, followed by academics Michiel Spapé, associate professor at the Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences at UM, and Benjamin Becker, professor at the Department of Psychology at the University of Hong Kong, as co-authors.
According to a press release released by UM regarding this investigation, one of the main conclusions is that AI “will probably not be a long-term solution to human loneliness”. Quoted in this note, Christian Montag stated that “if a person is lonely, they long for the physical presence of someone close to them”, and this “is very difficult to imitate with the available chatbots”.
"The major language models operate primarily through text communication. Clearly, this is not enough to provide lonely people with the best cure for loneliness: direct in-person support," he stated. According to the World Health Organization, “loneliness affects one in six people worldwide”, having been “identified as a global public health concern”.
Despite the sign, the study points to a positive side of this universe, noting that “AI technology has significant potential to support human beings in moments of psychological crisis, especially when human intervention is not available”. However, “the researchers argue that the technology must be made safer before it can be used in this context”, emphasizing “the importance of remembering our evolutionary heritage and the need for genuine interpersonal connections”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-17 01:04:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Luís Bernardino, academic: “We need to define a defense cooperation strategy” for the CPLP</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/25/luis-bernardino-academico-precisamos-definir-uma-estrategia-de-cooperacao-defesa-para-a-cplp/</link><description>The book “25 Years of Defense Cooperation at CPLP” was released in 2023 in digital format and, two years later, reached the printed version. Luís Bernardino, co-author linked to the Universidade Autónoma de Lisboa, highlights positive developments since the creation of the Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries, despite inaction and controversies with Equatorial Guinea
“25 Years of Defense Cooperation in the CPLP [Community of Portuguese Speaking Countries]” was released as an e-book and is now available in print. Why edit this book?
This book talks about the 25 years of cooperation in the CPLP defense area and is written by me, together with a colleague from Brazil, Camila Rizzi. It results from a research project developed at the CPLP Strategic Analysis Center, based in Mozambique. It has the CPLP defense component and makes strategic reflection on this topic. Due to the fact that 25 years of cooperation have passed in this area, we wanted to carry out an evaluation and the book so that it would remain in the history of the organization. In 2023, there were no financial conditions to publish the book on paper as we wanted, and it was now launched on November 18th, in Maputo.
There is criticism regarding the effective action of the CPLP. Do you consider that this organism has grown sustainably?
The assessment I make is in the area of ​​defense. When the CPLP was created, cooperation in the area of ​​defense was not included in the initial six areas. This area only emerged in 1998. The CPLP was born with six main areas – culture, language, political-diplomatic concentration – and currently has 26 areas of cooperation, which is proof that it has grown in a sustained manner. Obviously, with ups and downs, situations have become easier over these almost 30 years. But what stands out in this book, in the area of ​​defense, is that there was a very consolidated and participated growth. In these 25 years, a lot of interesting things have been done and the evaluation is positive.
And the future?
We need to define a defense cooperation strategy and what we want for the CPLP in this area over the next 25 years. This is the challenge we face, of greater activity and initiative, so that cooperation and defense can be strategic in what is cooperation within States. So that it can be more visible and effectively allow for growth, participation and development, or even greater commitment, in regional contexts.
But looking at the past, present and future, what has the dynamic been like in the defense area?
The book shows a certain dynamic of substantial constitutional growth in the first phase. Then there were very interesting developments, with some protocols and cooperation at the level of the Armed Forces, but there is still a lot to do, namely looking at the area of ​​defense cooperation as a strategic area.
The global geopolitical system appears to be changing very quickly, following a multipolar path. Should the CPLP have another role in this context, with actors such as China, Russia or the United States?
The CPLP is not a multilateral instrument, it is not an organization of that level. We have to place the CPLP at the level of the Commonwealth, for example, of organizations at a cultural, linguistic level, of partnership between countries, of concern for development. What I usually say is that the CPLP is a good diplomatic communication instrument, a soft power in areas related to conflict management and prevention. Let us not expect there to be armed forces, or an army, from the CPLP. This body is one of dialogue and cooperation. What we do, in terms of defense, is exactly that, create partnerships so that there are mechanisms for responding to disasters, to provide training capacity for the armed forces. There are even those who ask the question: why did the CPLP not intervene in Cabo Delgado, in Mozambique, on the issue of terrorism?
And why?
Because the CPLP is not a hard power mechanism, it has no capacity, doctrine, logistics, mandate or viability to be used in combat operations. And CPLP Member States are very aware that we are a very good mechanism for cooperation, partnership and development, with contributions to culture and language. Therefore, the CPLP will not intervene in the conflict between Russia and Ukraine, because that is not its area, nor does it have mechanisms for this dynamic.
Is the existence of the CPLP justified?
I think so, obviously, because, as I said, the CPLP is a very good instrument in terms of cooperation, the dissemination of the Portuguese language, of history. The fact is that we have around 350 million people who speak Portuguese. We have 30 countries that are associated observers, such as Ukraine, Chile, and Portuguese culture is represented in this organization. Each country has what it wants from the CPLP and gives it the importance it thinks it should give, and this depends on the foreign policy of each State. But I think the CPLP makes a lot of sense in the world we live in, and does so as a multilateral representative of language, culture, cooperation between Portuguese-speaking states, and those that ultimately have some affinity [with the Portuguese-speaking world]. The Macau issue is very specific to this organization.
Macau has the role of a commercial platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries, and China has an agenda for Lusophony.
Before 1999 Macau had its own status within the CPLP, as it was administered by Portuguese. There was a Joint Declaration that allowed Macau, not being a Member State, to have, in a certain way, a protocol [with the CPLP]. When it became a Macao SAR, things changed and it lost that connection status, and Macau is not a member of the CPLP, and obviously cannot be. Neither does China, and it cannot be. Therefore, there is an associated observer status here that arises for countries, international and regional organizations, and even territorial entities with their own administration, which is also not quite the case in Macau. The territory is in limbo, between having a very strong history linked to Lusofonia, and having an administration very linked to China, which gives it, in my perspective, two dynamics.
In what sense?
Macau is a fundamental element in the connection between the CPLP countries and China. For all reasons, but due to the issue of language, history, and its representation, it is a fundamental actor in this cooperation. Macau must effectively be seen as a partner and as a gateway for China to Portuguese-speaking countries. This is what, in a way, is already happening, and this is what the CPLP will be paying attention to, in this relationship in which Macau has a special status. Whether we like it or not, it has an impact. Macau is an attractive factor in facilitating relations between China and Angola, Portugal or Brazil.
Does Equatorial Guinea's stay in the CPLP raise questions of credibility?
I agree with you. In these 30 years, it has been one of the main difficult moments in creating consensus. I remember that Equatorial Guinea was admitted in 2014, but there was already a process in the previous analysis phase. There was always an extension, year after year, and it was difficult to reach a consensus within the CPLP countries. In 2014, there was a summit in Timor-Leste and, through the action of Brazil and Angola, there was, in a way, a lot of pressure for Equatorial Guinea to join. But there are two principles, for better and for worse, that justify Equatorial Guinea's presence in the CPLP.
What are…
The first argument is that, in fact, Equatorial Guinea has Portuguese as its official language in its Constitution, despite us knowing that the Portuguese language, for example, covers four or five percent of society as a whole, and I am already being quite generous. But there is a commitment from the Equatorial Guinea authorities to develop Portuguese as a working language and there is a historical connection to Portuguese culture and Lusophony. Another criterion is the promise that, in the next constitutional review, a commitment will be made to abolish the death penalty. As for Portuguese, it's something that takes generations, it's not done from one year to the next. Not even in the next 10 or 15 years will we have Portuguese perfectly implemented. There is some shyness, a commitment, in a way. As for the death penalty, the fact is that, it seems, some change has been achieved. There has never been a death penalty action again [since accession]. And there is hope that, in the next constitutional review, this fact will be abolished from the Constitution and that it may, effectively, cease to exist. As a member of the CPLP, these changes will be easier and more visible and, in the future, Equatorial Guinea can effectively assume CPLP status taking these premises into account. I don't know if it will happen, I leave here a reluctance, and this is a challenging moment for the CPLP itself. Work needs to be done from within, so that Equatorial Guinea can be at the same level as other countries, especially in these two areas.
What is certain is that there remains a certain lack of transparency regarding what is happening in the country.
We are aware that Equatorial Guinea has major problems with issues of democratic legitimacy and elections. There are a series of situations that we recognize are not perfectly adequate given the status of CPLP countries. I think there is hope that things can change, an attempt to create space for Portuguese to grow within Equatorial Guinea, and also a commitment to greater openness and participation. What is a fact is that Equatorial Guinea has participated in CPLP meetings, and I have participated in some. In international situations we have to be pragmatic, and we hope that, just because Equatorial Guinea is in the CPLP, this can help Guinea itself to develop some mechanical gestures.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Timor-Leste / Independence – Mari Alkatiri: Proclamation was anticipated by the Indonesian military presence</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/timor-leste-independencia-mari-alkatiri-proclamacao-foi-antecipada-pela-presenca-militar-indonesia/</link><description>Interview by Isabel Marisa Serafim, from the Lusa agency
The leader of the Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin), Mari Alkatiri, said that the unilateral proclamation of independence was scheduled for December 1, 1975, but was brought forward because Indonesian troops were already in the territory.
“It was initially scheduled for December 1st”, said Mari Alkatiri, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, which is marked on Friday, and of the Indonesian occupation, nine days later, on December 7th.
In November, Mari Alkatiri went on a “safari” through several African countries, mainly the Portuguese-speaking African Countries (PALOP), which involved participating in the declaration of Angola’s independence on November 11, 1975.
"After this 'tour', this African 'safari', I returned to the country. At the time I was in Maputo to prepare my return and I received a call from Nicolau Lobato not to return, because we needed to have someone outside the country", he recalled, highlighting that he did not follow the order from the then vice-president of Fretilin.
“So I returned to Dili on the 22nd or 23rd of November and the central committee and military political committee were meeting at the current headquarters of the National Police of Timor-Leste, which was the provisional headquarters of Fretilin, and the proclamation for December 1st was being discussed”, he explained. On November 28, Mari Alkatiri, then 25 years old, recalled that Nicolau Lobato came to her house and said that it was necessary to proclaim independence that day.
"We both left in his car for Lahane where Xavier do Amaral [former president of Fretilin] was and we conveyed this to Xavier Amaral, who clearly said to wait another three or four days. We said there was no time to wait and we decided to make the proclamation that day in the afternoon", he said.
"Fortunately, not only was the Constitution ready, but also the flag was ready. It was my mother who sewed the flag. There were minimum conditions for the proclamation of independence", stated the current secretary general of Fretilin, who also wrote the text of the proclamation.
“When I start talking about these days it’s not just memory, I actively participated in the unilateral proclamation of independence, although people try to cut out my photo, politics, but the truth is that there is only one person still alive who actively participated in the proclamation 50 years ago, that’s me”, he highlighted.
In the first Timorese Government, led by Nicolau Lobato and which only lasted nine days, Mari Alkatiri was appointed Minister of State for Political Affairs. Nocolau Lobato led the fight against the Indonesian occupation and was assassinated in December 1978. The restoration of independence took place on May 20, 2002, after a referendum for self-determination on August 30, 1999 and 24 years of resistance against Indonesia.
A question of egos
Mari Alkatiri also stated, in the same interview, that “egos” are preventing Timor-Leste from overcoming the challenges and that a more democratic, inclusive and comprehensive leadership culture is needed.
"If we managed it at the time, with all the difficulties, with all the challenges to overcome, at almost the speed of light, why can't we today? That's the question, the question of the cause. When the cause unites, the journey can go on, with many setbacks here and there, but we will succeed and we will win", said Mari Alkatiri in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, which marks this Friday.
Asked about the reason for no union, the leader of the Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin) ​​said it was “egos”.
“I am following the budget debate, when we continue to think about State matters in a 'cantin' way, we are not going anywhere”, criticized the former East Timorese Prime Minister, whose party chose to abstain in the final global vote on the State Budget.
Regarding criticism of the current government's options, Mari Alkatiri said she did not know if there was ever an option. "I don't see a strategy. There are some successes here and there, tries here and there, but there is no strategy, but there is a lot of support for strategic planning, strategic investment, but I don't see it", he stated.
“There is a need for a much more democratic, much more inclusive, very comprehensive leadership culture, with a sense of mission and vision for the future”, highlighted the secretary general of Fretilin. The party leader also warned not to wait for the “bomb to explode”.
“The delay bomb is there, the time bomb is there, I hope we don’t have to, after that, apologize for the truth, after the bomb goes off”, he highlighted. Asked if the “bomb” is dissatisfaction, the former prime minister said: “complete”.
"A country that after 24 years of restoring independence, with the means it had to work, why did it fail? Lack of sense of inclusion. We are building a State, we talk about the Democratic Rule of Law, is that true? Or oligarchic", he asked.
The new generations
Still in relation to young people, who represent the majority of the approximately 1.4 million inhabitants of Timor-Leste, Mari Alkatiri said that they feel lost. "Young people are naturally more generous when they are more considered, or more rebellious, when they are revolted. There are two facets here in youth, one of generosity when they embrace a cause, the other is a much more violent reaction of confrontation", he said.
Pointing out that more than 70% of the population is under 35 years old, Mari Alkatiri warned that those “two generations have already been sacrificed” due to “poor quality” education and “increasingly worse health” and “no prospects”. “Now, we all say that oil money will run out, I see that for the Government, the alternative to oil is oil”, he said.
In September, the capital of the Timor-Leste Petroleum Fund was US$18.95 billion (€16.4 billion). “We kept dreaming about Sunrise and as I usually say while we dream about Sunrise, we will have the ‘sunset’, because there is no politics, there are no plans, there are no programs”, he added.
Mari Alkatiri was referring to the Greater Sunrise gas field, located 150 kilometers from Timor-Leste and 450 kilometers from Darwin, whose project has been mired in an impasse, with Dili defending the construction of a gas pipeline to the south of the country, and Woodside, the consortium's second largest partner, leaning towards a connection to the existing unit in Darwin.
The consortium is made up of the Timorese company Timor Gap (56.56%), the operator Woodside Energy (33.44%) and Osaca Gás (10.00%). The Government of Timor-Leste announced on Saturday the signing of a cooperation agreement with the Australian Woodside Energy for studies to process and export gas to the country.
Missing discussions
The secretary general of the Revolutionary Front of Independent Timor-Leste (Fretilin), Mari Alkatiri, defended the need for “all together” to discuss what failed in the last 24 years, after the restoration of independence in May 2002.
"There is a lot of talk about new paradigms and the old paradigm, we are ready to sit down together to discuss the old paradigm, why did it fail? No", said the former Timorese prime minister, in an interview with Lusa on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the unilateral declaration of independence, which marks this Friday.
For Mari Alkatiri, everyone contributed with “their positive part, with their negative part”, but it is necessary to understand the failures in “individual terms”, in “collective terms” and there be “responsibility”. Asked by Lusa about the reasons why there is no such discussion, the leader of the Timorese opposition replied that a “leader who cannot sit at the table is not a leader”.
"The leader must know that there is a time to sit at the table. I made proposals. When I returned in 2018, I said 'my vote is so that the people can win', I didn't tell Fretilin to win. The message was clear, it was time for us all to think together. I ran the campaign saying Fretilin wins, Xanana wins", stated Mari Alkatiri.
The Fretilin leader said the response has been “revenge, hate”. "In such a way that to take revenge on me, it affects hundreds of people, families. If it's me, come and talk to me, you don't have to harm others, but this is a specific issue", he stated, referring to the Timorese Prime Minister, XAnana Gusmão. The fundamental issue, continued Maria Alkatiri, is “to have a sense of mission, a vision of the future and to have a common cause”.
"What is crucial is knowing all the money that was spent, what was done. A balance of collective and individual performance. When we were waging war, we knew what we wanted, to restore independence, 24 years after the restoration of independence we don't know where we are going", lamented the leader.
Mari Alkatiri also said he was “very concerned” about the report by the United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC), which warned on September 11 of the proliferation of criminal networks in Oecussi, a Timorese enclave on the Indonesian side of the island of Timor, highlighting that recent investigations show contamination of the region.
"It is already being absorbed by the mafia cartel, who are coming here in all their strength. We have closed kiosks and we think we are fighting the mafia. I am very worried," he said. For the future, Mari Alkatiri stated that he will continue to fight, but to “create critical mass”.
"My fight now is not the concern with electoral cycles, but how I can actually create a true critical mass in Timor-Leste. Let's end blindness, many of our academic intellectuals get pregnant through their ears, but they don't get pregnant", he highlighted.
The Fretilin leader also told everyone in his generation that it is time to put “egos” aside and start “thinking together”, highlighting that they have another five years to do so. “The next term of governance must be the product of understanding if we really want this country to move forward”, stated Mari Alkatiri, highlighting that the Timorese people deserve “much more and much better” than what has been given to date.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 17:33:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist activist, 34 years old, physical engineer, Romani national. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, gentle humor and a smile that leaves no one indifferent.
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and gypsies – in particular – have lived in Portugal for around five centuries. What happens so that gypsy communities continue to be “on the margins” of so-called society? 
We need to change the model of society. This is extremely stratified, placing people in subordinate positions to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the ‘margin’ of society is in fact an intrinsic place within it, which belongs to it. In other words, gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in a status of inferiority compared to white people, without the right to human dignity, to found a family, to choose their own language and religion, expropriated of any and all cultural and material rights. A place built and maintained to this day by genocidal and ethnocidal violence and persecution. In 1463, Vasco Gitano was granted an estate. In 1521, the gitanos, or gypsies, were already used as a reference for everything that is considered bad in the model of society. The “counter-example” compared to white that would stand out in a positive way. The ‘angel’ and the ‘demon’; the ‘other’, the enemy; the one against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending oneself, having weapons, any type of property, and the right to stay.
And is it because they are denied the right to stay that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country today?
Yes, without a doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, by prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Roma people, because they are Roma; and also through the gentrification process.
I read the results of a survey by the European Union Agency for Fundamental Rights, where it is said that approximately 80% of Roma respondents live below the risk of poverty threshold in their country; one in three gypsies lives in a house without running water; one in three Roma belongs to a family in which someone went to bed hungry at least once in the previous month; and 50% of Roma aged between 6 and 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historic persecution that continues. There is no impoverishment that does not have an external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation is imposed on the basis of violence. As early as 1648, D João IV, the Restorer, prohibited ‘giving or renting houses to gypsies’. The same D João IV who achieved the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 Knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who died defending Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Among prohibitions on staying, “that gypsies do not enter the kingdom and those who are in it leave” (D João III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, banishment to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with penalties of flogging, mutilation and death, systematically carried out to this day (still in 2011 the Municipal Council of Faro wanted to ban gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working for others (no one employs gypsy workers, and those who do do so in complete precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without rights and dignified conditions). They are unable to remain dependent on self-employment, they are unable to invest, due to extreme expropriation. They become dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it's like to live in pure neoliberalism, get to know the lives of gypsies. The reality of these is paradigmatic of the aggression and lack of protection that the “lords” are willing to go to, for their own benefit.
The gentlemen we are talking about, is it economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group has been in power since it instituted the current system of domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to put an end to ‘lords’ and establish a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model in which we live leads the gypsy community (and beyond) to economic exclusion, removing them from access to the consumption of products or excluding them from their production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; to education and consequently the social exclusion seen in the inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, healthcare, etc. How does a gypsy child feel when they realize they are not part of the whole? Children who never see themselves represented, not in films, not in books, not in cartoons, not even in an advertisement eating cereal, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is it a priori condemnation?
That's really the question. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, on the contrary, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', an Orwellian term, and people are under duress. Which concentration and extermination camp. In fact, the Nazi concentration camps are a more visual embodiment of what is called 'social exclusion' and, as here, they were not an 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are kept by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. Just like in the Nazi concentration camps.
And what you listed as an example of the ‘consequence’ of this ‘exclusion’, is in fact the means by which this exclusion also happens and is maintained. Gypsy people are outside the cinemas, either as consumers or producers (but they go to the cinema). They are outside of school, education and the Academy. Either as ‘users’ or as producers (but they go to school and are at the basis of the construction of knowledge and academic and scientific debates).
Even in the attack on the gypsy child's self-confidence, we speak of a mechanism for maintaining this situation. But gypsy people respond very well: with gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this modern model of society. And they resist and counter the power of domination and insist on being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the Academy, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you mean to say there is collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, gypsy people rolled up their sleeves and once again showed proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned by watching and doing. And here, it is again women who jump to the front line, show their face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or sons, and launch themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as app-based work (transport or couriers). In housing, in a pandemic context in which evictions were not stopped – as the law itself should and dictates – residents did not stop organizing and fighting against unfair evictions and demanding dignity in housing; residents associations allied in their action with other housing and anti-racist organizations.
It is also worth noting how they reinvented themselves and intensified to collect and distribute food items and mask/alcohol gel kits to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non-gypsies. In the anti-racist fight, new movements emerged and their actions intensified through social media. People who had never organized or become active before began their first steps in activism, joining this path of gypsy and anti-racist organization and popular action. People forget, or don't want to appreciate, but gypsy action has helped to determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large numbers and determined electoral results in the 2017 local councils, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the Presidential elections, second place was decided by an amount equivalent to the estimated number of gypsy voters. Apart from the non-gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-building power in opinion spaces, in local media, on social networks and in party and institutional political disputes. And most importantly, in popular action and in alliances with other social movements. We never stopped fighting by all means and we continued to resist.
On the other hand, there is more and more hate speech, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about that?
To begin with, these speeches are historical and European. They are neither current nor “extreme right-wing”. These speeches have been adopted and delivered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by various representatives of the center-right, conservatives, center-left, liberals, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-gypsy rhetoric has always worked in Portugal, as it is the most white-natured rhetoric. That is, it allows the creation and recognition of “white” as the superior of all. And thus please the white electorate who, when they feel good, compensate with their vote. Even if the policies implemented by your elected officials harm you even more.
Finally, I would like you to talk a little about your personal experience and how you became an activist?
I studied, fought for my studies, made alliances, graduated, and entered the “formal precarious” job market. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society into a better one. This certainty, combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering, makes anyone want to have a transformative attitude. I wanted to be an ‘inventor’ (physical engineer) and an anti-racist activist. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with other people, in turn, with other studies, training and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
This gives rise to two types of actions: transformative and survival. The fight against hate speech appears as survival, but its defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that – as people who want a better world – we have to do, namely work to criminalize hate speech; condemn and ban organizations with racist speeches and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logic that organizes Power and manages community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, from petitions to demonstrations. And we need more.
In addition to being a member of the SOS RACISMO movement, I participate in the Podcast “Viemos Para Ficar”, with Mamadou Ba and Joseph da Silva. And if everything goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the “Cigana Initiative” project, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-gypsyism, denouncing historical and ongoing genocide and working towards a new societal project. Also with new projects in the pipeline. And finally, there are always voluntary actions, without an organization, where I try to share what I discovered about Anti-Gypsyism and Romani history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and employment precariousness, racialized individuals, especially Roma nationals, are the most vulnerable to Covid-19. It is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which puts profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP | Unanimity regarding “Super Pole” in GT</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/05/gp-unanimidade-quanto-a-super-pole-nos-gt/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA) should continue to focus on the “Super Pole” system for the ninth FIA GT World Cup, if this race is once again included in the program of the 73rd Macau Grand Prix next year
For the first time, in last November's edition, the ten fastest in Qualifying 1 had 20 minutes to prepare for the first “Super Pole” in the history of the FIA ​​GT World Cup, in which, in reverse order of times, each driver entered the track alone for one out lap, two timed laps and one return lap, with one-minute intervals between competitors and the possibility of using a new set of tires. The best time obtained between the two timed laps determined Qualification 2 “Super Pole”, which defined the starting grid for the Classified Race.
Following the success of this initiative, the international federation intends to continue applying it in the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup, having even produced a promotional video to confirm this. Lutz Leif Linden, President of the GT Commission and the FIA ​​Constructors' Commission, admits that this is something “very exciting for the spectators as well as the drivers”.
Present in Macau during the Grand Prix, the influential Stéphane Ratel, CEO of SRO Motorsports Group, co-organizer of the Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup, also agrees with the measure, highlighting that it represents "an additional challenge and one that works. At SRO we do this on a global level. In the biggest events, like the 24 Hours of Spa, we have a 'Super Pole', and it is something we like."
Riders and brands agree
Drivers and brands were equally impressed with this first experience on the territory's streets. “Macau is already special and I think that, with this format, we had something even more special”, recalled Antonio Fuoco, the driver who gave Ferrari its first in Macau since 1995.
Ferdinando Cannizzo, head of Ferrari's Competizioni GT, reinforces the idea, highlighting the technical advantage when the challenge comes down to the driver and the circuit, without external interference. “Without cars, without traffic, you can really focus on your strengths and try to maximize the car’s performance”, said the Cavallino Rampante brand representative.
This qualification system, an important moment of the weekend given the difficulty of overtaking on the Guia Circuit, also adds an element of uncertainty and elevates the spectacle. Stefan Gugger, responsible for the development of Lamborghini's competition cars, said that, in his opinion, "it's an improvement for our fans. We can really see the performance of the driver and the car, which also represents a good challenge for the team."
Porsche, one of the brands that most advocated the mandatory introduction of expensive torque sensors in this race, was also one of the main drivers of the “Super Pole”. “I believe the new format is a real step forward,” said Thomas Laudenbach, Vice President of Porsche Motorsport. "It allows the drivers to have clean laps. It's a great step in the right direction, maybe with some tuning, but overall for me it's positive. I hope they maintain this format because it's fantastic."
Meanwhile, the date of the 2026 edition of the Macau Grand Prix is ​​expected to be confirmed next week, during the FIA ​​World Council, which will take place before the FIA ​​awards ceremony for 2025, in the city of Tashkent, Uzbekistan.</description><pubDate>2025-12-05 01:52:45</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | FIA will continue to invest in Formula Regional in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/24/gp-fia-vai-continuar-a-apostar-na-formula-regional-em-macau/</link><description>The fact that the FIA ​​switched from Formula 3 to Formula Regional (FR) continues to be a recurring theme when the topic is the Macau Grand Prix. Although the show's premier race did not disappoint in this year's edition, somewhat erasing the bad image left last year, there is still a widespread feeling that the international federation deprived the Grand Prix of its favorite race.
At the end of the 72nd edition, the Coordinator of the Organizing Committee of the Macau Grand Prix, Lei Si Leng, when questioned again by the local press about a possible return of Formula 3, stated that the organization will continue to cooperate with the FIA ​​to choose the races that best suit Macau. At the same time, the director of the Macau Sports Institute left the guarantee that the plan involves continuing to receive drivers of training age and who assert themselves as the future of motorsport.
“We have been communicating closely with the FIA ​​to find out which races can be held in Macau and the FIA ​​has selected the best drivers to come and compete here”, he said, adding that he hopes “that the best drivers can come to Macau and that we continue to collaborate with the FIA ​​to organize the most suitable races for Macau”.
On the FIA ​​side, there is the conviction that FR is the discipline that best adapts to the characteristics of the Guia Circuit, a layout that remains practically unchanged after seven decades of existence. The discontent that still exists is considered natural. “Motor sport is traditional, and I don't remember any change that was well received at the beginning, even good changes” admitted Emanuele Pirro, the current president of the FIA ​​Single Seater Commission, in conversation with journalists in Macau.
The former Italian driver, a connoisseur of the Guia Circuit and winner of the Guia Race with BMW, took advantage of his time in the Macao SAR to remember that “if we look at the history of Macau, it started with Formula 2, or Formula Pacific, and then moved on to Formula 3. In 1984, a journalist could have asked: 'why don't we race in Formula 2 anymore?' I think it's inevitable. Everything has a price. For us to have the privilege of having a circuit that has remained unchanged since Throughout its history, the price to pay is to use cars that continue to be reasonably safe. And I think Formula Regional offers a good balance in terms of speed.”
In a rare interview with the specialized magazine INSIDE, the former coordinator of the Grand Prix, José Manuel Costa Antunes, warned against letting the level of the race drop. "Today, with the transition to Formula Regional and Formula 4, which is not a problem, they are just different cars, we see more inexperienced drivers", said the man who was at the helm of the event for the longest time, touching on a sensitive topic: "Some people can simply buy a seat. That is worrying. As fans, we want real races, not red flags. We owe it to the history of the Grand Prix to recover that selection process, to ensure that only the best compete here."
Numbers support the decision
Looking at the time sheets, it can be concluded that the records for the main FR race were around 2m16s, around ten seconds slower than the times recorded in the last year of the FIA F3 single-seaters, in 2023. In historical terms, these times place the FR cars on a level similar to that of the Formula 3 cars of the late 1990s. However, from a safety point of view, the speeds reached in the “Sprint” for Curva Lisboa continues to be the main concern since Sophia Flörsch’s accident in 2018. With the suction cone, speeds above 290 km/h were common in 2023 with the Dallara F3, but the change to FR cars reduced these values to around 260 km/h.
In 2026, the new Formula Regional car, the Tatuus T-326, is expected to arrive in Macau, which is equipped with a three-cylinder, 1.6-liter Toyota ATM163T engine, prepared by Autotecnica Motori, which is more powerful and efficient. The chassis was designed according to the latest FIA specifications, in order to provide improvements in terms of performance, safety and aerodynamics, facilitating overtaking and promoting more lively racing. However, although lap times are expected to drop again, top speeds will probably not be dramatically higher.
It should be noted that the change to FR was not motivated solely by security concerns. When the FIA ​​granted Formula One Management (FOM) the commercial and promotional rights for Formula 3, the territory's race became a non-championship race of an international competition, limited to the participation of the same teams that competed in the championship. This change was received unfavorably by the promoter himself, as he never played a truly intervening role within the Grand Prix. Furthermore, holding the race in Macau, in November, involved particularly demanding logistics, with a negative impact on the planning and execution of pre-season tests.</description><pubDate>2025-11-24 05:37:32</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Date and two competitions confirmed</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/12/gp-data-e-duas-competicoes-confirmadas/</link><description>The final meeting of the 2025 FIA World Motor Sport Council took place last Wednesday, during FIA General Assembly Week, in Tashkent, Uzbekistan. The session was attended by delegates from the various National Sports Authorities (ASNs), from which important decisions were taken, some of which concern Macau
The date of the 73rd Macau Grand Prix has been officially revealed, confirming that the Macao SAR's biggest annual sporting event will take place from 19 to 22 November next year. The international federation also took the opportunity to announce that the date and location of the ninth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup, which has been contested at the Guia Circuit since its creation, as part of the Grand Prix program, have been approved by the GT Commission. The same entity did not reveal the guidelines for next year's race, which in this year's edition only featured sixteen competitors, but this is the first time it has confirmed it so early.
For its part, the Touring Car Commission confirmed the calendar for the next season of the Kumho TCR World Tour, which will once again end at the Guia Circuit, as in previous years. China's strong presence on the calendar stands out: the Macau and Zhuzhou races are joined by an absolute debut, the new Chengdu Tianfu International Circuit. With eight events – one in Mexico and three in Europe, including the visit to the Vila Real International Circuit -, Asia gains new importance with a total of four rounds.
Four of the 2026 Kumho TCR World Tour events will maintain the traditional two-race format, including Macau, while the remaining four – Mexico, Spain (Valencia), South Korea (Inje) and China (Chengdu) – will adopt the three-race-per-weekend format introduced last year, reaching a total of twenty races in the season.
The FIA ​​World Motor Sport Council has not publicly commented on the continuation, or not, of the Formula Regional (FR) and Formula 4 World Cups in the Macau Grand Prix program, even though the latter's project, which also involves the Chinese promoter Mintime and the Fédération Française du Sport Automobile (FFSA), was designed for three years.
Also bet on karting
The World Council also approved the regulations that support the expansion of Karting under the supervision of the FIA, at a time when the next phase of implementation of the “Global Karting Plan” begins, which, next year, will integrate new “Arrive &amp; Drive” championships, included in one of the most extensive calendars ever.
Following the auspicious start of the FIA ​​“Arrive &amp; Drive” Karting World Cup, held in Malaysia last month, the innovative format will be expanded with new continental championships, bringing these accessible and affordable events closer to communities around the world. The 2026 calendar, already approved, will feature a European Championship and an Asia-Pacific Championship, each consisting of three rounds, the winners of which will secure a place on the 2026 FIA “Arrive &amp; Drive” Karting World Cup grid, to be contested at the end of the season.
The Coloane Kart Track, still one of the most modern in Southeast Asia, will be part of this first edition of the “Arrive &amp; Drive” Asia-Pacific Championship, hosting the inaugural race on the weekend of June 20th and 21st. The calendar of this low-cost competition also includes two other stages: one in Zhuzhou, in Hunan Province, and another in Madras, India.</description><pubDate>2025-12-12 01:19:59</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau | Rosa Mota in second place in the minimarathon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/12/09/macau-rosa-mota-em-segundo-lugar-na-minimaratona/</link><description>The Portuguese Rosa Mota came second on Sunday in the Macau mini-marathon, a 4.5-kilometer race that is part of the International Marathon in the Chinese region. The 67-year-old former Olympic champion finished the race in 17 minutes and 10 seconds, 54 seconds more than the first, local athlete Kin I Chao.
In February, the Portuguese woman was discharged from hospital, following a planned surgical intervention, after overcoming a “serious problem”, a “dissecting aortic aneurysm”. Rosa Mota, born in Porto, was Olympic marathon champion at the Seoul Olympic Games in 1988, after having won bronze in Los Angeles in 1984. Her achievements also include three European titles (1982, 1986 and 1990) and one world title (1987).
She is still the national marathon record holder, with a time of 02.23.29 hours, a mark achieved in Chicago in 1985. In recent years, Rosa Mota had reappeared at the highest level and won several veteran races, having set in Barcelona, ​​in 2024, the world half-marathon record (1:24.27 hours), for the 65 to 69 age group.
Also last year, the Portuguese won the Macau mini-marathon, repeating the triumphs in 2018, 2019 and 2023. This year, the organization invited several athletes, nominated by the Association of Portuguese Language Olympic Committees (ACOLOP), from Portugal, Angola, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Mozambique, São Tomé and Príncipe, Sri Lanka and the state of Goa (India).
Lusophony highlighted
Portuguese speakers were in the spotlight in the half-marathon, with Cape Verdean Samuel Freire, from Sporting Clube de Portugal, finishing third in the men's race, behind winner Martin Ndungu and David Kipkorir Rono, both Kenyans.
In fourth place came the Portuguese Fábio Oliveira, 30th in the marathon of the first edition of the European Road Championships, in April, and part of the Portugal team that finished in fourth place. Soon after came the young Mozambican Pinto Victor Jequecene, aged 22, while Angolan David Jundo Elias finished in seventh place.
In the women's race, Angolan Lúcia Kawele Capingala came in third place, behind the winner, Kenyan Lucy Ndambuki, and Chinese Na Zhao. Already off the podium, in fourth position, finished the young Portuguese Joana Ferreira, who won the silver medal in the under-23 race of the national athletics championships in 10 thousand meters, in May.
Mozambican Domingas Ernesto Checane came in sixth place. Around 12 thousand participants signed up for the three races of the Macau International Marathon, with the title of the premier race going to Kenyan Victor Kipchirchir and Ethiopian Senay Mastewal Birhanu.
In addition to his triumph, Kipchirchir broke the Macau marathon record, finishing in two hours, nine minutes and 27 seconds, 34 seconds less than the previous record, set in 2017 by Ethiopian Felix Kiptoo Kirwa.</description><pubDate>2025-12-09 03:18:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorsport | GP will continue on the TCR World Tour in 2026</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/19/automobilismo-gp-continuara-no-tcr-world-tour-em-2026/</link><description>The Macau Grand Prix will once again form part of the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour calendar next season and, once again, as the season-ending event of a competition that will increase its presence in Asia in 2026
Marcelo Lotti, president of the WSC Group, confirmed to the press, during the weekend of the 72nd Macau Grand Prix, that next year's calendar should include a race in South Korea – home country of the tire brand and championship sponsor, Kumho, as well as Hyundai, the brand with the most cars on the starting grids of the world competition -, a second race in the People's Republic of China and the traditional end-of-season round at the Guia Circuit.
To increase the presence on the Asian continent, without affecting the teams' budgets, Australia will be left out of the calendar. The championship promoter will also not move forward with the possibility of organizing a second race on the American continent, with a visit to Mexico being a certainty. Already on the “old continent”, the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour will maintain its three events, with the Portuguese city circuit of Vila Real hosting one of these events in July.
For Marcello Lotti, “the Macau Grand Prix is ​​our equivalent to Monaco”, and for the Italian businessman, “all championships need an event like this”. Despite the smaller number of entrants that this year's event gathered in the territory, “leaving Macau is obviously out of the question”.
The 2026 Kumho FIA TCR World Tour season calendar is expected to be revealed to the public on December 13, when the FIA ​​World Council meets in Tashkent, Republic of Uzbekistan, at the same time as the FIA's annual awards ceremony.
Number questions
The list of participants for the Guia Race Macau – Kumho FIA TCR World Tour Event of Macau had only seventeen of the twenty-four cars initially registered. This would have been one of the smallest starting grids ever for the highly popular Guia Race, whose first edition took place in 1972. In part, this number below expectations was due to the absence, for unknown reasons, of teams and drivers from TCR China, one of the strongest national tourism championships in the world.
Meanwhile, Marcello Lotti said during the Grand Prix weekend that TCR is preparing to welcome a new brand to the championship. However, this announcement, scheduled for next Friday, is not expected to have an impact on the starting grids of the Kumho FIA TCR World Tour, as it will be a car group that already has a presence in the championship and will replace one of its brands with another. The Italian businessman also said he was in negotiations with a second brand.
Asia's influence on today's biggest Touring Car championship is not just limited to the Koreans from Kumho and Hyundai, as the competition also features the Chinese brand Link &amp; Co, at an official level, and the Japanese counterpart Honda. At a time when electric cars, SUVs and city cars are the focus of big brands, Asian manufacturers are still among the few that invest in cars, with fuel engines, with dimensions suitable for Touring events.</description><pubDate>2025-11-19 01:34:35</pubDate></item><item><title>Roadsport | Badaraco took the podium on his birthday, but ended up penalized</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/11/17/roadsport-badaraco-subiu-ao-podio-em-dia-de-aniversario-mas-acabou-penalizado/</link><description>On his birthday, Badaraco recovered from 17th to reach second place on the podium. Hours after the party, the bad news arrived, with a penalty relegating him to 15th. Rui Valente was placed off the track, after recovering several positions
On his birthday, Jerónimo Badaraco climbed to second place on the podium of the Roadsport Challenge race, after starting from 17th. However, the worst came later, when the top three, all local drivers, were penalized and relegated in the general classification, for overtaking other cars that had lost their way before the starting line, after the safety car had left.
The Macanese driver had a setback when he was relegated to 15th, after an almost perfect race: “It was very unfair and I think the stewards don't know what they are doing”, said Jerónimo. "I think the decision was not transparent. After the safety car came out, several drivers hit the barriers... of course we thought they weren't going to continue in the race after those crashes and we had to overtake them", he explained. “And even if we had stopped or slowed down in the face of these drivers' missteps, we would have created a much more dangerous situation for everyone, because the cars behind us would have been surprised by our braking, meaning there would have been more accidents”, he explained.
Even so, the Macanese assured HM that the penalty would not ruin his day: “I will continue to enjoy the day, I went up to the podium, drank the champagne, took the photos… More cup, less cup, I will continue to celebrate”, he guaranteed with a laugh.
Hours before, Badaraco had already explained that reaching the podium in Guia “is a different feeling” that justifies “80 percent” his choice to drive 26 years ago.
The driver was also satisfied with the race, considering that no one can take away the merit of what he achieved on the track, as he rose from 17th to 2nd: "Before the race I thought a lot about how I was going to approach the start, to recover positions, and I was confident of a good result. The most important thing was not to have given up, after qualifying, and not to have stopped believing that it was possible to reach the podium", explained the Macanese driver. “I know that the Guia Circuit always has a lot of changes throughout the race, there are a lot of safety cars and yellow flags, and I knew I had the experience, and also the calm, to be able to take advantage of the opportunities”, he highlighted.
“They ruined my race”
In turn, Rui Valente gave up and appeared disappointed, due to what he considered to be an excess on the part of the driver who tried to overtake him on the inside, on the curve leading to the São Francisco road. "I don't know what was going through the driver's head who tried to overtake me. I can't understand how he saw a space that simply didn't exist!", said Valente. "I was put out of the race. When I tried to make the turn, he touched me and that was it, my rear end was damaged and I had to go back to the pits to retire", he reported.
When the crash occurred that ended the race, Valente was circulating in the top 10, even after a less successful start, following the exit of the first Safety Car. Despite this aspect, the Macanese came to believe that it was possible to achieve a result in the top five: “I had a good pace, I was confident and I think I would achieve a result in the top five... It's the races...”, he lamented.
The Macanese also took stock of a “complicated” weekend in which he was also involved in another accident during the free practice session. "To be honest, it wasn't one of the weekends I had the most fun in Macau. I had that first touch, which conditioned my qualifying. In the race I actually did well, gaining positions, but they put me off the track...", he highlighted.
At 64 years old, Rui Valente now admits that he may be left out of the next edition of the Grand Prix: “With such a difficult qualifying model for Macau and then with races with so many accidents, I will consider what to do in the future”, he confessed. “I don't want to sit still, I want to stay active and involved in different activities, so if I find an activity that occupies me and makes me feel good, maybe I'll stay out of racing next year”, he said.
Results
1st Leung Tsz Wa Toyota GR86 40m09s237
2nd Adrian Chung Toyota GR86  at 0.148
3rd  Tsang Pak Yin Toyota GR86 at 0.407
(…)
15th Jerónimo Badaraco Toyota GR86 at 29,061
High and Low
High
Jerónimo Badaraco's performance, recovering several positions, shows the importance that experience has on the circuit
Low
The safety car was on the track for too many laps, which greatly reduced the race time</description><pubDate>2025-11-17 05:00:35</pubDate></item></channel></rss>