<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Myanmar | XI expresses the desire to “accelerate cooperation”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/myanmar-xi-manifesta-vontade-de-acelerar-cooperacao/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday sent a message to Myanmar Military Junta Chief, Min Aung Hlaing, expressing the willingness to “accelerate high quality cooperation” between China and ancient Burma.
Xi stressed that the friendship between China and Myanmar “resisted the test of time and was reinforced,” according to a statement issued by the 75th anniversary of the establishment of bilateral diplomatic relations, quoted by the Chinese official news agency Xinhua.
"The two countries have maintained a good neighborhood, deepened mutually beneficial cooperation and firmly leaned on issues related to their fundamental interests and essential concerns, thus giving an excellent example of friendly exchange between nations," said the Chinese head of state.
China attributes “great importance” to the development of ties with Myanmar and is willing to work with the country, using the 75th anniversary of diplomatic ties “as an opportunity to accelerate high quality cooperation within the track and route,” said Xi.
The Chinese president met with Min Aung Hlaing on May 9 in Moscow, in terms of the first personal meeting between the two since the coup d'état was carried out by the Military Board on February 1, 2021, with the arrest of President-elect Win Myint, as well as the former government party leader, Aung Suu Kyi, and other rulers and politicians.
Although diplomatic exchanges between Myanmar and China have not been interrupted by the coup, they have become more public over the years, such as Beijing's mediation in the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:50:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Must | Sam Hou Fai promises a favorable environment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/must-sam-hou-fai-promete-ambiente-favoravel/</link><description>The chief executive spoke on Saturday at the Undergraduate Ceremony of the Macao University and Technology (Must), promising that the government, “in collaboration with all sectors of society, will provide more opportunities, a larger stage and a more favorable environment for students and the young generation develop their talents, work, create their own businesses and realize their aspirations”.
In addition to professional success, Sam Hou Fai expressed the desire that "the patriotic spirit and love Macau will continue to be transmitted from generation to generation, and that the principle of" a country, two systems "proceed."
Sam Hou Fai stressed the stimulus given by President Xi Jinping, who visited Must in December last year, exchanging impressions with teachers, students and researchers at the university, and giving “valuable guidance and attention”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:23:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Borders | Number of entries and exits exceeded 100 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/fronteiras-numero-de-entradas-e-saidas-ultrapassou-100-milhoes/</link><description>From the beginning of the year until 2 pm on Saturday, authorities have accounted for 100 million entrances and exits at the Macao borders. According to data revealed yesterday by the Public Security Police Corps, the bar of 100 million border movements occurred 18 days earlier than last year.
Authorities add that it was "beaten again a shorter record of short time to reach one hundred million border passages, with a daily average of 0.6 million inputs and exits of Macao, representing an increase of 10.8 percent over the same period last year."
CPSP also points out that the volume of passengers/tickets at the Cerco doors border post exceeded 50 million on May 30, and that the Hungqin and Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Posts and Ponte reached the “annual flow of 10 million border passages, successively on May 7 and 9, earlier than the previous year”.
The 100 million entrances and exits, about 36.2 million were residents of Macao, while the border movements of visitors reached almost 34 million. From the beginning of the year, until last Saturday, 25.9 million non-resident and family workers have entered and left Macao.
The CPSP explains the increase in the flow of people on the borders this year with the "impulse of policies favorable to Macao as" one entry a week ", a visa of multiple entries' and 'circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong province'.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:39:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative Macau | New Miguel Quental exhibition with images of Goa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/creative-macau-nova-exposicao-de-miguel-quental-com-imagens-de-goa/</link><description>After the first photography exhibition at the University of Macau, Miguel Quental again shows images of his own, but this time about Goa. The show is welcomed from Saturday at Creative Macau and intends to show the public the “rich inheritance of vibrant color” of a territory that once was the “capital of an empire”
 
Creative Macau hosts, from Saturday, a new exhibition by Miguel Quental, better known for his work in law, but this time presents his images taken in Goa. “Colors of Goa” is the name of the exhibition that opens from 6.30 pm on Saturday, presenting images of what was “capital of an empire”, from which “a rich inheritance of vibrant colors, aromas, flavors, images and beliefs that transcend our imagination”, describes the author of the photos, quoted by a Creative Macau statement.
“In search of this legacy, I left for Goa, but the experience went far beyond what I could expect. Its ancient churches and other places of worship exhibit a captivating beauty, offering a unique and transcendent peace that goes beyond the spirituality to which they are dedicated. The manorial houses, full of history, details and emotion, resemble noble, majestic and impassible, full of art and memories.” It also describes.
Miguel Quental does not forget either “the alleys of Velha Goa, Pangim, Margão and the Fontaínhas neighborhood, which breathe and offer us a vibrant and almost magnetic heritage that touches the soul and invites us to go beyond the historical and cultural memories that memory does not allow us to forget”. "In this spirit, I share some of the many images I took there, but I'm aware that much more to find out," says the author, who hopes that she will "invite her to visit her soon."
I like the image
Residing in Macao since 2002, Miguel Quental has been in the third individual exhibition. The last one was at the University of Macao in November last year, being a photographic project that was born from an exchange trip from the Center for Legal and Judicial Studies of the University of Macao to Angola and Mozambique.
In addition to participating in the visit as a teacher, Miguel Quental photographed the daily lives of the populations of these countries. "As I like to do photography I was taking some images during these trips. This is a center that is dedicated to the comparative study of law and the publications that are made in Portuguese in its relationship with China, and I thought it was interesting to make known the culture and way of living from Angola and Mozambique to college students who never had access to this reality," he explained to HM at the time.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:52:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | 96 illegal employees in G-Dragon concert</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/dsal-detectadas-96-funcionarias-ilegais-em-concerto-de-g-dragon/</link><description>On Saturday, police and work services did an operation at the Korean singer G-Dragon merchandising stalls at the Galaxy Arena, where 96 possibly in illegal staff were found. Two officials of the organization were taken to the squadron for investigation
 
The past weekend was of great euphoria at Cotai, with three concerts by popular Korean singer G-Dragon in the Galaxy Arena. However, on Saturday morning a joint operation of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) detected 96 employees suspected of being in an illegal situation in the merchandising selling zone.
Subsequently, the CPSP issued a statement confirmed during the process of verifying the identity of the workers the presence of 96 non-resident workers, whose authorization to work would have to be confirmed with DSAL. Following the discovery, two officials of the concert organization were taken to the police squad for investigation.
The authorities did not add more information about the case, in addition to the admission of CPSP that would be investigating the situation and that were found infringements, the case will be treated according to the law. Until the closing of this edition, DSAL had not been pronounced on the occurrence, nor the company that organized the concerts, Tencent Music Entertainment Live.
The situation generated controversy and many publications on social networks. One of the most discussed theories pointed to a possible revenge of clandestine ticket sellers, who would have been expelled from the enclosure on Friday, which will allegedly warned the authorities for the illegal situation of the employees.
NETWORK TRAINS
In addition to revenge theory, images of publications were also shared to recruit part -time workers during concerts, especially on Chinese social networks. In one of the publications, the organizer sought to recruit women under 30, referring as a daily remuneration 200 Renminbis, as well as an additional bonus in accordance with sales. The announcement also indicated that the employer was willing to offer accommodation to employees who needed it.
Also at the level of the legitimate sale of tickets for the Korean star concert there was confusion. In Hong Kong, the cityline ticket sales platform has been complained due to the printing of the wrong date, number of wrong tickets and the passivity of employees in resolving and treatment of complaints.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:37:28</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural Week | Government wants to change events to Zhongshan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/semana-cultural-governo-quer-mudar-evento-para-zhongshan/</link><description>The executive intends that the 17th edition of the China Cultural Week and Portuguese-speaking countries will be fully held in Zhongshan, but the Lusophone associations involved in the event are against the change of the event's nevral center, despite supporting the expansion to the great bay.
 
The government intends that the 17th edition of the China Cultural Week and Portuguese -speaking countries will be fully held in Zhongshan, Canton province, despite being locally funded. Information about the Institute's plan for the promotion of commerce and investment of Macau (Ipim) was advanced by the platform newspaper in the Friday issue, but has the opposition of local associations.
According to the publication, IPIM maintained separated meetings with the Lusophone Associations involved in the event and told them that at least this year, the event will leave Macau to move inside. After the meetings, the associations have joined to refuse that the event be taken entirely to Zhongshan, although they agree that the interior penetration is positive for all parts.
According to the letter sent to the IPIM, Lusophone associations argue “the importance of preserving the event in the MSAR, maintaining it as the nerve center of this cultural celebration”. “Macao has been, throughout history, the bridge between Lusophone and Chinese cultures, and we believe this character must remain,” he was added.
To the platform, the Macao Forum did not deny the intention to hold the entire event in Zhongshan, and assumed that it aims to “ensure the success of the event, both in Macau and the Great Bay, for all parties involved, as well as for participants and the public”.
The Macao Forum also indicated that it is acting "in accordance with the decision taken by all parties participating in the Macao Forum, at the 20th Ordinary Meeting of the Permanent Secretariat, to include Elements of the Cultural Week in the Great Bay."
Still, the body has pointed out that "it is collaborating with all its partners, whether government or civil society, including the associations of Portuguese -speaking countries in Macau, with a view to welcoming and integrating all the ideas, concerns and contributions it has received and continues to receive."
"Wrapping paper"
In addition to the trip to Zhongshan, the associations complain about the new role they are taking into the event, since the integration of the Macao Forum in IPIM, which made them lose functional autonomy.
In addition to this aspect, the platform, the cultural week of China and Portuguese -speaking countries has been awarded to a company, which deals with all the details of the event, on the fringes of associations, who is responsible for the role of just indicating the names to be invited. This new reality led to a source of associations, which refused to be identified, to collapse to the newspaper that associations only feel as “package papers” to legitimize the event. Among the complaints against the new role is the fact that associations currently do not even have a maneuver room to receive or socialize with the artists or economic agents invited to the event of these countries. Given this reality, associations suggest the “limitation of the intervention of companies that do not know the cultural concept developed over the years” to ensure “loyalty to the original values ​​of the event”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:30:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Communities | Emídio Sousa succeeds José Cesário as secretary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/comunidades-emidio-sousa-sucede-a-jose-cesario-como-secretario/</link><description>The new secretary of the Portuguese communities has a governance experience in the environment and for more than 10 years has been mayor of Santa Maria da Feira. In turn, José Cesário will return to the functions of deputy
 
The Prime Minister of Portugal, Luís Montenegro, chose Emídio Sousa as the new Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities. The replacement of José Cesário, who had resumed these functions last year, and who fulfilled four distinct periods in office, was revealed with the announcement of the members who constitute the new Portuguese executive.
The appointment means to Emídio Sousa a change of folder, since in the previous government had performed the functions of Secretary of State for the Environment.
The new responsible for the Portuguese communities portfolio has a career essentially linked to policy and public administration. According to his profile on the LinkedIn social network, he has a degree in Public Administration, an area in which he also obtained a master's degree.
For about 20 years he worked in the waters of Gaia, where he reached the position of secretary general, and then, in October 2013, assumed the functions of mayor of Santa Maria da Feira, in the district of Aveiro, where he was for about 10 years. Before being elected mayor, he had performed the duties of councilman.
“With a quiet conscience”
In turn, after becoming a public that was no longer secretary of state of communities, José Cesário left a farewell message on social networks. “It was a great honor for me to have returned to perform these governmental functions in the government led by my friend Luís Montenegro and served the Portuguese resident abroad. It was a very difficult year, full of obstacles, in which, despite everything, it was possible to perform some measures, which I hope to translate into more valuses for those who live outside Portugal,” wrote Cesário. "The choice for a new passport and the expiration of its expiration date, the resolution of the salary problem of our employees in Brazil, the normalization of the activity of the Portuguese Communities Council and the alteration of the association support regime and communication of communities are good examples of this action," he was added. The extension of the passport period from 5 years to 10 years is not yet in force.
"Honestly, I leave with a quiet conscience, but with the certainty that there is a lot to do to have a closer and effective relationship with our communities," he said. "Of course, I wish my successor all luck to the world, being sure that, being a wise and hardworking man, everything will do to serve the Portuguese abroad," he said.
In place of always
Despite leaving the position of Secretary of State, José Cesário will assume the duties of deputy, after being elected by the circle outside Europe. This is a return to a parliament that Cesário has well known and for which he has been successively elected since 1983, with only an interregnum in 2022, first as representative of Aveiro and since 2005 as a representative of communities outside Europe.
"From today return to the Assembly of the Republic, as deputy elected from Europe, ceasing my duties of Secretary of State of Portuguese Communities," he wrote. “Now it's time to dedicate myself to parliamentary life, representing with determination, work and humility those who have elected me, whom I owe so much and with whom I have learned so much. Let's go to work!…”
Rita Santos regrets “friend”
The chairman of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) lamented that the “friend” José Cesário is no longer the Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities. “It was a surprise […] Dr. José Cesário, besides being a secretary of state, is our friend,” he acknowledged in statements to the Macau channel of TDM. "It is more for the human issue, for their ability to communicate with people, to solve the problems, so we have had a good relationship with him. Whether he is in government, or not, he is always willing to help people. We were sad, but we have to look forward," he added.
Rita Santos also pointed out that José Cesário will continue to defend the community, now in Parliament. "He is a deputy and I think that with the position of deputy he can continue to fight for the legitimate rights of the Portuguese to live outside Portugal," he said.
At the same time, he left wishes to establish a good relationship with the new Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities, Emídio Sousa. "With the new secretary of state we hope that there may be collaboration and good contact, as with Dr. José Cesário, and we wish them the biggest success, to solve the problems of the Portuguese who are quite enough," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Elections | Candidate lists fall to less than half</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/eleicoes-listas-candidatas-caem-para-menos-de-metade/</link><description>The Electoral Commission received at the end of the deadline for nine requests for direct suffrage to the Macao Parliament, less than half than in the previous elections in 2021. The next step will be the presentation of the lists of candidates and political programs by June 26
 
The Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal) received nine applications from candidate lists to the next legislative elections, less than half of the lists that tried to participate in the 2021 electoral act. There were 19 lists of candidates for the Legislative Assembly (AL), although five lists and 21 candidates -15 of which pro -democracy -were then excluded by “not defending the basic law” being “faithful to the sons”.
In a statement issued on Friday, the Electoral Commission stressed that, after finishing the deadline for requesting requests, the candidacy committees that were recognized may submit the list of candidates and political program by June 26. The list will only be “definitely admitted” to the “after passing” elections of the candidates, stressed the electoral body.
The State Security Defense Commission will determine "whether candidates defend the basic law and are faithful" to the MSar and issue a binding opinion, of which "there is no complaint or litigation."
This State Security Defense Committee will announce, by late, until July 15, the decision on the list of candidates for the legislatures, scheduled for September 14. The Electoral Commission promised to “rigorously” the new electoral law, approved after the 2021 exclusions, “which aims at greater implementation of the Macao principle governed by Patriots”.
In good Portuguese
On Tuesday, by submitting his application for candidacy, Portuguese deputy José Pereira Coutinho said he was confident that he will not be disqualified, despite being-along with Deputy Ron Lam-one of the few critical voices of the government in AL.
"The fact that being critical does not mean that I am not a patriot, I am also patriot," said the former candidate for the Assembly of the Portuguese Republic, in 2015, by the Party We Citizens.
“We have always worked here for Macao's good and for the good of the citizens of Macau,” added Pereira Coutinho. Thirty -three deputies are part of AL, 14 of which are elected by direct suffrage, 12 for indirect suffrage through associations, and seven are later appointed by the head of the local government.
In the case of the indirect suffrage, the Electoral Commission said it had received six application, more than in 2021, for the five sectors: industrial, commercial and financial; workers; Liberal professionals; social and educational services; and cultural and sports. Four years ago, the 19 initial lists of candidates for direct suffrage had three Lusodescendants.
Two of them, José Pereira Coutinho and Lídia Lourenço, were on the Nova Esperança list, linked to the Macao Public Function Workers Association. The third, architect Rui Leão, secretary general of the International Union of Architects, was part of the Civic Observatory list, headed by the then deputy Agnes Lam.
Pereira Coutinho did not disclose the composition of the list, but guaranteed the presence of Rita Santos, who requested in October the suspension of the office of the Portuguese communities to prepare the elections. Pereira Coutinho resigned in 2021 to the mandate of a counselor of the Portuguese communities, for which he had been elected in 2015 by the Circle of China, Macao and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:18:41</pubDate></item><item><title>Pecunaries Checks | Former Beneficiaries defend better assignment criteria</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/cheques-pecuniarios-ex-beneficiarios-defendem-melhores-criterios-de-atribuicao/</link><description>Given the changes to the pecuniary reimbursement plan, HM has heard three permanent residents who will no longer receive the check because they do not reside permanently in Macao, including a macanese born in the territory. Arnaldo Gonçalves, academic and former Beneficiary, defends a better distribution of support depending on the income of families
 
The rules for the attribution of pecuniary checks will change and now it is really necessary to be 183 days a year in the territory. The exceptions are some and arrest with students from Macau who are attending courses abroad or residents to work remotely to Macau and who are enrolled in the Social Security Fund, among other situations.
However, many people will be left out, even though they have lived for several decades in the territory or even macanese born in Macau, that is, many of the members of the Macanese diaspora.
In the case of Arnaldo Gonçalves, a permanent resident resident in Lisbon, he lived several decades in Macau, having worked for the government and was a university professor in the area of ​​political science. Six years ago, he returned to Portugal, being renovated, and told HM that he was already waiting for the day he was going to stop receiving the ten thousand dates annually.
"This measure aims to give people a counterpart, given the difficulties existing in consumption and the characteristics of life. I don't live in Macau, and I think from the point of view of equity, the government has never been able to make a fairer regime from the distributive point of view, because there is no system of attribution from the income, and deep down there are multimillionaires that gain the subseck, like the pensioners, all," he said. This is what Arnaldo Gonçalves says "lament". "It is hard work to make an assessment of people's economic possessions, and so everyone receives the same as it is more practical in administrative terms," ​​he said.
Maria João Ferreira, macaense of gem, daughter of the famous poet Adé, will also fail to receive the pecuniary check. He says he understands, but also criticizes the executive's positions. "I was already waiting and accepted with all the tranquility. It is fair, since I do not live there and I have the chance to be 183 days. I thank the time of checks that was dismissed. I lived in Macau until I was 16, but I was born there and still have family. Even the pandemic was there every year of vacation. mentioned.
Maria João Ferreira, currently in the direction of Macao's house in Lisbon, says she was “shocked” with a very concrete case. "A few years ago, when he was doing his doctorate, he learned of a civil servant who did two service committees in Macao and was a contemplated BIR money and even told me, not just me, that I thought it was funny as he was there so recently, he was entitled to such a benefit," he said.
"This is what I think is bad. It is one thing to go to do a service committee in public administration, or two or three, but it was never, in fact, resident. It is, as it were, an immigrant, because it will only work. This is how I see things," he added.
Patacas Amealdas
For Arnaldo Gonçalves, the ten thousand annual patacas served as a “Management Fund” for trips to the territory, where he still has family and where he travels frequently. "I've never used this money for personal purposes, you know? But I think these changes are a good measure, justifiable, and I even think it's selfish, that I've been entitled to this support for so many years. There are other people who need it," he said.
In the case of Maria João Ferreira, the cash of the pecuniary check was also used for expenses in Macao and with trips to the territory. "I have an account in Macao, and when I went there, if I needed to buy the plane ticket, my sister said the money here, or this money served to fund my stay in Macao," he explained.
Sofia Mota, a permanent resident and former Maradora in Macao, regrets the absence of explanations for these changes. "It depends on what the pecuniary check is for, whether it is a way of distributing the wealth or profits of casinos to the people who are part of the territory, or have already done; either if it is a condition to be part of the territory. I do not realize the premise in which the pecuniary check measure is based, and depending on the premise these changes may be more or less acceptable."
The teacher considers that "it makes no sense that those who contribute to social security at their own initiative, as is my case, are not covered." "It seems that there is a first and second and second social security system. People who come to Portugal to provide family care seem not to be covered and yet are out of the territory for reasons of force majeure. What is meant by providing subsistence to family members, is not realizing the function of the check and the coherence of exceptions," he said.
Sofia Mota confesses that she also used money to "a management fund to go to Macau, or to invest in formation."
The first reactions
The changes to the pecuniary reimbursement program were presented at the end of May and report that three groups will be exempt from the obligation to be 183 days a year in Macao and thus receive the check. They are the residents under 22 in 2024 and where one parent meets the requirements for receiving the check; the beneficiaries of the disability pension and the beneficiaries of disability allowance.
There are eight other situations where residents may have access to the check. This is what happens when residents attend higher education outside the territory; When they are hospitalized in a hospital outside the sons, those who are over 65 and live in the interior of China or, even under 65, have health reasons that justify the permanence inside China. Residents who work outside Macao are also covered by the exceptions to an employer registered at the MSAR Social Security Fund and residents outside the MSAR who are responsible for the family aggregate subsistence.
These are also attached to the exercise of official functions outside Macao; the registration of domicile, work or study in the deepened cooperation zone; And yet the work done in the cities of large bay except Hong Kong that is left out.
Deputy Pereira Coutinho manifested against the changes to the pecuniary check referring to violate the Macao Basic Law, namely in article 25, which guarantees the equality of the residents of Macao before the law and prohibits discrimination. The article determines that "the residents of Macao are equal before the law, without discrimination due to nationality, ancestry, race, gender, language, religion, political or ideological convictions, economic instruction and situation or social condition."
More recently, the Macao Synergy Association publicly stated that changes to the pecuniary reimbursement plan in economic development are not in accordance with the wishes of the population. Ron Lam also criticized the executive for applying the changes “in a hurry” which only came to cause more controversy: “the government was in a hurry and applied a sudden measure, without making any public consultation, with only behind -the -scenes movements leading to the population to question governance,” he said. "Consultations with local associations were simulated, which only generated more criticism and caused more unnecessary controversy," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:15:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar | XI expresses the desire to “accelerate cooperation”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/myanmar-xi-manifesta-vontade-de-acelerar-cooperacao/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday sent a message to Myanmar Military Junta Chief, Min Aung Hlaing, expressing the willingness to “accelerate high quality cooperation” between China and ancient Burma.
Xi stressed that the friendship between China and Myanmar “resisted the test of time and was reinforced,” according to a statement issued by the 75th anniversary of the establishment of bilateral diplomatic relations, quoted by the Chinese official news agency Xinhua.
"The two countries have maintained a good neighborhood, deepened mutually beneficial cooperation and firmly leaned on issues related to their fundamental interests and essential concerns, thus giving an excellent example of friendly exchange between nations," said the Chinese head of state.
China attributes “great importance” to the development of ties with Myanmar and is willing to work with the country, using the 75th anniversary of diplomatic ties “as an opportunity to accelerate high quality cooperation within the track and route,” said Xi.
The Chinese president met with Min Aung Hlaing on May 9 in Moscow, in terms of the first personal meeting between the two since the coup d'état was carried out by the Military Board on February 1, 2021, with the arrest of President-elect Win Myint, as well as the former government party leader, Aung Suu Kyi, and other rulers and politicians.
Although diplomatic exchanges between Myanmar and China have not been interrupted by the coup, they have become more public over the years, such as Beijing's mediation in the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:50:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Must | Sam Hou Fai promises a favorable environment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/must-sam-hou-fai-promete-ambiente-favoravel/</link><description>The chief executive spoke on Saturday at the Undergraduate Ceremony of the Macao University and Technology (Must), promising that the government, “in collaboration with all sectors of society, will provide more opportunities, a larger stage and a more favorable environment for students and the young generation develop their talents, work, create their own businesses and realize their aspirations”.
In addition to professional success, Sam Hou Fai expressed the desire that "the patriotic spirit and love Macau will continue to be transmitted from generation to generation, and that the principle of" a country, two systems "proceed."
Sam Hou Fai stressed the stimulus given by President Xi Jinping, who visited Must in December last year, exchanging impressions with teachers, students and researchers at the university, and giving “valuable guidance and attention”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:23:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Borders | Number of entries and exits exceeded 100 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/fronteiras-numero-de-entradas-e-saidas-ultrapassou-100-milhoes/</link><description>From the beginning of the year until 2 pm on Saturday, authorities have accounted for 100 million entrances and exits at the Macao borders. According to data revealed yesterday by the Public Security Police Corps, the bar of 100 million border movements occurred 18 days earlier than last year.
Authorities add that it was "beaten again a shorter record of short time to reach one hundred million border passages, with a daily average of 0.6 million inputs and exits of Macao, representing an increase of 10.8 percent over the same period last year."
CPSP also points out that the volume of passengers/tickets at the Cerco doors border post exceeded 50 million on May 30, and that the Hungqin and Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Posts and Ponte reached the “annual flow of 10 million border passages, successively on May 7 and 9, earlier than the previous year”.
The 100 million entrances and exits, about 36.2 million were residents of Macao, while the border movements of visitors reached almost 34 million. From the beginning of the year, until last Saturday, 25.9 million non-resident and family workers have entered and left Macao.
The CPSP explains the increase in the flow of people on the borders this year with the "impulse of policies favorable to Macao as" one entry a week ", a visa of multiple entries' and 'circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong province'.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:39:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative Macau | New Miguel Quental exhibition with images of Goa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/creative-macau-nova-exposicao-de-miguel-quental-com-imagens-de-goa/</link><description>After the first photography exhibition at the University of Macau, Miguel Quental again shows images of his own, but this time about Goa. The show is welcomed from Saturday at Creative Macau and intends to show the public the “rich inheritance of vibrant color” of a territory that once was the “capital of an empire”
 
Creative Macau hosts, from Saturday, a new exhibition by Miguel Quental, better known for his work in law, but this time presents his images taken in Goa. “Colors of Goa” is the name of the exhibition that opens from 6.30 pm on Saturday, presenting images of what was “capital of an empire”, from which “a rich inheritance of vibrant colors, aromas, flavors, images and beliefs that transcend our imagination”, describes the author of the photos, quoted by a Creative Macau statement.
“In search of this legacy, I left for Goa, but the experience went far beyond what I could expect. Its ancient churches and other places of worship exhibit a captivating beauty, offering a unique and transcendent peace that goes beyond the spirituality to which they are dedicated. The manorial houses, full of history, details and emotion, resemble noble, majestic and impassible, full of art and memories.” It also describes.
Miguel Quental does not forget either “the alleys of Velha Goa, Pangim, Margão and the Fontaínhas neighborhood, which breathe and offer us a vibrant and almost magnetic heritage that touches the soul and invites us to go beyond the historical and cultural memories that memory does not allow us to forget”. "In this spirit, I share some of the many images I took there, but I'm aware that much more to find out," says the author, who hopes that she will "invite her to visit her soon."
I like the image
Residing in Macao since 2002, Miguel Quental has been in the third individual exhibition. The last one was at the University of Macao in November last year, being a photographic project that was born from an exchange trip from the Center for Legal and Judicial Studies of the University of Macao to Angola and Mozambique.
In addition to participating in the visit as a teacher, Miguel Quental photographed the daily lives of the populations of these countries. "As I like to do photography I was taking some images during these trips. This is a center that is dedicated to the comparative study of law and the publications that are made in Portuguese in its relationship with China, and I thought it was interesting to make known the culture and way of living from Angola and Mozambique to college students who never had access to this reality," he explained to HM at the time.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:52:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Camões was Mozambique's “great‘ amateur ”, influencing his poetry</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/08/camoes-foi-grande-amador-de-mocambique-influenciando-a-sua-poesia/</link><description>The academic Lourenço do Rosario highlighted on Friday that Luís de Camões influenced Mozambican poets as a "great" amateur ", asking for more research to discover a camões hosted on the island of Mozambique, in the north of the country.
"Camões was a great amateur, was very fond of women and one of the reasons that he was always in prison was exactly because he had several problems with women, especially married (…). He arrives in 1567, had no money to continue the trip to Portugal, had no money to live on the island of Mozambique," said the academic Mozambican Lourenço do Rosário, after the opening of the second congress. 500 years of Camões.
Mozambique welcomes the second 500th anniversary Congress of the birth of Luís de Camões, emphasizing the relationship of the Portuguese poet with the Indian Ocean and the Mozambican territory. Lourenço do Rosário, essayist and professor of literature, said Camões was welcomed “in Macúti”, houses built with local material, “by Mutian women” (woman, in the local language of Nampula), when he arrived at Mozambique Island.
"He makes that poem‛ Endchas to Barbara Slave, "which is one of the most beautiful poems he wrote about women, so Camões knew how to sing the woman," added Lourenço do Rosário.
"An obligation"
The former dean of the Polytechnic University of Maputo and also a member of Leya Award criticized Portugal for not valuing the deeds of Camões for the Portuguese East Empire, arguing that one cannot “alienate this reality” that the poet “began to write and ended his works in Mozambique”.
"So, we have this obligation to rescue this reading of Camões and go see what he had critic had about Portugal's presence in the East Empire," said the teacher, asking for research to ensure the presence of Camões in schools from his action in the East.
From this perspective, Lourenço do Rosário also recalled that Camões should be seen in Mozambique as someone who was “arrested, expelled and degraded”, who fought as a military and lived poor, having undergone “deprivation” in the East before Portugal introduced him to the world as a “great Portuguese poet”.
Lourenço do Rosário has asked more research to influence political decisions in the face of Camões in education programs in the country. "It is necessary to value what is ours, and Camões is ours, because he wrote here."
“There is a whole generation, a group of [Eduardo] White, Nelson Health, Rui Knopfli, especially the poets that are linked to the island of Mozambique, have a lot of influence from Camões's writing, the look of Camões on the world, not only from the point of view of love, but also about social criticism, so I think Mozambican researchers have a lot of material to discover and influence our schools. But Camões ours, from Mozambique, ”he said.
The Portuguese Ambassador in Mozambique, also present at the opening of Congress, highlighted the academic movement in the praise of Camões as a “unifying element” of a culture and language that “is not only of the Portuguese”, pointing to the poet as a “symbol of projection of the Portuguese speaker community”.
The Camões in Africa and Asia Network, which promotes and encourages studies and publications about Camões, held the first Congress about the 500th anniversary of the poet's birth last year, in Macao, and for 2026, the same event is intended to go to Goa, making a tour of places where it passed and lived, explained the organization.
Born 501 years ago, on June 10, 1524, in Lisbon, the Soldado Poet Luís Vaz de Camões lived and wrote about two years on the island of Mozambique, in the old street of Fogo, where it will also make sense that love “is fire that burns without seeing”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-08 21:24:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong USA AI to predict Alzheimer's risks through retina images</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/hong-kong-usa-ia-para-prever-riscos-de-alzheimer-atraves-de-imagens-da-retina/</link><description>A Hong Kong Health Center has developed a system that uses Artificial Intelligence Technologies (AI) to predict the risk of Alzheimer's disease through retinal image analysis, a pioneering advance in the world.
The system is not invasively analyzes the bottom images of the eye, detecting early changes in blood vessels and retinal nerves that may be related to Alzheimer's disease, allowing to identify potential risk cases years before clinical symptoms appear.
Humansa Medical Center, a longevity-centered health center, has developed the system in collaboration with I-Cognitio Sciences, an ophthalmological technology company at the Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK).
The artificial intelligence of i-cognitio has been validated with a vast data set, which includes nearly 13,000 eye background images of 648 patients diagnosed with Alzheimer's and over 3,000 individuals with normal cognition.
A study published in 2022 in Lancet Digital Health, demonstrated that artificial intelligence technology developed to detect Alzheimer's risk reaches an accuracy of 80 percent to 92 percent in multi -deed populations from various countries.
Dementia affects about one third of people over 85 in the Asia Pacific region, according to recent data. In Hong Kong, dementia affects 10 percent of the population over 70 years old and Alzheimer's disease is responsible for more than half of diagnosed cases.
Scientific studies underline that up to 45 percent of dementia cases could be avoided or delayed through early interventions, stressing the importance of early detection to mitigate the impact of dementia on the population.
However, conventional cognitive tests and brain structural imaging have limited accuracy, while advanced methods such as amyloid pet and cerebrospinal fluid analysis are invasive and less accessible to the general population.
Crucial action
In this context, this study has developed a model based on deep learning with an approach that promises to offer “a simple, low -cost and poorly laborious solution” to identify potential patients in community environments and provide adequate accuracy and sensitivity.
In an effort to highlight AI relevance in the diagnosis and health care of the brain, Vincent Mok, director and founder of I-Cognitio, highlighted the fundamental role of the retina as a window to the brain. According to Mok, "through non -invasive eye photography, it is possible to identify changes in retinal blood vessels and retinal nerves linked to Alzheimer's disease."
The expert explained that these changes in the retina may manifest themselves 10 to 15 years before Alzheimer's clinical symptoms are evident, which represents a crucial opportunity for early intervention.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:49:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Facilitated entry to foreigners through the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/facilitada-entrada-a-estrangeiros-atraves-da-ponte-hong-kong-zhuhai-macau/</link><description>The Public Security Police body announced that tourists from 82 countries, including Portugal, Brazil and Cape Verde, will be able to enter the region through the largest sea bridge in the world, without having to leave the vehicle.
The measure comes into force today on the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge and covers all visitors from the 82 entry-expected countries, CPSP said. In a statement issued on Thursday, police said that all foreign tourists “armed with a valid passport”, regardless of nationality, will be able to leave Macao and enter the bridge without leaving the vehicle.
The goal of the police is to "promote international cultural exchange and help Macau become an open platform abroad (…) and an important window for the exchange between Chinese and Western civilizations." Police added that the measure, which covers vehicles that can transport up to nine people, was decided “after an in -depth evaluation of the demand for entry and exit” at the Bridge Border post.
To the other bank
The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, the world's longest maritime crossing, registered more than 172,000 foreign passengers by the end of April, an increase of 70 percent compared to the same period of 2024. “This increase is largely due to the expansion of visa exemption policies by China, and Zhuhai's terrestrial border post is the only one in continental territory Chinese that offers direct road access to Hong Kong International Airport, ”Chinese state news agency Xinhua said.
At the end of April, the Secretary for Macao Security announced plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors, without resident status or work authorization, through the use of automatic electronic channels. Authorities will expand self-service equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, explained Wong Sio Chak.
The secretary added that the government will study the extension of iris recognition technology in non -resident border controls in 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:38:37</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Du Mu (803-852), Chang'an's poet, who in his imperial employee career was sent in successive missions to distant posts of the capital, often showed his inconvenience in the face of repeated separations. In one of his most admired poems he looked at the old narrative told since the Han Dynasty, which explains a traditional festival celebrated on the seventh day of the seventh moon, where once a year the meeting of a couple, cowboy Niulang and weaver Zhinu, identified with two shiny stars separated by the Milkway through the rest of the year.
This festival, Qixi Jie, "The Night of the Setes", is known to be an occasion to publicly emphasize the virtues and work of ladies, then usually confined to Gypeu. One night the poet noticed in a lone girl:
«A silver candle shines in the fall
before the cold painted panel,
Holding a small range of gauze
Silk light, pushes the moths away.
Of the stairs arrives a breeze
fresh like water,
She sits down and contemplating
And among the stars
Discover Niulang and Zhinu. »
The other women celebrating in groups were dedicated to various activities. In addition to the contemplation of the stars, they offered the gods, recited prayers, or dedicated themselves to weaving.
All this in an environment of reverence and joy that can be observed, for example, in a horizontal roll of Ding Guanpeng (1708-1771), ladies on the night of the seven appealing to their talents (paper ink, 28.7 x 386.5 cm, at the Shanghai Museum). From the weavers there would be some, especially those of educated families who would be weaving maybe with human hair, a beloved figure of Buddhism, Bodhisattva Guanyin.
In such a way the adepts felt close to the one who "contemplates the sounds" of those who direct them, postponing their release to help the enlightenment of others, who redo their figure as a form of asceticis.
Fang Weyi (1585-1668) was a literate, poet and painter that was part of these literati who, with their artistic erudition, permeated Chan Buddhism. He was born in a family of high employees and married early in 1602 but in the same year he had been widowed and lost his daughter of this marriage.
It is possible that these "heartbreaks of the heart" have deepened their Buddhist faith, lived in the reserve of the home environment. Among the numerous examples of this devotion include poems and paintings figuring Luohans and a portrait of Guanyin dressed in white (vertical roll, paint on paper, 56 x 26.6 cm, at the Palace Museum in Beijing). Figurated in a contrast between thick and undulating black traces to show off his wide white robes and the light detail with which he portrays his welcoming face. And the face as human, as much as the free gesture of the garments, reveals a strange transcendence.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>ANA CRISTINA ALVES</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/ana-cristina-alves/</link><description>Ana Cristina Alves, auxiliary researcher and coordinator of the Educational Service of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center
May 20, 2025
Cultural Introduction and Comparison
What is the implicit popular philosophy in Wu Cheng´en's West Pilgrimage (吴承恩) 1500 - 1582? This was written during the Ming Dynasty and published in 1570, about the time when the Lusíadas de Luís Vaz de Camões, the Camonian epic, would be edited in 1572.
In the western pilgrimage, we are looking for an imaginary recreation of a group of pilgrims, headed by the monk of the Tang Xuanzang Dynasty (唐玄奘 Xuánzàng), to conquer a new spiritual world, that of Buddhist religion, to which the Chinese should adhere to a better ethical-moral conduct for a much-diverted population of good teachings and conduct.
Those who lead the initiative to free the Chinese from suffering is, of course, the deity of compassion, Guanyin (观音 Guānyīn), always attentive to all distressed souls, ready to launch their help.
Already in the case of Os Lusíadas, composed by Luís Vaz de Camões (1524/5-1580), a journey is also narrated, but it is real, inseparable from spiritual and religious aspects, because made in the name of the universality of the Christian faith, but being inseparable from the concrete journey, which implies the very human and Renaissance conquest of a better world for people, in which the Portuguese can not the Portuguese Just survive, but command and imperate, because they are worthy of an old history and very valuable warriors. Therefore, the heroism of the discoveries, living in the Christian faith, but accompanied and protected by the Renaissance Belling that recovers the classic spirit and deities, such as the protective Venus, a loving deity that sails for the Portuguese, and the aggressive and jealous Bacchus, the god of wine who wants to lose them.
The west pilgrimage by the Chinese is performed in the name of collective liberation and salvation, through contact with Buddhist sutras; The Portuguese “pilgrimage” to the east is also in the name of a collectivity, saves souls and extends to the whole land, given the proselytist vocation of Christianity and globalizing merchants, as well as the navigators, Camões his poetic herald desires the spread of faith by a great empire built by Portuguese heroes, as read in the first resort of singing first:
The weapons and the barons marked
That of the western Lusitana beach,
By seas never of before navigadas
Also passed beyond TAPROBAN,
In hardworking dangers and wars,
More than promised human strength,
And among remote people built
New kingdom, which so sublimated;
That would be translated into Chinese by Zhang Weimi 张维民 in 19981 as follows:
威武的船队 ， 强悍的勇士 ，
驶离卢济塔尼亚西部海岸 ，
越过自古茫无人迹的海崖 ，
甚至跨越塔普罗瓦那海角 ，
经历千难万险、无穷战争 ，
超出人力所能承受的极限 ，
在那荒僻遥远的异域之帮 ，
将灿烂辉煌的新帝国拓建。
张维民 (译) 《卢济塔尼亚人之歌 • 第一章 ， 一》
Both pilgrimages are true poetic adventure novels, the Lusíadas in poetry, the west pilgrimage in poetic prose and poetry. In the latter, Bodhisattva Guanyin will subdue 4 monsters who will be the companions of the monk Xuanzang. Bodhisattva takes an embroidered accent and a nine -lap ring to deliver to the monk. The latter, if effectively fulfilling his 14 -year mission, escapes the wheel of reincarnation (Jenner, 1994: 60), and his disciples, disobedient divine forces falling into the human world, will be able to return to heaven, where they will again occupy divine positions.
Guanyin also delivers a band, which causes terrible headaches to the disobedient King Monkey (Jenner, 1994: 60).
The monsters and indomitable spirits are presented.
First Sun Wukong (孙悟空 Sūn Wǔkōng), by King's disobedient monkey transits the obedient guardian of the Buddhist religion. Guanyin will free this indomitable spirit, prisoner in the mountain of the five elements (五行山 wǔxing shān), as punishment for the disobediences they have no account.
Then a heavenly marshal who will pass the pig. He is Marshal Tian Peng (天篷 Tiān Péng) of the Milky Way, tried to seduce the Divinity of the Moon, was punished by the emperor of Jade with axes and condemned to exile on earth. Bodhisattva baptized him with the nickname of Zhu Bajie (猪八戒 Zhū Bājiè), which means "Pig of the eight abstinences," and gave him the name Buddhist of Zhu Wuneng (猪悟能 Zhū Wǔnéng), ie "awakening pork for power" (1994: 63).
There will be an ogre that will be dominated and transformed into a sand monk. He was punished for being a distracted heavenly general. He paid the distraction with 800 whipping, having been exiled to Earth, where he devours travelers hidden in the waters of the floating river. Guanyin frees him, baptizing him with the nickname "sand" (沙 shā), and the Buddhist name of Wujing (牾净 Wǔjìng), which means "awake to purity."
Follows is the son of the West Sea Dragon King who will be metamorphosed on a white horse. He was denounced by his own father for burning the bright pearls of the palace. Jade emperor punished him, suspending him in the air. He gave him 300 whips, letting him wait for death. Prince Dragon is freed to turn into the white horse of the Xuánzàng monk, or as he is known in Chinese, on the white-dragon horse, (白龙马 白龙马 Lóng Mǎ).
In the term of the pilgrimage, Zhu Wuneng spiritualized, ascends to heaven, being rewarded with the heavenly position of cleans. But there are more honors to the group of victorious pilgrims who led the Sutras to China: the sand monk will receive the title of Golden Holy (Arhat), the monkey will be named Buddha of the victorious fight and the Sanzang monk will receive the title of Buddha do Merit (Buddha Candana-Punya.) As well as the white horse will rise the heavenly dragon.
Proverbial popular philosophy
Among the pilgrims are, as is well known, the monkey and the pig that escorts the great monk and Buddhist translator Xuanzang [唐玄奘 Xuánzàng (c. 602-664) or Sanzang (三藏 Sānzàng), the monk of the three Buddhist treasures (Buddha himself, teachings or Dharma, the monastic order or Sangha), the monastic order), Mandated by Emperor Emperor Táng Tàzōng (唐太宗, R. 626-649) to go to the Holy Scriptures from India. These will be delivered by the historic Buddha that resides in the Pico do Vulture, because "there are many greedy and evil creatures in the east, which are bought to cause suffering to others, killing and fighting nonstop." (Jenner, 1994: 58). Therefore, Buddha wanted to distribute the Scriptures through the Chinese world.
In popular and proverbial philosophy, which today rushes from mouth to mouth, it is drawn to the existential duel, between two of the five pilgrims, very similar to that of the work Don Quixote, by Miguel de Cervantes (1547-1616), composed between 1605 and 1615, in which the author puts in dialogue two opposing and complementary characters, Don Quixote and Sancho Pança: Romantic, dreamer and even utopian, almost only skin and bone, as it is like an incarnate spirit; The second, materialist, realistic, pragmatic, a very strong and plump "feet".
Mutatis Mutandis Zhu Bajie, the eight abstinence pig, and Sun Wugong, the west -west -awake to emptiness, have many of the opposite and complementary characteristics we find in D. Quixote and Sancho Pança. To confirm it, be aware of some of the said proverbials associated with King Monkey:
1) The seventy -two transformations of the monkey king (七十二变 qī shí èr bàn)
2) endless mutations (千变万化 qiān biàn wàn huà)
3) great confusion in the heavenly palace (大闹天宮 大闹天宮 nao tiān gōng)
4) Infinite Magic Powers (神通广大 Shéntōng-Guǎnggdà)
5) Appears and mysteriously disappears (神出鬼没 Shénchū-guǐmò)
He has an infinite spiritual ability, which allows him to accompany the universal movement and be in permanent transformation. It has numerous magical powers, learned from the best of Taoist masters, which enables him to successfully interfere in both the heavenly and earthly order, which is why he will be punished and only subjugated by the Buddha himself, which, tame it reveals it belongs to a superior spiritual and religious order.
After a five hundred -year -old punishment, inflicted by the Buddhism patriarch, will be able to join the group of pilgrims that will successfully introduce sutras and Buddhist teachings in China. Sun Wugong reveals to be a complex and multifaceted character, retaining and enhancing the best and worst of human nature in his portentous intelligence, challenging and disobedient. It has a lot of difficulty in dealing with Zhu Bajie, for the stupidity and lust of the partner, always ready to sloth out and surrender to exclusively carnal pleasures.
Zhu Bajie embodies some of the typical defects of human nature that are well revealed in the popular proverbial philosophy, as can be seen by some of the said mentioned:
1) Zhū Bájiè fails and never assumes his responsibilities (豬八戒上陈 Zhū Bájiè Shàng Chén)
2) Zhu Bajie is adorned with flowers (豬八戒戴花 Zhū Bájiè dài huā).
3) Zhū Bájiè is the mirror (CZHū Bájiè Kàn Jìngzi)
4) Zhū Bájiè departed by plane (豬八戒坐飞机 Zhū Bájiè Zuò Fēijī).
In the first proverb, there is the difficulty of the pig to assume guilt whenever it makes mistakes, and how to make mistakes is human, there are no accounts at the times when shaking responsibilities; Already in the second is denounced a very characteristic defect between the people, the vanity, that is, the constant need for ornaments, and not only from the physical point of view, because here not only counts the clothing but also the titles, positions and honors, in a total inability to strictly self -evaluate. In the third said, the physical and moral fealade, which attracts complaints from others, for the lack of composure and, finally, this expression is used when someone goes to the best, but in a worse way, that is, without dignity.
Finally, here are some more generally meaningful proverbs, taken from the west pilgrimage, who draw attention to the general evils of the world through the adventures of pilgrims, since, except Sun Wugong, others are very easily fooled by all kinds of monsters, demons, seductive spirits, etc., having great difficulty unraveling hypocritical behaviors in which they stumble through Journey, where they find “many guys to which they cannot see their hearts” or, in other words, abundant hypocrisy, as said (虚情假意 xū qing jiǎ yì).
Therefore, they are constantly involved in sarilhos or situations that “have no feet or head”, which is literally translated into Chinese by “unequal sizes” (七长八短 qīm tea bā duān). Now in a misleading world, pilgrims are those who with good intentions go with the greatest goal of saving China, so the group finds itself in the situation of “big ship, great storm”, or as it is said in Chinese, “great tree that attracts the wind” (树大招风 shūo fēng) in a world where when virtue grows a few centimeters, so wickedness increases several meters (， ， ， ， ， ， ， Give gāo yī chǐ, mó gāo yī zhàng).
Despite all the warnings, coming from popular wisdom and Romanesque adventures, the west pilgrimage and the Lusíadas end with the success of its protagonists, as the Portuguese expand around the world, Buddhism is introduced in China and all the characters in the poetic soap opera give rise to a proverbial source pedagogical.
Bibliographic references
ALVES, Ana Cristina.  2022. Chinese culture, a western perspective. Coord. Carmen Amando Mendes. Coimbra: Almedina and Macau Scientific and Cultural Center.
蔡志忠 (编绘) 2014 《西游记》北京: 现代出版社.
CAMões, Luís de. 1971. The Lusíadas. Lisbon: National Press of Lisbon.
CAMões, Luís de. 1998. 《卢济塔尼亚人之歌》. Beijing: East Foundation and Federation of China Artistic and Literary Associations.
JENNER, W.J.F. 1994. Wu Cheng'en. Journey to the West. «西遊記». Hong Kong: The Commercial Press.
吴承恩 2015 《西游记》. 全三册. 长沙: 岳麓书社.
“Proverbial stories related to Zhu Bajie”: 《描写猪八戒的成语》
http://wenwen.soso.com/z/q314030363.htm
“Proverbial stories related to Sun Wukong”: 《关于孙悟空的成语》 http://zhidao.baidu.com/question/95335747.html
This space has the collaboration of the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center in Lisbon, with the opinions expressed in the article of the entire responsibility of the authors ”https://www.ccccm.gov.pt
Beijing: East Foundation and Federation of China Artistic and Literary Associations.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Du Mu (803-852), Chang'an's poet, who in his imperial employee career was sent in successive missions to distant posts of the capital, often showed his inconvenience in the face of repeated separations. In one of his most admired poems he looked at the old narrative told since the Han Dynasty, which explains a traditional festival celebrated on the seventh day of the seventh moon, where once a year the meeting of a couple, cowboy Niulang and weaver Zhinu, identified with two shiny stars separated by the Milkway through the rest of the year.
This festival, Qixi Jie, "The Night of the Setes", is known to be an occasion to publicly emphasize the virtues and work of ladies, then usually confined to Gypeu. One night the poet noticed in a lone girl:
«A silver candle shines in the fall
before the cold painted panel,
Holding a small range of gauze
Silk light, pushes the moths away.
Of the stairs arrives a breeze
fresh like water,
She sits down and contemplating
And among the stars
Discover Niulang and Zhinu. »
The other women celebrating in groups were dedicated to various activities. In addition to the contemplation of the stars, they offered the gods, recited prayers, or dedicated themselves to weaving.
All this in an environment of reverence and joy that can be observed, for example, in a horizontal roll of Ding Guanpeng (1708-1771), ladies on the night of the seven appealing to their talents (paper ink, 28.7 x 386.5 cm, at the Shanghai Museum). From the weavers there would be some, especially those of educated families who would be weaving maybe with human hair, a beloved figure of Buddhism, Bodhisattva Guanyin.
In such a way the adepts felt close to the one who "contemplates the sounds" of those who direct them, postponing their release to help the enlightenment of others, who redo their figure as a form of asceticis.
Fang Weyi (1585-1668) was a literate, poet and painter that was part of these literati who, with their artistic erudition, permeated Chan Buddhism. He was born in a family of high employees and married early in 1602 but in the same year he had been widowed and lost his daughter of this marriage.
It is possible that these "heartbreaks of the heart" have deepened their Buddhist faith, lived in the reserve of the home environment. Among the numerous examples of this devotion include poems and paintings figuring Luohans and a portrait of Guanyin dressed in white (vertical roll, paint on paper, 56 x 26.6 cm, at the Palace Museum in Beijing). Figurated in a contrast between thick and undulating black traces to show off his wide white robes and the light detail with which he portrays his welcoming face. And the face as human, as much as the free gesture of the garments, reveals a strange transcendence.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Du Mu (803-852), Chang'an's poet, who in his imperial employee career was sent in successive missions to distant posts of the capital, often showed his inconvenience in the face of repeated separations. In one of his most admired poems he looked at the old narrative told since the Han Dynasty, which explains a traditional festival celebrated on the seventh day of the seventh moon, where once a year the meeting of a couple, cowboy Niulang and weaver Zhinu, identified with two shiny stars separated by the Milkway through the rest of the year.
This festival, Qixi Jie, "The Night of the Setes", is known to be an occasion to publicly emphasize the virtues and work of ladies, then usually confined to Gypeu. One night the poet noticed in a lone girl:
«A silver candle shines in the fall
before the cold painted panel,
Holding a small range of gauze
Silk light, pushes the moths away.
Of the stairs arrives a breeze
fresh like water,
She sits down and contemplating
And among the stars
Discover Niulang and Zhinu. »
The other women celebrating in groups were dedicated to various activities. In addition to the contemplation of the stars, they offered the gods, recited prayers, or dedicated themselves to weaving.
All this in an environment of reverence and joy that can be observed, for example, in a horizontal roll of Ding Guanpeng (1708-1771), ladies on the night of the seven appealing to their talents (paper ink, 28.7 x 386.5 cm, at the Shanghai Museum). From the weavers there would be some, especially those of educated families who would be weaving maybe with human hair, a beloved figure of Buddhism, Bodhisattva Guanyin.
In such a way the adepts felt close to the one who "contemplates the sounds" of those who direct them, postponing their release to help the enlightenment of others, who redo their figure as a form of asceticis.
Fang Weyi (1585-1668) was a literate, poet and painter that was part of these literati who, with their artistic erudition, permeated Chan Buddhism. He was born in a family of high employees and married early in 1602 but in the same year he had been widowed and lost his daughter of this marriage.
It is possible that these "heartbreaks of the heart" have deepened their Buddhist faith, lived in the reserve of the home environment. Among the numerous examples of this devotion include poems and paintings figuring Luohans and a portrait of Guanyin dressed in white (vertical roll, paint on paper, 56 x 26.6 cm, at the Palace Museum in Beijing). Figurated in a contrast between thick and undulating black traces to show off his wide white robes and the light detail with which he portrays his welcoming face. And the face as human, as much as the free gesture of the garments, reveals a strange transcendence.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Du Mu (803-852), Chang'an's poet, who in his imperial employee career was sent in successive missions to distant posts of the capital, often showed his inconvenience in the face of repeated separations. In one of his most admired poems he looked at the old narrative told since the Han Dynasty, which explains a traditional festival celebrated on the seventh day of the seventh moon, where once a year the meeting of a couple, cowboy Niulang and weaver Zhinu, identified with two shiny stars separated by the Milkway through the rest of the year.
This festival, Qixi Jie, "The Night of the Setes", is known to be an occasion to publicly emphasize the virtues and work of ladies, then usually confined to Gypeu. One night the poet noticed in a lone girl:
«A silver candle shines in the fall
before the cold painted panel,
Holding a small range of gauze
Silk light, pushes the moths away.
Of the stairs arrives a breeze
fresh like water,
She sits down and contemplating
And among the stars
Discover Niulang and Zhinu. »
The other women celebrating in groups were dedicated to various activities. In addition to the contemplation of the stars, they offered the gods, recited prayers, or dedicated themselves to weaving.
All this in an environment of reverence and joy that can be observed, for example, in a horizontal roll of Ding Guanpeng (1708-1771), ladies on the night of the seven appealing to their talents (paper ink, 28.7 x 386.5 cm, at the Shanghai Museum). From the weavers there would be some, especially those of educated families who would be weaving maybe with human hair, a beloved figure of Buddhism, Bodhisattva Guanyin.
In such a way the adepts felt close to the one who "contemplates the sounds" of those who direct them, postponing their release to help the enlightenment of others, who redo their figure as a form of asceticis.
Fang Weyi (1585-1668) was a literate, poet and painter that was part of these literati who, with their artistic erudition, permeated Chan Buddhism. He was born in a family of high employees and married early in 1602 but in the same year he had been widowed and lost his daughter of this marriage.
It is possible that these "heartbreaks of the heart" have deepened their Buddhist faith, lived in the reserve of the home environment. Among the numerous examples of this devotion include poems and paintings figuring Luohans and a portrait of Guanyin dressed in white (vertical roll, paint on paper, 56 x 26.6 cm, at the Palace Museum in Beijing). Figurated in a contrast between thick and undulating black traces to show off his wide white robes and the light detail with which he portrays his welcoming face. And the face as human, as much as the free gesture of the garments, reveals a strange transcendence.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Environment | Macau registers a new maximum temperatures in 2024</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/ambiente-macau-regista-novo-maximo-de-temperaturas-em-2024/</link><description>The direction of environmental protection services yesterday launched new data on the environmental landscape in the territory, in the Macao Encounters of the Macao 2024. The data is not encouraging: last year a new record of maximum temperatures, more rain and typhoons were recorded. More electricity and water was spent, more garbage was produced and fewer recyclable waste was collected
 
Lame
The Government of Macao, through the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) announced yesterday that 2024 reached a maximum temperature record in the territory, and there was also an increase in typhoons and precipitation.
According to the Macau 2024 state report, the average temperature last year was 23.6 ° C, precisely the value that had been reached in 2019, the highest since the records began, in 1952. The average temperature of 2024 was 0.8 ° C higher than the average climacteric (average of 30 years, between 1991 and 2020), according to the document prepared by DSPA.
In addition, Macau registered 42 days considered to be hot last year, more 10.7 days than the climacteric average, 29 hot nights, 17.5 than the average, and 29 cold days, less 10.1 days than the average.
Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) classify as hot days when the maximum temperature is equal to or greater than 33ºC and the nights at which the minimum temperature is at least 28ºC. As for the days considered cold, they are those at which the minimum temperature does not exceed 12ºC.
"With global warming, the occurrence of extreme weather phenomena is increasingly frequent," said DSPA in the report.
In 2024, Macau was affected by seven tropical cyclones, known as tuffons, and for the first time three tropical cyclones affected Macao in November, the last month of the typhoons, which begins in May.
According to the report, the region received last year a total precipitation of 2,029.2 mm, "slightly higher than the climacteric average." DSPA also said that since 1970, sea level in Macao has risen at an average rate of about 3.5 millimeters per year.
Also worldwide, 2024 was the hottest year that there are records and exceeded for the first time the 1.5 ° C above the pre-industrial level, in January the copernicus European service advanced in January. Last week, the world weather organization predicted that temperatures should continue to reach record values ​​by the end of the decade.
More people, more expenses
The DSPA report also tells that with the arrival of more tourists to Macau, there were also more waste and spending on water consumption, for example. "With the improvement of the economy, the number of visitors in 2024 increased 23.8 percent in annual terms for almost 35 million, having recovered about 90 percent of the pre-pound level. Tourist intensity also registered a certain increase, with GDP [Gross Domestic Product] climbed 8.8 percent. In addition, there was a slight increase in the population at the end of the year."
Thus, it is added, "in relation to environmental indicators, economic and population growth led to the rise of estimated local emissions of greenhouse gases, invoiced water volume, electricity consumption and the amount of urban solid waste, compared to 2023". "During the pandemic, there was a decrease in the various economic and environmental indicators. However, with the constant improvement of the economy, most of these indicators rose again," is explained.
With regard to the volume of invoiced water, in thousands of cubic meters, by 2023 the record was 89,164 and last year, 94.123, which constitutes an increase of 5.6 percent. Regarding electricity consumption, in millions of kW/h, in 2023 it was 5,740, while in 2024 consumption went to 6,030, plus 5.1 percent. The report also highlights the tons of urban solid waste produced, which in 2023 was 501,512, rising 5.1 percent last year to 526,979 tons.
Another worrying fact of waste level was the fall, for the third consecutive year, the volume of recyclable waste collected, which went from 24.5 percent at 2021 to 21.7 percent last year. Changed for kids, of all recyclable waste generated in Macao, only about one fifth are collected for recycling.
In the report, IP Kuong Lam, director of DSPA, indicates that last year, "with the ongoing economic recovery, there was greater pressure on various environmental indicators, while climate change became more severe." Despite the results, the official said that the objectives are "to encourage greater participation of the population in environmental initiatives and together to achieve the view of building a macao with low carbon emissions."
A question of gases
The report released yesterday by DSPA also accounts for the panorama of greenhouse gases (GHG) gases, and last year, a global increase of “about ten percent, including carbon dioxide (C02), which represented 90 percent”.
It also highlights DSPA that “the estimated emissions of GHE from the various sources have registered upon the same period (2023), except for landfill residues, and the most significant increases were verified in estimated emissions from local electricity production and air transport”.
In addition, it is stated that, in 2024, the main source of Emission of GHG and CO2 was land transport, followed by local electricity production, waste incineration, trade, domestic consumption and services. "The main sources of CH4 emissions [methane] were the waste deposited in landfills and the treatment of wastewater, while the latter was also the main source of N2O emission [nitrous oxide]," he stresses in the document.
DSPA clarifies, regarding the tendency of GHG emissions, that "after reaching the peak in 2017, local Emissions of GHG showed a decreasing tendency, year after year, having reached its lower value during the pandemic." However, with the recovery of economic activities and the great movement of people, especially "in the last two years, the estimated emissions of these gases has gradually rise again."
The air we breathe
Also with regard to air quality data is not encouraging, because in 2024 “the number of days with the average quality of air classified as 'good' or 'moderate' recorded in the six Macao air quality monitoring stations reached 88 percent, slightly lower than 2023”.
There was, in a total of the year, 15 to 34 days with “unhealthy” classification, and only two days obtained the classification of “very unhealthy”.
According to DSPA, “the pollutants detected in the air monitoring stations were mainly ozone (O3) and thin particles suspended (PM2.5)”, while “at Berma da Estrada station (Ká-Hó), the highest index detected all year round, classified as 'very unhealthy', was the O3 the main pollutant”.
Last year, July was the best air quality month, while October to December obtained the worst qualification according to data from Macao air monitoring stations.
The report also reveals that “in terms of compliance with atmospheric pollutant concentrations in 2024, average annual PM10 and PM2.5 concentrations recorded in the various monitoring stations were lower than standard values”, while “the average annual nitrogen dioxide concentrations (NO2) also set below standard values, except for Road Berma measures (Macao) and at the High Density Areas station (Macau) ”.
More optimistic data is also revealed “daily averages of sulfur dioxide concentrations (SO2) and the maximum averages of eight hours of carbon monoxide concentrations (CO) verified in the various stations throughout the year”, as “both were below standard values”.
“In all seasons there was a record of the maximum averages of eight hours of O3 concentrations to exceed standard values ​​in some days. In relation to atmospheric pollutant concentrations recorded in the monitoring stations, generally the average annual concentrations of PM2.5 and NO2, while PM10 and CO descended”, and “as in the road station season (Macao) Only in 2024 did SO2 and O3 begin to be monitored, no comparisons were made. ”</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:16:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Cooperation | A look at the approach to Spanish -speaking countries</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/cooperacao-um-olhar-sobre-a-aproximacao-aos-paises-de-lingua-espanhola/</link><description>The MSAR was already approaching Spain, but the chief executive began to refer to official speeches the importance of cooperation between Macao and Spanish -speaking countries, as well as the usual Lusophone world. Analysts relate these words to the current panorama of relations between China and Spain
 
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, has expressed in some discourses the importance of having to establish economic and commercial relations not only with Portuguese -speaking countries, but also with Spanish -speaking ones. Last month, on a public occasion, the government leader stated that the territory has to "welcome foreign friends to invest in Macau and also to realize his dreams in Macao." Sam Hou Fai highlighted the area of ​​advanced technology, stressing that “they can come from Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries” because “as long as they are in favor of economic diversification, they are always welcome,” he added.
Moreover, after the inauguration of the new government, Tai Kin IP, secretary for the economy and finance, made, in March, a visit to several European countries, leading a delegation that passed through Spain, Portugal, Belgium and Monaco to deepen “international links and explore opportunities for cooperation”, according to official information released at the time.
This approach to the Spanish -language universe, in addition to the usual connection already established between China and the Lusophone world, can have several origins: the growing relationship between China and Spain, as well as the desire to diversify the economy by MSAR, say analysts contacted by HM.
“The interpretation of Sam Hou Fai Declaration is very objective and pragmatic and can be summed up to the Macao economy diversification project, for which companies and investors are not only in Macao, but also from Portuguese-speaking countries. But the fact is that companies and institutions in Portuguese-speaking countries are not being effective in response to this need for Macao. For cooperation it seems logical to me, ”said economist Maria Fernanda Ilhéu, former resident of Macao and president of the Friends Association of the New Seda Route (ARS).
According to the leader, “Macau is a pure market economy, is classified by the World Trade Organization as a free port with its own international agreements both in the economic, commercial, investment, financial, health, sports, sports, international relations agreements with various organizations. Therefore, the business in Macau is very free, and the part of the government of Macau is to promote and frame this opening”. "As Sam Hou Fai says, all companies and investors who bring Macao economy diversification solutions are welcome," he added.
To Cátia Miriam Costa, professor at ISCTE - University Institute of Lisbon, and specialist in Chinese foreign policy and Macao, considered the HM that “this connection to the Spanish stems from the high -level official visits made by the Spanish government to China, that is, there is certainly one of the consequences of the repeated presence of Spanish diplomacy on a very high level, reinforcing the ties between the two. countries ”.
THE IMPORTANCE OF GLOBAL SOUTH
It is true that Beijing, in the words of President XI Jinping, has shown great interest in the approach of the countries of the so -called “global south”, where Portuguese and Spanish speaks, essentially. For Cátia Miriam Costa, here also resides another explanation for the change of paradigm in the field of commercial and economic cooperation.
"It seems to me that recent meetings with high Spanish political representatives have influenced this decision, along with China's increasing political investment in the global south where Portuguese and Spanish are, in fact, the most spoken languages."
For Académica, "the strategy of using Macau as a convergence point may be historically justified by its cosmopolitanism, but also by its traditional role in including the routes that connected Asia to Latin America." In addition, "adds to a historical perspective, a contemporary view for a region that needs economic diversification and benefits from this proximity to distant spaces, whether historical or culturally." Cátia Miriam Costa understands, therefore, that "Spanish can be seen as an additional value to Portuguese, without distorting the paradiplomacy strategy defined for Macao early on."
The inclusion of Equatorial Guinea in the Macao Forum cannot be ignored, as a result of its entry to the CPLP - community of Portuguese -speaking countries. However, Cátia Miriam Costa believes that this change has little or nothing to do with the inclusion of Spanish -speaking countries in the official commercial approach discourse.
"The inclusion of Equatorial Guinea in the Macao Forum stems from another circumstance, that of his participation as a member of the CPLP. In this sense, it was a logical step to its integration into the dynamics of the Forum. However and although it can count as a positive element in this approach, the leverage that Equatorial Guinea has in the Hispanic or Hispanic speaking world," he pointed out.
ASES BY ARE
Maria Fernanda Ilhéu also highlighted the fact that the only direct air connection between Macao and Europe will be for Madrid and not to Lisbon. “By chance, TAP or the Portuguese government have contacted Air Macau or the Macao government expressing interest in resuming this airline? I don't know, but I know that this connection will greatly contribute to strengthening the Spanish presence in Macao, whether in tourism, commerce or investment.”
The guardian highlights the complementarity factor of the air route. "Is the Portuguese and Spanish presence in Macau is incompatible? It doesn't look like, but it is competitive, it may even be beneficial if they know how to collaborate and gain scale in the Great Bay area, but Portugal has to strive more to their presence in Macau is not a historic relic."
Moreover, the economist does not forget the role that Portuguese foreign policy may play in this issue, with the removal of Huawei in Portugal and a closer approach to Beijing in recent times.
“Portugal's decision banning the use of Huawei equipment says mainly respect for the economic relations of Portugal with mainland China and it is framed by a fearful diplomatic relationship that the Portuguese government followed from 2019 to 2024, contrary to the Spanish diplomatic relationship. It should be noted that the Spanish Prime Minister visited China several times during this period and the Portuguese government alone was represented by the foreign business minister. At the Boao Forum in Hainan, with a brief pass for Beijing. ”
Thus, Maria Fernanda Ilhéu understands that between 2019 and 2024 “the Portuguese government and the Portuguese civil society were very conditioned by the American narrative of cold war and the formation of two antagonistic blocks, not knowing how to keep the line followed by 2019 to proceed with a relationship with China supported by the friendship and confidence of nearly 500 years of cooperation in Macau”.
The necessary work
For the economist and president of ANSRs, it is necessary to take into account the investments and business movements made in recent times to perceive the position of Portugal and Spain in this domain.
“The last major investment of a large Chinese company in Portugal was registered in 2020, and only now is this type of investment with Calb investment [SINE Battery producer] that is in the implementation and licensing phase. If we see the same type of investments in Spain from 2020 to 2024 we can record five major energy investments, by China Three Gorges and Huadian; Transport, Geely, Chery Auto and Envision Group; a major investment in agriculture by Yankuang Beijing Energy and also a major investment in the health sector by Worg Pharmaceuticals. ”
For the official, “a lot of work will have to be done by the new Portuguese government to develop Portuguese economic cooperation with mainland China and MSAR, but it will also have to be accompanied by Portuguese business fabric,” he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Budget 2025 | Government removes 12 billion from the estimates of the game's revenues</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/orcamento-2025-governo-retira-12-mil-milhoes-as-estimativas-das-receitas-do-jogo/</link><description>The advanced forecast in November by the executive, which pointed to 240 billion casinos gross revenues in 2025, was reviewed. The government now predicts that revenues have a break of 12 billion patacas, forcing the budgetary review yesterday by André Cheong yesterday
 
Yesterday were released by the Executive Council, the data on the budget review for this year, which happens due to the low forecast of the amount of gross revenues of the game, which depend, on large scale, the local economy and public revenues.
Thus, if the executive initially estimated that the game's gross gross revenues would be, this year, from 240 billion patacas, this value now drops to 228 billion, or 12 billion. Regarding the average monthly estimate, 19 billion patacas in gross revenues are now foreseen, because "the situation is not like the one planned."
In yesterday's presentation, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, and also spokesman for the Executive Board, said that “after study and analysis of the current global economic conjuncture and the effective situation of exploitation of the game sector from the beginning of this year to the present moment, it is proposed that the annual estimate of gross revenues of the game will be reduced from 240 billion to 228 billion, thus serving as to Main base of the financial budget financial revenues, and that relevant budgetary revenue rules are properly adjusted. ”
In November last year, when Ho Iat Seng was about to leave the position of Chief Executive, predictions for gross revenues were 240 billion, taking into account the initial version of the budget proposal for 2025. At the time, the forecast represented an increase in what had been estimated to 2024, which was the gross revenues of casinos by 216 billion Patacas, an increase of 11.1 percent. Given the gross game recipes in 2023, the estimate for 2025 was a 31.1 percent increase.
It is important to highlight that the new forecast below expected is an annual increase of only 0.5 percent in gross revenues, when the initial numbers translated into annual growth of 5.8 percent. In the first five months of this year, the game's revenues rose only 1.7 percent annually to 97.7 billion patacas.
Balance Guarantee
In response to journalists, the subdirector of finance services, Ho Silvestre in Mare, said the new calculations were based on the data provided by the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination Services (DICJ) in contrast to the first semester public expenses.
“In this proposed budget law we made an analysis of the global conjuncture and took into account a different model regarding the consumption of tourists in Macau. We made general considerations for these estimates and, according to DICJ, from January to April this year, an average of 19 billion and there was an increase to 21.1 billion (gross revenues). reaching the 20 billion [ragous game revenues, on average], so in the second half of the year there will be uncertainties. ”
"In this budget we intend to take a balance in expense and revenue. After an evaluation at the first half of the year, we can make an assessment taking into account the amount of 19 billion Patacas, and according to the current expense of the MSAR, we were able to get a more balanced budget," he added.
In general terms, and according to the explanatory note presented by André Cheong, the total amount of the ENGRICIAN INTEGRATED ORDINARY BUDGET for the 2025 economic year is 116.5 billion, when a revenue of the 121 billion patacas was expected to be expected to be expected to be expected to be expected to reduce the DSF's gross revenue revenue. The cut is 4.56 billion patacas.
In addition, the official said, only the reduction in the tax raised on the game, due to the break in gross revenues, translates into 450 million patacas for the administration. It should also be noted that budgetary expense within the PIDDA [Administration Development Investment and Development Plan] is reviewed to about 19.587 billion Patacas.
Budgetary expense rises 2.5 percent due to education and social support
The government ensures that, in the proposal for a budget for this year, the construction of a new campus of the University of Macau (one) on the island of Hengqin will contribute, in part, to the increase of expense, around 2.5 percent, as well as “the increase in budget in relation to subsidies attributed to vulnerable groups and investment in research and scientific and technological development”.
In the budget proposal presented yesterday, there is a approximate amount of 1.7 billion Patacas for the construction of the new UM campus, said the subdirect of Finance Services (DSF). In addition, at the level of scientific and technological investment was added the amount of 340 million patacas “for investments in the scope of science and technology, such as the acquisition of laboratory devices, to satisfy the measure and policies of the Government of Masters,” said Ho Silvestre in Mais.
"For construction is expected an expense of about eight billion patacas. As the campus is built on Hengqin Island, the cost must be calculated in Renminbis, which is about seven billion. This is the data we can have at this time," said the official.
Support for support
With regard to social support, the budget proposal for this year reveals an increase of 2.86 billion of Patacas in the expected expenses, as a way of reinforcing these supports. In total, the rise in expenses is 2.5 percent, to 116.2 billion patacas.
As for the preparation of the budget for next year, it is being prepared and the watchword is containment. "We are already elaborating the budget for the year 2026, and all services of the Government of MSAR need to consider more about their expenses, especially given the current conjuncture. In the budgetary elaboration phase we take a prudent and rigorous attitude towards the expenses," said the subdirector of DSF.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 00:29:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Pecunaries Checks | Former Beneficiaries defend better assignment criteria</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/cheques-pecuniarios-ex-beneficiarios-defendem-melhores-criterios-de-atribuicao/</link><description>Given the changes to the pecuniary reimbursement plan, HM has heard three permanent residents who will no longer receive the check because they do not reside permanently in Macao, including a macanese born in the territory. Arnaldo Gonçalves, academic and former Beneficiary, defends a better distribution of support depending on the income of families
 
The rules for the attribution of pecuniary checks will change and now it is really necessary to be 183 days a year in the territory. The exceptions are some and arrest with students from Macau who are attending courses abroad or residents to work remotely to Macau and who are enrolled in the Social Security Fund, among other situations.
However, many people will be left out, even though they have lived for several decades in the territory or even macanese born in Macau, that is, many of the members of the Macanese diaspora.
In the case of Arnaldo Gonçalves, a permanent resident resident in Lisbon, he lived several decades in Macau, having worked for the government and was a university professor in the area of ​​political science. Six years ago, he returned to Portugal, being renovated, and told HM that he was already waiting for the day he was going to stop receiving the ten thousand dates annually.
"This measure aims to give people a counterpart, given the difficulties existing in consumption and the characteristics of life. I don't live in Macau, and I think from the point of view of equity, the government has never been able to make a fairer regime from the distributive point of view, because there is no system of attribution from the income, and deep down there are multimillionaires that gain the subseck, like the pensioners, all," he said. This is what Arnaldo Gonçalves says "lament". "It is hard work to make an assessment of people's economic possessions, and so everyone receives the same as it is more practical in administrative terms," ​​he said.
Maria João Ferreira, macaense of gem, daughter of the famous poet Adé, will also fail to receive the pecuniary check. He says he understands, but also criticizes the executive's positions. "I was already waiting and accepted with all the tranquility. It is fair, since I do not live there and I have the chance to be 183 days. I thank the time of checks that was dismissed. I lived in Macau until I was 16, but I was born there and still have family. Even the pandemic was there every year of vacation. mentioned.
Maria João Ferreira, currently in the direction of Macao's house in Lisbon, says she was “shocked” with a very concrete case. "A few years ago, when he was doing his doctorate, he learned of a civil servant who did two service committees in Macao and was a contemplated BIR money and even told me, not just me, that I thought it was funny as he was there so recently, he was entitled to such a benefit," he said.
"This is what I think is bad. It is one thing to go to do a service committee in public administration, or two or three, but it was never, in fact, resident. It is, as it were, an immigrant, because it will only work. This is how I see things," he added.
Patacas Amealdas
For Arnaldo Gonçalves, the ten thousand annual patacas served as a “Management Fund” for trips to the territory, where he still has family and where he travels frequently. "I've never used this money for personal purposes, you know? But I think these changes are a good measure, justifiable, and I even think it's selfish, that I've been entitled to this support for so many years. There are other people who need it," he said.
In the case of Maria João Ferreira, the cash of the pecuniary check was also used for expenses in Macao and with trips to the territory. "I have an account in Macao, and when I went there, if I needed to buy the plane ticket, my sister said the money here, or this money served to fund my stay in Macao," he explained.
Sofia Mota, a permanent resident and former Maradora in Macao, regrets the absence of explanations for these changes. "It depends on what the pecuniary check is for, whether it is a way of distributing the wealth or profits of casinos to the people who are part of the territory, or have already done; either if it is a condition to be part of the territory. I do not realize the premise in which the pecuniary check measure is based, and depending on the premise these changes may be more or less acceptable."
The teacher considers that "it makes no sense that those who contribute to social security at their own initiative, as is my case, are not covered." "It seems that there is a first and second and second social security system. People who come to Portugal to provide family care seem not to be covered and yet are out of the territory for reasons of force majeure. What is meant by providing subsistence to family members, is not realizing the function of the check and the coherence of exceptions," he said.
Sofia Mota confesses that she also used money to "a management fund to go to Macau, or to invest in formation."
The first reactions
The changes to the pecuniary reimbursement program were presented at the end of May and report that three groups will be exempt from the obligation to be 183 days a year in Macao and thus receive the check. They are the residents under 22 in 2024 and where one parent meets the requirements for receiving the check; the beneficiaries of the disability pension and the beneficiaries of disability allowance.
There are eight other situations where residents may have access to the check. This is what happens when residents attend higher education outside the territory; When they are hospitalized in a hospital outside the sons, those who are over 65 and live in the interior of China or, even under 65, have health reasons that justify the permanence inside China. Residents who work outside Macao are also covered by the exceptions to an employer registered at the MSAR Social Security Fund and residents outside the MSAR who are responsible for the family aggregate subsistence.
These are also attached to the exercise of official functions outside Macao; the registration of domicile, work or study in the deepened cooperation zone; And yet the work done in the cities of large bay except Hong Kong that is left out.
Deputy Pereira Coutinho manifested against the changes to the pecuniary check referring to violate the Macao Basic Law, namely in article 25, which guarantees the equality of the residents of Macao before the law and prohibits discrimination. The article determines that "the residents of Macao are equal before the law, without discrimination due to nationality, ancestry, race, gender, language, religion, political or ideological convictions, economic instruction and situation or social condition."
More recently, the Macao Synergy Association publicly stated that changes to the pecuniary reimbursement plan in economic development are not in accordance with the wishes of the population. Ron Lam also criticized the executive for applying the changes “in a hurry” which only came to cause more controversy: “the government was in a hurry and applied a sudden measure, without making any public consultation, with only behind -the -scenes movements leading to the population to question governance,” he said. "Consultations with local associations were simulated, which only generated more criticism and caused more unnecessary controversy," he added.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:15:45</pubDate></item><item><title>EU has to be “much more vocal” about Israel in Gaza</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/03/ue-tem-de-ser-muito-mais-vocal-sobre-israel-em-gaza/</link><description>Former European doctor Elisa Ferreira demanded yesterday to the European Union to be “much more vocal” about the boundaries that Israel “is surpassing” in the war against Hamas, defending an articulated voice of the community bloc.
"Europe, even because of all the defense of human rights, has to be much more vocal to saying to Israel that it cannot exceed the boundaries it is exceeding, and that current international agreements do not allow certain actions," Elisa Ferreira said in statements to Lusa after a conference at the Consulate General of Portugal in Macau.
However, the academic noted that Member States have never attributed competencies to the European Union in defense that allow it, for example, to intervene with armament in cases of country invasions.
"That said, many countries-Ireland, Spain-they moved a lot, and I think there is a joint and joint voice to prevent us with a sense of impotence in the face of deaths that are absolutely unacceptable in the 21st century," said the former Minister of the Environment (1995-1999) and the planning and territorial planning (1999-2002) in the governments of António Guterres. Elisa Ferreira stressed that there have already been “there were some expressions of this will” by Lisbon and expects “to keep up”.
PEACE STEPS
In late May, Slovenia, Spain, Ireland and Norway, who recognized the Palestinian state a year ago, appealed to all countries to do the same compared to Palestine and Israel, as it is a necessary step for peace in the region.
"We remember that recognition is another step towards the implementation of the solution of both states and we appeal to the international community to take the necessary steps to make it a reality, among them, the individual recognition of Palestine and Israel by the countries that have not yet done it," reads a "joint statement."
Israel's retaliation for Hamas' attack on October 7 caused more than 54,000 dead, the destruction of almost all Gaza strip infrastructures and the forced displacement of hundreds of thousands of people.
Elisa Ferreira wants to look for new partners like China
Former European doctor Elisa Ferreira defended Lusa yesterday that the European Union must rethink partnerships and look for new interlocutors, including Beijing, to keep “a great actor” on the international scenario.
"If there is an opportunity in every crisis, as I think the Chinese say, there is also an opportunity in this US leadership crisis, because it has shown that Europe has to know where it wants to go and not lose control over its own agenda, and, on the other hand, it has to diversify partners abroad," said Lusa, the former Portuguese minister, after a conference at the Consulate General of Portugal.
In the current context of instability, China “has to be a great partner,” said the academic. "China is a great power. I think it has always been latent, now it is completely affirmed, especially in future areas, in stories of new digital and environmental technologies." "For a long time, Europe wanted to be driving out of new clean energy, energy savings technologies, etc.; I think China, when it defines it, when it determines, when it is organized, accelerates with an unstoppable speed," he noticed.
In Macao at an invitation from the Institute of European Studies, Elisa Ferreira inaugurated yesterday the “conversations in the Consulate” cycle, with the lecture “Portugal: from the successes of the democratic Portugal to the crossroads of the present”.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Dsal | Number of occupational accidents suffers slight breakdown in annual terms</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/03/dsal-numero-de-acidentes-laborais-sofre-quebra-ligeira-em-termos-anuais/</link><description>Data related to occupational accidents last year reveal stability compared to 2023: about five thousand people, 5,095, suffered accidents at work, slightly less than 5,293 victims of 2023, while the number of deadly victims arising from these incidents remained in a dozen
Photo: Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro
Data released on Friday by the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) show how in the space of one year, between 2023 and 2024, the panorama of occupational accidents remained stable, and even a light break in the number of occurrences and the same number of dead.
According to the report related to 2024, a total of 5,095 workers suffered an accident at work, and the main cause was the “fall of people”, which represented the 25.4 percent bar of the total of incidents, followed by the “raising in or between objects”, which represented 19.3 percent of all incidents, and the “march or shock in objects”, with 16.1 percent.
According to the DSAL report released last year, there were 5,293 victims of occupational accidents in 2023, and almost all occurrences (5,253) resulted in temporary work disability. Only 30 cases resulted in the person's permanent disability, and 10 people died. Last year, DSAL also recorded the same number of deaths from occupational accidents, and a case is associated with an alleged “infringement of occupational safety and health legislation”.
"All mortal cases were sent to the court organs for due processing, and, later, DSAL will adjust the data in accordance with the judgments given," reads the report relating to 2024.
DSSA says investigations to all labor incidents, having applied fines to two entities for “infringements to occupational safety and health” in cases involving two workers. In addition, fines to 43 persons were applied for infringement of the legal regime of reparation for emerging damages of occupational accidents and occupational diseases, involving 303 workers in total.
More men than women
The report also presents more specific data on occupational accidents last year. Thus, of the 5,095 cases, 5,063 resulted in temporary disability, and 557 workers managed to return to service on the same day of the occurrence of the accident highlights DSal. However, a total of 22 people ended up having permanent disability. Noteworthy is the number of people who were hit in the hands (1,336), followed by accidents in the feet zone with 894 occurrences, various parts of the body with 831 cases, and accidents in the trunk zone with 743 cases.
Statistical data also show that men dominate with regard to victims: thus, in 2024, 255 victims aged between 16 and 24 years. In this age group, 165 men suffered occupational accidents as opposed to 90 women. The numbers rise in people aged 25 to 44, in which there were 2,719 occurrences, reaching 1,568 men and 1,151 women.
From 45 to 64 there were 1,908 occurrences, this time, more women than men: 1,188 compared to 720 male workers. Highlight for 213 cases of occupational accidents involving people at renovation age, ie 65 years or older, where 120 women were affected in contrast with 93 men.
The 2024 data also look at the type of profession in which more accidents occurred: dominate the “administrative employees”, with 1,318 cases, followed by the “staff of services, sellers and similar work”, with 1,207 cases, as well as “unqualified workers” with 1,219 occurrences. There were also 413 occurrences in the group of “workers of industrial production and artisans” and 196 in “operators of machines, drivers and assemblers”. In the category of “intermediate level technicians and professionals” were registered 420 work incidents.
Let's go by parts
If we look at the numbers of occupational accidents taking into account the branch of economic activity, it is observed that they dominate “cultural and recreational activities, lottery and other services”, therefore, to the game and entertainment sector, with 1,512 cases occurred last year. Following are accidents in “hotels, restaurants and the like”, with 1,293 cases, as well as 414 incidents in the area of ​​“transport, storage and communications”. In the construction sector, there were 374 accidents.
It should be noted that the 2023 data is also similar in terms of economic activity where more work accidents occurred and in terms of the gender of workers, with 52 percent of men and 48 percent of affected women. In 2023, there was a higher incidence of occupational accidents in ages between 25 and 44 years, representing 53.6 percent, while at the age of 45 and 64 years, the percentage of accidents lowered to 37.2 percent.
The 2023 DSal report also showed that “cultural and recreational activities, lottery and other services” (29.5 percent), “hotels, restaurants and the like” (23.2 percent) and “transport, storage and communications” (10.8 percent) occupied the first three positions compared to the total number of occupational accident victims.
Regarding the professions, the “unqualified workers” (26 percent), the “staff of services, sellers and similar workers” (24 percent) and the “administrative employees” (22.9 percent) occupied the first three positions in relation to the total victims of occupational accidents.
Action and reaction
The 2024 DSA DSA report also reveals that 3,550 inspection visits were made to different workplaces, such as construction shipyards, industrial and commercial establishments, which resulted in 395 improvement recommendations and fines in 10 situations due to lack of safety.
Last year, four suspensions of the operation of shipyards were ordered in the context of occupational safety and health verification, the most serious consequence after the application of fines or awareness.
Dsal also points out that, last year, 404 seminars were performed for different sectors and types of work, which had the participation of 17,148 people. Regarding courses on occupational safety and health, formations were carried out to obtain the occupational security card in the construction, with 26,590 participants, which resulted in the issuance of 25,069 cards. The “Safety Training Courses in Specific Construction Works” had 3,167 participants, and 2,895 certificates were issued.
In another important area for the local economy, hotel and restoration, 25,965 participants participated in the “training courses to obtain the occupational safety card in hotel and restoration”, with the issuance of 25,020 cards.</description><pubDate>2025-06-03 01:08:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Physical Fitness | Study shows good results in preschool children</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/30/aptidao-fisica-estudo-mostra-bons-resultados-em-criancas-do-pre-escolar/</link><description>One study analyzed the physical fitness of preschool children in Macao. The results point to “modest growth and development”, “small increases in height and weight” and “improvements in speed, agility, muscle strength and flexibility”, thanks to the 2015 curriculum reform that bet on school sports
 
The government is to be congratulated with regard to sports in preschool, according to an academic study that evaluated children of kindergartens and statistical data of their physical fitness provided by the Institute of Sport (ID).
In "Temporal Trends of Physical Fitness in MSAR preschool children between 2002 and 2020", published in the Journal of Exercise &amp; Fitness, academics point to "modest growth and development among preschool students." Statistically evaluated parameters focus on performance in activities such as running, length jump or march. The work is by SIU Ming Choi, Faculty of Education, Grant R. Tomkinson, Justin J. Lang, Cristina Cadenas-Sanchez, Haoyu Dong, Si Man Lei, Eric Tsz Chun Poon, the latter linked to the Department of Sports Sciences and Physical Education at the Chinese University of Hong Kong.
The authors have taken the annual ID data to realize how the children's body has evolved in recent years, allowing you to perceive data related to weight, height and body measurements. Thus, it is read that there were “small increases in height, weight and circumferences, improvements in speed-agility, muscle strength and flexibility of the lower body and flexibility, and declines in the muscle power of the upper body and equilibrium capacity”.
The study reveals "significant but small increases at the time, weight and circumference of the chest," while "the physical aptitude trends were contradictory, with declines ranging from insignificant to small throwing and equilibrium performance." There were also “insignificant improvements to small in other measures” of the body, with the authors to point out that “no significant differences were found between genres, which indicates equitable development” between boys and girls.
In general terms, “an increase in body size and modest but significant improvements in various components of physical fitness, such as speed-agility, muscle power, and flexibility, and flexibility, and declines elsewhere” were recorded.
The authors consider that these results “can be attributed to a combination of factors of the education system and the domestic environment”, as “the Macao Education System and the curriculum guidelines have given priority to the development of physical education and the acquisition of motor skills”.
It is also noteworthy that Macau was "the first region of China to incorporate kindergarten in its free education system since 2007, making the education of its residents a fundamental priority."
The study also mentions the 2015 curriculum reform, which “explicitly emphasizes learning fundamental movement skills, such as locomotor (walking, running, bouncing, equilibrium, trigger) and object control (launch, catch) through various physical activities and games designed by teachers”.
The work emphasizes the importance of guardians in the connection of children with sport, remembering the pandemic years. “Parents' positive influence on the modeling of physical activity can also play a role in these improvements, especially during the COVID-19 pandemic, when children had less opportunities for physical activity away from home.”
Academics emphasize that it is important, for the authorities, to make a “continuous monitoring” and “support the physical fitness and overall health in early childhood”, and there must be “strategies to improve global physical fitness in early childhood”.
Jump and jump
For this study, data from children between the age of three and the age of five were analyzed in preschool, in 2002, 2005, 2010, 2015 and 2020, such as body size, with regard to height, weight and circumferences of the chest, waist and hip; And physical fitness, such as the 2 × 10 m shot, foot length heel, marching, continuous two -legged heel, head throttle and sitting and reaching. ”
In addition, "preschool children of six macaoal gardens were recruited through a combination of stratified and group random sampling methods." A total of 4,519 children, with 59 percent boys and 41 percent girls participated.
The results reveal “an equitable improvement of physical fitness” and the data put Macau at a better position on some European countries referred to in the study. “In contrast to previous investigations into the trends of the physical development of children and adolescents in Poland, which revealed stability at the time, but increases in weight and body mass index, our results suggest that macao preschool children have increased in size, perhaps due to the best living and nutritional conditions.”
Academics conclude that "results are particularly significant," and point out that "the improvement observed in the performance of the standing length of the Macao preschool is encouraging."
Such "contrasts with the investigation into similar populations in the Czech Republic and Poland, where declines were reported in the performance in the length of standing length with increases in the body mass index and in the cutaneous fold", is indicated.
Other signs
The study also reveals “a temporal improvement of flexibility in Macao preschoolers, which differs from the trends observed in pole preschoolers”, and there are “cultural, environmental factors or other factors that influence the development of flexibility in young children in different regions and populations”.
The work also points out that the masters “mixtures uniquely mix eastern and western cultures, which turns it into an intriguing scenario to examine trends in the physical fitness of preschool children”. It is also noted that "the region has a strong commitment to education, offering 15 years of free preschool education to high school and secondary education, ensuring broad access to education and development programs in early childhood childhood for all children."
The compliments of the academics continue, stressing the “remarkable life expectancy, which exceeds 84 years in 2019”, and “Macao gave priority to their health and social systems”.
“Recognizing the importance of physical health, standardized and systematic physical fitness tests were performed on people of all ages since the beginning of the century, when the government implemented a physical fitness surveillance system aligned with China's national physical fitness monitoring,” is also explained.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 00:30:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Communities | Emídio Sousa succeeds José Cesário as secretary</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/comunidades-emidio-sousa-sucede-a-jose-cesario-como-secretario/</link><description>The new secretary of the Portuguese communities has a governance experience in the environment and for more than 10 years has been mayor of Santa Maria da Feira. In turn, José Cesário will return to the functions of deputy
 
The Prime Minister of Portugal, Luís Montenegro, chose Emídio Sousa as the new Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities. The replacement of José Cesário, who had resumed these functions last year, and who fulfilled four distinct periods in office, was revealed with the announcement of the members who constitute the new Portuguese executive.
The appointment means to Emídio Sousa a change of folder, since in the previous government had performed the functions of Secretary of State for the Environment.
The new responsible for the Portuguese communities portfolio has a career essentially linked to policy and public administration. According to his profile on the LinkedIn social network, he has a degree in Public Administration, an area in which he also obtained a master's degree.
For about 20 years he worked in the waters of Gaia, where he reached the position of secretary general, and then, in October 2013, assumed the functions of mayor of Santa Maria da Feira, in the district of Aveiro, where he was for about 10 years. Before being elected mayor, he had performed the duties of councilman.
“With a quiet conscience”
In turn, after becoming a public that was no longer secretary of state of communities, José Cesário left a farewell message on social networks. “It was a great honor for me to have returned to perform these governmental functions in the government led by my friend Luís Montenegro and served the Portuguese resident abroad. It was a very difficult year, full of obstacles, in which, despite everything, it was possible to perform some measures, which I hope to translate into more valuses for those who live outside Portugal,” wrote Cesário. "The choice for a new passport and the expiration of its expiration date, the resolution of the salary problem of our employees in Brazil, the normalization of the activity of the Portuguese Communities Council and the alteration of the association support regime and communication of communities are good examples of this action," he was added. The extension of the passport period from 5 years to 10 years is not yet in force.
"Honestly, I leave with a quiet conscience, but with the certainty that there is a lot to do to have a closer and effective relationship with our communities," he said. "Of course, I wish my successor all luck to the world, being sure that, being a wise and hardworking man, everything will do to serve the Portuguese abroad," he said.
In place of always
Despite leaving the position of Secretary of State, José Cesário will assume the duties of deputy, after being elected by the circle outside Europe. This is a return to a parliament that Cesário has well known and for which he has been successively elected since 1983, with only an interregnum in 2022, first as representative of Aveiro and since 2005 as a representative of communities outside Europe.
"From today return to the Assembly of the Republic, as deputy elected from Europe, ceasing my duties of Secretary of State of Portuguese Communities," he wrote. “Now it's time to dedicate myself to parliamentary life, representing with determination, work and humility those who have elected me, whom I owe so much and with whom I have learned so much. Let's go to work!…”
Rita Santos regrets “friend”
The chairman of the Macao Public Function Association (ATFPM) lamented that the “friend” José Cesário is no longer the Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities. “It was a surprise […] Dr. José Cesário, besides being a secretary of state, is our friend,” he acknowledged in statements to the Macau channel of TDM. "It is more for the human issue, for their ability to communicate with people, to solve the problems, so we have had a good relationship with him. Whether he is in government, or not, he is always willing to help people. We were sad, but we have to look forward," he added.
Rita Santos also pointed out that José Cesário will continue to defend the community, now in Parliament. "He is a deputy and I think that with the position of deputy he can continue to fight for the legitimate rights of the Portuguese to live outside Portugal," he said.
At the same time, he left wishes to establish a good relationship with the new Secretary of State for Portuguese Communities, Emídio Sousa. "With the new secretary of state we hope that there may be collaboration and good contact, as with Dr. José Cesário, and we wish them the biggest success, to solve the problems of the Portuguese who are quite enough," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Must | Sam Hou Fai promises a favorable environment</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/must-sam-hou-fai-promete-ambiente-favoravel/</link><description>The chief executive spoke on Saturday at the Undergraduate Ceremony of the Macao University and Technology (Must), promising that the government, “in collaboration with all sectors of society, will provide more opportunities, a larger stage and a more favorable environment for students and the young generation develop their talents, work, create their own businesses and realize their aspirations”.
In addition to professional success, Sam Hou Fai expressed the desire that "the patriotic spirit and love Macau will continue to be transmitted from generation to generation, and that the principle of" a country, two systems "proceed."
Sam Hou Fai stressed the stimulus given by President Xi Jinping, who visited Must in December last year, exchanging impressions with teachers, students and researchers at the university, and giving “valuable guidance and attention”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:23:27</pubDate></item><item><title>Gold | Government prepares a new law for trade</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/ouro-governo-prepara-nova-lei-para-comercio/</link><description>The Consumer Council began listening to gold traders to change the legislation in force. The information was released through a press release.
"As the evolution of techniques in the sector and the change of consumer models in recent years, the CC proposes the optimization of the legal regime of Macao's Golden Articles, in order to allow the sector to correspond to the real needs in market development, increasing its competitiveness and protecting the rights and interests of the consumer," he was explained.
Thus there were three consultation sessions with the traders, although the dates were not revealed. The objective also involves Macao a world center for the purchase and sale of gold. "The CC has proceeded to the organization and analysis of their opinions and will optimize the legal regime […] according to the actual situation, in order to contribute to the position of Macao as the world center of tourism and leisure," he was added.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:20:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | Candidate lists fall to less than half</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/eleicoes-listas-candidatas-caem-para-menos-de-metade/</link><description>The Electoral Commission received at the end of the deadline for nine requests for direct suffrage to the Macao Parliament, less than half than in the previous elections in 2021. The next step will be the presentation of the lists of candidates and political programs by June 26
 
The Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal) received nine applications from candidate lists to the next legislative elections, less than half of the lists that tried to participate in the 2021 electoral act. There were 19 lists of candidates for the Legislative Assembly (AL), although five lists and 21 candidates -15 of which pro -democracy -were then excluded by “not defending the basic law” being “faithful to the sons”.
In a statement issued on Friday, the Electoral Commission stressed that, after finishing the deadline for requesting requests, the candidacy committees that were recognized may submit the list of candidates and political program by June 26. The list will only be “definitely admitted” to the “after passing” elections of the candidates, stressed the electoral body.
The State Security Defense Commission will determine "whether candidates defend the basic law and are faithful" to the MSar and issue a binding opinion, of which "there is no complaint or litigation."
This State Security Defense Committee will announce, by late, until July 15, the decision on the list of candidates for the legislatures, scheduled for September 14. The Electoral Commission promised to “rigorously” the new electoral law, approved after the 2021 exclusions, “which aims at greater implementation of the Macao principle governed by Patriots”.
In good Portuguese
On Tuesday, by submitting his application for candidacy, Portuguese deputy José Pereira Coutinho said he was confident that he will not be disqualified, despite being-along with Deputy Ron Lam-one of the few critical voices of the government in AL.
"The fact that being critical does not mean that I am not a patriot, I am also patriot," said the former candidate for the Assembly of the Portuguese Republic, in 2015, by the Party We Citizens.
“We have always worked here for Macao's good and for the good of the citizens of Macau,” added Pereira Coutinho. Thirty -three deputies are part of AL, 14 of which are elected by direct suffrage, 12 for indirect suffrage through associations, and seven are later appointed by the head of the local government.
In the case of the indirect suffrage, the Electoral Commission said it had received six application, more than in 2021, for the five sectors: industrial, commercial and financial; workers; Liberal professionals; social and educational services; and cultural and sports. Four years ago, the 19 initial lists of candidates for direct suffrage had three Lusodescendants.
Two of them, José Pereira Coutinho and Lídia Lourenço, were on the Nova Esperança list, linked to the Macao Public Function Workers Association. The third, architect Rui Leão, secretary general of the International Union of Architects, was part of the Civic Observatory list, headed by the then deputy Agnes Lam.
Pereira Coutinho did not disclose the composition of the list, but guaranteed the presence of Rita Santos, who requested in October the suspension of the office of the Portuguese communities to prepare the elections. Pereira Coutinho resigned in 2021 to the mandate of a counselor of the Portuguese communities, for which he had been elected in 2015 by the Circle of China, Macao and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:18:41</pubDate></item><item><title>IDQ / Inspections | Pereira Coutinho criticizes services suspension</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/idq-inspeccoes-pereira-coutinho-critica-suspensao-de-servicos/</link><description>Deputy José Pereira Coutinho has challenged the government about changes to the services provided by the Institute for Development and Quality (IDQ), which have “implications for quality and inspection in Macao”.
According to the question, the Deputy Citizens Office has received many complaints from “local entrepreneurs who express concern about the recent decision of the IDQ to suspend the provision of various essential services”, such as the “inspection of lifting equipment and the issuance of inspection certificates for private companies, as well as for their engineering projects”.
This change took place from March last year, and for Pereira Coutinho, “without notice, this decision raises several questions about the continuity of essential services that guarantee safety and quality in the construction sector, lifting equipment and engineering in Macao”.
The deputy also questions "how will be guaranteed in the future the fulfillment of various purposes of IDQ."</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:28:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Government refuses to penalize non -use of seat belts on back seats</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/governo-recusa-penalizar-nao-utilizacao-de-cintos-de-seguranca-nos-bancos-de-tras/</link><description>The government refuses to advance with fines to penalize passengers who do not use seat belts at rear seats. The executive's position was assumed at a meeting of the 1st Permanent Commission of the Legislative Assembly, by President and Deputy Ella Law.
Cited by the newspaper or Mun, the member of the Legislative Assembly stated that the non -use of safety belts in rear banks will not be penalized with the changes to the Traffic Law. In addition, the government said it needs more time to study as, for example, in Portugal, it came to be in 1994, even before the transition from Macao's transfer. The executive will also have indicated that any change will have to be made “step-by-step”.
Regarding the penalties for the non -use of the seat belt in the front seats the fine will become 300 patacas.
At yesterday's meeting, one of the discussions that raised the most controversial is a norm that gives power to public transport drivers to refuse passengers who behave or transport materials that can be regarded as dangerous to the driver and other passengers.
Great Debates
According to Ella Law, this issue was far from being peaceful among the deputies, with some questioning the possibility of random decisions of drivers. There will have been those who suggested to the government to drop the norm. However, the executive's representatives promised to elaborate, later, after the law, guiding lines for drivers.
After yesterday's meeting, Ella Lei admitted to unaware of whether it will be possible to finalize the discussion of traffic law changes until October, because the government still has to present a new version of the work text. In the event that it is not possible, the law will fall and will have to be presented again in general, and voted by the new deputies, and then the specialty is analyzed again.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:26:46</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections | FAOM DELIVERY APPLICATION APPLICATION</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/eleicoes-faom-entrega-pedido-de-candidatura/</link><description>The Union for Development List, led by the Macao Workers' Associations Federation (Faom), delivered on Wednesday the request for recognition of the candidacy committee, with 500 signatures. The agent of the list, Kong Ioi Fai, spoke of the group's preliminary ideas for these elections.
The team that competes is composed of 12 people and seeks to achieve the objectives set for the last elections. The agent also spoke of the group's long experience in electoral acts and in monitoring the problems of residents, in phases as distinct as the economic recession felt in Macao after the transition, the SARS epidemic in 2003; The 2008 financial crisis and the years of COVID-19. Kong Io Fai highlighted essential objectives such as the revitalization of the economy, the guarantee of the well-being of the population, the development of young people, the improvement of public administration and the protection of labor rights.
Union of business interests delivered a request for recognition
The Macao Business Interest Union list, linked to the Macao Commercial Association, delivered yesterday the request for the constitution of the application committee with the support of 103 legal persons. This is a list will participate in the elections of September 14 in the indirect suffrage and which in 2021 elected as deputies the entrepreneurs Kou Hoi In, José Chui Sai Peng, IP Sio Kai and Wang Sai Man.
The list participates in indirect suffrage by industrial, commercial and financial sectors and since 2021 has always competed without opposition. According to the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the agent of the list, businessman Ma Iao Lai, pointed out that after the request for recognition was confirmed by the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly, the list will give lectures to collect opinions and study the four candidates.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:24:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Young people and explored nominations</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/jovens-e-amas-explorados/</link><description>Politicians, associations, political parties are not tired of talking about the housing problem. Hollow words and that do not contribute to Portugal the serious problem of housing, especially the social, has a light at the bottom of the tunnel. Portugal is the country in Europe where the price of houses has increased. It is very motionless, but they are luxury condominiums, with access to rich only. The housing intended for affordable incomes is always focused on calendar.
And who suffers more from this decision -making inertia of the rulers are the poor and the young. These are still 40 years old living at their parents' home. Young people have no possibility of renting a house in Lisbon or Porto. Its secondary course ends and when they decide to go to a university in Lisbon it is absolutely impossible for them to lease a house and student homes are minimal and expensive. Do you know what happens in Lisbon? Young college students are exploited in an infamous way.
In the Capital Lisbon there are hundreds of owners of old houses that were built with six and seven bedrooms. Therefore, it turns out that these landlords rent the six or seven rooms to students for 500 and 600 euro a month and in the house there are only two bathrooms for all. Even worse is that explorers do not even pass receipts and escape the tax authorities regarding the approximate income of 4200 euros per month, if it is a six -room residence. Exploration and deplorable opportunism is fundamentally due to the lack of affordable housing, with the aggravation of being the parents of students paying the use of these rooms.
Where is institutional inspection? Of course we do not believe that it will not be possible to find out where these homes that explore the students exist. Only on a Lisbon avenue we were aware that there are more than 20 homes with students rented to students. This is a situation that the new government could consider creating a group, like ASAE, dedicated exclusively to the irregularities committed and the exploration of young people who need a bed and a table to be students in college.
The housing problem is also the decrease in birth rates. Obviously young people are unable to unite, contract family and live to think that the future is a problem. If they stay in their parents' homes, how can they acquire or lease a house to live with their mate and children who may be born? Impossible. We wrote with knowledge of the cause because we kept a chat with a young student from the Faculty of Letters who told us that he lives in a room of a residence with six more habitatures, all rented by 600 euros. And he stressed that the landlord reported that if he intended receipt Pecúlio to pay would have to be 750 euros. Deplorable.
Another serious problem that is registered in cities such as Lisbon, Porto, Coimbra, Braga and Évora, among others, is the situation of women who are hired by employment agencies in order to be elderly people with reduced mobility or various types of dementia. These women, namely Portuguese, Brazilian and African, receive a salary when they receive less than half of what the contractor pays to these employment agencies. It is usually the children of these seniors and patients who pay, for example, 3000 euros per month and AMA workers receive the equivalent of the minimum wage. Many of them work on Saturdays and Sundays without being paid to double as the law requires.
Sometimes they are women who live with family difficulties who have a job but will work on the weekend to raise some more money that helps in their survival. AMAs who have annual contract to work from Monday to Friday do not have any payment of Christmas allowance. Once again, we do not believe that the government is not aware of this reality and seeks to end with this kind of shameful exploitation. We all know how difficult it is to deal with day and night an elderly with dementia or that needs a wheelchair to move. These nominations still do extra jobs in the houses where they work, such as cooking, washing clothes and ironing, without any more remuneration.
There are still cases where the elderly have pets and there are the exploited nominations that have to treat the animals and take them to the street. This type of exploitation, in our understanding, is just a new kind of slavery. This is what it is, with the rulers to whistle aside. Two relevant cases that would be deserving of a radical change so that the “Chicos-Parts” did not think that the world is those who exploit and enslave their fellow man.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:54:06</pubDate></item><item><title>The meteorological systems of early alert and their importance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/os-sistemas-meteorologicos-de-alerta-precoce-e-a-sua-importancia-2/</link><description>(Continuation of the June 5th edition)
Despite having an efficient meteorological service (administration of atmospheric, geophysical and astronomical services of the Philippines - Pagasa1) the Philippines, due to Haiyan, were the scene of one of the great tragedies related to tropical cyclones. In the case of Haiyan, the warning newsletters were issued, regularly and attentively, before and during the typhoon, but the fact that the flood risk maps were outdated made many people perished for taking refuge in shelters in areas considered safe in these maps.
On the other hand, because there are many languages ​​in the country (over 180 languages ​​and regional dialects), bulletins are mainly issued in English and tagal, the two official languages. Thus, the reasons for such a large number of victims, besides the exceptional violence of the typhoon and flood risk maps were outdated, was the fact that the terms “Storm”, likely to be understood by much of the less educated population, were used. Among the recommendations expressed in the reports of the various missions in charge of evaluating the consequences of the typhoon excelled the need to urgently update the flood risk maps and the use in warning bulletins, less technical language in order to be easily understood by the populations.
The Philippines, and some international media, reported that the president of the Guiuan2 municipality, the first Filipine city that was on the forecast of the typhoon, sent messengers with altifalantes, in motorcycles, to the various “Barangays” 3 of the municipality near the coast, warning the approach of a tsunami. The term "tsunami", although not technically correct in this situation, warned the populations, poorly sensitized by the forecast of a storm tide, to follow the instructions of the Civil Protection Authority in order to be evacuated, which was successfully achieved.
It should be noted that people were well aware of the consequences of tsunamis, as news about the consequences of such a phenomenon that had occurred a few years earlier, in 2004, on the west of Sumatra, causing approximately 230,000 deadly victims in 14 different countries.
The WMO and the United Nations Office to reduce the risk of disasters (UNDRR) 5 have insisted on the need to enlarge this type of early alert systems to other phenomena, in addition to those related to meteorology. Thus, the concept of early warning systems of multiple risks (internationally known as “Multihard Early Warning Systems”-Mhews), which cover various types of risks, considering interrelationships between them. The main risks that may be a reason for issuing multirriscos are essentially flooding, extractic cyclones, tropical cyclones (cyclones, typhoons, hurricanes), storm tides, droughts, forest fires, heat waves, landslides, seismos and tsunamis.
According to the report “Global Status of Multi-Hazard Early Warning Systems 2024”, prepared by OMM and UNDRR (presented at COP29 by the United Nations Secretary-General António Guterres), countries with less developed systems have a mortality rate related to natural disasters of nearly six times higher than countries in which multirristers are most Advanced, and almost four times more people affected by catastrophes.
It is expected that in the next conference on the climate, to be held under the auspices of UNFCCC6 (COP30-November 15-21, 2025, in Belém, Brazil), measures to improve early warning systems in countries where they are not properly implemented.
References:
Pagasa - Philippine Atmospheric, Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration.
Guiuan - Important city in the history of the Philippines. It is reported that, in the 16th century, it was on the Homonhon Island, belonging to that municipality, that Fernão de Magalhães landed for the first time in that archipelago. Perhaps for this reason the population of the city is mostly Catholic.
Barangay - Administrative division in the Philippines, corresponding to the village.
“Escap/Wmo Typhoon Committee” - has been headquartered by the Secretariat in Macao since 2007.
UNDRR - United Nations Office for Disaster Risk Reduction.
UNFCCC - United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:55:24</pubDate></item><item><title>The meteorological systems of early alert and their importance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/os-sistemas-meteorologicos-de-alerta-precoce-e-a-sua-importancia/</link><description>Olavo Rasquinho *
General knowledge is the importance that weather warnings have for human activities. However, about a third of the 193 members of the World Meteorological Organization (MMO) do not yet have efficient early warning systems to warn populations to be careful against the loss of lives and goods before natural meteorological disasters.
In the face of this reality, OMM selected for the theme of the 2025 World Meteorological Day celebrations (DMM) “Closing the Early Warning Gap Together”, which can be translated by “We reduce the failures of early alert systems together”. The theme is part of the “Early Warly Warnings for All Initiative”), which aims to protect the global scale, relative to hazardous hydrometeorological, climate and related environmental events.
Early alert systems are essentially based on four components: knowledge of risk; Monitoring and forecasting; communication and dissemination of alerts and response capacity of the communities. The failure of any of these components compromises the effectiveness of measures to be taken to prevent a natural disaster from becoming a catastrophe.
Meteorological services, using means of a global observation network, and physical-mathematical models that simulate the behavior of the atmosphere, predict the occurrence of phenomena that may affect the lives of citizens. For example, the approximate time of the arrival of a typhoon the earth may be foreseen, but the simple fact that your movement slows or accelerates may result in not getting it right when it happens. Usually the typhoons, which always form at sea, decrease the speed of progression and intensity as they approach land.
However, sporadically, this may not happen. This is what happened with Typhoon Hato who, in August 2017, hit Macao with serious consequences. Instead of decreasing its displacement speed and weakening, it suffered sudden intensification and increased speed, surprising meteorologists. This happened with the aggravation of the arrival of the typhoon coincided with the high astronomical tide, which reinforced the consequences of the storm tide. It can then be deduced that the “monitoring and prediction” component and, consequently, the component “communication and spread of alerts” of the early alert system did not function a hundred percent due to the anommal behavior of the typhoon.
This happened on a territory where the early alert system is well structured and usually works with a high success rate. Imagine what may happen when this type of phenomena occurs in regions where there are no early warning systems or, therefore, are not effective enough due to deficiency in means or lack of human resources. As an example of this situation one can mention what happened in November 1970, in the so-called East Pakistan. This Pakistani province was hit by one of the most violent cyclones of the last century, the “Great Bhola Cyclone”, which caused a number of dead that is estimated between three hundred thousand at half a million.
It is considered the tropical cyclone that has caused the most victims since there are records. Winds of about 200 km/h, coincident with a high astronomical tide, dragged the waters of the Indian Earth-to-Dentro, invading much of the Ganges River delta, causing a large storm tide that reached 6 meters. The consequences were so serious that they contributed to the people's revolt, motivated by the weak response of the central government. The discontent generated contributed to intensify the struggle for the independence of the province, which was materialized in 1971, giving rise to a new country, Bangladeche.
Another example was what happened in Myanmar (former Burma) in May 2008. This country, directed for tens of years by military dictatorships, would not suffer so much the consequences of the Camis Cyclone if they were attached with a modern and efficient alert system. The more than 130,000 deadly victims caused by the storm tide associated with the tropical cyclone would certainly be largely avoided. A few days before the cyclone hit that country had already been issued by the Specialized Regional Meteorological Center (“Regional Specialized Meteorological Center - RSMC”), which is the center responsible for the Meteorological Surveillance for the Indian Norte Basin1.
Also the Meteorological Service of India warned the government of Myanmar about the high probability of occurring a large storm tide that would affect the Irauádi River Delta, which happened about 48 hours later, enough time to evacuate the populations.
In the case of Bhola and Nargis cyclones the alert systems were practically nonexistent in East Pakistan and Myanmar. However, in the Philippines, an average affected country, on average, by about twenty tropical storms and typhoons, although the meteorological and civil protection authorities were considered well organized, there were failures in two of the components of the early alert system in November 2013.
The components “Knowledge of Risk” and “Communication and Dissemination of Alerts” failed partly due to outdated flood risk maps and inadequate language used. Typhoon Haiyan (designated in the Philippines by Yolanda Superirty) caused a number of deadly victims of more than six thousand. The main reasons for the catastrophe to have reached such proportions were, in addition to the failures of two of the components of the early alert system, in the facts that the pressure was extremely low in the center (about 895 HPa), winds of great intensity and the typhoon had entered the land near the tide tide tide. These conjugated factors caused a storm tide that reached, in some places between 6 and 7 meters. Note that the decrease in pressure of 1 hPa corresponds to the elevation of the sea level of about 1 cm.
(continues)
*Meteorologist
- In the context of the OMM tropical cyclone program, five organizations were created, some of which classified as intergovernmental organizations, with the aim of studying and monitoring tropical cyclones: Tropical Cyclone Committee (Southwest Indian Ocean), WMO/Tropical Cyclone Panel (Bengal Bay and Arabic Sea), Tufões Committee) Escap/WMO (Northwest of the Pacific Ocean and Southern Sea of ​​China), Hurricane Committee of the IV Regional Association (North America, Central America and Caribbean), Tropical Cyclone Committee of the V Regional Association (South and Southeast Indian Ocean Pacific).</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 23:56:41</pubDate></item><item><title>The Star Door (I)</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/a-porta-das-estrelas-i/</link><description>“One must have chaos withself to Give Birth to a Dancing Star”
Friedrich Nietzsche
The project centered on artificial intelligence (AI) announced by Trump redefines the silicon valley hierarchies. And clarifies the industrial nature of AI. Since winning the elections, Donald Trump has spent a long time to talk about the stars. In the beginning was Musk, the famous «Nascent Astro», on the occasion of the first speech of the tycoon after the electoral victory. Subsequently, still linked to Elon, it was the turn of Mars, the red star and where to plant the star flag to update the manifest fate of such an exceptional people that it must become transglobal. And then, like a blue sky radius, the time has come for Stargate, the "door of the stars" with which Trump intends to relaunch the American dream, linking it to technological innovation and AI development, with the concrete objective of preserving world leadership.
The United States must maintain technological superiority from China that recently developed an AI (Deepseek) model capable of achieving chatgpt results with lower level hardware (according to them) and lower costs because only then Washington can establish with Beijing a "agreement" which is Trump's new word from a force position. Stargate is a potentially revolutionary project. It is about investing a hundred billion dollars immediately, intended to quintuple, to accelerate the development of the new generation of artificial intelligences, integrating the material production chain (data centers and chips) with the intangible (cloud computer management and algorithm writing). To do so, Trump trusts those elements of the technological world that, until yesterday, were far from the spotlight.
And sanction the end of those who, within the state, were occupied exactly with these issues. In short, the “Paypal Mafia” in its thielist and muskian currents will be out of the star door, occupying the antechamber in the company of Eric Schmidt, a former Google Democrat who presides over the (expensive) national security committee, now totally empty meaning. Trump's decision is clear. Like a new Adam Smith, the tycoon proposes a division of labor necessary so that none of the great men in the technological sector can accumulate too much power. There are no stars so brilliant that they can overshadow that of the president, which applies the most classic of divide et reepe. Will it work? To understand, we have to cross the door of the stars. When, last January 21, Trump appeared at the White House to announce the launch of Stargate, there were three people with him.
Less known than Elon Musk, often in disagreement with Tesla's founder and eager for showing the world as they can also be useful to the tycoon. After the president, the first to speak was Larry Ellison, co-founder and executive president of Oracle. Your company works with cloud, that is, it stores huge amounts of data for various technological companies. The eighty -year -old entrepreneur, against the president of his age, explains how AI can be useful for health. Your speech looks like an advertising announcement. But beware of appearances. Ellison theorizes the use of AI to implement a total surveillance system, necessary for "citizens to behave correctly." The president of Oracle is the only one who has not formally a role in organizing Stargate, but Trump introduced him as "CEO of everything" and also made it clear that he would be happy if they bought Tiktok.
Trump and Ellison are from the same generation, both are New Yorkers and have known each other for a long time. Probably understand each other very well. Then I intervened Masayoshi Son, known as Masa. He is the founder, representative director, corporate executive, chairman of the board and CEO of Softbank Group (SBG), a Japanese group of risk capital, and will be the financial responsible of Stargate. The task of bringing the capitalization of the star door to five hundred billion of dollars is, first of all, yours. But above all, as a good Japanese, Masa knows that the project was born with an antichinese function that "this is not just a business", making a point of specifying. It is about developing AI so as not to lose the race for innovation with China. And perhaps also create a container to promote the development of ARM, the English company that sells AI chips and that appears as the flagship of Softbank's investments. Last but not least, Sam Altman.
In November 2023, after the case that shook OpenAi's foundations due to its dismissal (later withdrawal), the state entered its company. Informally. But the presence of a figure like Larry Summers, a former treasure secretary and very close to national security devices on the ChatgPT mother's council council clearly shows how the government wanted to be aware of its internal dynamics.
Today, just over a year later, it is Altman who binds to the state. The founder of OpenAi will in fact play Stargate's role of operational responsible. And it has already obtained an important result, since Microsoft to which OpenAI is linked by a contract by 2030 granted Altman's company the ability to also use its competitors' cloud services for this project. In particular, obviously, those of Larry Ellison, CEO of everything.
The main actors are joined by Microsoft itself that will provide its stargate cloud platform and obviously NVIDIA. Because there is no GPU (Graphic Processing Units) to train the Machine Learning models. Jensen Huang's Nvidia is still, in fact, practically monopolistic in the sector, although the market is expanding and is increasingly difficult to meet demand. Finally, the United Arab Emirates Fund (MGX) specializing in technological investments will collaborate in the financial management of the operation. And so, almost as in a joke, Stargate is, in the end, a container in which a Bronx -born octogenarian, a sixty -year -old Japanese, a young AI guru, Microsoft, Jensen Huang with his leather coat and an Abu Dhabi background.
Trump's task will be to coordinate this heterogeneous human mass, joining it around a strategic goal of developing AI to reprogram the American dream and keep China a safe distance. All clear. How to proceed?
(Continues)</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 23:53:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Creative Macau | New Miguel Quental exhibition with images of Goa</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/creative-macau-nova-exposicao-de-miguel-quental-com-imagens-de-goa/</link><description>After the first photography exhibition at the University of Macau, Miguel Quental again shows images of his own, but this time about Goa. The show is welcomed from Saturday at Creative Macau and intends to show the public the “rich inheritance of vibrant color” of a territory that once was the “capital of an empire”
 
Creative Macau hosts, from Saturday, a new exhibition by Miguel Quental, better known for his work in law, but this time presents his images taken in Goa. “Colors of Goa” is the name of the exhibition that opens from 6.30 pm on Saturday, presenting images of what was “capital of an empire”, from which “a rich inheritance of vibrant colors, aromas, flavors, images and beliefs that transcend our imagination”, describes the author of the photos, quoted by a Creative Macau statement.
“In search of this legacy, I left for Goa, but the experience went far beyond what I could expect. Its ancient churches and other places of worship exhibit a captivating beauty, offering a unique and transcendent peace that goes beyond the spirituality to which they are dedicated. The manorial houses, full of history, details and emotion, resemble noble, majestic and impassible, full of art and memories.” It also describes.
Miguel Quental does not forget either “the alleys of Velha Goa, Pangim, Margão and the Fontaínhas neighborhood, which breathe and offer us a vibrant and almost magnetic heritage that touches the soul and invites us to go beyond the historical and cultural memories that memory does not allow us to forget”. "In this spirit, I share some of the many images I took there, but I'm aware that much more to find out," says the author, who hopes that she will "invite her to visit her soon."
I like the image
Residing in Macao since 2002, Miguel Quental has been in the third individual exhibition. The last one was at the University of Macao in November last year, being a photographic project that was born from an exchange trip from the Center for Legal and Judicial Studies of the University of Macao to Angola and Mozambique.
In addition to participating in the visit as a teacher, Miguel Quental photographed the daily lives of the populations of these countries. "As I like to do photography I was taking some images during these trips. This is a center that is dedicated to the comparative study of law and the publications that are made in Portuguese in its relationship with China, and I thought it was interesting to make known the culture and way of living from Angola and Mozambique to college students who never had access to this reality," he explained to HM at the time.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:52:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Camões was Mozambique's “great‘ amateur ”, influencing his poetry</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/08/camoes-foi-grande-amador-de-mocambique-influenciando-a-sua-poesia/</link><description>The academic Lourenço do Rosario highlighted on Friday that Luís de Camões influenced Mozambican poets as a "great" amateur ", asking for more research to discover a camões hosted on the island of Mozambique, in the north of the country.
"Camões was a great amateur, was very fond of women and one of the reasons that he was always in prison was exactly because he had several problems with women, especially married (…). He arrives in 1567, had no money to continue the trip to Portugal, had no money to live on the island of Mozambique," said the academic Mozambican Lourenço do Rosário, after the opening of the second congress. 500 years of Camões.
Mozambique welcomes the second 500th anniversary Congress of the birth of Luís de Camões, emphasizing the relationship of the Portuguese poet with the Indian Ocean and the Mozambican territory. Lourenço do Rosário, essayist and professor of literature, said Camões was welcomed “in Macúti”, houses built with local material, “by Mutian women” (woman, in the local language of Nampula), when he arrived at Mozambique Island.
"He makes that poem‛ Endchas to Barbara Slave, "which is one of the most beautiful poems he wrote about women, so Camões knew how to sing the woman," added Lourenço do Rosário.
"An obligation"
The former dean of the Polytechnic University of Maputo and also a member of Leya Award criticized Portugal for not valuing the deeds of Camões for the Portuguese East Empire, arguing that one cannot “alienate this reality” that the poet “began to write and ended his works in Mozambique”.
"So, we have this obligation to rescue this reading of Camões and go see what he had critic had about Portugal's presence in the East Empire," said the teacher, asking for research to ensure the presence of Camões in schools from his action in the East.
From this perspective, Lourenço do Rosário also recalled that Camões should be seen in Mozambique as someone who was “arrested, expelled and degraded”, who fought as a military and lived poor, having undergone “deprivation” in the East before Portugal introduced him to the world as a “great Portuguese poet”.
Lourenço do Rosário has asked more research to influence political decisions in the face of Camões in education programs in the country. "It is necessary to value what is ours, and Camões is ours, because he wrote here."
“There is a whole generation, a group of [Eduardo] White, Nelson Health, Rui Knopfli, especially the poets that are linked to the island of Mozambique, have a lot of influence from Camões writing, the look of Camões on the world, not only from the point of view of love, but also about social criticism, so I think Mozambican researchers have a lot of material to discover and influence our schools. But Camões ours, from Mozambique, ”he said.
The Portuguese Ambassador in Mozambique, also present at the opening of Congress, highlighted the academic movement in the praise of Camões as a “unifying element” of a culture and language that “is not only of the Portuguese”, pointing to the poet as a “symbol of projection of the Portuguese speaker community”.
The Camões in Africa and Asia Network, which promotes and encourages studies and publications about Camões, held the first Congress about the 500th anniversary of the poet's birth last year, in Macao, and for 2026, the same event is intended to go to Goa, making a tour of places where it passed and lived, explained the organization.
Born 501 years ago, on June 10, 1524, in Lisbon, the Soldado Poet Luís Vaz de Camões lived and wrote about two years on the island of Mozambique, in the old street of Fogo, where it will also make sense that love “is fire that burns without seeing”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-08 21:24:16</pubDate></item><item><title>Alliance Française | Presented today documentary about Maria Callas</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/alliance-francaise-apresentado-hoje-documentario-sobre-maria-callas/</link><description>It is today that the public can remember one of the great voices of our time, Maria Callas, and also know more about your life. This is because the Alliance Française de Macau hosts the exhibition of the documentary “Callas - Paris, 1958”, by French director Tom Volf. The exhibition takes place in the context of the French May festival, in partnership with Hong Kong
 
The Alliance Française de Macau, in collaboration with the Alliance Française de Hong Kong and French May Arts Fest, today in Macau the documentary film “Callas-Paris, 1958”, by Tom Volf, dating from 2023. The exhibition takes place from 7:30 pm in Studio City's room 4, integrating in the “French May Cinema Program” section ”section” section French May festival.
According to a press release of the organization, "the exhibition will be preceded by a presentation by Michel Reis, Melómane, author and host of Radio Macau's Classical Music Program," Scherzo ", and Peter Gordon, who has lived in Hong Kong since 1985 and works with the main opera companies of Hong Kong and Guangdong."
The film documents the premiere of “one of the greatest legends of opera, the quintessential diva, media sensation and face of twentieth -century opera, the extremely rare soprano 'plague'” Maria Callas in France. This was the concert in which Maria Callas was accompanied by the Orchestre de L'Epéra Nationale de Paris and Choeurs, under the direction of conductor Georges Sébastian, "a show that became a real legend."
It was, according to the same note, a show that integrated a gala of charity in favor of the works of “Légion d'Honneur”, being broadcast live on French television and televisions from other European countries through Eurovision, which was quite rare at the time. Announced by the press as "Le Plus Grand Spectacle du Monde" [the largest show in the world], "The concert was really exceptional."
Celebration order
The film was commissioned by Fondação Callas, through the Maria Callas Donations Fund, created by Volf himself, for the celebration of the centenary of the birth of the celebrated Greco American sopranic, which was marked on December 2, 2023. The foundation was created in Paris in 2017 by the world-known conductor Georges Prêtre, who developed a very close working relationship with the singer, who directed several times. This documentary took six years to complete and two years to color.
Volf was also the author of the critical documentary “Maria by Callas”, released in 2017 in more than 40 countries, which won awards at film festivals in Europe and the US. He also launched three books about the singer: “Maria by Callas”, “Callas Confidential” and “Maria Callas: Memoirs &amp; Letters”.
In the show chosen for this documentary, Maria Callas came up "with her most elegant sewing high couture clothing worth more than one million US dollars," the chosen repertoire "showed Callas at its heyday, both in recital and actress."
“It is noteworthy that he had sung 'Violetta' in a production of 'La Traviata' in Lisbon at the beginning of this year of 1958, at the famous São Carlos National Theater, considered his best Violetta of the more than 60 he played,” he reads.
Comments by famous actor and animator Pierre Tchernia, known as “Magic Tchernia”, were complemented by Pierre Dumayet during the intervals, both behind the scenes during the scenario changes, which conducted numerous interviews with figures such as Jean Cocteau, Patachou, Brigitte Bardot, Gilbert Bécaud, Zizi, Zizi Jeanmaire and Roland Petit, as well as Beguum Aga Khan, a program run by Roger Benarm entitled “La Grande Nuit de L'Opéra” [The Great Night of the Opera], under the tutelage of the Institut National de L'Audiovisuel (Ina).
The original filming of the concert were restored to the modern large screens by producer and a specialist in coloring and restoration of files and archive images, Samuel François-Steininger, from original 16mm coils, which, along with the matrix ribbons, were recently discovered in the Calla recordings file itself. The documentary aired Friday was produced in French with English subtitles and "shows the iconic opera singer at the height of her fame, preserving her voice in all her colors and amplitude for posterity."
“In the performance, visual elements are as important as the vocal dimensions in their art. Present in color, 4K resolution and surround dolby atmos, Tom Volf's meticulous work provided the public with a modern immersion in this historical action,” reads the same note.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Exhibition | Local artist Cheong Kin Man presents new show in Lisbon</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/04/exposicao-artista-local-cheong-kin-man-apresenta-nova-mostra-em-lisboa/</link><description>It is a creative path with several locations that Cheong Kin Man and Marta Sala perform in Lisbon from tomorrow: first, the show “The Slazing and Curious Travel”, to see at the Macao Scientific and Cultural Center until July 6, whose launch is preceded by a conversation with artists and a book release. Then, on Friday, there is another debate at the Goethe Institute
Image of: Guillaume-Galante
For several years based in Berlin, Cheong Kin Man has been a visual artist and anthropologist who has never left experimentation aside. Now, alongside the Polish artist Marta Sala, has been embedded in new artistic directions, which, this time, flow into Lisbon.
This happens in multiple forms. First with the show “The Slazing and Curious Travel”, which will be evident at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) between tomorrow and July 6. Curated by Lorena Tabares Salamanca, from Colombia, the show is a “cross -cultural exposure that crosses art, visual anthropology and personal archives, reflecting on displacements, memory and languages”, with the signature of Cheong Kin Man, Marta Sale and Deborah Uhde from Germany.
The public can see “immersive installations, textile pieces, video and self-ethnographs that reconfigure the relations between travel, history and knowledge,” says a press release of the Poland City Council. In the inaugural session of this Thursday there will also be a conversation with the artists, which is repeated on Friday, but this time at the Goethe Institute library in Lisbon at 18h.
Here, in “Creating Connections”, a conversation with the three artists of “The Slazing and Curious Travel”, which is “an intimate artistic meeting, in which Deborah Uhde, as well as the duo Marta Stanisława Sala and Cheong Kin Man, will share among themselves-and with the public-reflections on their practices and experiences in creating intercultural bonds through art, especially art, with emphasis on art. their paths in Berlin and the latest artist books. ”
These initiatives are supported by the Poland Embassy in Portugal, the Ministry of Culture and National Heritage and the Adam Mickiewicz Institute of Poland. They also have the partnership of the City Council of Krakow and the Boym Institute, also from Poland.
Fusions and Travel
The show that now presents at CCCM brings works of the duo Cheong Kin Man - Marta Sala, known “by the fusion of fabric, video and language experiments”, in which the public can “embark on a trip through parallel worlds and personal files” based on three multimedia projects, such as “The Utopian's compass”, “Revelations” and a new cycle of Macaense diaspora.
In the case of “The Utopia Compass”, it is a “bamboo and fabric installation composed of 13 textile compositions that materialize processes of cultural discovery and mutual learning”, and the work is inspired by the “Flora Sinensis” (1656), by the Jesuit Miguel Boym, who studied in Krakow; as well as “in the musicality of Cantonense poetry translated into chromatic shapes and in self-ethrical motifs associated with the migration of a Macaense family and the contemporary trips of the artists”.
In turn, the “Revelation” series, presented for the first time at the Macao Biennial in 2023, “combines text, textiles and video in a science fiction narrative”, and the fabric “which integrates this fiction coding episodes of the Polish family archive, including migration through the borders of the twentieth century - from Vilnius to the Mongolian steppes and, later, to current Poland”.
Also noteworthy is that the exhibition reveals “the experimental film project based on interviews within the Macaense Diaspora”, taking the public to Brazil, “where the nostalgia shared by humanity echoes in automatic translations for various languages”. There are also, associated with the video, the new publication entitled “Entrevista, MięDzy-Wizje. Roz-Mowa, disorder”, which is “in the form of Flipbook with Luso-Polaco glossary, which deconstructs an excerpt from the recording to reflect on each word said and the limits and possibilities of translation”. This Thursday's CCCM session begins with a guided tour of the artists at 5 pm, including the launch of "Revelation", a new book by artists.
In the case of Deborah Uhde, who accompanies the pair of artists from Macao and Poland, is a filmmaker and artist graduated in beautiful art and humanities, residing in Berlin. Obtained his diploma at the Art University of Braunschweig (2009–2015). It has a formation in Philosophy, History of Art and Journalism from the University of Leipzig (2006–2009). Deborah's work was recognized with several bags and awards.
New book
The duo Kin Man - Sala brings to Lisbon the new edition of the book "Revelations", which includes "a collection of fictional ideograms originally created at the house of Krakow in Nuremberg, the only cultural institution in the municipality of Krakow outside Poland."
This reprint now has over 600 pages and was supported by the Oriente Foundation. The artist book was originally commissioned for the Macau Biennial in 2023, containing “hundreds of ideograms originating from the Copenhagen with Love Exhibition,” held in Nuremberg in 2024, with the support of the East Foundation and the Municipal Chambers of Krakow and Nuremberg.</description><pubDate>2025-06-04 23:49:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Borders | Number of entries and exits exceeded 100 million</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/fronteiras-numero-de-entradas-e-saidas-ultrapassou-100-milhoes/</link><description>From the beginning of the year until 2 pm on Saturday, authorities have accounted for 100 million entrances and exits at the Macao borders. According to data revealed yesterday by the Public Security Police Corps, the bar of 100 million border movements occurred 18 days earlier than last year.
Authorities add that it was "beaten again a shorter record of short time to reach one hundred million border passages, with a daily average of 0.6 million inputs and exits of Macao, representing an increase of 10.8 percent over the same period last year."
CPSP also points out that the volume of passengers/tickets at the Cerco doors border post exceeded 50 million on May 30, and that the Hungqin and Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Posts and Ponte reached the “annual flow of 10 million border passages, successively on May 7 and 9, earlier than the previous year”.
The 100 million entrances and exits, about 36.2 million were residents of Macao, while the border movements of visitors reached almost 34 million. From the beginning of the year, until last Saturday, 25.9 million non-resident and family workers have entered and left Macao.
The CPSP explains the increase in the flow of people on the borders this year with the "impulse of policies favorable to Macao as" one entry a week ", a visa of multiple entries' and 'circulation of Macao vehicles in Guangdong province'.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:39:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Facilitated entry to foreigners through the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/facilitada-entrada-a-estrangeiros-atraves-da-ponte-hong-kong-zhuhai-macau/</link><description>The Public Security Police body announced that tourists from 82 countries, including Portugal, Brazil and Cape Verde, will be able to enter the region through the largest sea bridge in the world, without having to leave the vehicle.
The measure comes into force today on the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge and covers all visitors from the 82 entry-expected countries, CPSP said. In a statement issued on Thursday, police said that all foreign tourists “armed with a valid passport”, regardless of nationality, will be able to leave Macao and enter the bridge without leaving the vehicle.
The goal of the police is to "promote international cultural exchange and help Macau become an open platform abroad (…) and an important window for the exchange between Chinese and Western civilizations." Police added that the measure, which covers vehicles that can transport up to nine people, was decided “after an in -depth evaluation of the demand for entry and exit” at the Bridge Border post.
To the other bank
The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge, the world's longest maritime crossing, registered more than 172,000 foreign passengers by the end of April, an increase of 70 percent compared to the same period of 2024. “This increase is largely due to the expansion of visa exemption policies by China, and Zhuhai's terrestrial border post is the only one in continental territory Chinese that offers direct road access to Hong Kong International Airport, ”Chinese state news agency Xinhua said.
At the end of April, the Secretary for Macao Security announced plans to accelerate the border control of foreign visitors, without resident status or work authorization, through the use of automatic electronic channels. Authorities will expand self-service equipment to the biometric data collection system, which will apply to all foreign visitors, explained Wong Sio Chak.
The secretary added that the government will study the extension of iris recognition technology in non -resident border controls in 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:38:37</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | 96 illegal employees in G-Dragon concert</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/dsal-detectadas-96-funcionarias-ilegais-em-concerto-de-g-dragon/</link><description>On Saturday, police and work services did an operation at the Korean singer G-Dragon merchandising stalls at the Galaxy Arena, where 96 possibly in illegal staff were found. Two officials of the organization were taken to the squadron for investigation
 
The past weekend was of great euphoria at Cotai, with three concerts by popular Korean singer G-Dragon in the Galaxy Arena. However, on Saturday morning a joint operation of the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) and the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) detected 96 employees suspected of being in an illegal situation in the merchandising selling zone.
Subsequently, the CPSP issued a statement confirmed during the process of verifying the identity of the workers the presence of 96 non-resident workers, whose authorization to work would have to be confirmed with DSAL. Following the discovery, two officials of the concert organization were taken to the police squad for investigation.
The authorities did not add more information about the case, in addition to the admission of CPSP that would be investigating the situation and that were found infringements, the case will be treated according to the law. Until the closing of this edition, DSAL had not been pronounced on the occurrence, nor the company that organized the concerts, Tencent Music Entertainment Live.
The situation generated controversy and many publications on social networks. One of the most discussed theories pointed to a possible revenge of clandestine ticket sellers, who would have been expelled from the enclosure on Friday, which will allegedly warned the authorities for the illegal situation of the employees.
NETWORK TRAINS
In addition to revenge theory, images of publications were also shared to recruit part -time workers during concerts, especially on Chinese social networks. In one of the publications, the organizer sought to recruit women under 30, referring as a daily remuneration 200 Renminbis, as well as an additional bonus in accordance with sales. The announcement also indicated that the employer was willing to offer accommodation to employees who needed it.
Also at the level of the legitimate sale of tickets for the Korean star concert there was confusion. In Hong Kong, the cityline ticket sales platform has been complained due to the printing of the wrong date, number of wrong tickets and the passivity of employees in resolving and treatment of complaints.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:37:28</pubDate></item><item><title>DSAMA | They start maritime tours of the weekend</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/dsama-arrancam-passeios-maritimos-de-fim-de-semana/</link><description>The “Maritime Ride in the 2025 Fishing Defense period”, organized by the Macao Fisherman's Mutual Assistance Association, was officially inaugurated on Saturday. Until July 20, three daily sea trips will be operated on Saturdays and Sundays, between the Green Island Dock and the waters near Shizimen. The trips, which last about an hour and a half, have matches at 10:30, 14:30 and 4:30 pm.
Tours cost 40 patacas per person and are limited to a maximum of 26 passengers, and each person can only buy a maximum of four tickets. The vessel used on the tours is a traditional wooden fishing boat about 31 meters.
In a statement issued on Saturday, the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) states that the “itinerary allows the public to enjoy the landscape of the inner port, bridges and the modernization of the Shizimen commercial zone”.
On board the vessel are displayed devices and fishing equipment, as well as boat models. During the trip, fishermen will demonstrate traditional techniques of weaving and sharing personal stories about the profession. The tours are supported by Dsama and Galaxy, Melco, MGM and SJM dealers.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:34:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural Week | Government wants to change events to Zhongshan</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/semana-cultural-governo-quer-mudar-evento-para-zhongshan/</link><description>The executive intends that the 17th edition of the China Cultural Week and Portuguese-speaking countries will be fully held in Zhongshan, but the Lusophone associations involved in the event are against the change of the event's nevral center, despite supporting the expansion to the great bay.
 
The government intends that the 17th edition of the China Cultural Week and Portuguese -speaking countries will be fully held in Zhongshan, Canton province, despite being locally funded. Information about the Institute's plan for the promotion of commerce and investment of Macau (Ipim) was advanced by the platform newspaper in the Friday issue, but has the opposition of local associations.
According to the publication, IPIM maintained separated meetings with the Lusophone Associations involved in the event and told them that at least this year, the event will leave Macau to move inside. After the meetings, the associations have joined to refuse that the event be taken entirely to Zhongshan, although they agree that the interior penetration is positive for all parts.
According to the letter sent to the IPIM, Lusophone associations argue “the importance of preserving the event in the MSAR, maintaining it as the nerve center of this cultural celebration”. “Macao has been, throughout history, the bridge between Lusophone and Chinese cultures, and we believe this character must remain,” he was added.
To the platform, the Macao Forum did not deny the intention to hold the entire event in Zhongshan, and assumed that it aims to “ensure the success of the event, both in Macau and the Great Bay, for all parties involved, as well as for participants and the public”.
The Macao Forum also indicated that it is acting "in accordance with the decision taken by all parties participating in the Macao Forum, at the 20th Ordinary Meeting of the Permanent Secretariat, to include Elements of the Cultural Week in the Great Bay."
Still, the body has pointed out that "it is collaborating with all its partners, whether government or civil society, including the associations of Portuguese -speaking countries in Macau, with a view to welcoming and integrating all the ideas, concerns and contributions it has received and continues to receive."
"Wrapping paper"
In addition to the trip to Zhongshan, the associations complain about the new role they are taking into the event, since the integration of the Macao Forum in IPIM, which made them lose functional autonomy.
In addition to this aspect, the platform, the cultural week of China and Portuguese -speaking countries has been awarded to a company, which deals with all the details of the event, on the fringes of associations, who is responsible for the role of just indicating the names to be invited. This new reality led to a source of associations, which refused to be identified, to collapse to the newspaper that associations only feel as “package papers” to legitimize the event. Among the complaints against the new role is the fact that associations currently do not even have a maneuver room to receive or socialize with the artists or economic agents invited to the event of these countries. Given this reality, associations suggest the “limitation of the intervention of companies that do not know the cultural concept developed over the years” to ensure “loyalty to the original values ​​of the event”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:30:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing | Market shrinks more than 50% in a year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/habitacao-mercado-encolhe-mais-de-50-num-ano/</link><description>The housing market continues in contraction and within one year the average price of the square meter devalued 23.8 percent. If the comparison is made with the pre-pound period, prices fell 39.5 percent
 
In early May, the number of transactions in the housing market dropped to less than half, with a 57.6 percent reduction compared to the first half of May last year. The information is contained in the Statistics of the Directorate of Finance Services (DSF).
According to the most recent data, in the first half of May this year there was a total of 78 purchases and housing sales, which contrasts with the 184 transactions recorded in the first fifteen days of May 2024. This is a difference of 106 businesses.
Changes within one year did not become the number of transactions, the same happened with the average price of the square meter. In the first half of May this year the average housing price was 69,634 patacas per square meter, which means a 23.8 percent reduction compared to the same period, when the average price was 91,361 patacas per square meter.
The reduction means that if a person paid, last year, 5.80 million patacas for a housing, the same house would be worth 4.42 million patacas, which implies a devaluation of 1.38 million patacas.
In early May this year, Coloane was the region with the most expensive houses, where the average price was 90,755 patacas per square meter. Instead, on the Macao peninsula the average price per square meter was 69,132 patacas per square meter, the smallest.
Other realities
If the comparison is made with the first half of April this year, the reduction at both the number of transactions and the price is more moderate. In terms of housing price, within one month the reduction was 11 percent, given that at the beginning of April this year the average price of the square meter was set at 78,204 patacas.
When analyzing the tendency to the number of transactions, the reduction was 34.6 percent, greater than one third, since in early April had been registered with the DSF a total of 133 transactions. The latest number of transactions was only 78 purchases and sales, which means a difference of 55 transactions.
Comparisons with the pre-pound period show an even more pronounced contrast. At the level of the square meter, the comparison with the beginning of May 2019 shows a 39.5 percent reduction from 115,071 patacas per square meter to 69,634 patacas per square meter. Given these numbers, if a person had compared a housing in early May 2019 for 5.80 million patacas, this same house would now be valued at 3.51 million patacas, a difference of 2.29 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:36:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Iam | More than 60 products with export facilities</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/iam-mais-de-60-produtos-com-facilidades-de-exportacao/</link><description>More than 50 types of Macao foods have been covered by the “Cooperation Agreement in the Safety Control of food products manufactured in Macao and exported to the interior of China” since it was signed by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) with China entities in 2019.
According to an AMI note, besides these foods, “about 10 types of meat products were recommended by AMI to China's General Customs Administration to be successfully registered” in the country, such as “traditional pastry products, ready -to -eat swallow nests, meat products, among others”, under the “memorandum over sanitary inspection and veterinary requirements for meat products China ”, signed in 2023.
Chinese entities that have established cooperation with Macau are the General Management of China Customs and the Secretariat for Administration and Justice, creating “an innovative model of cooperative supervision”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:34:48</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad for us, in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Myanmar | XI expresses the desire to “accelerate cooperation”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/myanmar-xi-manifesta-vontade-de-acelerar-cooperacao/</link><description>Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday sent a message to Myanmar Military Junta Chief, Min Aung Hlaing, expressing the willingness to “accelerate high quality cooperation” between China and ancient Burma.
Xi stressed that the friendship between China and Myanmar “resisted the test of time and was reinforced,” according to a statement issued by the 75th anniversary of the establishment of bilateral diplomatic relations, quoted by the Chinese official news agency Xinhua.
"The two countries have maintained a good neighborhood, deepened mutually beneficial cooperation and firmly leaned on issues related to their fundamental interests and essential concerns, thus giving an excellent example of friendly exchange between nations," said the Chinese head of state.
China attributes “great importance” to the development of ties with Myanmar and is willing to work with the country, using the 75th anniversary of diplomatic ties “as an opportunity to accelerate high quality cooperation within the track and route,” said Xi.
The Chinese president met with Min Aung Hlaing on May 9 in Moscow, in terms of the first personal meeting between the two since the coup d'état was carried out by the Military Board on February 1, 2021, with the arrest of President-elect Win Myint, as well as the former government party leader, Aung Suu Kyi, and other rulers and politicians.
Although diplomatic exchanges between Myanmar and China have not been interrupted by the coup, they have become more public over the years, such as Beijing's mediation in the conflict.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:50:50</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong USA AI to predict Alzheimer's risks through retina images</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/hong-kong-usa-ia-para-prever-riscos-de-alzheimer-atraves-de-imagens-da-retina/</link><description>A Hong Kong Health Center has developed a system that uses Artificial Intelligence Technologies (AI) to predict the risk of Alzheimer's disease through retinal image analysis, a pioneering advance in the world.
The system is not invasively analyzes the bottom images of the eye, detecting early changes in blood vessels and retinal nerves that may be related to Alzheimer's disease, allowing to identify potential risk cases years before clinical symptoms appear.
Humansa Medical Center, a longevity-centered health center, has developed the system in collaboration with I-Cognitio Sciences, an ophthalmological technology company at the Chinese University of Hong Kong (CUHK).
The artificial intelligence of i-cognitio has been validated with a vast data set, which includes nearly 13,000 eye background images of 648 patients diagnosed with Alzheimer's and over 3,000 individuals with normal cognition.
A study published in 2022 in Lancet Digital Health journal showed that artificial intelligence technology developed for detecting Alzheimer's risk reaches a precision of 80 percent to 92 percent in multiethnic populations from various countries.
Dementia affects about one third of people over 85 in the Asia Pacific region, according to recent data. In Hong Kong, dementia affects 10 percent of the population over 70 years old and Alzheimer's disease is responsible for more than half of diagnosed cases.
Scientific studies underline that up to 45 percent of dementia cases could be avoided or delayed through early interventions, stressing the importance of early detection to mitigate the impact of dementia on the population.
However, conventional cognitive tests and brain structural imaging have limited accuracy, while advanced methods such as amyloid pet and cerebrospinal fluid analysis are invasive and less accessible to the general population.
Crucial action
In this context, this study has developed a model based on deep learning with an approach that promises to offer “a simple, low -cost and poorly laborious solution” to identify potential patients in community environments and provide adequate accuracy and sensitivity.
In an effort to highlight AI relevance in the diagnosis and health care of the brain, Vincent Mok, director and founder of I-Cognitio, highlighted the fundamental role of the retina as a window to the brain. According to Mok, "through non -invasive eye photography, it is possible to identify changes in retinal blood vessels and retinal nerves linked to Alzheimer's disease."
The expert explained that these changes in the retina may manifest themselves 10 to 15 years before Alzheimer's clinical symptoms are evident, which represents a crucial opportunity for early intervention.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:49:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese vice-prime minister in London to discuss tariffs with the US</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/vice-primeiro-ministro-chines-em-londres-pra-debater-tarifas-com-os-eua/</link><description>Chinese vice-master-master, he Lifeng, will lead the Chinese delegation in commercial negotiations with US representatives tomorrow in London, the China Ministry of Foreign Affairs announced Saturday.
In a statement quoted by the Spanish Agency of Efe, the Chinese Foreign Ministry indicated that He Lifeng will visit the United Kingdom from June 8 to 13 “at the invitation of the British government” and take advantage of its stay in the country to attend the “United States and Commercial Consultation Mechanism”.
He, very close to China President Xi Jinping, was in charge of leading the commercial negotiations held last month in Geneva with US Treasury Secretary Scott Bessent, who ended with a tariff truce between the two powers.
The announcement was made a day after US President Donald Trump anticipated that the meeting on tariffs between US and China commercial delegates, agreed on Thursday in a telephone call with Xi Jinping, will be held Monday in London.
The conversation between the two leaders occurred after last week Trump accused China, without giving details of violating the bilateral tariff pause agreement reached in May after the meeting in Geneva. Beijing answered arguing that it was Washington who violated the deal by imposing new chip restrictions and the cancellation of visas for Chinese students announced the week before.
Open war
Both countries had started a tariff escalation the day after Trump's announcement in early April of their so -called “reciprocal” tariffs, imposing at least 10 percent on all products entering the United States, regardless of their origin.
Chinese products were subject to a 34 percent surcharge, in addition to the 20 percent taxes under the fight against fentanyl trafficking, an opioce that is causing a severe health crisis in the United States, and the customs rights that existed before Donald Trump's reelection.
Beijing retaliated with equivalent tariffs, which led to a Customs War with Washington, reaching 125 percent and 145 percent, respectively, about the products of each country, causing a strong slowdown between the two giants.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:47:08</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Discarded tariff retaliation that compromises “successful DNA”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/09/hong-kong-descartada-retaliacao-tarifaria-que-comprometa-adn-de-sucesso/</link><description>John Lee defends the Statute of the Special Administrative Region as a Free Port and wants to diversify the territory market increasingly away from the United States
 
Hong Kong Chief Executive John Lee said the tensions between Beijing and Washington will not make the city adopt retaliation measures, which would compromise their “successful DNA” and free port zone status. In an interview with Hong Kong South China Morning Post, on the third anniversary of his administration, Lee said his government prepared "contingency plans for the worst scenarios."
He also assured that he is trying to counteract the impact of customs customs imposed by US President Donald Trump, China, who also affect the Special Chinese administrative region, despite the regime "one country, two systems."
Hong Kong leader reaffirmed that the metropolis will maintain its Porto Livre statute and excluded the possibility of retaliation against the US, even if relations between Beijing and Washington deteriorate. Lee has rejected that this attitude is “passive”, defending the strategy as a way of preserving Hong Kong's economic status.
According to the Hong Kong Basic Law, the mini-consumption that governs the city, the region will maintain its role as customs territory independent of China and will not impose tariffs unless the law sets the opposite, consolidating the position of Porto Livre.
By other waters
Lee also stated that in the two years left of her term, the Hong Kong government will intensify market diversification measures for the benefit of local companies, reducing their exposure to the United States and encouraging expansion to "blue oceans" in high potential economic regions, such as Southeast Asian and Middle East.
"With 180-190 global economies, opportunities are vast. We are talking about reorienting strategies, developing new abilities and forging strategic alliances," he said, stressing the need to consolidate Hong Kong's position as a world financial and commercial center in the face of geopolitical tensions.
The United States is the second largest Hong Kong export market, with a volume of $ 37.9 billion in goods in 2024, led by equipment and telecommunications parts and followed by computers, precious stones, jewelry, semiconductors and valves and electronic tubes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-09 03:45:35</pubDate></item><item><title>CITIGROUP | Fired 3,500 employees in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/citigroup-despedidos-3-500-funcionarios-na-china/</link><description>The US bank citigrigoup fired about 3,500 technology division employees in mainland China, as part of a global cost reduction strategy and operational restructuring, Jornal Financial Times said yesterday.
The cuts affect a division based in the cities of Shanghai and Dalian, responsible for the provision of computer services to Citigroup operations in more than 20 countries.
According to the bank, some of the jobs will be relocated to other countries, "to be closer to the business and products they support," without, however, revealing numbers or concrete destinations. The financial institution also indicated that the process should be completed "at the beginning of the fourth quarter."
"Although there is still work to do, many of our efforts have enabled the efficiency of our way of operating, our workforce and the global presence in infrastructure," said Marc Luet, Citi's head to Japan, North Asia and Australia, quoted by the Financial Times.
The bank, which has been present in mainland China since 1902, has ensured that the decision will not have an impact on the banking operations of its Chinese subsidiary, headquartered in Shanghai, nor the Canton -based technology team that continues to provide services to mainland China and Hong Kong.
Third largest United States Bank in terms of assets, Citigroup has sought to resolve persistent operational and profitability challenges through deep restructuring, which included the dismissal of thousands of workers and a simplification of the management structure.
This cut represents one of the largest discharges recorded between foreign financial groups in China in recent years, and reflects a growing trend of frame reduction in the technological area.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 01:00:12</pubDate></item><item><title>Japan Sea | Seoul rescues four North Koreans on boat</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/mar-do-japao-seul-resgata-quatro-norte-coreanos-em-barco-a-deriva/</link><description>South Korea announced yesterday that it rescued four North Koreans whose boat was allegedly drift in territorial waters in the Japan Sea.
The South Korean navy “detected a small North Korean wooden boat about 100 kilometers from the coast of Goseong”, on the east coast of South Korea, a military spokesman said. According to South Korean news agency Yonhap, the rescued had apparently crossed the sea border accidentally and asked to be returned to North Korea.
The four were delivered "to the competent [South Korean authorities]," the military said, adding that the incident happened in May. North Korean deserters are usually subject to interrogation by South Korean security services.
"If they wish to return to North Korea, we will guarantee rapid and safe repatriation for humanitarian reasons," said South Korean Unification Ministry. Seul said he is still awaiting a Pyongyang response about two North Korean repatriation found in similar circumstances for three months in the Yellow Sea, located between China, North Korea and South Korea.
In the inaugural speech on Wednesday, South Korea's new center-left president Lee Jae-Myung said he wanted to approach North Korea in a speech that contrasts with the hard line of the deposed predecessor Yoon Suk-Youol.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:58:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong | Appointed first foreign judge in one year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/hong-kong-nomeado-primeiro-juiz-estrangeiro-em-um-ano/</link><description>The Hong Kong Parliament approved the first appointment of a foreign judge to the Chinese semi -autonomous region of a one year after a series of layoffs. The Territory Legislative Council voted on Wednesday in favor of a government proposal to appoint William Young to Hong Kong's last court for a three-year term, which is expected to begin in June.
Hong Kong's number two number two, chief secretary Eric Chan Kwok-Ki stressed to the deputies that the judge led a commission of inquiry into the March 2019 attack on two Mosques in Christchurs. In August 2020, a white supremacist was sentenced to perpetual penalty without right to parole - the first sentence of this type in New Zealand - for having killed 51 Muslims.
The appointment of judges of other jurisdictions that share the system known as 'Common Law' inherited from the UK “contributed to the maintenance of a high level of confidence in the judicial system” of Hong Kong, defended Eric Chan. The chief secretary also said that the coming of foreign judges "demonstrates that the basic law [Hong Kong's" mini-constitution "guarantees the independent exercise of judicial power."
Return to the World
After reforming herself from the Supreme Court of New Zealand in 2022, William Young, 73, served as a judge in the seychelles higher courts, Samoa and the Fiji Islands. In July 2022, the New Zealand was appointed to the courts of the Dubai International Financial Center in the United Arab Emirates, but fired less than a month later.
At the time, Young gave the risk of “adverse perceptions” after the Human Rights Defense Organization Amnesty International accused the country of appointing foreign judges to try to legitimize the political regime.
Five non -permanent foreign judges (two from the United Kingdom and three from Australia) currently perform functions in the Hong Kong Superior Court, which also has Lusodescendent Roberto Ribeiro. Several foreign magistrates, including from the United Kingdom and Canada, have abandoned the territory of the last 12 months.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:57:13</pubDate></item><item><title>Education | China asks the US not to politicize exchanges</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/educacao-china-pede-aos-eua-para-nao-politizarem-intercambios/</link><description>China yesterday criticized the new restrictions imposed by US President Donald Trump at the entrance of foreign citizens, including those who affect Harvard University, and appealed to Washington to stop educational cooperation.
"Educational cooperation between China and the US is mutually beneficial. China has always opposed politicization in this area," the Ministry of Foreign Ministry Lin Jian said yesterday at a press conference.
Lin responded to Trump's signed order that suspends for six months the entry of new international students into Harvard on charges of “radicalism” and “worrying foreign connections” by the academic center. Beijing warned that this measure will “harm the US image and credibility” and has ensured that it will defend the legitimate rights of its students and academics abroad.
Harvard, one of the world's most prestigious universities, currently welcomes 10,158 international students from 150 countries, including 2,126 from China, according to data on the 2024/2025 school year published on the institution's international office portal.
The spokesman also reacted to the new ban on traveling to the United States for citizens from 12 countries, including Iran, Haiti, Equatorial Guinea, Somalia and Yemen, and the restrictions imposed on citizens of seven, such as Cuba and Venezuela.
"Interpersonal exchanges are the fundamental basis for promoting understanding and cooperation between countries. We hope that all parties will create conducive conditions for this purpose rather than raising barriers," Lin said.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:45:54</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Beijing offers rewards for the capture of computer pirates</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/taiwan-pequim-oferece-recompensas-pela-captura-de-piratas-informaticos/</link><description>Canton's Chinese City Public Security Office will offer rewards to those who help capture more than 20 Taiwan individuals accused of conducting cybership against a Chinese technology company.
This is the first time Chinese public security authorities have taken this measure to “combat Taiwan's separatist forces,” according to the Official Global Times. It is also “the first coordinated action to repression of criminal activities organized by the Taiwan information force, communications and electronics,” he added.
According to the Global Times, these “20 suspects of Taiwan Island” were involved in cybercats against a local Chinese technology company and are linked to the Progressive Democratic Party (DPP) authorities, currently in power in Taiwan.
"The cybership was directed and executed by the DPP information, communications and electronics command, which performs multiple illegal activities," said the Cantão Municipal Public Security Office, which issued search warrants for the 20 suspects.
Chinese authorities have added that those who provide valid clues and help capture suspects will receive a reward of 10,000 yuan for each of them.</description><pubDate>2025-06-06 00:43:55</pubDate></item><item><title>Filipe de Saavedra, Teacher: “A Camões Interpretative Center in Macau is missing”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/21/filipe-de-saavedra-docente-falta-um-centro-interpretativo-de-camoes-em-macau/</link><description>Professor at the University of Science and Technology of Macao and a scholar of the presence of Camões in Asia, Philip de Saavedra understands that Macau is missing an interpretative center about the poet's life and work. The academic spoke yesterday at the National Library in Lisbon, about the correspondence written by Luís de Camões in Asia
 
He participated yesterday at the “from Lisbon to Goa: What the Letters of Camões” participated. What path does the East arise portrayed in these letters, and who were directed?
The letters Camões wrote from Asia are in the order of the dozens. There is in them scholarship, philosophy, and also a lot of humor, sarcasm, and satire of humanist nature. Some were written from Ternate, others from Malaca, Macau, probably others from Cambodia, to recipients in India and Portugal. With the exception of the letters of Goa, where the identification of the writing site is generally present, maping those that were written during the rest of it would be a complex task. They are only given as written in Asia.
Can you give examples of written letters in this context?
I mention here two of the first he sent to the kingdom. The epistle whose first line is “The Poet Simony speaking” was written in January 1554, when Camões has just arrived in Goa, destined for his pupil, D. António de Noronha. It is a very emotional letter, giving it the storm that had plagued the Armada in the Cape of Good Hope, "seeing the death of the before me." Camões survived this limit experience aboard the São Bento ship, the only one to arrive that year to Goa, and which was lost in the turn of the Christmas lands, dying in this second bid the Captain Fernão de Álvares Cabral, and many of those who traveled with him. In addition to the news of his salvation, the poet was equally eager to tell his friend the expedition of D. Afonso de Noronha to Malabar, in which he had taken part in the previous month. In Irenal pages, Camões vehemently condemns the massacre of the few native troops by the “thick armed” of the disproportionate vice-king army. In his radical compliment of peace, the poet calls "true remedy" to the early death that cure the war crazes of those who want to live "by knights", for "who will walk by following the fero Mars always brings their eyes to their danger." Cruelly prophetic words: by irony of fate, at the moment the poet wrote these lines and sent them, that recipient diletus, for whose life he feared, already lay, lying during a military foray in Ceuta on April 29, 1553, only 17 years old.
And the second letter?
A year later, in January 1555, he wrote to a friend a different epistle in tone and in purpose, whose first line is "I wished so much", where he evoked the shock he suffered from the death of D. António, gathering a sonnet that had composed to his memory. It is clear that Camões also had great intimacy with this correspondent, who knew D. António and the poetry of Camões, Petrarch and Boscán. Interestingly, the letter includes some male lines, which Camões says they are mandatory in private letters, containing what can be called a resort conversation, so being worship or scholar did not prevent it if it were "bon vivant".
The presence of Camões in Macau is still wrapped in a certain myth. What are the concrete tests of your presence in the territory?
It is necessary to separate the waters. The landing of Camões in Patane's busty, then called “cave”, is surrounded by a beautiful legendary aura. But the presence of Camões in Macao, this is not involved in "myth", is a factual and historical reality, founded on a wide variety of testimonies, all independent of each other. Insisting on a chronology that contained in the sources, but which was flagrantly erroneous, it was deliberately sought to confuse the doubts that could have about his permanence in the sinned, although unjustified, with false doubts about the poet's stay in Macau, which are laughable and devoid of the minimum foundation. The joke ran a swimming, and little by little it was embedded in the collective imagination, to the point that some less informed people take it for a supposed “discovery” recent. However, nonsense was released in 1907, and soon dismantled in 1911 by Jordan de Freitas. Judge Eduardo Ribeiro put more “points in the iis” in this regard. In your time I will publish the full documentation about the presence of Camões in Macao, putting a definitive end to the mythical “myth”.
What life did Camões in Macau?
We can say that these two years were those of the greatest professional, economic and affective in his life. Is it written poetry? Constantly, as the dimension of the work attests. A significant part of “the Lusíadas” was composed here, although the poem had neither began nor ended in Macao. Not least in his life was that it was in Macao who publicly assumed a relationship with a young Chinese, most exactly the Tanka ethnicity of poor fishermen. This asymmetrical connection is not surprising and with a modest young woman: only disadvantaged families would not prevent daughters from relate to foreigners. This explains the fact that she left with Camões in 1565 to Goa, with concubine status. But the private vessel in which they followed, belonging to Chinese merchants, suffered a wreck by Cambodia, and Camões lost there the “kind lamp I loved so much”. It was only after his death that he would come to chrisma as Denamene, a Greek nymph of the waters, so that she could live forever in the ocean. The Chinese of Macao have a special relationship with Camões, such as the Portuguese and the Macanese.
How is this relationship?
It existed in the eighteenth century in Macao the first monument in honor of Camões, something that in Portugal only began to think about the following century. Recebeu mesmo uma inscrição em chinês, e até um pavilhão chinês foi construído sobre o santuário dele. The Viscount of Juromenha says that in 1845 the Viceroy of Canton and Imperial Commissioner Ki-A there was worshiped Camões as the “Portuguese Confucius”. And rightly, Camões shares many aspects of the sages of Chinese tradition: he established a dialogue with the masters through the recreation of larger works, cultivated a millennial tradition (he gloss two thousand years prior to his own time), practiced itinerary as a source of "sagesse", said the primacy of poetry, conceived the rivers as mythical entities, even personifying them, even personifying them, even demonstrou acentuada tendência para moralizar, e epitomou o seu pensamento em sentenças magistrais.
What connection did Camões have with Goa?
Unlike Macao, Goa raised in Camões mostly negative feelings. The first impressions he had, like a lawless land in which only the little turns were worse, could not have been worse, as read in the initial letter to which he alluded: "long land, from all the poor honorable grave." In the second letter, he goes on, "I can say that it is the mother of bad villains, and stepmother of honorable men." These impressions would not improve over time, as corroborated the satire that led to the expulsion to Ternate in 1556. Goa, where he became the deputy protected, to fall later in the greatest disfavor under D. Antão de Noronha, was in his texts the inverted mirror of the Kingdom, the corrupt and corrupt Babylon, theil of God, and the betrayal of God, King and the law. In what is not original, as there are other sources that reinforce this Jeremiac and apocalyptic portrait of the capital of the Portuguese East Empire. Remember Bocage: "From the land to worst you are, O goa." This said, obviously that he will also have lived there sweethearts, especially under the viceroyalty of his protectors, and in living with some companions of the poetic lines that then lived there, and which he evokes in the so-called “feast of trovas”. To one of these cultured spirits, the poet Luís Franco, even a copy of his almost complete works, including the 'self of filodemo' that had composed there, that they could be saved if another adversity survived in the kingdom to the kingdom.

Do you think Portugal should pay more attention to your writings, streamlining your work more? How?
In Lisbon it is necessary to build a great literary museum dedicated to Camões and its creations. The ideal place will be the Convent of St. Bento de Xabregas, where his friend Dom António had a grave at the Pantheon of the Line Chapel. Also in Goa the statue of Camões left for exile in the cruelly called “Archaeological Museum”, which is not the right place to end the poetry or image of a poet. Being the greatest intangible heritage of Macao, Camões has been poorly used in this region. multimedia.
What about Macau? Is Camões studied at higher education?
Two students from the Macao University of Sciences and Technology will now defend their master's theses. The first is an in -depth technical study of the translation of Zhang Weim of the Camões Odes. The second runs through the literary survival of the figure of Dinamene in contemporary Portuguese fiction, and are both excellent, bringing novelty.</description><pubDate>2025-05-21 22:42:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Leão, architect and co-author of “Layering the City” | A four -hand city</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/16/rui-leao-arquitecto-e-co-autor-de-layering-the-city-uma-cidade-a-quatro-maos/</link><description>Architects Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni have accumulated many drawings over the years, which have now been materialized in “Layering the City”, a work that was released last week at the Venice Architecture Biennial. The book results from two lives dedicated to architecture and two doctoral theses defended at the Royal Melbourne Institute of Technology
 
How does the initiative come to publish “Layering the City”, which makes the retrospective of your work a little?
This project is born from a dialogue between my dissertation thesis and Carlotta [Carlotta Bruni's] dissertation thesis, who both take different aspects of our contribution as architects to Macau, to the city. And therefore, the project of this book is the encounter of these two theses.
The title of the book refers to the idea of ​​a town in layers.
No, what happens is that in the case of our views, my and Carlotta, there is work brought by each one to the project, and which gives a response to the programmed request, what the client asks, to what lives in the alignment plant [of the project], or a series of questions at civic, public space or the right to quality of life. There are a number of social dimensions [to take into account] to make spaces for people, even when they are impossible [in terms] of politics and in the city. It is these layers that go into the projects and that, deep down, are creating opportunities to qualify the life of the city, the person, the street. And this has nothing to do with those who pay, it has to do with the management that the architect makes in the city through the project. It is these layers, the layers, in which the architect is enriching what is the project's offer to the city and creates several micro-projects within this larger project, which qualify the ride, social spaces and public space in a way that was not requested.
Therefore, in a project of architecture always persists the idea of ​​the people and the spaces they inhabit.
In the case of Macau there is this extreme situation where the public space is always the minimum, with a narrow walk, and where everything is resolved. Because there is a lack of more public space profile in the city, this management done by the architect through the project turns out to be a way to compensate for the city, to reconcile people with it, or the opposite.
The cover of the book refers to Fai Chi Kei's public housing project. I assume that they consider the project one of the great milestones of your studio.
Undoubtedly. This was the first large housing building in collective terms, where we had the opportunity to apply ideas that we had developed to the public space, in Praça do Lago, or even in the park next door. All of these projects have a lot of involvement with the public space and this was our first initiative with a housing program. We did a number of super important experiences that allowed us to demonstrate that it was possible to qualify public housing. We produce a series of gardens, packets, air gardens in various floors [from the building]. We were collecting the floors two to two and four to four to create communities inside the building, almost like a Chinese pharmacy that has drawers, social interaction sites since the bottom floor, and so on. All of this has been worked with small public terraces present throughout the project, and in this respect, it is very innovative. It is, in fact, a demonstration that, whether it is a housing building or a museum, it can indeed contribute to the qualification of people's lives. Any [architecture program, in order to order or contract] it serves for the architect to act on the project.
Que outros projectos constam neste livro?
We have the Barra station and the intermodal zone [related to the light meter]. There are two projects, for us, very important, because they also come to reconfirm the ability to overlap many and many layers. In the case of Barra Station, there is also a public park on top, and the two marginals, the historic and the new. It is an all -glass, transparent project that allows me to be on the side of the slaughterhouse and see the river and boats through the glass. The building turns out to be a kind of octopus that makes ground level connections, with the gardens around the season that connect with the roof. There is a certain complexity, in which almost a new city system is created and there is at the same time a trial overlap of the train, buses and the passing people. The book also has projects that are not yet built.
What was it like to combine the content of your doctoral thesis with that of Carlotta Bruni?
The book consists of texts by some critics about our work. There is a text by Jorge Figueira, for example, and a great interview conducted by Ana Vaz Milheiro [Academic] and then has our texts.
Is there a presence by architect Manuel Vicente in this work?
Manuel Vicente is very present, because some of these projects were made in partnership with him. Therefore, there is a continuity of these first projects for those who came next, already without Manuel Vicente, and who is very polished for us. Deep down, it has to do with what we not only inherited, but what we brought with us from Manuel.
Presenting this work at the Venice Architecture Biennial, and considering that the MSAR is also represented with an exhibition, is it important for your work and visibility of the studio?
Sim. A ideia de fazer a publicação, com a Actar Books, de Barcelona, tem a ver com o colocar a obra, e mais do que isso, a sua mensagem, que é muito específica a Macau e à nossa maneira de trabalhar, na comunidade internacional e de arquitectos, e isso passa muito pela Bienal. Foi também na Europa que se construiu um consenso ao nível das descrições [na arquitectura] desde há alguns séculos, e em que há uma discussão, nacional e internacional, em torno das questões da profissão. Queremos que a nossa obra esteja presente, quer através do livro, quer através da Actar Books, nessa comunidade internacional, para que faça parte do mundo.
Leaves and layers
“Layering the City” intends to establish with the international community of architects and passionate about the profession a dialogue showing the last years of work and the vision of the LBA - Rui Leão and Carlotta Bruni's architecture and planning. The work is born of the intersection between two doctoral theses of the two architects: “Designing by Increments: Opportunistic Planning as Urban Strategy for Macau” (by Rui Leão) and “Shaping Macau’s Unpurposed Space: Design in Context” (by Carlotta Bruni).
According to a book presentation, "LBA's intellectual contributions are evidenced through the space narratives that integrate complex urban contexts with culturally sensitive design strategies."
The two architects and their team "emphasize the importance of creating spaces that harmonize with their surroundings, while responding to the functional needs of modern urban life." It is therefore a “particularly relevant approach in Macao, where the juxtaposition of the old and the new is a defining characteristic of the city”, it reads.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 01:04:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Álvaro Barbosa, vice-rector of the University of São José: “Student visa is very limiting”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/alvaro-barbosa-vice-reitor-da-universidade-de-sao-jose-visto-de-estudante-e-muito-limitativo/</link><description>The University of São José continues the negotiation saga with the Chinese authorities to recruit students from the interior of China. Vice-rector Álvaro Barbosa expects, soon, the increase in master's students from 30 to 200. Regarding the internationalization of higher education, the official advocates changes in student visas to facilitate recruitment
 
Does the recruitment of students from the interior of China remain a matter pending to the University of Saint Joseph?
It is a process that is underway. We have had huge support from the Macao government in negotiations to obtain the quota for our university, and they have been tireless in the effort to try to resolve the issues raised by the central government. Many of the questions are legitimate and concern concerns that arise. We were granted a temporary quota of 30 students for masters ago over a probative period, which served to evaluate how we, as Western University, would host students from China. From China, there is this concern with the host of students in Macau. I think we have made a huge effort and the students who are there, included in this contingent, are quite satisfied.
Is this quota for masters just?
Yes. For a degree we do not have authorization yet. In this way, we are currently at the time we try to overcome this probative period in order to obtain a quota of about 200 students for masters. We are in the final phase of the evaluation process and everything has been doing well. We will have the possibility that, next academic year, expand this quota. That would be great, because for our university, to have a greater impact of our mission in Macao, it is essential to have access to students from mainland China. We cannot be a university in an integrated region in a country like China, and not contact with students from China.
Is it more difficult for USJ to compete with other universities, such as those of Hong Kong, by foreign students, outside China?
The issue of recruitment of international students has become a priority for Macao universities. In the last two or three years, it has become evident that this internationalization is very important. What difficulty is there? There is the issue related to student visas, as these visas currently do not allow students to do any kind of work, denying them that minimum local subsistence mechanism to be able to meet expenses. Nor is it contemplated the possibility of, when the student concludes his formation, to be in the territory and find work. What all countries and regions that are competitive in higher education do, such as Singapore, Hong Kong or Australia, is to have incentive policies. Allow students to work part -time, for example. In Hong Kong when a degree ends, the student can stay in the territory up to a maximum of two years to find a job. This kind of measures do not yet exist in Macau, but I think the government is pondering this possibility. From the moment the decision was made that the internationalization of higher education was important, this must be accompanied with the corresponding measures. The current student visa is extremely limiting and does not encourage the coming to Macao to study, only allows coming. This issue was not as present as it is now, but now there is a strategic policy of internationalization.
It is also a matter of survival for local universities.
Yes. Perhaps there is no greater example of a catalyst for the diversification of Macau's economy than higher education. We have ten institutions, 60,000 students in about 700,000 inhabitants. This is the potential of internationalization, to foster diversification.

And also the research that comes out of higher education.
The investigation, the dynamics of the work that is done. There are a number of vectors that higher education brings to a region or country, this happened to Portugal, for example, with the policy of doctoral scholarships for students from abroad, which completely changed the dynamics of higher education. Cape Verde developed thanks to the impact of higher education.
Then we need to make the system more flexible in Macau.
I don't know if it's a matter of having a holistic view of strategy. There may be an idea, but then it does not intervene in all the necessary dimensions to achieve a certain goal. But I am very optimistic. I believe this new student policy is a key step to be taken in Macau. The internationalization strategy followed by all these countries and regions I spoke, and were successful in capturing international students, was always the same. No need to invent much. First, one should increase the capacity and notoriety of universities, and then a policy of scholarships, which will enhance a student flow, creating a reference for the territory, so that studying there becomes a habit. After this flow of students for a few years, an image is already created and some scholarships can be removed, which students will continue to choose a particular territory to study in it. Australia has a huge higher education industry, for example, and I think that in Macau we just have to follow the same strategies. We do, at USJ, that a little.
How, in concrete terms?
We offer many scholarships, and in this sense the Diocese of Macao has helped us build this flow of international students that allow us to create this dynamic that we hope will be sustainable by itself in the future. I think the government is also doing this. There have always been scholarships in Macau, attributed mainly by the Macau Foundation, but this measure will be strengthened. Solving the student's visa issue, creating a scholarship incentive system for five to ten years, Macau will have a bright future as an international higher education destination. But we need to invest, continue, and it takes a few years.
USJ created the “Macau Hub” platform, in partnership with the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM) in 2023. At what stage is this project?
This project has to do with our interest in developing a relationship dynamic of Lusophone countries centered in Lisbon in the area of ​​entrepreneurship, first. This cabinet we have at CCCM is not intended to offer training in Portugal, but we want to do something else. As we are positioned in the Great Bay and with Hengqin, where it is intended to activate a business ecosystem, we want to take advantage of the fact that we have relations with the Lusophone world to activate the access of the startups of Portugal, Brazil and Angola, above all, to the great bay and hengqin. We are trying to create a kind of incubator of transnational companies, in which we support the development of Lusophone businesses that want to settle in the large bay and also the reverse system. Strategically, for a university, it is absolutely fundamental to have a dynamic in the area of ​​entrepreneurship. Currently, more than half of our students do not want to go to the corporate world, but create their own businesses. Just as universities have to have employability solutions, they also have to have them for entrepreneurs, who are increasingly. So a university has to have a business incubator. My vision of the future for higher education goes around: a university, besides having a library and canteen, will also have its own business incubator. I would say that most students of management or economy courses dream of having their own business, especially in China. China is perhaps one of the most entrepreneurial countries in the world. The CCCM welcomes this initiative in Portugal, but we also work with the Portuguese Catholic University.
And concrete results, already have it?
We have a number of small initial projects that are starting now, and we also work with many business organizations. We have now negotiated a series of projects, and I think everything will develop very quickly, based on the manifestations of interest we have. We were in Angola in December and we have already aligned a series of initiatives, we also have projects with Brazil and Portugal.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 22:56:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Adelina Moura, teacher and trainer: “The mobile phone is like a Swiss knife”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/04/07/adelina-moura-docente-e-formadora-o-telemovel-e-como-um-canivete-suico/</link><description>Graduated in the area of ​​educational technologies, Adelina Moura will conduct lectures to parents, students and teachers about the use of digital technologies in classrooms, within the “Letters &amp; Company” festival of the Portuguese Institute of the East. The teacher understands that prohibiting mobile phone in schools is not a solution
 
What are the challenges felt by teachers with the introduction of technologies in the classroom? Can the mobile phone actually be a complement to learning?
Yes. I've been saying this since 2005. The mobile phone can be an excellent learning tool, a means to motivate students and to enrich their learning. We have a kind of Swiss knife here, a very powerful equipment in the hands of the students and there is a school failure, because they do not work and help students enhance this equipment they have. What happens is that students learn in the worst way, in a destructed way, by attempt-rrove. There is a gap, as students are not alerted to the positive potential for mobile phone use. They face their mobile phones as a free time use, spending time on social networks and scrolling, and time consumes. It is essential that teachers are users, in their practices, mobile phones, and for the preparation of classes and other projects, to know how to prepare students. I consider that the school has lost several stages of students' preparation and awareness to use these equipment that lead to classes and with which schools have not spent any money. With the prohibition of bringing the mobile phone to the classroom we did not advance anything in this regard.
During the pandemic period, for example, the use of technologies, with distance learning, was quite enhanced.
But during the pandemic we also burned some steps regarding the use of digital by teachers, because before the pandemic many teachers did not believe or used. They thought it was a fashion and they saw no use in the use of mobile phones and other technologies. With the pandemic the use of these equipment proved that without them the situation of education would have been much worse. In these pandemic years, teachers have become more aware of the technologies that already exist and are available to anyone. With internet access on mobile phone, something that has existed since 2007 with the launch of the first iPhone, the e-learning system is enhanced and then we move to “Mobile Learning”, where you can learn anywhere and anytime with mobile devices. It is this reality that we see a little away from school.
And after the pandemic, how has it been?
I think we will take a few more steps towards digital literacy. With Artificial Intelligence (IA), it seems that we are as in the phase I created my first website in 1999 or email in 1995. We are at the beginning. But it is 30 years of technology where there have been many changes, and technology in fact goes on and if we immediately do not realize what we have available, we and students, we help create a moat that has happened in the past compared to digital. In the face of AI, if we do not look back and do not realize what was not done and should have been at school level, we are wasting time. Only a few years from now will people be alert to AI, and the gap is increasing. Hence it is very important to bet now, in this early stage, in the training of teachers, students and families.
Is there much ignorance of parents, removal from this reality?
We have parents who are from this century. That is, they were born with the existence of computers, internet, saw the appearance of the smartphone. But when they studied, the school did not talk about the potential of digital. So these former students came to society and did not bring this sensitivity to digital, to educate their children. We teachers, when we do digital training, are doing good to society because we are also preparing these young people for the future, because they will be parents and should be aware of educating their children. At school we do not only prepare for the job market, but for personal and family life. Hence teacher education is essential. The invitation I received from IPOR seems to me an excellent holistic view of everything, because the school includes several actors, connecting with society.
How should AI be introduced into the classroom?
We currently watch changes in search engines, in fact. We have search engines created from root to Age Age, for example. The best way to introduce AI into the classroom is to ask students and how they use it, and already resort to this tool. At the beginning of the academic year I always ask students to answer a questionnaire about their digital routines, and then I know more or less their practices. In 2023, when the chatgPT came out, I introduced AI in my classes, and realized that students were using this tool to deceive the teachers. Students have to realize that when using AI, they are falling into a certain trap because they are not learning. It is the law of the lowest effort, equal to the phase in which the internet emerged, when students selected, copied and sent to the teacher. We now have the problem that the answers are in Brazilian Portuguese, for example, and see as soon as I was used. We have, therefore, to dismantle this action in the heads and face them. I tell them that they are being intellectually dishonest and that they have not read the AI ​​response, for example. Since 2023, I feel that students, in the answers to this questionnaire I do, say they are afraid to use chatgpt because they are afraid of being caught by teachers. That is, it seems to have gained some conscience.
It will give these lectures in a different educational context in Asia, where the use of mobile phone can be earlier. How will you deal with these differences, or do you understand that the problems of using technology in the classroom are transversal?
It is a transverse question. Do we have to wonder if the use of a particular equipment and tool will make us wiser? It seems to me not, because we may have the equipment, but the use we make it varies a lot. I tell my students that they should be ashamed, because they have much easier access to content than in my time, when we truly had research and read in physical format. I tell them that with this technology they should all have a grade 20, and that they are wasting resources, being dishonest intellectually, because they sign works that are not theirs and do not read, even, they deliver. One of the works we have with students is to teach them how to make bibliographic references, refer to the sources. But I am an optimistic by nature, and I hope that in a decade, secondary education students who are fathers and mothers will be able to deal with these problems of social networks and increase fraud with their children. It is this “parents school” that the school can help create. We are in a moment with no return from digital, and forbidding is the most comfortable situation, but it is not the best to face reality. We have to use the right words to alert. We have in this time of alerts and consciences, encouraging the critical spirit of our students, which is little today.
 
Teach
Adelina Moura will teach a workshop for territory teachers on Saturday, with the session “Digital Literacy - Promotion of Positive Interactions”, aimed at teachers and agents of kindergarten, primary and secondary. The session takes place at the headquarters of IPOR, between 10am and 13h.
On the same day, but in the afternoon, the session will be directed to parents and children. Degree in Portuguese and French Teaching, Master in Pedagogical Supervision of Portuguese Teaching and Doctorate in Education Sciences, in the Specialty of Educational Technology, Adelina Moura has been developing research in the area of ​​Mobile Learning, with several publications in Portugal and abroad.
He is a teacher of Basic and Secondary Education, a tutor of distance learning courses at the Institute of Camões - Institute of Cooperation and Language and Training of Teacher Training, in specific didactics (Portuguese and French) and educational technology. On Wednesday, starting at 6:30 pm, Adelina Moura, Nuno Gomes and Min Yang will discuss “Artificial Intelligence in Education”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-07 01:11:29</pubDate></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
And what you have listed as an example of 'consequence' of this 'exclusion', is actually the means by which this exclusion also happens and remains. Gypsy people are out of theaters, both as consumers and producers (but go to the cinema). They are out of school, education and the gym. Either as 'users' or as producers (but go to school and are on the basis of knowledge construction and academic and scientific debates).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Macao's historicals get a GP clearance</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/20/historicos-de-macau-conseguem-apuramento-para-gp/</link><description>The Guangdong International Circuit welcomed, last weekend, the second and decisive double journey of Macao - Macau Road Sport Challenge cars, proof of finding for the most important motor racing of the season: the Macao Grand Prix. In a journey with few celebration reasons for the colors of the sinters, the veterans Jerónimo Badaraco and Rui Valente managed to ensure the qualification.
With a list of 68 subscribers, the grill was divided into two groups, A and B, with all the pilots competing with Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) or Subaru BRZ (ZD8) models. This year, with only one race scheduled for the Grand Prix Program - due to the inclusion of the FIA ​​Formula 4 World Cup - the number of riders was reduced to 36, which placed a supplementary pressure for both missing races. To complicate, the rain came, changing the turns to teams and riders.
In Group A, where Rui Valente faced a complicated weekend on the track around Zhaoqing, Célio Alves Dias and Maximiano Mannão failed to qualify, in a series dominated by Hong Kong pilots. In Saturday's race, the podium consisted of Wong Chuck Pan, Lo Pak Yu and Chan Ka Ping. On Sunday, these three repeated the feat, but with a new order: Lo Pak Yu, Chan Ka Ping and Wong Chuck Pan.
In difficult atmospheric conditions on Saturday, Rui Valente ended only 25th, due to an error in tuning, improving to 15th on Sunday, with the track dry. A penalty after the second race fired him to the 27th place. Still, the 7th place obtained on the first round was enough to secure a place in the Macao Grand Prix.
On the contrary, Maximiano Mannão, behind the wheel of a Toyota with the colors of the historic Macau Racing Team, ended on 26th and 14th, a result below the finding, but it turns out to be positive given that it was Jove Pilot's debut in these wanderings. Célio Alves Dias, with difficulties in his car since the first race, was 24th and 28th, far from the usual level of this experienced Macaense pilot.
Badaraco with final sprint '
On a weekend, where the lively races were broadcast on live streaming in Group B, Hong Kong riders stood out again. On Sunday, Adrian Chung won, with Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin completing the podium. In the second confrontation, Cheang Kin Sang reached a deserved victory, followed again by Leung Tsz Wa and Tsang Pak Yin.
Jerónimo Badaraco came to this challenging weekend without the assured clearance. A modest qualification and 11th Saturday place maintained the open outcome. However, a solid race on Sunday and an excellent 4th place assured veteran Macanese the much desired place on the grid of the Macao Grand Prix, along with countrymen Cheng Kin San, Leong Keng Hei, Lou Check In and Carson Tang.
Also outside the Grand Prix was Dionísio Albino Pereira, who finished 23rd in Saturday's race, but closed the time more forcefully, cutting the line of goal in 13th place in the second race.
At the end of the races, the competitors provisionally calculated had an extra technical verification, being forced to open engines and gearbox, to verify the legality of these two decisive organs of their vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-05-20 01:57:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Fit F4 World Cup will be in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/09/primeira-taca-do-mundo-de-f4-sera-em-macau/</link><description>The International Automobile Federation (FIA), announced on Wednesday afternoon that the 2025 Macao Grand Prix will feature its program with the first edition of the Formula 4 World Cup.
The World Council of Motorsport approved by electronic vote the creation of this Formula 4 World Cup in Macao, along with the return to the Territory of the Regional Formula World Cup, which in 2023 came to occupy the place of Formula 3, and the FIA ​​GT World Cup.
The concept of Formula 4 has been introduced by the FIA ​​for over a decade and has been one of the biggest success stories of motorized training sport, currently there are 13 different national championships within the technical and sports framework of the FIA. This will be the fourth time the discipline runs in Macao, having been a regular presence from 2020 to 2023, and was even “head of poster” in the three years the world was immersed in the pandemic.
The FIA ​​did not say how the pilots will be chosen, just referring in a statement that there will be "a rigorous selection process of pilots, with only the most talented young people to be authorized to compete." The International Federation also stressed that the Chinese company “Mintimes, organizer of the F4 Chinese Championship, will be the Single Operator, along with FFSA (Fédération Française du Sport Automobile), responsible for providing technical support to the F4 F4 World Cup”. This means that all competitors will have to use Mygale M21-F4 singleolugar, recently renamed Ligier JS F422.
Paris support
The chairman of the FIA ​​monoligae commission, the Italian Emanuele Pirro, said that “Macau is an essential part of the formation of a young pilot, and we have a duty to protect his legacy and future. There is as few challenges as the Macao Grand Prix that we feel that it was the right time to introduce the F4 Fia World Cup. From F4, which is a little more permissive than a regional formula car, so that when they return to a year or two to the FR world cup, they are prepared to truly show what they are capable. ”
Emanuele Pirro, a former guide race vender and an enthusiast of the MSAR test, also said that "we are also working hard to ensure that we take this opportunity to inspire and educate young Karting riders in the region. The potential for growth and development in China and the Asia Pacific region is huge as we boost participating in motorized sport."
Thinking about Macau
The FIA ​​long statement also states that this initiative “also aims to bring students from Karting de Macao, China and the region in general to watch the event in an observational manner, offering them the opportunity to experience a racing test and to obtain valuable knowledge for the next steps in their careers”.
Without going into detail, the international federation, which did not allow it to decline on the participation of Chinese teams in the regional formula cup last year, says that “this big step will undoubtedly benefit local Macao pilots, which will have access to a complete range of international events - Karting, Formula 4 and Regional Formula - on national soil”.
In a statement of Chong Coc Veng, president of the Macao-China General Automobile Association, he said: “We are happy to see FIA ​​hold a F4 World Cup at the Guide Circuit in Macao, which represents an opportunity for young people in the region to find their way of development from international Karting events to F4 and FR singleoligles, and become world champions in the future.”
The participation of MSAR pilots in this race has not yet been officially disclosed, but may be limited in number.</description><pubDate>2025-05-09 00:41:31</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Jaguar that won in Macau in 1984 returned to the tracks</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/06/06/gp-jaguar-que-venceu-em-macau-em-1984-regressou-as-pistas/</link><description>The more than seventy years of history of the Macau Grand Prix are people, machines and great moments. We were in 1984, when Tom Walkinshaw won Jaguar's only victory in the guide race. After years away from the audience, for the affected man, this same car returned to the tracks at the hands of an enthusiast of the MSAR MOTOR EVENT
 
Richard Meins, an English maritime transport entrepreneur who lived many years in Hong Kong, who participated on several occasions at the Macao Grand Prix, led this Jaguar XJs of Group A in the Historic Touring Car Challenge race, a competition for classics during the Donington Historic Festival. This “Big Cat”, Chassis No. 5 and one of the four original XJs still existing, is practically as it was in 1984, but given the limitations of tobacco advertising, today boasts the colors used in the European Tourism Championship, instead of the iconic black and gold decoration of John Player Special (JPS) that marked the ticket through the guide circuit.
Interestingly, this return to the clues, from a car that has been still in New Zealand and Japan, was scheduled for the Algarve International Race Track, but the Historic Touring Car Challenge canceled its race in early April in Portimão. So it was in lands of his majesty that Richard Meins made his first race with the British car.
“The car won in Macao in 1984, so I'm a big fan of this model,” Ricard Meins told the English magazine Motorsport News. “I still have the photographs I took this weekend in Macao,” said this avid classic competition car collector who, besides driving, supported several riders at the Macao Grand Prix.
In Donington Park, Richard Meins shared the imposing Jaguar XJS, equipped with a 5.3 -liter V12 engine with Jack Tetley, and ended in sixth place, winning in his class. Richard Meins had only guided the car once or twice, but plans to participate in more historic touring car challenge rounds with XJS 1984. “Let's try to put it on track more often now,” Ricard Meins said, who revealed that he was a stake in the Silverstone Festival in August with this very rare and striking copy of the 1980s tourism cars history.
Premiere of an iconic decoration
In the summer of 1984, Tom Walkinshaw accepted the challenge of the Portuguese organization of the Grand Prix to travel later this year to Macau. With the European title in his pocket, the English driver and team boss was accompanied by one of his usual riders, German Hans Heyer. The guide race was a BMW fiefdom and the controversial English wanted to put an end to the Bavarian domain in the race. To this end, it had the precious support of JPS, which was relaunching the brand, decorating its cars with the famous black and gold colors that would later be eternalized in Ayrton Senna's Lotus. At the time, the guide race took place three weeks before 1000 km from Bathurst, another important race on the worldwide calendar of tourist racing, and so TWR made a "two in one."
The 100 -mile race on the streets of Macau would not have much history, such as the cars built in the Kidlington workshops against the competition headed by the two BMW 635i Schnitzer officers, guided by Hans Stuck and Dieter Quester, and painted by rival Marlboro. Tom Walkinshaw ended first and Hans Heyer and m second.
At the end of the race, quoted by the Portuguese newspaper Autosport, Tom Walkinshaw said: “The circuit is fantastic. Tight, but with many curves, climbs and descents, which made the race become difficult. But I like difficult things and, for me, the race was great from beginning to end.
The Jaguar were again invited by the Macao Grand Prix committee to run in 1985, but Tom Walkinshaw had other plans for his cars. Fortunately, thanks to Richard Meins we will continue to see this beautiful car on the tracks.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>MOTOR EMBALISM | Project for new track in Zhuhai emerges</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/30/automobilismo-surge-projecto-para-nova-pista-em-zhuhai/</link><description>With a very black cloud to turn to the future of the Zhuhai International Circuit, there is a potential good news for the great bay of motoring: a project for a new permanent circuit in the Chinese city adjacent to the MSAR.
According to Hong Kong's Ta Kung Pao newspaper, Guangdong's provincial government recently published the document “Measures to promote high quality tourism and accelerate the construction of a strong tourist province”, which proposes, for the first time, the creation of an “industrial circle of culture and tourism of the Great Bay”, offering political support to the integrated development of culture and tourism in the region. With this, the first industrial and tourist complex of motorized sports in the Great Bay may emerge.
The project of the Zhuhai Chaoyue international circuit was recently presented at the Zhuhai Ocean Spring Resort, located in Doumen, not far from the city's airport, with an initial investment of 250 million Renminbis.
According to the first information, the project of this circuit provides for welcoming evidence such as Formula 3 and foster collaborative development between motorized sports sectors, cultural events and exhibition industry. The plan includes the holding of several international tests per year and foresees collaboration with Hong Kong and Macau to connect cities such as Jiangmen and Zhongshan, promoting “Multiple stops” and boosting the innovative development of “Event Economics + Cultural Tourism”.
According to Zhou Jian, China Travel Service (Zhuhai) Executive Director General Ocean Spring Resort Co., the FIA ​​grade certification-will also include a karting track, drift track and an interior space of 2,400 m² for exhibitions and events related to the automobile sector. With more than 50 international events projected annually, the goal is to become a "super IP" that joins running, leisure and tourism under the same concept.
The first phase of the Zhuhai Chaoyue International Circuit project will include international certification professionals, as well as support facilities. This project aims not only to fill “a gap in the high -end motorized sports sector in Zhuhai, but will also promote the modernization of the Great Bay's cultural, sports and tourist industries by conducting international racing and themed cultural events linked to motorsport.”
Uncertainties in the air
Last summer, the company Malay LBS Bina Group BHD announced that it sold its participation in the Zhuhai International Circuit (ZIC) - the first permanent circuit built in the interior of China - by 124.7 million ringits (about 214.15 million patacas). In a statement to Bursa Malaysia Securities BHD, the group reported that their subsidiary, Dragon Hill Corporation Ltd, sold all his participation in Lamdeal Investments Ltd (Lil) to Huafa Urban Operation (HK) Ltd, a well -known real estate operator. Lil Detinha 60 percent of Zhuhai International Circuit Limited (ZICL), circuit operator.
Raised in 1996 in order to receive the first major award from China from Formula 1 - something that never materialized - ZIC was still the initial motor of motoring in the country and a reference in Asian motorsport. Since its opening, it has welcomed several international evidence, such as the FIA ​​GT, A1 GP or the Intercontinental Le Mans Series. In recent years, track administration has chosen to organize its own events, abdicating the most costly international evidence.
Despite having received, in the past, auto competitions from MSAR, ZIC has been losing protagonism in local motorized sport, due to high prices, limited availability and reducing sports activity in favor of the most profitable commercial activities. The future of the circuit remains uncertain: it is only known that lease agreements between resident teams and the circuit have been frozen and are not being renewed. The track approval will also be about to expire, requiring a new certification to continue to receive competitions in the future.
However, on the weekend of June 14 and 15, the still only circuit of Zhuhai will host the third race of the Formula 4 China Championship season.</description><pubDate>2025-05-30 01:53:33</pubDate></item><item><title>ESPORTS | First Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup Decided in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/06/esports-primeira-taca-fia-girls-on-track-esports-decidida-em-macau/</link><description>Next June, for the first time in its history, Macau will host the Extraordinary General Meetings and the Conference of the International Automobile Federation (FIA). This event, which will take place at Galaxy International Convention Center, from 10 to 13 June, will be complemented with extra activity: the first edition of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup”
 
The worldwide body that governs motorized sport has announced this new competition of Sim Racing, which is being organized in partnership with the Advanced Simracing Race Simulation Cockpits and the popular SIM Racing Iracing game, will be directed to 16 or older female elements, regardless of the ESports previous experience. To apply, participants must register on the FIA ​​official website. In addition, it is necessary to have an active account in Iracing to compete.
Online qualifications for the competition, whose finals will be held at MSAR, have already started officially. The first phase consists of participants trying to record the fastest return on Iracing's Attack team. This online qualification phase ends on May 6th. After this first stage, the top 10 classifieds will be invited to participate in the Grande Final, which will take place at the Week of Extraordinary General Meetings and the 2025 FIA Conference, scheduled from June 10 to 13. In Macao, participants will compete in a several day -to -day face -to -face final, where the first champion of the “Fia Girls on Track Esports Cup” will be crowned.
"We know that eSports are the future, but for this discipline to grow and truly develop, we need to encourage more girls and women to get involved," said Ciscal Niroshan Pereira, the current chairman of the FIA ​​eSports committee. “We hope this competition will serve as a catalyst, encouraging aspiring pilot to experience our discipline and consider a career in motorized sport.”
According to FIA, the 10 finalists will also have access to a training program on how to deal with social communication and networking opportunities, gaining a valuable view of the motor sport industry.
Grow on all fronts
This is the first time the fia girls on track initiative has been involved in a eSports competition. His best known project was probably the Fia Girls On Track-Rising Stars program, an initiative aimed at promoting car sports with the female audience aged 13 to 18, and supported young women's pilots between 2020 and 2023. It is recalled that only 1.5 percent of the total sports licenses are women.
Burcu çetinkaya, the president of the FIA ​​Women in Motorsport committee, said that “FIA is committed to double participating in motorized sports and creating more opportunities for women and girls. Electronic sports allow us to reach more vast and younger audiences-especially those with discovering or with limited access to traditional motorized sports. The winner - at the event in Macau. ”
FIA's decision to launch a eSports competition exclusively for women also reinforces the body's bet on the digital landscape. Electronic sports are an increasingly important part of the FIA ​​base development program.
Last year, the Federation added an Appendix of ESPORTS (Appendix E) to the International Sports Code, allowing national sports authorities to regulate and manage national and international competitions. The FIA ​​also supported numerous regional eSports events, received a record number of 117 eSports participants in the Motorsport Games and further encouraged adhesion by offering 12 -month subscriptions from IRACING to member clubs.</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:31:27</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM | Carlos Lemos presents volume II of his book in October</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/05/02/gpm-carlos-lemos-apresenta-volume-ii-do-seu-livro-em-outubro/</link><description>After the success of Volume I, Macaense Carlos Lemos, residing in Toronto since 1974, is prepared to launch, in October, the Macao Grand Prix-Victor H.'s personal collection, 1954-1978, volume II (1967-1978), the second part of a book that intends to honor his father, Victor Hugo Lemos-an enthusiast of the great prize of Macao that Life, collected a vast number of photographs and everything that was related to the car races in Macau since 1954, the date of the first edition of the event.
About the second part of the work, Carlos Lemos explained to HM that it will be “very similar to volume I, but contains more newspaper clippings in English and Chinese of each year, as well as some financial reports of the Grand Prix. It also includes a poster of the Jubilee Year, which I made three limited copies and initialed in Canvas, offering one to the Macau (Apomac) retirees and pensioners association (Apomac) Lusitano, as a sign of thanks for the support provided. ”
Docued with photographs of the time and newspaper articles, there are some of the most emblematic periods of the mashed event, such as the evolution of the guide circuit, the first victim (Arsenio Laurel, 1967), the birth of the Grand Motor Motor Prize and the Guide Race, the arrival of the first factory teams and the first sponsors, the first television broadcast in direct, and the attempted Hong Kong to create his own great prize itself. Also in addition to a new chapter, with "ten pages of another collection of my father, called Motor Racing World, with some copies of 1900, autographed photographs of pilots, leaders and personalities of world motorsport."
After releasing volume I in 2023, the presentation of Volume II is scheduled for October 15 in Macao and on October 17 in the neighboring Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong.
More and bigger
The truth is that sales of the first volume exceeded expectations. "It was really a success," the author acknowledges, because "there are only two dozen copies left, which I kept for myself, for offers and reservations, if someone outside Macau is interested." However, for Carlos Lemos, “the biggest success was to be able to raise more than 41,000 patacas for charity”, intended for the Macau IC2 [I Can Too] institution, which supports people with autism or disability.
For this second volume, with more recent content, the number of copies produced will increase slightly. "The impression of volume I was 500 copies, and I found it a little" tight "to get a satisfactory number to offer friends and certain personalities and entities linked to the Grand Prix. So I had 550 copies this time."
Carlos Lemos further underlines that "Apomac and the Lusitanian Club of Hong Kong promised to support the launch of Volume II, which is very important." The book will have more pages - about one hundred more - and the author confirms: “I've received several reservations!”
Mission (almost) fulfilled
With the publication of the second volume, Carlos Lemos's first major goal will be fulfilled, because "my mission to honor my father is complete with regard to the Macao Grand Prix collection, though not entirely, because my father's biggest dream was to have his name in Guinness World Records."
This is also a curious story, as Victor H. Lemos has applied three times to Guinness World Records, to no avail. "God willing and all goes well, I will try once again, on his behalf, to present a new candidacy for the Guinness Book of Records and perhaps also to Fiva Hall of Fame." Fiva (International Federation of Old Vehicles) is a non -profit world organization dedicated to the protection, preservation and promotion of historical automobile heritage.
“This time, for Guinness World Records, I will submit the application with support documents, such as videos and photographs of the collection and books,” explains the former president of the Macao House in Toronto. "My father wrote only one letter without attaching any document, because in those days there was no ease we have today."
In addition to motoring, Carlos Lemos also reveals that he would like to “publish a book on the collection of matches of matches made in Macao. My father collected labels of matchboxes from around the world - has Portugal, Spain, several countries in Europe, etc. This project depends on the time available and the interest of people”. And we stay here for collections? Maybe not: "I have hundreds too, maybe thousands of old coins - so many that is complicated ... So I won't move (laughs)."</description><pubDate>2025-05-02 06:30:08</pubDate></item></channel></rss>