<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Hoje Macau EN</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/</link><description>Hoje Macau EN RSS</description><item><title>Manila | Hundreds manifest themselves in support of former President Duterte</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/manila-centenas-manifestam-se-em-apoio-ao-ex-presidente-duterte/</link><description>Hundreds of people manifested Saturday in the capital of the Philippines, Manila, to demonstrate support to former President Rodrigo Duterte, accused of crimes against humanity by the bloody anti-drug campaign they led. Duterte was arrested on Tuesday in the Philippines by the local authorities and, hours later, was sent to The Hague in the Netherlands, where he attended Friday before the Judges of the International Criminal Court.
“Bring him back” and “We supported President Rodrigo Duterte” were some of the most repeated phrases during the demonstration, which began with a prayer for the health of the former 79-year-old president.
During the presidency of Duterte, between 2016 and 2022, about 6,000 people were murdered in anti -drug operations and extrajudicial executions, police data. However, the estimates are contested by local non-governmental organizations that claim operations culminated in the deaths of more than 30,000 people.
The former president was arrested following a warrant captured from the International Criminal Court. The court considers Duterte responsible for humanity crimes and says there are “reasonable reasons” to believe that he led a death squad and used his power to carry out extrajudicial executions.
The Court's investigation into extrajudicial executions began in 2018 and, by 2021, the authorities and security forces were associated with the crimes committed, although Duterte removed the country from the organization in 2019 in an attempt not to be implied.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:01:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomacy | Paulo Rangel confirms trip to Beijing and Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/diplomacia-paulo-rangel-confirma-viagem-a-pequim-e-macau/</link><description>Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel will move to Macao and China at the end of the month, said to Lusa official source, and the trip to be defined.
Earlier this month, TDM indicated the presence of the Portuguese Executive's number two in Macao and China, and was expected to participate in the Boao Forum, which will take place between 25 and 28 March, in Hainan Province, and the holding of contacts with Chinese authorities, namely Chinese homologous, Wang Yi. Lusa, a source of Paulo Rangel's office, confirmed the trip at the end of the month, indicating that the travel program is not yet closed.
Macau will receive later this year the celebrations of June 10, which start in lakes, according to the presidency of the Republic, in February, in a note published on its website. “The President of the Republic designated the city of Lagos as headquarters of the celebrations, in 2025, of Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities, extending the celebrations to the Portuguese community in Macao”, reads in the text dated February 7.
According to the same note, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa decided to constitute the organization of the celebrations “a commission chaired by Dr. Lídia Jorge, writer, and who is part of the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, the Secretary General of the Presidency of the Republic and the head of the State Protocol”.
In December last year, the head of state had already admitted that his last June 10th of his term-which ends on March 9 next year-to be celebrated with more distant Portuguese emigrant communities such as Asia Pacific, Australia, Macao or Goa.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:46:07</pubDate></item><item><title>About 95% of the kidney patients receive free dialysis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/cerca-de-95-dos-doentes-renais-recebem-dialise-gratuita/</link><description>From the universe of 990 patients who received dialysis treatments in Macao in 2023, "about 95 percent of patients are people who enjoy free health care or who are exempt from paying dialysis expenses due to medical care," said the director of health services (SS), alvis lo, in response to Ron Lam written interpellation.
Alvis Lo recalls that dialysis medical treatments are not free, but there is a medical assistance mechanism for patients with lower financial possessions, which requires the assets assessment of the household and income.
According to data advanced by the SS director, of the 990 patients who received dialysis treatment, only about 50 had to pay the costs.
In written interplies, Ron Lam indicated that the hemodialysis rate charged to Macao residents at the Conde de S. Januario hospital center is 700 patacas for each consultation and in private hospital reaches 2 or 3 thousand patacas. Values ​​that, given that hemodialysis is done three times a week, “is a great economic pressure” for patients and their families.
In addition, the deputy cited complaints of residents regarding the increase in rigor in the consideration of requests for exemption from treatment costs in recent years, although the law has not been amended. Ron Lam claims to have received requests for support from residents who did not receive medical assistance due to the “per capita” income and the patient's household heritage is higher than the economic deficiency criteria defined by the Institute of Social Action. The government did not respond to this claim of tightness of rigor in the consideration of requests for exemption.

Inner harvest
Regarding the possibility of kidney transplantation, Alvis Lo states that patients interested in kidney transplantation, after examinations, can be "sent to the medical units in the interior of China through the overseas medical services regime."
The intervention presupposes the registration of the state system of distribution and sharing of human organs and in a waiting list for transplants. In this respect, Deputy Ron Lam had stressed that those who submit to transplantation in the interior of China must “prepare to pay hundreds of thousands of patacas”, a situation that was not addressed by Alvis Lo.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:11:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal highlights the importance of celebrating Camilo Castelo Branco</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/portugal-destaca-importancia-de-celebrar-camilo-castelo-branco/</link><description>The Minister of Culture in Portugal stressed, on Friday, the importance of honoring writer Camilo Castelo Branco, to days of her bicentenary, and stressed the need to preserve and disseminate the author's work across the country.
“It is essential to honor Camilo Castelo Branco as a historical figure, honor his legacy, which we have to study, preserve and disseminate. And, fundamentally, to be all over the territory. In other words, acting across the country means that the rulers recognize the importance of local singularities, but always present that these are figures […] that may be from Seide, but that may be from the whole country and the world, ”said the Minister of Culture, Dalila Rodrigues, to the departure of the opening ceremony of the International Congress“ Camilo Castelo Branco, 200 years later ”, at the Camilian Study Center Seide, in the municipality of Vila Nova de Famalicão.
Asked about the relevance of the author of "love of perdition" today, the ruler stressed that "the whole work of Camilo Castelo Branco is of great current," adding that what surprises her most in Camilo "is the emotional dimension that puts in her writing."
“Creio que a maioria dos portugueses leu Camilo Castelo Branco no contexto escolar e espero que o possam ler – quem não teve essa oportunidade – no âmbito das bibliotecas públicas cuja dinamização e transformação em unidades culturais de território estão a ser objecto das políticas culturais deste Governo”, afirmou Dalila Rodrigues, que lembrou que as bibliotecas vão “dinamizar um conjunto de programas que vão resultar de parcerias entre os municípios e o Ministério da Culture ”.
The minister also left a compliment to the municipality of Famalicão, for the work of preservation and dissemination of the work of Camilo Castelo Branco.
Congress and Exhibition
The international congress that began on Friday, which ended yesterday, the day of the Bicentennial of Camilo Castelo Branco (1825-1890), gathered at the place where the writer lived much of his life dozens of national and international experts in his work.
"Camilo is as valuable as a Machado de Assis, a Dante, a Shakespeare," this week told Lusa the director of the Camilian Study Center, Sérgio Guimarães de Sousa, adding that "in one way or another", even today the Portuguese are descendants of the writing of Camilo Castelo Branco and his "universe of election", referring to the northern region.
Until August 31, at the Study Center, it is possible to visit the exhibition “Jorge. Drawings of my son ”, consisting of drawings from the collection of the son of Camilo Castelo Branco and Ana Plácido, who had the edition of a catalog to accompany. Throughout the year, initiatives and literary editions will multiply to mark the 200th anniversary of the writer's birth.
Camilo Castelo Branco was born on March 16, 1825 at Rua da Rosa, in Lisbon, and lost his mother at 2 and his father at 10, having gone to live with an aunt to Vila Real. Throughout the extensive journalistic and literary career, he signed works that would become larger books of Portuguese literature, from “Love of Perdition” to “Twelve Happy Weddings”, among many others.
A man of various interests, professional and loving, arrested in the Porto's relationship chain, along with Ana Plácido, accused of adultery, given the existence of Placido's marriage to merchant Manuel Pinheiro Alves. Both were acquitted.
One of the two literary “giants” of the Portuguese nineteenth century, along with Eça de Queirós, in the opinion of Sérgio Guimarães de Sousa, Camilo Castelo Branco, already blind due to the syphilis he suffered, committed suicide on June 1, 1890.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:07:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire | Two fires take two women to the hospital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/fogo-dois-incendios-levam-duas-mulheres-ao-hospital/</link><description>Yesterday's fires at Hoi Fu building and the Jardim Iat Lai building rose to six the number of fireworks in dwellings within one month. Women taken to the hospital were considered in a stable situation
 
Two women were transported yesterday to the hospital, following a fire that launched in the Hoi Fu building. This was one of yesterday's two fires in housing buildings that raised to six the number of occurrences within one month.
According to information from the Fire Department, quoted by the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the origin of the flames will have been a short circuit in an air conditioner. None of the occupants of the house suffered serious injuries, but two women, 66 and 32, had to be transported to the hospital due to the inhalation of fumes.
In addition to the two wounded women, another 60 residents had to abandon the housing temporarily, having returned the house later. The fire, which took place on the 29th floor, caused large flames that were eventually extinguished by the firefighters.
After the intervention, the firefighters indicated that the whole apartment had smoke marks, although some divisions were affected more slightly.
Bend
In addition to the case in the Hoi Fu building, the Fire Department had to go into action around 9am at Toi San. According to the information available, he launched a fire in the Jardim Iat Lai building that made about 30 people had to temporarily abandon the dwellings.
Unlike the first occurrence of the morning, there was no need to transport any of the inhabitants of the building to the hospital, and the flames were extinguished by one of the administrators of the building. In this case, it is suspected of set fire, since traces of burnt papers were found on the seventh floor, near the place where the flames will have triggered.
In a reaction to the Hoi Fu building, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) indicated that it followed the first case with great attention and sent aid teams to the site. The occupants of the most affected apartment needed shelter. In addition, no more requests for assistance were registered.
In the case of Jardim IAT LAI building, IAS indicated that it has not received any request for help, although it is available to respond to any request.
In recent times, the territory has crossed a spot of fire in housing buildings, which has led some deputies, such as Lo Choi In and Si Ka Lon, to ask the authorities to adopt new security measures.
Lo Choi In, a deputy linked to the community of Jiangmen, was concerned about the fact that in the fire of the Lake building the alarm did not work. In turn, Si Ka Lon appealed to the government to consider the hypothesis of funding the use of natural gas by supporting the installation in local buildings of distribution pipes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:51:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club | Aborted plan to send 100 cats to zhuhai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/jockey-club-abortado-plano-para-enviar-100-gatos-para-zhuhai/</link><description>Macau Jockey Club intended to send 100 cats to Zhuhai, but aborted the plan after being pressured by citizens and animal protection associations
 
Macau Jockey Club and the Municipal Institute for Affairs (AMI) have canceled a plan to send about 100 cats to Zhuhai to a destination that the authorities did not want to reveal.
The controversy snapped at the end of Thursday, when the information began to circulate that about 100 cats, raised at Macau Jockey Club, would be sent to Zhuhai the next afternoon. However, the lack of guarantees on animal safety has led several citizens and animal protection associations to mobilize online, but also through Hong Kong communication agencies, to prevent the outcome that was tragic for the animals.
At the same time, accusations also began to emerge that Macau Jockey Club had promoted a "facade" adoption campaign with little promotion, only for two days, which only resulted in four adoptions. In addition, the institution will have refused that some citizens and animal protection associations would be with various cats, justifying that there would be no more animals for adoption.
Given the growing public criticism, on Friday morning, AMI issued a statement to defend Macau Jockey Club and ensuring that Zhuhai was able to receive the animals. However, AMI never identified where the cats would be taken. "Given the welfare of the animals, AMI is pleased with the sterilization of cats by Macau Jockey Club and with the measures taken," he was nominated. “This institute recently proceeded to the health inspection of these cats, including the introduction of microchips, anti-rabies vaccination and clinical examination. AMI will issue the necessary sanitary documents for the border passage of exported cats, in strict compliance with national provisions, providing support in the border passage, ”he was added.
The institute led by Chao Wai Ieng also defended the Jockey Club by ensuring that he had resorted to "several channels for some cats to be adopted by their workers and the public."
After all there was another
With the controversy to gain traction not only in Macau, but also in Hong Kong, Mary Jean Reimer, actress, lawyer and activist for the rights of Hong Kong animals, has been available to adopt all animals.
Reimer, who is married to Sean Hotung, from the famous Hotung family, also presented a plan to take cats to a terrain in the countryside, where the safety of animals guaranteed.
By this time, also Zoe Tang, president of Anima, revealed in statements to the All About Macau portal that was trying to contact the Jockey Club and owner and deputy Angela Leong to prevent the outcome, though to no avail. The anima was also receptive to stay with the animals until it could carry out more adoption campaigns.
In various online animal defense groups of Macao, Angela Leong was also the target of various criticisms, with accusations that she had not learned anything about how she had dealt with the 500 Galids in the canhy, which ended up abandoned on the spot, with local associations, as they would promote international adoption campaigns.
Final change
As a result of controversy and displeasure at the attitude of the authorities, around 5:30 pm, Macau Jockey Club announced that it has canceled the animals to Zhuhai, with about 60 felines to be sent to other associations.
In a statement, the company also underlined “respecting and valuing the concerns and opinions of animal protection groups” and that would promote an adoption campaign with Anima. Macau Jockey Club also highlighted fulfilling “their social responsibilities”.
In addition, a new adoption campaign was organized, in partnership with Anima, which took place yesterday and which made about 30 cats for adoption. In case they are not all adopted, the campaign continues next weekend.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:49:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Budget | Kevin Ho defends subsidies only for those who need the most</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/orcamento-kevin-ho-defende-subsidios-so-para-quem-mais-precisa/</link><description>At a time when the presentation of the government lines are expected, the first of the new government, Kevin Ho appeals to the accuracy in the distribution of social support
 
Macao deputy at the National Popular Assembly and businessman Kevin Ho argues that the government must be cautious with the budget of the MSAR, and make a more accurate distribution of social support. The message was left through statements made to TDM.
“With regard to social assistance beneficiaries, the government has to be more accurate in its distribution. Those who have the most needs should get more, ”said the businessman.
In recent times, several representatives of different associations have defended a new distribution of supports, although officially the budget of the MSAR is not deficient. In the first month of the year, the budget had a surplus of 3.68 billion patacas, less 1.74 billion patacas than in the first month of last year.
"Whether it is from previous, cash, or the various preferred policies for residents, such as the distribution of dividends of MSAR revenues […] those who have the greatest needs should receive more support," said the businessman.
One of the supports that has been targeted by some deputies and associations is the pecuniary reimbursement program, also known as the “pecuniary check”, from 10,000 patacas to permanent residents and 6,000 patacas for non-permanent residents. Although not targeted by Kevin Ho, there were several local political voices that requested the elimination of support for residents who do not live at least half of the year in the MSAR.
Confidence in the government
The public broadcaster also listened to Lao Chi Long, local businessman and member of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), who, despite recognizing the limitations in the current state of the economy, showed confidence in Sam Hou Fai executive to get around the situation.
"Although the economy may not perform as good as expected, I am confident that the MSAR government has the ability to change this situation and implement more policies to boost positive economic development," said Lao, quoted by Macau channel.
In recent times, more and more requests to support small and medium -sized companies have not benefited from the increase in the number of interior tourists.
Also different representatives of the real estate market, such as former deputy Ung Choi Kun, have advocated policies to support entrepreneurs, builders and tax reduction, to promote more purchases and sales of houses and commercial spaces.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:47:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Pass | CAEAL ATTENTION TO REQUESTS IN CHILLS</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/macau-pass-caeal-atenta-a-solicitacoes-em-trocas/</link><description>The Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly did not receive a “formal complaint” about the case of the elderly who was invited to sign a list for the elections while exchanging the Macau Pass card. Still, the commission says it is concerned and that it provides “special attention” to the situation
 
Even without any formal complaint, the Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) ensures that it will be aware of the process of exchanging macau pass to the elderly, as part of the consumer consumption incentive program.
"Even though it has not yet received a formal complaint about the situation, Caeal will be in contact with the direction of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) and closely monitor the situation and all news about legislative elections to take place this year," Caeal said in response to questions posed by HM.
It is recalled that last Monday, a resident told the Macau Forum Macau program microphones of Radio Macau, that his grandmother would have been invited to signing a proposal for the candidacy for legislative elections when exchanging the Macau Pass card to the elderly to participate in the major consumption award. About this episode, the body that organizes and supervises legislative elections, led by magistrate Seng Ioi Man, ensures that he is following the case.
“The comments fabrics by the Macau radio listener about changing the Macau Pass card to the elderly, Caeal pays special attention, and to find out the situation, immediately came into contact with DSEDT, which is responsible for coordinating the replacement work of that card with social service institutions and collaborating civic associations.”
Dry the competition
Last week, DSEDT told HM to have conducted training sessions, issued guidelines for civic associations that are collaborating with the government in the exchange of macau pass cards to the elderly and reminded employees that they should limit their service to card replacement. "DSEDT will continue to oversee all service posts, and if you check the guidelines in any of these, you will immediately cease the card replacement service provided by the service station involved," added the entity led by Yau Yun Wah to HM.
HM sought to know the consequences for cases in which civic associations with both Caeal and DSEDT. In addition to the closure of the card exchange posts, it was not referred to whether there would be any legal consequences, or infringement of the laws that regulate the elections.
Former deputy Au Kam San presented an explanation for the “nervousness” of the main traditional associations to resort to all expedients to collect as much as possible, even when they provide public services, such as the exchange of macau pass to the elderly.
“This is a tactic, because in the same election, any voter can only sign a list once (…), otherwise they are committing a crime. The more signatures a list can, the more space removes other lists. If an association gather 50,000 signatures, even if only 500 and the remaining 49,500 are lying in the trash, these voters will not be able to sign other lists, ”Au Kam San said in a Facebook post.
The former deputy points out that despite not being punished with arrest who signs more than a proposal of candidacy, in addition to the payment of a fine, the voter may have a criminal record.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:41:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul French, writer: Looking for Wallis Simpson in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/paul-french-escritor-a-procura-de-wallis-simpson-na-china/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival, which starts on Friday, will feature the presence of writer Paul French, who launched last year a new biographical book, "Her Lotus Year", which describes Wallis Simpson's experience in China before being a Duchess of Windsor. The British author will also talk about “Destination Macau”, a nostalgic and almost cinematic account of the city's history
 
How did you come to the history of Wallis Simpson's life experience in China?
I lived in Shanghai for many years and many visitors knew that Wallis Simpson had spent time in the city. Rumors ran on what he had done, and visitors always wanted to know if the rumors were true, such as the idea that she had learned esoteric sexual techniques or had posed naked for photographs. It was also said that he had belonged to a group of opium smuggling, or a group of bets that combined horses races. For me, as an author and expert in foreign experiences in Shanghai in the first half of the twentieth century, none of this made sense. So I thought this was the ideal time to really find out what Wallis had done in China. The fact that she was in the country in 1924 and 1925, two of the most fascinating years in the history of modern China, helped a lot.
How do you describe the life of the duchess in the country during that specific political period?
China was in total chaos when she was there, because Puyi, the last emperor, had been expelled from the forbidden city and occurred the biggest strikes ever in Hong Kong history. In addition, political fractions were recorded in Guangzhou, warlords of war in Shanghai and northern China. These were also the most wet years that there is a record in China, with crop production breaks and the occurrence of tiphoid and cholera fever outbreaks. He fired the number of bandits and pirates. Then, in March 1925, Sun Yat-Sen, leader of the Republican Revolution of 1911, died without leaving an obvious successor. Wallis came across all this, as he was retained on the island of Shamian, Guangzhou, while the city struggled; In Shanghai, he saw corpses to be brought to the city from the battles of the warlords; He saw victims of typhus and anger in Tianjin; and troops of the warlords threatening Beijing. But he was also largely in a foreign protective bubble that protected her from foreign soldiers and her white skin. He could delight in China's culture and aesthetics, while around him the whole country threatened to explode.
How was the personality of Wallis Simpson, a controversial figure in the context of the marriage to the Duke of Windsor?
It is very important not to confuse Wallis of 1924 with the later Wallis, from the long years of exile and controversy as Duchess of Windsor. In 1924 Wallis was only 28 years old, fleeing from a physically abusive husband (her first husband, Win Spencer, an American Navy commander) and was not yet particularly sophisticated or cosmopolitan. These were characteristics that would learn in China, mingling in the “colonies” [concessions] international foreign and bohemiums of Shanghai and Beijing. In fact, it was in Beijing that it first mixed with ambassadors, high -level Chinese politicians, high -ranking military officers and a stretch, and from them learned everything from playing Bridge and enjoying Jade to how to behave in high society. Obviously, this was useful a decade later when he met the Prince of Wales in England. Admittedly, the posterior Wallis, the Duchess, is a more difficult figure to like. Perhaps she and the Duke have made some bad political decisions and made some friendships, perhaps Wallis became a little bitter for not being accepted by the British royal family. But the truth is that in 1924 she was young, free of a bad husband and was in one of the most fascinating countries in the world.
What can readers perceive this figure and about China of that time, with "Her Lotus Year"?
China in 1925 was on the brink of potential explosion, as the whole country could have fallen into total chaos, dividing into the size of Portugal managed by warlords with private armies, or a resurgent Qing Dynasty supported by Japan in the North [China], the South and, of course, the foreign powers-England, America, France and Japan-who had Chinese lands like colonies. Ultimately, this did not happen, but no one knew this in 1925. Wallis herself oscillated between feeling incredibly comfortable and happy in what was her "year of lotus," as he described him, quoting Homer's Sopoifers who never want to return home; and feel terrified of the violence of the warlords or those who were against foreigners.
What are the biggest challenges, as a writer, in the process of researching the history of Wallis?
Wallis probably became the most photographed and spoken woman in history, more than Marilyn Monroe, more than Queen Isabel II. But in 1924 she was not famous at all. So it left a very difficult trail to follow. He wrote his memories, but these were "disinfected." A big problem was also the rumors that the British government and secret services circulated in 1936 in an attempt to destroy the idea of ​​a marriage between King Eduardo VIII and Wallis. The attempt failed because he abdicated the throne and they married, but these sexual rumors and insinuations, many of them racist and misogynists, have remained to this day, and they continue to be regularly recycled in the British and American Tabloid Press. I found the real Wallis a much more friendly character than I expected, and I hope readers will feel that too.
Is invited to another edition of Rota das Letras. How do you feel for being part of the festival?
I love to be part of the Macao Literary Festival. Although he had spoken before in Macao, namely in the Portuguese bookstore and other places, he had never participated in the festival. I look forward to being able to talk about Wallis Simpson and also about my new collection of rehearsals about Macau, entitled "Destination Macau". Some stories of Macao that have pleased me over the years, some of them presented with a more English look, as it were, may be interested and will be new to the local public.
Book | “Destination Macau”, the city between “The Imaginary and the Real”
Paul French has just launched the third volume of the “Destination” collection, which had editions of Shanghai or Beijing, and is now dedicated to telling stories of the ancient macao, a “place as imaginary as real”, as described the synopsis of the work. The work of the British author presents "The Macao by artists George Chinnery and George Smirnoff, the writers Deolinda da Conceição and Maurice Dekobra, to the fantasies of" Pulp Fiction "and febrile dreams of Josef Von Sternberg and Jean Delannoy."
There is still no shortage of Paul French, stories around historical figures such as Pedro José Lobo and Ian Fleming, author and creator of James Bond. Macao of the time of World War II, those who “came to Macao in search of gold, and those who sought war refuge” is described, not forgetting “the combatants looking for a secret passage through the 'neutral' macao”.
Paul French unveil mysteries or tells forgotten stories to many, such as the idea that Japan had tried to buy Macau in 1934 or the person who sailed with the Macau pirates queen, Lai Choi San. There are, in all, 18 stories “true of fascinating people who lived or visited Macau in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Manila | Hundreds manifest themselves in support of former President Duterte</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/manila-centenas-manifestam-se-em-apoio-ao-ex-presidente-duterte/</link><description>Hundreds of people manifested Saturday in the capital of the Philippines, Manila, to demonstrate support to former President Rodrigo Duterte, accused of crimes against humanity by the bloody anti-drug campaign they led. Duterte was arrested on Tuesday in the Philippines by the local authorities and, hours later, was sent to The Hague in the Netherlands, where he attended Friday before the Judges of the International Criminal Court.
“Bring him back” and “We supported President Rodrigo Duterte” were some of the most repeated phrases during the demonstration, which began with a prayer for the health of the former 79-year-old president.
During the presidency of Duterte, between 2016 and 2022, about 6,000 people were murdered in anti -drug operations and extrajudicial executions, police data. However, the estimates are contested by local non-governmental organizations that claim operations culminated in the deaths of more than 30,000 people.
The former president was arrested following a warrant captured from the International Criminal Court. The court considers Duterte responsible for humanity crimes and says there are “reasonable reasons” to believe that he led a death squad and used his power to carry out extrajudicial executions.
The Court's investigation into extrajudicial executions began in 2018 and, by 2021, the authorities and security forces were associated with the crimes committed, although Duterte removed the country from the organization in 2019 in an attempt not to be implied.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:01:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomacy | Paulo Rangel confirms trip to Beijing and Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/diplomacia-paulo-rangel-confirma-viagem-a-pequim-e-macau/</link><description>Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel will move to Macao and China at the end of the month, said to Lusa official source, and the trip to be defined.
Earlier this month, TDM indicated the presence of the Portuguese Executive's number two in Macao and China, and was expected to participate in the Boao Forum, which will take place between 25 and 28 March, in Hainan Province, and the holding of contacts with Chinese authorities, namely Chinese homologous, Wang Yi. Lusa, a source of Paulo Rangel's office, confirmed the trip at the end of the month, indicating that the travel program is not yet closed.
Macau will receive later this year the celebrations of June 10, which start in lakes, according to the presidency of the Republic, in February, in a note published on its website. “The President of the Republic designated the city of Lagos as headquarters of the celebrations, in 2025, of Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities, extending the celebrations to the Portuguese community in Macao”, reads in the text dated February 7.
According to the same note, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa decided to constitute the organization of the celebrations “a commission chaired by Dr. Lídia Jorge, writer, and who is part of the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, the Secretary General of the Presidency of the Republic and the head of the State Protocol”.
In December last year, the head of state had already admitted that his last June 10th of his term-which ends on March 9 next year-to be celebrated with more distant Portuguese emigrant communities such as Asia Pacific, Australia, Macao or Goa.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:46:07</pubDate></item><item><title>About 95% of the kidney patients receive free dialysis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/cerca-de-95-dos-doentes-renais-recebem-dialise-gratuita/</link><description>From the universe of 990 patients who received dialysis treatments in Macao in 2023, "about 95 percent of patients are people who enjoy free health care or who are exempt from paying dialysis expenses due to medical care," said the director of health services (SS), alvis lo, in response to Ron Lam written interpellation.
Alvis Lo recalls that dialysis medical treatments are not free, but there is a medical assistance mechanism for patients with lower financial possessions, which requires the assets assessment of the household and income.
According to data advanced by the SS director, of the 990 patients who received dialysis treatment, only about 50 had to pay the costs.
In written interplies, Ron Lam indicated that the hemodialysis rate charged to Macao residents at the Conde de S. Januario hospital center is 700 patacas for each consultation and in private hospital reaches 2 or 3 thousand patacas. Values ​​that, given that hemodialysis is done three times a week, “is a great economic pressure” for patients and their families.
In addition, the deputy cited complaints of residents regarding the increase in rigor in the consideration of requests for exemption from treatment costs in recent years, although the law has not been amended. Ron Lam claims to have received requests for support from residents who did not receive medical assistance due to the “per capita” income and the patient's household heritage is higher than the economic deficiency criteria defined by the Institute of Social Action. The government did not respond to this claim of tightness of rigor in the consideration of requests for exemption.

Inner harvest
Regarding the possibility of kidney transplantation, Alvis Lo states that patients interested in kidney transplantation, after examinations, can be "sent to the medical units in the interior of China through the overseas medical services regime."
The intervention presupposes the registration of the state system of distribution and sharing of human organs and in a waiting list for transplants. In this respect, Deputy Ron Lam had stressed that those who submit to transplantation in the interior of China must “prepare to pay hundreds of thousands of patacas”, a situation that was not addressed by Alvis Lo.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:11:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal highlights the importance of celebrating Camilo Castelo Branco</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/portugal-destaca-importancia-de-celebrar-camilo-castelo-branco/</link><description>The Minister of Culture in Portugal stressed, on Friday, the importance of honoring writer Camilo Castelo Branco, to days of her bicentenary, and stressed the need to preserve and disseminate the author's work across the country.
“It is essential to honor Camilo Castelo Branco as a historical figure, honor his legacy, which we have to study, preserve and disseminate. And, fundamentally, to be all over the territory. In other words, acting across the country means that the rulers recognize the importance of local singularities, but always present that these are figures […] that may be from Seide, but that may be from the whole country and the world, ”said the Minister of Culture, Dalila Rodrigues, to the departure of the opening ceremony of the International Congress“ Camilo Castelo Branco, 200 years later ”, at the Camilian Study Center Seide, in the municipality of Vila Nova de Famalicão.
Asked about the relevance of the author of "love of perdition" today, the ruler stressed that "the whole work of Camilo Castelo Branco is of great current," adding that what surprises her most in Camilo "is the emotional dimension that puts in her writing."
“Creio que a maioria dos portugueses leu Camilo Castelo Branco no contexto escolar e espero que o possam ler – quem não teve essa oportunidade – no âmbito das bibliotecas públicas cuja dinamização e transformação em unidades culturais de território estão a ser objecto das políticas culturais deste Governo”, afirmou Dalila Rodrigues, que lembrou que as bibliotecas vão “dinamizar um conjunto de programas que vão resultar de parcerias entre os municípios e o Ministério da Culture ”.
The minister also left a compliment to the municipality of Famalicão, for the work of preservation and dissemination of the work of Camilo Castelo Branco.
Congress and Exhibition
The international congress that began on Friday, which ended yesterday, the day of the Bicentennial of Camilo Castelo Branco (1825-1890), gathered at the place where the writer lived much of his life dozens of national and international experts in his work.
"Camilo is as valuable as a Machado de Assis, a Dante, a Shakespeare," this week told Lusa the director of the Camilian Study Center, Sérgio Guimarães de Sousa, adding that "in one way or another", even today the Portuguese are descendants of the writing of Camilo Castelo Branco and his "universe of election", referring to the northern region.
Until August 31, at the Study Center, it is possible to visit the exhibition “Jorge. Drawings of my son ”, consisting of drawings from the collection of the son of Camilo Castelo Branco and Ana Plácido, who had the edition of a catalog to accompany. Throughout the year, initiatives and literary editions will multiply to mark the 200th anniversary of the writer's birth.
Camilo Castelo Branco was born on March 16, 1825 at Rua da Rosa, in Lisbon, and lost his mother at 2 and his father at 10, having gone to live with an aunt to Vila Real. Throughout the extensive journalistic and literary career, he signed works that would become larger books of Portuguese literature, from “Love of Perdition” to “Twelve Happy Weddings”, among many others.
A man of various interests, professional and loving, arrested in the Porto's relationship chain, along with Ana Plácido, accused of adultery, given the existence of Placido's marriage to merchant Manuel Pinheiro Alves. Both were acquitted.
One of the two literary “giants” of the Portuguese nineteenth century, along with Eça de Queirós, in the opinion of Sérgio Guimarães de Sousa, Camilo Castelo Branco, already blind due to the syphilis he suffered, committed suicide on June 1, 1890.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:07:31</pubDate></item><item><title>CCCM | “Multissecular China seen through shapes and colors” to see until April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/cccm-a-china-multissecular-vista-atraves-de-formas-e-cores-para-ver-ate-abril/</link><description>Former Ambassador in China, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus launched himself in the painting and again presented his works in the one that is his second exhibition. “Multissecular China seen through shapes and colors” can be seen at the Macao scientific and cultural center until April 11
 
After a long career dedicated to diplomacy, as ambassador, with passages in Beijing and Pyongyang, but also Kinshasa or Brazzavile, among others, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus is now a man dedicated to books and the arts. Its artistic vein has been expressed through painting, whose works can now be seen in the latest patent exposure at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM). "China Multissecular viewed through shapes and colors" was inaugurated last Friday, in Lisbon and, at HM, the former ambassador explains that most of the paintings "are inspired by Chinese characters, ancient Chinese poetry and even a Poetry of Mao", written in 1925, which is titled "Alone I Stand In the Autumn Cold".
There are more than 20 paintings, one of them “on the evolution of the Sheng Castro - Life”, or another “based on a poetry of Niu Xi Ji, the poet of the sec. X E.C. ”. There are also paintings, such as number 14, "based on phrases from Jing's Dao, Lao Zì, inspired by a phrase" The Spirit of the Valley is immortal, is called the subtle or the deep vagina. "
Asked about China's perceptions, or Chinese culture itself, that the public may have with this show, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus assumes not being able to respond concretely. "Some people who know a little about the millennial Chinese culture may perhaps perceive, through painting, fundamental aspects of the two basic strains of Chinese culture, the Confucian and Lao Zi," he said.
Traveling
The former ambassador confessed to having traveled a lot and lived in many countries because of his diplomatic work, but the passage to China marked him a lot. “As a diplomat and ambassador I went through many European countries from Asia and America, but perhaps none marked me as much as China. I traveled many regions, very diverse, from that huge country. I tried to know its population and its various cultures. I fell in love in such a way that I studied and continue to study philosophical thinking and its remarkable poetic tradition. ”
Patent exposure at CCCM is the first of the person in charge in Portugal, but the second in the painter's quality, as it has already exposed in Beijing. "The fact that he was an ambassador in China is part of this exhibition," he said.
Currently, jubilated ambassador, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus was also linked to his teaching career at the Higher Institute of Social and Political Sciences of the University of Lisbon, as well as other Portuguese universities. It has been dedicated to studies and publications in the field of Asia, focusing on China, Chinese foreign policy, Africa and international relations.
One of the books he wrote about China was "The Garden in Chinese Mythical Thought," in 2002 or "China faces." In a more self-biographical vein, he edited, in 2007, “the other side of diplomacy-1960 to 2007”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:02:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Bangkok | Self -established collapse under construction causes five dead</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/banguecoque-derrocada-de-autoestrada-em-construcao-causa-cinco-mortos/</link><description>At least five people died, two remaining missing and 27 were injured on Saturday after the collapse of a high freeway, under construction south of Bangcoque, the authorities said.
The incident occurred in the district of Chom Thong, around 2:00, when the iron and concrete structure collapsed, at a time when a group of more than 20 workers was in the area.
Photographs published on social networks by the Municipal Council of Bangcoque and the Department of Public Relations of Samut Sakhon province, where the project is being carried out, show a pile of rubble due to the fall of beams and pillars.
The Department of Prevention and Mitigation of Thai disasters observed in a statement that this is the eighth accident resulting from the construction of this infrastructure, including the fall of a horizontal crane in November, which made six dead.
In June 2023, two people died and several were injured when a construction bridge collapsed over several cars that passed, in another accident related to the same project, which started in 2022.
Transport Minister Suriya Jungrunggreangkit ordered an investigation into Saturday's incident to avoid further deaths. Construction accidents are common in Thailand due to the poor application of safety standards and the use of unqualified personnel.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:59:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Work vacancies at Shake Shack and Barbie Love</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/dsal-vagas-de-trabalho-no-shake-shack-e-barbie-love/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) will organize three sessions of jobs, providing a total of 224 vacancies, on March 20, 21 and 24, to restoration sectors, retail trade and supermarkets, building administration and cleaning.
According to a statement released yesterday by DSAL, registrations for the three sessions open today and interested parties can apply on the Dsal website until noon of 19 March.
The first session is scheduled for the morning of March 20, with the offer of 80 vacancies to work at Shake Shack restaurants and Yum Cha Success, on Rua da Cantão, for the duties of store head, cook, cook assistant and restoration employee. On the afternoon of the same day, 14 vacancies will be available for store chief, seller and warehouse employee at two sports clothing stores.
On the morning of the next day, it will be the turn of the building administration and cleaning sectors, with 83 vacancies for customer service supervisor, building facilities maintenance officer, doorman, street sweeper and garbage collection worker.
On the morning of March 24, 47 vacancies will be offered to work at the “Barbie Love” supermarkets and the “San Fa Seng Supermarket” for the functions of cashier, shelves, warehouse employee, fruit and vegetables and meat cutter. The three sessions will take place at the Faom building, at Ribeira do Patane Street No. 2-6.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:22:28</pubDate></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Chen Jiru (1558-1639), the painter who wanted to be free from the ties of court staff to devote himself to knowing everything around him and pronounce independently, was therefore called the "Great Chancellor of the Mountains", the space where there are always new perspectives for the look and there are no cities limits.
Referring to the works that circulated among the collectors and lovers of his friend's paintings, the influential thinker of Huating (current Songjiang, Shanghai) Dong Qichang (1555-1636) had said without fate that "less than one in ten" of the paintings that were attributed to him would effectively works of his brush.
This will not be admired given the multiplicity of tasks required by a man of culture at the end of the Ming Dynasty and which, in his case, included the demonstration of his theories in caligraffes and paintings.
The names of some painters are known, which helped him in this function from the knowledge of the history of painting, studied in his valuable collection, such as his friend Zhao Zuo (C.1570- After 1630) or Shen Shichong (Act.C.1602-41).
The latter also originally from Huating, he would recreate an album of 1625, twelve perspectives from the Lejiao Yuan Private Garden, "Pleasures of the suburbs" of the distinguished painter Wang Shimin (1592-1680), where he has realized the eloquence of certain figures placed in favorable places.
The creation of gardens, Zaoyuan, a privileged space for the exercise of subjectivity, one of the activities to which the intellectuals were dedicated, had the prestige associated with the Zaowu or Zaohua expressions, the "creator of strength" or "transformation" used in Zhuangzi, with intrinsic affinities to the painter's or man of letters.
As Qi Baojia wrote (1602-1645) creating a garden is like “the painting of a great artist: not a single uninspirated brushstroke is allowed; just as a careful author writing: not a distant word is authorized.
Shen Shichong would make it in its own name, several paintings affirming its relationship with free space for walking, in a style that takes advantage of the abstract forms of Dong Qichang mountains with the nebula atmosphere and the noted spatial recession between professional painters.
Long horizontal rollers, exemplary of these characteristics are the landscape paintings of the four stations (Shangao Shuifang, High Mountains, Long Rivers, Ink and Paper Color, 28.6 x 761 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts of Boston) or the one that is considered his masterpiece, Tianxia Diyi, "first under the sky". Today known as mountain retreat (ink and color on paper, 33 x 1527 cm, for sale at Christies) in it are visible you are visible, bridges over the rivers, pines and walkers fearless in the fimbrias of the mountains in a figuration of the playful determination of its own time.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>PAULO MAIA AND CARMO</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/paulomaiaecarmo/</link><description>Chen Jiru (1558-1639), the painter who wanted to be free from the ties of court staff to devote himself to knowing everything around him and pronounce independently, was therefore called the "Great Chancellor of the Mountains", the space where there are always new perspectives for the look and there are no cities limits.
Referring to the works that circulated among the collectors and lovers of his friend's paintings, the influential thinker of Huating (current Songjiang, Shanghai) Dong Qichang (1555-1636) had said without fate that "less than one in ten" of the paintings that were attributed to him would effectively works of his brush.
This will not be admired given the multiplicity of tasks required by a man of culture at the end of the Ming Dynasty and which, in his case, included the demonstration of his theories in caligraffes and paintings.
The names of some painters are known, which helped him in this function from the knowledge of the history of painting, studied in his valuable collection, such as his friend Zhao Zuo (C.1570- After 1630) or Shen Shichong (Act.C.1602-41).
The latter also originally from Huating, he would recreate an album of 1625, twelve perspectives from the Lejiao Yuan Private Garden, "Pleasures of the suburbs" of the distinguished painter Wang Shimin (1592-1680), where he has realized the eloquence of certain figures placed in favorable places.
The creation of gardens, Zaoyuan, a privileged space for the exercise of subjectivity, one of the activities to which the intellectuals were dedicated, had the prestige associated with the Zaowu or Zaohua expressions, the "creator of strength" or "transformation" used in Zhuangzi, with intrinsic affinities to the painter's or man of letters.
As Qi Baojia wrote (1602-1645) creating a garden is like “the painting of a great artist: not a single uninspirated brushstroke is allowed; just as a careful author writing: not a distant word is authorized.
Shen Shichong would make it in its own name, several paintings affirming its relationship with free space for walking, in a style that takes advantage of the abstract forms of Dong Qichang mountains with the nebula atmosphere and the noted spatial recession between professional painters.
Long horizontal rollers, exemplary of these characteristics are the landscape paintings of the four stations (Shangao Shuifang, High Mountains, Long Rivers, Ink and Paper Color, 28.6 x 761 cm, at the Museum of Fine Arts of Boston) or the one that is considered his masterpiece, Tianxia Diyi, "first under the sky". Today known as mountain retreat (ink and color on paper, 33 x 1527 cm, for sale at Christies) in it are visible you are visible, bridges over the rivers, pines and walkers fearless in the fimbrias of the mountains in a figuration of the playful determination of its own time.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
“It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It is the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden, ”he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth training center, ”explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
“It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It is the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden, ”he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth training center, ”explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Today Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/autor/hoje-macau/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
“It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It is the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden, ”he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth training center, ”explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>IC | Launched book on the historical roots of Rua das Estlagês</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/ic-lancado-livro-sobre-as-raizes-historicas-da-rua-das-estalagens/</link><description>“In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Street of Estalagins” is the name of the work Bilingual, launched in digital format, which tells the story of this historic street of Macao, revealing the business that survived the passage of time. Production was in charge of the Macao Artists Society, with the support of the Cultural Institute and Sands China
 
The history serpes through the stalage street since the end of the nineteenth century. The narrow artery has always been the scene of an intense social and commercial rebolement and it was where Sun Yat-Sen, considered the father of modern China and the Republican Revolution, opened pharmacies and drugstores, especially from 1893. Over the years, Rua das Estalagem, in Porto, was a living example of commerce, and the Portuguese governors were progressively expanding the street, composed of the street Chinese -style buildings and temples, such as the Temple of the Bazaar and Goddess Temple NOVA WO.
All these pieces of history are now counting on the digital publication “In Search of Its Roots - An Illustrated History of Rua das Estlagês”, a work produced by the Society of Macao Artists and authored by Siguo Chen in Shirley Lule's texts and illustrations. Those responsible for the edition are the Cultural Institute (IC) and the game operator Sands China.
According to a press release of Sands China, the book, in Chinese and English, intends to “highlight the fascinating past of the historic Macau Street and the beauty of its legacy”, containing interviews with street -related figures, whether merchants or residents. Thus, it is intended to bring “residents and visitors to rediscover the preciousness of the centenary stores and the cultural heritage of the street through legendary stories” so that they can “widen their understanding of the transformation of the neighborhood and its inhabitants”.
The content of the book results from “close conversations with representatives of associations, business entities and residents of the neighborhood,” having dozens of oral stories that can easily be lost if not recorded. This work is not closed in the digital world, having been printed to appear in the public libraries of Macao and schools, in order to “promote the meaning of cultural heritage and enhance mutual ties among the people of Macao”, intending to be “a valuable community resource to deepen the understanding and appreciation of Macao and the street”.
200 years of history
One of the highlights given in the book is to the textile sector that has always predominated on Rua das Estlagenas. In the chapter entitled "Two Centuries of Prosperity: Spinning A Legacy in the Textiles Trade" [two centuries of prosperity: the construction of a legacy in the textile trade], it is read that "Street of Estlagins has always been a center for the textile industry." In the years when the textile sector had a larger presence in the territory, between the 70's and 90's, "Rua housed more than 20 stores with factory products, including three spaces from the Veng On Farm Store." “Around 30 businesses related to these stores, such as tailors, clothing stores, western products and funeral ornament stores, which brought a reputation to the street,” he reads. In Rua das Estlagenas “Tissue trade is over 200 years old,” says the same text.
Other chapters of the book speak of the presence of the republican revolutionary in Macao in “The Starting Point of Sun Yat-Sen’s Story” [The Starting Point of the story of Sun Yat-Sen] or stories of street-linked personalities and their commerce.
In the conclusion of the work, it refers that after the transition, the street "faced new challenges: the global financial crisis, the SARS epidemic, the COVID-19, and the uncertainty of the economy, leaving the need for renewal again."
“In the past, businesses flourished by themselves thanks to hard work and resilience. But nowadays the community joins with a shared view, actively planning [the development of the street] with the support of the Macao government and the integrated resort companies. With these efforts, there is a sense of hope that Rua das Estlagês briefly recovers its ancient vitality, being ready for a new era of prosperity, ”is pointed out.
Institutional view
IC President Deland Leong Wai Man pointed out that the book results from the “weighted effort to widen the discussion around preservation and revitalization [of the street],” according to the same press release. "Street renewal is expected to inspire more people to learn about the historic neighborhoods of Macao and participate in their preservation, combining ideas and resources to ensure that the city's culture and history continue to prosper during generations," he said.
In turn, Wilfred Wong, CEO of Sands China, argued that "Street of Estalagues is a microcosm of Macao itself, a place where a rich story meets a modern future."
“The walls of their alleys witnessed the transformation of Macao, and their stories and people deserve to be remembered, as they are precious sources of Macao's cultural heritage. Our effort to publish the book was possible thanks to the collaboration of our local team to conduct interviews with owners of historic stores, create illustrations and take photographs, among other works, ”he said.
New facades
It is recalled that this publication arises after the Government was announced by the Sands performance at the Rua das Estalagens Revitalization Plan, namely with the “Entrepreneurs Recruitment Program for Rua das Estlagês”, launched in April last year.
The game operator explains that the seven businesses selected for the initiative “have been opening through phases, bringing energy to the zone along with other new businesses, providing a platform for young ambitious entrepreneurs to realize their dreams”.
In addition, the game operator intends to revitalize stores' façades “with drawings that enhance their characteristics, resonating the history of the street and the city”. For this initiative, Sands has also collaborated with the Macao Artist Society, and the drawings will be created by two young local artists, Chek On Law and Sit Kat Kit.
"The aim is that, with a collective effort like this, the community can rediscover the history of the street and learn about its past stories and stores through the visual interpretations of these local artists from Macao and their perceptions of the territory," he reads.
Siguo Chen, the book's author, is a veteran journalist with a career of over 60 years who has been deeply linked to the media area in Macau and Hong Kong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 01:50:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Sun Yat-Sen | Marked centenary of the death of the “father of modern China”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/13/sun-yat-sen-assinalado-centenario-da-morte-do-pai-da-china-moderna/</link><description>Sun Yat-Sen died on March 12, 1925. Unavoidable figure in the political history of modern China and the father of the movement that led to the fall of the imperial regime, Sun Yat-Sen was celebrated yesterday in Guangzhou, where he was born, Beijing and Taiwan
 
The first president of China post-imperial and considered the father of the country's modern era, Sun Yat-Sen, was remembered yesterday in mainland China and Taiwan, the 100th anniversary of his death.
In Beijing, there was a “brief and solemn ceremony” of honor to Sun in Beijing Park that has its name. Authorities and “people from all the sectors of society” were present, kept silence and made three venias in front of their statue, the Xinhua official news agency said.
The Chinese Academy of History praised the political figure in his Weibo account, describing him as "a great national hero, a great patriot and a major precursor of the Democratic Revolution of China."
The city of Guangzhou, the capital of Guangdong Province, where Sun Yat-Sen was born, inaugurated on Tuesday an exhibition of old objects related to the man who was one of the promoters of the revolution that overthrew the Qing Dynasty (1644-1911). The Sun Yat-Sen Memorial Building in the city welcomed the first performance of a musical based on the revolutionary's youth.
In Guangzhou, where there is also a university named Sun Yat-Sen, this exhibition is exhibited, which includes objects such as the Sun Yat-Sen Graduation Exam report at the College of Medicine for Chinese, in Hong Kong, from 1892. The certificate of marriage between Sun Yat-Sen and Soong Ching-Ling is also highlighted in 1915, a woman later, woman later, Vice-President of China during the government of Mao Tse-Tung, embracing communism. In the same exhibition you can also see the bronze bust of Sun Yat-Sem itself, made by order of the Japanese friend Umeya Shokichi in 1929.
The "father" of modern China was also remembered in Taiwan, with a ceremony by the Sun Yat-sen memorial in Taipei, where flowers were deposited and express respect.
Double memories
Despite founding, in 1919, the Kuomitang, which would become the main rival of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), Sun is remembered in both mainland China and Taiwan. The Board of State's Taiwan Cabinet stated that Sun Yat-Sen “sought China's national unity and revitalization throughout his life,” appealing at the same time to the “compatriots of Taiwan to join us in the inheritance of his legacy” and to “oppose secession” of the island.
Born in 1866, Sun studied medicine in Hong Kong - then a British colony - and, after leading several revolts, gained notoriety as a revolutionary leader and as a driving force of an attempt to modernize the country.
In 1911, the Xinhai Revolution led to the fall of the Qing and Sun Yat-Sen dynasty was appointed provisional president of the New Republic of China in January 1912, but quickly gave power to the country's main military leader, Yuan Shikai, who, far from consolidating republican ideals, dissolved the parliament in 1914 and proclaimed herself in 1915, annulling Grande, annul Part of the democratic progress by which Sun had fought.
From then on, he continued to promote his ideal of a unified and republican China, reorganizing the KMT and seeking international support for his cause. In 1923, he established an alliance with the newly founded CCP and received the support of the Soviet Union to reinforce the political movement. However, he failed to consolidate a stable government before his death in 1925.
A LIFE OF FIGHT
In the work “Sisters Soong-the oldest, younger and redest,” by Jung Chang, some details of Sun Yat-Sen's life are described before embracing the revolutionary cause and the way he left his parents' house in Guangzhou, looking for a better life.
The place of destination was Hawaii, which on July 4, 1894 declared itself as a Republic, an event that, according to the book, "helped shape today's China." “A 27-year-old radical Chinese, Sun Yat-sen, landed in the archipelago and entered a world where the word 'republic' was in every mouth,” he is described.
In China, the agitation against the power of the empire became strong. The Republic "was a new concept," for "the monarchy was the only political system that China knew." "At the time, the country was governed by the Manchu dynasty," the Manchus "were not natural from China, but they had conquered the territory in the mid -seventeenth century." “Since they did not get more than one percent of the population, they were considered a minority of foreign rulers and had never lacking opposition from the native rebels Han. Sun was one of them, ”he describes himself in the same work.
Sun Yat-Sen was "a low, dark man with well-proposed and pleasant traits." Its home village, Cuiheng, had soils inappropriate for agriculture, which provided “a life of extreme misery” to those who lived there. As such, the revolutionary's family did not escape adverse conditions.
In his first escape from the context of poverty, Sun went to Hong Kong, finding shelter to the diocesan school and boys orphanage, then accepted a marriage arranged by the family as a gimmick to return to the village. Sun Yat-Sen married Mu-Zhen, had children, but was an absent figure and something carefree in the face of family responsibilities, traveling the world to seek support for the revolution he wanted for China.
Jung Chang's work describes how Sun's course linked to the "three sisters," Ei-Ling, May-Ling and Ching-Ling. Charlie Soong funded and supported Sun Yat-Sen in her revolutionary causes, one of her daughters, Ei-Ling, became the republican secretary. This, although married, had made attempts to approach loving and EI-Ling, but eventually had a relationship with Ching-Ling, who was nationalist, but later embraced communism, being known as the "red sister." Ching-ling was also known as the Madame Sun Yat-Sen, but at the time of Sun Yat-Sen's death, the relationship between them had cooled.
After the establishment of the Popular Republic of China, Ching-Ling was vice president of the country, between 1949 and 1954, and then between 1959 and 1975, and was vice president of the Permanent Commission of the National Assembly.
Passage through macau
Moreover, Sun Yat-Sen's life crossed Macao several times, where he lived a short time, unlike his woman, Mu-Zhen, and the children who remained in the territory longer. To remember the short period in which the Republican lived in the territory, at the time under Portuguese administration, the memorial house of dr. Sun Yat-Sen, where he "witnesses the short but significant stay in Macao in the early twentieth century when, running away from the power of imperial mandarins, tried to move his supporters forces in order to implement a new regime in China." “In Macau received support from some friends who were illustrious and influential figures of social and political life at the time,” reads the description of the museum.
Another interesting detail of the 1911 Republican Revolution is the proximity of dates against the establishment of the Republic in Portugal, which took place on October 5, 1910. Macau, in the midst of events in China and Portugal, was only aware that the constitutional monarchy had fallen into Lisbon thanks to the sending of a telegram published in an official bulletin on October 10, 1910, changing the governor in this context. Lame</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 01:04:43</pubDate></item><item><title>Clinical Psychology | The benefits and risks of the introduction of AI</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/12/psicologia-clinica-os-beneficios-e-riscos-da-introducao-da-ia/</link><description>Artificial intelligence is there to stay and its use in the field of psychology begins to be spoken. Recently, Deputy Lam Lon Wai defended its use and, in Portugal, the Order of Psychologists created the “PSIA” platform, which allows it to detect symptoms. Nuno Gomes and Goreti Lima, two resident therapists, talk about the benefits, risks and potential uses of technology
 
Understanding whether emotions can result in psychological forum diseases is something that is already possible to do using Artificial Intelligence (AI). The issue begins to discuss in Macao still shyly, namely through Deputy Lam Lon Wai, who in February interpelled the government about the need to apply AI tools in clinical cases with young people.
HM spoke to two clinical psychologists who work with residents of Macao, in person or distance, about the benefits and risks of betting on AI. Nuno Gomes, a psychologist in a local clinic, says that “is, for now, a help, and it will always be”.
“AI is an irreversible process and it is inevitable that it covers all fields of our lives, and in them is psychology and help people. But I come from a field of psychology that is the humanist school, which is based on the relationship with the patient, and therefore I do not see great benefits, for the use of AI, because in human relations AI does not enter, ”he defended.
Nuno Gomes believes that AI can help in the diagnostic phase, although he thinks "the psychologist will always be the central character." “AI can be an advantage in Macau for people who have difficulty asking for help. The use of the well -defined AI, even in ethical terms, may be very useful for the beginning of a therapy. However, at this moment we have no conditions for the use of AI at the level of a more complete and background therapy, ”he said.
Nuno Gomes also recalls that for those who want to talk to someone, AI "can give the feeling that we are not alone and that is someone on the other side." It is a feeling that is still "strange", but "in the future will no longer be, because AI will be part of our day."
The psychologist believes that AI "may work as long as it is ethically well regulated and can help in brief therapies, but always as a complement to a larger process."
Goreti Lima, who has lived in Macao, continues to do clinical psychology at a distance with residents living in the territory. It is more skeptical in relation to the use of AI, arguing that human relationship is always fundamental for quality monitoring.
“Therapy is done in the relationship and these applications do not contemplate this. I think very well that we can use AI to diagnose, see symptoms, but this we can also do with a book or article. ChatgPT already tells us some things in the area of ​​psychology, possible symptom analysis. AI helps in this process, but then the rest works in the therapeutic relationship. This is why people like more from one psychologist or another. Then there is the ethical question, the data is stored as? Where do you go? Can people trust? ”He asks.
Recommendations in Portugal
In a written interpeação directed to the Government of MSAR, Deputy Lam Lon Wai questioned whether there will be “cooperation” between government departments, technological companies and local academic institutions in the use of AI in the area of ​​mental health. However, Goreti Lam regrets that deputy "do not speak in the figure of the psychologist."
“Academics have a different experience from psychologists and therapists, who have gained this experience in practical terms. This develops over time. All these questions have to be thought of when applying AI. AI can identify what the person has and even techniques to be used, but then we have to take into account deontological conditions. The assessment always has nuances depending on the social context of the person, and this is never analyzed in AI, or is unquestionable, ”he added.
Portugal is one of the countries where the application of AI in Psychology begins to gain some form, to the point of the Order of Portuguese Psychologists (OPP) has created the online “Psia” tool, which allows you to state a series of symptoms and reach a diagnosis. Personal data appear to be protected with the introduction, on the website, the citizen card number, with the digital mobile key.
In addition, OPP has created a manual of good practices, entitled “The Human Factor in Artificial Intelligence - Strategic Recommendations for Sustainability”, which states that there are “virtual therapists who can identify, in communication with people, emotional difficulties that facilitate deliberate psychological education”, as well as enhancing “the learning of techniques and skills that aim, for example, to reduce anxiety”.
In addition, the OPP document concludes that "some studies suggest that these chatbots, developed based on validated therapeutic models, may be effective in reducing depressive symptoms and even that some people establish a bond similar to that of a human relationship." However, “these evidence is not consolidated and security-related (people and data), eventual dependence on technologies and the responsiveness of support given to different psychological difficulties are not clarified”, it reads.
Regarding PSIA, it is referred to the OPP website that "on very specific or complex issues should not be used in tasks that require specialized judgment and evaluation, deep technical analysis or professional counseling." It is also clarified that the answers provided are based on “available documents and information” until July 31 last year, and PSIA “does not replace the role of a psychologist or any supervision activities”.
In the case of Hong Kong, some solutions are also beginning to emerge, which motivated, by the way, the interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai. This is the case of Hollo, a mobile phone application developed in connection with the University of Hong Kong (UHK) that aims to “make mental health care more accessible to patients, service platforms and organizations”.
Hollo uses AI power and technologies to bring clinical practices standardized to another level of productivity, intelligence and digital connectivity. According to Cameron Van Breda, Hollo's CEO and co-founder, the company aims to be "an easily accessible tool in stress times, offering analysis and friendship suggestions for better mental health exercises." In practical terms, “focuses on young people from 12 to 24 years old, works in English and Chinese and introduce them to therapy and counseling practices through mindfulness activities and daily games,” reads UHK's website.
Almost the same
Asked about Macao's mental health landscape, Nuno Gomes understands that he persists "some conservatism and ignorance not only in what is AI and areas where one can apply, but also what psychology can do."
“Psychology is here to help people and in the context of Macao there is no such understanding yet. This stigma prevents many people from seeking help and AI can give this support. However, the older population is still very unaware of the operation of AI, but the younger ones will increasingly resort to this type of platforms, ”he said.
In general terms, “the picture of mental health has changed little from the pandemic”, because “in general, people are not necessary to express emotions and since they are encouraged to keep emotions, which when they are bad and stored a long time, they begin to hurt. People don't know how to express them out of shame or guilt. ” Goreti Lima also understands that in the area of ​​mental health there is still some ignorance in Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 03:36:41</pubDate></item><item><title>The garden of Almerindo in Timor-Leste can be watered from Portugal or England</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/a-horta-de-almerindo-em-timor-leste-pode-ser-regada-de-portugal-ou-inglaterra/</link><description>The Garden of the Timorese Almerindo Fernandes in Lautém, 231 kilometers east from Dili, can be watered from Portugal or England, after the civil engineer applied new technologies to the agricultural sector.
Almerindo Fernandes, 30, has a degree in Civil Engineering and for years has worked on rural road construction projects, but the 'animal' for agriculture spoke louder and today owns Timor-Leste's first 'smart farm'.
In Lautém, Almerindo Fernandes has about two hectares of terrain, where he planted eggplant, tomatoes and other vegetables, which watering through an intelligent irrigation system that controls through a platform on his mobile phone.
“It means that in Portugal or England we can water the garden with the mobile phone. It is the modern world, the world of technology, digitization. It's the opportunity to use technology, using the mobile phone to water my garden, ”he told Lusa. "It is a great opportunity to use technology to modernize agricultural productions," he said.
With about 1.3 million inhabitants, the agricultural sector in Timor-Leste is vital to the economy of the country, but production is low and did not follow the growth of the population. According to the United Nations Food and Agriculture Organization, more than 70% of the Timorese population lives in rural areas and most practice subsistence agriculture.
Almerindo Fernandes started the activity in 2017 with the money he was sparing while working as a civil engineer and today sells his production to the school lunch program, the Armed Forces and the markets of his municipality. “So far it was a private activity, but the government is supporting the expansion of the project to the other municipalities of the country,” explained Almerindo Fernandes.
The support was achieved after presenting the project to the vice-prime minister, coordinating minister of social affairs and Minister of Rural Development and Community Housing, Mariano Assanami Sabino, who eventually hired him as a specialized technician to bring the concept to the rest of the country.
“The government recognizes the creativity of young people and all citizens who have creative initiatives. It is a great opportunity and the government is supporting the transformation of the garden into a youth training center, ”explained Almerindo Fernandes.
In the garden, Almerindo Fernandes already has to work four people permanent and then hire others to plant, take the vegetables and do the maintenance, and at the same time gives training to young people who study agriculture.
Now, according to the civil engineer, the garden also serves to do experiences to improve the system, that is, to make it more efficient and effective, with “little spent and greater performance”. "It is the principle of modernization, increased production, minimal cost is the purpose of the intelligent garden system and it is a theory we have to adapt to Timor to develop the country," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:19:38</pubDate></item><item><title>Architecture | Liu Jiakun won Pritzker 2025 prize</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/07/arquitectura-liu-jiakun-venceu-premio-pritzker-2025/</link><description>Liu Jiakun won this year's Pritzker Prize. Chengdu's natural architect was chosen by the work “coherent”, in peace with nature and the surrounding world. The organization of the prize highlights the “path that was neither linear nor expected”, and architectural projects with “convincing answers” ​​in environmental terms
 
In Liu Jiakun's work is the citizen who rules, without fixed lines or barriers, combining the old and the modern. But above all, there is a kind of consistency. The Chinese architect, born in 1956 in Chengdu province, won this year's Pritzker Prize, a distinction often described as the Nobel Prize in Architecture. With this week's announcement, the point that was missing to consecrate the talent of a man who lived and worked in a changing China was added and who narrowly did not give up architecture. By the way, according to the official information of the Pritzker Award on Liu Jiakun, his journey “until architecture was neither linear nor expected”.
The mother was an internal doctor at Chengdu Second People's Hospital and it was there that much of her days spent during her childhood. In the years when China lived intensely Maoism and then during the process of reform and openness, Liu underwent all political and social transformations as it grew. He attended the program for “educated young people” in the area of ​​agriculture, and then the Chongqing Institute of Architecture and Engineering, later called the University of Chongqing University in 1978. “As in a dream, I suddenly realized that my life was important,” he said, according to the official information of the Pritzker award.
The studio in his own name, Jiakun Architects, only emerged in 1999 in his hometown, Chengdu, the capital of Sichuan province.
About himself and his work, Liu Jiakun said: "Aspire always being like water-permeating a place without having a fixed shape of his own and infiltrating me in the local environment and in the place itself." “Over time, water is gradually solidified, becoming architecture and perhaps even the highest form of human spiritual creation. However, it maintains all the qualities of this place, both good and bad, ”he added.
Regarding the attribution of Pritzker, the jury considered that the Chinese architect knew how to innovate, keeping the side more traditional than the profession can have. “Identity has as much to do with the individual and the collective meaning of belonging to a place. Liu Jiakun revisits Chinese tradition without nostalgic approach or ambiguity, but as a trampoline for innovation. Create a new architecture that is simultaneously historical record, infrastructure, landscape and a remarkable public space, ”says the organization.
Spatial commitment
Building houses or buildings can be much more than simple building, establishing a commitment to space and the environment. For the Pritzker jury, "in a global context where architecture strives to find adequate answers to rapidly evolving social challenges, Liu Jiakun gave convincing answers that also celebrate people's daily lives as well as their community and spiritual identities."
Also according to the jury, "through a remarkable work of deep consistency and constant quality, Liu Jiakun imagines and builds new worlds, free from any aesthetic or stylistic embarrassment."
“Instead of a style, it has developed a strategy that is never based on a recurring method, but rather the evaluation of the specific characteristics and demands of each project differently. That is, Liu Jiakun takes current realities and manipulates them to the point of offering a totally new scenario of everyday life. In addition to knowledge and technique, it adds common sense and wisdom to the designer toolbox, ”he adds.
The note that presented the award states that the architect can project “a built environment that is often being pulled in opposite directions”, rethinking “the foundations of density through cohabitation, creating an intelligent solution that balances the opposite forces at stake”.
The jury also describes that "through a remarkable work of deep consistency and constant quality, Liu Jiakun imagines and builds new worlds, free from any aesthetic or stylistic embarrassment."
The largest projects
This year's Pritzker statement highlights the “West Village” project in Chengdu, classified as “transformative”, where Liu Jiakun knew “reformulate the paradigm of public spaces and community life”, “inventing new independent and shared forms of living together, where density does not represent the opposite of an open system”. The architect created here a space that allows "adaptation, expansion and replicability."
Also noteworthy are “subtle and memorable museums” created by themselves, such as the Suzhou Museum of Imperial Kiln Brick or the Shuijingfang Museum, also in Chengdu. In turn, at the Huishan Memorial in Chengdu, the architect "understands that identity is a matter of collective and personal memory, brilliantly raising the individual perspective to a fundamental element of place creation in order to revive a community dimension."
Degree in 1982, Liu was part of the first generation of students responsible for the major projects of the so -called “Nova China”, already with Deng Xiaoping to the rudder of the central government. At the beginning of his career, he was linked to Chengdu's Institute for Research and Architectural Design, a state-owned entity, having moved to Nagqu in Tibeta, where he lived two years in the 1980s.
About this time, the architect recalled his “greatest strength at the time seemed to be my fear of nothing, beyond the abilities of painting and writing,” pionering books and writing at night when he did not project.
His career in architecture was almost set aside until Liu Jiakun saw Tang Hua's solo architecture exhibition, a former university colleague at the Shanghai Art Museum in 1993. Such “rekindled his passion for the profession and fueled a new mindset that he could also be diverted from prescribed social aesthetics,” describes the pritzker jury.
For Liu, "architecture must reveal something - abstract, distill and make visible the qualities inherent to local people," "the power to shape human behavior and create atmospheres, offering a sense of serenity and poetry, evoking compassion and mercy, and cultivating a meaning of shared community."</description><pubDate>2025-03-07 02:59:07</pubDate></item><item><title>Beijing | “Two sessions” start today focusing on the economy</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/04/pequim-duas-sessoes-arrancam-hoje-com-foco-na-economia/</link><description>The month of March is synonymous with political movements in Beijing, with the political advisory conference of the Chinese people, which begins today, and the session of the National Popular Assembly, which begins tomorrow. At meetings will be discussed goals and political and economic plans for this year, without forgetting the evolution of the International Panorama
 
Today begins another session of the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), in Beijing, while for tomorrow is scheduled the start of the National Assembly (APN). The two events are the most important of the Chinese political system, materializing the country's political representativeness system, with the participation of delegations all provinces and regions of China, including the special administrative regions of Macau and Hong Kong. CCPPC has, as the name implies, an advisory character, while APN is the most important legislative body in the country.
The so -called “two sessions”, with annual periodicity, draw the attention from around the world because it is at this time that the Chinese government presents its economic goals and main political measures for the rest of the year.
According to the Xinhua state agency, data related to the country's gross domestic product (GDP) is one of the most attention points attracts, but the "two sessions" will also serve to shed some lights on China's foreign policy, something particularly remarkable in a turbulent global scenario.
Until March 11, the expected date for the closure of the work, there are objectives, calendars and essential policies, shaping “the political direction of the country” in a “complex and challenging global environment”, reads in Xinhua.
Let us look, then, to what we can expect in matters of GDP values. “As the Chinese economy is oriented for high quality development, GDP is not the only measure of the economy, but it remains an important indicator. In 2024, China reached its objective of economic growth of about five percent, thanks largely to a number of significant macroeconomic measures, introduced to compensate for the pressure of economic recession, ”he reads.
Thus, "more concrete policies to stimulate economic activity are expected." According to Xinhua, "China has already given signs of change in its macroeconomic orientation." "At the last central conference of economic labor in December, political officials committed to apply more proactive macroeconomic policies in 2025."
Thus, the adoption of a “monetary policy‘ moderately flexible ’was decided, which represents a significant removal from the 'prudent' approach adopted in the last 14 years,” the agency describes. In this meeting were also defined “nine fundamental priorities”, the first “the increase of consumption”.
Thus, it is expected that in the “two sessions”, “China emphasizes internal demand as the main economic priority”, and this year it is expected “that large-scale equipment updates and consumer exchange programs will be promoted with greater intensity and more extended”.
It is indicated that "China will actively use the maneuver margin for a higher deficit and increase the issuance of special obligations of local administrations", as well as "continuing to issue Special Treasury obligations with a longer term and increase central government transfer payments to local administrations." The "two sessions" will reveal more details in this regard.
Featured
Still on the economic level, Xinhua describes how President XI Jinping underlines on other occasions “the main priorities, such as support for the growth of the private sector”, “the acceleration of the development of the digital economy” and the deepening of the country's opening.
APN members “will analyze the annual budget and government development plan”, and proposals and suggestions related to Artificial Intelligence (AI) ”are also expected to be expected. In fact, this is “one of the main points of interest to China observers”, along with GDP values. It should be noted that, in this field, the country has sought to score points and gain a growing positioning in the market with the creation of the Deepseek platform.
According to the Global Times newspaper, Chinese companies such as Tencent, Baidu and Byd are part of DeepSeek in the products and services they make available, and "some local governments have also announced collaborations with Deepseek IA models to improve public services."
“Many AI-related plans mentioned in work reports of provincial governments [from China] focus on building innovation platforms, promoting industry deeper integration and improving political staff. It is important to note that the rise of platforms such as DeepSeek reflects China's commitment to make leadership in technological advances and a greater strategic focus on talent cultivation and the existence of an innovation conducive environment, ”he reads.
The “two sessions” also constitute “a crucial platform for political legislators and counselors to present suggestions and promote ample consensus on national development” in the AI ​​area, and “some of them are executives of renowned companies and researchers”.
GDP: Maintenance
Still with regard to Chinese GDP, an analysis by Neil Thomas and Jing Qiang of the Asia Society Policy Institute argues that the “two sessions” should reveal “an even more agenda for growth than last year, with approximate objectives of five percent for GDP growth, four percent for the GDP tax deficit and two percent inflation in terms of consumption ”. "Measures should also be introduced to increase consumption and encourage the private sector in innovation," the authors write.
The same analysis of the Asia Society Policy Institute also highlights economic measures to prevent and combat unemployment, a problem that has affected the Chinese economy in recent times.
“China will also announce the annual goals for new jobs in urban areas and the urban unemployment rate. Last year, Beijing settled these objectives in 12 million new jobs and 5.5 percent unemployment rate, and this year's numbers will probably be similar, ”is mentioned.
With regard to domestic consumption, China is intended to be more and more “a hub for product launch, winter tourism and has a 'silver savings' focusing on the area of ​​restoration for an elderly population”. Also according to the analysis of the Asia Society Polycy Institute, "other priorities include rebalancing economic platform regulations, stimulating economic activity in small towns, greater integration into the area of ​​the large bay and expanding investment in maritime industries."
Attention to Investment
The "two sessions" take place with Donald Trump to return to the presidency of the United States of America and certainly that this point will mark the external agenda of the meetings in Beijing throughout the week.
But still regarding the economy, the Chinese authorities will seek to present and discuss measures that may maintain foreign investment attraction in the country, after the launch of the “Action Plan to stabilize foreign investment”, on February 19.
Here is a “strategic change in Beijing's approach, moving away from tax benefits and subsidies and addressing the liberalization of specific sectors, rationalizing regulation and incentives for re-inforings,” point the same analysts.
Therefore, Beijing intends to “frame foreign companies into China's regulatory framework to turn them into long -term stakeholders, making local expansion more attractive than capital reafect to other markets”. Analysts also expect the "two sessions" to reveal concrete policies in this regard.
Sam Hou Fai in Beijing
The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, has been in Beijing since yesterday to attend the opening ceremony of the third session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (APN), which takes place tomorrow.
Sam Hou Fai will be in the Chinese capital until Thursday of this week. According to a statement from the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai will be replaced by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, who acts interimly, the functions of Chief Executive.
In the 14th APN, the Government's work report will be reviewed and the analysis of the report on the implementation of the Annual National Economic and Social Development Plan for 2024. The agenda also includes analysis to the National Economic and Social Development Project for this year. The report on the implementation of the central and local budgets for 2024 will also be analyzed, as well as the central and local budget projects for 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:50:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Economy | Trips to China increase due to diversity and low prices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/03/economia-viagens-a-china-aumentam-devido-a-diversidade-e-precos-baixos/</link><description>Going to China has never been so easy, fast and cheap. Two residents of Macao of Portuguese nationality reveal to HM which leads them to cross the border frequently, especially the weekend. Cultural diversity, low prices and higher quality of service in bars and restaurants make all the difference
 
Macao Small and Medium-sized (SME) have faced, since the reopening of borders in the postpandeia period, huge difficulties to recover the business, especially those that are further away from the tourist areas. At a time when traveling to China has become extremely easy and cheap, two residents explain why they prefer to move often to the neighboring city of Zhuhai, or even Shenzhen, and consume there instead of being in Macao. Options like dinner outside, catching a taxi or drinking a glass are much cheaper, and the possibility of driving outside the territory has made this option more frequent. But electronic trade has also contributed to the fall of local consumption, they ensure.
Nelson Moura, journalist and resident of Portuguese nationality, goes to Zhuhai whenever he has a free weekend or holidays. It even goes between three to four times a month. “Costs are lower inside China, and then there is the novelty factor. It has never been easy for a non -Chinese resident of Macau to go to China. I previously needed to ask for a visa, had a reduced deadline, and this greatly limited my trips, and always chose more distant places in a context of tourist travel. Local residents could go to China before, but the current convenience, with organized and developed borders, especially Hengqin, with the connection to the light meter, allows for easier connections, ”he told HM.
Since China has flexed the policy of visas and increased the offer of border circulation, traveling to the country is no longer seen as a great trip. “As a foreigner residing in Macao, going to China was a bit like going traveling to another Asian country. In the pandemic we did not go practically from Macau, but now since the policy of visas to Portuguese has been flexible, it is possible to go to China whenever we want, ”said Nelson Moura.
“I am as easily as a Chinese resident, and it has become a viable option to go to the weekends and holidays to China, knowing different sites. The food is a third of the price of what is practiced in Macau, has more quality, with fresh products, the reception offers are better. Macao is a great city, but after three years of pandemic knows very well to get out of here whenever we want. It is a more convenient option now than before. ”
Nelson Moura also considers that "for the Chinese community of Macao and Hong Kong there is a greater convenience of travel," as "there are many residents leading all weekends to China just to go to large commercial surfaces, which allows you to buy large amounts of food."
“Traffic near the border of the HKZM siege or bridge is at a level never seen before. There is the option of being able to drive in the large bay zone which is good for small and expensive cities like are Macau and Hong Kong, ”he said.
PME, the eternal problem
On the side of Macau, associations linked to the Chinese community's commercial sector call for help, asking for more measures such as the great consumption award, or even consumer cards, that is, more campaigns and initiatives so that residents can buy more in Macao with discounts or support.
One of the last voices showing concern about this scenario was Stanley Au, president of the Macao SME association. To TDM Canal Macau, the official argued that in the next lines of government action the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, has to show effective measures to avoid closing and, consequently, more unemployment. “The most urgent and current situation is the closure of companies. I believe the population saw many stores closed in different neighborhoods of the territory. Sometimes, on the same street, there are more stores closed than opened. In addition, the biggest problem is that Macau is facing continuous economic slowdown. If we do not solve this problem, society does not improve, ”he added.
However, according to Nelson Moura, it will always be difficult to combat the attraction of the consumption of Greater China. “Macao's local commerce is a complicated issue. There is a major reduction in consumers, especially on weekends and days when people have time to leave the city. ”
Electronic trade also enhances a reduction in local consumption. “Residents know they find more and cheaper out there. There are Chinese electronic trade companies, such as TAOBAO, which allow purchases from all over China to Macao without transportation charges, which has reduced domestic consumption. People go to stores to see what they want to buy and then do it at Taobao. I don't know how this trend can be circumvented. It is capitalism to work, ”explained Nelson Moura.
The resident also draws attention to the fact that it is now easier to use online payment platforms in China with foreign cards or Macao banks, namely through MPay.
Nelson Moura believes that local SMEs have only endured so much time because they were in a kind of closed economic circuit. “Local businesses lived a little in an island economy, and they survived the fact that the Macao market is in the territory, without people could leave so much. Now that there has been competition with what China has to offer, companies suffer because they often don't offer the service so much quality and at such an attractive price. I know the situation in Hong Kong is similar. ”
“Like” in China
Macaense Miguel Rosa Duque has always worked in Macau and spent in the territory most of the days of the week, but since he started teaching in Zhuhai his life has become more across the border. Highlights the much cheaper night exits as well as the restoration offer. “Macao has no variety and people are filled with the fact that the territory is small. We have hotels and restaurants, but they are expensive because the lace are expensive. Faced with China, in terms of price, the difference is like between heaven and earth. I give an example: To take a taxi from the siege gates to the university where I teach it is 40 minutes of travel, 28 kilometers, and paid about 60 to 80 Renminbis. It's very cheap. In Macao, from the doors of the siege to Coloane we pay 150 patacas or more, the price difference is huge. ”
Miguel Rosa Duque says that the trips to China in her circle of friends have become so frequent that they even created a group on the WhatsApp social network to facilitate group walks. “I prefer to go to China a thousand times just for fun. I have a lot of variety of bars and nightclubs and in Macau everything is dead. A two -person massage costs 600 Renminbis in Macao costs twice. I don't talk about hotel massage. Customer service is much better in China, with more attention to customers, more attentive, and it's all cheaper. If we spend 1000 patacas on a night in Macao, China we spend 400 Renminbis and we are treated like kings. The variety is infinite in terms of restaurants. Macau can't compete, ”he said.
Miguel Rosa Duque says he has friends who, even with a car in Macau, eventually acquired another Chinese enrollment car who are parked in the border parking park because it is cheaper to rent a place to park.
Macanese understands that between local SMEs and trade in China “there is no possible competition”, especially with online sales platforms. “People no longer go to stores here, there are a thousand choices and you can buy it from home. My girlfriend rarely goes to the supermarket, does everything online, for example, ”he added.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Budget | Kevin Ho defends subsidies only for those who need the most</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/orcamento-kevin-ho-defende-subsidios-so-para-quem-mais-precisa/</link><description>At a time when the presentation of the government lines are expected, the first of the new government, Kevin Ho appeals to the accuracy in the distribution of social support
 
Macao deputy at the National Popular Assembly and businessman Kevin Ho argues that the government must be cautious with the budget of the MSAR, and make a more accurate distribution of social support. The message was left through statements made to TDM.
“With regard to social assistance beneficiaries, the government has to be more accurate in its distribution. Those who have the most needs should get more, ”said the businessman.
In recent times, several representatives of different associations have defended a new distribution of supports, although officially the budget of the MSAR is not deficient. In the first month of the year, the budget had a surplus of 3.68 billion patacas, less 1.74 billion patacas than in the first month of last year.
"Whether it is from previous, cash, or the various preferred policies for residents, such as the distribution of dividends of MSAR revenues […] those who have the greatest needs should receive more support," said the businessman.
One of the supports that has been targeted by some deputies and associations is the pecuniary reimbursement program, also known as the “pecuniary check”, from 10,000 patacas to permanent residents and 6,000 patacas for non-permanent residents. Although not targeted by Kevin Ho, there were several local political voices that requested the elimination of support for residents who do not live at least half of the year in the MSAR.
Confidence in the government
The public broadcaster also listened to Lao Chi Long, local businessman and member of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), who, despite recognizing the limitations in the current state of the economy, showed confidence in Sam Hou Fai executive to get around the situation.
"Although the economy may not perform as good as expected, I am confident that the MSAR government has the ability to change this situation and implement more policies to boost positive economic development," said Lao, quoted by Macau channel.
In recent times, more and more requests to support small and medium -sized companies have not benefited from the increase in the number of interior tourists.
Also different representatives of the real estate market, such as former deputy Ung Choi Kun, have advocated policies to support entrepreneurs, builders and tax reduction, to promote more purchases and sales of houses and commercial spaces.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:47:25</pubDate></item><item><title>Diplomacy | Paulo Rangel confirms trip to Beijing and Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/diplomacia-paulo-rangel-confirma-viagem-a-pequim-e-macau/</link><description>Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel will move to Macao and China at the end of the month, said to Lusa official source, and the trip to be defined.
Earlier this month, TDM indicated the presence of the Portuguese Executive's number two in Macao and China, and was expected to participate in the Boao Forum, which will take place between 25 and 28 March, in Hainan Province, and the holding of contacts with Chinese authorities, namely Chinese homologous, Wang Yi. Lusa, a source of Paulo Rangel's office, confirmed the trip at the end of the month, indicating that the travel program is not yet closed.
Macau will receive later this year the celebrations of June 10, which start in lakes, according to the presidency of the Republic, in February, in a note published on its website. “The President of the Republic designated the city of Lagos as headquarters of the celebrations, in 2025, of Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities, extending the celebrations to the Portuguese community in Macao”, reads in the text dated February 7.
According to the same note, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa decided to constitute the organization of the celebrations “a commission chaired by Dr. Lídia Jorge, writer, and who is part of the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, the Secretary General of the Presidency of the Republic and the head of the State Protocol”.
In December last year, the head of state had already admitted that his last June 10th of his term-which ends on March 9 next year-to be celebrated with more distant Portuguese emigrant communities such as Asia Pacific, Australia, Macao or Goa.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:46:07</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS | Nick Law defends community network widening</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/ias-nick-lei-defende-alargamento-de-rede-comunitaria/</link><description>Deputy Nick Lei wants the Community Collaboration Network, that the Institute of Social Action (IAS) uses to provide support in cooperation with civic associations and social entities, to be extended to more associations. In a written interpeação released on Saturday, also a leader in Fujian community associations mentioned the fire in a building, which launched earlier this month in the Toi San neighborhood, as an example of the need to widen the community support network.
Nick Lei states that the first association that arrived on the ground in this fire has received requests for help from residents, but as it does not belong to the community collaboration network eventually had to refer to requests to other entities.
It should be noted that the IAS cooperation network includes the General Union of Macao residents 'associations, the Macao Workers' Associations Federation, the Macao General Association of Macao and Macao, according to an IAS statement published in early March. Now, among the mentioned entities is not the covenant of the people, chaired by Nick Lei, linked to the Fujian community.
The deputy mentioned the statistics presented by the Fire Department, which between July 2019 and last month, proceeded to inspections to 1,742 apartments to detect potential gas escape risks, and found that less than one third of housing, 30.4 percent, passed the test. Given the unmelling numbers, Nick Law asks for more inspection and with higher quality.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:44:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Game | Davis Fong devalues ​​impact of Thai casinos</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/jogo-davis-fong-desvaloriza-impacto-de-casinos-tailandeses/</link><description>Davis Fong, academic and former deputy, considers that future casinos in Thailand will have more negative impact on the Singapore game sector than in Macao.
According to the newspaper or Mun, the director of the Institute of Studies on the Game Industry of the University of Macao, argued that, in the short term, future game concessions in Thailand will not be a threat to Macau, as the territory suffers more from the external economic environment. Davis Fong recalled that in 2010, the first year of the opening of casinos in Singapore, it was thought that Macau would lose players, but the truth is that it did not happen.
Davis Fong considers that one of Macao's advantages over these two territories is the fact that he gather casinos in one zone, such as Cotai, which absorbs about 70 percent of mass segment players. In case of bad luck, the gambler can go to the next casino, which will not happen in Thailand, believe, where infrastructures will be apart from each other.
He also argues that players will not set aside a closer betting site to move further, unlike VIP gamblers, who can move to Thailand because they have different betting and travel objectives. According to Davis Fong, the players of great sums make no difference if they play in Macau or Thailand.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:43:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Pass | CAEAL ATTENTION TO REQUESTS IN CHILLS</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/macau-pass-caeal-atenta-a-solicitacoes-em-trocas/</link><description>The Electoral Affairs Commission of the Legislative Assembly did not receive a “formal complaint” about the case of the elderly who was invited to sign a list for the elections while exchanging the Macau Pass card. Still, the commission says it is concerned and that it provides “special attention” to the situation
 
Even without any formal complaint, the Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) ensures that it will be aware of the process of exchanging macau pass to the elderly, as part of the consumer consumption incentive program.
"Even though it has not yet received a formal complaint about the situation, Caeal will be in contact with the direction of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) and closely monitor the situation and all news about legislative elections to take place this year," Caeal said in response to questions posed by HM.
It is recalled that last Monday, a resident told the Macau Forum Macau program microphones of Radio Macau, that his grandmother would have been invited to signing a proposal for the candidacy for legislative elections when exchanging the Macau Pass card to the elderly to participate in the major consumption award. About this episode, the body that organizes and supervises legislative elections, led by magistrate Seng Ioi Man, ensures that he is following the case.
“The comments fabrics by the Macau radio listener about changing the Macau Pass card to the elderly, Caeal pays special attention, and to find out the situation, immediately came into contact with DSEDT, which is responsible for coordinating the replacement work of that card with social service institutions and collaborating civic associations.”
Dry the competition
Last week, DSEDT told HM to have conducted training sessions, issued guidelines for civic associations that are collaborating with the government in the exchange of macau pass cards to the elderly and reminded employees that they should limit their service to card replacement. "DSEDT will continue to oversee all service posts, and if you check the guidelines in any of these, you will immediately cease the card replacement service provided by the service station involved," added the entity led by Yau Yun Wah to HM.
HM sought to know the consequences for cases in which civic associations with both Caeal and DSEDT. In addition to the closure of the card exchange posts, it was not referred to whether there would be any legal consequences, or infringement of the laws that regulate the elections.
Former deputy Au Kam San presented an explanation for the “nervousness” of the main traditional associations to resort to all expedients to collect as much as possible, even when they provide public services, such as the exchange of macau pass to the elderly.
“This is a tactic, because in the same election, any voter can only sign a list once (…), otherwise they are committing a crime. The more signatures a list can, the more space removes other lists. If an association gather 50,000 signatures, even if only 500 and the remaining 49,500 are lying in the trash, these voters will not be able to sign other lists, ”Au Kam San said in a Facebook post.
The former deputy points out that despite not being punished with arrest who signs more than a proposal of candidacy, in addition to the payment of a fine, the voter may have a criminal record.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:41:45</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Pass | Controversial card exchange due to collection</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/macau-pass-troca-de-cartao-polemica-devido-a-cobranca/</link><description>After an elderly man complaining about requested 50 patacas to change Macau Pass, the government said that from today there are no charges, after announcing that the exchange was free. As for the request to sign lists for the elections, the executive assured HM that if he is aware of irregularities will end card exchange posts
 
After a complaint on Monday that an elderly woman was invited to signing a candidacy report for legislative elections when she exchanged the Macau Pass card to the elderly to participate in the great consumption award in a local association, yesterday the process again got to know a new episode.
Once again, in the Macao Macao Forum Program of the Radio Macao Chinese channel, an elderly man complained of being charged 50 patacas to change the Macau Pass card to the elderly that allows you to participate in the program for discounts and incentive for consumption consumption consumption. The case occurred in a Macau Pass store where the employee will have informed the resident that he would be exchanged in one of about 60 exchange posts in social services and local associations the service would be free.
It is recalled that at the end of last week, the day the card exchange began, the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) issued a statement informing that “the treatment of replacement formalities” was free. Also the request for a temporary card would have no charges. “If the elderly need to use the card during the replacement period, Macau Pass will provide them with free temporary use card”, even at Macau Pass service centers.
After the complaint, DSEDT clarified that the 50 patacas charged would be returned in the balance of the new card. In addition, the government negotiated with Macau Pass to, starting today, finish the pre-ability of fees to change cards.
Electoral little leg
In addition to the collection of 50 patacas, the exchange of cards and the request of temporary cards that is made exclusively at Macau Pass stores has been criticized by the long lines it has generated. Deputy Pereira Coutinho was one of the voices that denounced the situation.
On the other hand, when the card exchange service was only three business days, a resident claimed that his grandmother was invited to sign a candidacy report to legislative elections while trying to change the Macau Pass card to the elderly in a local association.
HM contacted all public services involved (Institute of Social Action, Commission on Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly and DSEDT), to find out if any investigation related to electoral actions would be underway during the exchange of the elderly cards, and what the consequences, and only obtained response from DSEDT. The body led by Yau Yun Wah began by mentioning that DSEDT organized training sessions and clarification for "collaborating entities regarding elderly card replacement procedures."
In addition, DSEDT said it had elaborated "Operation and Confidentiality Guidelines" and requested "employees of all service posts that fulfilled them rigorously."
Regarding the request to sign candidates' propositions during card exchange, DSEDT points out that it has “remembered its employees that they should be conferenceed with residents assistance in replacing cards, limiting only the service available to card replacement”. Communication that DSEDT guaranteed HM, in an email sent late Wednesday afternoon, was reiterated "a few days ago."
Regarding possible consequences of electoral use of associations in the work of replacement of cards, the government guaranteed the HM that it will be aware. "DSEDT will continue to supervise all service posts, and if you check the violation of guidelines in any of these, you will immediately cease the card replacement service provided by the service station involved," he was added.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:10:35</pubDate></item><item><title>“Two Sessions” | Sam Hou Fai promises “concrete actions”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/duas-sessoes-sam-hou-fai-promete-accoes-concretas/</link><description>The chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, promises to hold "concrete actions" in Macao to "transform the spirit of the" two sessions "and the words of the Chinese leaders into practical actions, defended yesterday in a speech given at the" Two Sessions "transmission session of the National People's Assembly (APN) and this year's Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC).
Sam Hou Fai said the messages transmitted in the "two sessions" will "tirelessly open new development horizons to Macao in the context of participation and support for Chinese modernization, thus contributing even more significantly to the construction of a large country and national revitalization."
It is intended, for example, to “introduce new concepts of governance, to improve the forms of government action and to intensify communication and cooperation with society”, implementing “fully the principle of Macau ruled by patriots”. The ruler also said that will be taken to "deepen the reform of the public administration, reinforce coordination and concertation, and comprehensively raise government effectiveness."
Regarding the economy, diversification remains the main objective. "We will adopt a new mindset with more intensified efforts and more pragmatic measures that accelerate and promote proper economy diversification in order to achieve new advances and new results," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:08:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Fell from the power chair</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/caiu-da-cadeira-do-poder/</link><description>Possibly younger readers will not even know the history of dictator António Oliveira Salazar. But, I tell you a tragic-komic story that happened to the former chairman of the Council of Ministers during the time of the dictatorship that reigned before April 25, 1974.
Sources close to the dictator, Dona Maria, told us that the dictator was a daily listener of the humorous programs of the 'parody of Lisbon'. On one day, the dictator was in the ripation of the São Julião da Barra Fort, sitting in a canvas chair, catching his sun's rays and listening to a radio show from the team of Lisbon humorists. At one point, he found it so funny to a radio program that laughing several laughter and fell from his chair hitting his head on the floor stone and never recovered from the brain injury.
Now, after more than 50 years, another head of government has also fallen from the chair, but this one of power. Luís Montenegro when he took office as Prime Minister, due to AD's tangential victory, he said he was ready to rule for four years with transparency and stability. Two terms of the greatest importance in politics, but which were in no way fulfilled by the Prime Minister.
Last week, Luís Montenegro fell from the power chair for his sole fault. The politician, the PSD leader and prime minister in management began to walk in the mouths of the world for lack of transparency in his business that allegedly continued when he took seriousness and the lack of stability in his government due to the many cases that were registered in just over 300 days of governance, namely the 16 Portuguese who died that I INEM has made a strike and did not give clinical support to these people. About transparency it seems to me that everything is told and in the last chronicle we specified in detail the cambalachos of his family business and about the real estate of politicians who make them belong, while falling a singing star, in men wealthy with luxury houses, good Thursdays or a lot in Alentejo.
It happened that after two motions of censorship to the government had been failed, the Socialist Party entered the Assembly of the Republic with a potestative request for a parliamentary commission of inquiry into doubts in the activity of the Prime Minister's family business and which he never wanted to respond in full.
In the face of the socialist attitude, Luís Montenegro decided to gather the Council of Ministers and announce the presentation of a motion of trust in Parliament. Okay, it was the cradled broth. Everyone saw that Luís Montenegro had taken the blackmail and would confront the socialists in the sense if they withdrew the request for a parliamentary commission of inquiry, he also collected the motion of confidence. The parliamentary session that discussed and voted for the motion of trust was a shame in the history of 50 years of democracy. The government and parliamentary leader of the PSD made a very sad and disgusting figure who led to the condemnation of all parliamentarians, except a group called liberal initiative that still hopes to ally with AD and one day go to the Portuguese government. With the vote expressed in an absolute majority against the motion of trust we watched the fall of Montenegro, and its peers, from the chair of power.
Then the President of the Republic, who always disagreed with Montenegro in the presentation of a trusted motion, received the parties and gathered the Council of State announcing that the elections will be held on May 18.
The mess of the election campaign to end an election cycle never seen will begin. Montenegro is convinced that he will win and Pedro Nuno Santos convinced is. There are surveys for all tastes, some give AD to the socialist party. One thing is certain: the arrival will have much less deputies than it had in this legislature that now ends. We now surpass the electoral turbulence recorded in the second half of the 1st Republic, of bad memory.
During this period, four general elections were called to fill parliamentary seats: May 1919, July 1921, January 1922 and November 1925. Four electoral acts in six years and six months. Nonetheless, in a more dilated range than the hallucinating series of recent legislative elections: October 2019, January 2022, March 2024 and those that will follow on May 18. One hundred years ago, nothing substantial was being solved with successive calls to the polls. On the contrary, each touch the electoral rebound made the political and governing picture always more convivial. The story seems to indicate that everything will be repeated. The politicians of our day, whatever the quadrant, should assimilate the lessons of history. Before, however, it is indispensable to know her…</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:09:14</pubDate></item><item><title>Palestinian women</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/mulheres-palestinianas/</link><description>It took me too long to address the Palestinian issue in this space. I can't explain the delay. It is a complex and emotionally demanding theme. I am perplexed to see how, in my social circles, the legitimacy of the Palestinian struggle is widely recognized, while in other spaces, any support for the Palestinian people is quickly confused with an anti-Semitic attitude.
We live in an extreme world, where division persists into parallel realities, with no room for dialogue. And so the critical situation continues. What else can I say, but I feel revolt? Season my food with Za'Atar every day as a symbolic gesture to keep the conscience of a people who suffers from hunger and deprivation alive. We have seen an unprecedented ethnic cleansing, and Palestinian occupation, refugee camps and rubble are the epicenter of sociopolitical degradation of the modern world.
On Women's Day, I had the opportunity to listen to Shahd Wadi, a researcher and writer Palestinian, who has exploited the occupation and the arts as a form of witness to women's lives and experiences. Recently, he launched the poetry book “Rain of Jasmine”, where experiences and languages ​​are intertwined. Shahd chose Portugal as a refuge while awaiting the day when he can return to his family village, where his grandmother was forced from 1948. In this informal conversation, fundamental issues were discussed: women's narratives, the imposition of Western feminism that insists on seeing the Arab woman as a victim, the body as a memory instrument of an extermination.
The concept of intersectionality proves essential in this context, as it allows us to understand the resistance of a people in parallel with the social emancipation of women. It is a struggle against occupation, injustice and systemic violence. The stories shared by Shahd Wadi brought a new light to the way we perceive the creativity and resilience of Palestinian women. Like that woman who, seeing a man being arrested by Israeli soldiers, gives her baby to her arms and stages a discussion, pretending to be fed up with her husband's constant arrests, leaving her alone with the child. The soldiers, disconcerted with the situation, free it. The man returns the baby to this woman, who had never seen before. Or as, in the face of the threat of violation, some women say goodbye, destroying the pleasure that the aggressors expect to obtain by stealing their honor.
To reflect on the resistance of Palestinian women is also to recognize how their body has become a war target. It is the body that generates and ensures the continuity of a people at risk of extermination. Restrictions on access to sexual and reproductive health care are not accidental. A checkpoint can prevent a woman from arriving at the hospital to give birth, endangering the life of the baby and mother. Small details such as this highlight the insidious dimension of the ongoing ethnic cleaning process.
Shahd Wadi shared these and many other stories, assuming an essential role in preserving the Palestinian experience. He gave us permission to make them ours, integrating them into our political imagination of struggle and resistance. On Women's Day, and in so many others, who reflect on Palestinian women who continue to resist, not only for the right to decide on their bodies and future, but also for the right to exist with dignity, freedom and sovereignty.
His struggle is a testimony of courage and resilience and reminds us that feminism, anywhere in the world, must adapt to local realities. His stories and experiences are part of the struggle for the freedom of the Palestinian people, a struggle that belongs to all.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:43:21</pubDate></item><item><title>Geogostronomy and Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/13/geogastronomia-e-a-inteligencia-artificial-2/</link><description>The complex interaction of these perspectives reflects the broader debates in the world of cooking, addressing the way food systems can evolve by respecting cultural identities. The relationship between geogostronomy and AI is illustrated through several innovative case studies.
A convincing example is the domain of personalized nutrition. Emerging technologies use AI to analyze individual eating preferences, health metrics and genetic predispositions. Companies like Nutrigenomix use AI to adapt nutritional advice based on DNA analysis, emphasizing a more individualized food approach that takes into account both geographical context and personal health.
Another remarkable effort is the development of smart kitchens. Companies like Samsung and LG have introduced AI -based cooking devices that help prepare meals and suggestion of recipes.
These intelligent devices can offer personalized recipes based on available ingredients, improving cooking experience and reducing food waste. This innovation not only simplifies meals preparation, but also encourages consumers to explore local and seasonal ingredients. In addition, AI -based platforms, such as Tock, allow kitchen restorers to analyze customer data to improve service and adapt menus to preference evolution.
This adaptability, driven by data perception, illustrates the way AI can transform traditional business models in the cooking sector, while falling into the geographical context of gastronomic experience. Despite promising developments in the intersection between geogostronomy and AI, significant challenges and limitations persist. Concerns about data privacy raise ethical questions regarding consumer information.
As AI analyzes personal eating habits, protection of these data becomes fundamental. There is also the risk of exacerbating inequalities in access to food if technology becomes too centralized or if smaller producers do not have the resources to compete.
In addition, dependence on data -based approaches can overshadow the importance of human creativity in the kitchen. Although data can guide cooking innovation, the art of cooking is often a matter of experimentation and instinct.
As chefs adopt AI tools, they should remain vigilant to preserve the essence and joy of cooking creativity. The future of geogostronomy and AI depends on a synergistic approach that respects both technological and culinary advances. Educational initiatives centered on the integration of food studies with technology can pave the way to a new generation of cooking professionals equipped to navigate this evolving landscape.
Universities and cooking schools can incorporate IA training together with traditional culinary education to produce well -prepared and familiar chefs with both domains. In addition, collaboration efforts between technology creators, chefs and farmers can lead to more sustainable practices.
By using AI to address food transportation, waste management, and facility strategies, stakeholders can create a more efficient food system that respects local flavors and cultures. Finally, the implementation of AI in community agriculture is promising. Located AI initiatives can offer farmers information about climate data, crop rotation standards and market trends, thus promoting resilience against environmental challenges.
By improving local food networks, communities can become more self-sufficient, simultaneously promoting the rich exclusive agricultural heritage of their regions. The intersection between geogostronomy and AI is a dynamic domain and full of opportunities. Understanding how geographical factors influence the kitchen and by integrating AI technologies, we can promote cooking innovation, simultaneously respecting cultural heritage.
The synergy between tradition and technology has the potential to redefine our culinary landscape, paving the way to sustainable practices and improved gastronomic experiences. Ultimately, as this interdisciplinary dialogue continues, the world of cooking is in the forefront of transforming change, combining taste with technology in a way that enriches our global food culture.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 01:51:49</pubDate></item><item><title>Planet X</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/12/planeta-x/</link><description>- Each man has the exact number of children before the alphabet he should conceive before he even learned his linguistic composition. Later in communicating them, it should be entitled to interjections in the progressive appointment of the petitions who were not to blame for the ululant effects that would determine their fire systems, but how does this mess it takes place in the time of moons, how about cash? For example, 31! There is even such a fado, and only now we understand that it is a fetus developed almost on the edge of the 39th.-But okay. Let it be x.
- When we talked to the gods there was a highly germ, Jupiter; He was the king of Olympus and fertilized Gaia in all dimensions and was therefore regarded as the real and benign being of multiplication, the king of the gods, an impetuous expansionist who blinded parental abilities and alienated them as if they were still one of their gifts. We believe that all this force was then incubate in the herds guided by male gurus that would bring a great kingdom of fraternity to all the brothers, marveled by particles and sasta with a long-range device that would cover the entire earth in degrees, systems, organizations and empires, widening in vast brotherhood. Only not.
-The delirium was however a high representative of this procreative structure that made fetuses in the bowels of mothers to produce seminal gigantisms that would still numb the fertilization of being: the father, the absent creature, will be blocked in the son that in a succession of despair and will have no answer from him. However, the beauty of this myth subsists, intrigues, and made canon. "A father who displays a son as a shroud to say that he can be special but is not the only one, there is only one mother who will always be in the center of his heart as a seal, where transcendence is in his flesh the only living process." With him he went through the silver cord that will be the chain where the father can never pass.
A father names a child, to expose him still distant from the things of men, but already named to be his sacrificial lamb of a passing emblem, a tribute of his new germinal era with a robust tendency towards infantilism, and from this perspective an old statement is insurgent- A. W-son must be more noticed as interrogation, and may even be a paternal stressful. Only mothers call them by their names and “petit nom” that makes the child a memorable agent of phonetic diction so close to poetic feel. They also say: My Jesus, my John, my Simon, my Manuel, never occurring the dry snoring of any alphabetic sign. Ur! It is very beautiful and it would be perfect for the father to remember.
X is the son of a father of Mars who has already surpassed the nine shoots, that this planet is the ninth of the solar system, and the very Portuguese saying that "go to nine": its existence had already been expected to orbit in the ends of the solar system and it was quick to bring then the planet Y. We will suppose that we are facing a representative of the existing solar planets that make up twenty -the alphabet, wanting to say that the alphabet Genetic transmission accelerator is still halfway through Mars's visionary man expects to reach. We, arrived at twelve, from the alphas and the omegas, we have walked a lot of standstill without resolution, and now comes X and Y and Z, from a backward mart where we dream of putting our feet without delay of complex nominations. That all these orbits can only be explained if they have under the influence of an unknown planet. What's coming can be silent.
- There is a parallel star in the sun that you need to find out. Your language will be in the targets of consciousness, telepathy. When this happens also these words will be noisy.
There was still a cat named Chi, but we were in the presence of a very eastern composition that reversed us to harmony. The nine lives.</description><pubDate>2025-03-12 04:03:30</pubDate></item><item><title>Portugal highlights the importance of celebrating Camilo Castelo Branco</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/portugal-destaca-importancia-de-celebrar-camilo-castelo-branco/</link><description>The Minister of Culture in Portugal stressed, on Friday, the importance of honoring writer Camilo Castelo Branco, to days of her bicentenary, and stressed the need to preserve and disseminate the author's work across the country.
“It is essential to honor Camilo Castelo Branco as a historical figure, honor his legacy, which we have to study, preserve and disseminate. And, fundamentally, to be all over the territory. In other words, acting across the country means that the rulers recognize the importance of local singularities, but always present that these are figures […] that may be from Seide, but that may be from the whole country and the world, ”said the Minister of Culture, Dalila Rodrigues, to the departure of the opening ceremony of the International Congress“ Camilo Castelo Branco, 200 years later ”, at the Camilian Study Center Seide, in the municipality of Vila Nova de Famalicão.
Asked about the relevance of the author of "love of perdition" today, the ruler stressed that "the whole work of Camilo Castelo Branco is of great current," adding that what surprises her most in Camilo "is the emotional dimension that puts in her writing."
“Creio que a maioria dos portugueses leu Camilo Castelo Branco no contexto escolar e espero que o possam ler – quem não teve essa oportunidade – no âmbito das bibliotecas públicas cuja dinamização e transformação em unidades culturais de território estão a ser objecto das políticas culturais deste Governo”, afirmou Dalila Rodrigues, que lembrou que as bibliotecas vão “dinamizar um conjunto de programas que vão resultar de parcerias entre os municípios e o Ministério da Culture ”.
The minister also left a compliment to the municipality of Famalicão, for the work of preservation and dissemination of the work of Camilo Castelo Branco.
Congress and Exhibition
The international congress that began on Friday, which ended yesterday, the day of the Bicentennial of Camilo Castelo Branco (1825-1890), gathered at the place where the writer lived much of his life dozens of national and international experts in his work.
"Camilo is as valuable as a Machado de Assis, a Dante, a Shakespeare," this week told Lusa the director of the Camilian Study Center, Sérgio Guimarães de Sousa, adding that "in one way or another", even today the Portuguese are descendants of the writing of Camilo Castelo Branco and his "universe of election", referring to the northern region.
Until August 31, at the Study Center, it is possible to visit the exhibition “Jorge. Drawings of my son ”, consisting of drawings from the collection of the son of Camilo Castelo Branco and Ana Plácido, who had the edition of a catalog to accompany. Throughout the year, initiatives and literary editions will multiply to mark the 200th anniversary of the writer's birth.
Camilo Castelo Branco was born on March 16, 1825 at Rua da Rosa, in Lisbon, and lost his mother at 2 and his father at 10, having gone to live with an aunt to Vila Real. Throughout the extensive journalistic and literary career, he signed works that would become larger books of Portuguese literature, from “Love of Perdition” to “Twelve Happy Weddings”, among many others.
A man of various interests, professional and loving, arrested in the Porto's relationship chain, along with Ana Plácido, accused of adultery, given the existence of Placido's marriage to merchant Manuel Pinheiro Alves. Both were acquitted.
One of the two literary “giants” of the Portuguese nineteenth century, along with Eça de Queirós, in the opinion of Sérgio Guimarães de Sousa, Camilo Castelo Branco, already blind due to the syphilis he suffered, committed suicide on June 1, 1890.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:07:31</pubDate></item><item><title>CCCM | “Multissecular China seen through shapes and colors” to see until April</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/cccm-a-china-multissecular-vista-atraves-de-formas-e-cores-para-ver-ate-abril/</link><description>Former Ambassador in China, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus launched himself in the painting and again presented his works in the one that is his second exhibition. “Multissecular China seen through shapes and colors” can be seen at the Macao scientific and cultural center until April 11
 
After a long career dedicated to diplomacy, as ambassador, with passages in Beijing and Pyongyang, but also Kinshasa or Brazzavile, among others, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus is now a man dedicated to books and the arts. Its artistic vein has been expressed through painting, whose works can now be seen in the latest patent exposure at the Macau Scientific and Cultural Center (CCCM). "China Multissecular viewed through shapes and colors" was inaugurated last Friday, in Lisbon and, at HM, the former ambassador explains that most of the paintings "are inspired by Chinese characters, ancient Chinese poetry and even a Poetry of Mao", written in 1925, which is titled "Alone I Stand In the Autumn Cold".
There are more than 20 paintings, one of them “on the evolution of the Sheng Castro - Life”, or another “based on a poetry of Niu Xi Ji, the poet of the sec. X E.C. ”. There are also paintings, such as number 14, "based on phrases from Jing's Dao, Lao Zì, inspired by a phrase" The Spirit of the Valley is immortal, is called the subtle or the deep vagina. "
Asked about China's perceptions, or Chinese culture itself, that the public may have with this show, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus assumes not being able to respond concretely. "Some people who know a little about the millennial Chinese culture may perhaps perceive, through painting, fundamental aspects of the two basic strains of Chinese culture, the Confucian and Lao Zi," he said.
Traveling
The former ambassador confessed to having traveled a lot and lived in many countries because of his diplomatic work, but the passage to China marked him a lot. “As a diplomat and ambassador I went through many European countries from Asia and America, but perhaps none marked me as much as China. I traveled many regions, very diverse, from that huge country. I tried to know its population and its various cultures. I fell in love in such a way that I studied and continue to study philosophical thinking and its remarkable poetic tradition. ”
Patent exposure at CCCM is the first of the person in charge in Portugal, but the second in the painter's quality, as it has already exposed in Beijing. "The fact that he was an ambassador in China is part of this exhibition," he said.
Currently, jubilated ambassador, José Manuel Duarte de Jesus was also linked to his teaching career at the Higher Institute of Social and Political Sciences of the University of Lisbon, as well as other Portuguese universities. It has been dedicated to studies and publications in the field of Asia, focusing on China, Chinese foreign policy, Africa and international relations.
One of the books he wrote about China was "The Garden in Chinese Mythical Thought," in 2002 or "China faces." In a more self-biographical vein, he edited, in 2007, “the other side of diplomacy-1960 to 2007”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:02:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau has four more restaurants with Michelin stars</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/macau-tem-mais-quatro-restaurantes-com-estrelas-michelin/</link><description>Four restaurants in Macao yesterday won a Michelin star, among the 19 restaurants distinguished in the territory in this year's edition of the Michelin Guide from Hong Kong and Macau, yesterday announced at a ceremony. In last year's edition, Macau had won two more Michelin stars restaurants, totaling 15 establishments distinguished in the guide classification.
The restaurant “Sushi Kissho by Miyakawa” at the Galaxy Macau resort joined the group of establishments with a star, while “Zuicho” at the Grand Lisbon Palace, “Mizumi”, at Wynn Palace, and “Aji” at MGM Cotai, were promoted to “selected” to a star.
Eleven restaurants, against eight by 2024, now feature a Michelin star, including “Five Foot Road” (MGM Cotai), “Lai Heen” (Galaxy), “8 1/2 Otto and Mezzo - Bombana” (Galaxy), “City of Dreams”, “Pearl Dragon” (Stadio City ”,“ Hotel ” Altira), “Zi Yat Heen” (Hotel Four Seasons).
Two restaurants in Macao, "Robucuchon au Dôme" at the Grand Lisbon-Casino Hotel, and "Jade Dragon" at the resort "City of Dreams, kept three Michelin stars.
Group of six
On the other hand, Macao had six two -star restaurants, with the promotion of chef Tam's Seasons, on the resort 'Wynn Palace, which last year had a star.
Five kept two stars: "The Huaiyang Garden", "Alain Ducassy at Morpheus", "The Eight 8" (Grand Lisbon), "Feng Wei Ju" (Hotel Starworld) and "Wing Law" (Wynn Macau).
In the distinction “Bible Gourmand”, conferred on restaurants that offer three dishes for less than 400 patacas (almost 46 euros), Macao had 11 establishments in Macao, including the Portuguese “The Castitus”, more than in 2024.
In addition to these, highlighting 28 sealing restaurants, including four Portuguese cooking: “Chiado”, “A Lorcha”, “Portuguese” and “Manuel Cuisine Portuguese”. The only green star, which distinguishes a sustainable cuisine, continued to be the educational restaurant of the University of Tourism of Macao, macanese cuisine.
The Michelin guide from Hong Kong and Macau distinguished 95 Michelin Star Restaurants, 76 of which in Hong Kong and 19 in Macao. The awarding ceremony of the awards was held at the Grand Lisbon Palace, 'resort' of the Macau Games Society (SJM).</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:46:11</pubDate></item><item><title>Lisbon | First skate park opens this Saturday</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/lisboeta-primeiro-parque-de-skate-abre-este-sabado/</link><description>The Lisboeta Macau venture inaugurates tomorrow the first macao outdoor skate park, in partnership with the General Association of Macao Skate Sports Culture and Sports Development. The idea is to "promote the practice of skateboarding and improve its culture."
The park is located at the H853 Outdoor Event Space and will be managed by this association, starting the operation, still experimental, from Saturday. According to a statement, this space is intended to become a "privileged destination for radical sports enthusiasts, further enriching Macao's sports and leisure offers."
It is understood that this initiative, linked to radical sports, “aligns with Macao's strategy vision of Turismo + Sports, promoting synergies between cultural tourism and various experiences”, and reinforces “Macao's appeal as a dynamic and multifaceted destination”.
The entity that will manage this park is a collective of four associations, namely the Macao Skate Development Association, the Macao Skate Exchange and Learning Association and the Macao Skate Association. With this inauguration, it is expected to "develop the practice of skateboarding and its growth, involving more enthusiasts of Macao," in order to "bring joy to Macao, whether the skateboard is a sport or a form of cultural expression."</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:39:25</pubDate></item><item><title>About 95% of the kidney patients receive free dialysis</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/cerca-de-95-dos-doentes-renais-recebem-dialise-gratuita/</link><description>From the universe of 990 patients who received dialysis treatments in Macao in 2023, "about 95 percent of patients are people who enjoy free health care or who are exempt from paying dialysis expenses due to medical care," said the director of health services (SS), alvis lo, in response to Ron Lam written interpellation.
Alvis Lo recalls that dialysis medical treatments are not free, but there is a medical assistance mechanism for patients with lower financial possessions, which requires the assets assessment of the household and income.
According to data advanced by the SS director, of the 990 patients who received dialysis treatment, only about 50 had to pay the costs.
In written interplies, Ron Lam indicated that the hemodialysis rate charged to Macao residents at the Conde de S. Januario hospital center is 700 patacas for each consultation and in private hospital reaches 2 or 3 thousand patacas. Values ​​that, given that hemodialysis is done three times a week, “is a great economic pressure” for patients and their families.
In addition, the deputy cited complaints of residents regarding the increase in rigor in the consideration of requests for exemption from treatment costs in recent years, although the law has not been amended. Ron Lam claims to have received requests for support from residents who did not receive medical assistance due to the “per capita” income and the patient's household heritage is higher than the economic deficiency criteria defined by the Institute of Social Action. The government did not respond to this claim of tightness of rigor in the consideration of requests for exemption.

Inner harvest
Regarding the possibility of kidney transplantation, Alvis Lo states that patients interested in kidney transplantation, after examinations, can be "sent to the medical units in the interior of China through the overseas medical services regime."
The intervention presupposes the registration of the state system of distribution and sharing of human organs and in a waiting list for transplants. In this respect, Deputy Ron Lam had stressed that those who submit to transplantation in the interior of China must “prepare to pay hundreds of thousands of patacas”, a situation that was not addressed by Alvis Lo.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:11:02</pubDate></item><item><title>Fire | Two fires take two women to the hospital</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/fogo-dois-incendios-levam-duas-mulheres-ao-hospital/</link><description>Yesterday's fires at Hoi Fu building and the Jardim Iat Lai building rose to six the number of fireworks in dwellings within one month. Women taken to the hospital were considered in a stable situation
 
Two women were transported yesterday to the hospital, following a fire that launched in the Hoi Fu building. This was one of yesterday's two fires in housing buildings that raised to six the number of occurrences within one month.
According to information from the Fire Department, quoted by the Chinese channel of Radio Macau, the origin of the flames will have been a short circuit in an air conditioner. None of the occupants of the house suffered serious injuries, but two women, 66 and 32, had to be transported to the hospital due to the inhalation of fumes.
In addition to the two wounded women, another 60 residents had to abandon the housing temporarily, having returned the house later. The fire, which took place on the 29th floor, caused large flames that were eventually extinguished by the firefighters.
After the intervention, the firefighters indicated that the whole apartment had smoke marks, although some divisions were affected more slightly.
Bend
In addition to the case in the Hoi Fu building, the Fire Department had to go into action around 9am at Toi San. According to the information available, he launched a fire in the Jardim Iat Lai building that made about 30 people had to temporarily abandon the dwellings.
Unlike the first occurrence of the morning, there was no need to transport any of the inhabitants of the building to the hospital, and the flames were extinguished by one of the administrators of the building. In this case, it is suspected of set fire, since traces of burnt papers were found on the seventh floor, near the place where the flames will have triggered.
In a reaction to the Hoi Fu building, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) indicated that it followed the first case with great attention and sent aid teams to the site. The occupants of the most affected apartment needed shelter. In addition, no more requests for assistance were registered.
In the case of Jardim IAT LAI building, IAS indicated that it has not received any request for help, although it is available to respond to any request.
In recent times, the territory has crossed a spot of fire in housing buildings, which has led some deputies, such as Lo Choi In and Si Ka Lon, to ask the authorities to adopt new security measures.
Lo Choi In, a deputy linked to the community of Jiangmen, was concerned about the fact that in the fire of the Lake building the alarm did not work. In turn, Si Ka Lon appealed to the government to consider the hypothesis of funding the use of natural gas by supporting the installation in local buildings of distribution pipes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:51:40</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club | Aborted plan to send 100 cats to zhuhai</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/jockey-club-abortado-plano-para-enviar-100-gatos-para-zhuhai/</link><description>Macau Jockey Club intended to send 100 cats to Zhuhai, but aborted the plan after being pressured by citizens and animal protection associations
 
Macau Jockey Club and the Municipal Institute for Affairs (AMI) have canceled a plan to send about 100 cats to Zhuhai to a destination that the authorities did not want to reveal.
The controversy snapped at the end of Thursday, when the information began to circulate that about 100 cats, raised at Macau Jockey Club, would be sent to Zhuhai the next afternoon. However, the lack of guarantees on animal safety has led several citizens and animal protection associations to mobilize online, but also through Hong Kong communication agencies, to prevent the outcome that was tragic for the animals.
At the same time, accusations also began to emerge that Macau Jockey Club had promoted a "facade" adoption campaign with little promotion, only for two days, which only resulted in four adoptions. In addition, the institution will have refused that some citizens and animal protection associations would be with various cats, justifying that there would be no more animals for adoption.
Given the growing public criticism, on Friday morning, AMI issued a statement to defend Macau Jockey Club and ensuring that Zhuhai was able to receive the animals. However, AMI never identified where the cats would be taken. "Given the welfare of the animals, AMI is pleased with the sterilization of cats by Macau Jockey Club and with the measures taken," he was nominated. “This institute recently proceeded to the health inspection of these cats, including the introduction of microchips, anti-rabies vaccination and clinical examination. AMI will issue the necessary sanitary documents for the border passage of exported cats, in strict compliance with national provisions, providing support in the border passage, ”he was added.
The institute led by Chao Wai Ieng also defended the Jockey Club by ensuring that he had resorted to "several channels for some cats to be adopted by their workers and the public."
After all there was another
With the controversy to gain traction not only in Macau, but also in Hong Kong, Mary Jean Reimer, actress, lawyer and activist for the rights of Hong Kong animals, has been available to adopt all animals.
Reimer, who is married to Sean Hotung, from the famous Hotung family, also presented a plan to take cats to a terrain in the countryside, where the safety of animals guaranteed.
By this time, also Zoe Tang, president of Anima, revealed in statements to the All About Macau portal that was trying to contact the Jockey Club and owner and deputy Angela Leong to prevent the outcome, though to no avail. The anima was also receptive to stay with the animals until it could carry out more adoption campaigns.
In various online animal defense groups of Macao, Angela Leong was also the target of various criticisms, with accusations that she had not learned anything about how she had dealt with the 500 Galids in the canhy, which ended up abandoned on the spot, with local associations, as they would promote international adoption campaigns.
Final change
As a result of controversy and displeasure at the attitude of the authorities, around 5:30 pm, Macau Jockey Club announced that it has canceled the animals to Zhuhai, with about 60 felines to be sent to other associations.
In a statement, the company also underlined “respecting and valuing the concerns and opinions of animal protection groups” and that would promote an adoption campaign with Anima. Macau Jockey Club also highlighted fulfilling “their social responsibilities”.
In addition, a new adoption campaign was organized, in partnership with Anima, which took place yesterday and which made about 30 cats for adoption. In case they are not all adopted, the campaign continues next weekend.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:49:23</pubDate></item><item><title>Explosion | Taiwan reveals girl death in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/explosao-taiwan-revela-morte-de-menina-ocorrida-em-macau/</link><description>Information on the death of the two -year -old girl in Macao was only confirmed by health services (SS), after being revealed firsthand by the media of the former Formosa. SS consider that they have met the “all needs” of the victim and family in a timely manner
 
The two -year -old girl passed away who had been hit by debris projected by an explosion in Taiwan. Although the death happened on Friday at the Conde São Januário Hospital Center, the information was released on Wednesday night by the Taiwan media.
The case dates back to February 13, when a family with seven macao elements was touring Taichung and was hit by several objects projected to the street due to an explosion on the 12th floor of a shopping center. That day, two residents were declared dead, the family grandparents of the family. However, the two -year -old girl, granddaughter of the other deadly victims, stood in a coma, with brain injuries, linked to the machine and fighting for life.
The girl was transported to Macao on February 26, always remaining in a coma, and hospitalized at the Conde São Januário Hospital Center. On Friday night, March 7, it died. The information was communicated to Taiwan's media by the man who on the day of the accident helped transport the urgent girl to the hospital.
However, death information was not communicated in Macau. The information was only made public, then news has been advanced by the Taiwan media, where the case is still being investigated and promises many developments, because of the need to determine responsibilities about the accident and paid compensation to the victims' families. From the accident, with regard to victims of Macao, four other injuries were resulted in no problem.
Behind the injury
With the information of Taiwan's social communication agencies to be released on social networks, and reaching some local media agencies, health services ended up issuing a statement at dawn on Thursday in Chinese. The information in Portuguese was only made available in the morning.
"Health services reported that, after obtaining the consent of the family, it was now announced that the girl from Macao who was injured in the previous explosion of gas in Taichung died at Conde de S. Januario Hospital on the 7th of this month," was confirmed.
The authorities also defended the quality of services provided to the victim and family: “Health services expressed deep regret for the girl's death and presented the deepest condolences to her family, emotional support and care services to family members were also provided and their needs in time,” he was added.
Online criticism
With the news of the death by Taiwan's communication agencies, several online comments emerged to regret the succeeded and wish the condolences to the family.
However, the posture of Macau's government and social communication agencies was also the target of various criticisms, given the misunderstanding of the fact of the outcome of this case, which was highly media, was only known through the Taiwan media organs.
In some of the most popular conversation groups of the territory in traditional Chinese, the lack of transparency of the Government of Masters was lamented and the willingness of the media to report events outside the government agenda.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:24:47</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal | Work vacancies at Shake Shack and Barbie Love</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/dsal-vagas-de-trabalho-no-shake-shack-e-barbie-love/</link><description>The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) will organize three sessions of jobs, providing a total of 224 vacancies, on March 20, 21 and 24, to restoration sectors, retail trade and supermarkets, building administration and cleaning.
According to a statement released yesterday by DSAL, registrations for the three sessions open today and interested parties can apply on the Dsal website until noon of 19 March.
The first session is scheduled for the morning of March 20, with the offer of 80 vacancies to work at Shake Shack restaurants and Yum Cha Success, on Rua da Cantão, for the duties of store head, cook, cook assistant and restoration employee. On the afternoon of the same day, 14 vacancies will be available for store chief, seller and warehouse employee at two sports clothing stores.
On the morning of the next day, it will be the turn of the building administration and cleaning sectors, with 83 vacancies for customer service supervisor, building facilities maintenance officer, doorman, street sweeper and garbage collection worker.
On the morning of March 24, 47 vacancies will be offered to work at the “Barbie Love” supermarkets and the “San Fa Seng Supermarket” for the functions of cashier, shelves, warehouse employee, fruit and vegetables and meat cutter. The three sessions will take place at the Faom building, at Ribeira do Patane Street No. 2-6.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:22:28</pubDate></item><item><title>FUELS | New team to control prices</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/combustiveis-pedida-nova-equipa-para-controlar-precos/</link><description>The Power of the People's Association, chaired by Lam Weng Ioi, says that oil -derived products and services are excessive prices in the territory and calls for serious supervision by authorities
 
The Power of the People's Association defends the creation of a working group to control price fluctuations linked to oil -derived products in Macao. The position was taken by President Lam Weng Ioi, through a letter delivered to the executive headquarters.
According to the message released yesterday, the association considers it "evident" that prices need to be regulated because they "keep" always "very high", with an average of over 14 patacas per liter of gasoline, although the price of Crude suffers several fluctuations.
From the perspective of the association directed by LAM, the need for supervision becomes even clearer, when the prices practiced are very similar to those charged at other times when the price of oil was much higher. "Increasing prices of these first -need goods is invariably to increase population charges," he is argued.
Therefore, the Power of the People's Association suggests a group to “monitor and control the prices” of oil derivatives, and especially those of goods or services with the highest impact on the life of the population, such as the price of fuel, transport, communications and electricity. “Relevant companies must be subject to licensing and supervision,” was nominated.
The Association also indicates that companies "exploring public services must be required to disclose prices and limit their profits, and their financial data should be audited and published." "The government should evaluate the prices and operational performance of the companies in question and regularly review licenses, as well as introduce more competitors through regular public tenders," he was added.
Eternal struggle
Also in the letter the association is insisted on one of its main flags, the control of issuing authorizations for non -resident workers.
"According to the complaints of our members, some companies controlled or supervised by public services, such as parking parks or other services subcontracted by public services, are full of non -resident workers, for work such as cleaning, condominium management and even engineering," he was nominated.
"We do not support the discrimination of non -resident workers, but the government should take the initiative to encourage these companies to hire more resident workers, especially in the current economic situation," he was stressed. "The priority of local workers in access to employment should not just be an empty slogan," was concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:17:05</pubDate></item><item><title>Flora Garden | Ice rink completed this month</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/jardim-da-flora-pista-de-gelo-concluida-este-mes/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) has revealed that the construction works of an ice rink for children in the garden of Flora will be completed this month. The revelation was made during a colloquium on community matters in the parish of São Lázaro, on Wednesday.
According to the newspaper or Mun, AMI representatives explained that before being an ice rink, the place was a maze with plants. As this space was damaged by the sun and heavy rains, while other buildings prevented the construction of shelters for the vegetation, AMI decided to install a 450 square meter ice rink.
The AMI representatives also explained that in the current phase they are still correcting some defects in the works and that at a later stage, when safety is guaranteed, the track will be open to the public.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:14:03</pubDate></item><item><title>Zelensky vs Zelensky</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/31/zelensky-vs-zelensky/</link><description>10/27/22
A renovated Ukrainian, with the same name of the president, guilty Zelensky about the extension of the conflict that destroyed his village. Zelensky, the village, who has never left his land, now lives mortified because his favorite gravedigger died in the bomber.
This Zelensky, the village, represents half the world that reproves the other Zelensky, the villain, for not wanting to negotiate with Putin.
Negotiate what? The invader enters us through the house, pies us the wife and daughter (cf. recent UN report on Ukraine violations in this “special operation”), an act that forced us to watch, and then we say: Alto there, we are for peace, but we have to negotiate: You have not said the name you want to give to children!
A peace that is not worthy is but a cessation of rights. As severe as Russophobia that Putin inflicts his people.
 
10/28/22
In a lunch with several guests I hear a friend, who declares himself a spiritist, explaining about the particularities of his belief, in a serene and balanced way, would even say, without "irrationalism". He discussed long and serenely, devoid of any fanatical proselytizing. “Here is someone to whom belief brought weighting!” I thought, a rare alliance.
However, at one point a phrase that horrify me. He says, “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!” And I enter the voracious fauces of holism. Because holismo has a pathological aspect like all good things, a side of shadow.
Two examples: In Hinduism there is less sensitivity to existential dramas, if that child suffers in this life this is only an expression of the strict karmic symmetry, an effect of the acts she committed in her previous life. In Africa it is not accepted that death may have been accidental, and many women are accused by the dead family of having caused her husband's death, in an act of manifest dementia, and, in the blatant majority of cases, in a huge injustice to his wife - madness that spreads and infiltrates the social fabric.
Buddhism has introduced compassion and Christianity to Caritas, trying to break with this logic, but in many other beliefs and religions the cage of causalities prevails over sensitivity to experience, the need to respond to the now.
It is a tremendous logic that transforms the world into a platonic stage, where we are just the shadows of something -an inextricable law -in a determinism that calcines all singularities, but strangely fascinates many.
The conquest of modernity has anchored in the conquest of chance and random, subtracting the incidences of a life to this fierce determinism that closed the world in a web. When the Renaissance freed the body from the influence of the stars, at this moment sexuality was relieved of guilt and individualism and their volition could emerge.
There is an unequivocal moral implication in the phrase “There is no chance, nothing happens by chance!”, Which should work as a key to self-knowledge and self-judgment, but usually this phrase is managed to seek a reason for things abroad from us in the other. It is an alibi.
There is a holistic temptation in the world today, as in the Middle Ages there was a satanic temptation, without great reflection on its consequences. Because it is not enough we want to connect everything in a resonant chain of affection. Even the most unexpected: affection itself can kill.
I realize, thanks to this cultured, balanced, intelligent woman, that “the combat” moved at the beginning of this century. One of the great misconceptions of the twentieth century was the false dichotomy between "rationalism and irrationalism", a debate that extended to all fields, including art. First, rationality was confused (the positive side of reason) with rationalism (the pathological feature of reason), and articulated in this lack of discernment was confused irrationalism with freedom. Almost all the art of the twentieth century, with surrealism to the head, worked in this error. The fallacy still exists despite having consolidated the emergence of 'irrationalism' and the consequent relativist currents that followed it. Essentially much of what happened in the twentieth century, it turned around this shock between two paradigms: rationalism versus irrationalism.
Now, I see, the indetermination, chance, the random of the terrible temptation of the causal cage. Holism, in its pathological feature, can be the reductionism that is the way it puts the way as a new 'eschatological narrative'.
Is it "by chance" that the holism emerges at the moment when neo-liberalism and its cynical contempt for the human person besides all freedoms, all acquired rights?
Holistic consciousness has brought positively a greater ecological awareness but followed by scholastic rigor drifting reality under the blanket of a determinism that is much more than inconvenience: all great authoritarian ideologies are holistic.
My friend will know how to combine her holistic and transpersonal belief with the freedom and responsibility that every moment asks us - but how many will make the destruction, under a law that explains and encompasses everything?
How many will not be abandoned to what it is?
The awareness of the indeterminate brings tragic conscience, as the Greeks knew, but also brings the will and the courage of the decision. And of this we cannot abdicate.
In addition, as Drummond shows in Carlos Drummond de Andrade's poem “Quadrilha”:
"John loved Teresa who loved Raimundo/ who loved Maria who loved Joaquim who loved Lili/ who did not love anyone./ John went to the United States, Teresa to the convent,/ Raimundo died of disaster, Maria stayed to aunt,/ Joaquim suicide himself and Lili married J. Pinto Fernandes/ who had not entered the story."
Real always runs outside the track, in full exteriority to our concepts. This is what is worth a J. Pinto Fernandes at the exact moment we thought we had everything under control.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Nobel and others</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/10/17/do-nobel-e-outros/</link><description>9/10/22
Reading many people's reactions when the Nobel Prize in this year's literature was announced, I couldn't help but remind me of this repair of Jean-Pierre Siméon, in relation to another Nobel Prize: “An editor of a large national newspaper wrote five lines of indignation because the Nobel Prize for Literature, a complete stranger. But unknown to whom? How did not occur to this patented and paid literary columnist to do his work, that his apparent ignorance was a matter of incorrect professional conduct? Tranströmer was translated into many languages, it was available in French. »
There is always the choir of those who wait for the announcement of the prize to complain about not being invited to the jury of the prize, there is a subgroup of Irados that professes “never read and I will not bother to read”; It is an uncommon fauna, which inhabits social networks.
I don't always know all the winners-I was unaware of the existence of Louise Glück, who I find a great poet, or the Olga Tokarczuk, for example-but it only brings me the comfort of knowing that the world is not a soap opera where everyone knows each other and the joy of recognizing that the gauge of the world is not measured with my short measure and that on the contrary it gives me a new opportunity to face the unknown.
And perhaps the most cretin of reactions was the smart one who wrote, but there are still those who read French? Confirming only that today there is a new kind of ignorance that fires with a displeasure: the one who only read English.
I would also prefer that, in French, Pascal Quignard, Linda reads, or even Sollers, or, among the new ones, Mathias is awarded, but that does not take dignity to the work of Annie Ernaux (and it would be enough to have written the “Les Années”). There are books of her that I like less, like the vulgar "a simple passion," but this happens with almost every authors, they have a channel books and others that are like intervals in their itinerary. I advise reading a beautiful book of interviews with her, "L'Ecriture Comme un couteau".
11/10/22
Yesterday came an article in Maputo's morning “News”, realizing that the Pen Club narrative prize was assigned to my wife, Teresa Noronha, for her soap opera “Tornado”, which had already had the Maria Velho da Costa award.
The summary they made of the book does not even deserve comments, by pathetic, but what matters to highlight is the note of disqualification about their "Mozambicanity" by calling it Luso-Mozambican. It is not inaccurate, but for those who know the context, it is a dirty touch.
Because finally, following the same logic, Adelino Timóteo should be called Tsonga-Mozambican, to Álvaro Taruma-Mozambican, and Macua-Mozambican to the writers who are from the north, etc., etc. Which is not reported to happen.
At the beyond moment, in the soap opera, she writes:
«Our color has never been dominant. In colonial time we were not white, we were ripped from monories, gone mugs, the pejorative term to speak of a son of Goes and Portuguese. In the postcolonial period, I was not black and if, in Lisbon, they took me by Brazilian or Cape Verdean, already in France were lost in cogitations of where they would be and amazed when they found out it was African. There I had to explain my DNA's wanderings before relying on moorms. It took me a long time to accept that it was so because yes, and that it was no curse that were so; On the contrary, I could even discover intense patterns of fantasy and freedom in this shrewd cloak that is our genealogy… »
In the current Mozambique it is white… and this is overlapping it soon to what it does or what it is.
It is sad, but as Naipaul warned, through these stops the race is everything and is soaked in it as deeply as, elsewhere, in religion.
12/10/22
Bruno Latour, an anthropologist who studied the sciences and their procedures and legitimations, law, technique and religions died and entertained themselves to turn the guts to the dogmas of the “modern”. For him the place, the expert's function, was more defined by the perplexity he embodied than for the supposed truth he would support him.
He proposed, as an alternative to the kinds of multiculturalism and his mistaken password "all different all the same", the return to "diplomacy", given precisely, not from the presupposition that "we are unified because participants of the same nature" but simply reveal that we "do not yet share an ordinary world"; It is necessary to deal frontally with the "abyss of disagreement" that separates us, rather than wanting to delude it.
And about politics said, disassessedly:
«If transparency is required from the politician, we kill him; If one requires fidelity to what the other was or he says, kills him; If a mimetic relationship is required between what the crowd wants and what its representative says, the representation is killed. These must, therefore, by definition, betray, deceive, modify, distort the word. Without this ability to double the word and betray, political language would not exist. I put the perfectly plausible hypothesis that political vocabulary will become as inaccessible as the religious language of the last twenty, three or fifty years. (in “UN Monde Pluriel plus Commun”). I believe it will be missed to decipher this frantically complex world that fit us.</description><pubDate>2022-10-17 02:18:03</pubDate></item><item><title>The yo -yo</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/30/o-fuxi/</link><description>O my friends, companions of these funerals trips to countries as old as the stars and the moon, and as strange as the profound interior of our disgraceful souls, - that startle still awaits us, what secret spells we will have to overcome, what horrors will rise to our dilated pupils of amazement and terror?
Increasingly close to our precarious existences, howling the war monster, which threatens to merge humanity with the earth, incessantly traveled by the squalid spectrum of hunger and the invisible evil of ten thousand pests.
O human human, who cries superior to his own nature, but then reveals to you, once and again, unable to simply order your existence and do not understand that you are possessed by the fickle wrath and are slave to your own ambition! Do not be content with the white jade or the light gold, there is no treasure that gives you your inextinguishable thirst for other men, animals and things; for in you an eternal anguish in you; in you crawl the expelled snakes; For you grows, powerful and impossible, the very fertile ivy of evil!
This is perhaps why on the mound they call the white deer, where one of the eight immortals in sacred mount was evolved through the skies to Penglai, inhabits the fuxa, a bird whose form resembles that of the rooster, although topped by a human head. What strange copulas, what monstrous amplexes, what terrible procedures will have occurred to make the existence of this animal sinister possible? We do not know, but it is enough for our exhausted mind to dare to raise an answer, so we soon feel the skin traveled by horrendous goose bumps and the heart trigger in paraded, which wild horse beaten by the night whip of fear, oblivious to reins and containment.
May men refrain from going through the Mount of the deer, because although there are riches capable of calming the most misunderstanding ambitions, if they have the disgraced fortunate to glimpse a fuxa, it will be immediately triggered the cultivated fields, because it will be beheaded the soft animals, for it will be sacrificed the best young man and destroyed superb from countries.
Fuxi emits a sound that resembles its name. If you hear it, dark night or clear day, goose way, for the path where you find you is the most right of the ways for misfortune!</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Procrastinators Club</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2022/09/29/clube-dos-procrastinadores/</link><description>Walking in rereading of Easter, because of an article I prepare, I give this excerpt, extracted from “the universal man”:
«Every man morally is one and absolute; But you have to live with your personality to mitigate. (…) Coexistence is only possible among people reduced to a negative or hollow presence, which is constantly giving in. Hence, the emptiness of society, a huge ghost composed of numerous deceased. An upper man is antisocial or criminal. Its destination is jail and desert.
He is in thinking about whether she reflects here about the political-social conditioning that gagging, and worse, in a sad country as Portugal was in the middle of the Estado Novo (and the book is from 1931) where any possibilities of spontaneity and frankness in human relations were coarcet, or only lends the behavior of men (oppressed) a metaphysical frame, a “essence”, from a presumption of each one in the presumption of each one be in isolation “one and absolute”. Sometimes, to an excess of spirituality (or longing), it adds to Pascoaes to lack the world. He is a great poet, but he is a poet who takes gray-Jewish ampoules and is therefore written amiiude on a programmatic furor, ceasing to have pores; There is often a glass between him and the real, the same one who made him wring the Ballet, 1921: “Everything is ghost. There are only clouds, clouds of voices, clouds of souls, afflictions and tragedies! Clouds and more clouds, appearances and more appearances! It is a divine lightning that pierces them, the instant appearance that arises and throws us to the ground, dazzled! »
Sometimes I would like to remind him, as Antonio Sérgio did in the article “Regeneration and Tradition, Moral and Economy”, which dedicated to Easter: “Easter, Easter my dear friend: You are a pure, excellent and noble poet, but also a victim of this social environment, like us all: this horrible isolation that you praise and I”.
"As a child, he stole two melos," says Jacinto do Prado Coelho, stole him from a nest, and throb his lifetime remorse for it. The person, few more mischief is known to him. Only in Álvaro de Campos sprouts a twinge of evil and obscenity: “Oh, and ordinary and dirty people who always seem the same,/ who employs profanity as usual words,/ whose children steal at the grocery door/ and whose daughters at eight years-and I think this is beautiful and I love him! -/ masturbate decent -looking men on the stairs. » (Ode triumphal).
Both poets beaten by a certain idea of ​​holiness, they were identical to the inability of breaking the siege of the skin with the overflow of the dike, the same curse of sublimating Eros's concrete ferocity with the mansuity of the verses.
Of course, they are the two "Bigger Than Life", but sometimes unnerves to watch, from my hostor's post at the Procrastinators Club, to the tantrums between them, just to see who occupies, in the internal organization, the place of president and treasurer.
Although a person has guessed more, for example, this he wrote in the least known martial ode and that is declining in the situation we live today, differently, with the heart in his hands:
«Ode martial
(…)
Helahoho! Helahoho!
The sewing machine of the poor widow killed to the bayonet…
She sews in the afternoon indeterminate ...
The table where the old people played,
All mixed, all mixed with bodies, with blood,
All one river, one wave, one dragged horror.
Helahoho! Helahoho!
I dug up the child's can train based in the middle of the
[road,
And I cried like all the mothers in the world about the horror of life.
My pantheistic feet stumbled on the sewing machine
[Widow who killed the bayonet
And this poor instrument of peace put a spear in my heart.
Yes, I was to blame for everything, I was the soldier all
That killed, violated, burned and broke,
It was me and my shame and my remorse as a shadow
[MISSFORMA
Walk around the world like Ashavero,
But behind my steps sounds steps the size of infinity
And a physical dread of accounting for God makes me close the
[Eyes suddenly.
(…)
I sent, captain, to shoot the trembling peasants,
I let the daughters of all parents tied to trees,
Now I saw that it was inside my heart that all this happened,
And all scald and suffocate and I can't move without
[Everything is the same.
God have mercy on me that I had no one!
Là-bas, je ne sais où… »
What is clear today, at this disastrous moment when Cristiano &amp; Company failed in their mission in Braga, and where the self-sabotage of Russia pipelines recalls that Putin will even be willing to maintain dominion over referendum zones,
It is that, pump per bomb, the “bomb” of the fifth empire was preferable.
However, even in this, my dear, we were irresolution, a little more for the pielas than to the determined, and procrastinated.</description><pubDate>2022-09-29 02:34:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Manila | Hundreds manifest themselves in support of former President Duterte</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/manila-centenas-manifestam-se-em-apoio-ao-ex-presidente-duterte/</link><description>Hundreds of people manifested Saturday in the capital of the Philippines, Manila, to demonstrate support to former President Rodrigo Duterte, accused of crimes against humanity by the bloody anti-drug campaign they led. Duterte was arrested on Tuesday in the Philippines by the local authorities and, hours later, was sent to The Hague in the Netherlands, where he attended Friday before the Judges of the International Criminal Court.
“Bring him back” and “We supported President Rodrigo Duterte” were some of the most repeated phrases during the demonstration, which began with a prayer for the health of the former 79-year-old president.
During the presidency of Duterte, between 2016 and 2022, about 6,000 people were murdered in anti -drug operations and extrajudicial executions, police data. However, the estimates are contested by local non-governmental organizations that claim operations culminated in the deaths of more than 30,000 people.
The former president was arrested following a warrant captured from the International Criminal Court. The court considers Duterte responsible for humanity crimes and says there are “reasonable reasons” to believe that he led a death squad and used his power to carry out extrajudicial executions.
The Court's investigation into extrajudicial executions began in 2018 and, by 2021, the authorities and security forces were associated with the crimes committed, although Duterte removed the country from the organization in 2019 in an attempt not to be implied.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 01:01:01</pubDate></item><item><title>Bangkok | Self -established collapse under construction causes five dead</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/banguecoque-derrocada-de-autoestrada-em-construcao-causa-cinco-mortos/</link><description>At least five people died, two remaining missing and 27 were injured on Saturday after the collapse of a high freeway, under construction south of Bangcoque, the authorities said.
The incident occurred in the district of Chom Thong, around 2:00, when the iron and concrete structure collapsed, at a time when a group of more than 20 workers was in the area.
Photographs published on social networks by the Municipal Council of Bangcoque and the Department of Public Relations of Samut Sakhon province, where the project is being carried out, show a pile of rubble due to the fall of beams and pillars.
The Department of Prevention and Mitigation of Thai disasters observed in a statement that this is the eighth accident resulting from the construction of this infrastructure, including the fall of a horizontal crane in November, which made six dead.
In June 2023, two people died and several were injured when a construction bridge collapsed over several cars that passed, in another accident related to the same project, which started in 2022.
Transport Minister Suriya Jungrunggreangkit ordered an investigation into Saturday's incident to avoid further deaths. Construction accidents are common in Thailand due to the poor application of safety standards and the use of unqualified personnel.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:59:36</pubDate></item><item><title>Seoul | Thousands manifest themselves and against Yoon Suk Yeol</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/seul-milhares-manifestam-se-pro-e-contra-yoon-suk-yeol/</link><description>The dismissal of the former South Korean President, after his announcement of martial law and subsequent detention, has generated rides of assembling in the Asian country society
 
Thousands of South Koreans filled on Saturday the streets of downtown Seoul in major demonstrations in favor and against South Korea's deprived president Yoon Suk Yeol, without registered incidents. The demonstrations occur at a time when the South Korean Constitutional Court will decide next week about the formal dismissal of Yoon's position due to the imposition of martial law in December 2024.
Turning tracks and posters that demand the dismissal of the conservative president, large multitudes of anti-Yoon protesters filled the streets near the court, where police had recently reinforced security in anticipation of the expected decision next week.
Yoon's supporters gathered on nearby streets, shaking South Korean and American flags, and appealing to the return of their hero, whose mischievous power took memories of the military dictatorships in the 1980s.
Police sent thousands of agents to maintain security and there were no immediate reports of large clashes or injured. The organizers of the anti-Yoon protests estimated the influx of 1.1 million people, while police estimated that the number of participants was in tens of thousands.
Marching towards the streets near the court, the protesters sang and sang slogans demanding Yoon's dismissal and arrest because of the imposition of short -time martial law on December 3.
Yoon's powers were suspended after the opposition -controlled National Assembly, dismissed it 11 days later, on the 14th. "We can't wait for a single day," said one of the protest leaders on stage. "This is the order of our citizens - the Constitutional Court must immediately remove Yoon Suk Yeol, the leader of the rebellion!"
Divided country
For Yoon to be formally removed from office, at least six of the eight judges in the Constitutional Court have to approve the motion of dismissal approved by the deputies. If they do not, Yoon's presidential powers will be immediately restored.
Chung Sung-Il, a 72-year-old anti-Yonon, said he expected the court to depart Yoon, "100 percent." "If he is reinstated, many dangerous things can happen," he warned.
Pró-Yoon demonstrations were attended by members of the conservative popular power party, including Yoon Sang-Hyun, deputy in the last five terms, who defended the imposition of martial law by the president as an attempt to lock the “legislative dictatorship” of the liberals, which obstructed their agenda with the majority in the assembly.
The crowd repeatedly sang the name of Yoon Suk Yeol and grasped posters where they read the National Assembly. ” "President Yoon has declared the martial law to protect South Free and Democratic Korea," said Jin Woo-chan, a 20-year-old Yoon supporter.
Yoon argued that the martial decree was necessary to overcome the “anti-state” liberal opposition, which, he said, improperly used the legislative majority to block his agenda.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:58:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Ia | Baidu launches free models to compete with DeepSeek</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/ia-baidu-lanca-modelos-gratuitos-para-competir-com-deepseek/</link><description>Chinese Internet giant Baidu yesterday launched two new free models of Generative Artificial Intelligence (AI), at a time of fierce competition in the sector. The announcement comes two months after Chinese startup DeepSeek shaken the technology world with powerful low -cost conversation robot to work with fewer resources.
In a Wechat social network publication, Baidu has announced that it launched the latest X1 reasoning model - that the company claims to offer DeepSek's performance, but at a lower cost - as well as a new base model, Ernie 4.5.
These tools, which are free and were released two weeks ahead of expected, are available through Baidu's conversation robot, Ernie Bot. So far, users had to pay a monthly subscription fee to access the latest AI models of the company.
Baidu was one of the first Chinese companies to implement a general AI platform in 2023, but the conversation robots of rival companies, such as Bytedance, owner of Tiktok, and Moonshot AI, quickly saturated the market. Deepseek, on the other hand, came to change the panorama, with a model as effective as Americans, such as chatgPT, but at a much lower development cost.
Chinese government companies and agencies were quick to integrate Deepseek software in the tools themselves, making it available to the public. Baidu, for example, integrated DeepSek's R1 reasoning model with the traditional search engine.
In February, Tencent, owner of Wechat, also launched a new AI model that claims to respond to queries faster than DeepSeek, while using rival technology for the messaging platform.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:56:51</pubDate></item><item><title>Iran | Nuclear question in a “critical moment”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/irao-questao-nuclear-num-momento-critico/</link><description>At the end of a meeting in Beijing who brought together high representatives of China, Russia and Iran, Chinese foreign minister Wang Yi emphasized the determining moment that will cross the new US pressures.
 
China's Foreign Minister Wang Yi said on Friday that the Iranian nuclear issue reached a "critical moment" at the end of a tripartite meeting between China, Russia and Iran in Beijing.
"The international agreement on the Iranian nuclear issue was an important achievement achieved through dialogue and negotiation," said Wang Yi, quoted by the official newspaper China Daily, adding that the "situation has once again reached a critical moment."
Wang presented the five-point position of China to resolve the Iranian nuclear question during talks with Russian Foreign Deputy Minister Ryabkov Sergey Alexeevich, and Iranian Foreign Minister Kazem Gharibabadi, who are in Beijing, for a tripartite meeting.
"All parties should defend the vision of common, comprehensive, cooperative and sustainable security, actively create conditions for reacting dialogue and negotiations and avoid actions that cause a climb of tensions," he said.
Chinese diplomacy chief stated that Iran should continue to join their commitment not to develop nuclear weapons, while all parties must fully respect the right to Iran, as a signatory to the non -proliferation of nuclear weapons, to the peaceful use of nuclear power.
Iran signed a nuclear agreement, formally known as the Global Joint Action Plan (PACG) in July 2015, with six countries -Britain, China, France, Germany, Russia and the United States -, accepting restrictions on its nuclear program in exchange for relief from sanctions.
The US withdrew from the agreement in May 2018 and restored the sanctions. During the meeting, Wang called for a new consensus based on the PACG framework and expressed the hope that all parties will advance in the same direction and resume dialogue and negotiations as soon as possible.
The US must demonstrate political sincerity and return to conversations as soon as possible, he argued.
Washington last Thursday imposed new sanctions against Iranian Oil Minister Mohsen Paknejad, entities that sold Iranian Crude to China and ships involved in transfers of oil beyond foil (‘offshore’).
At Friday's trilateral meeting, the deputy ministers also stressed the importance of respecting the UN Security Council Resolution 2231, which consecrated the 2015 nuclear agreement with Tehran, as well as its "calendar." China and Russia greeted "reaffirmation by the peaceful nature of their nuclear program and the fact that it refrains from developing nuclear weapons," according to Xinhua.
They also praised “Iran's commitment to fully fulfill the obligations of the treaty” and expressed their support for Iran's “Cooperation Policy with the International Atomic Energy Agency (AIEA)”.
Mutual respect
Trilateral dialogue occurs in a period of growing tensions with Washington, which reactivated its “maximum pressure” policy over Iran, with new sanctions designed to reduce oil sales.
US President Donald Trump said earlier this month that he sent a letter to Tehran asking for the restart of negotiations, although the Iranian Supreme Leader, Ali Khamenei, rejected any dialogue with "arrogant countries."
Iranian Foreign Minister Abbas Araqchi has reaffirmed that they will “not negotiate under pressure or intimidation” and will only consider an agreement “based on mutual respect”. Iran has maintained conversations in Geneva with Germany, France and the United Kingdom, but without significant progress.
China and Russia are trying to consolidate themselves as mediators in a process where the West has hardened their pressure. Beijing reinforced his cooperation with Tehran at commercial and energetic level, while Moscow is a fundamental ally of the Persian country at the international scene.
The AIEA confirmed, however, that Tehran has accumulated 274 kilos of uranium enriched at 60 percent, approaching the threshold for military use. Tehran will have significantly accelerated its nuclear program in recent months, quadrupling its uranium enrichment rate to 60 percent and reducing cooperation with agency inspectors.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:55:39</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan | Actions register record sales abroad with falling TSMC</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/taiwan-accoes-registam-recorde-de-vendas-no-estrangeiro-com-queda-da-tsmc/</link><description>The actions of Taiwanese companies suffered the largest escape from foreign investors due to the alienation of Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company (TSMC), the largest semiconductor manufacturer in the world, Bloomberg said yesterday.
According to data from the scholarship market compiled by the news agency, global funds have reduced their positions in the last 12 sessions on the island's scholarship market, disintelating in the net value of 391 billion Taiwanese dollars since Wednesday.
TSMC, which represents more than a third of the weight of the Taiwanese scholarship market reference index, fell almost 10 percent during this period, as foreign investors sold 155 million actions, according to Bloomberg.
The Taiwan scholarship market was dragged by the global fall of semiconductor manufacturers' actions this year, due to concerns about the high appreciation of the sector and the appearance of DeepSek, one of China's most advanced artificial intelligence applications, Bloomberg explained.
TSMC, which recorded revenues equivalent to 15,500 million euros in the first two months of the year, 39.2 percent than in the same period of 2024, down 0.4 percent at the same time, after closed 1.75 percent the day before.
Headquarters of the world's largest semiconductor manufacturer (TSMC) and the world's largest technology automaker (Foxconn), Taiwan has benefited strongly from the growth of artificial intelligence and high performance computing, thanks to the good relationship between island companies and sector leaders such as Nvidia and AMD.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:32:31</pubDate></item><item><title>Teaching / AI | Courses in Beijing's primary and secondary schools later this year</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/ensino-ia-cursos-nas-escolas-primarias-e-secundarias-de-pequim-ainda-este-ano/</link><description>Since the second half of 2025, all Beijing primary and secondary schools will offer general artificial intelligence courses (AI) with a workload of at least 8 hours a year, according to the Plan for Promotion of Artificial Intelligence Education in Primary and Secondary Schools (2025-2027), recently released by the Municipal Beijing Education Commission, the People's Diary indicates.
The curriculum will cover all stages of education, from elementary school to high school, and aims to strengthen students' abilities in this key area. Schools will have the flexibility to create AI autonomous courses or combine them with other subjects, such as information technology, science, practical activities and work education, adds the publication.
In addition, under the program, the Chinese capital plans to train one hundred specialized teachers and a thousand prominent specialized teachers in AI teaching.
The initiative is part of Beijing's broader effort to accelerate the construction of an IA educational system with characteristics of the capital and, at the same time, promote the reform and development of basic education. Focusing on six key areas of AI application, including teaching, learning, promotion, evaluation, research and administration, the city will explore new AI application scenarios.
This ambitious plan puts Beijing as a pioneer in the integration of AI in education, to prepare students to navigate the digital world while using technology responsibly.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:31:10</pubDate></item><item><title>Oman's Gulf | China, Russia and will complete exercises</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/14/golfo-de-oma-china-russia-e-irao-completam-exercicios/</link><description>The Marinhas of the Three Nations carried out simulations of salvage of kidnapped vessels to reinforce the fighting capacity against maritime terrorism and piracy
 
China, Iran and Russia yesterday concluded a series of maritime exercises in the context of joint maneuvers near the Iranian port of Chabahar, in Oman's Gulf. According to the Chinese official press, the three sea simulated hijacked commercial ships rescue operations, with the aim of "strengthening the naval capacities of the three countries to cope with security threats."
The operation took place in a region near Chabahar Port and included attacks on maritime targets, approach and damage control, as well as joint search and rescue operations.
According to Chinese state television CCTV, the exercises included heavy machine gun shots at maritime targets, targeting nighttime training and hijacked simulated commercial vessels.
Quoted by Global Times official newspaper Zhang Junshe, an expert on Chinese military affairs, said the exercise focused on the fight against maritime terrorism and piracy. The exercises, nicknamed “Security Ties 2025”, aim to “deepen mutual military trust and pragmatic cooperation between the Armed Forces of participating countries,” the Chinese army said in a statement.
The story is repeated
The China Popular Liberation Army Navy (ELP) sent the Baotou Freemaker and the Gaoyouhu Supply Ship to participate in the exercises, detailed the same source.
The annual exercises were performed at a similar date in 2024, also in the waters of the Gulf of Oman, and involved Chinese forces with the Urumqi guided missile fidge, the Linyi missile frigate and the Dongotiasto Supply Ship.
Last year's exercise coincided with the Huthis rebels in Yemen against the Red Sea-parked US and British war ships to protect navigation on this strategic river way through which it is estimated to pass 15 percent from worldwide maritime trade.
This year's exercises coincide with a meeting in Beijing on Friday, between representatives from China, Russia and Iran on the Iranian nuclear question.</description><pubDate>2025-03-14 02:29:35</pubDate></item><item><title>USA | Japan regrets imposition of tariffs on steel</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/13/eua-japao-lamenta-imposicao-de-tarifas-sobre-o-aco/</link><description>Japan lamented yesterday to be the target of 25 -per cent customs tariffs on steel, imposed by the United States, warning that customs barriers may have a considerable impact on economic connections.
Tokyo government spokesman Yoshimasa Hayashi said it was “unfortunate” that Japan has not achieved exemption from steel and aluminum, in force since yesterday, marking a new stage in the United States and the main commercial partners.
In addition to Japan, European Union, Canada, China and Australia are affected by this measure, and the statement's declared goal, Donald Trump, is protecting US steel industry, which has seen production decrease from year to an increasingly strong competition from Asia (see page 11).
The United States imports about half of the steel and aluminum used in the country, for sectors as varied as the automotive and aeronautical industries, petrochemicals and basic consumption products, such as canned ones.
Hayashi also said that Japanese steel and aluminum do not compromise the national security of the United States and that Japanese products are of high quality, difficult to replace, reinforcing the competitiveness of the American transforming industry.
"Commercial restriction measures adopted by the United States will probably have a considerable impact on economic relations between Japan and the United States, as well as on the multilateral commercial system," the spokesman also warned, not to mention any reprisals.
Unlucky
Earlier this week, Japanese Minister Yoji Muto moved to Washington to try to get an exemption from the US administration, but without success. Japan exported 31.4 million tons of steel in 2024, including 1.12 million tons to the United States, according to data from the Japanese authorities.
This value corresponds to 4 percent of US steel imports, Tokyo being the sixth largest supplier, behind Canada, Brazil and Mexico. By 2022, Japan obtained exemption on export rights for the United States of 1.25 million tons of steel per year.
Donald Trump also threatens to aggravate rates on car imports from April. This is an important issue for Tokyo since last year the automotive industry represented about 28 percent of all Japanese exports to the United States.
During the first term, United States President Donald Trump had already imposed 25-per cent customs duties on steel and 10 percent over aluminum in an attempt to protect the American industry mainly from the US Center and West.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 01:53:44</pubDate></item><item><title>Paul French, writer: Looking for Wallis Simpson in China</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/17/paul-french-escritor-a-procura-de-wallis-simpson-na-china/</link><description>The Rota das Letras literary festival, which starts on Friday, will feature the presence of writer Paul French, who launched last year a new biographical book, "Her Lotus Year", which describes Wallis Simpson's experience in China before being a Duchess of Windsor. The British author will also talk about “Destination Macau”, a nostalgic and almost cinematic account of the city's history
 
How did you come to the history of Wallis Simpson's life experience in China?
I lived in Shanghai for many years and many visitors knew that Wallis Simpson had spent time in the city. Rumors ran on what he had done, and visitors always wanted to know if the rumors were true, such as the idea that she had learned esoteric sexual techniques or had posed naked for photographs. It was also said that he had belonged to a group of opium smuggling, or a group of bets that combined horses races. For me, as an author and expert in foreign experiences in Shanghai in the first half of the twentieth century, none of this made sense. So I thought this was the ideal time to really find out what Wallis had done in China. The fact that she was in the country in 1924 and 1925, two of the most fascinating years in the history of modern China, helped a lot.
How do you describe the life of the duchess in the country during that specific political period?
China was in total chaos when she was there, because Puyi, the last emperor, had been expelled from the forbidden city and occurred the biggest strikes ever in Hong Kong history. In addition, political fractions were recorded in Guangzhou, warlords of war in Shanghai and northern China. These were also the most wet years that there is a record in China, with crop production breaks and the occurrence of tiphoid and cholera fever outbreaks. He fired the number of bandits and pirates. Then, in March 1925, Sun Yat-Sen, leader of the Republican Revolution of 1911, died without leaving an obvious successor. Wallis came across all this, as he was retained on the island of Shamian, Guangzhou, while the city struggled; In Shanghai, he saw corpses to be brought to the city from the battles of the warlords; He saw victims of typhus and anger in Tianjin; and troops of the warlords threatening Beijing. But he was also largely in a foreign protective bubble that protected her from foreign soldiers and her white skin. He could delight in China's culture and aesthetics, while around him the whole country threatened to explode.
How was the personality of Wallis Simpson, a controversial figure in the context of the marriage to the Duke of Windsor?
It is very important not to confuse Wallis of 1924 with the later Wallis, from the long years of exile and controversy as Duchess of Windsor. In 1924 Wallis was only 28 years old, fleeing from a physically abusive husband (her first husband, Win Spencer, an American Navy commander) and was not yet particularly sophisticated or cosmopolitan. These were characteristics that would learn in China, mingling in the “colonies” [concessions] international foreign and bohemiums of Shanghai and Beijing. In fact, it was in Beijing that it first mixed with ambassadors, high -level Chinese politicians, high -ranking military officers and a stretch, and from them learned everything from playing Bridge and enjoying Jade to how to behave in high society. Obviously, this was useful a decade later when he met the Prince of Wales in England. Admittedly, the posterior Wallis, the Duchess, is a more difficult figure to like. Perhaps she and the Duke have made some bad political decisions and made some friendships, perhaps Wallis became a little bitter for not being accepted by the British royal family. But the truth is that in 1924 she was young, free of a bad husband and was in one of the most fascinating countries in the world.
What can readers perceive this figure and about China of that time, with "Her Lotus Year"?
China in 1925 was on the brink of potential explosion, as the whole country could have fallen into total chaos, dividing into the size of Portugal managed by warlords with private armies, or a resurgent Qing Dynasty supported by Japan in the North [China], the South and, of course, the foreign powers-England, America, France and Japan-who had Chinese lands like colonies. Ultimately, this did not happen, but no one knew this in 1925. Wallis herself oscillated between feeling incredibly comfortable and happy in what was her "year of lotus," as he described him, quoting Homer's Sopoifers who never want to return home; and feel terrified of the violence of the warlords or those who were against foreigners.
What are the biggest challenges, as a writer, in the process of researching the history of Wallis?
Wallis probably became the most photographed and spoken woman in history, more than Marilyn Monroe, more than Queen Isabel II. But in 1924 she was not famous at all. So it left a very difficult trail to follow. He wrote his memories, but these were "disinfected." A big problem was also the rumors that the British government and secret services circulated in 1936 in an attempt to destroy the idea of ​​a marriage between King Eduardo VIII and Wallis. The attempt failed because he abdicated the throne and they married, but these sexual rumors and insinuations, many of them racist and misogynists, have remained to this day, and they continue to be regularly recycled in the British and American Tabloid Press. I found the real Wallis a much more friendly character than I expected, and I hope readers will feel that too.
Is invited to another edition of Rota das Letras. How do you feel for being part of the festival?
I love to be part of the Macao Literary Festival. Although he had spoken before in Macao, namely in the Portuguese bookstore and other places, he had never participated in the festival. I look forward to being able to talk about Wallis Simpson and also about my new collection of rehearsals about Macau, entitled "Destination Macau". Some stories of Macao that have pleased me over the years, some of them presented with a more English look, as it were, may be interested and will be new to the local public.
Book | “Destination Macau”, the city between “The Imaginary and the Real”
Paul French has just launched the third volume of the “Destination” collection, which had editions of Shanghai or Beijing, and is now dedicated to telling stories of the ancient macao, a “place as imaginary as real”, as described the synopsis of the work. The work of the British author presents "The Macao by artists George Chinnery and George Smirnoff, the writers Deolinda da Conceição and Maurice Dekobra, to the fantasies of" Pulp Fiction "and febrile dreams of Josef Von Sternberg and Jean Delannoy."
There is still no shortage of Paul French, stories around historical figures such as Pedro José Lobo and Ian Fleming, author and creator of James Bond. Macao of the time of World War II, those who “came to Macao in search of gold, and those who sought war refuge” is described, not forgetting “the combatants looking for a secret passage through the 'neutral' macao”.
Paul French unveil mysteries or tells forgotten stories to many, such as the idea that Japan had tried to buy Macau in 1934 or the person who sailed with the Macau pirates queen, Lai Choi San. There are, in all, 18 stories “true of fascinating people who lived or visited Macau in the nineteenth and twentieth centuries”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:38:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Augusto Nogueira, President of Artm: “Macau is ahead of Hong Kong”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/augusto-nogueira-presidente-da-artm-macau-esta-a-frente-de-hong-kong/</link><description>The Macao toxicode dependent rehabilitation association is 25 years old this year. Augusto Nogueira makes a positive balance of the fourth century that began with a small therapeutic community and reached international recognition. The Association's president argues that, in prevention, Macau is at the head of Hong Kong and that the use of synthetic drugs is not yet problematic in the territory
 
 
What balance does the work developed by ArtM in these 25 years?
We do the balance very positive, because we started with a small area and a small therapeutic community. Nowadays we have a community with a capacity of 60 people, much more than the 15 we had at the time. We have developed several programs, namely the syringe distribution, which is a success, because it has led to a reduction and almost suppression of HIV contagion by people who inject drugs. For nine years there is the program and we have zero cases of infection. We developed support for social integration and follow -up after treatment, with “After Care”. We do preventive work in schools with the “Be Cool” program. We have the project “Hold on To Hope”, betting on vocational education, through coffee and the art gallery. It is a project that is well achieved and that turns out to be turned to tourism. We have visits from international entities and various non-governmental organizations, and the United Nations themselves. The most positive for us is to know how many people are recovered and who are well today. Unfortunately, we could not recover all people, but in each relapse there is always the possibility of the person coming again to do treatment.
How many people have recovered in 25 years?
We couldn't get this notion. We maintain contact with many people, but others have already left Macau, followed their lives. We have some contacts in the first two years after treatment, but then life goes on. People also want to go on a lifetime with no connection with the artm, sometimes marry and new companions don't know about their previous life and want to keep some confidentiality. But sometimes we meet. The other day they paid me a water without me knowing (laughs). These are small gestures that give us satisfaction to continue and make us believe that recovery is always possible.
What are the big challenges to maintain the ArtM project in terms of space and financing?
In terms of space and places for treatment we are well. The facilities are ten years old, there are maintenance problems, but this is more related to the panorama of construction in Macao. We need a space for the After Care, because what we have currently rented and is deteriorated. We are talking to the Institute of Social Action (IAS) to have a new space. With regard to the back, all our departments have financing, but we obviously seek support for our activities otherwise.
Regarding the authorities' posture regarding consumption and treatment, do you understand that it is still conservative in relation to other countries and regions?
This question is a little ambiguous. In terms of treatment and strategy in combating consumption, I think Macau is very ahead of Hong Kong, for example. In Macao, we have therapeutic community, we work on prevention and treatment, as well as our syringes and methadone distribution program. We have a range of treatments available to those in need. In the area of ​​prevention, the government has given a lot of support. The IAS has been quite open in strategies to combat consumption and prevention. In Hong Kong, for example, there is no syringe distribution program. Macao is from the few regions of Southeast Asia that has a government -supported syringes distribution program. But there could be another different interpretation of the law, with a differentiation between what is trafficking and their own consumption. For example, at this time if the person has a higher amount than that stipulated is soon considered trafficking, without proof. We think that in this case there should be a differentiation. It is then up to the police to investigate whether the quantities found are for consumption or trafficking. There should be an opening to give people more opportunities to be referred for treatment instead of going to prison. But lately, there have not been as many cases as that.
How do you describe the current consumer profile in Macau?
There is a large reduction in heroin consumption, and the few people who did so consume it today, or sleep. At this time the highest consumption is metabetamin, cannabis and some ketamine residues. As for the new synthetic drugs, there have been some records, but so far nothing alarming. But of course we have to be alert, we have to continue to do a good prevention job so that people are aware of the problems related to drug use. Regarding trafficking, we know that before the pandemic there was much cocaine trafficking to Macao, and after Covid-19 this situation almost ceased to happen. A good dissuasive work has been done and has to continue to be done so that there is less traffic to pass through Macau. It does not mean that there are no situations currently, but we are not in such a chaotic situation as that.
Speaking of synthetic drugs and their consumption, which according to the latest United Nations report has reached a worrying situation around the world. What is your comment to the scenario described in the annual report of the International Narcotics Control Board?
It is evident that the use of this type of drugs has been increasing over the years. Synthetic drugs are a real problem in the United States of America, for example, with fentanyl consumption, and Asia in some countries. It is a global problem because consumption and production are easy. Some of these drugs are made with other chemicals and many other products that are not well known to the origin and that can cause many overdoses. The UN suggests combating the production of ingredients that are used to produce these drugs, continue to reinforce the investigation to catch traffickers. But there are points of this report that it is necessary to follow, for many countries, which is the struggle between ideologies.
In what sense?
There is a struggle between those who argue that harm reduction is sufficient to combat all these problems that are arising, and that it is the solution to everything. Then we have those who think that harm reduction is not missing. In the artm we consider that there has to be a balance, because prevention is something important that cannot stop. What happened in Portugal, for example, when they liberalized the drug and failed to prevent and support treatment, [it was not good], and today Portugal is again in a slightly chaotic situation at consumption and trafficking. This means that prevention can never cease to exist. There should be quality treatments, with supervision of entities. The speed of access to treatment has to exist, and it can not be like in some countries where people have been waiting for a vacancy or permission to enter, as non -governmental organizations do not let the person enter until they receive the subsidy for each bed and patient. In these months a lot can happen. Damage reduction should be seen as a continuity for recovery, with rooms for consumption with medical and technical support, or syringe management programs. There is another problem, especially in Europe, which is heroin consumers, when they reach a more advanced age, already have many health problems and need sites to be, of a certain dignity. We have been wasting a lot of time with these ideological wars, and some of them exist for the sake of power, to influence the liberalization of drugs, and this is quite harmful. People's rights end when it is beginning to harm the rights of all other people, there must be a balance. As the report also says, there is a lack of medicines for some countries in Africa.

Art
To commemorate the 25th anniversary, the artm inaugurated on Friday the “Exhibition of the 25th Anniversary of Artm”, which is evident in the Hold on To Hope Gallery until the 23rd of this month. In the cultural space in the village of Nossa Senhora in Ká-Hó, which is part of the Occupational Therapy Program for the Arts users, you can see an art show done by these, with 45 works of ceramic, painting and wooden works. According to a press release of the association, the exhibition “celebrates resilience, creativity and healing”. “Throughout the last quarter of the century, the artm has been a symbol of hope for individuals on their journey of dependence recovery. This exhibition presents the extraordinary works of art created by our residents ”, reads.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 00:28:17</pubDate></item><item><title>Debbie Lai, director of the center of the good shepherd | “Victims need more protection”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/debbie-lai-directora-do-centro-do-bom-pastor-vitimas-precisam-de-mais-proteccao/</link><description>Regarding International Women's Day, which was celebrated around the world on Saturday, HM talked to Debbie Lai, director of the center of the good shepherd, one of the entities that welcomes victims of domestic violence in the territory. The official defends speed in investigations of cases of domestic violence and more days of maternity leave
 
 
Regarding domestic violence, the law remains not revised, with many cases where it cannot be accused or condemned the aggressor. What needs to be changed in current legislation?
You should accelerate the time spent in investigating the case, as well as to make a simple promotion of the law, to let people understand what they will face if they report the situation to the police. There is still afraid of the complaint to the police, so what happens is that the aggressor, before a complaint, gets angry, again committing violence and the family is departed.
How many women are currently at the center of the good shepherd?
According to the License of Service granted by the Institute of Social Action (IAS), we can welcome 14 people, including children. We currently have 11 people, six women, three children and two girls living in our center. Some of these women have problems due to emotional conflicts, and although they already have some stability at this level, they continue to have financial difficulties. Many of these women are not permanent residents, so they are unable to apply for government social housing, and they need more time to save money to pay an income in Macao, which is not cheap. If young children exist, it is harder for them to find a full -time job, so these women cannot move in a short time for a home, staying in our center a year. And in this situation, the center cannot have more empty rooms to help other women in crisis.
Do you consider that more reception centers are needed for victims of violence in Macao, or more resources to ensure the victim's safety, since the territory is so small?
I think the resources are sufficient, but the investigation process is time consuming. Victims need more protection, as there is always the risk that the perpetrator continues to threaten them.
What is necessary to increase the birth rate and ensure that women continue to have access to equal economic and employment opportunities?
A promoção precisa de ser contínua, e devem aumentar os dias de licença de maternidade, pois noutros países existem mais dias de licença de maternidade. Também se poderia diminuir o valor mensal das creches. Poderia ponderar-se também a atribuição de um subsídio por cada criança caso a família tenha problemas financeiros.
There is a lack of support for single -padded families, where women are alone with dependent children, or where women are caregivers? In concrete terms, what needs to be improved?
I think yes. I think some of them do not know that there are resources in society to help them, or may not have motivation to seek help. Many of these women also do not want to rely on government, not even non -governmental associations or organizations that provide services to the family. But these women can always apply for the subsidy attributed by the Institute of Social Action, which gives them some money and allows you to stay at home to take care of their children.
How do you describe women in Macao currently, especially the Chinese community? Are you more emancipated and equal to men regarding their rights?
Nowadays the capacity of women has changed a lot, as they have equal opportunities and the right to develop. Many local companies are already chaired by women, for example. In addition to having physical strength, they can choose their jobs, attend higher education, marry and have the ability to take leadership positions. However, there are many women who come to Macau and marry residents and have a lower social position, suffering from various family problems. I speak of machismo that still exists, the addiction of the game, situations of toxicodependence or lack of communication. There are men who control everything, creating a climate in which the wife has to hear her husband and is devoid of self-esteem to get out of this situation. In such cases, it is very easy to have discussions, conflicts and even cases of violence between the couple. These are situations that obviously also affect their children.
International Women's Day celebrated in Macau
International Women's Day was celebrated in Macao in very diverse ways. In the case of Sands China, flowers were offered to the operator's workers as a way of expressing “the appreciation for the indispensable contributions that women make in the workplace, in the family and society”, can read in a company statement. It was also organized a debate that focused on the issues around women, organized by the Sands Empowher volunteer team, a “global initiative of diversity and inclusion led by women, which aims to connect the team's female members to create network job opportunities”. This event was broadcast live on Sands China's various digital platforms.
Sands Empowher is, above all, to organize training and mentoring actions so that women can develop in professional and career terms.
In the same note, it states that the company “is committed to building and maintaining a workplace with respect and equality”, defending and guaranteeing women's rights. Regarding sexual harassment, Sands states that it has carried out a campaign to prevent cases since July 2018, as well as actions that reduce cases of discrimination against women.
This was “the first in Macao”, and a “training action with all team members” on these themes was also carried out. Regarding support for maternity, "the company also offers breastfeeding rooms for mothers and performs a wide variety of activities for parents and children to promote family harmony."
At the Portuguese School of Macao, International Women's Day was celebrated on Friday with the DAC project-“Women who inspire”, an initiative organized by the teachers of the disciplines of Portuguese, Philosophy and Mathematics, among others. The 10th grade students have developed several works on inspiring women in the most diverse areas. One of them was the recently deceased poet Maria Teresa Horta.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 03:54:15</pubDate></item><item><title>Bernardo Mendia, Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong: “Portugal should extend your hand”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/06/bernardo-mendia-camara-de-comercio-e-industria-portugal-hong-kong-portugal-deve-estender-a-mao/</link><description>The Secretary for Innovation, Technology and Industry of Hong Kong, Sun Dong, arrives today, accompanied by entrepreneurs from digital areas, online trade and technology. Bernardo Mendia, Mayor of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong, highlights the importance of visiting Portuguese companies and Raehk as a complement to Portuguese contacts in Macau
 
 
Last year, Portugal was visited by Christopher Hui Ching-Yu, Secretary of Hong Kong Financial Affairs and Treasury, and now another Hong Kong ruler passes through Portugal. Is it a visit with added meaning?
As a Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong we consider this visit extremely important, valuing the attention that is being given to Portugal. It is important, above all, because it is such a specific area as innovation. This is an area where Hong Kong bets a lot and has been a priority for the region's authorities, and this is something that exists in common with Portugal, which has also bet on technological and scientific development. What Portugal should do is take this opportunity, extend your hand to the secretary and work in partnership. Technological and economic development is only done with international partnerships, opening markets and collaborations. This is also what we promote as a Chamber of Commerce. We have been involved in organizing this trip, something that started months ago. We will lead Portuguese companies to identify potential synergies with the entities that come here, so that they know each other and then do their work.
Hong Kong has been present in all editions of Websummit in Lisbon. Does this visit give the idea that the region intends to expand and establish more concrete partnerships with Portugal?
Yes, no doubt. This has evidenced in official speeches of the most important members of the Hong Kong government, including the executive's own head. This is the region's strategy at this time, being a bridge for the rest of the world to be able to enter Asia. Then the territory competes with other platforms, as Hong Kong, Singapore and Tokyo are perhaps the three territories with the greatest expression in this [technological] area in Asia. But Hong Kong presents the best conditions, not only for the support it gives [to companies], but also for being part of China, despite having a different legal system and a different currency. There is a system completely open at the level of capital circulation and internet access. I think Hong Kong is better positioned in this field, but this is a competition that the territory has to do, such as Portugal when it will perform in Asia, competing with Spain and other European countries in attracting foreign direct investment.
Macao is usually the main connection to Portugal, for historical reasons and the presence of the Portuguese language. Can Hong Kong also be a binding territory between Portuguese companies and Asia?
Macau and Hong Kong are very complementary in this regard. Macao has this historical connection with Portugal and has very important companies based in the territory, some of them for over 100 years, namely the National Bank Overseas. This experience, and the fact that the Portuguese language is still official, is undoubtedly an advantage for Portuguese companies. If it is necessary to enter the capital market, Portuguese companies will opt for a number of services provided by Hong Kong. But Macau has its own advantages and I consider it two very complementary markets. The geographical proximity of Macau and Hong Kong also acts as an attractive point.
During Christopher Hui Ching-Yu's visit last year, Hong Kong's position as Fiscal Paradise was addressed. How do you look at this question?
This visit is organized by the Hong Kong Economic and Trade Office and the tax issues will now be set aside. But our position, as a Chamber of Commerce, is that it makes no sense Hong Kong being on the list of tax havens, and makes no sense or from a legal point of view. None of the markets we compete with Hong Kong as a fiscal paradise, nor the European Union itself. We just have to lose with it, because we create barriers to trade and foreign direct investment in Portugal, and also the investment that is made by Portuguese companies in Macao, which are eventually affected by it. It makes no sense to this designation from a legal point of view, because Hong Kong does not gather the conditions to be part of the list of tax havens, and from the political point of view because no other European country puts the territory in this category.
China is present in the Portuguese market through various investments. Hong Kong is trying to create its own way?
Not in these terms. The overwhelming majority of Chinese investment that is made in Portugal is through Hong Kong. Then, in this respect, Hong Kong and China work in a quite complementary way. Hong Kong acts as a "aircraft carrier" from China in terms of foreign investment, and there is no competition between the two, working, together.
Encounters in Oeiras | Taguspark today hosts exchange sessions and seminars
Dong Sun is accompanied by Portugal by Hong Kong's most important companies and entities in the areas of innovation, technology and digital media, either government, with Hong Kong Science and Technology Park and “Cyberport”, technology park with budget projects in two billion Hong Kong; either academic and research, attending the entourage of the Hong Kong Applied Science and Technology Research Institute and “Hong Kong Microelectronics Research and Development Institute”.
Exchange sessions and seminars take place today from 4 pm at Taguspark, Oeiras, where Oeiras Valley Investment Agency is located, whose representatives have already been present in Macao for commercial contacts.
In the afternoon there will be the opportunity for dialogue between the Secretary of Hong Kong, representatives of the Chamber of Commerce and Industry Portugal - Hong Kong and leaders of Raehk's technological parks and institutes, and in total 24 companies are represented.
In the Catalan road
In a statement issued by the Hong Kong executive, it is read that the program includes “meetings and exchanges with leaders of local political, business and innovation and technology sectors”, as well as visits to infrastructure, technological parks, research institutes and businesses.
The aim is to “reinforce ties and cooperation” with Portugal in this sector, “promoting the advantages of Hong Kong innovation and technology and exploring business opportunities abroad,” according to the statement.
Before passing through Lisbon, the delegation was in Barcelona to participate in the “Mobile World Congress”, considered one of the most influential technological events worldwide.
This is the second visit to Portugal of a member of the Hong Kong government within a year, after the secretary for financial services and treasure had passed through Lisbon in June. At the time, Christopher Hui Clay-Yu asked Portugal to remove Hong Kong from the list of tax havens and argued that it already fulfills the European Union standards to combat tax dropout.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>Piménio Ferreira: “Anti-igan rhetoric has always worked in Portugal”</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2021/04/26/pimenio-ferreira-a-retorica-anti-cigana-sempre-funcionou-em-portugal/</link><description>Piménio Ferreira, better known as Gitelles Ferreira, anti-racist militant, 34, physical engineer, national Romani. He is a man with a provocative speech, a corrosive, kind mood and a smile that leaves no one indifferent
Gitelles, we live in an intercultural land and the Gypsies - in particular - have lived about five centuries in Portugal. What is going on for Gypsy communities to remain “on the fringes” of the so -called society? 
The model of society remains to be changed. This is extremely stratified by placing people in subordinate places to privilege a violent minority. The white social structure is patriarchal and racist. What is called the "margin" of society is actually an intrinsic place to it, which belongs to it. In other words, Gypsy people have been included in this model of society since they discovered Europe and its kingdoms. The problem is the model of society that is maintained and the place to which they were relegated and how they were relegated: with violence, in inferior status against whites, without the right to human dignity, to constitute a family, to choose one's own language and religion, expropriated from any and all cultural and material law. A place built and maintained to this day by violence and genocidal and ethnicidal persecution. In 1463, a Gitano Vasco was drowned to an estate. In 1521, Gitans, or Gypsies, were already used as a reference for all that is considered bad in the model of society. The "counter-exemple" in the face of the white that would stand out for the positive. The 'angel' and the 'devil'; the 'other', the enemy; That against whom any attack and persecution is legitimate. Including the prohibition of defending, having weapons, any kind of goods, and the right of permanence.
And is this right to permanence that we still have nomadic gypsy communities within the country is denied?
Yes, no doubt. There are many ways to force nomadism: directly, prohibiting permanence and expelling with police or military force; indirectly, refusing public or private housing to Gypsy people, as they are Gypsy; and even through the gentrification process.
I read the result of an inquiry from the European Union Fundamental Rights Agency, which is said to be approximately 80% of the Gypsies responded to the risk threshold of poverty in their country; One in three Gypsies lives in a housing without channeled water; One in three Gypsies belongs to a family where someone hungry at least once the previous month; and 50% of Gypsies aged 6 to 24 do not attend school. Why does this happen like this? 
It is the historical persecution, which continues. There is no impoverishment that has no external cause. In this case, a political system of total expropriation and imposed on the basis of violence. Already in 1648, D John IV, the restorer, prohibited ‘Giving or Rent houses to Gypsies’. The same D John IV who got the kingdom of Portugal thanks to D. Jerónimo da Costa and his 250 knights. The same D. Jerónimo da Costa who had died to defend Portugal's independence from Castile. Gypsy, like his wife and children. Between prohibitions of permanence, “that do not enter Gypsies in the Kingdom and leave those who are” (D John III, 1526), ​​with expulsions, degred to the galleys, expropriation of goods and properties, imposed with stripping, mutilation and death, systematically performed to this day (still in 2011 Faro City Council wanted to ban Gypsies in the municipality).
The prohibition of working on others (no one employs Gypsy workers, and those who accept they do it in total precariousness, for poorly paid positions and without decent rights and conditions). They cannot be dependent on their own work, they cannot get investment means due to extreme expropriation. Are dependent on precariousness. If you want to know what it is like to live in pure neoliberalism, know the lives of Gypsies. Their reality is paradigmatic of the aggression and depletion to which the "gentlemen" are willing to go to their benefit.
Are you talking about economic and political power?
The group of political, social, cultural and economic power. The owner, the colonizer. This group that has been in power since it established the system of current domination. And that only makes sense within the hierarchically stratified sociopolitical model in which we live. Hence the need to end 'gentlemen' and institute a new model of society, healthy, free, without hierarchies or strata, whether of race, class or gender.
The model we live in leads to the Gypsy (and not only) community to economic exclusion, removing it from access to product consumption or excluding them from its production process; political exclusion associated with lack of access to information; To education and consequently the social exclusion that is seen in inequality of access to quality community areas such as restaurants, libraries, theater, cinema, concerts, health care, etc. How do you feel a gypsy child when you realize that it is not part of a whole? Children who are never represented, neither in movies, nor in books, nor in cartoons, not even in an announcement to eat cereals, for example? Is this a disaster for self-esteem, is a priori condemnation?
The question is that. Gypsy people are not “excluded from society”, by contrast, they are included in it. The problem is the existence of what is cynically called 'social exclusion', which term Orwellian, and there be under coercion, people. Which field of concentration and extermination. Incidentally, Nazi concentration camps are a more visual realization than called 'social exclusion' and, as here, were not a 'excluded' part of Nazi society, but rather its fundamental and characterizing structure. It is a place of violence, where people are maintained by violence, dedicated to their extermination, and designed so that few people can leave. And yet they resist. As in Nazi concentration camps.
E o que elencaste como exemplo de ‘consequência’ dessa ‘exclusão’, é na verdade o meio pelo qual essa exclusão também acontece e se mantém. Pessoas ciganas estão fora dos cinemas, quer como consumidoras quer produtoras (mas vão ao cinema). Estão fora da escola, da educação e da Academia. Quer como ‘utentes’ quer como produtoras (mas vão à escola e estão na base da construção de conhecimento e de debates académicos e científicos).
Even in attacking Gypsy children's self -confidence, we talk about a maintenance mechanism of this situation. But Gypsy people respond very well: with Gypsy pride. Another resistance, another aggression. Gypsy people are thus included in society. In a place that belongs to this model of modern society. And they resist and contradict the power of domination and make a point of being in the city, in the cinema, in the theater, in the gym, in all spaces. With a lot of struggle and always resisting, but they are there. Social exclusion, more than a “place outside of society”, is part of its social structure.
Do you want to say that there is a collective resistance?
At work, already in a context of absolute precariousness, during the pandemic, Gypsy people rolled up sleeves and showed once again proactivity and creativity in adversity. They learned seeing and doing. And here, it is again the women who jump to the front line, face, learn to use digital tools with their daughters or children, and throw themselves into the network. And so they explore online sales as well as application by application (transportation or rehabs). In housing, in a context of pandemic in which the evictions were not locked - as they owed and dictated the law itself - residents did not fail to organize and fight unjust evictions and claim dignity in housing; associations of allied residents in their action with other housing and anti-racist struggle organizations.
It should also be noted how they reinvented and intensified to raise and distribute dietary goods and kits of masks/alcohol gel to the most expropriated people. Gypsies and non -Gypsies. In the anti-racist struggle, new movements emerged and their actions intensified by social networks. People who had never been organized or militated before began their first steps in activism, thickening this way of the organization and popular gypsy and anti-racist action. People forget, or do not want to value, but Gypsy action has helped determine results in the political dispute. Gypsy citizens mobilized in large and determined electoral results in the municipalities of 2017, both in Alentejo and in the Lisbon Metropolitan Area, even causing electoral earthquakes.
And even in the presidential, second place was resolved by a value equivalent to the estimated number of Gypsy voters. Apart from the non -Gypsy votes that were mobilized by the action of Gypsy voters. Gypsy people are even co-considering power in the spaces of opinion, local media, social networks and party and institutional political dispute. And most importantly, in the popular Ação and alliances with other social movements. We have never stopped fighting for all means and continuing to resist.
In contrast there are more and more hate speeches, from the far right in particular. What do you have to say about it?
To start these speeches are historical and European. Not even current and even less “of the far right”. These speeches have been adopted and rendered for a long time, even in 'democracy and freedom', by several representatives of the center right, conservatives, left center, liberal, liberal left, even representatives of the PCP. Anti-egana rhetoric has always worked in Portugal as it is the whiter rhetoric [white genesis]. That is, it allows you to create and give the "white" as the superior of all. And so please the white electorate who, when feeling well, pays off with his vote. Even if the policies implemented by their elected harm him even more.
Finally, did you like them to talk a little about your personal experience and how did you get to the activist?
I studied, fought for studies, made alliances, graduated, went in the labor market of the “formal precariousness”. I started my militant action and here I am today. We can transform this society a better. This certainty combined with the fact that the current one has so much suffering makes anyone want to have a transformist attitude. I wanted to be 'inventor' (physical engineer) and anti -racist militant. And through study (not necessarily schooling) and organization with others, in turn, with other studies, formations and visions, I learned how the world works and how it can be changed. But before transforming, we need to survive.
Hence two types of actions arise: transformative and survival. The struggle against hate discourse arises as survival, but his defeat will be a transformative victory. There is a lot that - like people who want a better world - we have to do, namely working to criminalize hatred speech; condemn and prohibit organizations with racist discourses and practices; denounce the racist institutional structure and logics that organize power and generate community resources. And in this sense, there have been various types of actions, of petitions, to manifestations. And we need more.
I, besides being a military man in the SOS Racism movement, participate in the “We came to stay” podcast, with Mamadou BA and Joseph da Silva. And if all goes well, we will soon start a new project. With friendly people, we also have the project “Gypsy Initiative”, dedicated to reflecting and promoting transformative movements. Essentially focused on educating against anti-agigarism, denouncing historical and continued genocide and working for a new society project. Also with new projects on the gutter. And finally, there are always voluntary actions without an organization, where I try to share what I found out about anti-egism and Roman history in schools and with interested people. In addition, there is still the struggle for housing, because the evictions did not stop during the pandemic. Due to housing and work precariousness, the subjects racialized especially the Roma nationals are the most vulnerable to COVID-19. There is essential to have actions in this area; Of all the struggles, this is the most structural, as it goes against one of the main enemies of a healthy society: the real estate speculation of this capitalist system, which places profit and goods above people and their humanization.</description><pubDate /></item><item><title>GP Macau | FIA confirms GT World Cup</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/28/gp-macau-fia-confirma-taca-do-mundo-de-gt/</link><description>The World Council of the FIA ​​last Wednesday confirmed the expected, that the eighth edition of the FIA ​​GT World Cup will be held as part of the Macao's 72nd Grand Program, from November 13 to 16. However, there is a big news for this year's edition
 
The International Federation, which co-organizes this race in partnership with Sro Motorsports Group and the Macau-China General Automotive Association (AAMC), took the opportunity to announce a new qualification model for the race. In addition to the 30 -minute qualification session equal to the previous editions (Q1), a second qualification segment (Q2) was added, reserved for the top ten pilots of the first session.
The Q2 session will be held in Super Pole format, with each pilot to go to the track individually for a total of two qualification turns, and each pilot is also allowed to use a new tire set at this session. This novelty will allow qualification to be decided without interference from third parties.
O restante programa da prova rainha de GT permanecerá igual ao das edições anteriores, contando com a sessão de treinos-livres, a tradicional corrida classificativa de 12 voltas, na tarde de sábado, seguida da corrida principal de 16 voltas que decidirá o vencedor da Taça do Mundo no domingo.
Veterans compliments
These measures introduced by the FIA ​​were very well received by the most experienced GT riders. This is because traffic has always been a huge obstacle in obtaining a good qualification return on the guide circuit, something essential for those who aim to win this title.
"It's an excellent idea to introduce the Super Pole session in Macao," said German Maro Engel, the winner of the World Cup last edition by Mercedes-AMG. This will be one of the most spectacular and exciting sessions of the season and should also secure sports justice. Fans have a lot to yearn. ”
Raffaele Marciello, for two winning occasions of this trophy, and one of BMW's factory riders, also reacted positively, adding: “In Macao, it was always complicated to make a clean turn. With this new format, you will not hear the excuse of traffic or a red flag. Having only two laps will be very challenging, but now the fastest pilot will probably be in pole. ”
This is an opinion shared by Laurens Vanthoor, the World Cup winner in 2016, who said there will no longer be “apologies” in the qualification. Porsche's experienced Belgian pilot believes that “there will be an added pressure because you only have these two turns”, because in a difficult circuit like this, “if you make an error, there is nothing else to follow. In a normal qualification, you have more opportunities. Personally, a shootout is always something I appreciate a lot. For pilots, on a track like this, it will be almost the highlight of the weekend. ”
And the younger ones too
Chinese pilot Yifei Ye premiered at the Grand Prix last November at the World Cup. Ferrari's official pilot, which competes in the Endurance Fia World Championship (WEC), has left a good impression on the guide circuit, and he also welcomes the now introduced measurements.
“It's good to eliminate these red flag interventions and yellow flags, so that in the end, the one that really is the fastest to get pole position,” said Yifei Ye that she could return to the race this year. “In Macau, everyone is very close in terms of times, so it will be extremely difficult for pilots to try to reach Super Pole. I think it will also be great for viewers. ”</description><pubDate>2025-02-28 01:03:51</pubDate></item><item><title>GP | Célio Alves Dias will continue to run this season</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/24/gp-celio-alves-dias-vai-continuar-a-correr-esta-temporada/</link><description>Macaense pilot Célio Alves Dias was one of the long -term returns of the 2024 car.
 
The Macao Cup winner of Macau in 2021 was removed from motorsport at the time of 2023 for personal reasons, but last year made his debut in the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8). Despite the vast experience in tests of the specialty, having conducted several generations of tourism cars, Célio Alves Dias had never managed the new bobbinns that the Macao-China General Association (AAMC) introduced in its competition in 2023. Last time turned out to be of learning, with some difficulties in the tuning and behavior of the Japanese car.
Participation in races at the Zhuzhou International Circuit and the Macau Grand Prix made Célio Alves Dias realize that his Toyota GR86 was not at the strongest competition level. Based on the conclusions drawn from these experiences, he decided to start preparing for the new season.
“The car had to be all dismantled. My car was bought on Monday, and the chassis and the security arc, for me, were not well done, ”explained Fu Lei Racing Team pilot to HM. “This, made the car too hard and very difficult to bow. I tried a car from China, which was well assembled, and there is a difference. I had a long time in January, in China, with this car. Our cars, made in the same workshop, were very hard, which made it difficult to make turns fast. ”
If in the Macao Grand Prix, the house riders, excellent guide circuit, managed to equate the progress to their hong Kong opponents and the interior of China, in the initial races on the Zhuzhou track in Hunan province, it wasn't quite like that. “There are many differences between cars, but especially in chassis, because engines, in terms of power and horses, are almost all at the same level. Our opponents also experienced many pieces, many engines, even gearboxes, and chassis. Competition cars are always the same. You have to have engine power, but also chassis. Having only power is not enough. Having better a good chassis is the most important. ”
Silver Jubilee in November
Being a usual Portuguese name in the Macao Grand Prix in recent decades, Célio Alves Dias debuted at the Guide Circuit in 2000 and from then was a frequent presence and no faults in the race until 2023. This year, its objective is to account for its twenty-fifth participation in the biggest sports event of RAEM, but will have to align in the findings.
While awaiting the announcement of the 2025 calendar by AAMC, Célio Alves Dias details details to start his test program, because his Toyota, after being reviewed, "is ready to test" in the interior of China, something that will happen "very soon," says the pilot.
In the last edition of the Grand Prix, Célio Alves Dias qualified in 12th place for the Macau Roadsport Challenge race. However, his participation was short and unhappy: at the wheel of Toyota with dorsal No. 11, was forced to give up after being immobilized on the climb of San Francisco. The Macanese pilot was out of the race on the first lap, in an incident that caused the Safety Car.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 02:50:53</pubDate></item><item><title>Iame Asia finals of Karting back in December</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/11/finais-da-iame-asia-de-karting-voltam-em-dezembro/</link><description>The Macao Karting International Award will receive again, from December 11 to 14, the Iame Asian finals. Like last year, the coloane karting race will give invitations to the very coveted world end of Iame in 2026.
Organized by the Institute of Sport, Macau-China General Automobile Association (AAMC), Otk Kart Asia and Iame Asia, the 2024 event brought back the international spirit to one of the largest competitions of the sport on the Asian continent. Coloane's karting received several races and different categories of Iame Series Asia, recovering the international prestige of an event that has been the scene of the Cik-Fia World Championship events.
Pilots from the interior of China, Singapore, Philippines, Malaysia, Thailand, Indonesia, Japan, India, Sri Lanka, Australia, New Zealand, Sweden, Italy, France, Austria, the United States of America, Brazil, Hong Kong, and, of course, Macao, filled the track from the mashes in 2024 for four days of intense Competition, something that has not been seen for several years.
After the success of the previous edition, the formula is repeated this year. Singapore's organization again chooses Coloane's karting for its biggest event of the season, confirming the presence of the usual categories: Cadet, Junior, Senior and Master.
Thank you Macau!
The Iame (Italian American Motor Engineering) is one of the world's leading engine manufacturers for Karting. Founded in 1968 by Bruno Grana, the company is headquartered in Italy and is one of the references in Karting Internacional, having bet strongly in the Asian market in recent years. The presence in Macau is part of this strategy of growth and expansion.
The announcement of the return to the territory was made on social networks: “After an incredible debut in 2024, we are back with the Macao International Award and the Iame Asia final for another epic confrontation! The city of emotions at high speed and legendary races will be the stage again for the best pilots in Asia and around the world! Larger, more bold and even more intense. ”
Satisfied with the reception in 2024, Iame Asia organizers took the opportunity to leave a "huge thanks to AAMC and the Macao government for their continuous support and confidence to make it possible!"
In addition to the Macao test, the 2025 calendar of Iame Series Asia includes three events in Malaysia and three events in Thailand. However, for the first time, last weekend of March, the Iame Asia Cup will be held at the International Shanghai Circuit Karting.</description><pubDate>2025-03-11 01:04:32</pubDate></item><item><title>Return to GIC | Local tests return to Zhaoqing</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/03/10/regresso-ao-gic-provas-locais-voltam-a-zhaoqing/</link><description>The dates for the Macao of Tourism Car Championship (MTCs in the English acronym) were made known on the past Friday by the General Automóvel Association of Macau-China (AAMC) through a newsletter. The competition for local pilots and decides to find out the Macao Grand Prix in November will again return to the Guangdong International Circuit (GIC).
After a year when the MTCS headed to the Zhuzhou International Circuit in Hunan province, AAMC listened to most of the territory pilots and chose to make these important races closer to the main interveners' house - the pilots. In recent years, the circuit of the surroundings of Zhaoqing has been the preferred stage for the realization of these races, due to the proximity and the fact that it serves as an operational basis to most teams.
The first of the two events scheduled for the 2025 MTCS is scheduled from 18 to 20 April, while the second round is scheduled from 16 to 18 May. The AAMC newsletter says that "all riders must go through a selection process before they can participate in the 72nd edition of the Macao Grand Prix - Macau Touring Car Challenge."
Registration, for the competition that joins the Toyota Gr86 (ZN8) and the Subaru BRZ (ZD8), are open until March 29 and after the end of the registration period, "all applications will be subject to AAMC approval, which reserves the final right to accept or reject any registration."
The technical regulation was also published, as was officially confirmed the use of tires of the Italian brand Pirelli, which belongs to the Chinese conglomerate Sinochem, as had already happened on the last edition of the Macao Grand Prix.
Confirmation of the Great Bay
AAMC also confirmed the two findings for the GT Cup - Great Bay Race (GT4), which will be concomitant with the new Chinese Championship Sro GT Cup. The first race will be played from March 21 to 23, at the International Circuit of Shanghai, in the Formula 1 China Grand Prix. Zhuhai International. Also here Pirelli will be the only tire supplier.
These two tests will be determined for the big holiday party on the guide circuit, and it is defined that only 28 cars will be accepted on the starting grid in the mashed race. The 72nd edition of the Macau Grand Prix runs from November 13 to 16.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 04:17:32</pubDate></item><item><title>GP TCR | Australia confirms presence in Macau</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/19/gp-tcr-australia-confirma-presenca-em-macau/</link><description>The 2025 season of TCR Australia will end largely when joining the TCR World Tour in the race of the 72nd Macao Grand Prix, which will take place from 13 to 16 November
 
After welcoming TCR China by 2024, the FIA ​​TCR World Tour “worldwide” will have the company of the Australian competitors in the most demanding race of the season, as HM had already foreseen at the end of last year.
This announcement is the second news in the calendar of one of the largest national TCR competitions in the world, after the announcement of a new promoter for the championship.
One pilot who was certainly pleased with the news was Australian Ben Bargwanna, who ran on the streets of Macao in 2023. TCR Australia's first international participation was made possible by the global rights holder, the WSC Group, which will ensure full transportation costs for Australian teams traveling to Macau.
"TCR Australia has always been one of TCR's most important and exciting competitions, rooted in the long tradition of tourism motorsport in the country," said WSC Group president Marcello Lotti. The Italian businessman made it clear that “when logistical issues forced us to cancel the Australian rounds of Kumho Fia TCR World Tour last year, we immediately started working to return in 2025. It is fantastic to extend cooperation for a second event and offer Australian competitors the unique opportunity to finish the season in Macau.”
Other applause
TCR Australia Prosecutor David Sonenscher, an old acquaintance of Macao, highlighted the importance of the moment for the category.
"I am very happy to bring TCR Australia to one of the most iconic circuits in the world and certainly one of the biggest challenges for a pilot," said former Malaysian-based English driver and entrepreneur and co-founder of TCR Asia. “The opportunity to expand our cooperation with the TCR World Tour FIA and to show the talented Australian riders on the highest international stage in Macau demonstrates the unique opportunity that TCR Australia and the TCR Global Platform provide all participants.”
Confirmation of the presence of TCR Australia in the Guide Race should not be impeded to the participation of local and interior of China in the most celebrated tourist car race on the Asian continent.</description><pubDate>2025-02-19 01:54:58</pubDate></item><item><title>Motorcycling | FHO RACING WITH NEW FOCUS IN 2025</title><link>https://hojemacau.com.mo/2025/02/13/motociclismo-fho-racing-com-novo-foco-em-2025/</link><description>Doubts dissipated this week. Macau's businesswoman Foye Ho's FHO Racing will continue to active in the 2025 season, but without the initially announced riders. Peter Hickman and Davey Todd are leaving and goes to a new team called 8ten Racing
 
According to a statement sent by FHO Racing, BMW Motorrad UK has restructured its training for the 2025 British Superbike Championship, and FHO Racing BMW will compete with a single pilot aboard a BMW M 1000 RR. German 2024 Superbike Champion and Resistance World Cup driver, Ilya Mikhalchik, will make his debut in the British competition, at a time when team owner Faye Ho, realinhas the objectives of his team “to explore new activities in motorized new markets, with the support of BMW Motorrad Motorsport”.
Currently in his fifth year at the British Superbike Championship Paddock, Faye Ho has been a strong presence in the British competition, as well as in the popular road races, such as the Macao Grand Prix, as well as supporting several young female riders, helping them progress in their careers since the lower classes. Faye Ho, Stanley Ho's granddaughter and Clementina Leitão, has supported Kate Walker and Jamie Hanks-Bliott on BMW F 900 R Cup and, it seems, which will continue to support.
To be
Contrary to the rumors that put her from Paddock's departure, Faye Ho made it clear that she is a “great advocate of the British Superbike Championship, one of the world's most exciting and competitive competitions” and will keep her commitment to discipline. However, the territory entrepreneur now has new objectives for herself and its structure. The future will be in Asia and support for young female talents.
"Given my long -term goals, which include expanding motor sport activities in Asia and continuing to support young women in motorcycling, I realized that I cannot dedicate the same time to the British Superbike Championship and road races, which I have given them since I owned the team in 2021, due to additional commitments I have in Macau," Faye Ho said.
Another chapter
This announcement has put an end to a successful partnership, particularly on the island of Man TT, between Peter Hickman, four times winner of the Macao Motorcycle Grand Prix, and Fho Racing. Hickman left some words of thanks to his now former boss.
“I want to leave a huge thanks to Faye [Ho] and Fho Racing for all they have done for me over the past four years,” Hickman wrote in a Facebook social network post. “As it is normal in motorized sport, we had amazing moments and others more difficult, but Fho has always been and always will be a fundamental part of my career. I will be eternally grateful for this opportunity. ”
The new 8Ten Racing team, which will be officially presented on February 26, will be mostly composed of former FHO Racing elements. Hickman and Todd will maintain the important support of BMW Motorrad UK and are expected on the big prize starting grid in November.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 01:30:05</pubDate></item></channel></rss>