<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Birth decreased 12% in the first quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/natalidade-decresceu-12-primeiro-trimestre/</link><description>Less births were registered in Macao in the first quarter of this year-the annual break was 12%, while in quarterly terms decreased 24%. Between January and March, 750 babies were born, and more than 20 years are needed to find a lower number. Authorities have said that this year there may be less than 3,500 births in the territory. The people of the MSAR, in turn, rose in annual terms, having reached 687,900 people; the addition was mainly due to the increase in TNR
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The number of births in Macao fell two digits between January and March this year - either annually and quarterly. Data from the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) show that in the first quarter, 750 wrecks were recorded, 106 less compared to the first three months of 2024, equivalent to a 12%break. The decrease is more pronounced when we look at the last quarter of the last year: now 237 babies were born, translating into a 24%break.
It is necessary to retreat more than 20 years to find a lower number of births in the territory. In the second quarter of 2004, according to DSEC data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, 681 babies were born in Macau. In the first quarter of the same year there were also fewer births, 724 in total.
It is recalled that, at the beginning of the year, the Deputy Director of Health Services predicted that there should be less than 3,500 births in the territory this year, which, to happen, will be the lowest since 2004.
Data for the first three months of 2025 also indicate that more boys (377) than girls (373) were born.
In the general calculation of 2024, it is recalled, the birth signs of “continuing to go down”, and contrary to what happened in China, not even the fact that it was the dragon year-considered “favorable to procreation” by the characteristics of that Chinese zodiac sign-contributed to an increase in the number of births.
The number of undead totaled 3,607 last year, 105 in annual terms, with the rate of birth to 5.3 °, the lowest since 1985. Macau registered only 0.58 births per woman, the lowest fertility rate ever in the world and the lowest in the world.
In addition, according to DSEC, in the first quarter of this year, the mashes accounted for 637 deaths, a number that, on the one hand, reflects an annual decrease of four and, on the other, points out a quarterly increase of 26. The three main causes of death were tumors (225 deaths), circulatory diseases (181) and respiratory tract (76) 35.3%, 28.4% and 11.9% of the total deaths, respectively.
At the end of March, Macao's total population consisted of 687,900 people, plus 1,500 or 0.2% in annual terms, “mainly due to the number of non -resident workers (TNR) domiciled” in the territory. The number of TNR rose 826 to 183,368 compared to the end of the previous quarter. The quarterly comparison points to a break of 0.1%, the equivalent of 400 people.
The female population (369,600) continued to overcome the male (318,300), representing 53.7% of the total. In the period under analysis, the number of marriages also registered a decline, both annually and quarterly.
In particular, there were annual and quarterly breaks of 23% and 18% for 717 marriages, ie 220 and 156 marriages, respectively. According to DSEC, 565 men and 578 women first married.
As for the movement of the population, in the period under analysis, the number of individuals from the interior of China newly arrived to Macao holders from “Salvo-Conduct” (685) descended 41, in annual terms, and 547 in sequential terms. However, that of individuals to whom a new residence authorization was granted (539) grew 267, compared to the same period of 2024, and 253 compared to the last quarter of last year.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Apomac expects fulfillment of “promises” in supporting the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apomac-espera-cumprimento-de-promessas-apoio-aos-idosos/</link><description>Yesterday took office for a new term of three years the managing bodies of the Macao's retirees, retired and pensioners association, the same day it marked its 24th anniversary. In the speech given during the commemorative dinner, Francisco Mannão, president of the board, reinforced the hope that, "in the near future, all the benefits announced by the government will become realities without major changes or disorders." Meanwhile, Jorge Fão, president of the General Assembly, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that he remains a desire for the association to see, during the mandate of Sam Hou Fai, the construction of a “enterprise where the elderly can live quietly, with all the conditions of assistance and security”.
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The expansion of support for the elderly remains one of the “Master lines” of the leaders of the Macao Retired, Reformed and Pensioners Association (Apomac), who yesterday afternoon at the entity's headquarters took office for another three -year term.
At night, during a commemorative dinner of the association's 24th anniversary, held at the fishermen's dock and was attended by a few hundred members, the president of Apomac stressed in his speech “the importance of the retired community and the contribution each made that the next generation could have a better and happier life”.
Francisco Mannhão spoke of a 24 -year course “lived with some difficulty and very challenge, due to the change of politics and practices that require adjustments of the whole order, which also requires us to continuous changes to maintain a cooperative and more harmonious environment, so that they can reach our desired plans of action”.
The leader stressed that Apomac “did everything” what was within his reach, to be recognized as a “useful association for society” where he is inserted. “We believe that the goal has been achieved,” said Francisco Marnhão.
Ahead in his speech, the number one of the directive body said that the benefits recently announced by the Chief Executive "also had some contribution by Apomac, which did not spare themselves to efforts to propose, in a timely manner, and to remind those who address the destinies of this city our needs and desires."
Mannão said he hoped that "in the near future, all the benefits announced by the government will become realities without major changes or disorders."
Showing “conscious” that the coming times will be “uncertainties”, due to geopolitical issues, the president of the Apomac Board believes that “with the union of all and the participation of the association we will bring this small boat to good port”.
In the closing, it referred to the media, stating that "they always gave voice to the retirees."
 
Desire to see a complex for the elderly
Meanwhile, the President of the General Assembly of Apomac, Jorge Fão, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the association's leaders remain hope that, during the current exercise of Sam Hou Fai, it may be a reality to build a “enterprise where the elderly can live quietly, with all the conditions of assistance and safety”.
The leader would like Macau to adopt policies similar to what happens on other stops, giving the examples of Australia and Canada, "where everything is available, including medical care." In Macau, “it doesn't exist,” he says.
The idea had already been expressed by this former deputy in an interview with this newspaper, in May 2023, and said that there was knowledge that there are more and more people with Alzheimer.
"In Macau we have over 2,500 people suffering from Alzheimer's," he said at the time, considering that "dementia is a very serious disease and especially affects people." Therefore, he reinforced, "the government should think of building some gated community where these elderly - who cannot be treated at the hospital or at home, because family members are unable to treat them - they could be and where they would be supported by specialized personnel."
On Apomac's birthday, founded in 2001, about two years after the transfer of sovereignty, Jorge Fão urges the government to “show that the promises directed to Macao's elderly by Sam Hou Fai are put into practice”.
On the other hand, it expresses, "I wish the words given by the Chief Executive at the meeting with the Macanese, held a few months ago, saying that the community is important and continues to support our projects, can pass on concrete acts."
Considering that “social and population support is fundamental in a society”, the leader points out that “in this group, the old class is the most important”, so he expects “government to work more for the people for these four years”.
At the end of 24 years of existence of Apomac, Jorge Fão feels “very honorable and proud, for the confidence placed by the members” in these managing bodies that have just taken office. “We will continue to work for them,” concluded one of the three macanese who founded the association. The other two São Francisco Mannhão and Herculano Ribeiro, all former employees of the Portuguese Administration.
 
400 members receive free services
Apomac is an organism of social solidarity and, for this reason, subsidized annually by the Government of MSar through the Macau Foundation. It provides free services to more than four hundred members, many of which do not dominate the Portuguese language.
The aid in obtaining survival pensions from Portugal's GENERAL CAIXA and specifically the need for annual “life proof” and support for IRS exemption is one of Apomac's main services.
The Association has a restaurant/canteen, which aims to promote Portuguese and Macaense cuisine, attended daily by dozens of members, but also open to other people in the community and tourists.
In addition, Apomac has been supported by members with motor disability or housed in homes or nursing homes, making periodic visits.
In the entertainment aspect, Apomac has a room for the practice of Mahjong's Chinese game and organizes periodic tourist tours to China and Hong Kong. Annually, it also promotes lectures on the education of a healthier life.
It is recalled that Apomac has been operating at its headquarters, for almost 20 years, a clinic directed to its members. The space closed doors on March 1, 2022. At issue, a legislative change that dictated that the clinic could only be subsidized by health services, opening services to the population, not through support from the Macau Foundation.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trade war without visible reflexes in the game</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/guerra-comercial-sem-reflexos-visiveis-jogo/</link><description>Macao casinos recorded high levels of demand during the Golden Week Commemorative Labor Day, including among the great gamblers, according to Citigroup analysts, who minimize potential impacts of commercial disputes between China and the USA
 
George Choi and Timothy Chau, Citigroup analysts, collected “impressive” data on the flow of bets on Macao casinos during “on -site” observations throughout the golden worker day, holidays on the Chinese continent celebrated 1 to 5 May. The results of this month's inquiry “highlight again that players are still in love with the game”, despite the disputes between China and the US about commercial tariffs, the banking group reported by the Gggrasia portal.
"Sinum American commercial conflicts ongoing so far do not seem to be discouraging players to take advantage of game offers and not Macao play," the Citigroup team emphasizes, highlighting in concrete "inelasticity of searching for the game."
The pair of analysts said that, for the first time since the launch of these monthly visits to the Macao casinos, it has unveiled more than a high -value player or "whale" to bet more than one million dollars of Hong Kong (HKD) per hand in a single day. The term "whales" is used to define customers who make bets equal to or greater than 100,000 HKD.
For the second consecutive month, the “player of the month” was detected in the “Supreme” room of the MGM Cotai Casino. “This player had a pile of chips of 10 million HKD in front of him and bet 2.9 million, the highest amount in our records,” exceeding a 1.2 million bet on Venetian Macao, George Choi and Timothy Chau reveal.
Overall, analysts found 49 “whales” - against 37 in May last year - which bet a total of 13.8 million HKD, and the average of these bets grew 79% to 281,000 HKD in annual terms. On the other hand, the average minimum bet, in the amount of 2,300 hkd, lowered 8% over the previous year, however, rose 3% compared to the 2025 Chinese New Year and reached the highest level this year.
The amount observed in table bets in the premium mass segment increased by 54% to 27.2 million HKD, within one year, equaling the record record during the Golden Week of China National Day in 2024. In turn, the number of players in the premium mass market grew 22% to 949.
With regard to the market quotas of the six game concessionaires, considering bets on the premium segment, “US-based operators were responsible for 63% of the total” during the golden week, “what is well within the historical track of the local division,” the citigroup team estimated. "This probably suggests that current commercial conflicts between China and the US are not affecting players' preferences to date," the banking group insisted.
According to the same report, MGM China "jumped to first place with a quota of approximately 30% in the" premium 'mass bets, thanks to the "whale" of 2.9 million HKD. " "We have also seen 14 10,000 hkd tables in its Supreme Room (the largest number we have ever seen). We suspect that this force can be attributed to the fact that MGM Cotai received Chinese singer Han Hong for a concert tonight," says analysts, convinced that this "is another data that shows that the certain offers of game -related products can boost the growth of the game sector."
In total, the bets observed in MGM Cotai rose to 5.1 million HKD, also indicate, placing the Galaxy Entertainment in second place in the survey, with about 22% stake in detected bets.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Educational Fund has channeled more than 315 million for schools</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fundo-educativo-canalizou-mais-de-315-milhoes-para-escolas/</link><description>The educational fund granted, between January and March, more than 315.3 million patacas to schools, and 32% of the total was for the development of special education. Among the institutions supported by this scope are the Portuguese School of Macau and the D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten. In addition, more than 207,000 patacas were assigned to students from Portuguese -speaking and ASEAN countries. The Culture Development Fund and the Sport Fund assigned subsidies of around 71.5 million and 20 million Patacas, respectively
 
Catarina Pereira
 
In the first quarter of this year, the Educational Fund (FE) channeled to the territory schools of over 315.3 million patacas, which represents an increase of 889% over the same period of 2024, according to data available on the public dissemination platform of public financial support information. About 32% of the amount assigned - more than 101 million - served to finance several institutions in the special education, including the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) and D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten.
According to official data, between January and March, EPM received about 2.7 million Patacas, under the financing plan for the development of schools of the 2024/2025 school year, specifically to support special education. In the field of promotion for success in learning and extracurricular development, the Portuguese Matrix School was supported by 355,200 patacas, also for the current academic year.
In turn, the FE granted Costa Nunes a total amount of 903,892 Patacas, for the Special Education Support Project of 2024/2025. In this case, the kindergarten has not received support for other projects.
Generations - International School, in Seac Pai Van, also received financial support from the Educational Fund for the Special Education Support Project of the School Year 2024/2025. The school, which opened doors in 2023, received 249,865 patacas to develop this type of education.
Other institutions that stand out in this context include the Concórdia School for Special Education, which received more than 5 million patacas, as well as the São Paulo School, which was awarded financial support of almost 3.4 million patacas, and the Caritas de Macao school, which received about 3.17 million. In turn, the Fukien School and the Our Lady of Fatima School received support from around 2.8 and 2.4 million, respectively.
 
More than 207 thousand patacas for Lusophone students
From the support granted by the Educational Fund, there are also those who are for students from Portuguese -speaking countries and the Association of Southeast Asia Nations (Asean).
Two students were supported by 24,000 patacas as a subsistence subsidy, under the merit grant plan for excellent students to move to Macau for the continuation of the studies. For bribes and summer accommodation, more than 159 thousand patacas were granted to a total of four students.
In total, the FE supported more than 207,000 patacas these students who continued their studies in the territory.
Several merit scholarships were also granted for postgraduate studies in the interior of China, which helped a total of 88 students. In this case, the assigned supports exceeded 4 million patacas.
The Educational Fund is subordinate to the Folder of Social Affairs and Culture, aiming at the availability of funding to projects and activities that contribute to the guarantee of educational quality, integrated skills and the competitiveness of students, as well as the provision of school social action.
On the other hand, the Culture Development Fund (FDC) and the Sport Fund (FD) made available the information regarding the first quarter of this year. Until March, the FDC granted more than 71.5 million patacas, an increase compared to the 65.5 attributed in the same period of 2024. Casa de Portugal, for example, received 138,600 patacas to perform literary, musical and theatrical creation activities, under the 2025 financial support plan.
Already the FD attributed in the first quarter more than 20 million patacas to different associations. The Macao Football Association, for example, received more than 1.15 million Patacas elite alloy from Macao and F.A. Cup (local competitions), for the Macao Football Championship and for administrative operation expenses, affiliation quotas of international federations, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>XI wishes to reinforce partnership with EU</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/xi-deseja-reforcar-parceria-ue/</link><description>The Chinese president said yesterday that China and the European Union (EU) should “oppose unilateral harassment” on the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations, which coincides with commercial tensions with the US.
Xi Jinping stressed that China and EU have “one of the most influential bilateral relations in the world” and framed this bond in a global scenario marked by uncertainty. "Humanity is again in a historical crossroads," he said, highlighting the role of bilateral cooperation as an international reference model.
"A healthy and stable relationship between China and the EU not only benefits both parties, but enlightens the path of the world," he said.
Xi said he attributed great importance to the development of Brussels relations and expressed the desire to work with the president of the European Council, António Costa, and with the president of the European Commission, Ursula Von de Leyen, to “deepen strategic communication, expand mutual opening and properly manage frictions and disagreements”.
The message also included a response from European leaders, who highlighted the evolution of the bilateral relationship and expressed their willingness to “face shared challenges together and promote peace, safety and sustainable development,” said Chinese diplomacy.
XI's appeal comes at a time when Beijing seeks to reinforce cooperation with Brussels to the growing pressure that is being targeted by Washington. China has repeatedly criticized the economic measures imposed by the US - such as customs tariffs or technological restrictions - and appealed to the EU to maintain an independent policy based on multilateralism and mutual benefit.
Chinese Prime Minister Li Qiang also exchanged messages with Costa and Von der Leyen, reaffirming Beijing's commitment to a "stable, constructive and mutual benefit" relationship.
The anniversary celebration also coincided with the announcement of the full resuming of the Legislative Dialogue between Beijing and the European Parliament (PE), after the mutual survey of the restrictions imposed in 2021. Beijing confirmed that they raised sanctions against five members of the PE who criticized the repressive policies directed at the Muslim minorities in Xinjiang in northwest China.
The Chinese MNE reaffirmed that cooperation with the EU “weighs more than competition” at a time when both parties seek to preserve a common agenda in the face of increasing commercial tensions with the US.
China is also ready to receive the president of the European Commission and the president of the European Council, before a summit between Beijing and the EU. China and EU will keep “high-level dialogues in strategic, economic, ecological and digital domains,” said Lin Jian, MNE spokesman.
Lin did not specify when European leaders will be able to visit China. In April, a European Council spokesman announced that the next summit between Brussels and Beijing would be held in China in July.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Measures to encourage companies to recruit the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/garantidas-medidas-para-incentivar-empresas-recrutar-idosos/</link><description>The executive ensures that he will elaborate measures to “encourage companies to recruit the elderly”, as part of the elaboration of the next phase of the setting action plan for the elderly support services. According to the president of IAS, the two social restoration companies that employ the elderly have faced several obstacles
 
At a time when the government is starting the planning and preparation work of the next phase of the Settlement of Action for Elderly Support Services, the authorities guarantee that “relevant measures” will be prepared with the aim of “encouraging companies to recruit the elderly”. The information arises in response to an interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U, who points to the difficulties that older people have to find work.
"Although the government has adopted several measures to support the elderly in access to employment, there are still many social obstacles, and as the aging of the population of Macau gets worse, the problem of the reintegration of the elderly in the labor market becomes increasingly evident. Labor reintegration of this group of the population.
In the same response, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Hon Wai, recalls that within the “Financial Support Plan for the Promotion of Employment Employment through Social Companies”, there are two social companies for elderly in the area of ​​Restoration. These provide 16 places full time and six part -time.
Hon Wai admits, however, that there are difficulties in this field. Pointing out that both went into operation during the pandemic, the president of IAS states that the market environment, daily operation and the development of companies were "relatively affected". "After the pandemic, society and the economy of Macao gradually recovered, in view of the constant change of the Macao business environment, the operation of companies, including social companies of the elderly, are faced with many challenges and pressures," he explains.
In this sense, both social companies make “adjustments”, with a view to attracting residents to restaurants, for example, enlargement of opening hours and increasing promotional actions.
"After reviewing the situation of monthly operation, the status of revenue of these projects has improved, but they still face many difficulties, especially the change in the purchase motifs and the consumer standards of residents, which have a major impact on social company projects," can be read.
The president of IAS ensures that he will “continue to pay attention and to evaluate the operating situation of the two social company projects to balance the experiences obtained and to accurately take into account the development of social companies in Macao”.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Visitors in the golden week with an annual increase of 40%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-na-semana-dourada-aumento-anual-de-40/</link><description>In the Golden Week of May, Macau received 849,000 visitors, with the number increased by 40.8% in annual terms. Specifically, 79% (678,000 people) are from the interior of China, which reflects an annual rise of 39%. At the same time, local borders checked more than 3.75 million tickets, an annual increase of 25.6%
 
Between May 1 and 5, the golden period brought 849,000 visitors to Macau (a daily average of 170,000 visitors), which translates into an annual climb of 40.8%, the Public Security Police (CPSP) said. As noted, on the 5th, last day of the holidays of Labor Day in the interior of China, the MSAR registered 92,605 visitors.
According to the direction of tourism services, in addition to the 111,000 Hong Kong visitors (13% of the total), which increased 42% annually, 678 thousand visitors from the interior of China (79% of the total) were reflected an annual increase of 39%.
At the same time, Macao border posts accounted for more than 3.75 million inputs and exits, which means a daily volume of 750,000 and an annual increase of 25.6%. In addition, CPSP recalled that, on the 2nd, several records were established, for example, the volume of 837,000 border passages and the number of visitors of almost 222,000.
On the other hand, Cheung Kin Chung, director of the Macao Tourism Agencies Association, said that in the golden week, the occupancy rate of hotels in general exceeded 90%, and many had even exhausted rooms.
According to the Chinese language press, the associative leader pointed out that during this high season, the tourist itineraries that make up points of interest to Macau and Hengqin were well welcomed by visitors, especially those that include several thematic parks and those that allow to “explore outdoor nature”. In addition, he noted that the large amount of online publications that recommend Macao tourism on social networks in the interior of China also played an important role in attracting tourists.
Cheung Kin Chung also mentioned that the tourist and hotel sector is aware of the “low time” of tourism before summer holidays. To “maintain the popularity of Macao tourism” during this period, he will launch “a series of tourist products”, from discount packages to “deep exploration” activities that involve “gastronomy, cultural connotation and visits Macau-Hengqin”.
On the other hand, according to the gongbei customs, May 1 to 5, Zhuhai's border post on the delta bridge checked more than 120,000 vehicle tickets, which represents an annual increase of 44%. On the 5th, the flow of vehicles that passed through this border exceeded 28,000, establishing a new record, reflecting a 50%homologous increase.
From the beginning of the year and until May 5, the volume of border -border tickets for Hong Kong and Macau has exceeded 1.3 million, which means annual growth of 34%, said the gongbei customs, noticing that the car rides made by residents of the RAE and transfronted visits to family members were the main factors that propelled the increase in the flow of vehicles that crossed the flows that crossed those who crossed those who crossed those who crossed those who crossed them. borders.
In addition, he said that the Wanzai Border Post also registered two new records in the golden week, having served a total of 33,000 entries and outputs from visitors in these five days, a 55%homologous increase, as well as 416 boat matches, an annual rise of almost 30%.
Already according to a balance of the National Immigration Administration, in the golden week, four million border passages of residents of Hong Kong, Macao and Taiwan residents were recorded, with the volume increasing 37.1% compared to the accounting period in the same year.
On the other hand, it completed a year yesterday the implementation of the “Hengqin-Macau” excursion measure, authorized for multiple entries and exits within seven days. According to the post of border inspections of Hengqin, over the last year, 120,000 tourists used this type of visa, with the monthly number of tours from 4,000 to over 20,000, between 2024 and this year.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>30 vacancies for internships in Beijing and Shanghai</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/30-vagas-para-estagios-em-pequim-xangai/</link><description>泡泡玛特



The Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs has already opened registration for the “Specific Internship Program for Macao Youth in Cultural and Creative Industries”. The stages, which will take place in Beijing and Shanghai, have a limited number of 30 vacancies
 
Registration for the “Specific Internship Program for Macao Youth in Cultural and Creative Industries” is open until 12:00 of May 23, with 30 vacancies for stages of 12 weeks and to be held between June and September.
According to the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs (DSAL), “Beijing Pop Mart” has released 15 vacancies for “Graphic Design Designer”, in an initiative that aims to “form the professional capacity of Macao Youth”. In the same vein, “Shanghai Hero Esports” provided 15 places for assistant to the director, in charge of government relations, project assistant, brand assistant and commissioner of electronic sports education, among others.
During the internship period, DSSA will assign, to each participant, a subsistence subsidy worth five thousand patacas, for every four weeks, and a single subsidy of four thousand patacas for travel insurance and travel.
The Directorate of Subsistence Affairs Services in the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao in Hengqin, in turn, will assign to each trainee a subsistence subsidy worth four thousand Renminbis, an accommodation allowance of two thousand Renminbis for every four weeks and insurance against accidental damage. Meals and other expenses will be “supported on their own,” says DSal.
Interested parties should be under 35 years old, bear the resident identity ticket, as well as a valid safe conduct for the entry and exit of the interior of China, hold a higher degree and have the appropriate technical skills for the position to which they apply, the statement indicates. Interested parties can visit the DSAL website for more information and to register.
Pop Mart, headquartered in Beijing, is a renowned company in the “conception and sale of fashion brands toys”. Hero ESPORTS, in turn, is a “leading company in the electronic game industry”, based in Shanghai.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cuba's “Invisible Side” in unpublished images of Frank Law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lado-invisivel-de-cuba-em-imagens-ineditas-de-frank-lei/</link><description>Photos Ass. Cultural Vila Taipa










Photos Ass. Cultural Vila Taipa







Photos Ass. Cultural Vila Taipa







Photos Ass. Cultural Vila Taipa








Photos Ass. Cultural Vila Taipa




Until July, the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association will present an exhibition of “Unpublished Photographs” by artist Frank Lei, who died in 2018. The collection of images demonstrates “the invisible side” of a trip from photographer to Cuba
 
From tomorrow, the art space of the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association will host an exhibition of unpublished photographs of Frank Law, sponsored by the Cultural Development Fund, until July 9 and with free admission.
According to the Association, the images of a trip from the photographer to Cuba, "an extremely important place in Frank's artistic career," captured "the daily life and the emotions of the Cuban people from a more subtle and contained perspective."
Black and white photographs “never shown before they offer a new window through time and space”, whereby viewers can experience the “island scenery that so deeply captivated Frank's soul” and “comprises the invisible side of your trip”.
The association states that this exhibition is "a recognition of the relevance of photography to document human realities and people's life circumstances." In addition to being able to revisit Frank Law's works, viewers can "embrace the emotions they evoke about the survival of a society and a country like Cuba."
The photographer, who died in 2022, visited the country for the first time in 1992, passing through cities such as Havana and Santiago de Cuba, and demonstrated a “deep attention and exploitation of Cuban culture and community”. Ten years later, he launched the exhibition and the book called “Cuba Cuba”, with a narrative and color images that presented “a vibrant and living impression of the island nation”.
Frank Law moved from Beijing to Macau at the age of 10. He graduated in journalism and worked as a reporter for Macau Daily News. Later, he went to live to Paris, where he studied cinema and photography, having won the “Life on the Street” contest of the 1991 “Musée de La Fotographie”.
In 1993, he returned to Macao and held several exhibitions, individual and collective, between Macau, Hong Kong, South Korea and France. He founded the artistic group “Stone Commune” and the “Art Space of Old Ladies' House”. In 2006, he published the photographic anthology “Walking and Watching” with the Pin-To Bookstore.
The president of the association said that the exhibition “pays tribute to Frank's singular dedication to artistic and cultural creative industries” and “shows the passion for Cuban culture that filled his heart and soul”. João O said it was "an honor to collaborate with the dialect to present this unprecedented collection." For the organization, the exhibition “further consolidates the position of Vila da Taipa as a leading cultural and artistic destination in Macao”, underlining its “invaluable contribution” to local cultural and creative industries.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mural in staircase evokes neighborhood history</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mural-em-escadaria-evoca-historia-de-bairro/</link><description>羅憲新街梯級美化項目拍攝



The Cultural Institute, the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association and some young local artists have created a new mural on the stone staircase from Rua de Tomás da Rosa, under the theme “The Roda do Time of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood”, to promote cultural and historical elements of the community
 
At the invitation of the Cultural Institute (IC), young artists sought to represent the “historical changes” in the Horta da Mitra neighborhood over a century, on the mural of the stone staircase of Rua de Tomás da Rosa.
The artistic work, with the theme “The Roda do Time of the Horta da Mitra neighborhood”, resulted from a partnership between the IC and the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association, in order to “promote cultural tourism and economic development in community neighborhoods.”
With the support of community associations and representatives, Lam Ka Hou, Jian Jun Cheng, Lian Jing Siang, NG Ka Mei, Un UT Keong and Ho Kon Pang have created a mural that reports “The History of Changes in the Zone over a century” with various iconic cultural traits and symbols.
According to the IC, the mural displays “The Vitality and the Human Touch” of the neighborhood, through the representation of the Bananeiras, Birds, the origin of the name “Horta da Mitra Bairro”, the neighborhood market and popular parties such as Leo dances in the TAC FOC Temple. The mural takes advantage of the gap of the steps “to create a three -dimensional effect”, with each mirror adorned with colorful flowers and illustrations.
Since 2021, the institute has collaborated with local artists in various neighborhoods, creating thematic murals focused on the history and origins of communities, “through a fusion of cultural creativity and art”. According to the body, the Murals of Travessa da Assunção, Largo do Pagode da Barra, the outer wall of Nam Kwong warehouses, Travessa da Boa Vista and the ladder stairs in the mud have become popular photography points on social networks, spreading cultural tourism.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SHIN MIN AND SEUL GALLERY WATCH “MGM DISCOVERIES ART PRIZE”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/shin-min-galeria-de-seul-vencem-mgm-discoveries-art-prize/</link><description>The SHIN Min and Seoul Gallery project won the “MGM Discoveries Art Prize” in the latest edition of Art Basel Hong Kong. The prize celebrates the originality and creativity of emerging artists
 
Shin Min, represented by Seoul Gallery P21, won the first “MGM Discoveries Art Prize” with his work “Ew! There is Hair in the Food !!”. The awards ceremony took place at MGM Lounge during Art Basel Hong Kong.
According to MGM, Shin used “powerful symbolism and personal experiences to confront social norms and systemic injustices”, hoping that this work will serve “as a powerful tool for increasing society awareness” and improving working conditions for the public.
Shin min and P21 received a $ 50,000 monetary prize and an MGM invitation to hold an exhibition and participate in artistic exchanges in Macao.
According to the president and executive director of MGM China, the company and Art Basel Hong Kong share a “common vision of promoting global artistic and cultural development”. Kenneth Feng said the joint creation of "MGM Discoveries Art Prize" is "a commitment to discover emerging artists and celebrate their originality and creativity."
It also stressed that “Macao is closely united with Hong Kong” and expanding the global network and the exchange of Macao.
In the same vein, the director of Art Basel Hong Kong highlighted the “remarkable set of artists” presented in the “sector of the discoveries”, which presents solo projects of emerging artists. Angelle Siyang-Le thanked MGM for the “invaluable support”, as well as the artists, the galleries and the five members of the jury involved.
The operator also organized an exclusive guided tour of Art Basel Hong Kong for about 50 Macao's cultural and educational representatives and educational representatives. In a statement, MGM reiterates that continues to “be committed to bringing new art prospects to Macau and the Great Bay”, fostering creative talent and contributing to the growth of the region's artistic and cultural landscape.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PME ask for support for banks for credit access</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pme-pedem-apoio-aos-bancos-para-acesso-credito/</link><description>Since the launch of the Bank Credit Interest Bonus Plan for Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs), at the end of last month, some SMEs found that banks currently adopt requirements and higher conditions for loan approval than in gender plans implemented during the pandemic. According to the newspaper "or Mun", in this sense, Andy Wu, director of the Federal General Commercial Association of Small and Medium Enterprises of Macau, hopes that banking institutions, without prejudice to taking into account the financial risks, properly support the SMEs in loan approval, in order to relieve the pressing difficulties they are facing. In addition, Andy Wu urged the government, the bank sector and commercial associations to cooperate to reinforce the dissemination of procedures, requirements and formalities of request to the Bonus Plan, along with the SMEs. On the other hand, he warned that SMEs, in turn, should assess cautiously and comprehensively the risks before moving on with the requirements, and make good use of loans received and the annual 4% bonus rate to accelerate their update and transformation, increasing long -term competitiveness.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Conference in Lisbon addresses “Crossroads” Musical in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/conferencia-em-lisboa-aborda-encruzilhada-musical-em-macau/</link><description>The eighth edition of the Lisbon Conference: Chinese music and musical instruments/expand horizons: embracing the wide variety of music and Asian dance starts today at Mafra National Palace. On the last day of the event, Saturday, the sessions will take place at the Institute of Ethnomusiology. Highlight, at the opening of the four -day program, for the theme “Macau: A Crossroads for Chinese and European Music”, with interventions on Portuguese musical art in Macau, approach to musical instruments in the Chinese temples of Macao and the rebirth of Portuguese classical music concerts in the territory. The speakers are Shao Xiao Ling, from the University of Aveiro, Enio de Souza and Rui Magno, both from the Faculty of Social and Human Sciences of the New University of Lisbon (FCSH) and José Amável Pinto de Sá, from Portimão. In the late afternoon there will be a concert at the Casa da Música Francisco Alves Gato, in Mafra. The opening will also highlight Asia's traditional popular performance arts, including topics such as the “Introduction to Chinese Folk Music,” by Dutch researcher Franck KouWenhoven. MUSICAL ACTIONS will be followed, including “Yulong County Ethnic Culture Troupe” from the city of Lijiang. In the remaining days, the debates will focus on the integration and innovative development of Western musical heritage into the inner Mongolia, Chinese rock in the United Kingdom and the influence of Bollywood on Ethiopia's popular music. On the last day, are scheduled music sessions and conversations at the Institute of Ethnomusiology - Center for Studies in Music and Dance, based at FCSH.</description><pubDate>2025-05-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vatican installs chimney in the sistine chapel for the conclave</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/vaticano-instala-chamine-na-capela-sistina-para-conclave/</link><description>The Vatican installed, on the weekend, the chimney that will announce that the cardinals, confined to the Sistine Chapel from this week, elected the successor of Pope Francis.
A total of 133 cardinals will vote, starting on Wednesday, under Michelangelo frescoes to choose the new spiritual leader of the 1.4 billion Catholics. The so -called “Church Princes” will make four daily votes: two in the morning and two in the afternoon, except on the first day.
After voting, voting bulletins will be burned in a oven to announce the result to the world: black smoke if they cannot reach the necessary two -thirds majority; White smoke if "Habemus Papam".
Tens of thousands of people in St. Peter's Square and millions of people around the world who watch on television will be eyeing the narrow brown cylinder, waiting for the great announcement.
There is a “more spiritual,” AFP Diana Ispego, a Mexican resident in the US, told the AFP, pointing to the chimney.
The Sistine Chapel has two ovens linked to the same chimney, from which comes the only indication of what happens inside. In the oldest, voting bulletins and cardinals are burned. The second, more modern, is used to announce the result of the vote. From the latter, with the help of chemicals, comes the black smoke (if the cardinals do not reach an agreement) or white, when a new pope is elected.
The chimney was installed by a Firefighters from the Holy See, which climbed to the top of the roof of the majestic chapel. The work went unnoticed to most tourists present in St. Peter.
The installation coincided with the resumption of general congregations on Friday, where about 200 cardinals gathered to discuss the priorities for the future of this 2,000-year institution.
This meeting emphasized the spread of the Catholic faith, the need for unity, and the risk of “hiring”-problems such as sexual abuse and financial scandals-among other topics, said Vatican spokesman Matteo Bruni.
Bruni also reported that of the 133 cardinals able to vote for being under 80, only four left to arrive in Rome. He confirmed the absences of Spanish Antonio Cañizares and Kenyan John Njue.
Eighty percent of these voters were appointed by Francis. Many come from the “periphery” of the world, areas that for years have been marginalized by the Catholic Church. Most people are unknown and these meetings serve as a place to hear ideas and exchange views.
 
"There will be no Francis II"
Conclave is a meeting that dates back to the Middle Ages, when the idea of ​​electing a sovereign was a revolutionary idea.
The deliberations are kept strictly confidential, under penalty of instant excommunication. Mobile phones and any internet access are prohibited. Cardinals are not allowed to read newspapers, listen to radio or watch the television. Any contact with the outside world is prohibited.
"The world needs a completely coherent person," Cardinal Salvadoran Gregorio Rosa Chávez, 82, told reporters. "These people are not very common."
Many cardinals agree that the election will be short, but Vatican Marco Politi expert is skeptical.
"This is the first conclave in 50 years when there is a strong feeling of fracture within the church," explained the expert, who foresees a choice "between a decelected pope and another slowly advances."
“There will be no Francis II,” he predicts.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>