<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Deputies approve Budget 2026, but ask for more support for consumption</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputados-aprovam-orcamento-2026-mas-pedem-mais-apoios-ao-consumo/</link><description>The Hemicycle approved, in general, the 2026 Budget law proposal yesterday. However, several deputies asked for more measures to encourage consumption and the attribution of electronic cards. The Secretary for Economy and Finance stressed that forecasts must be cautious, due to uncertainties, and did not respond to these requests. Tai Kin Ip also said that the “savings” from cash checks – due to the ineligibility of residents who are not in Macau for at least half of the year – will be channeled into social support. On the other hand, he refused to advance forecasts for the Macao SAR's GDP for next year
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
Despite some doubts and requests for incentives for consumption and the launch of electronic cards, for example, the deputies approved yesterday, in general, and unanimously, the proposed law for the 2026 Budget. In the Legislative Assembly, the Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, stressed that “uncertainties persist in the external environment and in the economy”, despite the number of visitors having been growing and the integrated tourism and leisure sector maintaining a trend of “balanced growth”. In this sense, he stressed that forecasts must be “prudent”.
According to the proposal, revenues of 118.8 billion patacas are expected in 2026, expenses of 113.5 billion and a budget balance of 5.3 billion. As for the game's gross revenues for the entire year, the estimate is that they will reach 236 billion patacas, a value below that initially estimated for this year (240 billion), but above the revised value in the middle of this year (228 billion). As for measures to promote the well-being of the population, the amount to be channeled is 26.8 billion patacas, an increase of 3.8%, seen as “adequate and proportional” by the government official.
Despite the increase in the scope of support for residents, deputies defended the launch of other measures. Ella Lei was the first to speak, asking whether any measures are planned to encourage consumption. "We continue to see difficulties in the business environment of community neighborhoods, taking into account the change in the consumption behavior of visitors and residents. How will the situation be resolved? How does the budget take these difficulties into account", he asked, adding that policies to encourage consumption will "contribute to the reconversion and appreciation of the business fabric".
In the same vein, Chan Hao Weng pointed out that the consumer market “is weak” and that small and medium-sized companies and the population are struggling with “difficulties”. "In low seasons, will a consumer card be issued? For example, 10 thousand patacas", he said, stating that a traditional household appliances store in Macau, "Tai Peng Electronics and Appliances", will close its doors. His colleague, José Pereira Coutinho, followed the same path: "This electronic card, in addition to helping vulnerable families, can also support companies. Injecting 3,000 or 5,000 patacas into the consumer card could help a lot of people and revitalize community areas."
Pereira Coutinho also said it was “regrettable” that there would not be an increase in public servants’ salaries next year. Salaries will not change, following the opinions of the Public Service Workers' Remuneration Assessment Committee, indicates the justification note on the Budget law proposal.
 
“Savings” from checks allocated for social support
Ella Lei also asked Tai Kin Ip about how the amount saved under the cash contribution plan will be used, given that, from this year onwards, changes have been implemented, with eligible residents having to be in Macau at least 183 days a year.
In his response, the Secretary said that the “savings” will be allocated to social support. According to him, in the Budget for 2025, spending on checks was set at 7.48 billion patacas, based on 750 thousand beneficiaries. However, due to the introduction of new eligibility criteria, only 575 thousand people were “qualified”, resulting in a real expenditure of 5.6 billion patacas.
Due to the three-year period to appeal the decision, next year's budget will be a little more flexible, with an estimate of 6.64 billion patacas, explained Tai Kin Ip. As noted, although expenses with the granting of cash checks have decreased, expenses with welfare measures have increased by 800 million patacas. "The amount we keep will be used for the well-being of the population. It will be used for different assistance services to the population", he highlighted.
As part of measures to support the population, the Government will disburse 26.7 billion in 2026, an increase of 3.8%, said the Secretary. In addition to the cash check, there are also health vouchers, subsidies for the payment of electricity tariffs for housing units and the continuous development and improvement program, among others.
There are also measures aimed at education and support for the most vulnerable sections of the population, on which the Government will spend 15.3 billion. As part of the allocation of funds, as an extraordinary distribution of budget balances, the Executive will spend 3.68 billion.
On the other hand, in addition to continuing the tax deduction and exemption measures implemented throughout this year – such as the return to residents of 60% of the 2024 professional tax collection, up to a maximum of 14 thousand patacas, for example – the Executive also decided to move forward with the exemption from stamp duty on transfers of assets up to a value of six million patacas, in the acquisition of autonomous housing units by residents of legal age.
In this context, Chan Hao Weng wanted to know when the stamp duty exemption will come into effect, but the Secretary did not respond. "The main objective is to alleviate tax burdens for those interested in buying a house. We hope that residents will benefit as well as the real estate market", said Tai Kin Ip only. Kevin Ho asked the Government to consider moving forward with the same policy, but for commercial buildings.
 
Secretary does not risk making a GDP forecast
Noting that the budget “is very prudent”, deputy Joey Lao wanted to know how the Government arrived at the figure of 236 billion patacas in gross gaming revenue. “If we divide it by 12 months, it’s 19.66 billion patacas”, he said, also asking the government official to talk about the estimates for GDP in 2026.
In his reply, Tai Kin Ip said that, in terms of the game for this year, “five months did not meet expectations”. “Looking at the uncertainty inherent in the economy, this could bring a significant impact or challenge to our microeconomy”, he argued.
As for GDP, the Secretary did not venture a number. "It's extremely difficult to make an accurate forecast, no one can do it. The previous year we didn't make an optimistic forecast either, but in the end we came to know that it was better than what we predicted", he stated.
"Taking into account the geopolitical tension that we are seeing around us, there are uncertainties. On the one hand, we can count on the development of our country to support our economic growth, but on the other we have to be prepared against any slippage. As for GDP for next year, it is difficult to make an accurate forecast", he reiterated.
Joey Lao asked again about GDP, saying that cities and provinces on the Mainland make objective forecasts, and pointing out that this information is important for investors. Tai Kin Ip later said that in Mainland China “the conditions are much more stable”, which is why it is easier to make estimates. “We are subject to external factors, we are an economy exposed to the outside,” he added.
 
“Green light” for Advertising law and private health institutions
The Advertising Law and the Law on the activity of private institutions providing health care received the “green light” from deputies yesterday in the Legislative Assembly. Regarding the first, the discussion revolved around online advertising and misleading advertising involving other jurisdictions. In this context, the Secretary for Economy and Finance explained that, if other jurisdictions are involved, “it is necessary to see the connection link, to know if in Macau there is any center of activity, any headquarters or individual carrying out activity”. "If it exists, it is a connecting link and we can regulate and prosecute. If it is in another jurisdiction, we can do nothing," said Tai Kin Ip. Regarding private health institutions, several deputies asked questions about the role they will play in the development of 'big health', with the Government believing that it could be a “significant role”, in the words of the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>José Maneiras leaves an architectural legacy and an “example of civics”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jose-maneiras-deixa-legado-arquitectonico-um-exemplo-de-civismo/</link><description>Architect José Maneiras passed away in Macau at the age of 90. His work included collaboration on urban plans and the creation of residential and institutional architectural projects. He was president of the then Leal Senado, between 1989 and 1993. In the reactions to his death, recorded by the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Carlos Marreiros highlights the “work together” in the requalification of Tap Seac and the activity that José Maneiras maintained until the end of his life as a member of the Albergue. Rui Leão praises his professional colleague as someone who “fought hard for the city’s issues” and Jorge Neto Valente highlights his “example of civility”. Anabela Ritchie was “shocked” by the disappearance of the architect, with whom she had a “strong connection”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
José Maneiras passed away in Macau on Monday night at the age of 90. The architect dedicated his professional life to Macau and was one of the first professionals to begin practicing architecture from local studios. He was, in fact, one of the founders of the Macau Architects Association, in 1987.
His work, considered to have a “very unique style” by professional colleagues, was mainly aimed at residential buildings. He also worked on the project to requalify the Tap Seac square, alongside Carlos Marreiros and civil engineer José Chui Sai Peng, and also coordinated the design team for the road reorganization of the Carlos d’Assumpção roundabout.
José Celestino da Silva Maneiras was born in the territory in 1935, into a Macanese family rooted in local society. He remained in Portugal for nine years, where he arrived in 1953, in the post-war period, and when the Estado Novo regime allowed specific openings to the international context, as evidenced by the holding, in Lisbon, of the III congress of the International Union of Architects.
The return to their homeland was part of a brief migratory movement that brought a group of young Portuguese architects to Macau, such as Manuel Vicente, Natália Gomes, Ramires Fernandes and Jorge Silva. They then joined the local government's technical staff, developing urban plans for the city.
The team, coordinated by Manuel Vicente, chose to propose partial plans, containing guidelines for alignments and heights. He succeeded Manuel Vicente in overseeing the work on the Liceu Pedro Nolasco by Raul Chorão Ramalho (one of the most significant modern buildings in the Portuguese presence), later fighting against its demolition.
From 1967 onwards, José Maneiras embarked on private business, maintaining a “handmade” production studio, with the collaboration of one or two designers, and selecting orders, which allowed him to survive times when projects were less requested.
Of his work built during this phase, and located essentially in Macau, it is difficult to find intact examples. In the 1960s, the architect designed and created a set of residential buildings with a brutalist bent, within the framework of the demands of tropical regions, which probably constituted his most important creative phase.
Of this list, we highlight the housing complexes on Rua da Praia Grande (Conjunto São Francisco, 1964), on Estrada do Visconde de São Januário (two residences, 1965), “Belle Court” in Penha (house and block of apartments, 1968) or the residential program for the blind, at the request of Santa Casa da Misericórdia (1970), on Rua Sete do Bairro da Areia Preta.
The city's recent growth, however, has stigmatized “modern” buildings. The Si Toi – Hong Kong Bank commercial building (currently HSBC – “Hong Kong and Shanghai Bank Corporation”, 1982), also designed by him, is an exemplary case of this phenomenon.
He favored small-scale projects, such as renovations of buildings of heritage value, and continued “old” practices, such as monitoring the work or creating detailed drawings. The Monument to the Macanese Diaspora, on Rua São Tiago da Barra, opened in 2001, fits into these concerns.
He also became a consultant at the company Nam Van, for the Praia Grande Bay Plan, and president of the General Assembly of the Macau Civil Engineering Laboratory. In 2006, he was named honorary member of the Order of Architects of Portugal. His work in defense of the dignity of architectural practice, in a context of high professional competition, is considered an ethical example for new generations.
 
Great dedication to the land and “valuable” professional
José Maneiras' work, his way of being in society and his love for the city are evident in the reactions that the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper recorded.
Jorge Neto Valente lived with the architect for half a century. “As I came to Macau as a soldier, I met him through his father who was an army officer, and from then on we were friends throughout our lives”, recalls the lawyer, for whom the two were “companions in many struggles”, such as the founding of the Macau Democratic Center.
“He was an example of civics, putting great commitment to the civic activities in which he was involved, always showing great dedication to the land where he was born, as well as an example in his profession”, highlights Jorge Neto Valente. “Everyone sympathized”, he points out.
Carlos Marreiros expresses “enormous sadness” over his death. “He was a great friend, colleague and partner at the Albergue, who even at the age of 90 had ideas, always collaborating in activities”, he highlights, also pointing out the fact that José Maneiras was an honorary member of the Círculo dos Amigos da Cultura.
As a person, “he was a serious man, with principles and values, someone who did not question his independence and freedom”, he highlights. As an architect, he was a “very valuable” professional, he emphasizes, recalling the “work together” in the requalification of Praça do Tap Seac and the space. On the other hand, “it helped me a lot”, as president of Leal Senado, in pedestrianizing Praça do Leal Senado, he adds.
Among the works produced, Carlos Marreiros highlights the Center for the Blind at Santa Casa da Misericórdia, in the Areia Preta area. “It is closed today, but it was an advanced work for the time, all of it ramped to avoid stairs and architectural barriers.”
“This in the 60s was something innovative, a brutalist piece, with exposed concrete, the walls painted white”, he highlights, concluding that there are other works with an important mark by José Maneiras, such as a house for public servants, close to the Conde de São Januário Hospital, and a building located in front of the Military Club. “This is a building with a very rigorous geometry, very functionalist and one would almost say minimalist today, with no decoration, but a very well designed piece”, he points out.
 
“Big picture” of architecture
Rui Leão also spoke, heartfelt, about his now missing colleague. “First of all, he was a great friend and a person who played a very important civic and cultural role in Macau, having always been a reference for me”, he asserts. “Even as a studio architect and later as president of the Leal Senado, he was a person who fought hard for the city's issues, and in that sense he was a great figure in Macau's architecture”, he adds.
Rui Leão believes that his colleague leaves a legacy. “It has a very rich set of works and very good architecture, which it built between the 60s and 90s”.
Anabela Ritchie was “shocked” when she learned of the death of the Macanese architect. “I didn’t expect it, because he was well, despite his age”, said the former president of the Legislative Assembly, highlighting that she had a “strong connection with him”.
Both had, together, spent more than three years in the Leal Senado. They belonged to the administrative commission appointed by the Government of Portugal to prepare the elections for the Leal Senado. “I really enjoyed working with him, I on the culture, archive, public relations side, and he on the technical side, in a very interesting period”, he recalls.
José Maneiras was a “brother” of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia of Macau. The Ombudsman says he met him in the mid-70s, shortly after the 25th of April, and with him he had “the privilege of depriving and respecting”.
António José de Freitas emphasizes that he was “a prestigious figure recognized by all, who was part of those who believed in staying in Macau and in the continuity of our Holy House, of which he was a regular and participative Brother since 1997”. From his perspective, “Macau lost a reference Macanese who felt perfectly at home in the two cultures present in this city”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural exhibitions in Macau grew 905% in 10 years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/exposicoes-culturais-em-macau-cresceram-905-em-10-anos/</link><description>Between 2014 and 2024, more cultural and entertainment spaces were established in the Macao SAR, such as museums and cinemas, and, in general, the number of sessions and visitors increased significantly. On the other hand, cinemas, theaters and variety and dance shows have seen smaller audiences. However, artistic director Tam Chi Chun explained to TRIBUNA DE MACAU that reduced audiences are not necessarily a negative phenomenon. Rita Wong, director of operations at Cinemateca Paixão, also believes that, although there are now more convenient options than cinemas, such as streaming platforms, both can coexist



































PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The cultural and entertainment offer in Macau soared between 2014 and 2024, according to data from the Statistics and Census Services Department analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. During the period under review, the number of cultural sessions increased by almost double. In 2014, there were 41,441 cultural events, and last year this number reached 80,555. Similarly, and in general, the total number of spectators at cultural events grew by 158%, to 17.6 million, in 2024, which represents an increase of 10.8 million, compared to the 6.8 million recorded in 2014.
In terms of infrastructure, at the end of last year, there were 36 museums, 14 more (+64%) than in 2014. In the same period, the number of cinemas doubled to 10, with the number of screens almost tripling, from 16 to 47 (+194%). However, not all types of events registered positive developments, if we consider the relationship between the number of visitors and the number of sessions.
Cultural exhibitions grew 905% in 10 years, from 691 to a total of 6,946 last year. In 2024, there were also more than 4.3 million people visiting artistic exhibitions, 77% more than in 2014. However, the significant increase in the frequency of exhibitions diluted the average number of visitors per exhibition, which fell from 3,594 to 632.
For Tam Chi Chun, producer, director and artistic director of the Experimental Theater Group “Pequena Cidade”, “when the cultural audience in a city reaches a certain volume, visitors can go from spectators to ‘cultural curators’”, with increasingly specific interests, and choose to explore “alternative themes in greater depth”. “Under these circumstances, the number of spectators naturally becomes small”, he pointed out.
“I lived in Europe for some time and noticed that many cultural activities there have a relatively small number of visitors”, said Tam.
However, the member of the Cultural Development Advisory Council stressed that “this does not entirely reflect the situation in Macau”. “It is true that many activities are being organized, but with the aim of achieving some ‘key performance indicators’. Perhaps because the Government wants to hold more events, while the private sector also needs to organize activities”, highlighted Tam Chi Chun.
The theater producer argued that the city should invest in “in-depth projects, instead of looking for quantity”. "However, I believe that the emergence of more alternative cultural activities demonstrates that culture has really taken root in the territory. It is no longer just the model in which a master speaks on stage, while thousands of people worship him, then return home to wash clothes and cook, without transforming their own thinking."
Tam continued, with an example: "A master gave a lecture in Macau, having aroused someone's interest. A decade later, and after studying, this person decided to organize his own activity in Macau, with his own interest. His activity may attract only 10 spectators. But, isn't this the true transmission of culture? I think this has much more meaning than always following the model with a famous master in the lecture and a thousand people worshiping him", he asserted.
The artistic director believes that “a spectator who values ​​diverse perspectives and ways of thinking expects to be able to find activities on specific themes”. "I don't mind seeing more cultural events with a smaller audience, precisely because these activities are aimed at minority groups. It is through the abundance of alternative cultural activities that the cultural diversity of a city can be seen", he maintained.
“The cultural activities that we find on the streets of New York, Paris and Berlin are never repetitive, but quite diverse”, argued Tam Chi Chun. "Why do we perceive these cities as vibrant and dynamic? The ideal final form lies in an abundance of distinct cultural activities, each one not requiring a high number of visitors", he stressed.
“If the public has many options, the organizers do not need to feel sad because of a reduced number of spectators, or the difficulties in obtaining financial support, since the cultural themes they intend to explore are ‘alternative’”, he asserted.
Saying that the population is small, he considers that, “with a 900% increase in cultural activities, it is impossible for us to also gain 900% more time per year to attend these activities”. “The most important thing is not just to produce more programs, but to make society believe again that culture is not a mere accessory, but has its own reasons for existing”, concluded Tam.
However, Tam Chi Chun admitted that his perspective represents “a relatively idealistic desire that one still has to strive for.” “The central meaning of the existence of culture in Macau has not yet been seen as a social consensus”, pointed out the director of “Pequena Cidade”, stressing that this issue “represents a crucial issue for citizens, cultural creators and political decision-makers”.
 
Growth of Macau cinema
Last year, 68,846 film screenings were recorded, 91% more than the 36,133 recorded in 2014. In fact, 1,897 different films were shown throughout 2024, representing an increase of 277% compared to 2014. Furthermore, the screening of films produced in Macau more than quadrupled in that decade, going from 50 to 206 (+312%).
Rita Wong, head of operations at Cinemateca Paixão, believes that the number of local productions should continue to grow. “In 2014, Macau cinema was still taking ‘baby steps’”, recalled Rita Wong. "In the 2000s, there was no Macau cinema. It started around 2007, but only with documentaries and animations, without even short films and I believe the first short film appeared in 2012." “Local directors and students started producing short films between 2012 and 2013. Hence, there were already some films produced locally in 2014, with only one or two being feature films”, noted Rita Wong, also remembering the film “Sisterhood” by filmmaker Tracy Choi as a cultural landmark.
Rita Wong explained that the return of students from abroad, the organization of film festivals in Macau and other Government initiatives have encouraged film production in the territory, giving the example of the Panorama do Cinema de Macau festival. At the same time, “the Cinematheque was also established with the aim of presenting more Macau films”, he added.
Despite an explosion in the supply of films, in the decade under review, the number of spectators in cinemas fell by 41%, to just over one million, in 2024, coinciding with a period in which streaming services rose in terms of popularity. In 2024, the average number of spectators for each film showing in Macao SAR cinemas was 15, compared to 48 in 2014.
The director of the Audiovisual Association “CUT” also recognized that cinemas face challenges, however, she considers that the two consumption experiences are “completely different”. "Before Netflix, we also had 'DVDs,' 'Blu-Rays.'
The director added that, “especially nowadays, there are different types of experiences, like ‘IMAX’, in Taipa”. Furthermore, “different events are also organized, such as bringing directors or some guests to speak after the session, so that it is not just a film”. "After the film we can communicate with other people. It doesn't have to be one or the other, both [the experiences] can coexist", he considered.
With theaters, the same phenomenon occurred. Despite there being 524 more sessions than in 2014 (842), there were 19.7 thousand fewer spectators. The average number of viewers per session fell from 240 to 133.5 in 2024.
In the same period of time, variety shows and dances suffered drops of 22% and 56%, respectively, in session frequency. In terms of audience, variety shows lost 43% of spectators and dances lost more than half (-57%).
In the opposite direction, the concerts attracted more than 1.8 million spectators last year, compared to 481 thousand in 2014. Taking into account that 1,096 concerts were held in 2024, 291 fewer than a decade before, the average number of spectators per concert shot up to 1,701 people (+390%).
 
Students from abroad “monopolize” local art courses
In the field of education, if we look at higher education, comparing the 2014 and 2015 academic year with the 2024 to 2025 academic season, the total number of students enrolled in arts courses increased more than five times, from 1,129 to 5,855 (+419%).
However, within a decade, these vacancies began to be disproportionately filled by students from abroad compared to local students. Of the 5,855 students enrolled in the last academic year, 5,054 came from outside Macau, representing 86% of the total. A decade earlier, the 627 students from abroad represented just over half (56%).
If we only analyze the number of finalists from art courses, these increased from 140 to 1,143 (+716%), between 2014 and 2024. In 2014, the proportion of finalists resident and abroad was practically balanced, with 68 local and 72 coming from outside Macau. However, after 10 years, 998 students from abroad represented 87% of art course finalists, compared to just 145 local students.
Tam Chi Chun considers the phenomenon to be "a coin with two sides. On the one hand, it proves the attractiveness of Macau's artistic education, as it manages to attract students from abroad. However, the most important thing is that, in four years, students are able to absorb the local culture of Macau, by feeling and learning in this land", he emphasizes, "instead of simply acquiring knowledge that could be obtained anywhere in the world".
In this context, Tam rejected the idea that there is a risk of loss of cultural identity. “If students understand Macau, and learn the city’s cultural language, it can be known abroad, through these students who will take it to the world”. "In my opinion, this is what we should strive for. The presence of international students is a good start. By studying in Macau, they will feel the life, culture and humanistic environment of this land", reinforced the director.
At the same time, "local students or teachers they meet will probably discuss local arts with them. Or they might attend film festivals," he suggested. “All of this constitutes the process of cultural experience in Macau”.
However, although Tam Chi Chun recognized that there is a certain marginalization of local artists, he did not attribute full responsibility to the presence of international students. "It is known that international students tend to represent a high percentage among students at art institutions around the world. However, I consider that local artists are marginalized because the focus of the cultural market, such as concerts and highlight programs at art festivals or international music festivals, is usually biased towards artists from abroad", lamented the director.
Tam Chi Chun defended “financial support to be able to produce more localized programs and reissues”. "Essentially, a type of support that can allow artists to develop in a more stable way. But this financial support should not be short-term, for just one year, for example, or merely for the organization of a limited number of events", he concluded.
 
EVOLUTION BETWEEN 2014 AND 2024
Number of cultural events
increased from 41,441 to 80,555
 
Spectators of cultural sessions
rose from 6.8 million to 17.6 million
 
Cultural exhibitions
increased from 691
to 6,946
 
Film sessions
grew from 36,133
to 68,846
 
Film projections
produced in Macau
went from 50 to 206
 
Students on arts courses
rose from 1,129 to 5,855</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Revision of the Domestic Violence Law defended</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendida-revisao-da-lei-de-violencia-domestica/</link><description>Wong Kit Cheng yesterday defended the revision of the Law on preventing and combating domestic violence, as well as the provisions of the Penal Code relating to sexual crimes
 
Catarina Pereira
 
On the occasion of the International Day for the Elimination of Violence Against Women, Wong Kit Cheng took advantage of the period before the agenda, in the Legislative Assembly, to highlight the deficiencies that still exist in terms of support for victims of domestic violence in the territory, but also with regard to counseling for aggressors. The deputy immediately defended the review and improvement of legal diplomas.
"Next year marks the 10th year of the entry into force of the Domestic Violence Law and the 9th year of the revision of the provisions of the Penal Code relating to sexual crimes, therefore, all parties involved have already accumulated some cases and experiences in the field of law enforcement, judicial and support. Therefore, in my opinion, there is a need to review these legal diplomas, after a certain period of application", he stated. In this sense, he asked public services, associations, service institutions and frontline personnel to take stock and present a report on “the real situation observed in the execution of the law”.
Citing data from the Institute of Social Action, he noted that, in 2017, at the beginning of the law's validity, there were 96 cases of domestic violence, while in 2023 there were 40, in 2025 a total of 55 and in the first half of this year 27 cases. “There is, therefore, a decreasing trend, which reflects that, with the joint effort of the Government, associations and the population, the prevention and fight against domestic violence have achieved some results”, he added.
However, the deputy linked to the General Women's Association stressed that, according to the practical experience of the associations that deal with these cases, "there are still situations in which victims hesitate to report, either because of the concept of 'dirty laundry is washed at home', or because they want to 'guarantee children a complete family', or, even, because they are full-time family caregivers and feel economic and housing pressure".
“Moreover, mandatory participation in prevention plans or psychological counseling is only applicable to aggressors convicted of the ‘crime of domestic violence’, therefore, in relation to other cases in which the sentence has not yet been handed down or the aggressors have been convicted of another crime, they will not receive psychological counseling in a timely manner”, he continued.
In this sense, he suggested “a comprehensive and long-term support mechanism, to resolve problems of housing, economy, employment, child custody, marriage and support of victims, so that they and their families can adapt, in an orderly way, to life changes”. He also argued that it is necessary to “strengthen counseling services for perpetrators and victims, and their respective minors and family members”. In this field, he also called for the improvement of the rules on additional penalties, “obliging perpetrators to receive advice and education in advance”.
In addition to domestic violence, the parliamentarian also called for attention to cases of sexual violence against women and children. For Wong Kit Cheng, it is essential to promote dissemination actions about the Law to prevent and combat domestic violence and the legal provisions relating to sexual crimes, creating an environment of “zero tolerance”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UM launches three new master's degrees</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-lanca-tres-novos-mestrados/</link><description>In the next academic year, the University of Macau will launch three new master's courses, in line with the objective of economic diversification in the Macao SAR. At the end of the month, UM will also hold a graduation ceremony for more than two thousand students, taking advantage of the occasion to honor two renowned academics
 
The University of Macau (UM) will launch three new master's degrees, for the 2026/2027 academic year, in the areas of artificial intelligence (AI), intelligent energy networks and pharmaceutical sciences, “to support the diversification of the economy and respond to the needs of industries”. Interested parties will be able to apply until March 13th of next year, according to a press release from UM.
The Faculty of Education’s Master of Science in Artificial Intelligence and Education was designed to “cultivate education professionals for the Greater Bay Area, preparing them to integrate AI into academic curricula and administration, and offering support for teaching policymaking.” The curriculum covers “theoretical knowledge related to AI, the effective integration of AI technologies in classrooms, assessment systems and academic curricula, the application of appropriate AI technologies to optimize leadership and management of schools, the ethical and social implications of AI, and the analysis of the use of AI in educational contexts through critical thinking”.
In turn, the Master of Science in Smart Energy Grids from the Faculty of Science and Technology aims to “cultivate high-caliber research and technical professionals in the field of electrical engineering to meet the development needs of the energy industry” in the Greater Bay Area.
The Master of Philosophy in Pharmaceutical Sciences, taught by the Institute of Chinese Medical Sciences, aims to “nurture high-level pharmaceutical talent with expertise in innovative drug development, precision medicine and disease prevention”. This curriculum plan includes areas such as advanced pharmacology and toxicology and medicinal chemistry and phytochemistry, among others.
 
“Honoris causa” for two academics
UM will award honorary doctorate degrees to Ze Zhang, a specialist in materials science, and Thomas J. Sargent, Nobel laureate in Economic Sciences, “in recognition of their exceptional achievements and significant contributions to society”. The ceremony to award honorary and higher degrees will take place on November 30th, at 4 pm, in which more than 2,240 students will also be graduated.
Ze Zhang was elected an academician of the Chinese Academy of Sciences in 2001 and is currently a professor at the School of Materials Science and Engineering at Zhejiang University. According to UM, Ze's work has contributed significantly to advances in materials science.
Thomas J. Sargent, for his part, is “widely recognized as a pioneer of the ‘rational expectations revolution’ and a leading figure in contemporary economic science.
 
“Double-campus” model leads to doctorate in Hengqin
In addition to continuing to be taught at the main campus of the University of Macau, the Doctorate program in Public Health at the Faculty of Health Sciences will also take place in Hengqin, starting in 2026/2027. Through a “dual-campus” system, the university intends to “improve learning flexibility and regional accessibility”. The three-year program covers diverse disciplines, from epidemiology, biostatistics, environmental health, nutrition and social health, among others. The course aims to “cultivate public health professionals with strong leadership.” Applications are open until March 13, 2026.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies defend taking advantage of the success of the National Games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputados-defendem-aproveitamento-sucesso-dos-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>Some deputies yesterday took advantage of their interventions before the agenda to highlight the successful holding of the National Games and the results achieved by Macau's athletes. They also left a series of suggestions to the Executive, with a view to capitalizing on the momentum that the National Games generated and the importance of the sports industry in the Macao SAR
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Still in the aftermath of the National Games, several deputies yesterday took advantage of the period before the order of the day in the Legislative Assembly to welcome the successful holding of the event, the joint organization of the participating cities in the Greater Bay Area and the performance of Macau's athletes. On the occasion, they also shared some suggestions to enhance the social and economic boost given by the event.
Ella Lei said she hopes that “the Government will provide more support for the training and development of local athletes” and that preparation conditions for “young people with potential” will be improved. The deputy also mentioned that, taking into account the planned merger between the Cultural Institute and the Sports Institute, society hopes that this integration of resources will result in “new development opportunities”.
Despite having recognized that sports spaces for residents and schools have increased, Ella Lei considers that “there continue to be limitations in space and facilities to implement professional training programs, fields for athletes and organization of competitive events”.
For Lam Lon Wai, the holding of the National Games demonstrated “Macao's institutional advantages and its ability to manage major events”, broadened the Macao SAR's “international visibility” and promoted the integration of industry and the long-term development of the territory. The deputy stressed that the Government must accumulate and transform experiences, in order to continue “promoting Macau as a stage for high-level events”.
Angela Leong and Ma Chi Seng presented three suggestions to enhance the momentum given by the National Games. As a first point, an increase in investment in the sector was suggested, reinforcing “the systematic training and selection of young sporting talents” and raising “the competitive levels of Macau athletes”, in addition to opening the National Games sports facilities to the general public.
On another point, “more sports tourist itineraries with Macau characteristics” were requested for “an integrated multiplier effect” during the simultaneous holding of major events, as happened with the Macau Grand Prix.
The deputies also suggested the deepening of “synergistic cooperation between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, pointing, as an example, to the “Agreement on strengthening sports cooperation and promoting integrated development”, signed between the three regions.
For his part, Ngan Iek Hang defended the consolidation of “emblematic events”, the expansion of the content of the modalities and the continuous optimization of iconic events. Ngan also pointed out the Macao SAR's tourist strengths, the community economy, the improvement of sports facilities, the training of talents and regional cooperation as other aspects to be enhanced.
Deputy Lee Koi Ian called for a better “talent cultivation system for performance sport”, reinforcing physical education at school, improving the amateur training network and assigning “professional support teams dedicated to key projects”. Lee also believes that there should be a coordinated support mechanism between the Government, companies and society and “a platform for research, development and sale of event derivatives”.
Furthermore, “we must commit to [intellectual properties] (IP) for local sporting competitions, creating a sports consumption market with its own characteristics”, he argued. Lee also suggested improving the policy support and evaluation mechanism, optimizing support “for the participation of small and medium-sized companies in the competitive economy”, with easier access to goods, services and financing.
Finally, Chan Hao Weng highlighted the more than 3,500 volunteers who served the event, the cross-border cooperation, the performance of local athletes who participated and the economic and social benefits that the National Games provided.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Song Pek Kei suggests incentives for household appliances and meals</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/song-pek-kei-sugere-incentivos-para-electrodomesticos-refeicoes/</link><description>Deputy Song Pek Kei considers a consumption incentive model adopted in Mainland China to be viable for Macau, where authorities attribute subsidies and specific benefits to buyers of electronic products and household appliances and consumers in the restaurant sector
 
Faced with the “indisputable fact” that consumption continues to weaken and the emergence of “many unoccupied stores in Macau”, the Government must reinforce rationality, scientificity and precision in the distribution of resources, highlighted Song Pek Kei, in an intervention before the agenda in the Legislative Assembly.
The deputy defended that, given the structural change in consumption by residents and tourists, the authorities should take as a reference the measures taken by Mainland China, in order to increase subsidy plans and specific benefits for electronic products, household appliances and meals, with the aim of continuing to stimulate the community economy and stabilize confidence in social development.
Recognizing the “good effects” of the Grand Prize for Consumption, Song Pek Kei urged the Government to study the launch of new consumption subsidy plans, if financial conditions exist.
“With new development trends, such as consumption abroad, circulation of Guangdong vehicles in Hong Kong, popularization of online stores, etc., the most urgent thing is to increase the competitiveness of the community economy”, he emphasized, asking the Government to create “diversified consumption scenarios” to “respond quickly to cyclical changes”.
The deputy recalls that the Government tried to create, in the North Zone, a street where goldsmith shops were centralized, a measure that “had a stimulating effect”. From this perspective, Song Pek Kei suggested the creation of neighborhoods for Southeast Asian gastronomy, innovative electronic products and fashion, with a view to transforming and optimizing the development of the community economy.
On the other hand, looking at the “unbalanced distribution of tourism resources”, the deputy understands that, in terms of attractions for tourists, it is necessary to reinforce the fusion between the tourist resources of community neighborhoods and companies in the leisure sector. Specifically, it considers “itineraries with a new tourist experience that depart from these companies to community neighborhoods” to be viable.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Joey Lao wants to increase subsidy for hiring young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/joey-lao-quer-aumento-de-subsidio-para-contratacao-de-jovens/</link><description>For Joey Lao, the discrepancy between the subsidy criteria for hiring young people looking for their first job, provided for in the “Regulation on Incentives and Training for the Unemployed”, and the benefits within the scope of the “Financing plan for professional careers of young people in Macau in the Greater Bay Area” is worrying. In the period before the agenda, the deputy urged the Government to take that plan as a reference to carry out a review and update of the “Regulation on Incentives and Training for the Unemployed”, which has been in force for more than two decades, to increase, rationally, the subsidy for hiring young people looking for their first job.
Furthermore, he defended age-appropriate flexibility, “in order to better meet the real needs of young people in Macau in obtaining their first job”.
Specifically, Joey Lao pointed out that, under current regulations, employers who hire young people looking for their first job, under the age of 26 and without professional experience, can be supported with 12 thousand patacas, in six monthly installments, if the person hired has completed secondary education as an academic qualification. As for hiring young people with higher education, the employer is supported with 15 thousand patacas, that is, 2,500 per month.
“From the point of view of purchasing power theory, compared to 2,500 patacas 20 years ago, today, purchasing power is certainly lower”, he warned, highlighting that the aforementioned Plan to encourage local young people to work in the Greater Bay Area grants a support amount of 5,000 patacas per month, for a maximum accumulated period of 18 months, with the age limit being extended to 35 years.
“This plan demonstrates the Government's determination and commitment to encouraging young people to integrate into regional development, but, at the same time, it shows that the current regime in Macau is relatively outdated”, lamented Joey Lao.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco promises to relocate Mocha Royal staff</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-promete-realocar-pessoal-mocha-royal/</link><description>Melco announced that it will cease operations at the Mocha Hotel Royal at the end of December 28th. The gaming concessionaire also stated that the 64 affected workers will be relocated to other projects and that customers' rights will be protected. The Gaming Inspection and Coordination Department will “strictly supervise” the commitments made by Melco
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Mocha Hotel Royal will close its doors at 11:59 pm on December 28th, according to an announcement from Melco. The gaming operator also said that the 64 employees of the Mocha club will be relocated to perform functions in other Melco gaming spaces, “according to operational needs”, promising “a smooth transition” for the workers.
The concessionaire also guaranteed that all customer rights will be safeguarded after the end of operations. Mocha Hotel Royal customers will be able to use their game tickets (TITO) at the Altira Casino and at the Mocha clubs in Porto Interior, Golden Dragon and Sintra hotel. Additionally, all gaming machines at Mocha Hotel Royal will be redistributed by Melco casinos.
The Mocha Hotel Royal's closing procedures will be conducted in accordance with Macao SAR law and in close collaboration with the Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate (DICJ), to ensure a closure “in an orderly manner”, said Melco. To this end, the DICJ will send personnel to “strictly supervise” the closure of the gaming room, in order to ensure that it is conducted “in accordance with the respective closure proposal” presented to the Government, according to a statement from the organization.
In close communication with the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL), the DICJ stated that it intends to guarantee compliance with the commitments assumed by Melco regarding the relocation of workers and guarantees regarding remuneration, benefits and working conditions.
The DICJ also reported that yesterday the closure of the Mocha Hotel Grand Dragon “took place in accordance with the established procedures”, in close interdepartmental collaboration and in accordance with legal terms. During the process, DSAL deployed staff to the premises in order to “provide clarification to the workers concerned” and provide them with “information on an open line for further consultation”. The Public Security Police Corps and the Judiciary Police preserved public order at the site and in the surrounding area, according to the DICJ.
The DICJ intends to continue the coordination established with the concessionaires and competent services in jointly promoting the “healthy and orderly development” of the Macau gaming sector.
In the same sense, Melco stressed that it “will continue to actively defend its corporate responsibility and remains committed to contributing to the sustainable and healthy development of the Macao SAR gaming industry”.
 
Game recipes maintain resilience
The gaming sector continues to demonstrate resilience in November, particularly in the mass market, according to a report from Citigroup. “November is typically the weakest month of the fourth quarter, so the strength of the premium pasta market that we witnessed when we carried out our survey of tables in developments last Friday surprised us positively”, indicated analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau, cited by the GGRAsia portal. Observed bets totaled 14.4 million Hong Kong dollars (HKD), “19% more compared to November 2024”, they said. This month, analysts detected 540 bettors in the 'premium' mass segment, an annual increase of 5%, with the average bet per player growing 13% to 26,754 HKD. They also counted 31 “whales” – customers with bets equal to or greater than 100,000 HKD – nine more than in November 2024, with an average bet of 216 thousand HKD. Taking into account the data collected, analysts feel “comfortable” with the forecast for the game's gross revenue in November, of 20.5 billion patacas, an increase of 11% in the annual variation.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>American trio performs with the Macau Orchestra</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trio-americano-actua-orquestra-de-macau/</link><description>The North American string trio “Time For Three” will perform with the Macau Orchestra next Sunday at the Cultural Center, in a concert that fuses different musical styles
 
Violinists Nicolas Kendall and Charles Yang, and double bassist Ranaan Meyer, who make up the trio “Time For Three”, were invited to perform with the Macau Orchestra, in a concert scheduled for Sunday, 30 November, at 8pm, in the Grand Auditorium of the Cultural Center.
Known for its approach that is difficult to classify, the group adapts “bluegrass”, Americana and popular singer-songwriter styles through classical techniques, “creating a unique sound, both innovative and appealing”, according to a note from the Cultural Institute (IC).
The trio was awarded an Emmy for the live album “Time for Three in Concert”, with “Letters for the Future” receiving the Grammy award for “Best Classical Instrumental Solo Performance”.
The founding members met while students at the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. They initially discovered a mutual interest in “bluegrass” and “country fiddling,” and Meyer added jazz and improvisation to the mix as the three played together for fun.
The arrival of Charles Yang, replacing Depue, opened up new areas of musical exploration. Their penchant for singing spontaneously elevated the group's credentials. Since then, they have added several songs written by the members and others to their repertoire, including some with three-part harmony. Yang also plays guitar to introduce a different tone to some songs.
Since becoming a formal ensemble in 2003, the trio has performed alone and with symphony and chamber orchestras throughout the US and Europe. He has played in places as diverse as “Yoshi’s”, “Indianapolis Colts” games, the “Indianapolis 500” and on the aircraft carrier museum ship “USS Intrepid” (CV-11) in New York Harbor.
He signed a three-year contract as the Indianapolis Symphony Orchestra's first resident ensemble in 2009, and continued until April 2019, developing programs to broaden the orchestra's appeal in the local community.
As part of the educational work, “Time For Three” produced an anti-bullying video performing the song “Stronger”, by Kanye West/Daft Punk, which was released on YouTube and featured on CNN and “The Huffington Post”.
The trio's sixth album was released in 2022. “Letters for the Future: was recorded with the Philadelphia Orchestra, conducted by Xian Zhang, and contains “Contacts”, a concerto for string trio and orchestra by Kevin Puts, and a new recording of the aforementioned “Concerto 4-3” by Jennifer Higdon.
The album won the “Grammy” for “Best Classical Instrumental Solo” of 2023. “Contact”, by Kevin Puts, also won the “Grammy” for “Best Contemporary Classical Composition” of 2023.
The “Starry Symphony” concert is sponsored by the Sands China Performing Arts Program and will last approximately one hour and 30 minutes with one intermission. Tickets are on sale at the Macau Online Ticket Office, priced at 300, 250, 200 and 150 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jimmy O. Yang returns for Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jimmy-o-yang-regressa-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>Jimmy O. Yang returns to Macau for a comedy show at the Galaxy Arena on February 21st. Tickets will go on sale on December 4th
 
Jimmy O. Yang, star of cinema and stand-up comedy, is back in the territory for another comedy show, which will take place at the Galaxy Arena, on February 21st of next year. According to Galaxy Entertainment, the American comedian, born in Hong Kong, will present a concert with live musical performances, accompanied by several special guests and other surprises.
Tickets for the “show” will go on sale from 11am on December 4th, through Galaxy Ticketing, Trip.com, Damai, Maoyan, uutix and MPay. Prices vary between MOP380 and MOP880.
After six sold-out shows at the Broadway Theater in July this year, which attracted more than 13,000 fans, Jimmy O. Yang will return “funnier than ever” for a special holiday season.
As Macau welcomes the Chinese New Year, the show will “add a vibrant dose of happiness and auspicious energy to the festive season, with joy and good fortune”, says the same note, adding that “in the modern Galaxy Arena, Jimmy's return marks a significant step forward in scale and influence, and promises a unique and unforgettable experience for audiences across the region”.
Best known for his internationally acclaimed stand-up specials, which have attracted millions of viewers online and offline, and for his roles in “Silicon Valley” and “Crazy Rich Asians”, the 38-year-old comedian has become “a cultural force”.
Jimmy's humor “draws on his personal history and cultural heritage, resonating with audiences around the world and uniting East and West through his unique style of comedy,” Galaxy highlights.
As an actor, he is best known for playing the role of Jian-Yang in the HBO comedy series “Silicon Valley”, Dr. Chan Kaifang in Netflix's “Space Force” and Josh Lin in the Netflix romantic comedy film “Love Hard” in 2021.
His parents were from Shanghai and later moved to Hong Kong, where he was born. The family moved to Los Angeles in 2000, when Yang was 13 years old, having attended Beverly Hills High School.
In San Diego, the artist performed his first stand-up show at the age of 21 as “Lowball Jim” at the “Ha Ha Comedy Club”. He was a DJ at a strip club, accumulating clients at a comedy venue to support himself while he performed free stand-up sets at “The Comedy Palace”.
On television, she made her debut in the CBS 2 series “Broke Girls” in 2012 and played Tang-See in the 9th season of “It’s Always Sunny in Philadelphia”. He played his first role in a drama film as Dun “Danny” Meng, a Chinese immigrant who is kidnapped by the Tsarnaev brothers in “Patriots Day”, a 2016 action film.
His comedy special “Good Deal” was released on “Amazon Prime Video” in May 2020, and the following year he starred opposite Nina Dobrev in Netflix’s “Love Hard”, which was his first romantic film. In 2023, he voiced the Monkey King in the animated film “The Monkey King”, also on Netflix.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IIM organizes visits to historic neighborhoods</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iim-organiza-visita-bairros-historicos/</link><description>The International Institute of Macau (IIM) will carry out a guided community visit to historic neighborhoods, on December 6th, in which those interested will be able to appreciate sites in the Historic Center. The visit, entitled “Macaense Neighborhoods: Roots of a Multicultural City”, will cover iconic sites such as Largo do Lilau, Rua Central, Largo de Santo Agostinho and Rua da Felicidade, ending at the Dimensões M activity center, where a gathering and a drink will take place with the participants.
In a statement, the IIM states that the initiative aims to make known, “particularly to the younger public”, the experiences and histories of these neighborhoods, where “various cultural roots have been left by various communities over the years in Macau”.
Through a “relaxed” visit, with explanations provided by heritage ambassadors from the Association of Macau Heritage Ambassadors (MHAA), visitors “will be able to learn more about the historic neighborhoods and the IIM will also distribute its editions related to the theme, also encouraging reading among participants”.
Registration is open via IIM and MHAA social media, with a participation limit of 50 people for two separate sessions (25 in each), between 2:30 pm and 4:30 pm on that day.
The visit, carried out in conjunction with the 20th anniversary of the inscription of the Historic Center of Macau on the World Heritage List, has the support of the Macau Foundation, with an organizational partnership with the MHAA and the collaboration of the Association of Young Macanese and “Language Exchange and Culture Promotion”.
The IIM emphasizes that it intends to continue with more projects of this type in the future, “increasing the younger public’s knowledge of the cultural identity and historic neighborhoods of Macau”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies call for strengthening ties with the PLP in the cultural and legal spheres</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputados-pedem-reforco-dos-lacos-os-plp-nas-esferas-cultural-juridica/</link><description>In a joint intervention presented before the agenda, the nominated deputies Kou Kam Fai and Lam Fat Iam suggested that Macau organize, in synergy with the Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP) and Spanish-speaking countries, as well as the countries included in the “One Belt, One Route”, initiatives such as cultural years and arts festivals in the three cultural facilities that the Government intends to build in the International Zone of Integrated Tourism and Culture (ZITCI). The deputies believe that, in this way, the three facilities will be transformed into centers of exchange between Chinese culture and foreign civilizations, in favor of strengthening Macau's image in the international cultural arena. Furthermore, they argued that the ZITCI project must be in line with the profile of Macau, the Cultural City of East Asia, with the positioning of a Sino-Lusophone platform and with top museum institutions, such as the National Museum, the Imperial Palace Museum and the British Museum, in order to create a regular exchange mechanism, involving special exhibitions, loans of pieces and imports of internationally renowned curators and managers. Iau Teng Pio proposed that legal mechanisms for cooperation with the PLP and Spanish-speaking countries be improved in areas such as commercial mediation, arbitration and investment protection, to reinforce the international credibility of rules, “injecting lasting vitality into the rule of law under the principle of ‘one country, two systems’”.</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National Music Museum gives voice back to Mafra Palace and brings instruments to life</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/museu-nacional-da-musica-devolve-voz-ao-palacio-de-mafra-da-vida-aos-instrumentos/</link><description>ANA LEIRIA*
The once empty and silent palatial area of ​​Mafra has gained a “sound future” since Saturday, with the opening of the Music Museum, where contrasting instruments dialogue, and visitors play on pieces that give voice back to the palace. The National Music Museum, which for almost three decades occupied a space at the Alto dos Moinhos Metro station, in Lisbon, moved to the palatial area of ​​the Real Edifício de Mafra, used by the Escola das Armas during the 20th century.














“But the space has been empty for several decades, because it no longer had a destination and, therefore, in that sense we were very happy to be able to come here, because it is also a way of rehabilitating a space that is a world heritage site and that, for all reasons and more, deserves this highlight, this new future, this musical sound future”, said the museum director, Edward Ayres d’Abreu, in a guided tour behind the scenes of the installation.
The entrance is through a cold and austere corridor, with large vaults, permeated with the smell of paint and wood, which gives access to the museum space, made up of 15 exhibition rooms, spread over two thousand square meters, where large glass showcases store hundreds of objects organized in such a way as to make it a “living collection”.
“We will have around 500 objects on display, not only musical instruments, but also musical instrument construction tools, we have several paintings, varied iconography, scores, phonograms, which offer the visitor this journey through music throughout the centuries and regions”, stated the director.
The museum also encompasses another larger area, around seven thousand square meters, which will store reserves and provide common spaces, such as a cafeteria and shop.
Marking a difference to what the museum was previously, this exhibition is organized “not according to the technological aspect of the instrument, but rather according to the uses that these instruments had in some privileged contexts”.
The musicologist explained that collectors tend to classify instruments by the sound they produce, but here what happened was that they concluded that “the technological side is of little interest”, but rather “what tells us which musicians played which instruments, when and in what context”.
“We talk, for example, about the idea of ​​the transcendent, the idea of ​​power, how music can be an instrument of representation of a State, how music can be a means to reach some known beyond”, an “experience that invites us to rethink the place of music in our daily lives”, stated Edward Ayres d’Abreu.
That's why anyone who visits the exhibition notices the curator's concern to put seemingly contrasting instruments into dialogue, such as classical pieces alongside a self-portrait by former rapper Allen Halloween, examples of reco-reco alongside whistles from Barcelos, instruments from the 12th century alongside others from the 21st century, Portuguese instruments alongside instruments from Chinese, African and other European countries.
“Precisely because, despite being contrasting and apparently distant, for some reason, these instruments are actually very close, they were used in similar contexts, they were used for similar purposes, and this is the richness, this rich dialogue between distant objects that we want to highlight”.
The reborn Music Museum features pieces donated by the Azulejo Museum, the National Museum of Soares dos Reis, the Biscainhos Museum, the Mechanical Music Museum, the Contemporary Art Museum and private collectors.
In the apparent calm of the museum, still closed to the public, the contrast is also made between the organization of the already completed rooms with their illuminated showcases, vibrant with life and color, and the disorder caused by stacked crates, scattered cards and tangles of cables, wires and plastic spread across the floor.
One of these rooms, which was called "Plurality of listening", is an immersive room, in which the visitor "is invited to enter a space surrounded by 22 sound speakers, four giant LED screens. Then, in the center there are devices that translate sound and tactile vibrations, which can be felt with the hands and feet", he explained.
In this multimedia space, which will also show documentaries, the hustle and bustle was still great, days before the inauguration, with men equipped with various tools perched on scaffolding, or going up and down ladders, to place large and heavy curtains, from top to bottom, along the walls, “very important for acoustic control”.
“The vaults have already been treated to reduce reverberation and now the curtains will help even more”, explained the person in charge.
This project is another focus for the new museum: making it a multisensory and inclusive space, which is why, in addition to the possibility of feeling the sound, there is another room that will offer an olfactory experience, there will be a video guide in Portuguese sign language, audio description for the blind and vibrating vests that amplify and reinforce the vibrations felt with the hands and feet.
Still in this interactive perspective, all rooms will have at least one instrument that can be played by the visitor, the first of which is a gong, with three different mallets, which allow different sounds to be produced.
"The musician's instrument becomes part of his body. It is interesting for visitors to notice this, to pick up a tuba or piccolo [available in one of the rooms], experience the sound, the weight or just touch them."
Two men passing by the room, carrying a large object wrapped in white paper, were questioned by the museum director, who asked them to show that “exact replica of a 17th century harpanet that is displayed in one of the showcases”.
One of these men is the author of the piece, the chordophone builder Orlando Trindade, who also carried out several restoration interventions, and manufactured that instrument so that visitors could play.
"I tried to make it as similar as possible to the original, but with my own style. I had never made a harpanet, it was the first time", he said, demonstrating how it is played.
Among the hundreds of pieces on display, some deserved special attention from the museum director during the visit, such as a Stradivarius cello by D. Luis, a Regal, which is “a jewel” from the 16th century, loaned by the Lisbon Academy of Sciences and whose origin is unknown, a table pianoforte that is the oldest in the Iberian Peninsula, two tambourines painted by D. Carlos or a harpsichord by Louis XVI.
The research carried out by the team in the last two years, since the museum closed in Lisbon, regarding the change project, allowed “to get to know the collection better” and discover “very important things, such as wrong dating, wrongly attributed authorship, and even the number of instruments itself was changed”, he revealed.
“As part of our instrument restoration and conservation campaign, we discovered very important things and we must begin the process of classifying some objects as National Treasures, because they are extremely rare objects, technologically challenging for their time, they are in an excellent state of conservation and are extremely important for understanding what was and, to a certain extent, what the History of music in Portugal could be”, he highlighted, noting that he was talking about close to half a dozen pieces.
One of the big surprises was the discovery of a cacophone, “a curious and sophisticated instrument, which is not found anywhere else”, and whose origin was only realized after careful investigation: an almost unknown amateur who worked in a brickworks in Alcoutim.
Still being installed is a “room that will talk about the voice as an instrument”, and which will have a megaphone, lamiré, multimedia instruments and even a Drilbu, which marks the recitation, in Hindu religious practices.
Edward Ayres d’Abreu looks around at the unfinished rooms, the crowd of people finalizing installations, the scattered boxes and materials, rubble to tidy and clean, just a few days before the inauguration, which takes place on Saturday, the day from which entry will be free until the end of November.
Asked if he is panicking about what remains to be done, the museum director smiles and replies: “We are always in panic, but everything is under control”.
 
*Journalist at the Lusa agency. Text edited due to its length</description><pubDate>2025-11-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>