<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>António José de Freitas re-applies for Ombudsman of Santa Casa</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/antonio-jose-de-freitas-recandidata-se-provedor-da-santa-casa/</link><description>Having led Santa Casa da Misericórdia as Provedor for almost 26 years, António José de Freitas will reapply for the position with the same team, not believing that other lists will appear. To the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, he said that the priority is to continue with projects such as the Social Store or support for the payment of tuition fees
 
Catarina Pereira
 
António José de Freitas, Ombudsman of Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau, will reapply for the position for the 2026/2027 biennium. “I will move forward with the same work team, which I am very happy with”, he revealed, speaking to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper. At 73 years old, António José de Freitas has been a Provider since January 1, 2000. “I will complete 13 terms and 26 years of voluntary service to the institution”, he noted.
Unless more lists are delivered, the Provider will then begin his 14th term. The election will take place on November 20th, at 5:45 pm, at the institution's headquarters. According to the Santa Casa Commitment, the lists must be presented by the respective list leaders at the Brotherhood Secretariat, against receipt, by the 10th day before the election – in this case, by the 6th of November.
However, despite considering that it was time to pass the testimony, Freitas does not believe that there will be other lists: "I don't believe so, because it's not just about finding one person to be the Provider, you have to form a team, find 19 people. I don't think it's easy."
Furthermore, he highlighted, Santa Casa is a social solidarity association, in charge of a Home for 128 elderly people, two daycare centers, a Rehabilitation Center for the Blind, a Social Center and the Museum. “All of this implies daily management, not only of personnel but also of its operation”, he explained, adding: “To be a Provider you have to deal with the day-to-day running of these equipments on a daily basis, because in terms of size, Santa Casa already operates, perhaps, like a medium-sized company, so some availability is necessary. You have to be here every day”.
António José de Freitas stressed that the position does not just involve “signing papers”. "When I took on the role, I wanted to do my best. I'm a bit demanding, I like to see things perfect and that is difficult and sometimes causes stress", he admitted.
“Frankly, I confess that I'm already very tired, because it's not just Santa Casa, I have other things to do, but, as long as I'm healthy, it's worth continuing”, he said.
From his perspective, “the Brotherhood can be proud of the role that the institution has played among the population of Macau, after the transfer of sovereignty”. “Santa Casa today is very different from other times, it is completely integrated into the great family of social solidarity in Macau, we have contacts with practically all associations, with all institutions linked to social assistance”, he pointed out.
Confident that, in time, he will be able to give his place to someone else “with the conditions and availability to pursue the institution's objectives”, Freitas also says he is optimistic about the future. "I am confident that the Santa Casa will continue indefinitely, with the good will of the Sisters and Brothers. In the end, the Santa Casa belongs to all of us and is a very important vehicle for keeping our identity and the language of Camões alive", he stressed.
The list of António José de Freitas is composed, at the Board of Directors, by himself, as Provedor, by José Joaquim das Neves (secretary), António José Dias Azedo (treasurer), Manuel Gonçalves Pires Júnior and Bruno dos Santos Nunes (members), while the General Assembly is made up of Leonel Alves (president) and Anabela Granados and Luís Machado (secretaries). The Supervisory Board includes José Ricardo das Neves (president), Telmo da Silva Martins (secretary) and Paulo Augusto da Silva (rapporteur).
As for the priority for the future, “it is to be able to continue with the projects already implemented, such as subsidizing tuition fees for needy students at Escola Portuguesa and the Social Store, which has been operating for 13 years”. Noting that “the economic situation in Macau is not at its best”, Freitas admitted that it has been “very difficult” to find a sponsor for the December Social Store.
"If eventually we really can't manage it, I think the institution should bear this responsibility. It's 300 thousand patacas, but it's worth it and it's good to set an example", he defended. “The beneficiaries of Loja Social already know that they can count on Santa Casa every month and it doesn’t matter to them whether it is through this or that, as long as the support arrives”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Ten-Year Plan focuses on outpatient medical services and homes in Zhuhai</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-plano-decenal-aposta-em-servicos-medicos-externos-lares-em-zhuhai/</link><description>In the next decade, the Government will further promote external medical services and support local elderly people living in “pilot homes” in Zhuhai, as well as launch a “long-term care coupon” plan and a platform to help search for elderly people with dementia who have lost their way
 
The next Ten-Year Action Plan for Support Services for the Elderly (2026-2035) will be released to the public in the first quarter of next year, revealed the Institute of Social Action (IAS), noting that it will consist of short, medium and long-term measures. Specifically, there are 102 short-term plans implemented between 2026 and 2027.
According to the IAS, over the next two years, the Plan foresees greater promotion of external medical services, the creation of an “elderly database”, the launch of standards for the standardization of cross-border retirement services between Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, as well as the provision of support, on an experimental basis, to elderly people who want to live in homes in cities in Mainland China that are part of the Greater Bay Area.
In this regard, U Ka Wai, deputy head of the Social Solidarity Department of the IAS, said that the organization is trying to understand the living situation of residents who have already started living in nursing homes in Mainland China and studying the conditions of various homes in the Greater Bay Area.
The idea will be to recommend good quality homes in Zhuhai, as “pilot homes”, to local elderly people interested in spending their old age in Mainland China, and support them in terms of medical services, transport and family visits, in their use of these homes. The measure will be implemented over the next two years, said the official, quoted by the Chinese-language press.
Also between 2026 and 2027, the Government will launch a “health management points program”, develop personalized health improvement plans after assessing the condition of high-risk elderly people, investigate the demand for the application of new technologies in the development of services for the elderly and define instructions on the application of smart home devices.
On the other hand, the number of public services participating in the next Ten-Year Plan will increase to 18, with the new participants being the Administration and Public Service Services, the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the Directorate of Economic and Technological Development Services, the Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services and the Postal and Telecommunications Services.
According to U Ka Wai, the next Plan encompasses many measures that will encourage the elderly to live “better and healthier lives”. This includes creating a “15-minute circle of life” through the launch of an electronic map, which will allow seniors to access support services in different community neighborhoods within 15 minutes.
In addition to promoting housing remodeling so that homes adapt to the physical conditions of the elderly population, the Government intends to gradually boost the application of smart home products and encourage social service institutions to reinforce the use of smart technology equipment.
In the medium term, from 2028 to 2030, a “long-term care voucher” plan is planned to be implemented, on an experimental basis, within the scope of home care and support services. The IAS then hopes to expand the scope of the plan to homes and day care, between 2031 and 2035.
In addition, another medium-term measure consists of a new platform that provides help in finding lost elderly people with dementia. Specifically, new wearable devices will be introduced to speed up the search.
As for long-term measures (2031-2035), the IAS plans a “pilot plan for intelligent equipment for long-term care services”. In this context, the first facility will be opened in the territory where elderly people can receive fully intelligent long-term care.
Furthermore, in the balance of the Ten-Year Plan (2016-2025), the IAS revealed that 444 measures were completed, reflecting a completion rate of 99.3%.
Hon Wai, president of the IAS, noted that Macau will enter a super-aged society in 2029, with the elderly representing 21.4% of the total population. Given this social characteristic, the next Plan will focus on big-health, smart technologies, the services industry for the elderly and the creation of an inclusive and “elder-friendly” environment.
According to him, between 2016 and August this year, the benefit of bus fares aimed at the elderly registered around 270 million beneficiaries/times, totaling the subsidized amount 1.21 billion patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputies again ask for consumer cards</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputados-voltam-pedir-cartoes-de-consumo/</link><description>Several deputies once again asked the Government to issue a consumption card to the population, at a time when the territory's economy remains “unstable”. The “operational pressure” of SMEs and their survival also continues to worry the Hemicycle
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macau's “unstable” economy continues to worry the deputies of the Legislative Assembly (AL), who, during the interventions before the agenda, took the opportunity to suggest measures to respond to the “structural problems of the economy and employment”, as Si Ka Lon said. The deputy elected by indirect suffrage considers that these development tasks “remain heavy”.
In this sense, he proposed “optimizing” the employment subsidy policy and “accelerating” the “complicated procedures and excessively long deadlines” for labor import requests. For Si Ka Lon, it would also be important to launch, together with traders, “Community Neighborhood Consumption Vouchers for Residents and Visitors”. “Economic development requires long-term efforts, and it is necessary to face challenges, and also strengthen confidence”, he argued.
In turn, José Pereira Coutinho insisted on the need for a consumer card. “The elderly are waiting for the allocation of electronic consumption cards to alleviate the cost of living, namely the constant increase in prices of the main essential goods”, he stated, adding: “It has been proven that these cards are effective in supporting SMEs and actively boosting domestic consumption”.
For the deputy elected directly and the most voted in the elections, due to the “absence of effective policies”, small businesses “survive with many difficulties”. In this sense, he defended the implementation of support policies with subsidized interest, “that is, instead of banking institutions negotiating and charging interest”, a subsidy would be granted by the “competent authorities” that covered part or all of the interest.
Pereira Coutinho's colleague, newcomer to the AL, Chan Hao Weng, also asked for the distribution of consumption cards, worth 10,000 patacas, to qualified residents. “The distribution of consumption cards can alleviate the life pressure of residents and also more effectively stimulate domestic demand, boosting the local consumption cycle and quickly boosting the economy,” he stated.
According to him, the funds could help SMEs to “stabilize their operations, guarantee the job market and achieve the social sharing of economic fruits”. On the other hand, he suggested updating the salary index for public servants.
In turn, Joey Lao, who returns to AL directly, after a break, asked the Executive to “stabilize domestic demand”. “I suggest to the Government that, when the financial situation allows, it carries out a study on a new round of the consumer card, to boost and revitalize SMEs in community areas, and alleviate the burden and pressure on the lives of residents”, he stated.
Fellow newcomer Kevin Ho, elected indirectly, also addressed the “operational pressure” that SMEs are feeling. Asking for “more attention” from the Government to SMEs and “adequate and timely support”, the deputy warned that “a possible greater wave of SME bankruptcies could shake the confidence of society and the economy and result in an irreversible economic crisis”.
Therefore, Kevin Ho said he hopes that the Government will take the initiative to study the launch of a “cross-border consumption voucher 2.0” “as a starting point to attract international tourists to consume in small stores, combining leverage through various prizes and electronic wallets, with a view to channeling the purchasing power of tourists to community areas, and boosting the SME economy”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wong Chio Sak calls for “unity” and “cooperation” between services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wong-chio-sak-pede-uniao-cooperacao-entre-servicos/</link><description>Public services must “persist in the reformist and innovative spirit”, reinforce “unity” and cooperation, and assume their responsibilities, highlighted the Secretary for Administration and Justice in a series of visits to bodies under his supervision
 
After assuming the role of Secretary for Administration and Justice, on October 16, Wong Sio Chak visited in recent days the Directorate of Justice Affairs Services (DSAJ), the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), the Directorate of Administration and Public Service Services (SAFP) and the Official Press (IO), to exchange views with management and leadership staff and frontline workers, providing them with work guidelines.
According to a note from his office, the Secretary urged the directors and heads of services to work towards “strengthening unity and cooperation”, as well as “promoting horizontal and positive communication”, in favor of “team synergy”. Furthermore, he stressed that they must “persist in the reformist and innovative spirit” and “assume their responsibilities”.
For Wong Sio Chak, management and management personnel “must defend the principles of justice, objectivity, scientificity and rationality, and always be in accordance with the general interests”. Highlighting the need to comply with the principle of “population-based and service provision-based”, he also encouraged staff to “get closer to the public and listen to their opinions, with the aim of responding, in a pragmatic way, to their needs”.
On Monday afternoon, Wong Sio Chak met with SAFP leaders to discuss work to promote Public Administration reform, issues relating to voter registration and public service at the front line of the Public Information Center. The government official instructed the organization to “well carry out the core tasks of Public Administration reform in the coming years, in addition to being aware of the development situation of the Macau Single Account within the scope of electronic governance”.
On the same day, he also visited the IO to learn about the process of organizing workers in that service after integration into the DSAJ, starting this Friday, in addition to the main work of the Press. Wong Sio Chak took the opportunity to urge frontline workers to remain firm in their posts to ensure the smooth progress of work.
The agenda of the previous days included trips to the registry and notary services, as well as to several municipal facilities related to the life of the population, namely the Government Office Building (Qingmao), the Novo Mercado Abastecedor da Ilha Verde, the Municipal Complex of Mercado do Patane, the Laboratory of the Laboratory Division and the monitoring and control system of the rainwater and wastewater pumping station. During these visits, which were attended by his chief of staff and several advisors, Wong Sio Chak listened to citizens and workers, collecting suggestions on optimizing facilities and services.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vanessa da Mata and Orquestra Chinesa share the CCM stage</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vanessa-da-mata-orquestra-chinesa-partilham-palco-ccm/</link><description>Singer Vanessa da Mata, one of the stars of Brazilian contemporary music, will perform with the Macau Chinese Orchestra on November 15th, in a show included in the Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries
 
The Grand Auditorium of the Macau Cultural Center (CCM) will welcome Vanessa da Mata for a concert with the Macau Chinese Orchestra on November 15th, at 8:00 pm. Part of the 7th edition of the “Encounter in Macau – Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries”, the show will bring to Macau “one of the most influential voices in Brazilian contemporary music”, says the Cultural Institute (IC), highlighting that Vanessa da Mata is a “singer and composer recognized for her artistic versatility and the emotional strength of her works”.
"Her unmistakable voice and striking style have won over fans all over the world, making her one of the main representatives of Brazilian popular music. Her songs combine different musical genres, namely MPB (Brazilian popular music), R&amp;B, pop, frevo, samba and reggae. Among her biggest hits is the song “Boa Sorte/Good Luck”, which achieved international recognition", highlights a note from the organization.
On the CCM stage, Vanessa da Mata will come across “the charm and sonic delicacy of the Macau Chinese Orchestra, promising a memorable night of different sounds”.
The concert will be conducted by Zhang Lie, music director and principal conductor of the Chinese Orchestra who is “recognized as a first-class conductor nationally” and has led several orchestras in international performances. Under her direction, the Chinese Orchestra will perform emblematic songs by Vanessa da Mata, specially prepared for this occasion.
“Combining the subtlety and lyricism of traditional Chinese music with the intense and colorful rhythms of Brazil, it will offer the public a transcultural and unforgettable musical experience”, anticipates the IC.
Tickets for the concert are available at the “Enjoy Macao” box office, priced at 400, 300 and 200 patacas. Holders of a Macau Resident Identity Card, Macau Teacher Card, Full-Time Student Card, Special Benefits Card for the Elderly or Disability Assessment Registration Card can enjoy a 50% discount. Friends of the CCM, Friends of the Macau Orchestra and Friends of the Macau Chinese Orchestra are entitled to a 20% discount.
In addition, upon presentation of a ticket for the Film Festival between China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries or proof of consumption of the Chinese and Portuguese Illustrated Book Exhibition, you will be able to purchase tickets with a 20% discount at the physical ticket offices.
The Festival of Arts and Culture between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries” is guided by the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture, organized by the Cultural Institute and supported by the Tourism Department, Institute for Municipal Affairs, TDM and Air Macau.
 
IC will cooperate with Capital Library
The president of the Cultural Institute (IC), Leong Wai Man, and the deputy director of the Library of the Capital of China, Zhang Juan, signed an agreement that opens “a new phase” in exchange and cooperation between the Macao SAR and Beijing in the area of ​​public libraries. According to the IC, the agreement with the Beijing library calls for strengthening cooperation in several operational areas, including staff exchange, professional training, joint organization of activities and exhibitions, the sharing of collections and the creation of “a regular contact mechanism to facilitate the sharing of resources”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sino-Lusophone alliance wants to apply AI to “healthy longevity”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alianca-sino-lusofona-quer-aplicar-ia-na-longevidade-saudavel/</link><description>Nine universities from Portugal and China launched an alliance on Tuesday in Macau to study how to use new technologies, including artificial intelligence (AI), to guarantee “healthy longevity” to the population. The agreement was signed at the University of São José (USJ), which gave rise to the initiative to create the Alliance for Innovation and Development in Health Technologies for Longevity between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries.
"We have very strong relations with Portuguese-speaking countries. It is natural that this idea was born here in Macau", the dean of the Academy for Innovation and Development in Smart Health and Longevity at USJ, Dai Jianbiao, told Lusa.
In addition to USJ, the alliance's founders include Zhuhai's Zunyi Medical University campus and Guangzhou's Xinhua University. On the Portuguese side, they include the University of Évora, University of Aveiro, University of Beira Interior, University of Minho, University of Algarve and the Portuguese Catholic University.
But the vice-rector for Research, Innovation and Internationalization at the University of Évora stressed that the alliance is open to other Portuguese-speaking countries, with invitations already made to institutions in Brazil and Timor-Leste.
Despite admitting that, unlike Portugal, the remaining Portuguese-speaking countries still have relatively young populations, Paulo Quaresma believes that the alliance has “a theme that is transversal”. “Even in young countries like these, there is certainly an interest in their elderly people being able to live longer and in better health conditions, which is, in essence, the main objective”, he said.
Macau's population is aging rapidly, mainly due to the lowest birth rate in the world, while that of mainland China decreased in 2024, for the third consecutive year.
"In fact, this happens all over the world. So this is our very strong message to academics: We should be concerned about this", argued Dai Jianbiao.
But Paulo Quaresma stressed that the alliance also wants to bring together companies and other institutions, both public and private, that can complement scientific research carried out in academia. This is because the ultimate objective is “to have real solutions that are transferred to society and then, honestly, no one knows how to reach everyone better than companies”, defended the researcher.
Quaresma mentioned, as an example of technological solutions that the alliance can study, a set of sensors, which, using AI, can alert to possible health problems in elderly people who live alone. “This could allow people to be in their environment, with their family, for longer, and not have to be displaced, whether admitted to hospitals or nursing homes”, he explained.
Furthermore, he said, AI can allow medical treatment to be personalized, extending something that is already done, through genetic analysis, for some types of cancer.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rita Santos cleared in the case regarding elections in Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rita-santos-ilibada-caso-sobre-eleicoes-em-portugal/</link><description>The Portuguese Public Prosecutor's Office decided to archive the complaint filed against Rita Santos by some Socialist Party activists residing in Macau. The case dates back to May this year, regarding the elections for the Assembly of the Republic
 
Rita Santos, counselor for Portuguese communities, saw the Public Ministry of Portugal (MP) archive the complaint process that had been targeted by some Socialist Party (PS) activists. According to news released by TDM, Rita Santos herself reported that the MP's order explains that no evidence was found of irregularities committed in Macau during the elections for the Assembly of the Republic, whose political force with the most votes was the Democratic Alliance, made up of the PSD and the CDS.
The Macau judicial authorities collected evidence, at the request of the Portuguese MP, in order to determine whether a Macanese “responsible for an association” had committed a crime against Portuguese electoral law. In June, the MSAR MP confirmed that he had received a request for cooperation from the Portuguese counterpart institution, regarding a criminal case related to the elections for the Assembly of the Republic.
At the beginning of May, the PS filed a complaint with the Portuguese National Elections Commission, accusing the Macau Public Service Workers' Association (ATFPM) of interfering in voting by mail, which was denied at the time by both José Pereira Coutinho, president of the ATFPM, and by Rita Santos, also a member of the board.
The group of socialist residents filed the complaint because they considered that “the confidentiality and personality of the vote” was at stake. Photos of alleged illegalities were even presented, reporting the presence of individuals who identified themselves as 'volunteers' at the door of a post office in Macau, approaching voters. According to PS-Macau, this same practice had occurred in the 2024 legislative elections.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chan Lai Kei wants reforms to increase birth rate</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chan-lai-kei-quer-reformas-para-elevar-natalidade/</link><description>The drop in the birth rate in the Macao SAR constitutes a threat to the labor sector, social security and the economy of the territory, according to Chan Lai Kei, who predicts that families with just one child or none at all will become increasingly common. The new deputy suggested, among several measures, the implementation of more subsidies and the extension of maternity leave
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
Deputy Chan Lai Kei warned about the impacts of the continued decline in the birth rate, which will pose “profound challenges regarding the recruitment of labor, the social security system and the economic vitality of Macau”. In an intervention in the period before the agenda, he said it was “predictable that family structures characterized by ‘families with a single child’ or even ‘families without children’ will become increasingly common”.
Pointing to the economic pressure that families currently face, the new deputy argued that subsidized childcare places should be increased and a study carried out on the extension of this support to children up to six years old. Furthermore, a “progressive subsidy” could be implemented, the amount of which increases depending on the number of children, in order to ensure that the amount corresponds to the families’ living costs.
In relation to housing, he requested the publication of the current status and results of the “Feasibility study on the economic housing exchange regime” already underway. At the same time, “interest subsidies on housing loans” should be studied or “a special subsidy should be granted to families with children, with a view to supporting daily expenses”.
For Chan Lai Kei, there is also “room for improvements in the current maternity and paternity leave regime”. In this context, he suggested a gradual increase in paid maternity leave to 98 days, in line with Mainland China and Hong Kong and with the recommendations of the International Labor Organization. He also suggested another study on the creation of an exclusive license for parents to be able to accompany births and another authorization for parents to be able to accompany their sick children.
Another suggested measure was the implementation, on an experimental basis, of the “family-friendly employer certification pilot program” in public services and gaming operators. This would include “a flexible work organization for pregnant women and workers with children under three years of age”, exempting them from “night shifts” or “consecutive” shifts and “extreme weather situations”, argued Chan.
The deputy also urged the Social Action Institute to accelerate and prepare the “Crech Services Development Plan for the years 2026 to 2030” and to extend “the hours and scope of child care services”. Furthermore, he pointed out the need for an “innovative and diversified development of non-higher education”. Improving the allocation of teachers, supporting special education students and increasing the extraordinary education subsidy for disadvantaged families are necessary conditions to “relieve the pressure on families” and “increase the desire to start a family with children”, he asserted.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National Games torch will travel 2.6 kilometers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tocha-dos-jogos-nacionais-vai-percorrer-26-quilometros/</link><description>Next Sunday, the National Games torch will travel through several emblematic locations on the Macau Peninsula, on a 2.6 kilometer route. 50 relays will participate. The departure will take place at the Government Headquarters and the arrival will take place at the Ruins of São Paulo
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The torch route for the National Games, scheduled for November 2nd, will pass through several iconic locations on the Peninsula, starting at the Government Headquarters and arriving at the Ruins of São Paulo. The ceremony will start at 9:30 am and will take place simultaneously in Hong Kong and Guangzhou. Half an hour earlier it will be held in Shenzhen.
The flame transport will travel 2.6 km, for around two hours, passing through the avenues of Praia Grande, Dr. Mário Soares and D. João IV, as well as Largo da Sé, Rua de Pedro Nolasco da Silva, Rua do Campo, Avenida do Conselheiro Ferreira de Almeida, Rua de D. Belchior Carneiro, Calçada de S. Paulo and Largo da Companhia de Jesus.
The group of relays, totaling 50, is made up of representatives from the sports sector, sponsors, young people and socially renowned personalities, among others.
Furthermore, to create an image of torch carrying with “passion, warmth, green and ecology”, the organization combines the symbol and music. The first, “Haiyanzhiling” (Spirit of Sea Flame) shows waves, Chinese white dolphins and flame elements, while the musical component has the theme “Xiang Guang Qian Hang” (Forward towards the Light), demonstrating the resilience of life and belief of fighting in sportsmanship.
In Macau, the event will cause some traffic restrictions, between 8:30 am and 12:00 pm, and the police will, in phases and zones, control the 17 main roads and adjacent roads that are on the route. As for buses, around 20 routes will be affected.
At a press conference, Pun Weng Kun, coordinator of the Preparatory Office of the Macau organization, said that, for the territory, a route was designed under the theme “Cultural integration”, in order to “create a better competitive environment for the arrival of the Games”.
After the torch carrying activities, representatives from the four cities will send the flame back to Guangzhou. On the afternoon of the same day, the concluding ceremony will take place at the Olympic Sports Center in that Chinese city.
 
Visitors can increase up to 20%
The holding of the National Games and the Grand Prix could increase the number of visitors by between 10% and 20%, as well as increase the hotel occupancy rate. The estimate is from the president of the Macau Tourism Industry Association. Speaking to Jornal Ou Mun, Andy Wu also predicted that the two events will encourage demand for hotels in Hengqin, “which will constitute a scenario of mutual benefits for the sector in both regions”.
 
Young people defend more sports facilities
A survey carried out by the Chinese Association for the Progress of Youth of Macau, which interviewed 1,015 people between the ages of 18 and 45, showed that 73% understand that there is room for improvement in terms of the number of sports facilities in the territory and 66% support the creation of new facilities, despite almost 71% considering that the current ones are “satisfactory”. For 72%, the location of these spaces should be improved, while 68% expect rates to be adjusted. According to the survey, 61% had used sports facilities in the last six months, with 75% preferring those that are free. On the other hand, almost 73% prefer to use these outdoor spaces, while 76% have become accustomed to using sports facilities with other people. The data also shows that 76% suggested exclusive sports areas for young people and 75% proposed optimizing the smart booking system.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trio brings “tradition and innovation” to “Musical Journeys”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trio-traz-tradicao-inovacao-as-jornadas-musicais/</link><description>Clube Militar will host another night of the “Jornadas Musicais” series. The “Vantage Trio” ensemble will present “Povo do Ar”, with performances by Cindy Ho, Jiyoung Choi and Ruda Lee
 
This Friday, at 7pm, the Stanley Ho Hall of the Clube Militar de Macau will host another session of the “Musical Journeys” cycle, for a concert by the group “Vantage Trio”, with guest appearances by pianist Cindy Ho, cellist Jiyoung Choi and violinist Ruda Lee. The “Povo do Ar” program will feature the themes “Gipsy” by Haydn and “Otoño Porteño” by Piazzolla, in addition to a piano composition by Frédéric Chopin.
Founded in 2015 by Cindy Ho, the “Vantage Trio” brought together “exceptional artists from the international classical music scene to provide in-depth chamber music experiences”, according to Clube Militar. The group even participated in the inaugural concert of the “Viennese Legacy” series, at the “Wiener Konzerthaus”, in 2018.
With the addition of Ruda Lee and Jiyoung Choi, the group is now preparing “a new and exciting phase”, which includes the series “Sweet Sound That Breathes Upon a Bank of Violets”, with works by Chopin and Rabel, and other performances in Macau. The “Vantage Trio” remains “committed to tradition and innovation” and aims to “captivate audiences with their musical integrity and distinct artistic talent”.
Hong Kong native Cindy Ho is recognized for her contributions to music, having received the title of Associate of the “Royal Academy of Music” and the “Paul Creston Award” in 2016 and 2017, respectively. As musical director of “Vantage Music”, she organized and participated in several concerts, including “A Splendid Wintry Carpet”, “Inspirational Liaisons”, “Opus Medtner”, “With a Clear Voice, Sound a Fiddle String” and “In Paradism”, among others.
Graduated from the “Royal Academy of Music” and “King’s College London”, Cindy Ho is dedicated to developing new talents, having founded the “Young Musicians Series”, a platform for young soloists. His mentors were Choi Sown Le, Ruth Nye, Aaron Shorr and Alfred Lee.
Jiyoung Choi, in turn, began his journey as a cellist at the “Weill Recital Hall of Carnegie Hall”, at just 10 years old, at the “Young Talents World Festival of Performing Arts”. Master in Musical Arts and Music from the Yale School of Music, she studied with names such as Aldo Parisot and Ole Akahoshi, having also been mentored by William Bai, at Ewha Women's University.
In addition to being a member of the “Bene Trio”, Jiyoung Choi is also a cellist with the National Symphony Orchestra of Korea. In addition, he participated in the Fort Worth Symphony Orchestra and the Gyunggi Philharmonic Orchestra, among others, and performed with conductors such as Peter Oundjian, Marin Alsop, Giancarlo Guerrero and Philippe Auguin.
In turn, Ruda Lee made her debut at the age of six in the “World Symphony Orchestra Competition”, becoming the youngest winner of the competition. His achievements include, among others, the “Seoul President's Award”, the “Strad Magazine Award”, the “Music Magazine Competition” and the “KCO Competition”. He performed at renowned festivals such as “Tanglewood”, “Kronberg”, “Norfolk”, “Banff” and “Great Mountain”. Currently, she is the artistic director of “Virtuoso Fiesta” and “Young Virtuosi HK”, initiatives that combine “classical music with innovative 21st century approaches”.
Tickets for the concert including cocktail cost 120 patacas, while tickets with dinner included cost 300 patacas.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR brings Qinghai products closer to Portuguese-speaking markets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-aproxima-produtos-de-qinghai-aos-mercados-lusofonos/</link><description>This week, Sam Hou Fai received, at Government Headquarters, Luo Dongchuan, governor of Qinghai province, to exchange “impressions on economic development, tourism cooperation and the training of qualified personnel”, according to a statement from the Social Communication Office. The Chief Executive highlighted the role of platform that the Macao SAR can play to “help Qinghai's characteristic products explore more promotion and sales channels within Portuguese-speaking countries”. The Macao SAR leader also said that “both parties can work together to explore more tourism products to realize mutual complementarity of advantages and common development”, as Qinghai is a tourism destination sought after by Macau residents. On the other hand, during the “Qinghai-Macau Economic and Commercial Exchange Promotion Conference”, promoted by the Macau Forum Secretariat, Luo Dongchuan stressed that “the path of cooperation between Qinghai and Macau has become increasingly broader” and that agricultural products from the province he governs “have successful access to the markets of Portuguese-speaking Countries”. On that occasion, a Framework Cooperation Agreement was also signed between the parties.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New faces leading AL Commissions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novas-caras-na-lideranca-das-comissoes-da-al/</link><description>In the second plenary session of the VIII legislature of the Legislative Assembly (AL), deputies elected new presidents and secretaries for the various Committees. From the outset, the Rules and Mandates Committee is now led by José Chui Sai Peng, with Iau Teng Pio as secretary. At the head of the 1st Standing Committee is Wong Kit Cheng, supported by Nick Lei (secretary), while the 2nd Committee is now chaired by Ip Sio Kai, with Lam Lon Wai as secretary. The 3rd Standing Committee, in turn, has Leong Sun Iok as president and Leong Hong Sai as secretary. In the monitoring committees, the new leaders are Ella Lei, (Land Affairs and Public Concessions), Song Pek Kei (Public Finance Affairs) and Ma Chi Seng (Public Administration Affairs). As secretaries of these Commissions are Jowy Lao, Ngan Iek Hang and Kou Kam Fai. In the same session, Angela Leong was elected president of the AL Board of Directors.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau celebrates 90 years of the National Anthem</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-celebra-90-anos-hino-nacional/</link><description>紀念《義勇軍進行曲》創作90周年系列活動啟動禮、烽火匯演



The “March of Volunteers” turns 90 years old and Macau celebrates the anniversary with a series of activities, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC) and the Education and Youth Development Services Department (DSEDJ), with the support of the Tianhan Foundation of China. The intention is to “promote the spirit of the National Anthem among the public”. “Melodies in Times of Fire – The Soul of the Nation” was the opening show of this series of activities, which includes a lecture on the 90th Anniversary of the “March of Volunteers” and the Photographic Exhibition “Appeal to Progress through the Ages: Tian Han and the National Anthem”, which will be on display at the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum, until December 1st. The photographic exhibition features around 100 photographs. The authorities thus intend to “transmit and publicize the indomitable spirit of the Chinese nation” and “further awaken patriotism among young people”. After the Mukden Incident, China was drawn into a 14-year War of Resistance against Japanese Aggression, the IC said in a statement. It was during this national crisis that the “March of Volunteers” was born. It was composed in 1935, with lyrics by Tian Han and music by Nie Er. Initially the musical theme for the film “Children of Chaotic Times”, the song told the heroic story of young patriots who mobilized for combat on the front line to defend the nation against Japanese aggression. On October 1, 1949, the “March of the Volunteers” was performed at the Founding Ceremony of the People's Republic of China. In 2004, it was enshrined in the Chinese Constitution as the National Anthem.</description><pubDate>2025-10-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Loewe has a parade full of colors in its new phase after Anderson</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/loewe-tem-desfile-repleto-de-cores-na-sua-nova-fase-apos-anderson/</link><description>Spanish Loewe bet on intense colors and refined modeling in Paris, at the debut of Jack McCollough and Lazaro Hernandez, the brand's new artistic directors after the departure of Jonathan Anderson.
 



















The Americans took over the position of the now Dior designer, after a decade under the command of Loewe, during which he intensely rejuvenated the brand, transforming it into a sales and notoriety success.
For their debut at the Spanish brand, currently part of the French group LVMH, McCollough and Hernandez opted for an explosion of colors, and some proposals directly recalled the multicolored aesthetic of filmmaker Pedro Almodóvar.
The designers were inspired by the chromatic ideas of the American abstract painter Ellsworth Kelly (1923-2015), and especially by the painting “Yellow Panel with Red Curve”.
“In it resides a vitality and a texture that we consider fundamental to the brand, a chromatic intensity and a sensuality that we consider inherent to its Spanish roots and, ultimately, an optimism and a spirit with which we deeply identify”, they stated in a message on the networks.
The duo, who founded the New York brand Proenza Schouler in 2002, placed a special emphasis on leather, a tradition of Loewe, founded in Madrid in 1846 as a leather goods house.
Short dresses in this material, almost shaped like sculptures, came in vibrant colors or printed versions. Structured and polished jackets gained shades such as radiant blue and coral red.
McCollough and Hernandez, both born in 1978, tend to work a lot with materials and combine different textures.
Jeans-style pants featured soft, plush fabrics, strapless dresses were made from flannel, and tops were made from knits with wavy shapes.
The parade was held in a large white space with glazed ceramic benches, in the south of Paris. Pedro Almodóvar, a supporter of the brand, attended the fashion show with actress Milena Smit, with whom he filmed ‘Mães Paralelas’.
“There is a very bright color palette, I think everything in general is very feminine, very in favor of the female silhouette,” the Spanish director told AFP.
The American duo had a great responsibility in taking over one of the best-positioned brands in the luxury industry, which is facing economic and commercial difficulties.
According to the Lyst index, specialized in fashion, in the second quarter of 2025, Loewe occupied second place among the hottest brands, behind Miu Miu. In the previous period, it led the ranking.
The Loewe show was one of the most anticipated at Paris Women's Fashion Week, and critics considered it a success.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>