<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Employment prospects worry more than 70% of women</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/perspectivas-de-emprego-inquietam-mais-de-70-das-mulheres/</link><description>The “financial conditions” are one of the reasons for “pressure” that feel 77% of women, along with the duty to take care of their children and the elderly of the family (48%). These are some conclusions of an inquiry carried out by Faom on the occasion of Women's Day. The association also came to the conclusion that 73% of respondents are concerned about employment prospects
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Almost 80% of women (77%) consider that the pressure they feel in their lives results mainly from “financial conditions”, while 48% report that this stress comes from having to take care of children and the elderly. These are some of the results of an inquiry made by the Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom), at the time of Women's Day.
The study on the life situation and use of women in 2025 was held between January and February, with 970 valid questionnaires directed to women aged 18 or more. Among the interviewees, 50% are aged between 25 and 44 years, half has higher education or older. About 71% are married, 20% single, and the remaining divorced or widowed.
The results compiled by Faom indicate that about 80% of women suffered salary reductions or unchanged remuneration in the economic recovery phase, "which reflects that the employment environment has not improved after pandemic." According to the data, the monthly income of income of most women in the last year was between 10,000 and 14,000 patacas, followed by the range of 15,000 to 19,000 patacas.
The main expenses of women are in the scope of food (80.5%), water bills, electricity and gas (54.6%), children's expenses (53.6%) and parental support (50.8%).
With regard to employment prospects, 73% said they were concerned about the future. For this reason, about 70% expect the government to increase employment and professional development opportunities for local women. 90% want the government to launch a new round of financial support.
In addition, and in the field of work at home, 67% of respondents have to take care of elderly or minor children, and more than 70% "have to treat two or more family members at the same time."
According to the data, more than 70% considers that the most effective measure to encourage birth would be to increase maternity leave to 90 days and raise the amount of birth allowance. Thus, Deputy Ella Law, who is also vice president of Faom, has returned to the increase in maternity leave, but also of paternity. In this context, they also suggested legislation to ensure breastfeeding time.
Also Deputy Ho Ion Sang, vice president of the General Union of Macao Residents Associations, questioned the government about plans to increase maternity and paternity licenses.
Given the scenario mirrored by the inquiry, Faom also considers that the government “should optimize the various beneficial measures for the population, including the cash reimbursement, the distribution of consumer coupons, the subsidy of water tariffs and electricity and health valleys”. He really believes that these measures can face economic challenges and increase women's quality of life.
Regarding housing, the association insisted on the need to create an exchange mechanism in the case of economic housing - something the government said was already creating. He also suggested optimization of the subsidy for caregivers to widen the coverage of this type of support.
On the other hand, it also proposed that the government reinforces cooperation with associations to improve home care, monitoring of consultations, among others.
 
Xi Jinping Felicita Chinese women
Chinese President Xi Jinping has issued a congratulation votes, wishing for the best of Chinese women “of all ethnic groups and all sectors,” including women from Hong Kong, Macao and Taiwan. The message came two days before the Women's Day was celebrated. On the other hand, in the “two sessions”, in Beijing, several MSAR vowels in the Popular National Assembly and the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC) approached Women's Day. Ng Siu Lai, a vowel at CCPPC, for example, said he hoped the family government more family-friendly policies so that women have more time to participate in politics or develop more professionally. In addition, he suggested a child care allowance to encourage birth. In turn, Wong Kit Cheng, equally vowel at CCPPC, suggested reinforcing awareness of society so that housework is divided, so that women can better balance family and work. He also assured that he will continue to insist on prolonging the maternity leave.
 
Mandar guarantees policies to build an “equality society”
Within the scope of Women's Day, the Government of MSAR has ensured that “it will continue to foster, through various policies and measures, the participation and development of women in different areas, with a view to developing the power of women and building a society of equality and inclusion”. In a statement issued by the Institute of Social Action, a point of situation is made about the various areas of women's life and their public participation. For example, it is said that women's life expectancy went from 80.5 years (in 1999) to 86.1 (in 2024), and that in the school year 2023/2024, women's access rate to the university was 97.5%, more than 0.5 percentage points than men. As for the salary difference, it was 2% in 2023, "lower than the average value compared to countries member for the organization for economic cooperation and development and similar to that of the Nordic countries." IAS also recalls that, in 2023, the proportion of civil service workers and the positions of women's management and leadership staff was similar, 44.9%and 40.7%, respectively, being a judge of 51.3%. Already in the VI Government of MSAR, there are three women among the nine holders of the main positions, occupying 33.3%. “The data reflect that Macao women have opportunities for equality in the political regime, the position of public administration and the performance of the public function, etc.”, can be read.
 
Sands evoked “indispensable contributions” of women
Sands China celebrated Women's Day with the team, "continuing an annual tradition of expressing appreciation for the indispensable contributions that women make in the workplace, in the family and society." The gambling operator offered all women's women's flowers at an event that was organized by the “Sands Empowher” team - a global initiative of diversity and inclusion, led by women, who aims to connect the team's female members to create networking and developmental job opportunities. “The 27,000 members of our team are the company's backbone and the most valuable asset. At Sands China, half of these members are women who are dedicated to daily operations. Many of these members of the women's team also balance responsibilities at work with home responsibilities. This event is a way for the company to express our appreciation for its many contributions, ”said Grant Chum, Executive Director of Sands China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Senhor dos Passos procession attracted thousands of faithful and tourists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/procissao-senhor-dos-passos-atraiu-milhares-de-fieis-turistas/</link><description>The procession in memory of the path taken by Jesus Christ from his condemnation of death in the Pretorio to his burial, after being crucified on Calvary, again filled the streets of the city center. Thousands of faithful, but also tourists or simply curious, witnessed the one that is one of the most important religious traditions of the Christian faith. Yesterday's parade began in the Cathedral and ended in the Church of St. Augustine



































Victor Rebelo
 
Every year devotion by the Lord of Bom Jesus dos Passos takes a few thousand people to the streets of downtown Macao and this time the procession environment did not escape the rule, for two days when weather conditions helped. Mild temperature, no strong sun and no rain.
The one that is considered as one of the greatest manifestations of Catholic Caress in the territory (along with the ceremonies alluding to Our Lady of Fatima) is always held on two days, Saturday and Sunday, and in both the day of this year's veneration, the streets have been filled with faithful, but also with tourists, especially Chinese, some of which purposely move from the continent and Hong Kong.
In a first route from the Church of St. Augustine to the Cathedral and then, the next day, in the opposite direction, in this case, a longer itinerary, the processions again had the presence of a human mass that accumulated in the road to the road as the procession passed.
On Saturday, the procession of the cross left St. Augustine at 19h00, arriving at the Cathedral around 20:00, there was the usual sermon of the garden. Yesterday, the ceremonies began shortly after 16:00, with the procession to pull around 4:45 pm, counting, as usual, with more public than the day before, to which it is not oblivious to the fact that it is held in the afternoon.
Before the length, there was a Pretorium sermon in the Chinese language inside the church, followed by the slow exit of the representation of the Lord. In the square of the See many hundreds of people waited to see, from camera in hand, the Andor that carried the effigy, and could feel some anxiety for this always special moment of the first visual contact of the image with the population.
One of the faithful told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that he is a frequent escort of the parade. "I come to watch the procession every year and at a time the feeling seems renewed, I do not lose this act of such great symbolism."
The old Sé, also known as the Nataric Church of Our Lady, built around 1622 and rebuilt in 1850 after the destruction caused by a typhoon, opened the doors of the main entrance to pass the Andor and all the procession ritual, with many children and young people, in front of the parade, cateched, volunteers and other elements that usually participate in religious activities Diocese and in the organization of the procession.
At that time, it was heard of the church bell, in strong beats, which made the moment even more special and with a certain emotion for those who were there, perhaps for a long time, to attend the celebration and follow the course of the Lord of Passos.
The Andor with the image of the Lord was adorned with flowers and was transported by the brothers of the Brotherhood of the Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos, as has happened for hundreds of years. In the procession also followed the bishop of Macau, D. Stephen Lee, flanked by Father Daniel Ribeiro, parish priest of the diocese and other priests.
The atmosphere was even more solemn thanks to the music and the drums of the Public Security Police Band drums, which “for about 70 years has been following the entire route of religious manifestation,” as JTM told JTM one of its members. This time, the group had 38 elements, which wielded various instruments, clarinets, trumpets, trombones and the drums already mentioned.
To this apparatus, which aroused great curiosity especially to those who do not know tradition, joined the natural traffic congestion, controlled as best as possible by many police officers highlighted for this purpose.
The slow procession left the Largo da Sé and was passing, among others, through Travessa do Roquete, Street of São Domingos, consulate general of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, where one of the seven stations of “Via Sacra” was located. In each stop, Veronica, with his white dress and boasting an image, in photography, from the Lord of the Passos, sang the responsibility in Latin, and the faithful responded with a song, after a few words given by Father João Lau.
Senhor dos Passos then followed by Rua do Campo, observing a large number of people in the iconic artery of the city. After Praia Grande, the procession continued to walk to the final destination, the Church of St. Augustine. The procession ended shortly after 18; 30, when the bells of the church located next to the Seminary of St. Joseph sounded, having followed the sermon of Calvary in Portuguese and the blessing of the Sagrada Cruz.
With a long story, dating back to 1708, the procession of the Lord Bom Jesus dos Passos takes place every year in Macau, on the first Saturday and Sunday of Lent, constituting an invocation of Jesus Christ and a special devotion in the Catholic Church addressed to him. The parade has a memory of the path taken by Jesus Christ from his condemnation of death in the Pretorio to his burial, after being crucified on Calvary.
In September 2017, this procession and that of Our Lady of Fatima entered the list of intangible heritage of MSAR.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao in Vienna to discuss drug combat actions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-em-viena-para-discutir-accoes-de-combate-as-drogas/</link><description>Five organizations or institutions in Macau will be present at the annual meeting of the United Nations Narcotics Commission, which starts today in Vienna. Prevention will be one of the main themes of the Austrian capital meeting, in which about 200 countries or regions will be present. Augusto Nogueira, president of the toxicodependent Rehabilitation Association, told the Jornal of Macao that the meeting is of great importance and again argued that “the best way to combat the drug is prevention, to avoid, of course, new consumptions”.
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The fight against drugs in the world will be once again under review at the annual meeting of the United Nations (CND) Narcotics Commission, which for five days, from March 10 to 14, is held on the same stage of several years, Vienna, the capital of Austria.
For the first time Macau will feature five organizations, which will participate, with interventions, in the bilateral events of the session. About 200 countries or regions around the world will be represented in the various events.
In addition to the usual presence of the toxicodependent Rehabilitation Association (ART), the meeting will feature representations of the Macao Youth Christians Association (YMCA), University of São José (USJ), Judicial Police (PJ) and Institute for Social Action (IAS), although the latter two are integrated into the China delegation.
One of the strong themes of this year's meeting is prevention, although treatment, harm reduction and social reintegration, among other related aspects, are part of the issues to be debated from today and until Friday.
Augusto Nogueira, President of ArtM, highlights, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, the importance of this meeting, because he understands that "the best way to combat drugs is prevention, to obviously prevent further consumptions."
The artm leader is one of those who will be hit by this priority strategy, stressing that “there is a need for everyone to work in these policies, including treatment, prevention, harm reduction, social reintegration, and other important aspects”.
According to Augusto Nogueira, “the key is that we all work together to deal with problems, because each has their important part to comply with, and not spend life, among non -governmental organizations (NGO), fighting for power and ideology that harm reduction is the best solution for everything, which, in my opinion, is not,” says the president of ArtM, an association that integrates the bodies of “Vien Board” bodies which makes the connection between member states and civil society.
The definition of harm reduction consists of the strategies that are guided by respect for the citizen, such as being trained to define their treatment objectives, seeking forms of less damage to their health.
This theme seems to divide the opinions of CND members and therefore will be on the table on the work schedule, as some representatives believe that focus is essentially on reducing damage, not preventing drug use.
There are also experts who understand that abstinence can be one of the guidelines of therapies within harm reduction and that the main objective is to defend life, assuming that drug extinction is impossible.
 
Teach to consume to avoid “overdoses”
For Augusto Nogueira, the importance of prevention is followed by harm reduction, "because there are people who, in their consumption, need sharing of syringes, need, instead of consuming on the street, consumer rooms, wards, various types of support." Therefore, he adds, the reduction of harm also consists of "teaching people to consume to prevent them from having overdoses."
The official states that there are groups that defend the complete legalization of the drug, intending only the reduction of harm and eliminating treatment, prevention and other types of policies. "This is what the United Nations want to combat, while advising their members to bet on social reeducation, that is, to make people, after being recovered, are reinstated in society and having jobs, becoming normal citizens," he expresses.
For the session parallel to the main work of the CND, under the responsibility and guidance of the ArtM, which will take place on Monday, Augusto Nogueira invited some institutions and personalities, who work in the same way as the ArtM, to share their experiences, such as the Ares do Pinhal community, which fights for social inclusion, and João Goulão, president of the institute for additive behaviors and the dependencies of Portugal, Spanish, and the project, from Portugal, and Spanish Giovanna Campello, director of the United Nations Treatment and Prevention.
"These people will talk, deep down, about this need to stop fighting for ideologies and make efforts to find solutions," concludes the president of the ArtM.
During the week, and in other parallel events, it will be the turn of the remaining representatives of Macau to disclose the actions they develop in the fight against the drug equally. YMCA will talk about prevention work at Macau universities and will also be involved in a youth event. USJ, represented by Helen Lui, will participate in a session of the European Action Against Drugs, showing what has been done in prison, especially the promotion of courses, education and training of social workers from prisoners.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reinforced protection of archaeological traces</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reforcada-proteccao-de-vestigios-arqueologicos/</link><description>The Archaeological Traces Zone on D. Belchior Carneiro Street will be the target of landfill to reinforce the protection of this historical space, the Cultural Institute announced
 
The Cultural Institute (IC) will implement protection measures to facilitate the preservation of the historical traces of the pit located on D. Belchior Carneiro Street. After analyzing the conservation suggestions presented by experts from the Institute of Archeology of the China Academy of Social Sciences, the IC decided to start, Monday, the work of landfill where the historical traces were found and removed.
Given the execution needs of this work and the respective public safety, the conservation and exposure area of ​​the pit archaeological traces on D. Belchior Carneiro Street and the Permanent Exhibition “Seda and Macau Route” will be temporarily closed to the public. According to the IC, the conclusion of the works is scheduled for early May.
Between 2010 and 2012, the IC charged the Institute of Archeology of the China Academy of Social Sciences to develop an archaeological work in four phases on D. Belchior Carneiro Street, which once was part of the land of the São Paulo College. A large moat was discovered on the scene, with a diameter of about 5.8 meters and a depth of about 9.9 meters, as a well -dug into the rocky substrate on the northern side of the hill of the fortress of the Monte.
During the excavations, archaeologs found numerous fragments of ceramic, building materials and other archaeological artifacts. Researchers believe that most of these fragments go back to the period between the late 16th and early 16th century, corresponding significantly to the reign of Emperor Wanli and the reigns of the Ming Dynasty Tianqi and Chongzhen emperors, and there are some pieces of the time of the Kangxi of the Qing dynasty.
Excavated on a rock surface, the pit has a relatively regular form in the horizontal plane, with traces of lavulation on the four walls. Researchers do not rule out the possibility of a relationship between this pit and the water well referred to in the Macao College Anua Letter.
"From the moment in the Portuguese they settled in Macao, the territory became a base for foreign trade, from which Chinese products such as silk and porcelain, from Macau to Japan, Southeast Asia and Europe were exported," recalls the cultural institute in one of its electronic pages dedicated to heritage. In this context, underlines the IC, “the large number of porcelain and ceramic fragments of Ming Dynasty and Early Qing Dynasty, found in the archaeological excavations open on D. Belchior Carneiro Street, is a great importance for the study of the history of Macao, also witnessing the significant role of Macao as a commercial port and commercial post at the time of the sea silk. and the maritime trade between the East and the West. ”</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China tries to position himself as reliable power in the face of Trump who wants "jungle law"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/china-tenta-posicionar-se-como-potencia-fiavel-face-trump-quer-lei-da-selva/</link><description>Chinese foreign minister accused Donald Trump's administration of wanting to return to the “jungle law” and positioned China as a “responsible” power and “reliable” partner. In the presentation of Beijing's diplomatic script for next year, Wang Yi accused the US of being "obsessed with showing a position of strength" and warned that the world cannot return to the "jungle law." “We have to advance and not retreat, and for this, important countries have to assume their international obligations. A great power cannot go there to intimidate the weakest, ”he said, on the sidelines of the Plenary Session of the National Popular Assembly. Wang has insisted that Washington is trying to "contain" China when "mutual respect is the basic principle that should govern bilateral relations." "No country should have the fantasy that you can repress and maintain good relationships with China at the same time," he criticized, adding that Trump's "double -sided" "does not help build mutual confidence." Comments appear at a time of increasing tensions between the two powers, marked by commercial disputes. China reacted harshly after Trump doubled to 20% additional customs on goods from the Asian country. Beijing announced more customs rates on US goods, an ambitious defense budget and warned that he is willing to fight "until the end." “China will continue to retaliate if the US continues to exert pressure. The US and China may be partners, but the relationship has to be based on respect, cooperation and peaceful coexistence, ”Wang said, appealing to Trump to" have a rational and objective view of China's development. " “We argue that all countries dialogue and put aside their differences. The world expects China to play an important role in response to global challenges, ”he said. Beijing will continue to be “constructive” in obtaining a lasting peace in Ukraine and will work in conjunction with the international community “according to the wishes of the parties”, based on their “objective and impartial” position on the conflict, he said. “Let's make sure this uncertain world. We will be a fair and correct force for world peace and stability, ”he said. Wang defended, however, the ties between China and Russia, and took a conciliatory tone with Europe: "There are more reasons than ever to Beijing and Brussels maintain a good relationship and reinforce it," when cleavage between the continental block and the US is seen after Trump's return of power. Wang also rejected Trump's plan to assume Gaza's control, because the enclave "belongs to the Palestinian people," and said that "changing their status will not bring peace, but more chaos," reiterating support for a "two -state solution" so that "the Arab and Jewish people can coexist in the long run." "China will always be with developing countries," he said. The diplomat defended emerging economies, which represent more than 40% of world GDP, as a "fundamental strength to maintain global peace and development and the key to bringing stability to the world." Wang did not fail to include a reference to Taiwan, whose Beijing sovereignty complains and which is its main 'red line' in the matter of foreign policy, and another to the Southern Sea of ​​China, where it attributed the friction - recently characterized by maritime confrontations - the "external forces".
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Law Wun Kong starts leading superior council of law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lei-wun-kong-passa-liderar-conselho-superior-da-advocacia/</link><description>Law Wun Kong was elected president of the Superior Council of Advocacy (CSA) for the 2025-2026 biennium, replacing Paulino commander who had led the agency since 2021. Kuong Iok Kao and António Dias Azedo remain vice president and secretary, respectively. These three positions are held by causal registered at the Macao Lawyers Association for 10 or more years.
The list also includes vowels Cao Lemeng, Henrique Lei and Hoi Peng (registered with the association less than 10 years ago), and members Wang Huating (Judicial Magistrate), Pak Wa Ngai (prosecutor's magistrate) and Li Zhe (appointed by the executive head).
As alternate vowels were elected lawyers Cheang Seng Cheong, António Almeida and Cheong Wang Chit (enrolled in the association for over 10 years) and Lo Chek In, João Varela and Júlio Anjos (registered less than 10 years ago). Already the group of alternate members integrates Lou In Leng (judicial magistrate), Leong Choi Man (prosecutor's magistrate) and Wang Chao (appointed by the chief executive).
According to the CSA, the new president of the agency, Law Wun Kong, promised to perform the board's work well along with the members. "At this stage, the priority is to treat complaints according to legal provisions and, at the same time, continue to promote the elevation of professional deontology of the sector, in order to provide quality professional services to citizens," says the same note.
The Superior Council of Advocacy is a high school and independent body that exercises the exclusive disciplinary jurisdiction about lawyers and interns. Disciplinary action is established by the Board's own initiative or based on participation subscribed by anyone who is aware of facts likely to integrate disciplinary offense.
 
Vong hin Fai elected vice president of the Union of Lusophone Lawyers
Vong Hin Fai, leader of the Macao Lawyers Association, was elected vice president of the Portuguese Language Lawyers Union for a two-year term, said TDM. Júlio Martins, from Cape Verde, assumed the presidency of the Board, following the election held during the General Assembly of the Union in Lisbon.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sub-reported women in the scientific area</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mulheres-sub-representadas-na-area-cientifica/</link><description>Professor XU Yi, from the Institute of Space Science of the University of Science and Technology of Macau (Must), poses for photography at the facilities of the Chinese State Reference Laboratory for the Lunar and Planetary Sciences, in Taipa, Macao, China, March 5, 2025. (Accompanies Lusa text on March 6, 2025). Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Jing Wu and Catarina Domingues*
The UN told Lusa that women in the Pacific Asia region remain “significantly underreported” in the scientific domain, with the loss of interest often happening at the beginning of the school path.
When Xu Yi was studying at college, only five of the 50 students in the classroom were women. Today, in the laboratory where he works in Macao, the numbers are not very different: five women in a universe of 40 scientists.
“I grew up listening to teachers to discourage girls from attending courses in the Stem area [English for Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics],” says the scientist of the State Reference Laboratory for Lunar and Planetary Science at the Macao University of Science and Technology.
When disciplines like physics and mathematics became more difficult, teachers repeated that “women were not as good as men,” recalls Xu Yi, who was born and raised in mainland China.
Women remain “significantly underrected” in the Stem domain in the Pacific Asia region. The work world in this area “remains dominated by men, excluding and adamant,” he told Lusa in an email response to UN women in the region. This is “a frequent problem,” said the organization on the occasion of International Women's Day (March 8) and the 25th anniversary of Resolution 1325 of the Security Council, signed in 2000 for the promotion of gender equality and women's rights.
An investigation in the 2022 Philippines also notes UN Women, states that gender prejudices start early, with students to lose interest in this scientific area at the age of ten, because they believe it is a men's paste.
This year is also the 30th anniversary of Beijing's historic historic statement and action platform, a document adopted at the United Nations World Conference on women, held in the Chinese capital, in September 1995, in which governments pledged to ensure that gender equality will be reflected in policies.
But Xu Yi, who studied in the US Physics, Microelectronics and Electronic and Informatics Engineering, makes sense in the skin. “In the Stem domain, most of the colleagues around us are men, who do not think of cooperating with us, only after we have some achievements in the curriculum and people approve of us,” he says.
UN Data Women Asia Pacific 2022 point out that, globally, women represent 35% of students in Stem courses and only 3% of students in the area of ​​Information and Communication Technologies. In the workplace, 19.9% ​​of science and engineering professionals are female.
Despite the increase of registered in higher education in this area, “persistent prejudices and gender norms continue to push women away from Stem careers,” says the UN.
Lusa found, however, that in another state laboratory in Macau has already been a balance.
The Academic and Scientist Li Ting, from the State Reference Laboratory for Quality Research in Chinese Medicine at the University of Macau, says that students intentionally selects students depending on the genre. And choose the balance.
“After giving birth, as a mother, the pressure is significant, and I think this is one of the greatest career twists of all women,” he says.
Also scientist Betty Law-Yuen Kwan, a native of Hong Kong and working in the same laboratory, explains that when he was in the secondary, a third of fellow women opted for the scientific area. “I welcome half boys and half girls, I think they can complement it,” he says.
Despite this example, in the leadership of the two reports referred to are only male names. And this reality “discourages the participation” of women in the area, according to UN Women for the Pacific Asia region. “Therefore, mentoring programs are crucial,” he says.
In 2023, the UN criticized the sub-representation of women in top positions in public administration and private companies of Macao. The United Nations Economic, Social and Cultural Rights Committee “remains concerned with the information that gender stereotypes persist and that the representation of women in higher positions in public administration and private companies remains unsatisfactory”.
The most important positions of the current government of Macao, for example, are held by five men (head of government, secretaries for the economy and finance, administration and justice, economy, transport and public works), and a woman (social affairs and culture).
In the working world, 41% of leadership positions were in 2022 in the hands of women, according to statistics from the Macao Institute of Social Action (IAS). Between 2014 and 2023, the average monthly work of women was lower than local men by about 5% to 10%, according to IAS.
 
*From the Lusa Agency</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese vice-PM TREND “Three expectations” with the MSar vowels at ANP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vice-pm-chines-vinca-tres-expectativas-junto-dos-vogais-da-raem-na-anp/</link><description>To the Macao vowels at ANP, the Chinese vice-PM pointed out “three expectations”, including a good transmission of the spirit of the “two sessions” and the reinforced support to the Government of the field
 
In Beijing, Chinese vice-master-master, Ding Xuexiang, attended at a meeting of the delegation of masters representatives at the National Popular Assembly (ANP). According to the delegation spokesman, Chui Sai Peng, the vice-PM transmitted “three expectations” to the Macao vowels.
Ding Xuexiang expects the vowels to "transmit well" the spirit of the "two sessions." In addition, he urged them to further support the executive to govern according to the law, as well as the chief executive and his team to effectively propel Macao's development. On the other hand, it also hopes that the Macao Society of Macao's deputies to “do the work well for the stability and prosperity of the MSAR”.
According to the Chinese language press, at a joint meeting of the RAE vowels at the Chinese Political Advisory Conference (CCPPC), the Vice-PM also stressed that they have the mission of consolidating the barrier to safeguarding national security and strengthening the unique position and advantages of Hong Kong and Macau.
On the other hand, Chinese President Xi Jinping visited the vowels at the CCPPC of Education. According to Fanny Vong, Macao vowel, the educational sector feels “very encouraged” for the visit. Revealing that Xi Jinping stressed the importance of forming staff at the level of morality, Fanny Vong pointed out that the head of state's speech given this meeting also included the deepening of education reform and the advancement of disciplines with the evolution of the times, which, for vowel, are equally applicable to Macao.
Also in the “two sessions”, Guangdong Governor Wang Weizhong has revealed that it is being promoted to implement a border form with exemption from document reading at the Hengqin post.
 
ANP highlights maintenance of the constitutional order of RAE
An ANP plenary meeting was also held, with Zhao Leji, chairman of the agency's permanent committee, to present the work report of this committee. According to this year, it is necessary to maintain the constitutional order of the special administrative regions defined in the Constitution and in basic laws.
At the same meeting, Zhang Jun, president of the Supreme Popular Court (STP), revealed that the STP completed the trial of 27,000 cases related to RAE and Taiwan in 2024, which reflects an annual rise of 4.3%. At the same time, it treated 7,840 cases of legal and mutual assistance involving Hong Kong, Macau and Taiwan, which means an annual break of 15.4%. In addition, he revealed that Guangdong Courts absorbed, last year, seven RAE arbitration entities as specially invited mediation organizations.
In addition, at CCPPC's third plenary meeting, Lao Nga Wong, a member of Macao of the Consultative Permanent Committee, argued that Macau must play the single role as a Sino-Musso platform to provide services of various levels to companies in China for international “navigation”.
On the other hand, a proposal presented by nine Macao vowels at CCPPC, including Chan Wa Keong and Leonel Alves, suggests the entry of products from Lusophone countries in Hengqin with customs rights exemption. In Beijing, Leonel Alves also pointed out that Macau is a window from China to the world and should internationalize in relations with the Lusophone world, to help the country's economic development and international projection.
 
Governors of Mand will study spirit of the “two sessions”
The five secretaries of the Government of the MSAR have issued communications by ensuring that they will scrupulously study the spirit of the “two sessions” and put it into practice, a guarantee that was also given by the Commander General of Unit Police Services, the Director General of Customs Services and the Commissioners against Corruption and Audit. Among them, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, stressed that "the works inherent to Administration and Justice will be implemented, closely coincidentally and in accordance with the learning and implementation of the spirit consecrated in the" two sessions ". In turn, the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, said that his guardianship “will study, implement and seriously implement the same spirit,“ boldly assuming his responsibilities ”, in order to contribute to the stability and longevity of the“ one country, two systems ”principle.
 
ALS President says elections will meet expectations
Kou Hoi In, member of the Permanent Committee of the Popular National Assembly and President of the Legislative Assembly (AL), said he believed that the deputies who will be elected this year for Al will correspond to the “Macau Governed by Patriotas” requirement and the expectations of residents. At an open meeting of the Macao delegation in Beijing, Kou Hoi In emphasized that the new electoral law allows more solid guarantees to residents at the exercise of “democratic rights”, according to the law.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dumont will replace Goldstein as CEO of Sands</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dumont-substituira-goldstein-como-ceo-da-sands/</link><description>Robert Goldstein will leave the leadership of Las Vegas Sands and Sands China, working as a consultant as on March 1, 2026. For his place, the Las Vegas Board of Directors intends to appoint Patrick Dumont, current director of operations who is son -in -law Adelson, the group's late founder founder
 
Las Vegas Sands (LVS) and Sands China leaders, their subsidiary in Macao, will change from March 1 next year, with Robert G. Goldstein, current president and CEO, to “move” to the role of senior consultant for two years. “In this role, Goldstein will help administration in its government relations activities, efforts to look for new physical development opportunities and company game strategies,” LVS said.
The same statement said that the LVS board "intends" to name Patrick Dumont, 51, as a 69 -year -old Goldstein replacement. Dumont, who is the son-in-law of Sheldon Adelson, a deceased founder of the US group, currently accumulates the positions of LVS president and operations director.
Goldstein joined Adelson in 1995, and has played a “fundamental role in the company's many hits in the last 30 years,” said LVS.
“This company has transformed the industry from a game -centered model for the integrated resort model and, through a different strategic approach in each market, significantly changed the tourist panorama in Las Vegas, Macau and Singapore. I was lucky enough to work with a large team of people over the years and I want to specifically express my gratitude to Sheldon for their support and friendship, ”said Goldstein, quoted in the statement.
Having entered the LVS before the inauguration of the Venetian Las Vegas, Goldstein was very involved in the development of the resort, becoming president when he was inaugurated in 1999. He was also the main responsible for the Grand Canal Shopps, the project's large shopping center.
“All these years later, it is evident that the inauguration of Venetian was a turning point in the history of Las Vegas Strip. Sheldon was widely criticized at the time, but his vision and the work we started together 30 years ago resisted more than the time test, ”said Goldstein.
In 2004, Goldstein led the company's efforts to sell his retail offers at Venetian and Palazzo, not yet opened for $ 1.5 billion. "At the time, the sector analysts praised the sale as a 'historical business' for the real estate value of Las Vegas Strip," says the American company, also praising the participation process in the LVS listing on the New York Stock Exchange, "where the most valuable company in the sector would become based on the scholarship capitalization."
In late 2014, after performing the functions of president of global game operations, Goldstein was appointed president and director of operations of the company and continued to work closely with Adelson in Las Vegas, Macau and Singapore. After Adelson's death in January 2021, he was appointed president and CEO of the company.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>EPM wins for the first time school title of the echelon to</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/epm-conquista-pela-primeira-vez-titulo-escolar-escalao/</link><description>The Portuguese school's soccer team of Macau won the echelon of older students in the championship organized by DSEDJ. In the final, EPM young people surpassed the application school attached to the University of Macau 1-0. Miguel Resende scored the goal of victory in the extension of the match held at the Taipa stadium
 
Victor Rebelo
 
For the first time in its history, the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM) won the school soccer title (age students until 18), after defeating in the final the school of application attached to the University of Macao, by the minimum margin.
The challenge, held in the best football amphitheater in the territory, the Taipa stadium, was dominated over the 70 minutes by the EPM formation, but sinned by the poor finish, despite the various opportunities created. The only exception, which earned the title, happened in the final minutes of the extension, through a low, crossed shot, the striker and team captain Miguel Resende, assisted by Eduardo.
The game, which was broadcast on the TDM's sports channel, culminated another time of school soccer of the age -level age -level, organized by the direction of Youth Education and Development Services, with the support of the Macao Football Association.
In the semi-finals, the formation of the Lusa matrix educational establishment exceeded the Yuet Wah school also 1-0, while the application school attached to the University of Macao, champion in 2024-2025, defeated the Salesian Institute through penalties, after 2-2 in regular time.
Luis Moura, coach of the team, who was assisted by Arlindo Serro, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the triumph was deserved. "For what we did throughout the championship, in which we have not lost any challenge, I think we deserve the title and so the players are to be congratulated," adding that the victory "involves the entire educational community."
This championship for students attending the 11th and 12th year of schooling is considered as an authentic competition parallel to that that is promoted by the Macau Football Association (Juniors Under 19), as it integrates players who are federated in some teams of the 1st division and therefore records great rivalry among schools in the territory.
In the case of EPM, Miguel Resende and Atif act in Chiba, while Eduardo and goalkeeper Gabrielle Croce play at Benfica, a club that is also guided by Luís Moura.
With several titles achieved in the remaining levels, especially B, as happened in the previous school year, the EPM for six years that has not participated in the EMA Echelon A. “After the interregnum, we bet on this year's participation and managed, not only win the tournament of this season, but to win the title for the first time in the history of our participation in echelons A”, concluded Luís Moura.
After finishing the challenge, players and coaches received the champion cup and their medals in an environment of enthusiasm, also shared by the EPM director, Acácio de Brito. The team was also to thank, in front of the central bench of the stadium, the support of colleagues and teachers who watched the game.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Environmental Cooperation Forum introduces this year green energy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forum-de-cooperacao-ambiental-introduz-este-ano-energia-verde/</link><description>The forum and international exhibition of environmental cooperation will introduce this year for the first time renewable energy, becoming at the first event in Macao using green energy. MIECF's objective is to demonstrate the concept of sustainable development and encourage high quality development. The exhibition will take place from March 27-29 at Cotai Expo do Venetian
 
The 2025 edition of the Forum and International Exhibition of Environmental Cooperation (MIECF) will approve, for the first time, the green energy transaction and will receive the Green Energy Certificate issued by the National Center for Renewable Energy Information Management. For the event organizers, the objective is to demonstrate the practical application of green energy, “which will mark an important step in the convention and exhibition industry towards sustainable development” in the sense of working to achieve the national “carbon goal”.
Green energy refers to renewable energies with high environmental and low carbon emissions, such as solar, wind and hydroelectric energies, which have less impact on the environment and climate.
As in previous years, during the exhibition period, activities such as the “green showcase” and the “green electricity tariffs plan” plan ”, aiming to encourage all sectors to implement environmental protection measures, as well as emphasize the concept of waste reduction, transformation of energy into energy”, says the forum.
According to the organization, 90% of the event assembly materials are recyclable, in which it is considered a very high rate. Subordinate to the theme “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for the Construction of Beautiful Cities”, MIECF will also promote a series of parallel activities, including international professional forums, assessment events and the launch of a carbon neutrality guide, as well as the “ESG excellency awards” initiative that will bring together green, hotel and finance sectors, to stimulate exchange companies and cooperation.
The “Global Carbon Credit Market Development Forum”, in turn, will provide a dialogue platform between governments and companies from Macau and various regions, with a view to deepening the carbon market exchange and contributing to the development of diverse industries. In turn, the event “Construction of the Smart City Has the sustainable development of the hotel industry”, aims to help the industry achieve the “double carbon goal” and build a green and low carbon future.
In addition, this year's MIECF, which will take place between March 27 and 29, at Cota Expo do Venetian, will present seminars, guided by guest experts, on topics such as Intelligent Energy Management and Green Technologies. The participation of young people is also encouraged, “to give a new boost to high quality development,” says the forum statement.
The event, the government's responsibility, has the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macao and the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services as official coordinating entities.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost five million visitors "felt" the illuminating Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-cinco-milhoes-de-visitantes-sentiram-iluminar-macau/</link><description>Macao illuminated has reached a total of 4.9 million people who went to the six zones with facilities and the places of video mapping screenings. The event, under the theme “Immersion of Time and Space”, brought together artists and companies from eight creative design cities from various countries or regions

























For 84 days, starting on December 7, 2024 and end on February 28, 2025, Macao enlightened several districts and cultures, having closed “with great success,” according to the organizing entity, the Board of Tourism Services (STD).
Mobile data collected by STDs through a local telecommunications company indicates that during the event, the number of people who moved to the six zones with facilities and the places of Mapping video screenings reached a total of 4.9 million visits.
Under the theme “Immersion of Time and Space”, the tourist attraction program brought together artists and companies from eight creative design cities, including Beijing, Shanghai, Chongqing, Shenzhen, Nagoya (Japan), Mexico City, Montreal (Canada) and Sidnei (Australia), as well as Macau and Hong Kong, and the participation of Portugal and the new. Zealand.
The festival, which attracted people flows to the community zones and boosted tourism and the night economy, provided an authentic party of light, celebrating with residents and visitors the commemorative day of the establishment of Marem, Winter Solstice, Christmas, New Year, Chinese New Year, Festival of Lanterns and Valentine's Day, among other important holidays. The event made known six zones with six subthemes in Macao, Taipa and Coloane: "Pulse of the Future" in the Manduco beach zone, "Interlude of the Ocean" in Praia Grande, "Glorious Epoch" in Nape, "Realm of Fantasy" in the North Zone, "Fusion of Arts and Culture" in Taipa and "Nostalgic Aura" in Colaane.
On the other hand, it had several facilities, namely six emblematic, four artistic, 12 luminous and nine interactive, totaling 31, distributed by 23 places from Macau, Taipa and Coloane. There were also three Mapping video shows: “Create the Future”, “Connect” and “100 Fun”, which took place separately in the square in front of the Macao Science Center and the Firefighters Largo in the mud. The two locations made a total of 1,008 projections.
During the period of illuminating Macau, every Saturday night, 66 intermittent animation activities were performed at specific places in the six zones, including giant inflatable doll, electronic synthesizer show, balloon modeling, workshop for parents and children, cartoon painting, minibanda, drum for parents and children, guitar and culmination action, Electronic, among others.
The Luminescent Night at Travessa do Armazém Velho 2024 ”extension activity also painted the Velho Warehouse Travessa area with different luminous elements, in conjunction with online games and face -to -face workshops, showing the night's night charm.
Lighting Macau 2024 “joined efforts with different public services and integrated tourism and leisure companies to create a night brand event and promote the development of tourism and event actions,” says STD.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM students went to clean the beach</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-da-upm-foram-limpar-praia/</link><description>The Student Division of the Macao Polytechnic University (DAE-UPM) organized the activity “Love the Earth and clean the beach 2025”, taking students to the beach to clean marine waste and protect the coastal edge with concrete actions, in order to reinforce the environmental awareness of university students. On the day of activity, the UPM Sustainable Development Association, consisting of volunteers and students from various courses, participated in collecting plastic bottles, fishing nets and fishing instruments fragments left along the waterfront, as well as another tide trash. Non-biodegradable plastic waste stood out as the most common, the UPM warned. The action “Loving the Earth and Cleaning the 2025 Beach” is one of the educational activities promoted by the UPM in response to the united nations sustainable development objectives. DAE-UPM believes this type of initiatives "encourages students to actively promote the concept of ecological civilization."</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Nha Trang coral reefs in Vietname are the risk of collapse</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/recifes-de-coral-de-nha-trang-vietname-correm-risco-de-colapso/</link><description>The soft waves of the coast of Nha Trang, in the center of Vietnam, hide an open secret: the vital coral reefs underneath are dying. The waters are frighteningly devoid of fish. The abundance of the ocean is coming to an end.
That's why Binh Van - who has fished in these waters for over two decades - now rents his boat to Vietnamese tourists who want to experience the thrill of fishing in the deep water of the Southern Sea of ​​China. However, for fishing, there are only squids, which are flourishing in oceans heated by climate change. Its passengers do not care as the boat moves away from Nha Trang's beach sparklers. But, Van is thoughtful.
It was not always like that. There was a time when it fished 70 pounds of fish, such as tuna and cherne, in one night. In fact, you can't make money from the squid. "Now I usually go home empty," he said.
Southeast Asia coral reefs are more than one third of the world's coral reefs and are part of the “coral triangle”, a biodiversity -rich marine area that usually extends from the Philippines to Indonesia and the Solomon Islands. But most now risk being destroyed. Only 1% of Vietnam's reefs are still healthy, and in these cases due to their removal, according to the World Resources Institute.
Reefs from around the world are at risk due to the warmer and more acidic waters that weaken coral reefs and result in their bleaching because they expelled the algae that helped them survive. White corals need time to recover, but bleaching events - when many corals lose color at the same time - are happening more often because of climate change, Clint Oakley said, who studies corals at Victoria de Wellington, New Zealand.
“It's an aggravated problem. "They take more than a year to completely recover," he said.
Nha Trang coral reefs also had to deal with local pressures as Vietnam's economy prospered and coastal cities grew. Construction sediments impair corals. The flow of agriculture, sewage and expanding aquaculture triggers the proliferation of algae that block sunlight and suffocate the corals.
Excessive and excessive fishing killed fish that support the health of reefs. In 2019, an outbreak of a spinous and predatory star-which became more likely because Recife's ecological balance was disturbed-killed almost 90% of surviving reefs when eating corals, said Konstantin S. Tkachenko, professor of marine ecology at Samara University of Russia, who has been studying Vietnam's reefs for years.
This has affected not only the local fishing industry - reefs provide food, shelter and areas of reproduction for fish - but also Vietname's tourist industry, especially among the divers around the world that migrates to the country from Southeast Asia because of its long coastline.
The underwater landscape is becoming famous for different types of waste: glass bottles where revelers celebrate, nylon fishing lines where fishing boats hide and plastic everywhere. The fish that clean the reefs and keep them healthy eating algae or parasites, such as the characteristic pecasso-bilist fish and the Indian papagao fish, disappeared, said Michael Blum of Rainbow Divers, a dive company in Vietname, clarifying that “when there are no cleaning products, the (reefs) suffocates”.
Tkachenko, the Russian scientist, said Southeast Asia could do more to protect them. It could create more marine parks where protections were actually applied, force the tourism industry to restore vegetation on the back to reduce sediment eviction in the ocean, restore degraded reefs through coral culture and the introduction of animals that balance reef ecosystems and regulate fishing.
He pointed to the dozens of fishing vessels that sprinkle the back of Nha Trang. "Who thinks it may be the hypothesis of survival of any small fish or inhabitant from the bottom of the sea, on such daily fishing pressure?" He stressed.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>