<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>More effective communication between services is a goal to be achieved by Wong Sio Chak</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/comunicacao-mais-eficaz-entre-servicos-e-meta-atingir-por-wong-sio-chak/</link><description>The two new Secretaries, who are responsible for the Administration, Justice and Security portfolios, as well as the new Public Prosecutor, took office yesterday. Wong Sio Chak, Chan Tsz King and Tong Hio Fong took the oath before the Chief Executive, in a ceremony at Government Headquarters. Among the statements made after the inauguration, Wong Sio Chak highlighted that he will “promote horizontal mobility” to increase the efficiency of communication between services, as well as rectify bad habits of inaction”
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO AND VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Chief Executive yesterday presided over the inauguration and oath ceremonies of the two new Government Secretaries, namely, Wong Sio Chak, in the Administration and Justice portfolio, and Chan Tsz King, who will be responsible for the Security area, as well as the new Public Prosecutor (MP), Tong Hio Fong. The event took place at the Government Headquarters, in front of an audience of around 260 guests, including holders of the Macao SAR's main political positions. At the same time, Wong Sio Chak also took office as a member of the Executive Board.
After the National Anthem was sung and sung, there was silence for the moments of commitment of loyalty from the new government members and the MP leadership, with short statements, followed by the handshake of the Chief Executive. Later, on the sidelines of the oath ceremony for the new deputies to the Legislative Assembly, Wong Sio Chak, Chan Tsz Kin and Tong Hio Fong made their first statements to the journalists who were waiting for them in one of the Forum's interior rooms.
The Secretary for Administration and Justice, who moved from Security, said that he will be governed by some principles, such as “creating an efficient government, improving the organic structure, strengthening personnel management, increasing electronic governance and promoting the good execution of the Lines of Government Action”.
Recalling the work done by his predecessor, André Cheong, who established “principles and goals” to be achieved in the reform of Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak stated that he will establish a legal system “with characteristics specific to Macau”, as well as reinforce coordination between the executive and the legislative, and promote municipal work, such as the revitalization of markets “to create a better environment to live in”. Furthermore, he mentioned the intention of “promoting the integration of Macau with the Greater Bay Area and the Deep Cooperation Zone”.
The Secretary also spoke about the restructuring of public administration, mentioning that the “regulations have already been published”, having established “a goal, a framework”. “We will have some work to do, for example simplifying the structure, this being the main task”, he added.
Asked about how the responsibility regime would be created, he assured that he would develop “horizontal mobility” to increase the efficiency of communication between services. “And we are going to rectify the bad habits of inaction, therefore, it is very important to facilitate and channel communication between services, with the need to take advantage of the various interdepartmental working groups to take advantage of their organizational function”, he said.
Recalling his 11 years of experience in the Security area, Wong Sio Chak used the word unity, “which is the most important thing to carry out our work, increase the capacity of staff and stimulate their potential”. On the other hand, he assumed that innovation, technology, will occupy a priority place, “to increase the capacity to serve the population”.
 
Secretary for Security relies on experience from delegates
Chan Tsz King, in turn, acknowledged that the appointment to the position of Secretary for Security “is not only an honor but also a responsibility”, admitting that “it is a very big challenge”, as he “has little experience” in an area with which he “has never had contact”. The new member of the Government highlighted the “experienced personnel” under his supervision, with particular attention to the general commander of the Unitary Police Services and the general director of the Customs Services.
“I will draw on my experiences throughout my roles as Anti-Corruption Commissioner and Prosecutor, firmly adhere to the spirit of the rule of law, strengthen system construction, improve law enforcement collaboration and supervision mechanism, to ensure that police officers are principled and impartial, and continuously increase the level of professionalism, modernization and intelligence of the security team,” he said.
Referring to Lam In Sang's appointment as head of his Cabinet, Chan Tsz King said it was “a vote of confidence”. "We have had many working contacts over time, from the Public Ministry. I believe we will have very close cooperation." Lam was appointed yesterday, by order of the Secretary for Security.
Regarding the next work he intends to carry out, the Secretary said that “legal diplomas are already being produced” that will be implemented in the future. “National security has long-term development”, he emphasized, promising “to continue improving the regime”, assuming that “the construction of the [law supervision] mechanism will still take some time to be improved”.
The former MP prosecutor promised to “make every effort to implement the Chief’s governance philosophy, firmly defend national security and realize the overall security perspective”. “We will always improve, constantly develop new thoughts and ensure that Macau is a safe, stable city based on the rule of law”, assured Chan.
 
Prosecutor wants to reinforce confidence in Justice
Tong Hio Fong, the new MP Prosecutor, promised to “preserve the rule of law” and “the rights and interests of citizens”, using the “sacred function” of the prosecutor's office to combat crime. Tong intends to “conserve the constitutional order established by the Constitution and the Basic Law” and protect “national sovereignty, national security and national development interests”, under the motto “justice for the people, serve the people”.
He stated that he will lead this Public Prosecutor's Office team “with all integrity to continue with inspection missions, increase judicial efficiency and also preserve the position of the MP”, asserted the Prosecutor. “For the people to have confidence in the MP, it is necessary to have an integral and professional team”.
Tong Hio Fong also intends to “maintain positive interaction with all other government entities and departments” and review the constitution of its staff “to review whether there are aspects to improve and increase efficiency”.
In response to a question about the current status of the case of former deputy Au Kam San, for alleged violations of the State Security Defense Law, Tong did not provide any information, arguing that he cannot do so while the case “is in the investigation phase” so that it “has a smooth procedure”.
 
Known names of Cabinet heads
The heads of Cabinet of the new members of the Government were made public through orders from the respective office holders. Thus, Chang Cheong was appointed to carry out these functions with the Secretary for Administration and Justice, until December 19, 2026. Lam In Sang will also head the Office of the Secretary for Security, for the same period. Meanwhile, Wong Hio Nam will perform identical functions in the Prosecutor's Office, while Ng Meng Tai will be deputy chief, both for one year, starting yesterday. In another order published in the Official Gazette, the Chief Executive appointed Wong Sio Chak as spokesperson for the Executive Council. Sam Hou Fai also appointed, on an occasional service commission basis, four public service workers to the bodies of the Executive Committee of the Deep Cooperation Zone. They are Sou Hoi Chi and Lei Teng Ian, from the Administration and Civil Service Bureau, and Ju Xiaoxi and Ng Chon Fat, from the Institute for Municipal Affairs.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unanimous hemicycle in the election of the president and three more positions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/hemiciclo-unanime-na-eleicao-presidente-mais-tres-cargos/</link><description>With 33 votes, André Cheong was elected president of the Legislative Assembly. Yesterday, in the Hemicycle, there was total harmony, as in four votes – for the president, vice-president and first and second secretaries – those chosen all obtained exactly 33 in favor. On the sidelines of the plenary session, and after the former Secretary for Administration and Justice had taken the oath before the Chief Executive, André Cheong highlighted the fact that the AL is now “younger” and argued that one of the objectives of the legislative body is “to reinforce positive interaction with the Government”

Catarina Pereira
 
André Cheong was unanimously elected president of the Legislative Assembly (AL) yesterday. The name of the former Secretary for Administration and Justice was repeated 33 times by the deputies who scrutinized the votes, in what was the first session of the new legislature.
After the election, the president of the legislative body and the deputies went to the Service Platform Complex for Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, where André Cheong took the oath before the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai. The ceremony was attended by hundreds of guests, including the first Chief Executive of the Macao SAR, Edmund Ho, the Secretaries of the current Government and the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the PRC in the Macao SAR, Liu Xianfa.
After the AL plenary session concluded, André Cheong spoke to journalists, stating that the body he presides over will “insist on the principle of predominance of executive power and legislative and supervisory work”, as well as “reinforce positive interaction with the Government”.
But in what way? “Both in legislative work and in monitoring the Government, the AL and the Government may have different opinions and we hope that the AL can make the proposed laws more responsive to public opinion and more in line with public expectations”, he stated. “We will learn from the work experiences of me and other deputies who have worked for many years in different areas, as well as the successful experiences of the last seven ALs”, added André Cheong.
For the now president of the AL, “in recent years, there has been a significant improvement in the interaction between the AL and the Government, however, there is still room for improvement”. “One of the most important points for the AL is for the Government to deliver the legislative plans, and in this work I hope that the Government communicates in advance, so that the AL understands which legislative projects are priorities for the following year”, he continued, admitting that after the laws are delivered “there are both political problems and technical problems” that need to be resolved.
From his perspective, the most important thing is that there is communication with technical advisors and between the Government and deputies. “Through these communication and discussion actions, we hope that the proposed laws will be more in line with public opinion and the needs of the population”, he stressed.
André Cheong believes that the legislative work will focus on the legal system of State security, improving the well-being of the population and the business environment, promoting the development of adequate diversification of the economy and strengthening the interconnection of systems and regimes with the Deep Cooperation Zone, in addition to strengthening Public Administration reform.
On the occasion, the former Secretary also noted that “after Macau returned to its homeland, the great contributions of previous presidents prepared a very solid and robust basis for the work of the AL”. He also recalled that the election for the Hemicycle was the first under the new Electoral Law, “which further consolidated the principle of ‘Macau governed by patriots’”.
Furthermore, André Cheong noted that of the 33 deputies, 15 are new compared to the last legislature, with 14 taking office for the first time. “The deputies come from different sectors of society and have made the AL younger and more professional”, he argued, highlighting that “with the joint efforts of all the deputies, the work of the new edition of the AL will make new contributions to the prosperity of the Macao SAR”.
It should be noted that this is the first time that the AL will be chaired by a deputy appointed by the Chief, as his predecessors – Susana Chou, Lau Cheok Va, Ho Iat Seng and Kou Hoi In – were all elected by indirect suffrage.
Born in Beijing in 1966, André Cheong graduated in Portuguese Language (Beijing University of Foreign Studies) and Law (Faculty of Law, University of Macau). In December 2019, Cheong joined the Ho Iat Seng Government as Secretary for Administration and Justice, a position he held until the day before yesterday. Previously, he was Commissioner against Corruption.
 
Ho Ion Sang is deputy, Si Ka Lon and Ella Lei as secretaries
After the election of the president and the oath ceremony, André Cheong and the remaining deputies returned to the Hemicycle for the plenary meeting where the vice-president, first secretary and second secretary of the AL were elected.
Like the vote for the president, the three elections that followed could not have been more unanimous, as all deputies were in complete agreement: all 33 deputies voted for Ho Ion Sang as vice-president of the AL, all 33 deputies chose Si Ka Lon as first secretary and all 33 deputies elected Ella Lei as second secretary.
On the sidelines of the plenary session, AL vice-president-elect, Ho Ion Sang, promised “full support” for André Cheong’s work. As a deputy, he ensured the fulfillment of functions and responsibilities and learning from other deputies. Ho Ion Sang also highlighted that he is convinced that, under the leadership of the new president, the work of the AL will be implemented in a better way, and that the AL will be able to perform its functions well, boosting the economic and social development of the Macao SAR and also matters related to the Greater Bay Area and the Deep Cooperation Zone.
In the same vein, Si Ka Lon, first secretary, and Ella Lei, second secretary of the AL, guaranteed support for the new president and vice-president of the AL. Si Ka Lon highlighted that he will insist on his “initial objective” and will continue to “serve citizens”, also ensuring more communication with the Government in favor of the economy and interaction between the legislative and executive powers. Ella Lei assured that, as a deputy, she will continue to carry out legislative work and promote policies.
In the morning, also at the Service Platform Complex for Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking Countries, Sam Hou Fai had already sworn in the deputies, elected and appointed, for a four-year term in the AL. The deputies, in turn, also took the oath.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caritas opens rehabilitation center in Zone A at the end of this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caritas-abre-centro-de-reabilitacao-na-zona-final-deste-ano/</link><description>At the end of this year, Caritas will open an integrated rehabilitation services center in the Tong Kai Building, in Zone A of the New Landfills. According to the general secretary of Caritas, the center will provide 20 temporary care places, 40 professional training places and 40 intellectual development places, for people with disabilities. In the last “charity run”, Caritas raised 660 thousand patacas, an amount that will be channeled to the social company “We Connect”, which provides support to the elderly at home

Caritas Macau will open an integrated rehabilitation services center in the Tong Kai Building, an affordable housing located in Zone A of the New Landfills. The project is in the preparatory phase and should begin operating at the end of this year, revealed Paul Pun, general secretary of Caritas.
According to him, the new center will provide a total of 100 service places for people with disabilities, including 20 temporary care, 40 professional training and 40 intellectual development.
Currently, Caritas offers seven rehabilitation services for people with disabilities. The services focus on accommodation, meals, therapy and professional training, also covering a regular shuttle bus service on the Peninsula, for people with reduced mobility. In addition, the institution is preparing a pastry shop in the São Lázaro neighborhood, intending for four or five people with disabilities to work in this establishment per day. The sale of bread and cakes will begin when a mentor is found, according to Paul Pun.
On the other hand, the same person in charge indicated that, in the last eight editions of the Caritas “charity race”, the institution managed to obtain more than three million patacas. This year, the race organized together with the University of Macau at the end of September raised around 660 thousand patacas (before expenses were deducted) and the participation of around two thousand people.
Paul Pun revealed that the funds raised through charity races will be used to build new nursing homes and develop some projects not subsidized by the Government.
This time, the total raised will be used to cover the operating expenses of “We Connect”, a Caritas social enterprise that provides support to the elderly, as well as to help partially subsidize some users who need this service fully, but face financial limitations.
This social enterprise began operations at the end of 2024, sending helpers at home or to designated locations to provide monitoring, daily care and health preservation services to elderly people in need.
Caritas also recently promoted a community awareness activity on dementia in Taipa, with the aim of deepening the public's knowledge about this pathology. Lam Sok Fan, coordinator of the Caritas Special Longevity Care Center, whose users are 55 years of age or older, pointed to a trend of decreasing the average age of people with dementia in Macau.
Noting that there are currently around 6,000 people diagnosed with dementia in the Macao SAR, Lam Sok Fan argued that the emergence of more relatively young dementia patients is related to increased public knowledge about the disease, which translates into greater use of medical consultations.
 
Charity Bazaar scheduled for November 1st and 2nd
Caritas will hold the 56th Charity Bazaar, next to Lake Nam Van, on the 1st and 2nd of November. The funds raised are intended to develop innovative social services and optimize current projects not subsidized by the Government, stated the institution, announcing that, at the same time, charity flags will be sold in several areas in the territory. The Bazaar will have 77 gaming stands, 14 gastronomy stands and four children's entertainment stands, involving 95 participating entities. More than 100 thousand Bazaar raffle coupons worth 10 patacas have already been sold. In 2024, Caritas received 20.57 million patacas in donations, including 6.45 million in the Bazaar. At a press conference about the initiative, the secretary general of Caritas highlighted several services launched by the institution this year, including an online consultation line and platform for counseling and emotional support for students, and a new community services team to “give care to the elderly”. Regarding the Caritas clinic, in Areia Preta, he indicated that, as soon as the Health Services issue the license, it will start operating, charging a “low fee”. Caritas will also organize Christmas activities, intending to offer gifts and food packages to 800 local children from low-income families and 750 from poor families in Timor-Leste, Bangladesh and Pakistan.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic diversification is “at a key stage”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/diversificacao-economica-esta-numa-fase-chave/</link><description>The Secretary for Economy and Finance says that Macau is at a crucial stage in terms of the strategy to promote economic diversification. Tai Kin Ip visited several associations to gather opinions within the scope of the Lines of Government Action and promised to implement the governance philosophy based on “focusing on economic growth, promoting diversification, benefiting the lives of the population and seeking development”
 
Macau “is at a key stage in promoting adequate economic diversification”, highlighted the Secretary for Economy and Finance during a series of meetings with local associations to gather opinions and suggestions on their supervision, as part of the preparation of the Governing Action Lines (LAG) for next year. According to a statement from his office, Tai Kin Ip promised to implement the governance philosophy based on “focusing on economic growth, promoting diversification, benefiting people's lives and seeking development”, in addition to adhering to the '1+4' industry development direction, deepening the construction of the Hengqin Deep Cooperation Zone and further optimizing the business environment”.
The government official, who led a group of supervisory leaders, assured, on the other hand, that support will be provided to small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) to “improve their quality, stabilize local employment, create more development opportunities for residents and continually improve measures to guarantee the well-being of the population”.
He also expressed special thanks to the various associations for their cooperation with the Government in responding to the recent super-typhoon, for the rapid mobilization of forces and for encouraging residents to help each other. He also highlighted the implementation of solid preparations for disaster prevention, which, in his view, contributed to “effectively” reducing the economic losses caused by the storm and promoting the rapid recovery of the local business environment.
During the sessions, representatives of the associations presented suggestions in areas that included “commitment to the development of adequate diversification of the economy, the improvement of the structure of Macau's industries, the promotion of collaborative development between Macau and Hengqin and the continuous revitalization of the community economy”.
The “improvement of measures to support the population and companies”, “continuous” support for SMEs, “revitalization of the business environment in historic areas”, “guaranteeing employment for residents”, “increasing investment attraction” and “support for technological innovation” were some of the other topics discussed with the Secretary.
Several service directors participated in the meetings, namely Tourism, Economy and Technological Development, Labor Affairs, Finance and Statistics and Census, in addition to heads of other entities, including the Monetary Authority and the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Climate litigation in China is led by prosecutors… not activists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/litigios-climaticos-na-china-sao-liderados-por-procuradores-nao-por-activistas/</link><description>Environmental and climate litigation is on the rise in China, with thousands of courts and more than a million recent cases. And, unlike other countries, it is the prosecutors who drive these processes. China is the largest emitter of greenhouse gases and its performance in this field will determine the trajectory of climate change in the world. Around the world, national and international courts are the new battleground for pressuring governments on climate issues. Perhaps the most high-profile victory came in July at the International Court of Justice, which declared that countries have a duty to address climate change. But in China, cases tend to focus on enforcement, and NGOs and activists often remain on the sidelines. The courts ensure compliance with the government's climate rules, which are spread across various laws and regulations, but do not promote changes to these environmental policies, explains Zhu Mingzhe, a law professor at the University of Glasgow. Although many cases “contribute to the mitigation” of climate change “they do not directly address” this phenomenon, he summarizes. Ahead of November's COP30 climate summit, President Xi Jinping presented China's first emissions targets, with a promise to reduce greenhouse gases by 7 to 10% within a decade. The numbers are lower than experts consider necessary, but there is little chance they will be challenged in court. Instead, “courts and prosecutors ensure that laws are effective,” Boya Jiang, a climate lawyer at ClientEarth in Beijing, told AFP. A decade ago, an environmental authority could avoid being sanctioned for failing to comply with environmental duties if it achieved economic growth. Now, “she will be taken to court and there will be severe punishments,” Jiang assured. Companies must also consider environmental impacts, he said. Between 2019 and 2023, the courts resolved more than a million cases, according to state media, almost 20% more than in the previous five years. There is broad support for environmental litigation in public opinion and the government has empowered prosecutors, said Lu Xu, a law professor at Lancaster University. It is a “politically correct” topic at all levels, he commented. For example, in 2020, prosecutors in Huzhou province won a public interest case against a company that used freon, a refrigerant gas banned due to its powerful greenhouse effect. The company had to pay harsh compensation. More than 95% of potential cases are resolved before reaching court, and the mere threat of litigation is an effective mechanism for enforcing laws. NGOs are marginal actors who cannot sue the government or officials, however, they can accuse private and state companies. In 2017, Friends of the Earth – one of China's oldest environmental NGOs – accused state-owned companies of excluding wind and solar energy sources in favor of polluting sources. The case was resolved in 2023 when the state network promised to invest in increasing renewable sources. An environmental lawyer from an NGO admits that public prosecutors have more power, but that other actors still have an important role. According to the lawyer, who requested anonymity to avoid harming his organization, prosecutors sometimes “consider local interests and economic pressures, therefore, they avoid prosecuting”. NGOs have more freedom, “so we can present cases”. China's new Ecological and Environmental Code, which is expected to come into force in 2026, and a climate law more than a decade in the making, could pave the way to present more ambitious cases, Jiang said.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National Games cycling will cross the Delta Bridge</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ciclismo-dos-jogos-nacionais-vai-cruzar-ponte-delta/</link><description>Macau's urban road will be part of the route of the men's individual cycling event at the National Games through the Delta Bridge. The route will also pass through Hong Kong, Zhuhai and the Deep Zone in Hengqin, totaling 231.8 kilometers in length. More than a hundred athletes from across the country will participate in the competition
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The first cross-border event in the history of the National Games of the People's Republic of China will connect the urban roads of Hong Kong, Macau, Zhuhai and the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin, through the Delta Bridge, in a cycling race that will feature around a hundred athletes representing all provinces of the country. The event was presented in Zhuhai at a press conference to publicize the cycling events included in the program of the 15th edition of the National Games.
The men's individual category, the one that will pass through the REAM urban route, will take place on November 8th, covering a length of 231.8 kilometers. The race will also be the only cross-border and emblematic race connecting Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau.
The entire route of the Macau Competition Zone passes through the Macau Bridge and the Taipa Pac On Ferry Terminal, with tests having already been carried out in the three regions in November 2024, which “worked well”, according to the deputy coordinator of the Executive Committee of the Zhuhai Competition Zone and vice-president of the Zhuhai People's Government, Huang Zhenqiu.
Igualmente, no dia 30 de Setembro, teve lugar um simulacro integrado antes das competições com Zhuhai e Macau, com o objectivo de testar especialmente a coordenação entre a competição e o sistema de comando de segurança das três regiões, o sistema de passagem fronteiriça RFID, os sinais da rede, a protecção de saúde, a assistência em caso de emergência, entre outros.
“The drill took place normally,” said the coordinator of the Hong Kong Competition Zone Coordination Office, Yeung Tak Keung, during the meeting with the media.
Macao SAR was represented at the press conference by the coordinator of the Preparatory Office for the Organization of the Macau Competition Zone. Pun Weng Kun highlighted that, “in order to prepare well for the race, public services have maintained close contacts with Guangdong and Hong Kong, carrying out several on-site visits to the race sites”.
On the other hand, Pun Weng Kun said he hopes that the race's passage through the territory's urban road can once again demonstrate the charm of Macau, and with the joint efforts of Guangdong and Hong Kong, in order to guarantee the holding of a historic cross-border event”.
Cycling at the National Games will have other races, which will not have Macau as the stage, between November 7th and November 9th, including men's and women's time trials and men's and women's individual events.
Meanwhile, the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) promoted a Volunteer Mobilization Meeting for the National Games, in an event that brought together teachers and students.
At the animation ceremony, the rector of UPM, Marcus Im, stated that, “since the launch of volunteer recruitment, the institution has been organizing students and teachers to participate in recruitment”.
After the Mobilization Meeting, a session was organized on the distribution of volunteer work for the official competitions of the National Games.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese open restaurant in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/portugueses-abrem-restaurante-em-hengqin/</link><description>A Mediterranean cuisine restaurant officially opens this Saturday in the Deep Cooperation Zone in Hengqin. Located in the Huafa shopping center, the Vivo restaurant is a project by two Portuguese people who saw an opportunity to bring two geographies closer together – China and southern Europe.



















It's not about fusion cuisine. Still, several traditions coexist in this restaurant: Portuguese, Spanish and Italian cuisine, prepared by a chef from Shanghai with Chinese raw materials.
“We are in China, we want to invest in fresh Chinese products”, one of the partners, João Maria Pegado, tells Lusa.
So much so that, for now, there is no traditional octopus à lagareiro on the menu. You have to continue browsing local markets until you find the ideal product, explains Pegado.
"We could go to Macau to get frozen octopus, but our main objective was to work with fresh products in China. In terms of cost, it makes it much more profitable, but we also want to take advantage and create this fusion between Chinese products and Portuguese dishes", he says.
Vivo has been in ‘soft opening’ mode since July 18th. And João Maria Pegado does not complain about the journey he has taken so far, despite the difficulty of the language.
To Lusa, he says that he will soon compete for support from the Macau Government, at a time when the authorities are encouraging investment in the Deep Cooperation Zone, a special economic area, created in 2021 with a view to economic diversification and regional integration of the Macao SAR with the rest of the country.
And Hengqin is attracting more and more visitors from Macau, says the investor. In this area managed by both sides of the border, the movement of drivers from Macau is now permitted, for example, upon request for a license, recalls Pegado.
But there are other attractions: gasoline is cheaper – “the cars in Macau come to fill up at the weekend, we [Portuguese] are like in Badajoz” – supermarkets are more affordable, more space and more green areas. "An open space where you can relax without being in the middle of the city. That's the big reason why people leave Macau for Hengqin on the weekends and sometimes even during the week, at lunchtime", he reflects.
Hengqin also seems to be a more economical option for Chinese people visiting Macau, where, according to data for August, the average price of a hotel room is 1,461 patacas.
"Hengqin has increasingly become a point of concentration, of sleeping, used by many visitors. Many of the buildings that were built as offices, the Government gave licenses (…) to build Airbnb-style hotels [local accommodation]", he said.
Hong Kong and Macau are, for now, the origin of the majority of the restaurant's visitors, but João Maria Pegado also hopes to reach more consumers from Mainland China.
“There are still few people who know what Mediterranean [the concept] means”, he highlights, noting, however, that, for many of those who have visited Vivo, black paella has been a recurring choice.
This dish is joined by other specialties of the house, such as fisherman's rice, guilloche prawns or barbecue chicken, says Pegado, who left a career linked to sport to dedicate himself to the restaurant business.
“It’s special”, he admits. “I felt that there was a lack of a Western food restaurant, and that it could be successful in that area (…). I have lived in Hengqin for three years and it is a place that I really appreciate, it allows me to be close to Macau, the city where I grew up and with which I feel identified”, he concludes.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR present at Justice Forum on “both sides of the Strait”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-presente-em-forum-de-justica-dos-dois-lados-estreito/</link><description>The president of the Court of Final Appeal (TUI), Song Man Lei, led a delegation from the Macao SAR to Hong Kong to participate in the “8th High-Level Forum on Justice on both sides of the Taiwan Strait, Hong Kong and Macau”, organized by the judicial body of the neighboring region. The event was attended by around 160 representatives of the judicial sector from both sides of the Taiwan Strait, Hong Kong and Macau. The forum's theme was “Challenges and Opportunities faced by the Judiciary in the New Era” and was subdivided into four subthemes: “Construction of Diversified Mechanisms for the Resolution of Civil and Commercial Disputes”, “Optimization of the Civil and Commercial Process Regime”, “Application of Artificial Intelligence” and “Practice and Development of the Jurisprudence Regime”, according to a note issued by the Office of the President of the TUI. Throughout the forum, “judicial representatives from both sides of the Taiwan Strait, Hong Kong and Macau widely debated the proposed sub-themes and shared experiences and learned from each other”, the statement also indicates. For the organization, “the forum was a complete success, produced fruitful results, infused new vitality into judicial cooperation and exchange between different jurisdictions and contributed to the advancement of the judicial cause”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2487/</link><description>Restaurant “earnings” fell 39% in 2024
The gross surplus of restaurants and similar establishments in the Macao SAR amounted to 89.23 million patacas in 2024, representing an annual decline of 38.8%, with revenues rising 3.4% to 12.75 billion and expenses increasing 3.8% to 12.68 billion, reported the Statistics and Census Service. Takeaway stores recorded a deficit of 149 million, which “continuously narrowed” compared to 2023, having recorded revenues of 2.25 billion (+2.7%) and expenses of 2.40 billion (-0.4%). On the other hand, revenues (46.86 million) and expenses (26.88 million) of food and beverage outlets in municipal markets showed year-on-year increases of 10.0% and 17.9%, respectively. The gross surplus in this branch amounted to 19.98 million. In 2024, 4,930 catering establishments were in operation, including 2,470 restaurants and similar with space to serve meals, 80 food and drink outlets in municipal markets and 2,380 food and drink takeaway stores without space to serve meals. The survey excludes catering establishments operated directly by hotels and gaming companies, as well as street food stalls.
 
Tourist prices show a slight increase until September
The Tourist Price Index (IPT) in Macau increased by 0.57% in the first nine months of this year, compared to the same period in 2024, according to data from the Statistics and Census Bureau. Even so, in the third quarter, the IPT decreased by 0.82%, in annual terms, mainly due to the decrease in hotel room prices, in contrast to the increases in jewelry and entertainment and leisure. On the other hand, between July and September, the IPT grew 2.12%, when compared to the previous quarter, stimulated by the increase in the price of hotel rooms and plane tickets during the summer holidays. The average IPT for the four quarters ending in the reference quarter, in relation to the four immediately previous quarters, rose 0.69%.
 
Fashion show will present work by seven designers
Wong Chi Un, Leong Man Teng, Ding Zhen, Ng Ka Wai, Wong Man I, Lei Wei Cheng and Vong Si Weng will be the designers represented in the “Fashion Design Sample Creation Subsidy Program Work Parade”, which will take place on October 22nd (Wednesday), at 4:45 pm, at the Florence Hall of the Venetian Macau, with free entry. Organized by the Cultural Institute (IC) and coordinated by the Macau Productivity and Technology Transfer Center, the event is part of the “Macao Fashion Festival 2025”. According to the IC, more than 56 sets of clothing will be presented at this show, which will also feature the presence of professionals from the local fashion sector and other regions, “with the aim of enhancing the visibility of local fashion brands, raising the reputation of the sector and promoting partnerships and business opportunities”.
 
Flu virus almost at alert level
The Health Services (SSM) warned that the flu virus has shown a more active trend, reaching almost the alert level. Therefore, the organization renewed its appeals to the population to redouble their attention and precautions. According to the SSM, the number of flu patients began to rise in mid-September, with adult and pediatric emergency consultations increasing by more than 30% last week, in monthly terms. On the other hand, cases of collective flu infections have increased since the beginning of the new academic year. These cases, none of which were serious, were recorded mainly in secondary and primary education.
 
Government Headquarters opens to the public on the weekend
The Government Headquarters will open to the public on the weekend, between 9:00 am and 6:00 pm, and visitors can visit the Protocolar Palace and the garden, where there is a flower exhibition dedicated to the National Games, and also watch shows, namely, by the CPSP Band and students from the Macau Conservatory's School of Music and School of Dance. The exhibition is divided into four thematic zones, with the ping pong chrysanthemum being the main flower, in addition to more than 20 species of flowers being used. The public will be able to visit the Multipurpose, Lotus Flower, Green, Yellow and Blue rooms.
 
New job combination offers 179 vacancies
The Labor Affairs Services and the Federation of Workers' Associations will organize four labor conjugation sessions, with 179 offers. On the 23rd, the Hotel Roosevelt offers 54 vacancies, for shift manager, room manager, reception supervisor, receptionist, concierge and network technician. The next day, MGM has 31 vacancies, for assistant chef of catering, catering supervisor and cook. In turn, CDFG Macau will offer 30 positions for salespeople and Nova Galaxy Entretenimento 2006 will have a session with 64 vacancies on the 28th, for assistant restaurant manager, restaurant supervisor, reception agent, bar employee, among others.
 
Registration open for UPM postgraduate courses
Until May 15, 2026, registration is open for master's and doctoral courses in the academic year 2026/2027 at the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM). The courses cover areas such as technological innovation, 'big health', sports sciences, language translation, culture and creativity, public administration, business management and finance, among others, indicated the higher education institution.
 
Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro wins award in Budapest
Photojournalist Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro was awarded the Gold award in the Editorial/Political category of the “Budapest International Foto Awards” (BIFA), with a photo report on the visit of the Chinese President, Xi Jinping, to Macau, during the celebrations of the 25th anniversary of the Macao SAR. Created for Agência Lusa, the photographic series “documents key moments of the presidential visit, with images that capture the solemn atmosphere of the official ceremonies and the political symbolism of the occasion”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New IMF forecasts foresee slower growth in the Macao SAR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novas-previsoes-fmi-anteveem-crescimento-mais-lento-da-raem/</link><description>Macau's Gross Domestic Product is expected to grow 2.6% this year, according to new forecasts from the International Monetary Fund, and in April, estimates pointed to annual growth of 3.6%. The IMF also reduced its projections for 2026 in Macau, pointing to growth of 2.8%, below the 3.5% previously forecast. Inflation is also expected to slow down more than expected in April, growing just 0.5% and 1.2%, in 2025 and 2026, respectively. On the other hand, forecasts for the world economy have improved
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
 
The International Monetary Fund (IMF) once again revised downwards its forecasts for the growth of the Macao SAR's Gross Domestic Product (GDP), according to the most recent report on the “World Economic Outlook”. This year, GDP is expected to grow just 2.6%, below the IMF forecasts published in April, which pointed to a 3.6% increase. For next year, the same institution predicts that GDP will grow 2.8%, 0.7 percentage points less than what it anticipated six months ago.
According to data from Macau's Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), the value of the territory's GDP only increased 1.8% in the first six months of 2025, in real and annual terms, representing 87% of the economic volume of the same period in 2019, the pre-pandemic year. Between April and June, the local economy advanced 5.1% in real terms, compared to the same quarter of 2024, and 0.62% compared to the previous three months.
The latest IMF estimates also point to inflation in Macau being 0.5% in 2025, below the 0.9% initially forecast in April. For 2026, the organization expects inflation to be 1.2%, which would contradict the downward trend that has been observed since 2023, in the territory.
The latest data from DSEC shows that the annual inflation rate completed 14 consecutive months of slowdown, standing at 0.25% in August. In the general calculation of 2024, inflation was estimated at 0.74%.
Furthermore, with regard to unemployment rates this year and 2026, the IMF maintained its April projections, both at 1.7%. In turn, DSEC reported that the general unemployment rate stood at 2.0% between June and August 2025 and 2.6%, maintaining the level of the previous period (May to July).
Conversely, the international institution's forecasts for the Macao SAR's balance sheet for 2025 and 2026 improved by 5.5 and six percentage points, respectively, to 35.5% and 34.9%.
For 2030, the IMF estimates that Macau's GDP will grow by 3% and an inflation rate of 2.2%, values ​​identical to those predicted in April. Furthermore, it also expects the Macao SAR's balance sheet to be 33.2% at the end of the decade, above the 28.9% projected half a year ago.
Forecasts for GDP growth in the Macao SAR remain above estimates for the average of advanced economies in the world, whose value will grow by 1.6%, both in 2025 and 2026, predicts the IMF. China's GDP is expected to grow 4.8% this year and 4.2% next year. In turn, the US economy will grow by 2% and 2.1% in 2025 and 2026, respectively. In turn, Portugal's economy will increase by 1.9% in 2025 and 2.1% next year. Overall, analysts have revised upwards projections for the world economy, expecting it to grow 3.2% in 2025 and 3.1% next year, whereas in April expectations were that it would grow 2.8% and 3%, respectively. However, “risks remain tilted downwards”, warns the IMF.
In the universe of advanced economies in Asia-Pacific, the IMF forecasts overall growth of 4.5% and 4.1% in 2025 and 2026, respectively. In estimates for 2025, the Macao SAR is now behind Taiwan (+3.7%), but continues to surpass the increases projected for Hong Kong (+2.4%), Singapore (+2.2%), Australia (+1.8%), Japan (+1.1%), South Korea (+0.9%) and New Zealand (+0.8%). Overall for Asia, including large emerging economies such as China and India, the IMF anticipates increases of 4.5% this year and 4.1% in 2026.
In advanced economies worldwide, inflation is expected to slow down, to an average of 2.5% this year, and 2.2% in 2026. According to the IMF, price developments in China will stagnate this year and register an increase of 0.7% next year. US inflation will be 2.7% and 2.4% in 2025 and 2026, respectively. Portugal will see its inflation rate stabilize at 2.2% and 2.1% between this year and next.
Regarding China's unemployment rate, the IMF predicts that this indicator will remain at 4.9% until the end of next year. In the cases of the USA and Portugal, unemployment is expected to fall by 0.1 percentage point between 2025 and 2026. The USA will record an unemployment rate of 4.2% in 2025 and 4.1% next year, while Portugal's rate will decrease from 6.4% to 6.3% in the same time frame.
 
“Modest” impact of trade tariffs
In the report published in April, the IMF highlighted the impact that trade tariffs imposed by the US on most of its partners could have on the world economy. In the same month, North American President Donald Trump had announced the application of a series of customs duties on imports from several countries, which generated uncertainty and destabilized international markets. After six months, the organization considers that the effect of the new rates has been “modest”.
“The impact of the trade shock on growth has been moderate so far,” said IMF chief economist Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas, quoted by AFP. The agility of the private sector, which accelerated imports in the first half of the year, in anticipation of the tariffs coming into force, and reorganized its supply chains, containment by some countries and the various agreements between the US and its partners “kept the commercial system open”.
However, the IMF believes that trade tensions continue to "cast a shadow over the global economy, with trade policy uncertainty remaining high. The effect of these tensions may well increase over time as companies gradually pass tariffs on to consumers as trade is redirected more permanently and the global economy gradually becomes less efficient." “Everything is very fluid,” observed Gourinchas. “It’s a very useful reminder that we live in a world where this kind of escalation of trade tensions and political uncertainty can emerge at any time,” he added.
In the preface to the report, Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas also points out the existence of “other important forces”, such as a “poorly balanced” labor market and an unchanged unemployment rate. For example, in the US, “tighter immigration policies are reducing the work provided by foreign workers, another negative shock”. For the chief economist, “until we see, this has been offset by a relatively equivalent decline in labor demand, resulting from a cooling cycle after many years of strong employment growth”. The devaluation of the dollar also worsened inflation driven by the North American country's new tariffs.
On the other hand, emerging markets and developing economies have benefited from easier access to financing, due to the depreciation of the dollar. In China, the country most targeted by the Donald Trump administration's tariffs, economic growth is expected to slow down “modestly”, influenced by the depreciation of the effective exchange rate, a boost in exports to Asian and European partners and some fiscal measures. In the eurozone, growth was also driven by Germany's fiscal policies.
The IMF expects the world economy to slow down by the end of the year and register a “partial recovery” in 2026, having also listed a set of potential risks such as the possible overvaluation of the artificial intelligence industry, the weak prospects for China's real estate sector, the public accounts of some countries and the growing political pressure that central banks face.
Pierre-Olivier Gourinchas encourages governments “to ensure that private entrepreneurs can innovate, prosper and generate the growth of tomorrow”. “While it may be tempting to implement industrial policies, evidence suggests that their effectiveness may be very limited and the side effects significant.” “The use of horizontal policies is preferable”, argues the Frenchman, such as investing in education, research, public infrastructure, good governance, macroeconomic and financial stability and a regulatory environment that balances, with caution, flexibility and innovation.
For the economist, an important factor in the resilience of the world economy is the fact that most countries "exercised restraint in retaliating against trade policies, sought to forge better deals, and are still operating under the well-established norms of world trade. Recent geopolitical tensions highlight how the need for an adaptable and pragmatic multilateral system is greater than ever", concludes Gourinchas.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Airport will have 56 parking platforms after expansion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aeroporto-tera-56-plataformas-de-estacionamento-apos-expansao/</link><description>At a meeting of the Islands' Community Services Advisory Council, the Civil Aviation Authority revealed that the number of parking platforms at Macau Airport will increase from 36 to 56 when the airport's expansion is completed.
 
After the completion of the expansion of Macau International Airport, scheduled for 2030, the number of parking platforms will be increased from 36 to 56, said Li Yongjian, deputy coordinator of the Islands Community Services Advisory Council, and Ieong Weng Kuong, member of that advisory board, citing representatives from the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM).
According to them, the construction of the new parking platforms will be completed in 2028.
According to Chinese-language media, at a meeting of the respective advisory body, AACM representatives presented the planning for the airport's expansion and corresponding arrangements. At the meeting, the organization also recalled that the expansion project began in April this year, and the works will increase the airport's capacity from 10 million to 13 million passengers per year. At the end of the contracts, the airport's usable space is expected to increase from 177 to 325 hectares.
On the other hand, AACM representatives stated that they had already submitted contingency plans to the Government in terms of preventing floods and typhoons during the period of works at the airport. Ieong Weng Kuong said that the quarterly results of environmental and flood prevention tests have been completed.
As noted, one of the landing and take-off runways will be closed from 0:00 to 8:00, but not daily, throughout the works.
 
Air Macau will launch Macau-Jinan route in December
From December 11th, Air Macau will operate a new air route, between Macau and Jinan, capital of Shandong province, served by A320 aircraft. According to the Chinese press, there will be three flights per week (on Tuesdays, Thursdays and Saturdays). It is worth remembering that Air Macau first opened the route to Jinan in 2013, but ended up suspending this connection due to market adjustments.
 
Government will encourage the exploration of more scenarios for the use of drones
The Civil Aviation Authority (AACM) revealed that the Working Group for the Development of the Low Altitude Economy is studying the optimization of the approval process for the use of drones, in order to support companies and scientific research institutions in carrying out more commercial applications and tests. In response to a written inquiry from Congressman Si Ka Lon, the AACM promised that the Government will continue to encourage the sector to explore application scenarios for drone technology, and will proactively deepen exchanges and cooperation with neighboring regions, such as the Greater Bay Area, exploring possibilities for collaboration in the field of low-altitude economics. Furthermore, he revealed that he will study, with the aeronautical authorities of Mainland China and the HKSAR, coordinated control between unmanned aircraft and traditional civil aviation, creating a timely communication mechanism. Furthermore, he indicated that the Tourism Services plan to introduce drone presentations in “Iluminar Macau 2025”, scheduled for December, “as a concrete practice in the local low-altitude economy scenario”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAS points to advances in women's development</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ias-aponta-para-avancos-desenvolvimento-das-mulheres/</link><description>The plans for the second period of the “Macao Women's Development Objectives”, which will run between 2026 and 2032, will be “even more in line” with the needs of women, according to the president of the Institute of Social Action. The organization pointed to advances in this matter
 
The results of the first policies related to the development of women in Macau and the presentation of the second objectives, to be achieved by 2032, were the themes of a sharing session at the Science Center.
Around 120 people were present at the event promoted by the Council for Women and Children's Affairs, including representatives of public services, current and former members of that body, workers from private associations and social service institutions.
After creating a specific group for this purpose, seven years ago, “the dynamic efforts of several public services and the joint participation of private institutions and social sectors” led to the implementation of the measures and the obtaining of “significant results”, according to the Institute of Social Action (IAS).
For the second planning, between 2026 and 2032, the president of the organization and vice-president of the Council for Women and Children's Affairs said that the number of public services participating in these objectives will increase to 21.
Furthermore, Hon Wai highlighted that work on “gender mainstreaming” will continue, as well as that authorities will launch more measures to encourage motherhood, including plans for daycare centers. They will also create a support course on childcare knowledge to provide help to new parents in need and will promote the updating of the division of domestic work “to resolve contradictions between different generations”.
For the 278 action plans drawn up in the first phase, “all goals were achieved”, concluded the IAS number one.
Regarding the assessment of the first period of women's development objectives, carried out between 2019 and 2025, one of the examples focused on was the “gender mainstreaming” of public sector workers. In this parameter, one of the conclusions points to the fact that the salary difference is now “extremely small”, placing it in an advanced position worldwide, according to the IAS.
On the other hand, opportunities were created for women to participate in international affairs, “training young people to be aware of social participation”, he highlighted. As for medical care, the improvement of health policies “allowed a significant increase in the level of health of women, whose life expectancy became the first worldwide”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Carlos Lemos launches new book with photos of the Grand Prix</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/carlos-lemos-lanca-novo-livro-fotos-grande-premio/</link><description>Almost a hundred autographed photographs of car drivers who participated in the Macau Grand Prix, between 1954 and 1978, are included in the second volume of the book dedicated to the motorsport event, written by Carlos Lemos, which will be launched on November 6th. The author, who will be present at the session, told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that the publication aims to publicize the vast collection of around 1,900 photographs, newspaper clippings and posters kept by his father Victor Lemos

 
VÍTOR REBELO
At a time when Macau is undergoing a period of preparation for another edition of the Grand Prix (GPM), the international automobile event is the subject of a publication by Carlos Lemos, which will be launched on November 6th, at 3pm, at the headquarters of the Association of Retirees, Retirees and Pensioners of Macau (APOMAC).
The second volume of the book, with photographs taken between 1967 and 1978, completes the history of the GPM reported in the first volume, between 1954 and 1966. It is a personal collection of Victor H. de Lemos – now deceased, a motor sports enthusiast – which his son Carlos Lemos decided to publish in a book.
The second volume has 356 pages, 100 more than the first. The content and composition are very identical, including more Chinese newspaper clippings. The main highlights are the first fatal accident of the GPM, the failed attempt to create the Far East Motor Racing Association Circuit, the first “Guia Race”, the Race of Giants and the gradual evolution of the event, from amateur races to becoming a world-class sporting event, recognized by the International Automobile Federation (FIA) for Formula Atlantic and Formula 3 races.

The book contains around 471 photographs, as well as an introduction to another collection by Victor H. de Lemos, “World of Motor Racing”, consisting of more than 1,900 autographed photographs of internationally renowned drivers, car owners and designers, such as “II Commendatore” Enzo Ferrari, Stirling Moss, Michael Schumacher, Roy Salvadori, Dan Gurney, Jack Brabham, Juan Manuel Fangio, Helmut Marko, Colin Chapman, Jackie Stewart, Janet Guthrie, Sid Walkins, Tony and Mary Hulman (owners of the Indianapolis circuit), Frank Williams, Charlie Whiting, Louis Meyer, among others.
“It was always his desire to gather all the photographs, many of which contain autographs from drivers, managers and other people directly linked to the automotive world, but also newspaper clippings, posters, circuit access tickets and other elements alluding to the event”, the author of the publication, who will be present at the launch session, revealed to Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU.
Having emigrated to Canada since 1978, Carlos Lemos, 77 years old, says that his father's estate is quite valuable. “If it were not published, it would be losing a great legacy”, he highlights, recognizing that “at that time, in 1978, when he finished his collection, it was very difficult to compile everything into a book, but now, with new technologies, it becomes easier”.
In a publicity note, APOMAC emphasizes that Victor H. de Lemos “was the greatest motorsport enthusiast who, for successive years, followed, very closely, the races on the Guia circuit, having managed to gather a vast collection of photographs and autographs of great drivers”.
This book “will be a relic for all lovers of motor sport and particularly for all those who participated in that event and, as well, for collectors of iconographic records”, adds the introductory document.
“The book is very well organized, with clippings from Portuguese, English and Chinese newspapers, being a work that completes the first”, said the president of the APOMAC board, Francisco Manhão.
The cover price of the publication is 400 patacas, with a discount to 350 during the promotion period. Part of the net proceeds from the sale will go to the Macau IC2 Association (I Can Too), which supports people with autism and other disabilities, with the other part going to APOMAC. The book can be purchased in advance via the email address [email protected] and delivery will be made on the day of release.</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese women's consumption is in countercycle with the economy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/consumo-das-mulheres-chinesas-em-contraciclo-economia/</link><description>The consumption trends of women who are spending on themselves, especially on personal care and travel, have attracted attention in China, in a context of slowdown in the world's second largest economy. As President Xi Jinping's leadership works hard to encourage marriages and procreation in an attempt to stem the declining birth rate, these independent women appear unfazed.
The size of the market, called the “female economy”, is estimated at more than 10 trillion yuan per year.
An all-male dance group whose name literally means “Male Dog Theater” in Chinese has become extremely popular thanks to fan engagement strategies such as photo shoots and autograph signings.
Known for their sensual choreography, the group performed around 340 shows this year in just over a hundred cities in China. The presence of minors under 16 years of age is not permitted at the performance venues.
Fans scream as the group members take off their coats to show off their shapely, semi-naked bodies.
“We try to create a stage where the audience can reveal their true selves and have fun,” said Mr. Ge Junyi, 32, founder of the group.
The driving force behind the “women's economy” are Chinese women in their 20s and 40s, who grew up under the country's one-child policy. Typically, they completed higher education, especially in urban areas, and became financially independent. The wage gap between women and men has also decreased.
With economic prospects uncertain and social values ​​changing, many women do not want to marry or have children.
Income is money to be spent to “pamper ourselves”, as an employee in Shanghai said, as a reward for the exhaustion of hard work and fierce competition in society.
New types of services have emerged for women in China, such as hiking guides accompanying women on mountain trails and amusement parks with handsome men.
While some see this trend as a sign of the improved status of women, others oppose the “commodification” of men.
Traditional Chinese values ​​expect women to be good wives and wise mothers.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>