<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Macao and China reject “interference” of the EU around Au Kam San arrest</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-china-rejeitam-interferencia-da-ue-em-torno-da-detencao-de-au-kam-san/</link><description>Olympus Digital Camera



Following the arrest of Au Kam San, for alleged violations of the State Security Defense, Portugal commented, saying that it is following the case, while the European Union condemned the detention and showed concern. For its part, China's mission in the EU, the RPC MNE Commissioner in Macao and the Government of Masters exhorted Brussels not to interfere with “internal affairs” and not weaving “irresponsible comments”
Catarina Pereira
The case of former deputy Au Kam San - who is awaiting trial in pre -trial detention, on suspicion of violating the law on the defense of State Security - deserved reactions of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (MNE) of Portugal, which claims to be following the situation of the Portuguese citizen, as well as the European Union (EU), which condemned the detention and expressed concern about the “erosion of political pluralism and freedom of expression”. After the comments of Brussels, Macao and Beijing opposed “firmly” to the “interference” of the EU “in the internal affairs of MSAR” and China.
Following the detention of Au Kam San, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao requested a reaction to the MNE of Portugal, also questioning that the joint statement on the issue of Macao, signed in 1987, has been being fulfilled with regard to rights and freedoms - a question that was unanswered.
In the email sent to this newspaper, Portuguese diplomacy states that MNE “is following this subject, through the consulate general of Portugal in Macau”. Paulo Rangel's office also assured that the case "will deserve the best attention of the Portuguese authorities, from the outset in future meetings at the political level, in the spirit of the joint statement."
However, the liberal initiative (IL) will propose to the Portuguese Republic Assembly (AR) a vote of condemnation of the detention of AU and to ask the government to request clarification from the Chinese authorities. According to the voting project to which Lusa had access, IL states that the Portuguese State has the “duty to rigorously follow” the case and ensure respect for the commitments made in the joint statement. The air “cannot remain silent in the face of the arrest of a fellow citizen that dedicated his life to the defense of freedom, nor can ignore the degradation of the regime of freedoms in Macao,” he argues.
In turn, the EU condemned "the detention of the European citizen and former deputy of Macao", in which "the first application of the law on the defense of state security in the since of its adoption in 2009" is constituted. The European service for external action adds that "this development aggravates existing concerns about the continuing erosion of political pluralism and freedom of expression in the MSAR."
Noting that “respect for human rights and fundamental freedoms is a central element of the Macao Basic Law and the“ a country, two systems ”principle”, EU diplomacy also recalls China's duty to respect that the premise of respect for the rights of Macao residents was also established through the Sino-Portuguese joint statement and the international pact on civil and political rights.
It is recalled that the PJ said it had "strong evidence" that Au Kam San was in collusion with a "anti-china organization", having provided "a large amount of false provocative information, for public display abroad and online." In addition, he will "disturb" the election to the 2024 Chief Executive, as well as "to which foreign countries take measures against Macao." The former deputy is thus accused of the crime of “establishment of connections with organizations, associations or individuals from outside the MSAR for acts against state security”, whose prison sentence may be from three to 10 years.
However, this newspaper sent a series of issues to PJ, in order to clarify some aspects, but the authorities did not advance more information. We asked, in particular, if there are more people to be investigated on suspicion of violation of the State Security Defense, that false information was disclosed by Au and with which “anti-china” organizations, as well as how the former deputy disturbed the election of the chief executive, given that “it took place within normal”, as the authorities said at the time.
“China's internal affairs”
China's mission in the EU, in turn, expressed “strong discontent and firm opposition” to Brussels' statements. “The application of the law where it exists and the punishment of violations are basic principles of a society governed by law,” said the spokesman, considering that the measures taken are “blameless”: “The government of the Masters, by punishing in accordance with the National Security Acts with hostile forces abroad that in danger of national security, has legal foundation and rational justification, in accordance with international law and international law common ”.
In addition, he stressed that "Macau's affairs are purely internal issues in China" and "the EU has no right to make irresponsible comments." The mission of China thus urged the European part "to scrupulously respect international law and the fundamental rules of international relations, to respect China's sovereignty and the rule of law in Macao, and immediately cease interference with Macao and China's internal affairs."
Also the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of China in the masters repudiated the "illusory comments", classifying them as a "gross interference in Macao affairs and in the internal affairs of China." "We urge the EU immediately to make remarks and unfounded accusations about Macao's affairs and stop immediately to interfere with Macao's affairs and China's internal affairs!"
In the same note, he says he supports "firmly the government government in the performance of his duties in accordance with the law", as well as the police "in taking law enforcement measures against the anti-china rebels against Macau, in accordance with the law."
The Commissioner even argues that "since the return of Macau to the country, the" one country, two systems "system has been continually improved and national sovereignty, safety and the interests of development have been effectively safeguarded." "The democratic political system has been perfected and the residents of Macao enjoy a wider range of rights and freedoms than in any other moment in history," he adds.
In this sense, “the maintenance of national security is the prior condition and the most important and fundamental basis for the survival and development of the State”, so “the government of the MSAR, in accordance with the National Security Act, punishes the acts of collusion with hostile forces outside the territory that endanger national security, which is in accordance with international law and common international practice, and is justified by the reasonable, unquestionable and unquestionable law!
Also the Government of Misrees repudiated “vehemently” the EU's statements, opposing “firmly”. In a statement, the Executive points out that "in the investigation process, MSAR police and judicial authorities have always dealt with the case scrupulously under the law" and adds that "the defendant's procedural law is effectively guaranteed under the law."
It also states that "the fundamental rights of MSAR residents, including the right of suffrage and freedom of expression, are fully safeguarded." By the way, “since the return to the homeland, the mashes has reached worldwide notable successes in safeguarding human rights, and no one can overlook them,” he says.
The executive later states that the application of the law on the State Security by the MSAR “is strictly an internal subject of China and its special administrative region”, so “any foreign or abroad bodies, including the European Union, have no right to interference”.
"Mand will continue, as always, to comply with the duties of state security defense under the law, in favor of lasting and stable successful application of the" one country, two systems, "he adds.
Au Kam San in Preventive Prison
Au Kam San will wait for the trial in pre -trial detention. According to the Public Prosecution Service (MP), the coercion measure was applied by the criminal court judgment "for concluding the existence of strong evidence of the crime of establishing bonds with organizations, associations or individuals outside the sinhel to practice acts against state security." The MP also underlines that "it will actually fulfill its legally established functions and strictly perform the tasks defined by the law on the defense of state security." Finally, it appeals to citizens to “do not practice any acts against state security”, as it adds, “the responsibility and duty of the defense of national security must be assumed by each people in China, including residents of Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casa de Portugal receives jazz concert to 23rd Fringe Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casa-de-portugal-recebe-concerto-de-jazz-para-23o-festival-fringe/</link><description>The Fringe Festival will return in September, with a program of activities and shows distributed throughout the city. Casa de Portugal will host the performance “Jazzés &amp; The Blackbird”, in which a trio of musicians will sing classic jazz themes, with an artistic installation by Elisa Vilaça






























Between September 5 and 28, the Cultural Institute (IC) will organize the “23rd Fringe Festival of the city of Macau”, which will take place in a total of 28 locations. According to a press release, the porch of the House of Portugal will receive three musicians, for the “Jazzés &amp; The Blackbird”, on 22 and 23, at 13:30 and 15:30.
The trio will sing “jazz classics on a makeshift stage” and “adorned by an artistic installation of giant birds by Elisa Vilaça”.
Under the “Urban Ride” theme, Fringe will feature 18 shows and 13 activities, including workshops, exhibitions and lectures, among others.
This year's edition will present the series “Crème de La Fringe”, with the subthemes “Tomato” and “Clowns for the Complicit Festival”. Curated by Erik Kuong, the interactive digital theater show “Tomato” covers four programs, namely “The Monster”, “Daily A Deriva”, “Vela Shine” and “A Hidden Window in Macao”. In turn, “Clowns for the Curner Chan Lai Nei Current Festival” will present the activities “The Kung Food: Vegetarian Martial Art”, “The Menu of Today” and “You or Me?”.
The “Extra Festival” will also have two activities, which aim to “break the boundaries of traditional theater through digital platforms” and “lead the audience to find moments that resonate in the heart”. For this edition, the festival organization also invited the Japanese art group “CO.Scoopp” to present the street show “to survive in the cities!”, A comedy “that combines elements of aerial acrobatics, interaction and juggling”.
Experimental programs include “oscillating deck,” presented by ieong Pui San and Zhang Hui, which resort to augmented reality, so that participants can experience the inner port, “where memories merge with dream visions”. Suzuku Chengi will present “thanks for being here”, an immersive play in which “a temporal and spatial dialogue” will address the theme of maternity. In “Dream Machine, Useless Class,” from PO Art Studio, participants will be “judges” and will experience various types of self-service machines from a shopping center.
Own Theater will tell a story of “search for child innocence” with acrobatics, youth and air dance in “Wendy and Wonderland”. “Congregation” is “a dynamic experience that combines environment, music and technology”, which resulted from the collaboration between British sound artist Ray Lee and “Tempest Projects”. "Through the emission of sounds, the suspended sphere guides participants by paths and alleys that can be familiar or a discovery," says the IC.
Presented by Un Iat Hou, Cai Jiajie and Lin Xiaoran, the show “Chow T. II” is a contemporary performance “in the form of a monologue, staging a dialogue between mother and son who crosses time”. Through music and narrative the “Dirks Theater Art Association” will tell a story of “piglet trafficking”.
In the show “A Meeting in Solitude”, with Chan Si Kei, will be woven “considerations on evocative vignettes of family dinners”, with an old tea hall as a backdrop. The "seven sins" will be fought with a "herb tea", by Jason Fong and the Association for the Development of Herbal Tea Culture. The immersive sound installation “a sea in the old house of orchids”, inspired by “orchids to the old house”, rebuilds “excerpts from the original text through a fusion of narration” on “The physical and emotional journey of protagonist Cheang Hoi”.
The session “Can the immersive performances fail?” It will explore a new relationship between the public and the artists. The “Interactive Medical Tea Workshop” will examine the history of medicinal tea, the principles of traditional Chinese medicine and the creative concepts of the Association for the Development of Herbal Tea Culture. The playful games of the “Family Acrobatics Workshop” will want to strengthen “physical connection between parents and children through acrobatic movements in partnership”.
In turn, the festival's guided tours will be conducted by experienced art critics, in order to demonstrate "the essential skills and the perspectives of art criticism." A group of art critics will participate in “Fringe Chat” for dialogues about the current festival edition. Finally, the “Exchange Fringe” will bring together local artists with festival curators from around the world.
The organization will also hold three sessions of “Creative Workshops for All” on the weekend of August 30 and 31, at the Fai Chi Kei Activities Center. Participants' works in paper collage workshops, glass painting and ceramic mosaic can be displayed at the “Art Exhibition for All”.
Tickets for the festival will be on sale from 10 am on August 10, at the “Enjoy Macao” ticketers, by telephone and online reserve. The “Friends of CCM”, “Friends of the OM”, “Friends of the Chinese Orchestra of Macao”, “Friends of Mam” and people of the Macao Teacher Card will benefit from a 10%discount. In turn, the Student Card, Special Benefit Card for the elderly, or the disability assessment card may enjoy a 50%discount.
Registration for the festival will be open from 10 am on August 11, through the Macao Single Account. The IC informs that the number of vacancies is limited and some activities require the payment of a participation fee. Admitted subscribers will be notified by SMS or electronic mail.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casinos “Fold” projections with new postpandy maximum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casinos-dobram-projeccoes-novo-maximo-pos-pandemia/</link><description>Dealer Or Croupier Shuffles Poker Cards in A Casino on the Background of A Table, Chips. Concept of Poker Game, Game Business. Playing for Money, Big Win, Jackpot, Gambling, A DESIRE TO GET RICH.



Gross Macao game revenues grew 19% in July, in annual terms, exceeding the first time of 22 billion patacas since the start of the pandemic. Reinforcing the recent acceleration trend, the growth recorded last month represents about twice the average projections of analysts and maintains the invoicing of casinos well above government forecasts, which have been low magazines in the table of changes to the budget of the MSAR to 2025
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Macao casinos have established a new record since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic ending July with gross revenues of nearly 22.13 billion patacas, according to data published on the electronics page of the DICJ Inspection and Coordination Directorate. The previous maximum postcovid dated May this year, when revenues reached 21.19 billion, driven by the increase of visitors during the “Golden Week” commemorative Labor Day.
July revenues represent a 5% increase compared to 21.06 billion accounted for the previous month and an increase of 19% compared to 18.60 billion in the same period of 2024. In addition, the comparison with 24.45 billion recorded in July 2019, the pre-pound year, illustrates a recovery of 90.5%, above the levels of resumption verified in June (88.5%) and May) and May levels (81.7%).
With the July accounts closed, the amount accumulated in the first seven months of this year was around 140.90 billion patacas, reflecting an increase of 6.5% for the same period of 2024, when the billing reached 132.35 billion. Between January and July, the total of gross revenues corresponded to 81% of the first seven months of 2019 (173.96 billion).
After having advanced 19% in June in the homologous variation, gross revenues thus consolidated the recent acceleration trend, which some analysts have largely attributed to the impact of several shows held on game operators enterprises. Despite coinciding with the beginning of the third quarter of the year, which is usually the least productive period for casinos, immediately due to the absence of “golden weeks” in the interior of China, the July result was still much higher than general expectations.
According to Steven Pizzella, an analyst at Deutsche Bank, the latest information from consultants and investment houses suggested annual growth between 12% and 16%. The average projection of the “Consensus metrix consensus” platform foreseen a 9.5%increase.
With the monthly average to be encrypted by 20.13 billion Patacas between January and July, casinos are also counteracting the traditionally more conservative forecasts of the Executive, and may end the year with total revenues of 241.54 billion if they maintain this record. However, this bar should also be exceeded, as the seasonality factor may further expand the prospects for the second half.
In the initial budget for 2025, the Government of MSAR predicted gross revenues of the game of about 240 billion this year. However, in the proposal of amendment approved in June, the estimate was reviewed at low to 228 billion Patacas. It is recalled that, in the general calculation of 2024, the casinos raised 226.78 billion, more 23.9% than in 2023 and 77.5% of 2019 level.
For this month, Deutsche Bank foresees an annual rise from 10.5% to $ 2.73 billion (22.10 billion patacas to the current exchange rate). On the other hand, using historical records, notes that between 2013 and 2019, the daily average revenue rose 2.1% between July and August, which could translate this month into an annual increase of 14.5%.
Analyst Steven Pizzella now anticipates revenues of US $ 7.81 billion (63.17 billion patacas) in the third quarter and $ 30.30 billion for the entire year (244.95 billion patacas), which would equivalent to homologous climbs of 12.3% and 6%, respectively. The projection for 2026 advocates an annual increase of 3.5%to $ 31.35 billion (253.45 billion patacas).</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>First local cases of chikungunya fever</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/registados-primeiros-casos-locais-de-febre-chikungunya/</link><description>Two residents, workers of the junction of the new landfills, were diagnosed as the first local cases of chikungunya fever in Macau
 
On the 1st of this month, Health Services (SSM) were notified of the first local chikungunya fever case in Macao, which is related to the workers of the works of the new landfills. This is a 34-year-old resident who lives in Block 8 of Jardim Kong Fok On building on Central Rua da Areia Preta.
The patient is stable, being admitted to the Conde de São Januário hospital center for isolation treatment. On August 1, he began to record rash and continued to feel a sore throat.
According to the travel history, the time to start symptoms and the results of laboratory tests, this case was considered by the SSM as the first place of chikungunya fever, whose source of infection is equal to that of cases diagnosed in area workers notified inside China.
Given this case, the SSM took mosquito elimination measures in the risk areas in the block where the patient lives, on Central Rua da Areia Preta and 1 de Maio Street.
However, Macau registered, on Saturday, the second local case of chikungunya fever, diagnosed in a 34-year resident, also related to Zona A shipyard workers. Its symptoms include eruption and fever.
According to the SSM, the patient visited Japan from July 13 to 21, having not been bitten by mosquitoes on this trip. And between July 22 and 29, except on the afternoon of the 26th and the 27th, it has always been to work in a shipyard in zone A. This case also shares origin of infection with cases notified by the Chinese continent.
The SSM adopted mosquito elimination measures in the risk areas in the building where the patient lives, on Central Street and Rua dos Hols. At the same time, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) carried out chemical elimination work on municipal facilities in this area, such as parks. In addition, the inspection of mosquito proliferation sources in the respective zone will be reinforced.
On the other hand, in addition to requiring the shipyards of works that make a full elimination of mosquitoes at least twice a week and order the suspension of the works ongoing in the shipyards concerned, public works and soil services and urban construction services performed on Saturday afternoon chemical elimination of mosquitoes on all zone A shipyards.
In addition, the SSM yesterday launched the joint action of prevention and control of dengue fever and chikungunya fever. However, SSM, AMIs and non -resident and indonesian non -resident workers associations triggered disclosure activities for prevention in the area of the three lamps, having contacted about 720 people.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National games with “high priority”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogos-nacionais-prioridade-elevada/</link><description>The chief executive considers that national games will be "an important stage for the development of the great bay." During the ceremony that marked the decreasing count of 100 days to the beginning of the 15th edition of the National Games, Sam Hou Fai said the event will demonstrate national competitiveness
 
Sam Hou Fai stated that the 15th edition of the National Games, in which the mashes participates for the first time as a co-organizer, will constitute “an important stage for the integrated development of the Great Bay”, injecting “a strong boost in building a 'dynamic macao'”. The chief executive also asserted that the government attributes “high priority” to this year's edition during a speech at the opening ceremony of the “march for the decreasing count of the 100 days”, which took place in the ruins of São Paulo.
The MSAR leader also said that national games are "a crucial platform for demonstrating the global competitiveness of the nation and fostering exchange and sports cooperation at national level." The Macao government also hopes that the event can “promote sports at the population level, organize more diverse sports activities, with a view to raising the physical and mental health of residents,” according to a statement from the Social Communication Office.
Macau will host competitions from the National Table Tennis, Three Basketball, Five Basketball, Five Basketball, Volleyball (Female Adults) and Karaté, as well as the two Badminton tests of the Special Olympics for Disabled.
The Macao Organizing Committee is close to completing preparations in the areas of facilities and the organization of competitions, service and transport and, according to the government, all sectors of society have participated, “uniting efforts to ensure the successful and successful accomplishment of activities”. “Hand in hand, we will continue to move forward, we will hold a splendid sports event to all the people of the country, we will publicize the spirit‘ together in the great bay, together in the national games, ”continued Sam Hou Fai.
The chief executive also expressed “sincere compliments to all individualities that contributed his tireless effort to perform all preparation work, and has profoundly thanked residents and social sectors for the constant support”, can be read.
The commemorative activity ripped into São Paulo Ruins Square, one of the places of the Macao World Heritage, in the presence of citizens and tourists. At the site, participants together formed the number “100”, symbolizing the number of remaining days for the national games. The march passed the Street of Palha, through the Church of São Domingos and ended in Senate Largo. Upon arrival, the mascots of Xiyangyang and Lerongrong received the guests “enthusiastically”, with the performances provided “a lively and cheerful atmosphere”.
According to the statement, "the event of the night was filled with shows, with tiger and dragon dance, karate, basketball exhibitions with children, basketball demonstration and table tennis, as well as musical performances." "On site, there was also the opportunity for sports experiences and game tents."
In addition to representatives of different social and volunteer sectors, the occasion brought together the secretary for social affairs and culture, LAM, the director of the central government connection on MSAR, Zheng Xincong, the secretary general of the 15th edition of the National Games, Wang XI, and the Commissioner of the Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China, Liu Xianfa, among others.
On Saturday night, Sam Hou Fai was also at a ceremony held in Shenzhen, in the scope of the decreasing count of 100 days for the national games.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief praises “great achievements” of the popular liberation army</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-enaltece-grandes-conquistas-exercito-de-libertacao-popular/</link><description>The chief executive praised the “great achievements” of the Liberation Army of the Chinese people on the occasion of his 98 years. As for Macau, he highlighted the existence of a “heroic” garrison. Sam Hou Fai also pointed out that the principle “a country, two systems” entered “in a new phase”
 
On the 98th anniversary of the establishment of the Chinese people's liberation army, the head of the MSAR Executive, Sam Hou Fai, provided him with his “highest tribute”, adding that he has “guided by noble ideals and firm convictions, has accompanied the evolution of times with commitment and innovative spirit, honoring the glorious tradition with the conduct of excellence”. Sam Hou Fai also signaled the "great historical achievements" he made.
For the leader of the MSAR, the popular liberation army "continues to create new conjunctures of the modernization of national defense and the Armed Forces, heading towards the goal defined for the centenary" of its creation.
The chief executive also stressed that "major changes, unpublished in the last 100 years, are accelerating the evolution of the world, and the world has entered a new period of turbulence and change." "Macao discusses the drastic and complex mutations that occur in the internal and external conjuncture and the practice of 'a country, two systems' has also entered a new phase," he said.
In this sense, Sam Hou Fai assured that "the Government of MSar will continue, as always, to maintain the close connection and sincere cooperation with the garrison in Macao, to unite and lead the macao compatriots to value even more, and to safeguard with commitment, stability and social harmony, nothing easy to achieve."
"We will persist on the right track and bet on innovation, we will work with an entrepreneurial spirit and move on with common purposes, to continue to write new chapters of high quality development of the cause" a country, two systems ". With firmness and notion of responsibility and pragmatically, we will continue to fight for the materialization of building a large country and the grand national revitalization," he said.
As for the garrison in Macao, he considered that "he is a heroic garrison of the liberation army of the Chinese people." "Since its parking lot in Macao, it has always been persisted in defending sovereignty, security and interests of the country's development, comprehensive and accurate implementation of the 'country, two systems' and 'Macau ruled by their people' principles, and in the scrupulous observance of the basic law, the law of troop parking lot and other legislation,” said Sam Hou Hou Hou Hou Fai.
"Fullly, he has fulfilled his defense attributions and supported the Government of the Government in the Government Action," he continued. Sam Hou Fai also pointed out that the garrison has had interaction with the Macao society in the various aspects, as well as “deepened the transmission of patriotic value to young people from Macao”.
"It gives us confidence and support for the successful application of the principle" a country, two systems "with characteristics of Macao, which greeted him the extensive compliment and sincere respect of Macao's compatriots and social sectors," added the chief executive, taking the opportunity to thank the officers and soldiers.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched this year 3rd phase of capture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancada-este-ano-3a-fase-de-captacao-de-quadros/</link><description>This year will be launched the third edition of the qualified frame capture program. In addition, two working groups are being created in order to “capture, use well and retain pictures”
 
This year will be launched the third edition of the Qualified Books Capture Program, “with the nuclear objective of attracting staff capable of leading, promoting and supporting the development of key industries,” said the chief executive, who is also chairman of the Qualified Table Development Commission (CDQQ). During this year's first ordinary plenary meeting, Sam Hou Fai said that preparatory work to create an interdepartal cooperation mechanism and two interdepartal working groups will also be initiated, in order to “capture, use well and retain pictures”.
On the other hand, the MSAR leader said the commission will “continue to play an active role, present professional opinions and contribute to wisdom and strength to a high quality development of Macao”.
The secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, Vice President of CDQQ, said that the Government of MSAR “continues to improve qualified frames capture policies to strengthen attractiveness and competitiveness”.
In addition, “with a view to the transformation of Macao in a place of aggregation of international qualified staff, it will further reinforce the exchange with countries and neighboring regions in the area of qualified tables”.
In this sense, LAM announced that in October, the Executive of the MSar will hold, in Macao, for the first time, the “Conference on High Quality Development of the Great Guangdong-Hong Kong Kong-Macau Bay”, to publicize and promote qualified frames capture.
According to Kong Chi Meng, CDQQ secretary general, during the first two phases of the program, 150 qualified frames were imported. The same responsible also explained, in relation to the two groups that will be created, that they aim to provide support services to the work ranging from the search for qualified pictures to the fixation in Macao.
The idea is also to create a mechanism for interconnecting information between these two groups, to be aware of the situation of the coming of these frames to Macau, in order to support their needs.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco will “recover” Hotel Countdown</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-vai-recuperar-hotel-countdown/</link><description>Encounted since 2021, the former Hard Rock Countdown Hotel will be the target of a “complete renewal” to reopen within a year with a new brand and 150 luxury suites, thus reinforcing the resort City of Dreams offer in the luxury segment. At the same time, Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment is remodeling several play areas to boost recipes
 
The Countdown Hotel, which has been closed for four years in Cotai, will be the target of a large transformation, revealed Lawrence Ho, president and executive director of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, during a teleconference with analysts about the company's second quarter of 2025. 2026. The hotel will have a new brand, with approximately 150 high -luxury suites, ”he explained, adding that the average size of the rooms will be more than a thousand square feet (about 93 square meters).
Lawrence Ho expressed the conviction that the concept of this remodeling “will provide a unique experience to Macau and will contribute to the portfolio of luxury high -end hotels” at City of Dreams.
In April 2017, Melco announced that the then Hard Rock Hotel would operate with the Countdown brand between July of this year and March 31, 2018, and after this period would adopt a new designation. "The hotel will feature a decreasing count scheduled to open a new phase of city of Dreams," he said at the time, referring to the opening of Morpheus.
In 2021, the 330 -room Countdown ended for works, however, the plan to rename the hotel tower as Libertine did not materialize, largely due to the impact of the pandemic.
Countdown's new conversion project is part of a “series of additional initiatives in Macau to boost traffic and recipes,” said Lawrence Ho. According to the last year and a half, the company has promoted "improvements" in the play areas of all its casinos in Macao to extend the offer of services and products and "raise the" premium "customers of the game's pasta premium.
In this domain, City of Dreams now has a new space for high limit slot machines and turned an old VIP area into a premium players with three private rooms and unlinmed game attractions, including golf and racing simulators, polytons, darts and “pinball” machines. On the other hand, Evan Winkler, president and executive director of Melco International Development, indicated that Studio City plans to open a medical center run by Hong Kong's IRAD group.
Lawrence Ho also highlighted the impact of relaunch in May of the show resident House of Dancing Water at City of Dreams. "We received great feedback, with an average occupation of 98% since opening," he said, emphasizing that the show had a contribution to EBITDA (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) during the second quarter.
Between April and June, Melco's Global Ebitda, which operates resorts with casinos in Macao, Manila and Cyprus, rose to US $ 377.7 million (about 3 billion patacas to the current exchange rate), marking an annual increase of 24.2%. Net profits dropped 19.6% to $ 17.2 million in the second quarter, in annual terms, however, it grew by 36% to 49.7 million in the first half.
Operating revenues reached $ 1.33 billion in the second quarter and 2.56 billion in the semester, reflecting annual growth of 14.5% and 12.7%, respectively.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Environment without barriers with studies ready in 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ambiente-sem-barreiras-estudos-prontos-em-2026/</link><description>IAS intends to conclude next year the preliminary plans of legislation for the creation of conditions without barriers, including studies on the subject
 
Together with the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), Fire Department, Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU), Directorate of Public Works Services, among other Public Services, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) is developing preliminary plans of legislation for the creation of accessibility conditions, providing relevant work in 2026.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Nick Law, IAS has ensured that the government will collect opinions from stakeholders, the Commission for rehabilitation matters, and entities that provide rehabilitation services and people with disabilities and rehabilitation. Legislative work on the free environment of barriers will be included in the new “planning of MSAR rehabilitation services for the next decony”.
The body also pointed out that, in recent years, when the works of optimization of public roads, AMI has evaluated the environmental conditions of the surrounding constructions, in order to improve the design without architectural barriers, provided that conditions allow it, including optimization and remodeling of directional tactile floors.
At the same time, he recalled that AMI has studied the "optimization of travel without barriers in Macao". However,, this study stressed only the foundation for internal work, in order to promote, together, the construction of a barrier -free society.
Regarding private works, it reiterated that DSSCU requires the new buildings under construction to comply with legal provisions regarding the creation of barriers free facilities.
 
Support for accessibility with permanent coordinators
On the other hand, taking into account the “positive results” of the “Project-Pilot Project to make access coordinator available”, it has been a permanent measure since 1 August. Currently, Macao has accessibility support coordinators in 56 locations, under 27 public services.
According to IAS, between September and December this year, the project will be extended to cover 65 places, from 33 public services, with the aim of ensuring better service and support for people with disabilities and special needs, fostering their autonomy and independence in the use of public services. In this sense, the project will be joined by the project, monetary authority, consumer council, correctional services, security forces services and maritime and water services services.
The government organized coordinators' training actions in July and this month, intended for more than 30 public services.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Forum reinforces “principle of cooperation” with Bissau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/forum-reforca-principio-de-cooperacao-bissau/</link><description>The Permanent Secretariat of the Macao Forum recently moved to Guinea-Bissau for a meeting with the Minister of Economy of the African country, where they addressed future cooperation
 
Last week, Ji Xianzheng, Secretary-General of the Macao Forum Permanent Secretariat, led a delegation to Guinea-Bissau, for a meeting with the Minister of Economy, Plan and Regional Integration of the country, Soares Sambú. The Guinean minister “praised the role and influence of the Macao Forum platform, reiterating the availability of Guinea-Bissau in his proactive participation in the forum affairs,” according to a statement from the Permanent Secretariat of the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries.
Ji Xianzheng, in turn, said that the countries participating in the Macao Forum "have remained faithful to the initial aspiration for common development and kept inabalable commitments to the principle of shared gain cooperation." The secretary general also highlighted progress in implementing the action plan for economic and commercial cooperation and stressed the secretariat's commitment to “maintain close communication to the related departments of the Guinea-Bissau government for joint advancement of the effective implementation of the plan”.
Minister Soares Sambú also expressed the desire to “take advantage of the important instruments of financing”, such as the Cooperation and Development Fund between China and Portuguese -speaking countries. He also said that the country will “join efforts” with the countries participating in the Forum for a “joint implementation” of the action plan for economic and commercial cooperation.
Guinea-Bissau aims to “continue to deepen cooperation in various sectors”, especially “agriculture, fisheries, infrastructure construction and small and medium-sized businesses, as well as explore opportunities for cooperation in emerging domains, including digital economy”, can read.
China's ambassador to Guinea-Bissau, Yang Renhuo, said that in the first half of this year, several Chinese businessmen visited the African country "to explore the market and investment opportunities." China has actively provided support to Guinea-Bissau, "promoting initiatives within the Macao Forum" and "fostering sustainable economic development." Yang also recalled President Umaro Sissoco Embaló's “successful” visit to China last year to establish “a strategic partnership between the two countries”.
In the same week, Ji Xhianzheng headed a delegation to Equatorial Guinea, as part of the “Meeting of Entrepreneurs for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”, which took place in Malabo. The same responsible chaired a “exchange session session with government departments related to Macao Forum Affairs”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong and Macau Biennial Patent in Canton Museum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bienal-de-hong-kong-macau-patente-em-museu-de-cantao/</link><description>After having been in Beijing, the “Hong Kong and Macau Visual Arts Biennial” is now evident to the public museum of the Canton Painting Academy, until the 15th. The Macao section has works by 10 artists, including Ricardo Filipe dos Santos Meireles

The “Hong Kong and Macao Visual Arts Biennial” is evident at the Canton Painting Academy Museum of Art until August 15. With the theme “Integration and Dialogue”, this edition of the Biennial addresses the visual arts, the intangible cultural heritage and design, technological innovation and public design, among other subthemes.
The Macau Expository Section has as its theme “Not Macau, but it is called Macau”, presenting works by 10 local artists in various supports, including oil and acrylic on canvas, photography, mixed technique, video, dynamic digital images, installation and spaces with immersive experiences, indicates the Cultural Institute (IC) in a statement. They are works by Cai Guojie, Ieong Wan Si, IM Fong, Lam IM Peng, Lo Hio Ieng, Lou Kam Ieng, Ng Sang Kei, Ricardo Filipe dos Santos Meireles, Sit Ka Kit and Xie Yun.
The 30 works (sets) of contemporary art on display "reveal the ties and emotional links of artists with" Macau " - distant but intimate, strange but indispensable."
The first three stages of this edition took place, with remarkable success in Hangzhou (October 2024), Nanjing (March 2025) and Beijing (June 2025), attracting more than 140,000 visitors. In Beijing, the show was evident at the National Center for Performative Arts, a national artistic space, having attracted almost 80,000 visitors, "establishing a new record of visitors to a single stage of the tour."
“Beijing's very successful exhibition not only provided high quality artistic experiences to the capital's residents, but also deepened cultural exchange and interaction between Beijing, Hong Kong and Macau”, read in the IC note. It is now in Canton, "thus enriching the artistic environment of Lingnan (Guangdong) with the cultural auras and the distinct artistic languages of Hong Kong and Macao."
Since its inception in 2008, the “Hong Kong and Macao Visual Arts Biennial” has become an “important cultural bridge” between Hong Kong, Macau and the interior of China, as well as an emblematic event for artistic exchange, points out the body led by Leong Wai Man.
Organized by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Popular Republic of China, the Directorate of Raehk Culture, Sport and Tourism Services and the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture of MSAR, the show is coordinated by the Hong Kong, Macao and Taiwan Office of the China Ministry of Culture and Tourism, the Hong Kong Leisure and Cultural Services, the IC and the China Group of the Arts and Entertainment Lda.
The opening ceremony took place on the night of July 25, with the presence of the Substitute Vice President of the IC, I am Kin Meng, and the artists of Macau Lou Kam Ieng, NG Seng Kei, Sit Kat Kit, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD promotes MSAR TOURISM IN APEC MEETING</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-promove-turismo-da-raem-em-encontro-da-apec/</link><description>The Directorate of Tourism Services represented Macao, at the last meeting of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation Working Group. The body took advantage of the event to “further increase Macau's participation and influence on international tourism organizations”
 
The South Korean city of Inheon welcomed the 65th Meeting of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation Working Group (APEC), in which the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) represented the masters. STD shared Macao promotion work and exchanged opinions with representatives of participating economies “on tourist industry development trends, to further increase Macau's participation and influence on international tourism organizations”, according to a statement.
MSAR representatives took advantage of this international platform “to be aware of the latest news from APEC Tourism Working Group, exchange with member economies representatives and acquire valuable experiences”. For STD, “participation allowed Macau's involvement in international tourism organizations, reinforce international contacts and contribute to the sustainable development of Macao's tourist industry”.
Jennifer Si Tou, subdirector of STD, headed the delegation that moved to South Korea and presented, on the last day, "the current situation of the development of the Macao tourist industry." He also shared the number of visitors from APEC member countries in the first half of 2025.
As part of the theme “Tourism +’ to call, innovate and prosper ”, STD also presented practical cases of Macao, in the areas of“ Tourism + Gastronomy ”,“ Tourism + Culture and Creativity ”and public-private collaboration,“ with a view to promoting the construction of Macau as a world tourism and leisure center through intersectory integration ”.
Participants also discussed the four priority areas of APEC Strategic Tourism Plan, namely “digital transformation”, “human capital development”, “facilitation and competitiveness of tourism” and “implementation of sustainable tourism and economic growth”.
According to the tour authorities of the MSAR, there was also a debate session and a thematic discussion, focused on the themes “connection, innovation and prosperity”. The program also included the discussion of work plans, cooperation between different areas, familiarization visits, a launch ceremony and a closing session, among other activities.
APEC's Tourism Working Group was created in 1991, with the aim of gathering the tourism of member countries to share information and exchange opinions, develop a platform role and promote the cooperation and development of tourism and commerce. Since 2001, MSar has participated in the event. The meeting of the APEC Tourism Group is held twice a year, and the STD participates regularly, representing Macau as “invited member economy”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Number of visitors exceeded 22 million between January and July</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/numero-de-visitantes-superou-22-milhoes-entre-janeiro-julho/</link><description>Provisional official data indicate that in July Macau received 3.45 million visitors, meaning a daily average of more than 110,000. Thus, the number of visitors in the first seven months of this year exceeded 22 million, representing an annual rise of about 14%, Cheng Wai Tong, Substitute Director of Tourism Services (STD), said. He said, on the other hand, the hotel occupancy rate exceeded 90% last month. For the person responsible, the results in terms of the volume of visitors are “very good”, meeting the expectations of the beginning of the year. Regarding summer holidays, he believes that the results of the tourism sector will be generally satisfactory. In addition, Cheng Wai Tong said that visitors' expenses grew in the 2nd quarter of this year in quarterly and annual terms. On the other hand, the STD substitute director has been convinced that the 15th edition of the National Games will attract many sports enthusiasts to Macau watch the competitions, while the offer of local hotels in November will be able to meet the search. In addition, it mentioned that the government will move in September and October, Wuhan, Portugal, Spain and Southeast Asia, with the purpose of holding tourist dissemination actions, being the National Games one of the outbreaks of the disclosure. In this context, it also revealed that the Government of MSar will communicate with the authorities of Hong Kong and Guangdong, to launch tourist packages that include tickets from the national games.</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Switch 2 fires Nintendo's quarterly recipes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/switch-2-dispara-receitas-trimestrais-da-nintendo/</link><description>Nintendo has announced that its quarterly recipes more than doubled over the previous year thanks to Switch 2, the fastest sold video game console in the world after being released in June.
The high demand of this new Japanese brand device that created “Super Mario” revived the enthusiasm of the fans, who sold out the stocks and made the stores open until midnight.
Like the original popular switch, the second model is a hybrid console that can be portable or attached to a television, with a larger screen and greater processing potential than its predecessor.
The console hit all records of the sector by selling 3.5 million units in the first four days. And in the first month, the number increased to 5.8 million, Nintendo announced.
"Net sales increased significantly in the first quarter, mainly due to the launch of Nintendo Switch 2," the company said by announcing an inter-annual increase in revenues from April to June, until reaching 572 billion yen (over 31 billion patacas to the current exchange rate). The quarter's net profit also grew 19% over the previous year.
However, maintaining successful games for the new console will be a challenge for Nintendo, warned Serkan Toto, a video game industry consultant, in statements to the AFP agency.
"There are new games of the Pokémon, Metroid and Kirby franchises that will go for sale later this year, but some fans have started asking even more titles," he said.
However, “the launch of Switch 2 exceeded the expectations of many people” and it will be difficult for another console to equal their good start, the analyst added. "Nintendo should enjoy this impulse during the holidays and by 2026," he played.
Despite these good numbers, Nintendo has not changed its financial predictions and modest console sales goals for all the year that will end in March 2026, with a forecast of 15 million units. Bloomberg Intelligence's Nathan Naidu, said it is "likely" that the company will increase this amount, as it has sold 40% of this goal.
The launch of Switch 2 positions the company “for a big return after four consecutive years of poor boost in its sales, except if US tariffs force Nintendo to climb hardware prices,” the analyst wrote.
Although Nintendo is diversifying with successful movies and thematic parks, consoles remain the core of their business.
The original switch fired in popularity during pandemic with games like “Animal Crossing” during long confinement around the world. 153 million units have been sold since its launch in 2017.
Switch 2, which features new features, such as controls that can also be used as a computer rat, costs $ 449.99 in the US, more expensive than the original release price of $ 299.99.
"Once Nintendo's unconditional fans' market is running out, the company will have to move on to the following level by convincing players to jump to Switch 2," said Toto.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>