<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Ecological vehicles only represent 6% of the management fleet</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/veiculos-ecologicos-so-representam-6-da-frota-da-administracao/</link><description>The Fleet of the Government of MSAR is made up of more than 4,300 vehicles, but only a very small part, 6% of the total, are “friends of the environment”. The guidelines dictate that public entities choose, “whenever possible”, vehicles moved exclusively the electricity when the acquisition or replacement of motor vehicles. However, neither the direction of finance services nor the direction of environmental protection services have data on how many are replaced, but are not exchanged for “green vehicles”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The "green transformation of land transport" is one of the government's objectives, which aims that the area of ​​vehicles can "reach almost zero emissions before 2050". To this end, it has launched an electric vehicle promotion plan, hoping that by 2035 the goal of 100% of vehicles (light, motorcycles and mopeds) can be reached new registered zero emissions. The Fleet of Administration, however, still only includes a small part of “Friends of the Environment” vehicles.
According to the inventory and registration of the Heritage Heritage for the vehicles, by the end of 2024, "the Government of MSAR has a total of 2,774 cars and 1,566 motorcycles/cyclomotors," said the direction of Finance Services (DSF) in response to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. In total there are 4,340 vehicles, but only 6% are “green vehicles”. It refers to DSF that of the total, "60 are hybrid cars, 138 electric cars and 53 motorcycles/electric mopeds."
The body indicates that “in order to promote the greatest use of vehicles moved exclusively to electricity”, issued, in 2022, “through offices, internal guidelines to public entities, urging them to choose, whenever possible, moved vehicles exclusively the electricity when the acquisition or replacement of motor vehicles ”.
However, when asked about how many cars or bikes were exchanged for new vehicles in 2023 and 2024 and of these, how many were not replaced by “vehicles moved exclusively to electricity,” DSF said it did not have this data. “We regret that we do not have the requested information,” read it.
The Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) referred all questions to other organisms, indicating only that, in 2022, the executive launched, in two phases, the financial support plans for the slaughter of obsolete motorcycles and the replacement by electric vehicles New as well as the Support Plan for the slaughter of old motorcycles.
According to data sent to this newspaper, until December 31 last year, through the foreground, 3,969 obsolete motorcycles registered or recorded on or before December 31, 2013 were replaced by new electrical motorcycles. Already under the other plane, 952 old vehicles moved to diesel enrolled or registered on or before December 31, 2013, said DSPA.
In early January, the Chinese government released a list of environmental objectives, which includes a rise review of the previous goal for electric vehicles, which was 20% to 2025. In the second half of last year, the tramful ones already represented more than Half sales of new vehicles, according to data from the China Passenger Automobile Association.
However, recently, environmentalist Joe Chan Chon Meng told Lusa that it is “absolutely impossible” Macau to follow the goal for electric vehicles in mainland China, of 45% of new sales by 2027.
In the MSAR, 31.4% of the new vehicles recorded in 2024 were electric, according to official data. But the president of “Macau Green Student Union” stressed that fossil -powered vehicles “continue to represent a great proportion” of the territory park. At the end of December, Macau had a total of 253,182 vehicles, of which 12,302 (4.8%) were existing electrical, according to the direction of services for traffic affairs.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Age of the Airport includes expansion projects and improvement of infrastructure</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-era-aeroporto-inclui-projectos-de-expansao-melhoria-das-infra-estruturas/</link><description>Macao International Airport celebrates this year the 30th anniversary of the beginning of operations and 2025 may bring an 8.5 million passenger volume, in a forecast that would mean an increase of 11.8% compared to 2024. For this year, the year Betting of the company that manages the airport, CAM, involves implementing expansion projects and improvement of infrastructure, including renewal of security channels and starting areas, planned to start during this first quarter. Regarding long -haul flights, specifically to Europe, the president of the Cam executive committee rules out this possibility, pointing to the continuity of traffic travel from Asian cities
 
Victor Rebelo
 
There are many projects that Macao International Airport Society (CAM) plans to implement in 2025, the year in which the 30th anniversary is celebrated since the aircraft landing and dropping place began its operations in December 1995.
Once 30 years, Macao International Airport (AIM) enters a new era of expansion and modernization of infrastructure, betting on implementing various improvement projects. The objective, according to their guardians, is to provide “safety, efficiency and effectiveness” in the search for growth in a limited space, simultaneously optimizing operational efficiency to raise passenger service experience.
CAM states that “taking into account the surrounding environment and the dynamics of the sector”, it is expected that the passenger volume in 2025 could reach 8.5 million, which, to confirm, will mean an increase of 11, 8% compared to the 7.6 million recorded in the previous year in almost 60,000 aircraft movements.
It is also foreseen in flights to about 65,000, which will translate into an increase of 10%. Both passenger and aircraft volume registered an annual increase of over 40%by 2024.
In the executive aviation segment, there were 957 flights in 2024, serving more than 5,080 passengers, with an increase of 3.6%. The expectation for 2025 is also positive in this area, and it is estimated that there are more than 1,100 passengers, which will represent a 15%increase.
In addition, the load movement also had a positive performance, moving more than 108,000 tons, which reflects an annual growth of 70%. For 2025 113 thousand tons are foreseen.
In terms of revenues, Cam raised about 1.475 billion patacas by 2024, an increase of 5.1% over the previous year, which is estimated to have returned to 81% of the 2019 pre-standard year.
In the general calculation of AIM operations, the 2024 balance is considered quite positive, and percentage increase values ​​have been reached in all major segments, which was highlighted by their officials.
For Mao Iao Hang, president of CAM's Administrative Board, the airport is “actively aligning the development of its infrastructures with the rapid growth of the local tourism industry”. The goal, he says, is to "reinforce safety, improve efficiency and optimize services, thus providing passengers with a safer, comfortable and more comfortable travel experience."
 
No plans for long -haul flights
Regarding the possibility of long -running flights, specifically to Europe, always long -longed and requested by passengers, CAM executive committee chairman Simon Chan Weng Hong rules out this hypothesis for now.
“In fact we have no plans for this to happen in the near future,” he revealed during the annual spring lunch with the media, adding that the bet will continue to go through the “hub-to-hub” service, “instead direct flight ”. The intention is also to reduce the time in transit, expecting "to be between two and five hours, which seems to be convenient."
Simon Chan mentioned that, using aircraft departing from the airport to make flights to Beijing, Taiwan, Colombo, Singapore and Bangkok, as transitional points, “We can sell the entire trip to Europe, with the possibility of passengers sending their Baggage from Macao and directly to the final destination ”, which can be for countries from various continents, such as Europe and America (United States and Canada).
Regarding development plans for this year, some represent the continuity of projects already started in the late 2024, as is the case with the expansion and recovery of the airport, as well as the construction of the upstream hengqin upstream terminal, which is expected to start in the first quarter and will be completed until 2026.
In addition, CAM states that it is “systematically implementing infrastructure updating initiatives”.
These initiatives include three large subprojects, namely the rehabilitation of the track floor, the improvement of safety channels and departure areas, and the renewal of the traffic corridor and arrival channel, “all in order to continually improve the service capacity of the Regional Aviation Center, ”said the official of CAM.
The rehabilitation of the ground floor floor is expected to start in the fourth quarter of this year, using a night construction. The works will be segmented to ensure the normal operation of operations.
 
Intelligent safety equipment
Regarding the renewal of safety in the starting channels and arrival areas, it is expected to begin during the first three months of 2025, with improvements expected in half of the year and completion in the third quarter. Intelligent safety equipment will be included and “One ID” to increase safety processing capacity by 80% and improve passenger treatment capacity.
In addition, he stressed the responsible, the engineering and installation work of low voltage equipment in the Taipa Ferry Terminal Heliport began in early December last year, with a six -month construction calendar that “ensures alignment with the Government's objective to officially inaugurate the heliport in the second half of 2025 ”.
Simon Chan stressed that, in the future, the Taipa Maritime Terminal and Heliport, as well as Macao International Airport, "will have perfect connectivity, facilitating coordinated maritime and air transport." This will allow you to “increase the convenience of traveling to passengers in the surrounding areas, thus providing transportation for transportation for the development of the large bay area”.
At the end of lunch and direct contact with journalists, the president of the Cam executive committee stated that, about the accident that occurred in South Korea, where a plane collided with a wall of the airport, “there are certainly concerns in this regard, because our rail is in the middle of the sea. ”
Noting that Macao Airport has a barrier to protect the rail from extreme weather conditions, Simon Chan Weng Hong points out that "all safety tools and a rescue area governed by international standards." Even so, he concludes, "we will in the future extend the rail a little on both sides, so that the security distance is a little longer than the one that currently exists."</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BNU's profit exceeded 580 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-bnu-voltou-superar-580-milhoes/</link><description>The BNU ended the financial year 2024 with net profits of 585.1 million patacas, almost equaling the result of the previous year, announced the institution, which exceeded the overall performance of the bank sector
 
Net profit after taxes from the National Bank Overseas (BNU) cifed at 585.1 million patacas last year, reflecting a decrease of only 0.4% compared to the 587.3 million accounted for in 2023, revealed unused data released yesterday by the institution.
BNU results thus surpassed the overall performance of the sector, given that, as a whole, the operational profits of local banks fell 21.3% to 4.01 billion patacas, marking the fourth consecutive homologous break and the value Lowest since 2010, according to data recently released by the monetary authority.
In the financial year of 2024, BNU's net interest income decreased 4.2% to 43.0 million patacas, in annual terms, due to “changes in the composition of deposits and the context of current interest rates”, clarified the bank in a statement. This break was partially offset by an increase of 11.3%to 9.2 million patacas in liquid commissions and rates, “underlining the recovery of economic activity”.
On the other hand, the results of financial operations reached 13.4 million patacas, translating a growth of 30.7% that the bank mainly attributes “to the absence of losses with the sale of obligations recorded in 2023”.
Provisions for financial credits and investments totaled 35.4 million patacas in 2024, illustrating a significant annual decrease of 23.4 million or 39.8%. Ensuring that the quality of its assets remains “robust”, BNU stresses that it continues to “prioritize prudent risk management and maintain proper provisional coverage for potential macroeconomic uncertainties”.
BNU's total capital ratio grew to 24.4% in 2024 (1.9 more percentage points than in 2023), with “robust liquidity reserves that confirm the solidity of the bank balance”. These indicators, according to Vinca, derive from "disciplined financial management, solid risk mitigation practices and the ability to navigate complex economic conditions, maintaining support to customers and stakeholders."
According to the same data, operating expenses retreated 0.2% compared to 2023, “demonstrating the effectiveness of cost optimization measures”. “The simplification of operational processes and the strategic review of the service portfolio compensated for high investments in digital transformation initiatives, talent development programs and brand visibility campaigns,” says BNU, reiterating that these investments reinforce the commitment to ““ Improve customer experience, increase operational efficiency and adapt to the acceleration of digitization. ”
At the same time, the bank also continues to integrate ex -ex -(environmental, social and governance) principles in its operations in order to ensure “sustainable growth that benefits communities and environment”.
The BNU also emphasizes “the fundamental role” of its Hengqin branch in support for Macau and Hong Kong investors, including individuals and companies, in a context of deepening the integration of the Great Bay (GBA) and the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macao. “Forming as a strategic platform, the branch facilitates transfrontic economic integration through adapted financial solutions, support for mainland China, Macao and Lusophone countries, and promoting a diversified business ecosystem in GBA,” he emphasizes.
In a general analysis, BNU considers that the financial results of 2024 “highlight their ability to balance short -term challenges with long -term strategic priorities”. With a “disciplined execution of business strategies and investments directed in innovation and sustainability”, the bank believes that “it remains well positioned to reinforce its competitiveness in the market and contribute to regional economic progress”.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended moved in the attribution of the pecuniary reimbursement</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidas-mexidas-na-atribuicao-da-comparticipacao-pecuniaria/</link><description>Economist Henry Law suggested legislation on pecuniary reimbursement and adjustments to the plan, including increasing the amount of checks attributed to smaller and elderly residents. Already Leong in Pong, subdirector of the Kaifong Social Affairs Commission, expects the government to demand from the beneficiaries of the measure a minimum limit regarding the number of days of stay in Macau
 
Henry Lei, an economist and subdirector of the Macao Economic Association, considers that the pecuniary reimbursement plan has already become a financial aid that represents a very significant help for less possessions residents. To increase the stability of the plan, responding to the claims of residents, the matter must be legislated, he defended.
In addition, in a “or mun tin toi” program, Henry Lei stressed that maintaining the form of cash checks can increase the feeling of gain among residents, and suggested that the amount of checks be elevated to raise the upstream of the checks to the minors and the elderly.
As for residents beneficiaries of pecuniary reimbursement who do not live in Macau, Henry Lei pointed out that expenses spent in this plan have a limited effect on the stimulation of consumption in the territory.
Nelson Kot, president of the Macao Social Synthetic Studies Association, also hopes that the government announces, in the next lines of government action, a legislation plan, to clarify the eligibility of the beneficiaries of the monetary reimbursement and a mechanism for adjusting the amount of checks . In addition, the associative leader, who has already applied in two elections for the Legislative Assembly, proposed to the government to change some details of the plan, for example, raising the amount of checks attributed to low income residents and lowering the value of those granted to the granted to citizens with high income.
In turn, Leong in Pong, subdirector of the Social Affairs Commission of the General Union of Residents Associations (“Kaifong”), stressed that in 2024 the government sent pecuniary checks to about 48,000 residents living abroad. In this sense, it suggested that, as in the central pension scheme, the beneficiaries be required a minimum limit for the number of days of stay in Macau, although without removing the possibility of “tolerance clauses”. As for money spared, it considers that it can be used for the launch of consumer cards, among other measures to encourage the economy.
Leong in pong is not the first to defend the end of the attribution of checks to those outside Macao. Later this month, Deputy Ron Lam shared the same opinion, two weeks after Deputy Lo Choi in made the same suggestion.
Regarding the suggestion for the amounts of the checks to be differentiated to certain groups of the population, the representative of the Kaifong understands that the financial difficulties of the elderly should be relieved through policies for the elderly, while caregivers and people with disabilities already enjoy of various benefits and guarantees. In this sense, Leong in Pong has asked the authorities to cautiously consider whether the pecuniary reimbursement, as a measure of economic support, should be “inclined” to certain groups of the population.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau leads main categories of Forbes Travel Guide</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-lidera-principais-categorias-guia-de-viagens-da-forbes/</link><description>Macau reinforced the lead in Forbes magazine travel guide in the three main categories: hotels, restaurants and spas. In the hotel aspect, the number of five -star ventures rose to 24, four more than in London, the second city of the ranking. The Galaxy Macau remains the integrated resort that brings together more hotels with the maximum distinction in a guide where the masters also absorbs almost a third of the best restaurants worldwide

Sérgio Terra
 
For the third consecutive year, Macau occupies the first position of the “ranking” of cities with the most five -star hotels by Forbes magazine. In the 2025 edition of its Travel Guide, the prestigious US publication granted the maximum score to 24 MSA Hotels, two more than in 2024, keeping London in second place, with 20, the same number last year.
Macao hotels had already led in 2015, 2018, 2023 and 2024, in isolation, as well as their first place with Hong Kong, New York and London (2014) and Paris (2016 and 2017).
This year, the domain has been reinforced with two more entries in the hotel elite: Epic Tower, Studio City, and Raffles in the Galaxy Macau. The five -star rating distinguishes 17 more Cotai projects: Banyan Tree, two MGM Cotai units (Emerald Tower and Skylofts), Four Seasons, Grand Suites at Four Seasons, Galaxy Macao, Grand Lisboa Palace, Okura, Karl Lagerfeld, Londoner Court, Londoner Hotel, Morpheus, Nüwa, Paiza Lofts in Parisian, The Ritz-Carlton, Star Tower of Studio City and Wynn Palace.
In the same list there are four hotels on the peninsula (Encore, Grand Lisbon, MGM Macau and Wynn Macau) and one in the Taipa (Altira). In addition, Forbes has again assigned four stars to the Mandarin East, Conrad, Grand Hyatt and St. Regis hotels, and placed three (Parisian, Venetian and JW Marriott) on the “recommended” lot.
Also for the third consecutive year, Galaxy Macau stands out as the resort integrated with the largest number of world elite hotels under the same ceiling: Raffles, Galaxy, Banyan Tree, Ritz-Carlton and Okura. The Mega Resort also celebrated the five stars of two spas (Banyan Tree and Ritz Carlton) and two restaurants (Yamazato and 8 1/2 Otto and Mezzo Bombana).
“We are honored to be recognized by Forbes Travel Guide and eager to continue to raise the level of luxury hospitality worldwide, while further reinforcing Macao status as a 'World Tourism and Leisure Center' Center ' ”Holded Kevin Kelley, director of operations at Galaxy Entertainment, quoted in a group statement.
Described as “the most diverse geographically” in 67 travel guide editions, the 2025 world list encompasses 336 five -star hotels (four less than in 2024), 645 with four stars (plus 45) and 567 “recommended” ( more 64). The Maldives maintain third place among five -star hotels with 15, ahead of Dubai (13), Paris (12), New York and Tokyo (9), Hong Kong and Los Cabos, in Mexico (7) and Alps (6). Las Vegas only has four.
In Asia, the new Singapore Paiza Collection, at the top of Marina Bay Sands and specializing in butler services, also entered the five -star lot to 2025. Forbes further emphasizes that, outside Macao, China “received the largest compliments for two very high towers ”: Rosewood Guangzhou and The Ritz-Carlton in Hong Kong.
Worldwide, Forbes also included 79 restaurants with the five -star rating (one more than in 2024), 131 with four stars (plus 10) and 67 “recommended” (eight more), as well as 124 spas with five star (minus two) and 224 with four (plus 23). It also distinguished 14 ocean cruise ships, including seven with four stars and seven "recommended".
 
Macau has almost a third of the best restaurants
In the restoration sector, Macau also continues to show clear domain, now gathering 31.6% of all five -star restaurants worldwide. In the 2025 guide, this statute is shared by 25 MSAR restaurants, two more than last year.
In this group, the premieres of Aurora (Altira), chef Tam's Seasons (Wynn Palace), Don Alfonso (Palazzo Versace), The Huaiyang Garden (The Londoner Hotel), Table by José Avillez (Karl Lagerfeld), Yamazato Macau (Okura) and Zuicho (Grand Lisboa Palace). These seven thus joined the restaurants 8 1/2 Otto and Mezzo Bombana, Alain Ducasse Morpheus, The Eight, Five Foot Road, Golden Flower Encore, Imperial Court, Jade Dragon, Mizumi No Wynn Palace, Palace Garden, Pearl Dragon, Robuchon Au Dôme, Sushi Mizumi, Sw Steakhouse No Wynn Palace, Tenmasa, Wing Law at Wynn Macau, Ying, Yí and Zi Yat Heen.
With four stars come the Lai Heen restaurants, Rich Life and Saffron.
Among the "Spas", Macao also preserved the lead with 18 evaluated with five stars, two more than in 2024, with the entrances of spaces operated in the Epic Tower and Palazzo Versace hotels. The list also includes Altira's "spas", Banyan Tree, Morpheus, Nüwa, The Ritz-Carlton, Encore, Four Seasons, Grand Lisbon Palace, Grand Lisbon, East Mandarin, Karl Lagerfeld, Wynn Macau, Wynn Palace, Tria ( MGM Cotai and MGM Macau) and Zensa. Already the "spas" Bodhi and Iridium, in St. Regis, kept the four stars.
Forbes ensures that travel guide classifications are “objective, independent and data based”. "Anonymous inspectors are passed on ordinary guests, checking hotels, boarding cruises, participating in spa treatments and having dinner in exquisite restaurants," to test "rigorous norms that emphasize exceptional service," says the American magazine , explaining that the service level weighs 70% in the evaluation of enterprises and the remaining 30% are determined by the quality and conditions of the facilities.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Metro transported 230 thousand during Chinese New Year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/metro-transportou-230-mil-durante-ano-novo-chines/</link><description>Metro registered more than 230,000 passengers during the eight days of the Lunar New Year's Golden Week, revealed representatives of the Light Metro Society at a meeting of the Islands Community Services Advisory Board. The company promised to study several suggestions from the members of the Advisory Board to optimize the services of the Metro
 
During the eight days of Chinese New Year's holidays in the interior of China, Macao's light meter transported more than 230,000 passengers/times, Leong Chon Kit, vowel of the Islands Community Services Advisory Board, citing representatives of the Metro Society Light Macau (MLM).
At a meeting of the Advisory Body, the same vowel recalled that in January this year, the Metro registered an average daily volume of 25,300 passengers, which means a notorious increase compared to the number verified before the entry into operation of the Father Seac lines Van and hengqin.
According to the Chinese language press, during the meeting, some vowels advocated the introduction of more electronic payment to automatic sales machines and the launch a daily pass of the metro to facilitate passenger travel. In addition, a vowel advised to reduce administrative expenses derived from the return of Metro cards. These suggestions will be studied by MLM, guaranteed the company's representatives.
Still in relation to the slight meter, some vowels have expressed hope that the links between seasons and public bus services will be perfected. In this domain, the creation of a night bus career was suggested to take Metro passengers to the airport when the daily operations of the subway are over.
On the other hand, the vowel Un Su Kei noted that during the Chinese New Year period, many visitors had to wait between one and two hours at Hengqin's border post to enter Macao. In your opinion, it is important for the authorities to update the data on tickets on each border so that they can guide tourists to move outside peak hours. At the same time, the vowel considers that it is necessary to increase the number of automatic machines for border passengers in the Hengqin post.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>55 athletes received pecuniary awards</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/55-atletas-receberam-premios-pecuniarios/</link><description>A total of 55 athletes and 17 coaches, youth training coaches and technical support personnel were distinguished with pecuniary prizes “because they had exceptional performance in 10 competitions of six sports modalities, with 46 medals won”, having “the number was“ the number higher ”in the last five years. In addition, merit certificates were assigned to 157 athletes and 39 coaches and technical support staff of 17 sports modalities, the Sports Institute (ID) indicated.
Recognizing the “efforts” by the award -winning members of the MSAR selections in various international competitions in 2024, the secretary for social affairs and culture stressed that “the development of the sports panorama of Macau would not be possible without the hard work and the dedication of several generations. of sports agents ”. LAM stressed that the government persists in the parallel development of “sport for all” and high performance sports.
For the preparation of this year's national games and the 2026 Asian Games, the secretary said, an improved version of the “glory program of national games/Asian Games” will be released. He said, cited in a statement, "will enable the government's broader support to athletes who fulfill competition requirements, in order to create better conditions for their preparation."
LAM also pointed out that the “Training Plan for International Sports Technical Officers” will be studied, aiming, through the complementary support given by the government, to create conditions for athletes, coaches and personnel to organize qualified competitions to participate in work developed by international sports organizations.
The ruler also assured that the ID, together with youth education and development services and health services, “will provide athletes with complete and comprehensive support, including support for studies, renovation provisions and medicine Sports, in order to allow them to get better results. ” LAM had the opportunity to dialogue with young athletes, namely about the supports necessary for the sports career.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Registered break in the requests for residence of Portuguese</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/registada-quebra-nos-pedidos-de-residencia-de-portugueses/</link><description>The number of requests for residence made by Portuguese and approved by the authorities fell by 2024, in annual terms, according to data from the Public Security Police (CPSP), and after the imposition of restrictions on Portuguese emigration.
Twenty requests were forwarded by Portuguese to migration authorities last year and, of these, 13 (65%) were approved, according to the Macau of TDM channel, citing CPSP data.
In 2023, the number of requests totaled 56, and was given green light at 52 (92%).
Macau has not accepted since August 2023 new requests for residence for Portuguese, for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing only justification of family meeting or previous connection to the territory.
The guidelines eliminate a practice signed after the transition. The alternative for a Portuguese to guarantee the BIR undergo a candidacy for qualified frame capture programs. Another hypothesis is the "Blue Card", limited authorization to the work bond, without the benefits of residents, namely at health or education level.
The TDM tried to understand with the authorities what the reasoning for the approved and rejected requests, but did not get a response.
The numbers also show that 2024 has values ​​lower than the pandemic period, when there were strict restrictions, including the closure of borders.
In 2022, Portuguese submitted 32 requests of residence, with the authorities to approve 31 (96%); In 2021 there were 20 requests, with 17 to obtain a favorable assessment (85%), and in 2020-which includes processes of 2019-56 orders were submitted and the approval rate was 100%.
Retracting to 2019, the authorities granted 112 of the 116 requests, with an approval rate of 96%.
About the new guidelines, the Portugal Consul General in Macau, Alexandre Leitão, said in December it was a sign. “Obviously, this decision was a sign. (…) And a sudden change, after COVID-19, at a time when it came to the recovery and the need for economic diversification, when it means in any city in the world and China itself, openness, ”he said.
"Let's say that we have the right to look at this signal as frustrating and contrary to our expectations and above all difficult to understand by the moment and the fact that there are few Portuguese who come from Portugal to look for Macau," he said.
Alexandre Leitão said he believed “to be in the interest of the region to benefit from the qualified contribution of more Portuguese”.
The 2021 census indicates that there were over 2,200 people born in Portugal living in Macau. The last estimate given to Lusa by the Portuguese Consulate-General pointed to about 155,000 Portuguese passport people between residents of Macau and Hong Kong.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>History of Gordo Macaense Tea Explained in Lisbon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/historia-cha-gordo-macaense-explicada-em-lisboa/</link><description>The Lisbon Geography Society will host on February 20, at 15:00 (Portuguese time), a conference entitled “The Macaense Fat Tea: Narratives and History”. Promoted by the Asian Commission of that institution, with the support of the Macao House in Portugal, the conference will be given by Professor Manuel Fernandes Rodrigues, born in Macau and scholar of the identity issues of the Macaenses.
The event will take place in hybrid format and can be accompanied via zoom, and the address, ID of the meeting and password are available on the Electronic page of the Lisbon Geography Society (https://socgeographylisboa.pt/evento/o-cha -Gord-Macaense-Narrativas-and-Historia/).
At the launch of the event, the organization begins that there are "many similarities between fat tea and European and Asian banquets." “The banquets of the peoples of the spice islands, the European banquets that many associate with the ancient times of the Greeks and Romans with the Italian anti-Pasto whose origin is attributed to the milestone after their passage through China, to the Portuguese arabic inheritance of Az-Zibib Arabic. Yam Chinese tea, they say, named the meal itself and its composition, ”he says, noting that“ these are many of the myths that are the origin of the fat tea of ​​macanese cuisine ”.
“Other more recent reflections associate fat tea with the tradition of High Tea English tea and suggest the possibility of the diversity of fat tea dishes originated in Macao bourgeois society in the nineteenth centuries. However, these narratives are essentially speculative and perhaps based on the imagination of reports of oral tradition, ”can be read in the synopsis.
The speaker will try to “look for another line of exposure centered on the research of historical events that result from maritime epic characterized by the tragedy, resilience and devotion of the macanese, particularities that have been perpetuated as identity traits.”
Former Assistant Professor at the University of York, Toronto (Canada), where he graduated and completed a master's degree in Economics, Manuel Fernandes Rodrigues also made postgraduate studies at Virginia and Michigan (USA) and European College (Bruges, Belgium ), and was an economist at “Ontario Energy Board” in Toronto. Reformed official of the European Commission, is the author of the work “History of Macaense-Contribute Gastronomy for the reinforcement of a unique identity” and several articles at Daxiyangguo-Portuguese Journal of Asian Studies at the University of Lisbon, in the Cultural Institute Journal of Culture Macao and in Vox magazine of Aiace-Anntern of Brussels.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Predicted 400 children in the 1st year of kindergarten</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/previstas-menos-400-criancas-1o-ano-ensino-infantil/</link><description>In the school year 2025/2026, about 4,000 children will attend the first year of kindergarten, anticipated the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), which will translate into a break of 9.2% compared to 2024 /2025, when Macau's kindergarten received 4,406 students from the 1st year. The body stated that the central register of children's school access to kindergarten for the first time is still underway for the next school year. According to the assistant coordinator of the Central Zone Advisory Board of Community Services, Wu Hang San, DSEDJ has ensured that, taking into account the decrease in the number of people at school attendance in recent years, it has actively communicated to schools regarding schools the school dimension, the development of the subjects and the transfer of teachers. The idea is to define development directions for educational establishments and improve the quality of school education. In concrete, DSEDJ stressed that it will make good use of the flexible mechanism that foresees between 25 and 35 students in each class, adjusting the overall size of the classes. At the same time, it will seek to reduce the impact of the low birth rate on schools, through the Educational Fund, school funding plan, among other support measures. On the other hand, according to Wu Hang San, the body stressed that it will encourage schools to reinforce healthy and harmonious family concepts among students. In addition, it will run positive campaigns with parents and other citizens to foster a good atmosphere in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2342/</link><description>Contracted by Raehk network to traffic drugs in Macau
A 31 -year -old resident was arrested, who also holds Raehk Identity Ticket on suspicions of drug trafficking. Police found that the young man would have been "hired" by a Hong Kong criminal network to traffic drugs in the territory. In the early hours of yesterday, it was intercepted at the border post of the Delta Bridge. In his inauguration, 42.2 grams of cocaine were found, valued at 84 thousand patacas. In another case, police detained a 51 -year -old woman from the countryside of China, who had, since the second half of last month, three illegal currency exchange transactions in Macao, and collected profits by $ 10.4 million from Hong Kong. In a casino in Cotai, he was arrested in the act, having been found in possession of the suspicion of 200,000 HKD and game sheets evaluated at 131,000 HKD.
 
Ends soon application to the residence for the elderly
Those who want to move to the residence for the elderly should apply until tomorrow, said the Institute of Social Action (IAS). The presentation of the candidacy in person should be held within the hours of office hours, and online can be done until 11:59 pm tomorrow. Between January 1 last year and February 10 this year, IAS received 440 candidacies.
 
Named members of the Specialized Commission of the Game
It is composed of the specialized committee of the fortune or unlucky games sector. There are six members appointed by the chief executive, according to the order published in an official bulletin. Chan Kak is the representative of the chief's office, while Lam Chi Long represents the secretary's office for administration and justice. Secretaries' offices for economics and finances and security were appointed LO Chi Fai and Chang Cheong, respectively. Lin Yuan and Lam Sio one represent the secretary's offices for social and culture and secretary for transport and public works, respectively.
 
PJ removes human trafficking in the case of five residents
The Judicial Police (PJ) clarified that the case of the five residents entitled to participate in a network of telephone burla abroad did not imply human trafficking, stressing that the description of these residents as “victims” of this crime by an OCS in Portuguese is “information wrong ”. Assuming that authorities have been able to have good results in preventing and combating human trafficking, with the rate of this type of crime “extremely low” or “even zero”, PJ has reiterated that since December last year, there have been no new cases of burla related to jobs abroad.
 
Intercepted prostitute in a hotel in Nape
In a Hotel in Nape, the Judiciary Police (PJ) intercepted a woman from the interior of China who will have committed prostitution. Admitting this conduct, the woman claimed to receive 300 patacas for each "transaction". After discarding this person's involvement in more criminal cases, PJ referred it to migration services for activities not corresponding to the quality of tourist.</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Santa Casa provider proposed birth subsidy of 30 thousand patacas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/provedor-da-santa-casa-propos-subsidio-de-nascimento-de-30-mil-patacas/</link><description>In a meeting with the secretary for social affairs and culture, the provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia proposed several measures related to birth and population aging. One of them was the increase in the birth allowance of current 5,418 Patacas, a value that considers “derisory” to 30,000 patacas. As for aging, he gave the idea of ​​turning the lower floors of the residence into an elderly
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia proposed a series of births and aging measures to the secretary for social and culture affairs, Lam. Increased birth allowance, free day care and use of residence for the elderly to create a home were the ideas transmitted By António José de Freitas, who expressed concern with the phenomena of the low birth rate and the aging of the population in an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
“I proposed that the Macao government should increase monetary support to encourage the birth rate. In Hong Kong there are 20 thousand for every child born and it is good not to forget that there are over seven million inhabitants. Macao doesn't even have 10%. Macao gives 5,418 patacas, which is derisory. Last year, only 3,000 children were born, ”noted António José de Freitas.
In this sense, in a meeting with LAM, where members of the social sector of the Electoral Commission of the Chief Executive were present, the Holy House provider made a proposal in this context: “I suggested the secretary that the value, at least, should be 30 thousand Patacas. Every 1,000 children who are born only represent 30 million patacas. ” "It's nothing," he said, pointing to the revenues of 6,300 million from MSAR.
In the same field, he noted that “it is a luck for children” to be 15 years of free education in the territory, “something that does not happen everywhere”, however, argues that it takes more. “The government should also exempt children who need preschool, that is, the day care. Because whether families have money or not, they have to pay a monthly fee, ”he said.
As for the reaction of the secretary, António José de Freitas said it was “good”: “I think that, by her reaction, this will move forward. The birth subsidy will not be 5,000 Patacas for sure, ”he said in a preview of the government lines.
With the low birth rate in the territory, day care centers are already impacting. With two day care centers -one in Nape, subsidized by the government, and another on Avenida da República, the Lara Reis day care center -the Santa Casa was also affected, with these two spaces accounted for “losses” last year, due to decreased number of babies.
The oldest daycare in Nape has a capacity of 258 children, currently counting less than 200. “And according to the numbers of the Social Action Institute, our day care is one of the highest occupancy rate. There were day care centers that had to close rooms, ”said the provider. The Lara Reis day care center, with space for 70 children, welcomes, at the moment, 24. "All this is derived from the low birth rate," he noted.
Recently, the Deputy Director of Health Services (SSM), Kuok Cheong U, predicted that the MSAR should register less than 3,500 births in 2025, a number that would be the lowest since 2004. After visiting the first babies born in the lunar year of the serpent, He said he hopes that the birth rate "continues to fall" and added that "it will be good" if the number of births reaches 3,500.
If Kuok's forecast is accurate, this will be the least fertile year since 2004, when Macau registered 3,308 births. According to official data, 3,712 births were 43.5% than 10 years (6,571) and out of a maximum of 7,913 set in 1988, which was a lunar year of the dragon.
 
Residence for the elderly must host home
On the other hand, the tendency of aging of the population that will only be aggravated in the coming years also worries António José de Freitas. For this reason, it was also one of the topics he addressed with the secretary for social affairs and culture. The provider took official data from the Institute of Social Action, according to which 1,800 people were waiting to enter the homes of the elderly.
As this newspaper reported in January, there were only about five hundred hundred homes in elderly homes, and the waiting list was quite extensive. Vago places did not even cover a third of the people who were waiting to enter these spaces, which totaled about 1,800.
“I said 1,800 are many beds. Doing the math, a home with a capacity of 100 beds is already a very good home, has to have some space. We need 18 homes to be able to satisfy these requests. This is now, but in some time it will be worse, because the aging of the population gradually worsens, ”he said.
Stating that there is always talk of the home that is being built in zone A of the new landfills, the provider argued that it cannot be expected. “Why not enjoy the residence for the elderly, whose occupancy rate is too low? This has 37 floors, each floor has nine autonomous fractions… ”, he continued, saying that the idea would be to“ enjoy the lower floors ”.
In your opinion, taking advantage of that space to create a home would be "a perfect idea," because "when they enter the residence for the elderly, people have no guarantee about the future." According to the rules, people who can live in those fractions have to be independent. “The elderly who enter now have total independence, but in 10 or 15 years from now they are dependent, it is the law of nature. And then? They have to go back to the place of origin and have no guarantee of taking place in the elderly homes, ”he lamented.
Thus, the idea would be that, after being dependent, these seniors will pay, instead of the income of the residence for the elderly, the tuition of the home - which would be on the lower floors of that building. "It is a quick, effective solution and we enjoy the space that is already created," he said.
Home of Misericórdias, of Santa Casa, has 129 beds, currently welcoming 95 elderly. The space never fills because the third floor is dedicated to independent people, and 98% of the elderly who are admitted are bedridden and dependent.
Asked if it believes that in the lines of government action will be announced measures in this context, António José de Freitas said that there will be "a major revision regarding the distribution of benefits to the needy people." "And I think the consumer card will be an announced thing," he added.
 
Santa Casa with positive balance of 34.5 million
The Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao ended 2024 with a positive balance of 34.5 million patacas, “thanks to rigorous management,” said the provider, António José de Freitas, to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, indicating that Last year, all tenants of commercial spaces again paid the incomes, after several years of pandemic in which the amounts were cut, resulting from the economic situation that lived. The revenues “collected” by the Brotherhood ascended 102 million Patacas, a 6% increase in 2023. Most of the lace earnings of stores (42% of the total), in a value of 43.7 million; Following the subsidies of the Institute of Social Action and Health Services, of 17.6 million (17.4%), and interest on time deposits and the Order was worth 17.6 million (17.2%). As for the expenses, they totaled 67.6 million, and the spending on the staff were the ones who had the most “weight”, a total of 50 million patacas. Asked if this year there will be an increase in salaries, António José de Freitas said that no now, but "probably next year." In 2023, Santa Casa rose the salaries of employees by 5%.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Real estate sector wants land auctions to invert crisis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-imobiliario-quer-leiloes-de-terras-para-inverter-crise/</link><description>The president of the Macao Real Estate Entrepreneurs Association considers that the sector is living the “worst scenario in the last 40 years”, having recorded only an average of 3,000 transactions of housing fractions in the last three years. To inject vitality to the sector, Ung Choi Kun suggested, for example, that the government has been auctions of land to erect housing for exchange in urban renewal
 
The real estate sector of the territory is experiencing the “worst scenario in the last 40 years,” warned Ung Choi Kun, president of the Macao Real Estate Entrepreneurs Association, pointing out that, according to data from the Finance Services Directorate, 3,057 were registered. Transactions of housing fractions at MSAR last year. The average number of house transactions has reached only about 3,000 in the last three years, it has accentuated.
On the sidelines of the Spring Lunch organized by the Association, Ung Choi Kun also pointed to the constant increase in old buildings built over four decades in Macao. Given this context, he suggested to the authorities to advance with land auctions to build housing for exchange in urban renewal, in order to give more opportunities to the real estate sector.
According to the Chinese language press, the associative leader hopes to see various measures to counteract the crisis panorama, including the “deep integration” between the “1+4” industries and the real estate sector. In this respect, it has exemplified that the development of traditional Chinese medicine and Big Health requires modern industrial parks, laboratories and advanced equipment, as well as cold chain storage and logistics facilities. However, he warned that the current conditions of factories in Macao "can no longer meet the requirements for the development of modern industry."
In addition, Ung Choi Kun proposed to the government to take the initiative to erect a “complex with the nature of former libris”, encouraging the financial and banking sectors to support the participation of real estate industry in this project.
On the other hand, it stressed that small and medium -sized SME (SME) currently face “multiple challenges” related to capital, technical and market. Therefore, it expects a “high-tech industry incubation center to be built, which provides“ One-Stop ”SME services including offices, technical support and financing services. In your opinion, this solution will not only strengthen the competitiveness of SMEs, but will also foster more leases and investments for the real estate sector.
At the same time, Ung Choi Kun asked the authorities to launch “favorable and facilitating measures for the population” as a “one-stop” measure to open commercial establishments to stimulate internal demand and strengthen investor confidence .</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rushdie was “dangerously close to dying,” says prosecution</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/rushdie-esteve-perigosamente-perto-de-morrer-diz-acusacao/</link><description>Writer Salman Rushdie was "dangerously close to dying," the prosecutor said during the trial of the alleged author of the attack that made the author of "Satanic Verses" lose the sight of one eye.
Hari kills, a 27-year-old Lebanese American, shouted “Palestine free!” Upon entering the Chautauqua County Court in Mayville, New York, accused of attempted murder and aggression. The accused, arrested at the scene of the attack, stabbed the author of "The Midnight Children" a dozen times on his face, neck and abdomen on August 12, 2022, which left the victim between life and death during weeks.
Prosecutor Jason Schmidt recalled that Rushdie had just sat down to give a talk at the Chautauqua amphitheater to about 1,000 people when “a young man in median stature wearing a dark mask (…) appeared in the theater and once on stage, accelerated all over speed".
“Killing dug the knife in Mr. Rushdie with strength, efficiency and speed repeatedly, striking and stabbing the head, neck, abdomen and top of the thigh” of the writer. According to Schmidt, Rushdie lifted her hands to defend himself, but remained sitting after being hit several times.
Deborah Moore Kushmaul, an employee at the Cultural Center, told the jury that she collected the knife used in the attack and handed it to the police. “I saw blood, I saw people cluster. The audience, in much of the elderly, shouted. My biggest concern was that there could be a bomb in the bags, that there could be another aggressor. ”
The author of the attack was “dangerously close” to kill Rushdie, said Jason Schmidt, adding that he was stabbed in his right eye so fury that the optic nerve was affected. “Blood pressure was low. He lost a lot of blood. ”
The 77-year-old British-American writer, born in India and a resident in New York, did not attend the trial, but should give testimony. Rushdie has received death threats since his work “The Satanic Verses” was declared blasphemma in 1989 by the then Supreme Leader of Iran, Ayatola Ruhollah Khomeini. Iran denied any connection with the aggressor and said the only culprit for the incident was Rushdie.
Killing, who declared himself innocent from the attempted murder, was also accused in July by a Federal Court of providing support and appeals to the Lebanese Shiite movement Hezbollah, linked to Iran, who supported Fatwa. Lawyer Lynn Schaffer warned that prosecutors "make assumptions about killing that affect the way they investigate."
Killing, who wore a blue shirt and often spoke to his five -member legal team, told the New York Post after his arrest, who had read only two pages of Rushdie's novel, but believed the author. had "attacked Islam."
Even the attack of killing, Rushdie was the victim of more than six frustrated murder attempts. After living under escort for several years and hidden in London, Rushdie has settled in New York in 2000. Since then, she has an intense social life.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>