<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Government grants 230 million for childhood support</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-concede-230-milhoes-para-apoio-na-infancia/</link><description>The government will attribute, tomorrow, the childhood assistance allowance for this year, in a single installment, to the qualified persons of the first round, in the amount of 18,000 patacas. According to IAS, until July 31, 13,000 cases were presented and approved, and the total amount of assignment of the respective subsidy will be more than 230 million Patacas
 
Tomorrow, September 4, the Government will assign the childhood assistance for this year, of single performance to the qualified persons of the first round, in the amount of 18,000 patacas, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) announced yesterday.
According to the body, until July 31 this year, about 13,000 lawsuits were presented and approved. The father, mother or tutor of babies or children who have been born from 2022 to 2025 and who hold the permanent resident identity ticket of the MSAR, may submit the request of the childhood assistance allowance for the year 2025 since July 16 this year and until June 30, 2026.
IAS has revealed that it will assign the subsidy for this year to qualified persons, tomorrow, through bank transfer, being the total amount of attribution of more than 230 million patacas.
On the other hand, in relation to the requests submitted between August 1 this year and June 30 of next year, the allowance will be awarded within 60 days from the day after the date on which the request has been approved, IAS added, recalling that the creation of this support aims to “encourage the birth and to realize financial support measures for families with babies or children”.
It is recalled that, according to the stipulations defined by the authorities, the support, paid in a single provision, provisional in nature and intended for families with permanent babies or permanent resident children, has a value of 18,000 patacas, which means that in the three years, the beneficiary family will receive a total of 54,000 patacas.
Regarding the possibility of the measure continuity after 2027, IAS President Hon Wai said in June this year that, being a new plan, it is necessary to “collect more data” and make an analysis and then make a decision. Already the spokesman for the Executive Board and Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, added that intention is not to “cut” the measure after three years, reiterating that it is necessary to do an analysis and understand if the plan must be optimized or, for example, create a different measure.
Birth in the territory has continued to give signs of decrease, having registered, in the second quarter of this year, the lowest number of births since at least 1998, according to data from statistics and census services. Between April and June, 671 babies were counted, 79 less than the 750 registered in the first three months of the year.
Looking at the semester, 1,421 babies were born in Macao, 17% less compared to last year's same-year period, when 1,710 was registered.
It is recalled that, at the beginning of the year, the Deputy Director of Health Services predicted that there should be less than 3,500 births in the territory this year, which, to happen, will be the lowest since 2004.
In the general calculation of last year, the number of undead totaled 3,607, 105 less in terms, with the birth rate to be 5.3 °, the lowest since 1985. Macau registered only 0.58 births per woman, the lowest fertility rate ever in the world and the lowest in the world.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gilberto Camacho appointed Costa Nunes Subdirector</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gilberto-camacho-nomeado-subdirector-costa-nunes/</link><description>D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten this year has a subdirector. This is Gilberto Camacho, who took office on the first day of September. For Miguel de Senna Fernandes, president of the Macanese Instruction Promoter Association, the day care manager, the appointment arrested with the school's work needs and because “now conditions are increasingly complex and the requirements of education services are more strict”. The nursery starts today for another school year and has a new reduction of children. There will be 191, less 33 than in 2024/2025. The director, Felizbina Carmelita Gomes, notes that there is a decrease in the number of children for three consecutive years

Victor Rebelo
 
There is a new position in the organic structure of the kindergarten D. José da Costa Nunes, with the entry of a subdirector, a position that has not existed in the institution for about 10 years. This is Gilberto Camacho, who hitherto performed duties in the computer sector of the same child school, and that from the first day of September began to assist the director, Felizbina Carmelita Gomes.
For the president of the Macanese Instruction Association (Apim), who manages the day care center, the appointment was a decision “for the kind of kindergarten”, because “now conditions are increasingly complex and the requirements of education services (DSEDJ) are more rigorous, so that, in order to charge all this, it is necessary, beyond the competence of the director, that there is someone who can coad.”
Miguel de Senna Fernandes told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "during this time, the computer man eventually met all the intricacies of the house, and is therefore the person who could best hold his hand to the director, with all due respect for all employees who work on Costa Nunes."
The leader adds that Apim also wants, "with this opportunity, to make known that he is aware of the situation and working conditions of all staff." Therefore, he stresses, "we want to reinforce Apim's own administrative body, and, as we have this close relationship with the kindergarten, we naturally intend the best for school, that is, to endow it with another very important person, at least to give it the status he had long been having in practice, which was the subdirector."
The number one of the Apim points out that this is a “very good bet”, hoping that the element recently promoted to a management position “can charge all the situations that are placed”.
It concludes, admitting that the association itself will strive to reinforce the administrative body, "since there must be a new vision on how to act."
Since Macaense took the lead of Apim in 2016, "there has never been a subdirector," he said. “I remember that the school was subdirector Pedro Ascension, who would later assume the roles of director after the departure of Lola Couto do Rosário,” said Senna Fernandes.
Regarding the appointment of Gilberto Camacho, the director of the infantary, Felizbina Carmelita Gomes, confirmed to JTM that the entry of a subdirector, proposed by Apim, “actually comes to help with the work we have and the connection with DSEDJ, since it takes more personal to work in the part of the school itself, to provide better services to the community”.
The nursery starts today another academic year, after yesterday a meeting with parents and guardians of children of children.
Regarding the number of students enrolled for 2025/2026, it is totaling 191, less 33 than last year, when the school was 224, divided by three levels, from three to five years of age. Children will be distributed by 11 classes, less than in the previous school year, and 10 of the rooms are intended for regular education and one to special education.
It is recalled that in 2023/2024 there were Nunes 13 classes (12+1) on the Costa Nunes and a total of 250 students. There has been, therefore, the reduction of a class in each of the last three years.
The low birth rate remains the main reason for decreasing students. "This is the reality, that is, reduction of students directly caused by the weak birth in Macao, a situation that has been reflected at the beginning of each academic year for three consecutive years," noted the director of the nursery.
Despite the reduction of children, the school did not reduce the number of educators, who are currently 24, including the director, who join nine teaching agents and 12 assistants, as well as a dozen employees who perform diverse functions in the school. "It is our policy not to say goodbye to anyone, notwithstanding this decrease of children, therefore, there is no exits or entries," the guardian reinforces.
In the previous school year, Costa Nunes had a lack of speech therapists, but the situation is already resolved. "We are not lacking these experts for this year," he said in statements to this newspaper.
 
English language development
Another important part of teaching is the learning and development of the English language. In this field, the nursery has an educator expressly for this purpose, teaching all classes once a week. “Through the DSEDJ subsidy, we had a contract to provide this type of work and service that we have been doing for two years, encompassing children from the three levels of the school,” he says.
Regarding extracurricular activities, which will take place throughout the year, “after classes, because sometimes parents have this need to leave children”, the childhood garden will keep entertainment dedicated to sport, specifically soccer, and also painting, cooking, Chinese martial arts, yoga, among others.
Felizbina Carmelita Gomes, director of Costa Nunes since 2022, says that these activities are performed by semesters. "After registration in the first, parents decide if the child wants to develop another type of activities in the second half, this is how we work," he says, adding that "the school is always open to the suggestions of parents and guardians."
Already in the musical component, "this aspect is mandatory in our curriculum," he says, specifying that "for the students of K3 (five years) the music is properly incorporated into their classes, while children from K1 and K2 (three and four years) have a discipline once a week."</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“A prioridade absoluta será a elevação da qualidade de vida dos cidadãos”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/a-prioridade-absoluta-sera-elevacao-da-qualidade-de-vida-dos-cidadaos/</link><description>The New Hope, list number 2 candidate for elections for the Legislative Assembly, says defending “uncompromising” the rights of citizens, as well as protecting “the most fragile”. In an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, he says that “the absolute priority” will be to help raise the quality of life of citizens. For this, it promises to focus on issues such as housing, employment, health and social security. Stressing that "it is the only list that intervenes in the hemiciclo simultaneously in the two official languages," the new hope reiterates that these are "the most renamed elections ever." The objective is to keep two seats, but it considers it “very positive” if it achieves a single mandate
 
What reasons led the new hope list to apply for the Legislative Assembly?
-The New Hope (NE), this year, drawn with number 2, emerged in 2001, founded by a group of citizens with deep roots in Macao, from various ethnicities and cultures, whose families have lived here for several generations. The central objective was to ensure, in the hemiciclo, an independent voice and fully dedicated to the service of communities and citizens. After an electoral debut in which he was on the verge of winning a mandate in 2001, the Nee guaranteed for the first time in 2005 a parliamentary representation. It currently maintains two deputies in the Legislative Assembly (AL). It will be important to note that the new hope list is the only list that intervenes in the hemiciclo simultaneously in the two official languages. It is also the only list that always intervenes in Portuguese in the period before the order of the Plenary Day of AL from 2005 to the present date.
 
What way is this candidacy different from the rest?
-The more distinctive trait of the NE over the 26 years of establishing of the MSAR is its condition of being an independent, reliable, predictable list and the confidence of citizens. The confidence of citizens is not purchased, but it is gained with time and daily work of interconnection with official entities in solving citizens' problems. It is also distinguished by the uncompromising defense of the fundamental rights of citizens, the valorization of the preservation of local culture and rights, and the strict observance of the “one country, two systems” principle. The distinctive mark of NE is to always remain true to its fundamental principles.
Because we say the truths that others shut up, bringing urgent social problems and needs to government knowledge.
 
What are the priority problems and what solutions propose to solve them?
-We do uncompromisingly the rights of citizens and protect the most fragile.
The absolute priority will be the elevation of the general quality of life of citizens. In the next four years, we will fight for:
Housing: Ensure access in a timely manner and without time to public housing in terms of dimension and quality of construction materials. It should reduce the income of the government's residence to the elderly who are currently out of the financial reach of many elderly. Income should be calculated according to their financial capabilities. Housing must be built for the staff of the FSM and civil personnel of the Public Administration pursuant to paragraph 2) of paragraph 2 of article 55 of Law No. 13/2013 (Land Law). Public housing of T2 and T3 should be built and rented to young people wishing to constitute a family and thus contribute to the increase in the number of births.
Employment: Combat unemployment and regulate part -time work, ensuring these workers fundamental rights such as vacation and sick leave. The number of non-“white collar” workers should be reduced by freeing these vacancies to young licenses resident in Macao.
Health: Improve the quality of primary health care and increase human resources by appealing them with better medical equipment and medicines. We suggest new medical specialties due to population aging, diversify medical specialties and raise their formation within robotic surgical operations and use of artificial intelligence in the early diagnosis of disease. We suggest the acquisition of modern equipment and ensure that everyone has access to quality medicines.
Social Security: Create a permanent pecuniary reimbursement plan, with a legally established minimum appropriation, from MOP 15,000 to relieve the current cost of living. Establish an electronic annual consumption support card from MOP 10,000 to activate the current weak domestic consumption and help the most needy families.
A future for young people: instituting specific plans for young people to be a family with lease supports and bonus interest for their own housing acquisition.
Macao Platform Role: There should be a deeper realization of the role of Macao in economic, cultural and commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries with the improvement of air and port infrastructure with the purpose of capturing foreign tourists.
In this sense, the direct coming of foreign tourists implies the expansion of Macao International Airport so that aircraft can park on ample platforms and medium and long -level aircraft (Airbus 380) can perform tasks that facilitate passenger boarding and landing. It will be necessary to expand the current spaces (hangar and courtyards) for replenishment and maintenance, ie with multiple stands. On the other hand, it should be opened immediately competitive space of airline routes by attracting more renowned airlines to operate on the MSAR.
Air Macao has an obligation and duty to position itself as “the air bridge between China and Portuguese-speaking countries” highlighting the unique cultural, patrimonial and geographical advantage of MSAR. The company should employ more residents of Macau, namely hiring cabin crew and pilots. The company must strive to renew the current fleet (A320neo or A321neo) and increase its aircraft fleet with new and efficient short, medium and long course aircraft to reduce noise and fuel. It must also establish strategic partnerships with other foreign companies such as TAP de Portugal and other European carriers to increase the value and network of benefits to passengers. The catering service should be improved by raising the quality of meals by offering food options that reflect Macau's unique gastronomic inheritance (a sino-Portuguese fusion) and introduce special menus (vegetarian, kosher, halal) in a consistent and easy to request.
The MSAR is now worldwide known as the city of Tourism and Games, but the Ká-Ho in Coloane's port port remains a quite underused strategic active and should be transformed into a competitive “hub” at the scope connected with the large bay for better development of macao role as a platform between China and Lusophone countries. To achieve these objectives, the current infrastructure is consolidated by the modernization of the quay with continuous dredging and deepening, ensuring that the depth of the channel and the evolution basins are permanently maintained to accommodate the container load ships.
 
What are the expectations in terms of elections? How many seats do you expect to win at the Legislative Assembly?
-Tal as we have stated, we confront the most renamed elections ever since the establishment of the reduced number of competing lists, which leads to a higher concentration of votes and requires a significantly higher number of suffrages to elect each candidate. The current D'Hondt method is an electoral calculation system of proportional representation that benefits the lists that receive more votes. In this context, and, despite these difficulties, we aim to maintain our representation, considering the result of gaining a single term. That's why we appeal to vote on September 14.
 
JTM and Electoral Act
In accordance with the electoral law, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao continues to cover the campaign for legislative elections on September 14. Like previous years, we will adopt a model that aims to inform our readers about the ideas defended by the various candidacies, under the premise of granting the same journalistic treatment to all competing lists in direct suffrage. Without prejudice to any general reports on the elections, never focused on specific lists, we will present interviews with the different candidacy teams, which will be entitled to a page until the campaign is closed, naturally without any charges for the lists, as a way to provide a public interest service to readers.
In this sense, we sent a fixed set of questions to all applications, whose answers will be published over the next few days, in increasing order of the number of the lists in the voting newsletters, among those we have received until the day of production of the edition.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Music, food and workshops “connect” communities in Coloane</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/musica-comida-workshops-conectam-comunidades-em-coloane/</link><description>The event “Connections-Music.Movement.Nature” will return to the last weekend this month, with seven thematic areas. The initiative will take place in the “Urban Farm”, in Colaane, in a wide space, where activities will be performed for all ages. There will be a gastronomic area, music, handicrafts, workshops and health and well-being sessions, among other activities

Pedro Milheirão
During the weekend of September 27th and 28th, the “Urban Farm” space in Coloane will host the “Connections-Music.Movement.Nature” event, according to a statement from the organization. The new larger space will allow various activities to be performed, spread throughout seven distinct areas. The event will feature music, activities for families, “body and holistic” workshops, a gastronomy zone and a local artisans market, according to “Connections - Community Gathering”.
The “Village”, a space inspired by the traditional Chinese villages, with wooden houses and an oriental garden, will be the meal, drinks and craft zone. "Larry's Place", "Concept H", "Black Lotus", "Cakes by Rose &amp; Muse", "Juk" and "Happy Stand" will take care of the food. In turn, the 12 artisans include Dreama, Neska, Zarja's Selections, Ceragigi, Ododoodo, Dollfie, Wickd, White Lodge Dreamland, Wutoyah, Gems Awakening, Lylon Skincare and Knotme. In this area, there will also be a musical team “more organic, lounge, and focused on songs in the world”.
At “Gipsy Camp”, participants will have the opportunity to explore musical instruments, such as Asalato or Drums, and a Handpan concert of the duo, which was responsible for the curatorship of the countryside. In addition, the space will have pillows, resting places, as well as a “fire ritual”, a lecture on spirituality and “individual tarot and soul reading sessions”.
Families will find in “Family Tent” collective meditation sessions, mandala paintings, crochet, construction of cardboard masks, interactive reading moments, fishing and agricultural activities, among other pastime. The idea, stresses the organization, is that "the younger ones can participate in any activity that is taking place on the grounds, provided they are accompanied by parents, and can also explore the offer of" Urban Farm ", which provides fishing canas to fish and agriculture activities."
In the cup of a tree will be the “Treetop”, a mezzanine that will be the scene of “body exploration activities and more serene moments, meditation and relaxation”. The different sessions include zumba, bachelor, conscious dance and “insideflow,” beyond yoga, “gyrokinessis” and pilates. There will also be sessions of "Sound Bath", mantras and "meditations to sunset and connection to nature."
Yurte Mongol will host Quiz night, “very popular activity among the Portuguese community”, which the organization has prepared in English, “so that more people can participate in the session,” according to the statement. In the “Concrete” zone, there will be graffiti and urban art sessions, with the collectives of local artists “Outloud International Street Art Festival” and “Mid Age of Dawn Skateboards”. In a clearing of a small woods, under the name of “Woods”, the audience will find electronic music and outdoor dance, with multiple local and regional DJs.
According to the organization, the “Early Bird” period ends this Friday, with prices of 150 and 250 patacas, for one or two days of event, respectively. Urban Farm also provides parking spaces that can be reserved.
Those responsible are “a collective creation that combines a conscious way of life with unique experiences” and want to “provide‘ family activities, lectures and workshops, exploration of well-being and artistic expression, ”the statement says. The “joyful celebration” of “Connections” has brought together “people and passions” since 2018, having held an event this year and another in 2019, in an area next to the Ka-Hó dam.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Katia Guerreiro takes Fado to Beijing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/katia-guerreiro-leva-fado-pequim/</link><description>The Portuguese Guerreiro will take Fado to Beijing, at a concert to take place on September 7, at 7:30 pm, at the Forbidden City Concert Hall. The musical moment is integrated at the Fado 2025 Festival - Beijing edition, dedicated to the centenary of the illustrious Portuguese guitarist Carlos Paredes, according to Xinhua.
The Chinese audiences will have the opportunity to appreciate 15 classic works of fado, including “Red Rose”, “who would say” and “Amelia, name of Lisbon”, among other topics.
The fadista will be accompanied by a band of Portuguese musicians, including guitar musician Pedro de Castro, classic guitarist André Ramos and acoustic bassist Francisco Gaspar.
Haverá ainda uma participação especial, de Hou Yu, renomada artista chinesa da Ópera de Pequim, que interpretará trechos clássicos da peça “Dui Hua Qiang”, de acordo com o programa.
“Esta interculturalidade artística visa promover, através do diálogo musical, a exploração das expressões comuns de vida, saudade e emoção em diferentes contextos culturais”, refere a agência de notícias.
The event offers a “comprehensive” cultural experience that includes various cultural activities such as a Portuguese guitar -themed artistic exhibition; The screening of the movie “Guitars to the Portuguese”; and a lecture given by Pedro de Castro. “The festival will enable the public a complete dive in the culture of Fado de Portugal”, can read.
Katia Guerreiro began her musical career in 2000, simultaneously with medical studies. With the birth of his daughter in 2012, "The growing love for fado led her to dedicate herself fully to singing."
Subsequently, “recognized for the remarkable contributions”, the fadista was awarded the Order of Infante D. Henrique by President Cavaco Silva, in 2015, and with the title of the Order of Arts and Letters, one of the highest titles attributed by the French government to foreign citizens, consolidating itself as one of the most important contemporary artists of Fado and International Ambassador of Portuguese Culture.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Completed preparations for renewal of fixed network licenses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concluidos-preparativos-para-renovacao-das-licencas-de-rede-fixa/</link><description>Preparations for the renewal of the CTM and MTEL fixed network license are already ready, the CTT director said that this time the renewal will not have a very long deadline. In addition, it will bring clearer provisions to future operators or for reforming the telecommunications sector
 
All preparatory work has been completed for the renewal of the installation and public telecommunications installation licenses and licensed services of the Macao Telecommunications Company (CTM) and the MTEL Telecommunications Company, Derby Lau, director of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT), revealed.
The licenses of the fixed network and the “interchange review of the public telecommunications service concession contract” will have the deadline on the 30th of this month. According to the Chinese language press, Derby Lau stated that the renewal of licenses will be announced later, in an official bulletin, with the government to explain, more detail, the respective approach.
According to the CTT director, this time, the renewal of licenses will be “a little different”, and the renewal period will not be too long. Given other planning, new contracts are not just a simple renewal, Derby Lau stressed, adding that the procedure is expected to bring “clearer” provisions to future operators or for reforming the telecommunications sector.
It is recalled that in September 2024, the government entered into with the CTM the additional contract to that concession agreement, as the underground conduct network affects fixed telecommunications, as well as the facilities and equipment of the Fixed Phone Service, among other CTM assets, will be part of RAEM's assets. After its contract, the government has a basic full telecommunications network, which, according to the CTT, establishes a base that allows future qualified users to access, with greater equity, to the assets of telecommunications.
In May of this year, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Wong Kit Cheng, the CTT reported that the government will continue to review the contractual clauses, detailing the measures related to the opening of the use of the concession assets. In the same answer, regarding the legislative process relating to the proposal of the “Telecommunications Law”, a work already started in the previous term of the government, the body indicated that the executive will continue to promote the corresponding legislative work in order to support the sustainable development of the telecommunications sector.
In addition, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ron Lam, the CTT discarded plans to create an advisory board for the development of the telecommunications sector.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Denunciadas más condições de trabalho nos casinos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/denunciadas-mas-condicoes-de-trabalho-nos-casinos/</link><description>Game sector workers have suffered “heavy” workloads and more pressure at work, according to Leong Sun Iok. The deputy believes that the introduction of electronic game tables, an insufficient number of employees and irregular hours, among other factors, have aggravated the working conditions of casinos employees
 
Pedro Milheirão
Game operators employees continue to suffer heavier workloads and increased pressure at work, following the implementation of electronic game tables, considers Leong Sun IOK, according to a statement. During the “Game Industry Personnel Consultation Forum”, organized by the Macao Game Employees Association, of which Leong is president, the deputy noted that employees have felt “more likely to make mistakes” and concerned with their potential impacts on their own job.
According to Leong, electronic gaming tables oblige employees to perform various operations within specific terms, and in the event of misconceptions and the supervisors are not understanding, they are subject to warning letters. Moreover, the effects that illegal money chambers and portoins have on the functioning of casinos have been affecting the workers themselves, who are sometimes “unjustly guilty of supervisors who do not understand the circumstances”, he argued.
He also said that “the number of employees is still insufficient,” given the growing number of visitors in casinos. In addition, there have been complaints about “chaotic shift systems” and “difficulties in requesting annual vacations”. According to prolonged night shifts, they became the norm, resulting in “irregular” times, with “last-minute changes”, which makes it difficult to plan rest periods and time with the family.
At the same time, he defended the increase in the number of vacation days and the simplification of the respective request process, adding that casinos workers "rarely have genuine autonomy in choosing the dates." Recognizing that the Labor Relations Law stipulates that the annual holidays are negotiated between employers and workers, urged the game companies to perform “a comprehensive review of the intensity of work” and to optimize shifts, safeguarding the “right of employees to rest”.
Leong Sun Iok also stressed that employees are "the most valuable active of a company." In this sense, he urged game dealers to implement “human policies, treat employees with respect, relieve the pressures of work and refrain from issuing letters of light warning”, ensuring “tranquility” to workers. The deputy stressed that the game industry, being the largest sector of Macao in terms of employment, has an impact on the subsistence of tens of thousands of families.
Considering the current climate of employment of MSAR, and the difficulties that residents face in guaranteeing work, the government "should further promote the location and ascending mobility in the game sector," he defended. In addition, the policy of "excluding non-resident workers from positions such as" Croupier and Supervisor "should be maintained.
Generally speaking, operators should ensure reasonable levels of personnel, regularly inspect electronic equipment and minimize long time, reinforcing occupational safety and health measures, reiterated Leong. Working conditions must be optimized and perfected license systems, “in order to improve the morals and physical and mental health of the staff,” he said.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gastronomic experiences shared in Thailand</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/experiencias-gastronomicas-partilhadas-na-tailandia/</link><description>Macau was one of UNESCO's creative cities in gastronomy invited to participate in an international conference, which took place in Songkhla, Thailand. The seminar served to share experiences and publicize the gastronomic culture
 
The city of Songkhla, an important port of southern Thailand, received delegations from various countries and regions for a conference on gastronomy, in which Macau was present, having shared experiences as a creative city and publicized to its gastronomic culture.
As one of UNESCO's creative cities in gastronomy invited to participate in the seminar, the masters presented culinary demonstrations, as well as conducting familiarization visits to fishing and sustainable agriculture projects, creative industries and restoration, as well as other activities included in the three -day event program, highlighting the development of creative cities.
The Deputy Director of Tourism Services (STD), Cheng Wai Tong, along with the Sous Chef of the Galaxy Macau Raffles Hotel, Justin Je, among others, participated in the conference, which took place under the theme “Creative Cities for Sustainability of Lake Songkhla”.
The event has gathered representatives and chefs from other creative cities of gastronomy, including Phuket and Phetchaburi (Thailand), Thessalonki (Greece) and Belo Horizonte (Brazil), as well as from Thai cities from other creative areas, along with academics, businessmen, artists, among others.
In a knowledge exchange panel on development of sustainable creative cities, Cheng Wai Tong figured as one of the speakers and talked about Macau's experience as a creative city of gastronomy, focusing on topics such as vision and political alignment, creative industries and local integration, community participation, intersectory collaboration, challenges and lessons learned.
In turn, Justin Je released the gastronomic inheritance of cross -west and west of Macao, in sharing sessions and culinary demonstrations of exchange with Songkhla chefs and other creative cities of gastronomy. Using two famous ingredients from Songkhla, sea bass and sugar, the chef also created a dish inspired by Portuguese codfish dumplings and a famous macao shrimp paste brand.
In a statement, STD recalls that, after the designation of Macao as UNESCO Creative City in Gastronomy in 2017, the government launched the implementation of the related work plan, noting that STD regularly participates in UNESCO Creative Cities Network, “trying to invite industry representatives and chefs to participate together to take advantage of opportunities for exchange, learning and collaboration”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Imagination and creative practice to have children and young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/imaginacao-pratica-criativa-ao-dispor-de-criancas-jovens/</link><description>Artistic workshops designed for children and youth, promoted by the Macao Art Museum and the Cultural Institute, will work through close contact with artistic creations and cultural relics. The activity will take place between October and December and is inspired by the observation, imagination and creative practice of the participants. Registration is open until September 21
 
The Macau Museum of Art (MAM) and the Cultural Institute (IC) will organize “Art Without Borders - Children's Workshop” between October and December, including seven artistic workshops designed for children and young people from four to 16 years old.
Through close contact with MAM's artistic creations and cultural relics, sessions will be inspired by participants' observation, imagination and creative practice, allowing them to “experiment with the unlimited possibilities of art,” according to promoters of the initiative.
Interested parties, speakers of different languages, can apply to the “Activities Registration” page of the single account until September 21st.
In the text released by the IC, it can be read that “as the main event of the 'friends of the mam', which takes place twice a year, 'Art Without Borders' has always been well-received between parents and children,” adding that this series of workshops will lead children and young people to “embark on a time”, starting with the contemporary creations of “Macau Art 2025”, before traveling the old porcelain route to “experimentation the merger and cultural and artistic connection between China and Portugal ”.
The “Art for Kids and Graduates-Artistic Creation Workshop for Families” is adequate for children from four to 6 years, where they join parents to follow the footsteps of artistic masters, sharing the joy of creation between families, can read. Children from five to 10 can choose from “Cantonese sessions of“ Let's Play with Art - Artistic Creation Workshop for Children ”(a total of five classes) to explore the creative spirit of contemporary and ancient art through multimedia creation.
On the other hand, young people between 11 and 16 can sign up for the “blue and white-porcelain painting rhapsody for young people”, exploring the cultural connotation of ancient blue and white porcelain, while learning to transform traditional patterns into contemporary aesthetics.
Each workshop lasts 12 hours, with a rate of 240 patacas, held at Espaço Zero, R/C of MAM or in the square of art, R/C of the Museum of Offerings on the transfer of sovereignty of Macao.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Taiwan singer takes melodies to Studio City</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cantora-de-taiwan-leva-melodias-ao-studio-city/</link><description>Winnie Hsin, Taiwan's singer, known as the “Queen of Cure”, celebrates 40 years of career with a concert in Macau, integrated into the “My Melodies - Our Memories” tour. The show will take place at the Studio City event center, on November 29
 
Reimaginated songs from different times and timeless classics will be focused on the Winnie HSI concert in Macau, scheduled for November 29th, at the Studio City event center.
The 63 -year -old and four -year career singer has joined masters for the “My Melodies - My Memories” tour, where she will essentially play melodies, a style of music that have noted her.
Known as the “Queen of Healing” and for her crystal clear Soprano voice, the artist “will illuminate Macao's night landscape with cure, resonate and permanent songs,” according to an introductory note of the show organized by Melco Resorts.
Over the course of four decades, Winnie Hsin “has won the heart of several generations with her delicate but deeply expressive voice, and also with her comforting affection,” says the document, enumerating some of the excerpts of the singer's authorship, such as “Love Runs Deep”, “Someone in the Night” and “Forget”, which became an “emotional resonance between Generations, since their moving lyrics and melodies have created deep connections with the public. ”
For this exclusive concert in Macao, the canonetista will revisit her favorite repertoire, playing reimaginated excerpts from various eras - from bumps moving to urban and cheerful love songs, “creating a sincere tribute to her illustrious musical career and an intimate celebration with her fans,” says the text.
From Hsin's biography he highlights the fact that in 1995 he gave voice to the main character in the folded Mandarin version of Walt Disney's animation movie “Pocahontas”, and also played the version of the same language as the film's song, “Colings of the Wind”, and some other soundtrack songs.
In 2009, he held his first solo concert in Shanghai and seven years later released the album “Flow”, in celebration of the 30 years of musical career. In 2018, he launched “Believe in Love”. Some of the topics of these successful albums should be presented at their concert in Macao, for which ticket tickets are already on sale. Prices range from 388 to 1,388 patacas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casa Garden welcomes lecture on collective housing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casa-garden-acolhe-palestra-sobre-habitacao-colectiva/</link><description>Today starts the international cycle of lectures on twentieth -century collective housing, in the auditorium of Casa Garden, with the colloquium “Heroic Housing in Lisbon, Porto, Macao and Maputo”, by Jorge Figueira, according to a press release. In partnership with the East Foundation, Docomomo Macau will organize a total of five lectures, until November, with specialists from Portugal, the United Kingdom, Singapore and Macao. The series “The Advent of Collective Housing in the twentieth century” will explore “the architectural, political and social dimensions of collective housing”. Next Friday, Ana Vaz Milheiro will present “The Macao Collective Housing Stories” from the 1950s until 1980. On October 30, Carlotta Bruni will “rethink Macao's urban fabric”. Already on November 6, it will be the turn of Johannes Widodo, who will talk about the “evolution of Singapore Public Housing”. On the 11th of the same month, Miles Glendinning will conclude the series, with a discussion about the "global history of Hong Kong's mass housing." The lectures are intended for the general public, architects, historians and students interested in reflecting “about the legacy and future of collective life”, says Docomomo Macau. The entrance is free.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“New Chapter” for Galaxy with office in Singapore</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-capitulo-para-galaxy-escritorio-em-singapura/</link><description>Galaxy Entertainment Group (GEG) has opened an office at Singapore's Galaxy Lion City, located at Singapore, marking a “new chapter in the GEG growth path,” says a press release. In line with the vision of the Government of MSA, the group's new space “will support tourism consultations, meetings, incentives and conferences and exhibitions (MICE)”. The office reflects the “innovative approach” of GEG, focused on the client and regional collaboration. The operator also hopes that the new venture signes its intention to "improve brand visibility and promote significant connections with travelers and stakeholders throughout Asia." Singapore is "one of the most vibrant and cosmopolitan countries in Asia", can be read in the note, and the new space will serve "as a dedicated center to improve connections with the business community of the country." Elmen Lee, director of GEG's integrated resort services, stressed that "Singapore has always been an important origin market for Macao." "The taste and sophistication of Singapore travelers are naturally aligned with those of Macao," he added. "GEG continues to expand its base of international visitors to inject more vitality in Macao," he reiterated. Lee also highlighted Galaxy Macau, Broadway Macao and Starworld Macau, which "gathers luxury housing, award -winning restaurants, premium stores and world -class entertainment facilities."</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Postponed visit from Sam Hou Fai to Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/adiada-visita-de-sam-hou-fai-portugal/</link><description>The visit of the Chief Executive to Portugal and Spain, who was scheduled for the period from 16 to 23 September, was postponed, learned the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. The trip to the Iberian Peninsula had been announced late last week, but the program was not yet known. It is recalled that the visit was scheduled for the first half of this year, but was eventually postponed due to the change of government in Portugal. It is not known now for when the official visit should be resigned.</description><pubDate>2025-09-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Minors use Ia to generate sexual images of colleagues in school photos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/menores-usam-ia-para-gerar-imagens-sexuais-de-colegas-em-fotos-escolares/</link><description>False sexual images of children are being generated with photos of school events and albums of finalists, and released on social networks. In some cases, the minors themselves are the authors, with elementary and secondary students to use Deepfake technology through general AI sites and other tools.
The National Police Agency (NPA) plans to investigate the main image that generates images to discover any irregularity and elaborate prevention measures.
A elementary school student in eastern Japan will have generated a false image of nudity from a basic education girl who attended the same sports class and published the image in a group of chat on social networks. "I used the Generative AI to edit a photograph of the face of a girl I like," he said, according to police.
Many websites and applications allow users to generate images by giving instructions to AI, with some allowing users to generate false sexual images based on children's photos.
The boy will have used images shared by the class to his colleagues.
According to NPA, police received more than 100 consultations and complaints about false sexual sexual images in 2024. Most involved allegations such as "nudity images made with my face are on social networks."
Most victims are elementary and secondary students.
In most cases, known people are suspected of generating the images. Seventeen cases were identified as involving images made by AI with photos of school events and finalist albums.
The harassment directed to same -sex colleagues was a reason in some cases.
There have also been serious enough cases to trigger criminal investigations. In the Tokai region in downtown Japan, a basic student was sent to the prosecutor on suspicion of defamation for generating a false image of nudity using the photo of a classmate and share it with friends.
The possession and production of sexual images of children are regulated by the prevention law of child prostitution and child pornography. However, the law presupposes that cases involve a real image of a child, which makes it difficult to accuse deepfakes.
Therefore, police across the country are applying other laws and regulations to these cases. A survey by a US security company found that 95,820 deepfake videos were identified online by 2023, 98% pornographic.
"The cases that the police are aware of are just the tip of the iceberg," said a high police official. Given this situation, the NPA is focusing on about 10 websites and applications of images generating images that are especially popular among elementary and secondary students, among the many found online.
Police will investigate and the results will be used not only for criminal investigations, but also for awareness -raising campaigns through delinquency prevention classes and similar programs.
"If sophisticated false images spread online, it violates the privacy of children whose photos are misused, even if they are false," said Masaki Ueda, an associate professor of criminal law at Kanagawa University, familiar with regulations on obscenity.
"The psychological impact is significant, so the deepfake images should be treated similarly to child pornography and should be considered legal regulations," said Ueda.
Countries increasingly regulate sexually explicit deepfakes.
In South Korea, a bill was approved in September 2024 to punish not only the creation of Deepfake images, but also the act of visualizing or possessing them.
In the United States, a federal law was promulgated in May that prohibited the publication of sexually explicit images or videos online without the consent of the subject in question. The law made it mandatory that social networking platforms and other operators remove these images and videos within 48 hours of receiving a request from the victims.
The United Kingdom and Australia also regulate the sharing of sexually explicit depfake images.
In Japan, the government of Tottori province reviewed in August a decree to ban - with penalties - the creation of sexually explicit false images using photos of children.
Appeals to action, including legislation, within the central government's working group that discusses the use of the internet by young people. However, the discussions did not advance much.
Childfund Japan, an international non -governmental organization based in Tokyo, interviewed 1,200 men and women across the country from January to February. About 70% of respondents believe that sexual images of children, including false images, should be regulated by law, regardless of whether subjects in the images actually exist.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-02 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>