<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Xia Baolong praises Lag</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/xia-baolong-elogia-abrangencia-das-lag/</link><description>[‘Xia Baolong Yesterday completed the fourth of the six days of his inspection visit to Macao. At a meeting with the head of the Executive of the MSAR, the Director of the Cabinet for Rae Affairs with the Council of State considered that the new government "had a good start" and that the lag for this year include "comprehensive content"

Hong Kong and Macau's Office Director for the Council of State, Xia Baolong, began a six-day visit program on Thursday afternoon to be aware of the current development of the MSAR. In Santa Sancha, where he was received by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, and the director of the Central Government Cabinet on MSAR, Zheng Xincong, Xia Baolong transmitted the “warm greetings and consideration” of President XI Jinping to Macao residents, and the “recognition” of the central government for the “good start of the new government”.
The morning of the next day, Xia Baolong had a meeting with the chief executive. On this occasion, he stressed that Sam Hou Fai, in leading the new governing team of the MSAR, determines with determination the spirit consecrated in the important speeches of President XI Jinping given during his visit to Macao, and the policies and plans of the central government.
According to the Social Communication Office (GCS), Xia mentioned that the lines of governing action (LAG) for the current year, with “comprehensive content covering all governive areas”, reflect a “committed and brave spirit”. In this sense, the lag “have full recognition and support from the central government,” he said.
On the other hand, on Friday afternoon, the Chinese leader met at the Government headquarters with representatives of 14 associations with "Love to the Fatherland and Macao." At the meeting, opinions were exchanged the importance of constituting high quality patriotic associations and the combination of efforts to accelerate the proper diversification of the Macao economy and the development of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin.
Present at the meeting, the Secretary for Administration and Justice revealed that Xia Baolong encouraged associations that “love the homeland and macau” to fully support the government action under the law. According to André Cheong, the director of the cabinet for Hong Kong and Macau expects that the associations themselves will be dedicated to the development of high quality, to bring more individualities together with love for the homeland and Macao.
The secretary also said that Xia pointed out that the various sectors of the society of Macao must converge forces to jointly promote the proper diversification of the economy, and should always keep in mind this task and the awareness of "preparing for adversity in prosperous times." As indicated, Xia reiterated that they should all take into account the development of hengqin and take it as their own subject.
André Cheong has assured that the team of its guardianship will advance with the reform of the public administration in the framework of the structure, personnel and the provision of services, to raise the efficiency of governance. In parallel, it will intensify the bet on human resources and other aspects, in order to dedicate with dedication the promotion of the in -depth cooperation zone.
 
From maritime areas to quality of life
On the third day of the visit, on Saturday, Xia Baolong had a meeting with representatives of the elderly and visited the temple of A-Má, manifesting themselves to the exploitation and transmission of Macao's history and culture. He was also in the Maritime Museum to find out the evolution of maritime history of the territory.
Later, he participated on a boat trip to observe the maritime areas. Security Secretary Wong Sio Chak said Xia expects the Government of MSA to scientifically plan and enjoy the maritime areas and new landfills in the light of Macao's developmental needs, as well as fully benefit from central government policies.
The Secretary for Security has ensured that the team of his guardianship will continue to proceed well to planning in that domain, including the work of maritime safety. In this regard, he stressed that customs services will continue to acquire advanced equipment, reinforce personnel formation and improve law enforcement capabilities, in order to provide a safety guarantee for sustainable development and high quality MSAR.
In the afternoon, the director observed several lots of planned land to receive construction projects. The Secretary for Transport and Public Works said that Xia Baolong expressed “great attention” to the general development of Macao, improving the environment of old neighborhoods and increasing the quality of life of the population. According to Raymond Tam, Xia urged the government to execute well the urban plan of new landfills and raise the quality of life of the population, through urban renewal and other measures.
The secretary has asserted that his guardianship will make the most of the position of MSAR development, actively boost the proper diversification of the economy and improve the various urban infrastructure, in order to increase the feeling of happiness and well-being of the population.
On the same day, Xia Baolong also moved to the Macao Giant Panda Pavilion. According to Chao Wai Ieng, president of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the leader emphasized the importance of the conservation work of giant pandas.
The pavilion received 370,000 visitors in 2024 and has already promoted this year a dozen school dissemination activities, which had the participation of more than 2,000 students, Chao Wai Ieng said.
 
Determination to the tariff war
Xia started yesterday's agenda with a breakfast at a restaurant in the central zone with representatives of the Masters vowels at the Popular National Assembly (ANP) and the Chinese people's political advisory conference (CCPPC). Quoting Xia Baolong, Lao Ngai Leong, Master's deputy to ANP, stressed that it is necessary to determine the difficulties derived from the current complex international environment, especially the US tariff war, a situation that also had impact on local companies. According to Lao Ngai Leong, in this sense, the Chinese leader insisted that Macau should accelerate economic diversification and integrated hengqin development, as well as strengthen consumption.
In turn, Leonel Alves, a vowel at CCPPC, reiterated that more efforts should be made to achieve greater integration between the laws of Macao and Hengqin. In addition, it argued that the laws of the Great Bay should be disclosed, especially those of the cooperation zone, with the Lusophone countries, in order to boost their commercial cooperation.
Yesterday morning, Xia Baolong also met with the deputies of the Legislative Assembly (AL). On the fringes of this activity, he made praise for the professionalism and hard work of Macao journalists, according to the GCS. According to AL, Kou Hoi In, the director of the cabinet for Hong Kong and Macau affairs recognized the work of AL, but requested the reinforcement of the relationship between administration and legislation.
In addition, the director visited the Qingmao Border Post in the afternoon, and the D. Pedro V Theater, between various cultural and tourist projects.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New captive Pope Catholics of Macau for the humility and emphasis on peace</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/novo-papa-cativa-catolicos-de-macau-pela-humildade-enfase-na-paz/</link><description>EPASELECT EPA12090267 POPE Leo XIV Waves at Faithfuls As He Walks Inside The Vatican Before The Regina Coeli Prayer, Vatican City, 11 May 2025. EPA/Riccardo Antimiani



The concern for world peace, tied by the new Pope in his first speech, is one of the main points of the reaction in Macao to the election of Robert Francis Prevost, now Leo XIV. He wants to "bring us love, joy, justice, and peace of Christ," said the bishop of the D. Stephen Lee territory. For priests Daniel Ribeiro and Luís Sequeira, the choice was "a big surprise." Both consider the simplicity and proximity to the people as one of the main characteristics of the Holy Father
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Just like all over the Catholic world, in Macao the faithful lived with expectation and anxiety about the choice of Francis' successor to the place of the Holy See's maximum representative. The reactions to the nomination of the American Robert Francis Prevost did not expect, with a message from Bishop D. Stephen Lee.
"This joy is not just a joy of the heart or a joy of having a new Pope in the structure of the Church, but a spiritual, even theological joy, because any Pope is the representative of God on earth, the father of the Catholic Church-the father of the parents and the servant of all servants," he can be read in the diocese of Macao, with the bishop to consider that all Catholics share this "human and transcendent joy."
In the letter, D. Stephen Lee points out that the new Pope “wants to bring us love, joy, justice, and peace of Christ,” urging the local Catholic community to follow Leo XIV “with all our heart and soul, in fulfilling our evangelical mission!”
Father Daniel Ribeiro also reacted to his appointment, recognizing that he was a "big surprise". However, "after choice, thinking, reflecting," the parish priest of the diocese understands that "it makes a lot of sense and there is reason to choose both the name and the person."
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the Brazilian cleric indicates that the main criterion of the Pope's choice is not nationality, "but the personality." "That's why the cardinals have nine days of prayer of coexistence and then the conclave," he noticed.
From the optics of Father Daniel Ribeiro, possibly the Church wanted the new Pope to have the characteristics of Francis, and as Leo XIV did in parishes, "having done a very strong pastoral work," concretely as a missionary in Peru, "this allowed him an experience with the people, which must have helped a lot in choice."
Another point that has been taken into consideration, in the opinion of Daniel Ribeiro, “was the fact that the American was mayor of the Congregation for Bishops, Dicker, responsible for the Pope's choice and counseling for the appointment of the new bishops”, maintaining direct contact with the bishops around the world.
In short, the parish priest states that "you can realize that Leo XIV is simple, humble, thoughtful, conciliatory and spoke in peace several times." “It has the simplicity of Pope Francis, the clarity and doctrine of ideas of Pope Benedict XVI,” he says.
About "reforms, changes in the church as a divine institution," the diocese's guardian considers that the "church, as a human institution, is always seeking to improve, mature, deepening and sacrificing itself, because the Church is holy and was created by God."
Thus, he mentions, "the changes, adaptations, reforms, are normal and have been made." The new Pope "will not come, contrary to what people think, change some dogma, some truth of faith, some value," he said, adding that "the Pope's main mission is not to create new teachings, but to defend and propagate what is the deposit of faith."
Father Daniel Ribeiro believes that the new Pontiff will continue the characteristics of Francis, while "a person close to the people, since he has this charisma of sympathy." As for the choice of name, he follows Leo XIII, "who wrote the encyclical of the social doctrine of the Church, in a time of many political ideologies and conflicts."
 
Provide a different dimension of the Church
Father Luís Sequeira also pointed out to JTM that Leo XIV "spoke soon of peace." "This Pope is capable of bringing great vigor in search of peace, seriously, which is what we need today, because politicians are too concerned about the economy and militarism," he said.
There are three aspects that play the cleric that has been in Macau for almost 50 years. First, the fact that the Pope is Augustinian, "can bring the spirituality of the heart." Second, "he is a missionary early on, and is therefore able to provide a different dimension of the Church, often bureaucratic and very institutional." Third, the attention given "to the poor and abandoned, or the most forgotten, specifically in Peru, there in the mountains, where he was a great missionary and very open to those more disadvantaged."
As for many people, or not linked to the church, Robert Prevost's appointment was a surprise, as it was not included in the list of major favorites. “It was also a surprise in the sense of understanding the Spirit of God, which is a bit different sometimes from our human fragility,” says the Jesuit.
For Luís Sequeira, the challenge now is to show "our worldliness and our humanity, which would almost say, the conspiracies, that things come out many times the opposite." One bishop who was "hidden" was that it appeared.
"I like to see these contrasts," says the priest, for whom "sometimes our human reality, the" Mass Media "seems that they want to discover the gunpowder, but there is exactly the other side, with a different dimension many times from our human and earthly sense of things."
 
Build dialogue bridges
The JTM heard other Catholics from local society. José Miguel Incarnation states that the election translates the choice of the pontiff “more universal to date”, attributing to the new Holy Father the “Global Papa” epithet, being born in the US, being a descendant of Europeans, having mission in Latin America, as well as other continents.
After Francis “having approached the Catholic Church to those who no longer claimed in Catholicism as a spiritual and caritative force for the resolution of their daily problems,” Leo XIV arises “at a time when the world faces a world war, as Francis often stated,” he attests.
In the opinion of the editor of the Portuguese section of the Catholic weekly “O Clarim”, the “transnational” human formation and structure of Leo XIV “will allow you to build dialogue bridges between the two main views of seeing the world, today again very embodied in the western and oriental axes”.
Addressing the case of China and the two RAE, PREVOST has led until last Thursday the dickest to the bishops, "so it is perfectly intended from the premises of the agreement between the Holy See and the Popular Republic of China for the nomination of the Chinese bishops."
The journalist emphasizes, on the other hand, that "although the appointment and all the relationship of the bishops of Macau and Hong Kong with the Holy See is made through the dicker for evangelization, and not through the dickestory to the bishops, they are still two prelates to the service of the Catholic Church, whose activity unfolds in Chinese territory."
For all this, he believes that Pope Leo XIV "will know how to take care of the faithful who have always been with the Church, that Francisco won, and those who for more political-economic forum had a greater difficulty in following the footsteps of the Argentine pontiff."
Finally, the Catholic Charlot Norway states that "this is the right pope for this moment," a young, modern, popular pontiff, who knows theology well and "will bring a new dynamism to the Holy See."
In his free time, “like to read, walk and travel to new and diverse sites,” which indicates “your interest in learning more about the world,” he says.
Being a pope with “global leadership experience” who spoke of the church as “sinodal” in his first speech, he is expected to “continue the reforms of our late Pope Francis”, with which he presents “many similarities.
In many social issues, “it is seen as a progressive, who defended the migrants and the poor, the name Leão reflects this commitment,” says Charlot Norway. However, he warns, "it will face many challenges," especially with "so many controversial issues we are currently faced."
Exhorting the Christian community to keep the Pope in their daily prayers, the participant in some church activities, believes that the new Pope will be able to overcome these challenges, since "he is a man with universal meaning."</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Melco is negotiating departure from Manila</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/melco-esta-negociar-saida-de-manila/</link><description>Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment has already started contacts with “potential buyers” of its participation in the resort City of Dreams Manila, whose financial results have been affected by the growing “competitive environment”. The probable departure of the Philippines is part of the new strategy of “light assets” adopted by Melco, which remains optimistic about the future of the Macau market
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The Philippine Game market should even come out of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment's interest, with the sale of the participation it has in the resort City of Dreams Manila, currently managed by Melco Resorts Leisure, his subsidiary Philippine. Developed in conjunction with SM Investments Corporation, Belle Corporation and Premium Leisure Amusement, the venture has generated results below expectations, leading Melco to bet on its alienation in the framework of a strategic review that privileges “light assets”.
"We continue to conduct the process with consultants. Potential buyers are signing (confidentiality agreements) in the virtual database and answering a series of questions. Over time, we will reduce this group to a restricted list for the bidding process," said Geoff Davis, Melco's executive vice president and financial director, in teleconference for analysis of the results of the first quarter this year.
During the dialogue with analysts, Lawrence Ho, President and CEO of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, admitted that “the intensified competitive environment” in the Philippines had a negative impact on the operations of Manila between January and March. “We are adjusting our cost structure and reviewing marketing programs” to increase the contribution of EBITDA (results before interest, taxes, amortizations, and amortizations, and amortizations, and scarce. Depreciation) in the Philippines, clarified the group leader, who also explores casinos in Macau and Cyprus, and is expected to open one at Sri Lanka in the third quarter of this year.
Segundo os dados divulgados pela operadora de jogo, os ganhos EBITDA do City of Dreams Manila caíram 20,4% para cerca de 30,1 milhões de dólares americanos (241 milhões de patacas ao câmbio actual) no trimestre encerrado a 31 de Março, em termos anuais, enquanto as receitas operacionais decresceram 8,2% para 101,6 milhões de dólares (814 milhões de patacas). As receitas brutas do casino na capital filipina cifraram-se em cerca de 109 milhões de dólares (873 milhões de patacas), recuando 13% num ano e 27% em apenas três meses.
Still, due to the good results obtained in Macau, Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment ended the first quarter accounts with US $ 32.5 million profits (about 260.2 million patacas), which translates an annual rise of 114% and contrasts with a loss of $ 20.3 million (162.6 million) in the previous three months. Ebitda profit grew 14.1% to $ 341 million (2.7 billion patacas) in annual variation, driven by an 11% increase in operating revenues ($ 1.23 billion or 9.8 billion patacas).
The “solid set” of results in the first quarter “demonstrates our strength and growth prospects in Macao,” said Lawrence Ho, further stressing that bets on the game's mass market reached “record levels” on both casinos at Cotai - City of Dreams and Studio City.
"Studio City has successfully repositioned during and after Covid and City of Dreams now reopening the House of Dancing Water, I think we found our pace and rediscovered our identity," said Lawrence Ho.
According to Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, its quota in the game market in Macau rose to 15.7% compared to the 14.7% registered in the fourth quarter of 2024.
On the other hand, in quarterly terms, the group's operating expenses dropped from $ 3.2 to 3.1 million a day, Geoff Davis indicated, stressing that the value does not include costs related to the "House of Dancing Water" and Studio City's residence shows. "We continue to refine our cost base to identify areas to increase efficiency and flow, and we intend to leave the second quarter of 2025 with operating expenses of $ 3.0 million a day," he added.
The Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment financial director also stressed that “all operators in Macau are more rational now than a year ago,” as regards the reinvestment in the market.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Marcelo reinforces appeal to the vote</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/marcelo-reforca-apelo-ao-voto/</link><description>EPA12090728 PORTUGUESE PRESIDENT MARCELO REBELO DE SOUSA (L) CASTS HIS VOTA DURING EARLY VOTING DAY FOR THE LEGISLATIVE ELECTIONS AT A POLLING STATION IN VILLAGE REAL OF SANTO ANTONIO, Southern Portugal, 11 May 2025. OVER 333,000 VOTERS ARE ELIGIBLE TO PARTICIPATION, WHILE ELECTION DAY IS SET FOR FOR May. Epa/Luis Forra



The Portuguese president appealed yesterday to vote, noting that in the next 12 months there can be no elections, and said he considered that the number of people to vote in advance is a sign that abstention could lower. Speaking to journalists after voting in advance at the Vila Real de Santo António Chamber, Faro, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa stressed that in the six months following the convening of legislative elections it is not possible to have new elections, as in the final six months of the presidential mandate.
According to the President of the Republic, this means that only in the late spring, early summer of 2026, is that if necessary, there could be new elections, which, he said, hopes it will not happen, appealing to the Portuguese to abandon the idea of ​​correcting tomorrow what they do today. "My appeal is to vote. Vote for a very simple reason. The world is as it is, not easy, it is harder than a year ago and on the other hand there can be no elections next year," he said.
While waiting in line to vote, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa spoke to the people who were also waiting for his turn, explaining that he asked for the early vote to be able to go to the Vatican to the inaugural mass of Pope Leo XIV's pontificate, scheduled for May 18, early legislative elections in Portugal.
The president was "very impressed by the number of voters, both in general and here, in particular, I never thought it was so many people to vote."
Asked if he is concerned about abstention, he argued that the high number of people who have signed up to vote in advance is a sign that people want to vote. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa also praised the way the election campaign has elapsed, which he considers that he has been going on very well. "It took place very well, there are no public policy problems, there is no insecurity, punctual things, but nothing exceptionally serious, and on the other there a huge concern of the parties in television debates and now, in the election campaign to explain everything" to voters, he concluded.
More than 333,000 voters registered to vote yesterday, the largest number of always deciding to exercise their voting rights in advance since this modality was instituted.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Draft tie advances the title decision for the last day</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/desporto/empate-derbi-adia-decisao-titulo-para-ultima-jornada/</link><description>Benfica`s Kokcu (R) Fights for the Ball with Sporting`s Trincao During Their Portuguese First League Soccer Match at Luz Stadium, Lisbon, Portugal, 10th May 2025. Rodrigo Antunes/Lusa



Benfica and Sporting tied to a ball, in a derby that could decide the outcome of the 2024/25 edition of the Portuguese Football League, keeping the 'lions' in first place, with the same points and in advantage over the 'eagles'. Trincão, who wasted the penalty that, this season, 'gave' the League Cup to Benfica, scored first, on the four minutes, to the national champions, who, in the 'Hell of Light', did not give the advantage won in the first lap, even with the draw of Aktürkoglu, in the second half, at 63.

Without early champion, he wins the 34th and last day, which is decisive, scheduled for the May 18 Electoral weekend, when Sporting is the host of Vitória de Guimarães and Benfica visits Sporting de Braga. To Sporting, a result is just like or better than Benfica.
The 1st Portuguese League could, after 90 editions, be decided in a derby, among the largest clubs in the capital, on the largest national stage, Estádio da Luz, in Lisbon, in a game where Sporting turned out to be better in the first half and Benfica in the second.
Champion Sporting could revalidate the title for the first time since 1953/54, when he then won the tetra, in the house of the eternal rival, needing to win. But, as always, the finals can have two winners, and host Benfica could recover the national ceptro if he defeated the 'lions' for more than one goal.
The environment that preceded the derby, the third of the season, before the Portuguese Cup final, was exciting, with the benfiquists corresponding to the appeal of coach Bruno Lage to push the "incarnate" team. It was practically an hour of songs, to watch the duel between the top two classifieds, which presented the expected initial teams, with the returns of Di María and Carreras on the 'incarnate' side and Hjulmand and Diomande of 'Green and White'.
Bruno Lage presented his traditional 4-2-3-1, with Trubin in goal, Tomás Araújo, António Silva, Otamendi and Carreras in defense, behind midfielder Florentino and Kökçü, with Di María, Aursnes and Aktürkoglu in support of the offensive reference Pavlidis. On the 'Leonino' side, Rui Borges, unsurprisingly, kept '3-4-3', consisting of Eduardo Quaresma, Diomande and Gonçalo Inácio, ahead of goalkeeper Rui Silva, midfielders Geny Catamo, Hjulmand, Girl and Maxi Araújo, with Trincão, Pedro Gonçalves and Gyökeres in the attack.
Sporting was ahead, after four minutes, by Trincão, well served by Gyökeres, who, in his 100th game by the Lions, paved the way, diverting António Silva and Tomás Araújo, to the shot, first marking, which gave the first derby goal.
This was the first moment of silence of the effervescent 'incarnate' enclosure, which immediately reacted to adversity, such as Di María on the pitch, turned only two minutes, with a shot at the entrance of the 'Leonina' area, slightly over the goal defended by Rui Silva. As almost always, the Argentine extreme was the main bet to create imbalances in the Benfica team, even at a time when the derby was taken by picardies, fouls and individual duels that were valid for yellow cards to the Hjulmand and Otamendi captains.
Maxi Araújo deflected a corner of Trincão, but over the goal, at 17, before, once again, Di María reaches Sporting's 'area' and serving Carreras, which, at first, could not get the ball.
At 28, the goalkeeper Rui Silva took the protagonism of the game, 'save' his goal, when he was thrown at the feet of Aktürkoglu, when the Turkish seemed thrown into the goal, and with the ball controlled.
At a disadvantage, impatience took over Benfica players - even Di María made a foolish pass to the back of Carreras - and, above all, the fans, who returned to ‘freezing’, when Pedro Gonçalves, in a refill to a row of Gyökeres, returned to Trubin, in a bid invalidated by lack of the Swedish front.
In the second half, after a new 'injection' support of supporters, encouraged by the old 'glory' Jonas, Benfica comes on the field without Di María, but with Schjelderup, the 'hero' hero of the League Cup final against this same opponent.
Benfica came in more cracking and sent Sporting to their most defensive zone, but leaving some room for the in -depth releases of Rui Borges's team, invariably looking for Gyökeres.
The 'incarnate' pressure began at 63, when Aktürkoglu, already in the small area, deflected to the goal of Pavlidis' slalom, which practically 'sat' four Sporting players.
The draw did not displease the 'lions', who remained at the front of the championship, and a sign of this was that only at 84 Gyökeres could unravel from António Silva to a weak front shot into Trubin's hands in the last threat of altering the scoring of the meeting.
The balance of the derby and 'temperature' joined the controversy at the end of the game, with the scams between players -and even a benfiquist fan who entered the pitch -who ended with the alternate Ricardo Esgaio expelled, after the end of the game and seven minutes of compensation.
 
Sporting de Braga defeated is 3rd place at risk
Sporting de Braga added the third game in a row without winning, losing 2-1 on a visit to Casa Pia. In Rio Maior, Zalazar put the bracarenses ahead, 20 minutes, but Casa Pia came around with goals from Benala (45) and Livolant (79). With the defeat, Sporting de Braga, which on the last round receives Benfica, kept the 65 points, and continues in fourth position with FC Porto, third, who visited Boavista after the closing of this edition, while Casa Pia is seventh with 45.
Gil Vicente and Arouca, who already had the situation defined in the I Liga, tied 1-1 in Barcelos. The Arouquenses advanced on 56 minutes, by Miguel Puche, but the gilistas repused their equality by Santi García at 58. Arouca follows in 12th position with 35 points, while Gil Vicente is 14 with 33.
Santa Clara remained in the fight for fifth place by winning at the reception to Famalicão 2-1. Wendel Costa scored the two goals of the Ponta Delgada team at 23 and 81 minutes, while Gustavo Sá still drew in the middle, at 58, in a meeting where the two formations ended reduced to 10 elements. With this victory, Santa Clara remains in sixth position, with 54 points, equally with Vitória de Guimarães, which is fifth classified and will still play with Farense, and just a triumph of Victorians to hold the last vacancy for Europe. Famalicão is seventh, with 44 points.
Nacional tied 3-3 at home with Rio Ave, after being losing for three goals. A 'bis' of Tiknaz, which scored at three and 44 minutes, and a Bakoulas goal, at 28, left the village-miles with a comfortable advantage, but in the second half André Sousa (46), Leo Santos (90), and a self-collateral of Kosmoulas (90+4), allowed the National to match the match.
Rio Ave rose to 10th position, with 37 points, more than Moreirense, while Nacional, who in the next round visits FC Porto, is 12th with 34.
 
Portugal in your best
Sebastião rests a week and Eng. Felix pays everything
If for a week, the Portuguese media were divided between the Vatican and the Stadium of Luz, the Saturday has only taken place around the derby. I admit that civil engineer Carlos Manuel Félix Coins, Alentejo de Beja, mayor in Lisbon, was the most impaired of this everyday scene. Politically, it gave him much more way than some of the teams had been champion, to brighten the Marquis and still be able to take [the team] to the county's paces, before Sunday's legislatures (in time of technical draw, Dixit polls, “with a vote gets… with one gets lost!”). Like the rich countries, they did what they do: “summoned” huge police operations that confused tourists, closed metropolitan stations around the Marquis, bordeed streets and alleys in the same zone, put on the workers to make pawns circuits and arranged buses for the trip of fans. Extraordinary hours and hours, which will pay again next week. From the 40 -meter pedestal top, Sebastião [José de Carvalho and Melo] rests another week, and caresses the lion that the sculptors put it next door. Is it necessary to wait for next week?
 
JRD
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss returns to “blink the eye” to Latin America</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-volta-piscar-olho-a-america-latina/</link><description>The use of regional advantages to establishing a liaison bridge between the Great Bay and Latin America was approached at a meeting that the leader of the MGI kept with the head of Uruguay diplomacy. Sam Hou Fai told Mario Lubetkin that Macau will intensify the economic, commercial and financial cooperation and exchange of people with Portuguese and Spanish countries
 
Cultural and tourist sectors, as well as education, economic and commercial contacts and technological innovation, can be used for greater cooperation with Uruguay and other Spanish -speaking countries. This was one of the main points addressed at a meeting between the head of the Executive of the MSAR and the Minister of Foreign Affairs of that South American country, held at the Government's headquarters.
During the meeting with Mario Lubetkin, Sam Hou Fai said he hoped that, through the deepening of pragmatic cooperation with Uruguay, “a system of cooperation at various levels” can be created in comprehensive and multidirectional areas, “in order to achieve collaborative development”. Being Macao one of the central cities of the Great Bay, “is endowed with regional advantages and the ability to play the role of platform to serve as a binding bridge between the region and Latin America,” said the chief executive.
According to information from the meeting, released by the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai stressed that the MSA will be committed to opening the international market, “further intensifying the economic, commercial and financial cooperation and exchange of people with Portuguese and Spanish-speaking countries”. It is recalled that this strategy had already been nominated during the presentation of the government lines for 2025.
He also ensured that his government intends to focus on reinforcing connectivity with both China and the rest of the world, "in the sense of better integration in the conjuncture of national development and serving the country."
At the meeting were also present, among others, the commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the People's Republic of China, Liu Xianfa, the secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, the Eastern Republic of Uruguay in China, Fernando Lugris, and that country's consul general in Hong Kong and Macau, Frederico Lage.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sponsorship for Social Store benefits 372 needy families</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/patrocinio-para-loja-social-beneficia-372-familias-carenciadas/</link><description>The Santa Casa Social Store distributed Cabazes with first -need goods to almost 400 families, with the support of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment
 
With the sponsorship of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, in the amount of 300,000 Patacas, the Santa Casa da Misericódia Social Store of Macao (SCMM) will support this month 372 low -income families through the distribution of gabies with first -need goods. The beneficiaries group includes 300 families nominated by the General Union of Residents Associations (UGAMM) and Federation of Macao Workers' Associations (Faom), 47 accompanied directly by Santa Casa and 25 referred by the Association of Family members in charge of mental disabled.
Raymond Lo, senior vice president of Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment and director of the international market and general manager of Altira and Mocha, represented the company in the delivery of the sponsorship check to the SCMM provider, António José de Freitas. The ceremony, held on Saturday, was also attended by the president of the Santa Casa Fiscal Council, José Ricardo das Neves, the UGAMM Fiscal Council, Leong Heng Kau, and Faom Vice-President and Secretary General Leong Wai Fong, as well as a team of 15 Melco volunteers.
António José de Freitas took the opportunity to thank Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment for the continuous support, 13 years ago, the social store, underlining the company's commitment to social responsibility and care dedicated to the most vulnerable. It also praised the fact that the volunteers organized the distribution of food book and aided in transportation, demonstrating team spirit and corporate cohesion.
In turn, Raymond Lo manifested himself honored to represent Melco in this activity of social solidarity and reaffirmed the group's support for regular social store operations, with the aim of helping needy families improve their living conditions.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Garbage deteriorates hygiene of “three zeros” buildings</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lixo-deteriora-higiene-de-predios-de-tres-zeros/</link><description>Many buildings that do not have companies or business condominiums continue to reveal serious environmental hygiene problems, namely with regard to waste and stagnation of water, according to AMI
 
The city's beautification and cleaning working group has detected several cases of household waste accumulation on the stairs and pans of many “three zeros” buildings, ie buildings without owners' assembly, organization of residents or business company. In addition, objects and containers with stagnant waters were found, the Institute said for municipal affairs (AMI), ensuring that cases will be accompanied by relevant services.
"If hygiene problems or risks to public health are encountered, the Inter-Serviços Working Group will follow their follow-up, to encourage owners and residents to make the proper improvements and create a habitable environment together," said AMI, stressing that the hygiene conditions of the "Three Zeros" buildings have always been "worry of concern".
As members of the beautification and cleaning working group, AMI and health services, together with representatives of social service associations, visited “three zeros” buildings in various areas during the “city cleaning campaign”, which took place between April and May. During these visits, residents and owners were urged to improve the environmental hygiene conditions of the public spaces of the buildings.
Between the second half of April and May 6th, the group visited more than a hundred buildings of “three zeros” in traditional ancient neighborhoods, such as the North Zone, Manduco Beach or Porto Interior. Group members distributed leaflets and placed informative posters on environmental hygiene, with emphasis on issues related to rats and mosquito prevention and stagnant water removal.
In addition, according to AMI, authorities have been cooperating with associations, giving lectures to “three zero” buildings, explaining the correct form of prevention against rats and mosquitoes, and other housing hygiene problems.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GCS devalues ​​online and monthly press exclusions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gcs-desvaloriza-exclusoes-da-imprensa-online-mensal/</link><description>The exclusion of the online and monthly press from a public event is “common practice,” Macao's Social Communication Office (GCS) told Lusa. "The organizer defines the appropriate provisions for the news coverage of the event according to nature, content and place (…), giving priority to television and radio stations, publications with more frequent pereity and news agencies," said GCS, in a written response.
This principle was followed on Thursday at the signature ceremony at Misremio of an agreement between Macao and France for the creation of a joint scientific research program. “Only daily and weekly newspapers reporters, TV stations, radios and news agencies are invited to interview,” said the Fund for the Development of Science and Technology (FDCT) in the Agenda Note.
Lusa asked the FDCT the reasons for excluding the ceremony online and monthly press, but received no response. The GCS said that "it is noteworthy that the media professionals must fulfill the laws and regulations in performing their functions."
Asked by Lusa, the GCS gave no reason to, after the signature ceremony of the agreement, chaired by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, the journalists present not entitled to ask questions.
It is recalled that on April 17, two journalists from “All About Macau”, an online newspaper with a monthly paper version, were detained by police while trying to enter the Legislative Assembly Plenary room (AL) to attend the presentation of the political program in the area of ​​administration and justice to 2025.
Last Tuesday, in the first public comment to the incident, AL claimed that there was a "great influx" of journalists and that "the space for interviews, as well as the places available in the Plenary Room are limited." This justification had already been rejected on 17 April by the "All About Macau", since "apparently there were still vacant places" for the media in the main hall.
On Tuesday, the newspaper accused Al from preventing "repeatedly All About Macao journalists from doing their normal reporting work under false pretexts."
The Macao Journalists Association (AJM) stated that it “deeply regrets” the detention of reporters, including the president of this organization, Ian Sio Tou. This group of Chinese journalists had previously expressed concern about the increase of official events without coverage of social communication and “discriminatory practices” with the sector.
"The unprecedented situation that occurred is sad and worries us, because we consider that it opens a precedent-at least-embarrassing," also reacted to Lusa the president of the Macao Press and English Press Association (Aipim), José Miguel Incarnation.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>One and nanjing release double degree in Physics and Chemistry</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/um-nanquim-lancam-dupla-licenciatura-em-fisica-quimica/</link><description>Scientist Dropping the Reagent Into Test Tube for Reaction Testing in Chemical Laboratory.



The University of Macao (one) and the University of Nanjing (NJU) have launched a double degree program in applied physics and chemistry, with the aim of “increasing international student competitiveness” and training specialists in these fields for the large bay and the country. Considering that physics and chemistry are “fundamental disciplines” and “important pillars for technological innovation”, one argues that the formation of experts in these areas is “great importance to promote the economic diversification of Macao”.
The program will last four and a half years. Students should complete the first two and a half years of applied physics and chemistry courses at UM, followed by two years of applied physics at NJU. Students who meet the undergraduate requirements will receive a diploma in applied and chemical physics from one and the other in NJU applied physics, both recognized in MSAR and mainland China.
According to one, this double degree encompasses materials such as solid, optoelectronic state physics, semiconductor physics, thermodynamics, statistical physics and material magnetism. “It provides students with a solid base in physics and interdisciplinary knowledge of the applications of physics and chemistry, widening their professional experience and, at the same time, promoting innovative thinking and problem solving skills,” he says.
NJU is one of the higher education institutions selected for national initiatives and is part of the lot of the first universities of the continent to offer the teaching of physics. Dozens of academics from the Chinese Academy of Sciences and the Chinese Engineering Academy studied or worked at NJU.
The launch of the program is “an important milestone” in cooperation with NJU, it offers “valuable opportunities for students in Macau and Hong Kong to study at an interior university and represents“ a strong demonstration of integrated development of education in Macao and mainland China ”, he emphasizes that the two institutions also plan to establish a double degree in Computer Science.
 
Open applications for “gaokao” students
However, one is accepting, by June 26, online students of “Gaokao” student (National Exam) of the continent for the 2025/2026 academic year's degree programs. Candidates must reach the minimum score required for admission to top universities (or special admission programs) in the 2025 "look" and get at least 110 points in English.
The institution will select students based on the grades in “Gaokao” and the number of vacancies available. Students with the best scores in the “Gaokao” can qualify for a Scholarship of UM, which fully covers the bribes and accommodation rates. In addition, one offers special scholarships to students of the Great Bay “Gaokao”, as well as Bonus points for Beijing, Guangdong, Zhuhai students who live and study in Hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Four “parallel worlds” of Macau reflected in the Venice Biennial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quatro-mundos-paralelos-de-macau-reflectidos-na-bienal-de-veneza/</link><description>Images of the urban landscape and artistic facilities make up the Macau exhibition patent until November at the Venice Architecture Biennial. According to the president of the Cultural Institute, the show “Mundos Parallels” highlights “The Precious Cultural Content of Macao”

The exhibition “Mundos Parallels”, which represents Macao at the 19th International Exhibition of Architecture of the Venice Biennial, was inaugurated on Thursday in the Italian city, presenting “the urban fabric of the city where Chinese and Western cultures, the old and new styles have been coexisting for over 400 years,” said the Cultural Institute (IC).
Having as curators the architects Wang Shu and Lu Wenyu, this exhibition combines images of the Macao Urban Landscape captured by the well -known humanistic architecture photographer Iwan Baan and facilities created by teachers and students from the Faculty of Architecture of the China Academy of Arts and the Faculty of Architecture and Design at the University of São José de Macau.
According to the IC, the exhibition is divided into four “parallel worlds”: “the deep space of the historical city; the hotel architecture that embodies the merger between East and West; the geometric order of the modern city, representing its vibrant development; and the future projection of a digitized and intangible city that defines an innovative vision to Macau”.
"Four mirrors reflect the fact that Macau keeps their cultural roots in the midst of globalization, while embracing the future with an open attitude," the body stresses.
Through aerial photography and a unique perspective, Iwan Baan sought to show the relationship between architecture, the urban landscape and the natural environment of Macau. Young people from the Colleges of the Academy of Arts of China and the University of São José conceived several creative facilities that provide ideas regarding the future development of Macao's urban architecture.
In speaking at the opening ceremony of the exhibition, IC president Leong Wai Man, stressed that Macau has been a bridge between China and the West for several centuries and a center of cultural exchange. "The world cultural heritage focused on the historic center of Macau and the modern buildings spread throughout the city show the harmony between the past and the present, constituting a vivid representation of the integration of Chinese and Western cultures. This exhibition reflects exactly the precious cultural content of Macau," he said, according to the IC statement.
Organized by the Cultural Institute and executed by the Macau Museum of Art, with the support of MGM, the exhibition “Parallels” will be evident until November 23 this year at Arsenale, Campo Della Tana, Castello 2126/A, 30122, in Venice, with free admission. The show ends on Mondays, except holidays.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Orchestra honors children with songs by Frozen</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/orquestra-homenageia-criancas-musicas-de-frozen/</link><description>The Macao Orchestra will hold the first symphonic concerts in the territory of “Frozen”, Disney animated film, to celebrate World Children's Day. Presented together by the Cultural Institute (IC), Macau and MGM Orchestra Society, the concerts will take place on May 31 (20:00) and June 1 (15:00) at the MGM Cotai Theater.
“This charming and fantastic concert will combine live symphonic music with skull technology, taking adult children and friends from Macau to the magician cold world,” said the IC, adding that the orchestra will play several iconic songs from the “Frozen” soundtrack, synchronized with images projected on a 900-square-meter ultra-hd screen, installed in theater, installed in the theater, installed in the theater with the 19.1 Channel L-Sound System.
“This fusion of sound and image will create an immersive experience that transports viewers to a fascinating kingdom of ice and snow. With the excellence of international level and audiovisual equipment, the MGM Theater was officially recognized by Disney as a space to perform Disney concerts in Macao and this year is hosting another spectacular production of Disney,” says the same note.
The concert will feature the participation of “top” musicians and singers from Macao and abroad. Under the direction of the assistant conductor of the Macau Orchestra, Tony Cheng-Te Ye, the songs of the animation will be played by the orchestra and several international renowned singers, such as Alyssa Fox, who played Elsa in the American tour of the Broadway musical “Frozen”, Ray Liu, who folds and sings Anna's voice in the Mandarin version, RJ Woessner, who gives life to life to life Characters Kristoff and Hans E, CJ Tan as Olaf, as well as the vocal group Semiscon Vocal Band.
“Frozen” premiered in 2013 and won the Oscar for Best Animation Movie. Its soundtrack, especially the theme “Let It Go”-has become a global phenomenon, notes the IC, adding that songs like “Do You Want to Build to Snowman?” and “For the First Time in Forever” also captivated audiences of all ages. “Let It Go” raised Oscar for best original song at the 86th edition of the Academy Awards and three important awards at the 57th edition of the “Grammy Awards”.
This concert will have a duration of approximately two hours, including interval, and tickets are now available on Macauticket, priced between 300 and 600 patacas.
The 2024-25 season of the Macao Orchestra is organized by the IC, the Macao Orchestra Society and the six game operators, with the support of Boc Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Lisboa Palace opened art gallery</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/grand-lisboa-palace-abriu-galeria-de-arte/</link><description>The Grand Lisbon Palace Art Gallery ”was inaugurated with the exhibition“ The Lisbon, Stories of Macau ”. With this space at Grand Lisboa Palace, SJM opens a new chapter in promoting the city's history and heritage



















SJM Resorts (SJM) has inaugurated a new creative space to “boost the development of Macao's cultural landscape and celebrate the contemporary artistic expression”. The Grand Lisbon Palace Art Gallery ”features the inaugural exhibition“ The Lisbon, Stories of Macau ”, on the second floor of the Cotai resort, in a tribute“ to the rich Cultural Tapestry of Macao ”, which has been“ shaped by centuries of exchange ”between the West and the East, according to the SJM statement.
The exhibition focuses on the folkloric traditions, urban narratives and the historical landmarks of the city of the last 500 years, presenting “a dynamic and multidimensional portrait” of Macau. The public can visit different times of the city's past through models, rare artifacts, virtual projections, simulated street landscapes and interactive technologies.
By combining heritage with technology, this show presents a “captivating trip” that highlights “the heat and humanity” of the population of Macao. The exhibition begins with a panoramic film that traces the history of the city, from its origins as one of the first commercial ports of the Ming Dynasty, passing through the period of Portuguese administration, to the return of territory to China.
In the main hall, visitors are welcomed by a gold-boat of wooden and later guided by eight thematic zones, which represent different facets of the past, present and future of Macao. The different spaces include the Kun Iam Temple, the Lisbon Hotel, the Dom Pedro V Theater, the Tap Seac, the Ruins of Sao Paulo, the Garden House, the A-Má Temple and the San Ma Lo.
The main exhibition area integrates an interactive map with information about more than 30 iconic milestones from Macau and 50 fascinating and less known stories of the city.
The gallery will also present the space “The Lisboa Collection”, with the exhibition “Chinese Treaster: Qing Dynasty Court Art”. On display will be artifacts that “offer a glimpse of the splendor of the art of Qing dynasty and the old Chinese culture”, such as an imperial throne of Emperor Kangxi, a “finely glazed” egg peel bowl and an “intricately sculpted” jade censer.
The experience will culminate in a “breathtaking end,” says SJM. The New Gallery also includes a souvenir and design products store created in collaboration with local independent local artists and creative brands, which will allow visitors to bring with them “a piece of Macao's cultural memory”.
The Grand Lisboa Palace Gallery also includes a space dedicated to art and creation, “open to artists and cultural organizations” from around the world, which will serve “as a vital platform for local cultural education and artistic development”.
During the inauguration ceremony, SJM administrator Daisy Ho said the company's “personifies the commitment” gallery to “shape tourism with cultural activities” and that the inaugural exhibition created an inclusive cultural platform that “strengthens the public's connection to the city's heritage”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Study shows that children remember more than believed</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/estudo-mostra-criancas-lembram-se-de-mais-coisas-se-acreditava/</link><description>The early years of humans are a period of rapid learning, but we are not usually able to remind us of specific experiences of this time, a phenomenon known as children's amnesia. A new study published last week in the prestigious scientific journal Science challenges assumptions about child memory, demonstrating that the minds of young people are able to form memories.
“I've always been fascinated by this mysterious emptiness in our personal history,” Nick Turk-Bowne, professor of Psychology in Yale and lead author of the study, told AFP.
Around a year of age, children become extraordinary apprentices: they acquire language, walk, recognize objects, understand social bonds and more.
"However, we do not remember any of these experiences, as there is a kind of maladjustment between this incredible plasticity and our learning capacity," he said.
Sigmund Freud, founder of psychoanalysis, suggested the hypothesis that the first memories are repressed, although since then science has largely discarded the idea of ​​an active suppression process. Modern theories focus on the hippocampus, an area of ​​the crucial brain for episodic memory, which does not develop completely in childhood.
Turk-browne was intrigued by the previous behavioral studies clues. Since babies cannot verbally communicate the memories before acquiring language, their tendency to observe family objects longer gave it important clues.
So far, combining the observations of young children with brain images has been out of reach, as babies are known poorly cooperative when it comes to being quiet inside a functional magnetic resonance imaging (FMRI), the device that tracks blood flow to “see” brain activity.
To overcome this challenge, the Turk-Bowne team has used methods that their lab has perfected over the years: working with families to incorporate animal pacifiers, blankets and pussy; Keep babies stable with pillows so they don't move; and use background psychoadelic patterns to attach your attention.
The inevitable movement, however, produced blurred images that had to be discarded, but the team solved the problem through hundreds of sessions.
In total, 26 babies participated in the experience (half of being under one year and the other half, larger). They had the brain scanned during a memory task, an adult study exercise adapted to them.
First, they showed babies, images of faces, scenes and objects. Then, after seeing other images, one showed one they had seen before with a new one.
“We quantified the time they looked at what they had seen and this is a measure of their memory for this image,” explained Turk-Bowne.
By comparing brain activity during the successful formation of memories with forgotten images, researchers confirmed that the hippocampus actively participates in memory coding from an early age. This was seen in 11 of 13 babies over a year, but not in the smallest.
They also found that babies with better performance in memory tasks have had a greater activity in the hippocampus.
"We can accurately conclude that babies have the ability to coding episodic memories in the hippocampus since approximately one year of age," said Turk-Bowne.
"The ingenuity of your experimental approach should not be underestimated," wrote researchers Adam Ramsaran and Paul Frankland in an editorial of the famous Science magazine.
But what follows unanswered is what happens to these remote memories. They may never completely consolidate themselves in the long run or maybe they persist, but become inaccessible.
Turk-browne suspects in the second hypothesis and is now in charge of a new study that evaluates whether babies and young children can recognize recorded music videos from their own perspective when they were babies.
The first provisional results suggest that these memories may persist until about three years before they disappear. Turk-browne is said to be intrigued especially with the possibility that these fragments can be reactivated someday in later stages of life.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>