<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Inquiry reveals the inaction of residents in the preparation of the reform</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inquerito-revela-inaccao-dos-residentes-na-preparacao-da-reforma/</link><description>Residents of Macao aged 45 or older are below the interior of China with regard to the preparation for the reform, concluded an inquiry from the coordinating office of social services Sheng Kung Hui. In addition to some inction of this issue overall, the inquiry reveals that the “level of savings sufficiency for reform” is lower, with only 3.92 points on a scale from zero to 10
 
An inquiry carried out by the Coordinating Office of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui Macau reveals some inaction from residents in the preparation of post-reform life. The interviewees registered an average of 5.45 points, on a scale from zero to 10, in the “Reform Preparation Index”. The score in this parameter was slightly lower than 5.53 points obtained from a group of residents from the interior of China.
According to the association, the results reflect that the respondents “had already thought, but have not yet put into practice” the organization of that period of life. Note that valid responses of 786 residents aged 45 years were collected.
Although residents on their way to retirement “be aware of the importance and responsibility of finances to that time in life, they have not taken enough practical actions to prepare retirement,” says the investigation. Specifically, from a scale from zero to 10, respondents obtained 7.62 points regarding the “degree of knowledge of financial planning” and 7.05 points regarding “consciousness for responsibilities in reform”.
However, as regards the “degree of completion of the retirement plan” and the “level of savings sufficiency for reform”, respondents were evaluated with only 4.28 and 3.92 points, respectively.
On the other hand, about 32% of listened residents do not exercise sufficient exercise, while 66% predicted that they would not be able to fulfill housework after reform. In addition, for about 31% of respondents, it is possible that their reform lives will be “even more boring” than now.
In the health scope, the study reveals that 70% of respondents consider that “medicine/insurance” will constitute one of the main sources of expenses after retirement. On the other hand, about 19% need to be accompanied at the mental health level.
Another conclusion of the study “Preparation of Macao residents for reform and happiness index in reform life 2024” is that 25.7% of respondents said they will consider Zhuhai as a place to live after reform, while 21.7% will consider other cities in the interior of China in this regard.
The association expects more companies, financial institutions and social groups to be encouraged by the government to provide consultations and advice on retirement planning, so that the most residents, especially young people who are working, can gain greater awareness to the importance of preparing for reform life.
 
30% have already felt a high degree of loneliness
On the other hand, the Coordinating Office of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui Macau also released the results of the “Balance Sheet Study and Perspectives for the 'Friendly City of the Elderly'”, performed annually since 2020, and for which 1,500 elderly people were heard. According to this inquiry, 30% of the elderly listened to “had already felt a high degree of loneliness”; Regarding the use rate of "smartphones" among local elderly, it increased from 50% to 91.2%, between 2020 and 2023.
According to the association, in general, respondents have "positive opinions" regarding the "degree of the city friendly of the elderly" in relation to Macau in the aspects of transport and travel, housing and space and outdoor buildings. In conclusion, the Coordinating Office of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui suggested that it is constantly reinforced the sensitization of the public for the concept of the “friendly city of the elderly”, and at the same time forming more professional cadres in services for the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Universal Health Coverage” praised by WHO</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cobertura-universal-de-saude-elogiada-pela-oms/</link><description>The work done by MSAR for “Universal Health Coverage” was praised by WHO, along with the issue of vaccination and promotion in the area of ​​health
 
The director of the region for the Pacific-West World Health Organization (WHO), Ma'u Piukala Skirt, and the Executive Director of the Planning and Management Department, Liu Yue, met the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, and the Director of Health Services (SSM), Alvis Lo, among other elements. In the Colloquium, and according to a statement, Saia Ma'u Piukala “praised the results obtained in the development of the health sector” of the territory.
In concrete, he considered that "Macau has been doing a good job of carrying out the goal of" Universal Health Coverage ", with a relatively high health protection level for residents." On the other hand, he also stressed that vaccination work "has obtained remarkable results." In this context, he stated that a “comprehensive vaccination program was established that includes several common diseases,“ which significantly reduced the incidence of communicable diseases, thus protecting the health of residents ”.
It is not known if MA'U Piukala came out addressed the issue of non -resident workers, who do not have the same health benefits as residents. At least in the SSM statement, nothing is said about it.
Regarding health promotion work, through various plans and programs, “it has been promoted comprehensively, together with all parties involved, a healthy lifestyle, raising the general health level of the population, which provides valuable experiences for regional health,” said the same WHO. Alongside this, the creation of the WHO traditional medical cooperation center in the MSAR “constitutes a broad platform for the development and exchange of traditional medicine, promoting international cooperation”.
The Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, in turn, said that the Government of MSAR and WHO has been maintaining a relationship of narrow cooperation over the years. For example, Lam noted that, in articulation with the “General Planning of the Planning of“ Healthy China ”, Macau elaborated the“ Healthy Macao Action Plan ”, integrating health elements in all public policies.
This year, the “Healthy Community” program will be launched, together with the “Healthy Company”, “Healthy Building” and “Healthy School” programs, among others, to strengthen the government's interdepartal cooperation, develop synergies in collaboration with associations and institutions, and promote a healthy lifestyle.
Lam also recalled that Macau became in a region of the Pacific-West polio without polio, eliminating measles and rubella, controlling hepatitis B infection in children, "fully demonstrating the effectiveness of the government of masters in the elevation of the global level of public health."
In the Colloquium, the representatives of the SSM presented the Macao Health System and the situation of cooperation with WHO. Remembered, for example, that in 2024 Macau attended 16 online and face-to-face meetings of the WHO Pacific-West Region, covering topics such as universal health coverage, primary health care, smoking control, antibiotic resistance and vaccination. In turn, the Kiang Wu Hospital representative shared the results of the work in promoting the development of traditional Chinese medicine.
During the Colloquium, participants discussed with Ma'u Piukala skirt and their delegation on the reinforcement of cooperation, including the sharing of experiences and the exchange of opinions in the areas of traditional medicine, primary health care, public health, among others. “Everyone agreed to work together to further contribute to the improvement of public health level in the region,” he can read.
Present were also the director of the Department of General Affairs of the Commissioner of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Popular Republic of China in the MSAR, Guo Xiaofeng, as well as the department of the General Division of the Department of Propaganda and Culture of the Central Government Conduct Cabinet on the Central Government, Liu Rui.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Stable” economy but wrapped in uncertainties</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-estavel-mas-envolta-em-incertezas/</link><description>Although Macao's economy remains “stable” in the first quarter, the economic association believes performance “could be slightly weaker than expected”. It also foresees that, between March and May, a series of uncertainties - external and internal - may affect Macau
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Macao's global economic perspectives “remain stable,” however, the performance of several indicators “remains inconsistent,” the Macao Economic Association pointed out in the last report on trends in the territory. In concrete, it provides that, between March and May, the index of the perspectives of the local economy remains between 6.4 and 6.6 points.
The association believes that "economic performance in the first quarter may be slightly weaker than expected" and warns that "carefully analyzing future trends".
First of all, Macao's current external conjuncture "is quite complicated and severe, still facing many uncertainties"-in addition to the US-applied commercial tariffs, there is the softening of China's economic growth and the weakening of Renminbi, factors in which Macau, "as a small economy, can hardly remain isolated." In addition, the opening of casinos in neighboring regions “also brought some competition” to the MSAR, he notes.
According to preliminary estimates, gross game revenues in the first nine days of March were approximately 5.75 billion patacas, with a daily average of 639 million. Citing recent casinic revenue forecasts this month, which may be between 19 billion and 20 million patacas, the Association emphasizes that, to happen, the results of the game in the first quarter “will not be able to achieve the goal of budgetary revenues” announced by the government late last year, a monthly average of 20 billion.
On the other hand, "consumer habits and the standards of the continent's tourists have also changed, and their purchasing power decreased, especially the demand for luxury goods and top marks." In this sense, the association states that "the local retailer sector faces unprecedented challenges and many traders have lamented the difficulty in doing business." For this reason, "they may have to be prudent in their assessment of future economic perspectives."
In an analysis in the early months of the year, the Economic Association indicates that the trust of investors and consumers "remains low due to economic uncertainty." Although the number of visitors and the hotel occupancy rate are at a good level, "per capita purchase power has decreased." To illustrate the scenario, it recalls that retail annual sales last year fell 14.9% over the previous year.
Alongside this, "due to a number of complex internal and external factors, internal loan demand was weak," with the association that the ratio between loans and deposits from local banks continued to fall to 78.5% and the Malparado credit ratio increased to 5.68%, "reflecting the challenges faced by the bank sector."
It is recalled that debt loans not paid by small and medium-sized companies ciphed at 4.87 billion patacas at the end of 2024, noting an increase of 67% or 1.95 billion within one year. They thus completed a cycle of two years of consecutive climbs. As this newspaper has already reported, official data show that liquidation debts grew 29.4 times, or 4.70 billion patacas, compared to the end of 2019.
The latest official data indicate that MSAR Gross Domestic Product (GDP) increased by 8.8% in 2024, in annual and real terms, falling short of government projections and the International Monetary Fund (IMF). Calculated at current prices, the value of GDP was 403.3 billion patacas last year, corresponding to 86.4% of the volume of 2019, ie, before the pandemic, according to the direction of statistics and census services.
In the last three months of last year, homologous growth has reached only 3.4%, reflecting the fifth consecutive quarterly deceleration.
In October, the IMF estimated that the economy of Macao could grow 7.3% by 2025, thus reviewing the previous projection, which pointed to an increase of 9.6%. On the other hand, the forecast on the rise in 2029 remained in 3.0%.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey Club cats have to be hosted until March 25</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gatos-jockey-club-tem-de-ser-acolhidos-ate-25-de-marco/</link><description>More than 80 stray cats that Jockey Club had been sheltering in its facilities will be in Macao, contrary to the initial intention of transferring the felines to a shelter in Zhuhai. The “Volt-Faca” was possible thanks to a sealed agreement between Anima, the Horse Race Company and the Institute for Municipal Affairs. Several animal protection groups in the territory have already received 60 cats. The rest will have to be collected until March 25th. A first adoption campaign took place yesterday and eight animals already have host families
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The disclosure of news from the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) on the follow -up that has given the transfer and accommodation of all animals in the Jockey Club field, has released the warning about the situation of more than 80 stray cats on the land of the Macao Horse Race Company. Quickly the news came to the public and the animal protection groups, specifically to the Macao Animal Protective Society (Anima), which, through an agreement with AMI and the horses' running company, prevents cats from being transferred to Zhuhai, as was the initial intention of the Jockey Club after the presentation of an AMI plan.
According to the Tribuna de Macau newspaper, the president of the animal executive committee, "the 83 cats under the care of the Jockey Club will have to be collected by animal protection organizations, or adopted, until March 25, otherwise they have to be effectively sent to the continent."
Zoe Tang is hoping that this transfer does not happen, "but it is necessary, on the one hand, that cats are received in the shelters of Macao's animal protection groups, and, on the other, that may be adopted by people, which would be ideal."
The leader stresses that 60 felines are already in shelters of organizations that are dedicated to welcoming and protecting animals, so that they remain. “I hope that those missing can quickly find a shelter or a family,” says Anima's guardian.
However, the first adoption campaign was held yesterday, which registered 15 procedures of intent, culminating with the effective adoption of eight cats. “We now have to see what results will emerge from these actions, but we will probably have to organize another campaign next weekend,” noted Zoe Tang.
De salientar que todos os 83 gatos foram sujeitos a esterilização, da responsabilidade do Jockey Club, uma vez que o plano estaria prestes a ser cumprido, ou seja, o envio dos animais para Zhuhai. AMI underlines being “satisfied” with the sterilization of animals and the measures taken, “taking into account their welfare”.
Recently, AMI has proceeded to the health inspection of these cats, including the introduction of microchips, anti-rabies and clinical examination, and declared that it would issue the necessary sanitary documents for the border passage of exported cats, in strict compliance with national provisions, and providing all support.
On the afternoon of Friday, the first transfer was scheduled, which would include 30 animals, a situation that eventually did not happen due to the intervention of Anima, which feared for animal safety.
In view of the agreement, AMI has returned back in the decision, but established the period of 25 March so that the anima and the remaining protection groups can solve the reception problem.
Zoe Tang took the initiative, along with the Jockey Club, to contact local counterparts, which agreed to receive cats. They are, in addition to the anima, which collected 20 feline, “Cats and Dogs Guardian Angel Association” (seven), animal shelter (three), abandoned animal protection association of Macau (20) and “Catfee” (10).
In the past, the Jockey Club had promoted adoption campaigns, but "some did not result due to the difficulty of adapting cats to a home environment and also due to health or behavioral reasons," the company said, adding that Zhuhai's reallation plan "served only as a contingency - developed in consultation with AMI."
The former horse racing operator stressed that "these measures would be in accordance with the regulations of both governments." In addition, he asserted, the shelter for cats in Zhuhai would fulfill the required rules and employ professionals to take care of the animals.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kenyans beat records in the 10km race</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quenianos-batem-recordes-na-corrida-dos-10km/</link><description>For the third consecutive year, the athletes representing Kenya won the macao's 10km international race, obtaining record times, in both male and female. Vincent Kibet and Betty Sigei won the individual titles. 7,000 foundists participated in the main race and 3,000 in “Fun Run”



















Victor Rebelo
 
A large contingent of Athletes from Kenya participated this year in the 10km road race in Macao and hit all the competition, both in the men's and female category. In the competition of men, the superiority of Kenyans is well mirrored in the classification of the first 20, with 17 founders of that African country.
In the general individual, the title of this year's edition was the Vincent Kibet Lagat, with a time of 28 minutes and 08 seconds, only faster 11 hundredths of second than the main rival, Ethiopian Teresa Nyakola Gera. The third position was reached by Kenyan Harrison Wanjiru.
In women, Kenya also dominated, occupying the first five posts. The victory was by Betty Sigei, with the mark of 31.23, against 31.34 of the second, Cintia Chepngeno. In the final position of the podium, Daisilah Jerono was positioned (31.46).
In both categories were beaten the records of the MSAR competition, which were on 29.02 and 33.53, respectively in male and female.
With the new maximums obtained, the winners of each of the classes have loved a $ 15,000 monetary check (about 120,000 patacas), to which they add 10,000 (close to 80,000 patacas) as a victory award.
Thus, in this trip to Macau to run less than half an hour on the city roads, the champions take a check of about 200,000 patacas in their backs.
The first non-African in the men's test was a representative of Macau, Kun Wang, with the time of 31.27. In women, the Chinese Qing Zhu ended in the twelfth position, while Hoi Long met as the best of sinters in tenth eighth with 38.42.
This year's race has again departed at Praça do Lago Sai Van, where the 10,000 registered athletes were concentrated, representing more than two dozen countries or regions, divided by the main race (7,000 foundists) and Fun Run (3,000), close to six kilometers long.
Participants of the 10km International Race, organized by the Sports Institute, Sands China and the Macao General Athletics Association, started at 7 am, while the competitors of the fun competition departed 45 minutes later, before a temperature of 15 degrees Celsius and a relative humidity around 60%.
In both races, the arrival site was the Olympic Sports Center, commonly assigned to Taipa stadium, after a route that passed the SAI Van bridge and the Cotai strip.
The 10km International Race premiered in 2021, in the middle of pandemic, and at that time having only local athletes and the continent. In 2022, the athletics event was canceled, returning in 2023 and already attended by foreign athletes, with emphasis on Africans and especially the Kenyans, who have won all the titles in the last three years.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sensitized game industry for the “green revolution”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/industria-jogo-sensibilizada-para-revolucao-verde/</link><description>Macao Polytechnic University organized a symposium on green development and leisure industry, which was attended by representatives of six casinos operators
 
Responsible for the six integrated casinos and resort operators, game equipment suppliers and International Macau Exchange of limited carbon emissions, as well as students and teachers at Macao Polytechnic University (UPM), participated in a symposium on global carbon neutrality trends and ex -compliance - acronym used for environmental, social and governance practices - in the international game industry. Organized by the UPM Pedagogical and Scientific Center in the Game and Tourism (CJT), the initiative was part of the United Nations Sustainable Development Objectives and aimed to “promote the green and low carbon development of Macao Tourism”.
According to a UPM statement, Shi Yun and Hu Jiyuan, a guest vice president and researcher at the Macao Association of Development and Financial Technology, respectively, addressed the “relationship between global carbon emissions reduction trends and the tourism and leisure industries, as well as the beginning of a green revolution” in this sector in the territory. The speakers also dialogued with participants about the context of carbon neutrality worldwide, the national strategy of the “double carbon target” and 60 and the impact of environmental policies on listed companies, among other relevant topics.
In turn, Wang Changbin, coordinator of the CJT, said the symposium "stimulated the exchange between the academic community and the sector." For the academic, “the green transformation of the Macao tourism and leisure industry” will contribute to elevating the “international competitiveness” of the territory and achieving the objective of emissions peak and carbon neutrality.
The CJT promises to continue to conduct studies related to UN objectives and cooperate with sectors to jointly boost the sustainable low carbon development of the Macao tourism and leisure industry.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Discussed “optimization” of services for the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/discutida-optimizacao-de-servicos-para-idosos/</link><description>Authorities recently discussed the “optimization of medical services for the elderly” and the guidelines for collaboration between public and private entities in health care for the elderly. They also addressed the plan to expand the pilot projects of teleconsulting services for the elderly
 
Given the aging of the population and increasing health care needs, health services (SSM) have continually invested in the “Prevention, Treatment and Rehabilitation Services Chain through the provision of specialized medical services, community health care and proximity medical services”, said the president of the body, Alvis LO, at the last plenary meeting of the Council for medical affairs.
The meeting focused on the “optimization of medical services for the elderly” and the “directions of collaboration between public and private health institutions”.
The SSM leader, who chairs the Council for Medical Affairs, also stressed the need to reinforce interdepartal cooperation, to encourage associations to participate and implement policies and measures for the elderly, in favor of a “happy macao”.
The head of the Elderly Services Division of the Institute of Social Action (IAS), Kam Kit Leng, hopes that the reinforcement of health and social assistance cooperation will continue and to prioritize the development of Big Health technology and industry for a friendly and inclusive environment for the elderly, can be read in the statement.
In the same vein, the SSM elderly subject group plans to increase the elderly for the elderly for the health of the “Healthy Macao Macao Action Plan” and launch a drug integration plan. Group head, Pun Weng Hong, has presented a work plan that aims to optimize medical services to the elderly, widen and deepen existing services, explore cooperation between interdepportional, non -profit and private medical institutions, and professional associations and at the same time help the development of the medical service industry intended for the elderly.
At the meeting, a reference was made to the projections of statistical and census services (2022-2041), according to which the elderly group should represent 21.4% of the population, making the region in a “super-aged society”.
In turn, the head of the IAS Department of Social Solidarity, Choi Sio Un, highlighted the attention given to the policy of providing the elderly and children by the government. Given the conclusion, soon of the “Decenal Action Plan for the Support Services for the Elderly 2016-2025”, Choi Sio Un said that the preparatory work of the next phase has already been started.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Soho Residence has finally use license</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/soho-residence-tem-finalmente-licenca-de-utilizacao/</link><description>Soho Residence, next to Sin Fong Garden, finally received green light in the process of inspection after the completion of the work, more than 10 years after the start of the contract
 
More than a decade after the construction of the Soho Residence building, the direction of soil services and urban construction (DSSCU) has now granted the building's occupation license. The project suffered delays due to the connection with the Sin Fong Garden controversy.
With 27 floors and 126 fractions, Soho Residence is a luxury venture located next to Sin Fong Garden - a building that had to be rebuilt after structural problems have been detected in 2012, forcing the withdrawal of more than 200 residents. Alongside concerns about the poor quality of the concrete used at Sin Fong Garden, MSar courts considered that the company responsible for Soho Residence was also responsible for structural damage in the neighboring building.
In a statement now issued, DSSCU explains that Soho Residence's work was completed in August 2024 and that in October, the contract was requested. During the on -site lawsuit, members of the survey committee detected “disabilities”, so the contractor was required to follow up these gaps.
For the survey to be approved, the contractor delivered a change project in December. However, after the project's appreciation, "DSSCU considered that it was still necessary to follow up on various aspects." Thus, the contractor later handed over to the body a new change project.
"After the contractor has followed the aspects pointed out and verified that it was fulfilled to that required by the competent services in the survey, DSSCU approved on March 12 the issuance of the respective license of use," read the press release. The license will be issued at most until tomorrow.
After having the license at hand, the contractor may start selling the autonomous fractions and requesting the issuance of the certificate of completion of the work, he says.
DSSCU stresses that the work survey is “an important stage of building the building”, which aims to safeguard the rights and interests of residents and consumers. "The contractor has an obligation to fulfill the opinions of public services, following and effectively correcting the deficiencies pointed out, in order to obtain the respective license as soon as possible," he adds.
The organism also states that in recent years it has “progressively introduced” several improvements in the work circuit, in order to increase the effectiveness of project appreciation and, in harmony with the entry into force of the urban construction legal regime, “simplify the various procedures, from the project delivery phase to the completed works inspection phase, with a view to facilitating residents and construction sector in the treatment of formalities”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>First Aid for safer tourism</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/primeiros-socorros-para-um-turismo-mais-seguro/</link><description>In collaboration with the Red Cross of Macao, Tourism Services (STD) organized a first aid seminar for the front line workers of the tourist sector. STD has sought to “reinforce the trust and ability of tourist industry workers to respond to life emergencies” and promote “first aid education,” according to a statement.
The seminar addressed issues such as the basic principles of first aid, the treatment of burns and scalps, medical emergencies such as heat blows and cardiorespiratory stops and the use of automatic external defibrillator, among others. Wong Ka Keong, Red Cross First Aid instructor, was responsible for demonstrating the techniques to more than 400 participants.
When speaking at the event, STD Substitute Director Cheng Wai Tong predicted that the number of tourists who will visit the MSAR this year exceeds the 35 million accounted for in 2024, "so the safety of visitors in Macao also grows in importance." In this context, the body expects “tour operators to reinforce safety and emergency response awareness” and help offer “a safe and quiet tourist environment” to those visiting the territory.
STD intends to continue to “organize different types of training courses, workshops and seminars for tourist operators”, in close cooperation with training institutions. It also reiterates that it will continue to support and encourage the Macao tourist sector to “continually raise the quality of services, enrich offers as a world center of tourism and leisure and promote sustainable and high quality development in the local tourist industry”.
In addition to Cheng and Wong, the president of the Central Council of the Red Cross of Macao, Eddie Wong, the president of the Macao Red Cross, Chum Pak Tak, representatives of the support entities of the quality tourism assessment program and tour operators. The organization of the seminar was supported by the Consumer Council, the University of Tourism of Macao and various associations.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Elite League moves to the mud in April</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/liga-de-elite-muda-se-para-taipa-em-abril/</link><description>Macao's main soccer championship, the Elite League, returns to the Taipa stadium in early April, after the first five journeys were held at the Canidromo field. The period of maintenance of the grass in the main amphitheater of the "king sport" of the MSA has come to an end, thus allowing the 1st division to be played there in the early days of next month
 
Every year, at the beginning of each season, around the end of February, the Macao Football Association (AFM) needs to “divert” the championship to the Canidrome field, due to the mandatory period of maintenance and rest of the Natural Lawn of Taipa.
The time when it already took place was no exception and so the first five days took place on the peninsula, in the field of the canhy, with several inconvenience, both for the viewers and the teams. From April, but still with no date set, although everything points to the 4th, Friday, the Elite League returns to its favorite place, whose grass will certainly be in better condition than for about two months in the Canidromo field.
Confirmation of the change was given to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao by Chan Ka Chong, AFM leader.
With a larger field and with conditions far superior to the canhy, especially for viewers, the Olympic Sports Center, commonly known as Taipa Stadium, will host the remaining rounds of the first phase of the race, in system of all subsidiaries, probably on the weekends, Friday, Saturday and Sunday, unlike here, since the challenges took place half the week.
Then there will be a two-lap mini-championship for the champion's determination, where the top five will be, and another group, of the remaining five positioned, in the fight for permanence.
At this point, the Elite League is led, with some surprise, by the University of Macau, which has not yet wasted anywhere in the four meetings held. The young people oriented by Luís Amorim opened the championship with a win over the current champion, Benfica, 3-1, heading 2-0 to the gala, 5-1 to Lun Lok and 9-0 to Sporting.
In second position is the formation of Must IPO, with 10 points, having recorded a draw at two goals compared to the Ching Fung. Following are Benfica (9), Ching Fung (8), Gala (7), Chiba and Hang Sai (3) and Lun Lok and Sporting (0).
The ultimate round to be made in the field of the canhy, before the move to the mud, will take place between March 26 and 28, presenting as “strong dishes” the University of Macau-Ching Fung and Must Ipo-Shao Jiang.
This week the Elite League suffers an interregnum, due to the participation of the mashed selection in a friendly game against Hong Kong. The meeting will take place at Raehk, at Mong Kok Stadium, at 20h00 next Wednesday, the day after tomorrow. It will be the first major test of the team now oriented by Kenneth Kwok, who in late last year replaced Luso-Angolano Lázaro Oliveira.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy concert cycle excels in diversity</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ciclo-de-concertos-da-galaxy-prima-pela-diversidade/</link><description>A show of Andrea Bocelli and a stage of singer Wakin Chau's world tour are some of the concerts that Galaxy promotes in the coming months in Macao. Three enclosures will receive renowned artists, including Jisoo, K-Pop singer and member of Blackpink, as well as Kim Jaejoong and the bands Hyukoh, from South Korea, and Thailand Gemini Fourth. Several of the concerts are scheduled for the second half of March
 
A diverse program of musical shows with renowned artists from the region, but also from abroad, promoted by Galaxy Entertainment in its three rooms, arena, Broadway Theater and G Box, will fill several weekends of the coming months. Some concerts are scheduled for this month.
On the 21st and 22nd, at 20h00 at the Galaxy Arena, he will act Jisoo, considered an international sensation of K-Pop, a member of the Blackpint, which performs his first Asian solo Asian tour. Tickets are already on sale.
Jisoo recently released the “Amortage” mini-album with the song “Eartquake” reaching first place in Billboard's worldwide digital sales table. The album also dominated the iTunes list in 45 countries and secured first place in the comprehensive K-pop graphic of Tencent Music in China.
Also on the 22nd, at 17h00, and the next day, at 16h00, the Broadway Theater will host the singer, songwriter and South Korean actor Kim Jaejoong, "The Perfect Man of Barbie", at the J-Party "Home" concert.
On March 29, at the Galaxy Arena, Andrea Bocelli fans will have the opportunity to listen to the famous Italian tenor, who returns to Macau almost nine years after the opening of Wynn Palace in August 2016. Bocelli will perform on stage next to his son, Matteo, for a special duet, in a “show” that will be “simultaneously” Intimate and grandiose, ”says the Galaxy.
On the same day 29, at 5 pm, but at Broadway Theater, the audience can watch the show of the South Korean band Hyukoh, along with Taiwan Sunset Rollercoaster artist. This is a protagonist of pop synthesizer, also called Tecnopop, subgenre of the song “New Have” that became prominent in the late 1970s, presenting the use of the synthesizer keyboard as a dominant musical instrument.
On March 30, at 12:00 pm, again on Broadway, the Gemini Fourth, the new generation of Thailand idols.
At the Galaxy music events plan, more shows are scheduled for May, such as the one that will be starred by the pop wakin chau icon, which will bring its world tour for the first time. Stage design promises to have great innovations, intertwining modern martial arts with music scenes, giving the feeling of watching two concerts at the same time. Wakin will play successes such as "Rain or Shine", "Sleepless Nights" and "Friends."
Also in May will be the artist of Taiwan Hsiao Chu, known as show Lo, who debuted in 1996 as a member of the Four Heavenly Kings. The concept of tour is "Amusement Park", which symbolizes its original 30 -year -old aspiration since its debut - "spread joy and happiness." The best known songs of show LO include “Showtime”, “Dance Gate”, “Love Corner”, among others.
Tickets are now available for these two concerts at the Galaxy Arena.
In June, concert lovers will enjoy “Jacky Cheung 60+” with the legendary “god of songs” of the Chinese music scene to hold their 10th solo shows in 2025. Tickets will be put for sale tomorrow.
Another musical event, still without a date, is the “Johnson Lee’s All - Comedy &amp; Music Extravaganza 2.0 at G Box, which will come to the second time to the territory,“ providing an unforgettable experience full of laughter and entertainment ”, as the Galaxy stresses the programming of its concerts for the coming months.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Zou Li talent translated into gongbi art pieces</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/talento-de-zou-li-traduzido-em-pecas-de-arte-gongbi/</link><description>The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) inaugurates this Tuesday, at 18:30, the Gongbi art exhibition “Burning Lotus”, by Zou Li, renowned painter with over 50 years of career, whose artistic focus focuses mainly on themes related to the history of Chinese women.



















Until April 5, the artist will present a collection of 30 gongbi art pieces, a traditional technique of fine and delicate brush, about Japanese rice role or silk fabric, and on oriental silk fans. The works in question were executed between 1997 and 2022.
The talent of Zou Li, and the awareness of femininity through its extraordinary artistic expression, are present in the creations “harmonious and moving of the beauty of the body and soul of women,” according to Ung Si Meng, honorary president of the Friendship and Coordination Association of former Macao National Assembly and former members of Macao at the Chinese people's political advisory conference.
“For a long time, to fulfill his social responsibilities and his vocation as a professional painter, Zou Li actively participated in several important historical creations, including the‘ Imperatriz Wu Zetian ’and other major projects, such as the Hundred Chinese Concubinas Collection’. Chinese, ”says Ung Si Meng, who signs the manifesto of this exhibition.
According to a FRC note, Zou Li's work reflects the dimension of his academic and artistic knowledge, which have long attached wide attention in national and international artistic circles. His works have been much appreciated by art galleries, museums, art institutions, public and private, and collectors.
Throughout her career, the artist has created more than a thousand works, now scattered around China and the rest of the world, has carried out more than 50 individual exhibitions, in her country and abroad, and published more than a dozen individual art catalogs. In April 2024, the National Museum of Women and Children from China acquired a collection of 593 pieces of his own.
Zou Li is a member of the China Artists Association, a researcher at the Wenshi Research Hall of the Guangdong Province Government, director of the Guangdong Chinese Painting Institute and Honorary President of the Foshan Artists Association. In addition, he performed the duties of deputy director of the southern branch of the China Central Institute of Culture and History, where he also developed research work.</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MNE Portuguese confirms a visit to China and Mand</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mne-portugues-confirma-visita-a-china-raem/</link><description>Portugal Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel will move to Macau and China at the end of the month, confirmed to Lusa official source.
Earlier this month, TDM indicated the presence of the Portuguese Executive's number two in Macao and China, and was expected to participate in the Boao Forum, which will take place between 25 and 28 March, in Haião province, and contact with Chinese authorities, namely with Foreign Minister Wang Yi. Lusa, a source of Paulo Rangel's office, confirmed the trip at the end of the month, indicating that the travel program is not yet closed.
Macau will receive later this year the celebrations of June 10, which start in lakes, according to the presidency of the Republic, in February, in a note published on its website. “The President of the Republic designated the city of Lagos as headquarters of the celebrations, in 2025, of Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities, extending the celebrations to the Portuguese community in Macao,” reads the text dated 7 February.
According to the same note, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa decided to constitute the organization of the celebrations “a commission chaired by Dr. Lídia Jorge, writer, and who is part of the Chief of Staff of the Armed Forces, the Secretary General of the Presidency of the Republic and the head of the State Protocol”.
In December last year, the head of state had already admitted that his last June 10th of his term-which ends on March 9 next year-to be celebrated with more distant Portuguese emigrant communities such as Asia Pacific, Australia, Macao or Goa. The President of the Republic was at MSAR in 2019, during its state visit to the Popular Republic of China.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong Museum puts Picasso in dialogue with Asian art</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/museu-de-hong-kong-coloca-picasso-em-dialogo-arte-asiatica/</link><description>EPA11960531 Visitors Take pictures of (L-R) 'Seated Woman with Arms Crossed,' 'Portrait of Dora Maar,' and 'Portrait of Nusch Eluard' By Pablo Ruiz Picasso During A Media Preview at the M+ Museum in Hong Kong, China, 13 March, 2025. 'The Hong Kong Jockey Club Series: Picasso for Asia-Conversation,' The Exhibition, Co-Organized by M+ and The Musee National Picasso-Paris, Showcases More Than Sixty Works by the Spanish Artist Picasso Picasso, Exhibited AlongSide Pieces by Asian and Asian-Diansporic Artists.  EPA/Leung Man Hei



More than a century ago, Pablo Picasso transformed the Basilica of Sacré Coeur, Paris, into a web of tangled lines on his screen, deconstructing reality with the brushstrokes of the Cubist master.
In the exhibition that was inaugurated in Hong Kong on Saturday, this painting was shown alongside a more literal way of deconstruction, a drawing with Chinese artist Cai Guo-Qiang as part of an intercultural dialogue.
“Interest in Picasso's life and work has not even diminished, even in Asia,” says Doryung Chong, M+Museum's chief curator and curator.
The exhibition “Picasso to Asia - a conversation” combines more than 60 pieces of the Spanish master borrowed by the Picasso de Paris Museum with 130 works by artists from Asia or Asian diaspora. Organized in collaboration with the Picasso de Paris National Museum, the show features pieces from the M+ Collection for the first time in the region, along with loans from institutions such as the Reina Sofía Museum and private collections.
The highlights include “portrait of a man” from the blue period of Picasso, the sketch of a horse's head to his famous “guernica” and “massacre in the Korea”, an anti-thebe expressionist painting of 1951.
"Picasso's exhibitions tend to be very monographic," said Doryung Chong. “We felt it would be more productive to understand Picasso (…) create these unexpected juxtapositions and dialogues,” he explained.
Cecile Debray, president of the Picasso Museum in Paris, praised the “western decentralized approach”.
It is important to remember that the last great exhibition of the artist's work in Hong Kong had been organized in 2012 and attracted a large audience.
In the last decade, Picasso's reputation was affected by the #Metoo movement and criticism of the abusive treatment he gave to his companions.
"Of course we are very open and honest about the most disturbing aspects of your biography, but we shouldn't let it determine the meaning of your entire career," Doryung Chong argued.
Authorities of this special Chinese administrative region have praised the four -month exhibition and expect this type cultural events to boost the international visibility of Hong Kong, weakened by the repression of mass and often violent democratic protests in 2019.
Since its inauguration at the end of 2021, the M+ Museum has received more than eight million visitors, one of the few successes of the Creative Project of the West Kowloon Cultural District.
Chong underlines that the M+ Museum aims to connect Asian culture with the rest of the world, citing as an example Picasso's exposure alongside Luis Chan, a self -taught painter of Hong Kong.
Luis Chan, who takes much of his Spanish master's inspiration in his works, was part of “an old generation, where formal artistic formation was not possible in Hong Kong”.
“Even so, he was connected to the art world at that time in Paris and a very important figure in that context, Picasso,” says Chong.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>