<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>"Serpent" will put "multiple challenges" and "opportunities" in the destination of Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/serpente-colocara-multiplos-desafios-oportunidades-destino-de-macau/</link><description>Lunar New Year celebrations in Macao, January 23, 2025. It is the main party of Chinese families, equivalent to Christmas in Western countries, and for many workers the breaks and holidays granted on this court constitute the only holidays of the year. (Accompanies text on January 26, 2025). Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro/Lusa



Based on the theory of “Feng Shui”, Mickey Hung foresees that in the year of the serpent (or snake), Macau will face “multiple challenges and opportunities”. Still, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the local master foresees “new solutions” found for Macau in the domains of the game, tourism, economic diversification, construction of the Sino-Lusophone platform, protection of cultural heritage and health. On the other hand, the divine anticipates that the current chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, "will face an even more severe test" this year, including "challenges from the public." In addition, Mickey Hung warns of health problems that can challenge several secretaries in 2025

With the approach of the Lunar New Year, which will be governed by the sign Serpent (or Cobra) in 2025, the Jornal Tribuna de Macau listened to the local Master of “Feng Shui” Mickey Hung, to find out some possibilities related to the fate of the MSAR , based on the theory of “Feng Shui”.
According to Mickey Hung, in the year of the serpent, the “early spring” period begins on February 3, symbolizing the arrival of spring and the beginning of a new year in Macao. However, in the system of “Ba Zi Gan Zhi” (Chinese Numerology used to analyze the nature “yin” or “yang” and the property between the “five elements” of all existences in the world), as the mashes was born in the month of “Zi”, a “star-related star” may appear in the territory in 2025. This “star” will be subject to “a combination that shows a lack of wealth stars”, which “could weaken power of the star of the governmental cause ”. At this point, the master interprets that there will be a "unlucky sign."
“If the star of the governmental cause is shaken, the reputation of government leaders may be impaired. The reputation is crucial for defending wealth and maintaining public trust in the government. If the star of the government cause would be impaired, it would decrease the population's degree of confidence. Thus, instead of depending on government support, the population could prefer to pursue material benefits, ”says Mickey Hung.
According to their predictions, given these challenges brought by the “serpent”, the current government, especially the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, “will face an even more severe test to find a balance between maintaining the government's credibility, reinforcing the public confidence in the authorities and impulse the development of the economy. ” "If the government is able to deal with these challenges effectively, it will be possible that the development of Macao embraces new opportunities over the next five years," says Vivinho.
Still, Mickey Hung considers that, on the other hand, in the theory of "Ba Zi", the combination of the elements related to "early spring" (namely "Yi Si", "Wu Yin", "Gui Mao" and " Gui Hai ”) reflects“ a trend full of dynamism and positivity ”. This is because “Gui, of water, represents vitality and hope; Yi, of wood, symbolizes passion and driving force; Wu, from land, is stability and the base, while yin and hand, of wood, have ascending characteristics, so this combination indicates that Macau will embrace opportunities for economic recovery, especially in the aspects of tourism and of the game industry ”.
In detail, the “Feng Shui” master believes that, under the influence of “snake”, the global economy will record improvements in 2025 and this trend will include the reduction of tourist restrictions around the world. In this context, the Macao Tourism sector will continue to recover its power this year, and the city will be able to receive more tourists from the interior of China and abroad. At the same time, the growth of the tourism sector will directly boost the development of restoration and hospitality, anticipates, clarifying that the combination “Gui mao” will make the Macao game industry “get into transformation, raise the quality of the Service and explore more diverse game options ”to attract young customers.
However, the master warns of increasing challenges for the game sector due to the opening of casinos in Southeast Asia. To reduce impact, Mickey Hung suggests that the local sector "resort to technological means to improve customer experience as well as develop online game platforms to adapt to market modifications."
In addition, it adds that by 2025 the new government will intensify support for science and technology, innovation, medical sector, health maintenance and cultural and creative industries, in order to boost the proper diversification of the economy.
Asked about the “luck” of Macao's development as a sino-illusophone platform, the “Feng Shui” expert reiterates the role of the “Water” element in the theory of “Ba Zi”, which will dominate the “beginning of Spring". From its perspective, the “Gui, of Water” means that Macau, as a bridge between China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP), will record new development opportunities, with the government further strengthening exchange and cooperation With Lusophone countries, boosting mutual integration in the areas of trade, investment and culture.
“Particularly, in the fields of agricultural products, energies and environmental protection, Macao will become an important center for Sino-Misophone trade and give impulse to the joint development of the economy of the two parts. In addition, MSar will actively organize cultural exchange activities between China and Lusophone countries, which will contribute to the increase of citizens' knowledge of the PLP and the reinforcement of friendly relationships between the peoples on both sides ” , anticipates.
Regarding the protection and revitalization of heritage, Mickey Hung points out that, in the year of the serpent, more attention to Macao's intangible cultural heritage will be paid, especially the sectors linked to the activity of guessing the theory of “Feng Shui” or through reading the palm of the hands.
Regarding public health, Mickey Hung points out that with population aging increasingly influenced Macao, health and medical services related to the elderly should be some of the most important subjects for the development of masters in 2025.
In his opinion, in addition to dedicating himself even more to the development of traditional Chinese medicine and the construction of infrastructure in public health, with the aim of ensuring the quality and efficiency of medical services, the Government of MSar will introduce more techniques and advanced medical equipment and reinforce the training of health professionals. Given that medical services are “controlled by the dirt star”, they will generally record improvements, anticipate. It also points out that, at the same time, the authorities will not forget to promote health education, in order to reinforce public awareness and satisfy the growing demand for health residents.
On the other hand, Mickey Hung believes that, in terms of the population's life and well-being, the "serpent" will foster an "economic scenario of greater prosperity." "As more lines of the slight meter go into operation, the resumption of economic activities on the southwest side of Macau will lead to fortune to the Northeast, which will stimulate the prosperity of the economy of the North Zone and create more job opportunities," he says .
At the level of employment, the master predicts that the authorities will strengthen support for young people, providing more training and professional guidance actions, so as to help young places to find a successful job. At the same time, it argues that, in the year of snake, "the government and companies should attribute importance to the guarantee of the well-being of the population, so that the fruits of economic growth can benefit all residents."
In addition, the divine also foreshadows new opportunities for Macau in 2025, derived from the “deepening the construction of the great bay”. In concrete, it predicts that the “serpent” will lead the masters to actively integrate into the great bay and to promote the cooperation and complementarity of resources with neighboring cities.
“In terms of industrial cooperation, Macau will actively explore the industrial connection with Canton, Zhongshan, Shenzhen, among other cities, as well as promote in -depth cooperation in the areas of science and technology, finance and culture, so that more complete industrial chains are formed ”Indicates Mickey Hung.
Alongside this, it provides that the construction of transport infrastructures by the Government of MGA will be reinforced, which “will strengthen the connection between Macao and other cities in the Great Bay, will facilitate the displacement of residents and tourists, and will stimulate even more the dynamism and growth of the economy ”.
Generally speaking, the Master of Feng Shui Prognosis that in 2025 Macau will face “multiple challenges and opportunities”. Still, “Macao will make efforts to find new solutions in the game industry transformation, tourism sector recovery, economic diversification, construction of the Sino-Madphone platform, protection of cultural heritage and health. Actively dealing with the various challenges, Macao could make, in the future, sustainable economic growth and harmonious social development, ”concludes Mickey Hung.
 
Suggested “sources” to increase wealth
Faced with Macao's "challenges and opportunities" brought by the "serpent," Mickey Hung considers that the MSar government may take into account some of their suggestions to be more lucky this year. Warning that in “Feng Shui”, the city's economy is closely related to the “dragon vein” and the roads mean “dragon”, the master defends the maintenance of road fluidity and the shortening of traffic time, with The purpose of improving the emotions of residents and tourists and the luck of mashes itself.
"Therefore, reinforcing the improvement of urban transport and maintaining the fluidity of the roads constitute important responsibilities within the public transport system in 2025," he says.
In addition, it suggests more afforestation facilities and plants in the city, especially in old neighborhoods and sights, as “green plants can strengthen vitality and improve luck”.
On the other hand, as in “Feng Shui” theory the “water” represents fortune, Mickey Hung proposes new water landscapes or sources in the Manduco beach zone, so as to “increase running water elements, thus facilitating the entry of wealth".
 
Wong Sio Chak will be the most blessed
On the other hand, as in recent years, the master has once again analyzed, based on “Feng Shui”, the lucky trends of the Chief Executive and the five secretaries of MSAR. Looking at the new governing team, Mickey Hung points out that, in the theory of “di zhi” (consisting of a total of 12 elements to describe the year, month, day and time), the current leader of MSAR, in its governance, “ It may face challenges from the public, ”since“ there may be four elements of 'd zhi' simultaneously, namely 'Zi', 'Wu', 'Mao' and 'You', which will constitute a concentration of flower stars. of Peach [star related to interpersonal or loving relationships in the theory of “Feng Shui”], a scenario that also reflects the dependence of Macao from tourism and the game ”.
“In addition, according to the theory of facial traits, Sam Hou Fai's face has the shape of the '同' character, with a full forehead and a straight nasal back. These characteristics show that Sam Hou Fai has a stable temperament and good leadership capacity, ”he describes. However, the “Feng Shui” master warns that the chief executive, in his future governance, will have to deal with “multiple challenges” and seek innovative proposals to increase government credibility and promote social harmony and prosperity.
In turn, the Secretary for Administration and Justice “will face a certain work pressure” in 2025, given that André Cheong was born in 1966 and his Chinese sign is horse, “stressed” animal in the work field in the year of Snake. In addition, the divine warns that the “horse” may neglect the management of your health. "Nevertheless, as this secretary belongs to 'land' in the 'five elements', he will be able to effectively conclude his work, performing the orders of the Chief Executive," he continues.
Regarding the new Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP (born in 1968), whose sign is that of the monkey, the divine warns that “the fire (element of the serpent) challenges gold (monkey element)”. For the divine, the theory of “Feng Shui” warns Tai Kin IP to “be careful with health problems” and “reinforce communication techniques in the distribution of work”.
Also having the monkey as a sign, the secretary for security, Wong Sio Chak, “will work well and without starter” in the year of the snake, since the “direction of luck” of this ruler is the south, which “corresponds exactly to Macao Geographic Location ”. In addition, the “Feng Shui” master recalls that Wong Sio Chak has a “prosperous professional career” with an “excellent performance since 2018”.
About the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, the “Feng Shui” expert warns that the sign of O Lam, who was born in 1974, is Tiger, an animal that “will not be in harmony” with the “snake”. Therefore, it suggests to the secretary to "in the new work, strengthen personal relationships, and be mentally prepared to treat small problems and misunderstandings."
For its part, the new secretary for transport and public works, Raymond Tam (born 1960), will benefit from the "harmony" between the "serpent" and the "rat", so it will have "excellent performance" in your work this year. However, Mickey Hung catches this ruler's attention to his health, as "water (mouse element) and fire (snake element) constitute conflict." "So it would be easy to get sick if your heart was under pressure," warns the "Feng Shui" master.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“More tourists mean more business”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-turistas-significam-mais-negocios/</link><description>During the Lunar New Year holidays, business should benefit from the increase in the number of tourists. Tourism services point to a daily average of 185,000, but the sector warns of transport -related concerns, since even on normal buses look full and taxis are scarce. In this festive period, Macao, being a “safe city”, can benefit from the fact that countries such as Thailand and South Korea are being affected by “some unstable conditions”
~~
Catarina Pereira
 
Business in Macao should “warm up” during the new year Lunar, the sector believes, which warns, on the other hand, to the difficulties regarding public transport. If “more tourists mean more business”, more tourists also mean more full buses, less taxis available and less space space to walk. The director of tourism services, Helena de Senna Fernandes, said that the flow of visitors could reach an average of 185 thousand per day, a number of which the president of the Macao Tourist Industry Association, Andy Wu, says be "optimistic".
“This Chinese New Year, Macau's tourist market will be very 'hot'. This is because new beneficial tourist policies were launched for Macao, ”he says in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Andy Wu also suggested that in some time the new visa policies can be extended to other cities in the Great Bay, arguing that the territory has a “different tourist care capacity than 2019”.
The associative leader also said that government services, specifically those responsible for the border passage, "should improve the arrangements about the passage at Hengqin border post, because before it took a long time." "The border passage capacity must be improved, to give tourists a pleasant feeling when traveling in Macao," he added.
In addition to tourists from mainland China and neighboring Hong Kong - attracted to entertainment, concerts, food and game - other points in Asia may also arrive. Penny Wan, a professor at the University of Tourism of Macau (UTM), warns that the territory can benefit from "some unstable conditions" that are affecting countries such as Thailand and South Korea and "may not be safe to travel."
“Macao and Hong Kong, being safe cities, will be able to attract many tourists, especially the Philippines, Korea, Thailand, Malaysia, Singapore and Taiwan, who want to take a short -distance trip, and those from other countries, such as Canada and Australia , who are looking for long distance trips, ”Penny Wan told this newspaper.
The same states Rutger Verschuren, vice president of the Macao Hotel Association: "Since some Asia countries unfortunately have temporarily lost their attraction to the mainland China market, Macau is an excellent alternative with a similar or even lower budget."
The UTM professor pointed to a daily average of 130,000 to 150,000 visitors during the Chinese New Year, and in the first four days it could reach between 150 thousand and 180 thousand. A slightly more conservative perspective, but in relation to business, Penny Wan seems somewhat more optimistic.
"More tourists mean more sure business, whether large, medium or small," he said, and then add: "However, companies located in non -tourist areas may not benefit." From its perspective, it is important that people do not focus only on some areas, "since commercial operators cannot effectively exercise their activities if they are blocked by the crowd."
 
Transportes lack improvements
In this sense, Penny Wan considers that "authorities may have to examine the street to see how roads and alleys can be widened or unlocked by obstacles such as garages to facilitate passenger circulation." In your opinion, you should also "be affixed clearer signaling to guide people."
As for public transport, the UTM teacher states that they are “a serious problem”. “Even during weekdays and weekends, buses are always full. And it's not just public transport - walking is also very difficult, ”he notes, giving as an example the path to the ruins of São Paulo. “It's always full of people and when I go through that small street I can't breathe,” he says.
“There must be immediate strategies to deal with these issues, using good planning,” he continues. For Penny Wan there are some solutions, or at least measures that can help: “Block some streets to use pedestrians only over a certain period of time, put more police on the streets to regulate traffic, make more promotion of different attractions of Macau Instead of the most popular, put more helpers on the streets to answer tourists' questions and make tourists move quickly… These are some strategies that can work. ”
Andy Wu also considers that "there is room for improvement in public buses." "I believe that the management of services for traffic issues will place special bus careers during the Chinese New Year," he said, saying to expect passengers to be diverted through the actual flow of visitors.
"I believe that now the government can highlight buses that take people from sights directly to the border stations, in order to divert the flow of visitors and to separate, in a way, tourists from residents users of public buses," he said.
In the opinion of the associative leader, in the future, taxis, tourist buses and public buses should be able to enter Hengqin “to contribute to the deepening and acceleration of integration with the deepened cooperation zone, which will also boost synergistic tourism development between the two sides of the border. ”
Rutger Verschuren, in turn, said that public transport will be a "concern." “Many hotels offer hotel transportation services for popular tourist attractions, and public transport centers around hotels will also help, even if tourists often find it difficult to find the correct number of the bus and the direction for yours Destination, ”he noted, noting that the meter“ is very useful ”for travel to some parts of the city, especially for those coming from Hengqin.
The Macao Hotel Association representative suggests that "during this fresh time, walking may be more convenient for visitors to reach tourist destinations, especially on the peninsula." According to this newspaper, "sometimes guests manifest their frustration over transportation to hotel employees, as calling a taxi can be time consuming and not everyone understands scarcity."
Noting that by the end of January there will be 400 new taxis, raising the total to 1,900, Verschuren considers that "it is not much, taking into account the many borders, attractions and hotels of Macao." In this sense, he continued, “Let us hope that soon, an application like Didi, which is successfully allowed in the interior of China, to be allowed in our sons, and that taxi drivers and drivers of private automobiles can qualify and subscribe to this application".</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Many hotels” face “staff scarcity”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/muitos-hoteis-enfrentam-escassez-de-pessoal/</link><description>The vice president of the Macao Hotel Association indicated to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that on some days of the Chinese New Year the hotel occupancy rate exceeds 95%. Rutger Verschuren also admitted that in this peak period, “many” hotel establishments face “scarcity” of labor, but still considers that “they are very well prepared to meet the flow of visitors”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
As usual during the Chinese New Year, “hotel activity tends to be very busy, since families and friends gather and travel, especially for popular destinations like Macau, which is full of activities,” says the deputy President of the Macao Hotel Association, Rutger Verschuren. According to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, in a few days of the spring party the hotel occupancy rate exceeds 95% and this year the markings before and after this festive period seem to remain strong. Verschuren also spoke of some challenges, and the scarcity of labor is one of the most affecting hotel establishments.
Rutger Verschuren guarantees that "hotels are very well prepared to meet the flow of visitors," adding that "most have festive activities and packages for their guests." However, "many hotels in Macau are facing some challenges during this period." “One of them is the shortage of staff during peak, since hotels usually have personal to deal with their annual average occupancy levels, and during peaks they need to add occasional labor, which is not easy to Finding and is expensive during the Chinese New Year, ”he said, adding that, for this reason, employees are“ working hard ”, with no people on vacation.
According to it, most hotels will be “with more than 95% or even full from January 31 to February 3, and more than 90% in the two to three days before and after” of the festive season. Generally speaking, says Verschuren, "the Chinese New Year period will be a great success in terms of occupation." Pointing out that there is normally a “strong break” before and after this time, the association's vice president said that this year “activity before and after the Chinese New Year seems to be strong in terms of volume”, pointing out that normally The success of this period is evaluated given the combination of revenues from January and February.
As for prices, the associative leader noted that the spring party “requires a higher rate”, pointing to the peak for the period between January 31 and February 3. "Outside these days, they will be slightly lower," he continued. Adding that “for the entire Chinese New Year period, the tariffs are, however, slightly lower than 2024, and also lower than 2019”, without advanced concrete prices.
“Many resorts integrated with casinos have blocked a large number of rooms with priority for the game, not having many freely available in the market… Sometimes hotels sell a number of rooms to travel agencies, which resell them to a very high fare Although the hotel's real fare is not that excessive, ”he said, saying that this is reflected“ negatively ”in hotels.
Another challenge that hotel establishments face is to ensure that hotels can offer rooms to guests that are time for check-in. “In Macau, the normal check-in time is at 15h00, which can differ from practices in many other parts of China. This difference can create some confusion, ”he said, noticing that many ask for late checkout.
“This can put pressure on the hotel to manage the transition between the departing guests and those who arrive. Each room has to be cleaned thoroughly, which takes about 30 minutes per room. On a busy day where hundreds of rooms come out around noon, you can do the math to have them ready at 15h00… ”said Rutger Verschuren.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>238 -meter dragon will cheer up the city</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dragao-de-238-metros-vai-animar-cidade/</link><description>A 238 -meter -long golden giant dragon will be one of the main attractions of the activities that tourism services will lead to Macao community areas during Lunar New Year. The dragon will be accompanied by 18 lions and the god of fortune

The ruins of São Paulo will be the scene of a “Chinese New Year's Activities” ceremony of community animation, this Wednesday, at 11:00. The event will mark the first day of the celebrations and will feature a giant gold dragon 238 meters long.
To him will join 18 lions and the god of fortune, the three gods of happiness, longevity and prosperity, pair of boys, the sign of the snake and the mascot mascot of Macao “Mak mak”, then moving off the way From the Senate to offer “gold ingots” and wish a good year to residents and visitors.
Then, the Giant Dragon Dragon parade will travel the sidewalk of the Velho Trunk, Largo de Santo Agostinho, Central Street, Paiva's Travessa, Government Headquarters, Padre Narciso's Travessa, S. Lourenço Church, Lilau's Largo and Rua da Barra until it reaches the temple of A-Má.
On the other hand, during the afternoon of the first and second days of the Lunar New Year, the activities program will integrate performances in various neighborhoods of the Macao Peninsula and the islands, including Dragon and Lion dance, artistic group shows and distribution of “Gold Raws” by auspicious dolls.
The Anim ‘Art Nam Van, the Museum of the Great Prize and Doca dos Fishermen, Posto Qingmao Border, Iao Hon Market garden and Jardim da Areia Preta in the North Zone are the places of the exhibitions on the afternoon of the first day.
On the second day, the animation will be centered, among other places, in the ruins of S. Paulo, Largo do Pagode do Bazar, Central and South, Largo Eduardo Marques in Coloane and Houses da Taipa, Lotus Square of the Ilha Verde neighborhood and Leisure Zone of the Lok Yeong Fa Yuen Building (Rua do General Ivens Ferraz) in the North Zone.
In addition to the participation of local and abroad animation groups, artists from Huzhou (interior of China) and Anseong (South Korea) were specially invited, which are also “East Asia Cultural Cities” in 2025. Hong Kong, France, Spain, Colombia, India and Romania will be equally represented.
These events, promoted by the Directorate of Tourism Services, return this year to be integrated into the “Happy Chinese New Year” activities of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Popular Republic of China.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Stories of admiration and longing for an “exceptional” teacher</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/historias-de-admiracao-saudade-de-uma-professora-excepcional/</link><description>If he were alive, Graciete Batalha would be 100 years old this Thursday. He died in 1992, but the memories of those who lived with the teacher and educator, lecturer, researcher and essayist, who dedicated a large part of his life to Macau, are still alive. Many of those who have ran his hands in the classrooms, or who cemented friendships throughout their passage through the territory, recall the "exceptional woman." In the centenary of his birth, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao pays tribute to one of the most striking personalities in the panorama of the contemporary culture of Macao, through the testimonies of Anabela Ritchie, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, Carlos Marreiros, António Dias Alado and Arnaldo Braga



















Victor Rebelo
 
The centenary of the birth of Graciete Batalha, which is marked on January 30, was a reason for collecting testimonies of people who dealt directly with the teacher and educator, lecturer, researcher and essayist, considered one of the most striking personalities in the scenario of culture Contemporary of Macao.
Inserting themselves in the lineage of the great teachers who served in the Macao High School, along with culture, education, with civic intervention, published work and a huge professionality, the woman who left marks well tied in various quadrants of society, probably For eternity, it is now remembered. The Jornal Tribuna de Macao is associated with this historic date, having heard some testimonies of current residents of the Mishes that revive memories of contact with Graciete Batalha.
Anabela Ritchie was, besides a student, also a friend. “Throughout my life I was lucky enough to have had admirable and exceptional people who have accompanied me and consider my great masters, whom I owe so much of what I am and learned. One of them was, I have no doubt, Graciete Batalha, ”he began by revealing the former Macao High School student.
“Excellent teacher, it was evident to us who prepared the classes with immense care, always clear and objective in the presentation of the subjects,” he says. Despite its slightly austere appearance, "it was sympathetic, patient and pleasant to everyone."
It was, however, in the 6th and 7th years of the complementary course that Anabela Ritchie acknowledges that it was possible to better appreciate Graciete Batalha's competence and dedication in teaching the subjects of her responsibility. The friendship between both, who was already coming from behind, "deepened very much at that time."
After joining the Lisbon Faculty of Letters, Anabela Ritchie confirmed the certainty of the “magnificent preparation” that had been given by Graciete Batalha, to the point of one day, in a linguistic class, the teacher was surprised to hear her develops issues With a medieval chronicle and wanted to know who had been his Portuguese literature teacher. “That day I felt immensely proud of my Macao High School”, confirming that the preparation I had received from the teacher was “solid, deep and extensive,” he confesses.
 
Precious dictionaries of various languages
Continuing to tell a little about his youth life story, Anabela Ritchie says she returned to Macau almost 10 years later and went to teach in the High School. It was then that of the student spent the colleague of Graciete Batalha. The two took tours along Avenida da República and liked to go to the highest point of the Noble Carvalho Bridge. "We ate sponge bread, which for me Graciete did better than anyone."
Years later, after the teacher was working in the Ad Hoc Council, created to support the governor, and when they began to discuss the closing works of Praia Grande Bay, Graciete Batalha proved to be "disagreement", little convinced of goodness of the solution. "He managed to convince me to accompany her to an audience he asked engineer Luís Vasconcelos, at the time deputy secretary for public works, because he thought it was his to present and try to clarify the doubts he had."
After the death of her friend, Anabela Ritchie received a call from her husband one day, who asked her for a meeting at her home. “I went and was gaping, since the waiting was books that Graciete had separated for me. So many, so many. I got precious books that today occupy several shelves of my shelves, which I keep religiously and consult often, great and valuable dictionaries of various languages, Portuguese (12 volumes), French, English, even Latin, medical records, support books, Grammars, studies, essays, everything she thought they could be helpful to me and are actually. ”
When he looks back, Anabela Ritchie recognizes feeling a very sweet "longing" from her friend. And it is with a taste and sense of “deep gratitude and tribute” that shares these small grades, when recalls the extraordinary person who was and marks the invaluable contribution that made, with so much enthusiasm and affection, to the education of his students in Macao.
 
Civic provision and coherence of positions
Carlos Marreiros was a student of Graciete Batalha and recalls her with “a lot of friendship and affection”, stating that she was demanding and rigorous. “The key to the secret had to be discovered to open his reserved form of being, because when he could he was a charming person. Pedagogical and didactically a great teacher ”.
For Macaense, Graciete Batalha also had his civic provision. Shortly after April 25, an agency had issued a great compliment to the old regime at the time, and soon after many people wanted to praise the Armed Forces. “She was against, having the manhood of being coherent, of saying that she could not praise two precisely opposite situations, with a difference of such a short time,” says Carlos Marreiros.
This continues, “unlike causing some discomfort in the said Democrats or progressives of Macao, it soon had an effect on the coherence of its position. She was a conservative lady and she remained. ”
Another “funny” detail dates back to 1984. “We made a dramatization of Camilo Pessanha's poems, in an experimental piece, with recites. Graciete Batalha participated and even sat on the floor, contrary to what many would think about the fact that it has, say, an aristocratic style size. ”
When Carlos Marreiros was president of the Cultural Institute, the body issued the book “Good Morning S'Tor”, a publication of Memories of Graciete Batalha as a teacher. “It's a well -written book, very simple, having been released with pomp and circumstance in 1992,” says the former student.
 
Authority and respect in a distinct lady
Miguel de Senna Fernandes heard for the first time in the name of Graciete Batalha when he had joined the National High School Infante D. Henrique. He had just “landed” in the then 1st year of the preparatory cycle (currently the 5th) and had been “praxed”.
He says that there was also this in the High School, where the freshmen were subject to haircut, namely in the parts where the blow would inflict the victim's greatest ridiculous, or to measure with sticks of the huge school of the school, and other trials to Flavor of the fertile imagination of the finalists, whose result was invariably a "does not satisfy" with consequent punishment.
But the initial "terror" continues the lawyer, was also fed "by the same older artists." With this, the names of some illustrious teachers came to Baila, such as the “respectable” doctor Fernanda Salvador dos Santos Ferreira, a name of the mathematics discipline that later became mythical “among students like me”, who only knew numbers negative. But there were also other legendary figures such as Ana Amaro, Aureliano Jorge, António Conceição. And there was Graciete Batalha.
However, he points out Miguel de Senna Fernandes, "I did not meet her in high school, but rather fortuitously in the office of her husband, the late doctor José Batalha, where, by chance, she also eventually appeared." After knowing that "I had entered the High School, tried to talk to me, so a shy boy who was barely talking to strangers, saying that one day she would be my Portuguese teacher, if God wanted him."
In the sixth year, student Miguel was ahead of this “distinct lady with thin, elegant, dark-haired skin, sporting a beautiful smile, despite the smallness of her mouth, but with a sharp look that accompanied an all-plated posture of authority. and respect ”. It says the Macaense that the teacher did not exalt herself, for the tone of her voice, "with the nuances she behaved, was enough to remove any bass of any mandi that ventured to lack her consideration."
A weak student in Portuguese, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, was a little disinterested for the discipline. “Perhaps this was the reason why I was shy, as was the case with most of the macanese colleagues and foreseeing the disappointment in the discipline, to the disappointment of my father. The more I thought about it, the more anxious it became, the more mute it became. But Graciete Batalha, made everything more pleasant, ”he says.
 
Portuguese classes were story sessions
Formation philologist, “knew all the intricacies and tricks of the treacherous tongue”. “He never lacked his rigor and refused condescension, for Portuguese, or taught himself as it should be, or would be a pure waste of time. Nevertheless, he knew how to captivate his class, along with the trendy hours of deambulation by literature, ”says the president of the Macanese Association.
Every Friday, Senna Fernandes continues, “Portuguese classes were stories sessions that told the great literary works”, such as “The Morgadinha dos Canaviais” and “The Pupils of Mr. Rector” by Julio Dinis, and Also “and everything the wind took” by Margaret Mitchell, among others.
“There was always a way of being with your students without betraying your craft. It was fined who was caught talking Chinese, with five patacas per word, joining everything in a velvet bag, money that would later be used for a snack with the class, ”he recalls.
Miguel de Senna Fernandes states that Graciete Batalha was generous in the celebration of the fifteen Portuguese lesson, which he was called “fiftieth anniversary”, appealing the class of sandwiches, lacassá and gaseous. “I remember how she invited seventh-year finalists (current 11), knowing that the following year many would leave Macau, to follow their studies in Portugal, as was my case,” he recalls.
However, he acknowledges that what most marked him was that she understood her difficulties and the "core of shyness in expressing in the language of Camões as required." With her, he notes, "we didn't embarrass our 'second Portuguese', because she respected the peculiar way the macanese communicated, with her own rules that fled the Portuguese grammarian rule."
 
Proximity expressed in the book “Good Morning S'Tora”
Miguel de Senna Fernandes admits that it was not known that the teacher was doing a philological study about Patuá, because for her there resident the richness of the national language. “I remember that I was chosen to declare a poem of his own to a Cultural Lyceum soiree in 1978, held in the then newly opened diocesan theater”, a poem written in the language used by the everyday Macaense. "He told me that it was a more modern patuá and close to Portuguese, not exactly what was used by Adé dos Santos Ferreira."
Recognizing being very nervous this day, because it was the first time he had a stage in front of an audience, where he was, among others, the governor and his father, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, pointed out that at night, at home, the father said "That though nervous, he had managed to declare himself Macaense," because Graciete's poem played us all. "
The proximity she was able to crash with her students is well expressed in the book she wrote, entitled "Good morning," Stora! "," Which even moved me when I read my name referred to there, about this soiree. " The lawyer considers that it is difficult, "if not unfair," summarize Graciete Batalha. But it is right to say that it was important that it was "our teacher", a "full-hand" teacher, with knowledge of cause and undisputed love for Macao and his children. “Until always,‘ Stora! ”He concludes.
 
Memory of generations of macanese
António Dias Azedo begins his statement with the phrase "Remember is Living". Writing and talking about your teacher and living these moments when you spent more than 30 years about your death and a distance of over 50 years as a student, "it's a painful and not easy task."
The lawyer emphasizes that it is "a good exercise of memories if memory does not twist us and we do not let ourselves run over over time or the foam of the days." Graciete Batalha was “teacher and memory of generations of Macanese”.
The teacher, he points out, “is well remembered with Dói tenderness, with great affection and longing for all who were called to the black or green painting while stressed students and bell -mouth pants, from that Infante D. Henrique national high school”. For António Dias Azedo, Graciete Batalha was always attentive to the teaching of good Portuguese and Portuguese literature in the province of the holy name of God, "in a world where the children of the land predominantly spoke all Chinese."
It was in the corridors and classes, he adds, that they were forced to express themselves in the language of Camões, and to read and interpret the hurts, feelings, pains, passions and bitterness of the compiled texts and authors and authors and selected, for those who wanted to go through the year and not have a lead in the Portuguese discipline ”. From what he learned and says he knows of Portuguese literature, Dias Azedo says that “it was all thanks to the dedication and commitment of Master Graciete Batalha”.
The former student states that “it was painful to see the sacrifice of some colleagues who with their family and at home, they only spoke the Chinese, and that in class they were 'forced' to read the cister's monk, the engagement of the tomb, or the Camonian Sonnets ”. The lawyer complements the memory pointing out that "either the program and the readings were fulfilled and the notes and the story was devoured, or it was a very large fox, posted on the walls of the entrance of the High School at the end of the year."
According to António Dias Azedo, students were always required to comply with the norms of speaking Portuguese, as they were directives that had to be fulfilled. "If we were Chinese with colleagues in class or in the corridors, we were punished to stand with our face facing the wall while the class lasted, or punished in a fine, today jound," he comments.
António Dias Azedo recalls that "it was all so calm there by the bands of Ferreira do Amaral and Sei Wan Square." The Hotel Lisboa was already beginning to exist. He recalls these moments of the life of the high school, the friends he still keeps, some with friendship and others missed. "The great teacher Graciete Batalha was inside and very deep, with longing I keep and remember her now."
Arnaldo Braga, Macaense who lives today in Sydney, also pays a sense of Graciete Batalha. “A personality that dedicated itself to education having performed his teaching activities in the National Lyceum Infante D. Henrique and the Macao Magisterium School and has been entirely integrated into various aspects of Macao's culture, becoming a striking personality in the areas of Education, culture and even government functions. But for me, it was my teacher, ”he says.
“In the corridors of the High School, the living room with your folder where it contained the literary texts of the past centuries or perhaps even the Lusíadas that you taught us with such passion, patience and dedication. You were to me and, no doubt, to many other students, an inspiring and influencer source. With great gratitude I tell you 'thank you', ”says Arnaldo Braga, in a dedication directed to Graciete Batalha.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pilots estate releases GPM history in the museum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/espolio-de-pilotos-divulga-historia-gpm-museu/</link><description>An exhibition that displays the valuable estate of SJM -sponsored pilots, including helmets and running facts, will be able to be appreciated by the public, free of charge between tomorrow and 4 February, at the Grand Prix Museum. The space will also offer destic calligraphy and provide a virtual tire change challenge

The Macau Grand Prix Museum (GPM) will be associated with the festivities of the year of the serpent, through some activities, in which visitors can participate for free. The exhibition “Racing Legacy - Drivers' Collection Exhibition”, which is evident in the basement until February 3, releases the history of the competition and displays the valuable estate of SJM sponsored riders, including helmets, gloves, running facts and clothing team.
Among the displayed pieces are autographed helmets and gloves from the former GPM winners Alex Lynn and Felix Rosenqvist and current Formula 1 and Formula 2 pilots.
Meanwhile, until February 17, the interactive device “VR F3 Pit Stop Challenge” the result of the collaboration between the GPM Museum and MGM remains open to the public on the 1st floor of space. Participants are invited to enter a tire change challenge in the virtual racing maintenance workshop through interactive devices, being challenged to perform two tasks in less than two minutes.
The activity simulates the “feeling of live competition, allowing visitors to look for the speed and spirit of precise and perfect cooperation during the process,” says a note of tourism services.
On the other hand, it was transferred from the museum's basement to the 1st floor the display of Formula 3 model 3: 1 scale, designed and assembled by the Lego Certificate professional Andy Hung.
The GPM Museum will be open on February 4 (seventh day of the Lunar New Year), not ending as usual on Tuesday. The opening hours are from 10:00 to 18:00.
Another event, which will take place between tomorrow and 4th February, from 12:00 to 13:00 and from 15:00 to 16:00, is the offer of calligraphy of DISTICS for the year of the serpent. Specialized personnel will write and distribute “New Year's Dististics” and “Spring/Happiness” characters.
During the opening period of the museum, between 10:00 and 18:00, support materials such as paper, brush and ink will also be available for those interested to write their own destics and bring the blessing with them.
It should be noted that, since Saturday, MGP has launched audio-guide and video language video services for exposed articles, meeting the needs of different visitors. These can choose the desired service by scanning the QR code installed on each exhibition through the mobile phone.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>TAP SEAC hosts New Year Fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tap-seac-acolhe-feira-ano-novo/</link><description>In celebration of the year of the serpent, the Institute for Municipal Affairs organizes various activities, especially the usual Panchões burning, but also a fair at TAP Seac, Chinese handwriting sessions, fireworks and an approximation to nature
 
With the Chinese New Year to the Door, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) is preparing to promote various celebration activities for the local population and visitors. The traditional festive events of this time of year include the usual burning of Panchões, Chinese calligraphy sessions, distribution of allusive destics, a flower sales fair and snacks on TAP Seac and an approximation ride to nature.
AMI will create zones for the sale and burning of panchões, fireworks and rockets on the Macao peninsula and the mud. The first is located at Dr. Sun Yat-Sen Avenue (near the new urban landfills, next to the Macau Tower) and the second next to the Almirante Marques Sparteiro road near the coastal edge. In both areas will be installed six and four panchões sales tents, fireworks and rockets, respectively, being the opening time today from 12:00 to 01:00 the following day, while, from 29 to 2 February , the public can make the burning of Panchões between 10:00 to 24:00.
AMI will make free buses available to transport people from these places to Ferreira do Amaral Square.
During the lunar New Year, to make it easier to buy paper fans and taps, 10 temporary tents will be created on the ride that flanks the coastal edge, near the bar of the Barra pagoda.
Meanwhile, the Lunar New Year's Eve Fair will take place in Tap Seac Square, with 14 Chinese New Year's Holidays, six of the time of the time and four with snacks.
During the event period, AMI will organize several activities and cultural and recreational shows on site. Simultaneously, they will be available for consideration of large floral art exhibitions and decorative illuminations.
On Afonso de Albuquerque Street, next to Tap Seac Square, there will be cargo and discharges of passengers and goods for the public and authorized vehicles.
On January 30 and 31, IAM will promote, in the Pai Van Seac Park, the “Chinese New Year Ride - Ecological Garden of Medicinal and Aromatic Plants and Chinese Medicinal Plants Garden”. On February 1st and 2nd will be the turn of the “Harvest Day” on the Oscar Granja in Coloane.
 
AI inspect plants on the doors of the siege
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) has installed a provisional place of landscape fitsanitary inspection at the border post of the siege gates. The objective is to facilitate citizens the acquisition, inside China, of flowers for personal use, namely in the decoration of the houses. The inspection post, which lasted three days, ends today at 23:00. AMI warns people not carrying threatened wild plants without authorization and emphasizes that the flowers and cuts cut, weeds, mosses and landscape plants (with roots) that exceed the number of inspection exemption must be bounded by that border post. . Otherwise they will be seized. Transported plants that do not exceed one kilogram at a time, or a total daily weight of 5 kg, are exempt from inspection. AMI appeals to citizens so that, if they are not certified and license issued by economics and technological development services, they do not carry orchids, churches, aloes, cacti, and other endangered plants.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Café Portuense inspired photographs of Lúcia Lemos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cafe-portuense-inspirou-fotografias-de-lucia-lemos/</link><description>The iconic coffee “Majestic” in Porto served as inspiration to Lucia Lemos for a series of photographs that will be exhibited in the “Hold on To Hope” gallery. The work of “Meeting the Middle Light” involves the spirit of a meeting place that was part of the author's youth
 
The “Majestic” coffee in Porto served as a backdrop for a series of photographic “clicks” through the artist Lúcia Lemos chamber lens. It was there, in that iconic space, that the author recorded several photographs, 10 of which will be exhibited in the “Hope on To Hope” gallery, in the village of Our Lady in Ká-Hó, between February 1 and 23.
In the introduction of the show “Meeting the Half Light”, which will be inaugurated at 4:00 pm on Saturday, Lúcia Lemos says that the photos captured inside the coffee “convey the very peculiar light and warmth of the establishment”. The light of low intensity, "crosses the entrance of the bearers, illuminates the stem-recorded leather arms and fixed on the Flemish crystal mirrors to Belle Époque, proving to fascinating the middle interior of space."
“It's so beautiful and romantic,” he says, stressing that “going to Porto and not meeting at Majestic cafe is like returning to the place and not visiting his mother”.
In this emblematic Café Lúcia Lemos spent a few years of his youth. "Majestic was a point of pleasurable encounters where the coffee was drunk in a cup and later the short coffee in cup called Cimbalino after the Italian brand arrived in Porto," says the photographer, for whom the people who come in "feel Immersed in the beauty of the facade and its interior of Art Nouveau style that exerts magnificent and welcoming energy. ”
Lúcia Lemos, a native of Famalicão, points out that “Majestic” is an inviting space for frequent dating and gathering dating for painters, musicians, actors, scientists, politicians, writers, poets, bankers and traders. “Even today, when I get to Porto,” he confesses, “that's where Marco the meetings with those who enjoy the service of receiving customers with elegance and class”. It is from there that “the city of Porto is presented to someone very special,” he says.
For the artist, former coordinator of Creative Macau, now dedicated to personal projects in the cultural area, coffee has survived socio-economic fluctuations and has become a tourist framework of the unbeaten city. “Majestic and Casa da Música are, for me, the most beautiful and contrasting buildings in Porto, so I photographed them in 2006 with my 1954 Rolleiflex in black and white Kodak movies 6 x 6 cm” , describes.
In the introduction of the exhibition, the Hold on To Hope, a project of the Macao Toxicode Rehabilitation Association (ArtM), says that this photographic trip “not only celebrates the rich history of coffee”, but also “encapsulates the spirit of a Beloved meeting place that continues to inspire and delight. ”
Lúcia Lemos is a visual artist who crosses various arts and experiences and uses organic materials to body ideas through different languages ​​and aesthetic forms to express meanings to her art. He has participated in Macao in collective exhibitions with video art, engraving, jewelery, ceramic, sculpture and artistic facilities of which some were recognized and awarded.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>File displays models of fishing reeds</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arquivo-exibe-modelos-de-juncos-de-pesca/</link><description>溫泉先生作品展暨捐贈儀式



The Macao Archive presents until February 16 an exhibition of Wan Chun fishing reed models, an experienced naval builder of the territory. All exposed wood models were handmade by Wan Chun, being inspired by typical fishing reeds that used to operate on the coast of Macao.
The Cultural Institute (IC) believes that this exhibition provides the public a deeper knowledge about the role of the fishing industry in the history of Macau.
Former President of the Macao Shipyard Workers Association, Wan Chun was distinguished with the silver lotus medal in 2011. Born in a family of Macao fishermen, he grew up in the zone of Almirante Lacerda Avenue, where there were many Naval shipyards with over 100 years of history of shipbuilding.
He started to be an apprentice in this industry when he was 14 years old. He worked at shipyards of Macau, Taipa and Coloane, having participated in the manufacture of more than 200 fishing reeds. Since 2014, Wan Chun has been making miniature reed models, exhibited regularly at the entrance of the Macao Archive, “demonstrating traditional naval construction techniques that are extinct,” according to IC.
Currently, Wan Chun performs duties as a volunteer instructor in courses organized by the IC, teaching graduates the traditional craft of Macao naval construction, his history and culture.
At the inauguration of this show, the director of the Macao Archive, Lou Hong Wai, on behalf of the IC, handed a donation certificate to Wan Chun and thanked him his strong support for the development and preservation of Macao's traditional culture. In turn, Wan Chun shared with those present the history of donated wooden reeds.
The exhibition of Wan Chun fishing reed models ”is patent daily from 10:00 to 18:00, except Monday. The entrance is free.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Art of gold and silver “shines” on tap seac</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arte-ouro-prata-brilha-tap-seac/</link><description>“熠熠生輝 - 河北省和貴洲省金銀器手工藝術展”



More than 160 pieces and sets of jewelery and exquisite gold and silver articles from Hebei and bean provinces make up a patent exhibition at the TAP Seac Gallery
 
The Tap Seac Gallery presents until February 23rd the exhibition “Brightness of Art”, with pieces of handicrafts in gold and silver of the provinces of Hebei and Guizhou. Organized by the Office for Hong Kong, Macao and Taiwan affairs of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism, Cultural Institute (IC) and by the Departments of Culture and Tourism of the two provinces, co-organized by the Department of Advertising and Culture of the Central Government connection at MSAR and coordinated by the Center for the Development of Ethnic and Popular Arts and Literatures of the Ministry of Culture and Tourism, this show is part of the Serpente Lunar New Year's Commemorative Program and aims to publicize a type of traditional Chinese handicrafts with over 3,000 years of history.
In this context, IC highlights as “particularly brilliant examples” the art -embedded art and Chinese art in Cloisonné de Hebei and the goldsmithing of the Miao de Guizhou ethnic group, all included in the national list of representative items of China's intangible cultural heritage. The pieces of art inlaid in filigree and Cloisonné de Hebei are distinguished by the high degree of technical refinement, diversity of their motives and stunning ornamentation, having great artistic value, while the goldsmith of the Miao ethnic group denotes a multiplicity of cultural connotations.
This exhibition integrates over 160 pieces/sets of jewelery and exquisite gold and silver articles. Created by heirs of intangible cultural heritage and masters artisans, these works present “sophisticated formats, a very high degree of technical refinement and a variety of styles,” says the IC, noting that “traditional art pieces radiate a contemporary aura”.
In order to allow the public a more direct contact with the Gold and Silver Crafts on display, the organization will hold four workshops on February 8 and 9, with instructors from Hebei and Guizhou, “representative heirs” at the provincial level of their respective techniques . All workshops will take place in the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum, on Francisco Xavier Pereira Street, being conducted in Mandarin and making 16 vacancies available, upon registration.
Throughout the exhibition period, guided tours will also be available, open to the general public, with Sessions in Cantonense at 15:00 and Mandarin at 16:15.
The exhibition can be visited daily, including holidays, from 10:00 to 19:00, with free admission.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>A “Odyssey” of Portuguese in the “Sea of ​​People” of the lunar year of China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/uma-odisseia-de-portugueses-mar-de-gente-ano-lunar-da-china/</link><description>Ðâ.
1 ôâ20èõ £ ¬âãiô provided ° ° ° Hitch
´óöð¹úâ · · îäººººººSTRO¯óðïþ «ë» ñï¤ £ ¬õëases ± ± ¾ ¢ ¢ ¢ ¡¡¡¢ ⇒ãöý brand · · · µ »µ µäê ^^ Æ »® Ôúa20èõvis27èõæú professional £ ¬ã ° ° ° ° ¬íùéïêö® ° 47áðça=ßção £ ¬ôeýôëá £ £ £ £ £ £
Ðâ.



João Simões is concerned, on the eve of train traveling to the woman's homeland in Chenzhou, because he has not yet bought the tickets, and the traffic of hundreds of millions of Chinese in the new lunar year does not expect.
“This year I still haven't been able to buy tickets. Every year it is difficult. But usually a week before I have tickets. Perhaps there are more people traveling, ”risked the Portuguese based in Macau.
During a 'golden week', hundreds of millions of people will travel in the interior of China, in the largest annual migration in the world, to welcome from family members the lunar year of the serpent, which this year is going to match January 28 and February 4.
In this odyssey, once again, three Portuguese, who described Lusa, as it is to travel at this time of year.
Since January 14, when Chunyun began, a period of 40 days before and after the beginning of the lunar year of the serpent, and until Friday, the Chinese state railway company China State Railway Group had sold more than 297 online Millions of tickets.
"For me, Chinese New Year has always been synonymous with many people and starts just passing the border" to mainland China, says João Simões, a professor at the Institute for the investigation into Portuguese -speaking countries at the City of Macao University.
At the MSAR, the police decided to highlight more personal for border posts, facing the forecast of entries and exits of almost 5.4 million people during the 'golden week', 3% more than in the same period of 2024.
“A sea of ​​people. That arrival at the Canton South Train Station. This is the first idea I have from the Chinese New Year, since the early years I started passing them in mainland China, ”says Simões.
According to the state press, nearly 20.2 million passengers are expected to go through Canton South, one of the busiest railway stations in China, in the capital of Guangdong Province. The station recruited 1,575 volunteers to help travelers during this period, including some who speak English and Cantonese.
João Coimbra Sampayo, a Portuguese married for six years with a Chinese, also says that “traveling in China alone is not easy”, but in the Chinese New Year, “is much more boring because of the queues”.
João Simões describes them: “There are all the filthos for [the control of] safety. There is the line to go buy I don't know what, some cookies, for example. There is the line to enter the train… ”.
Despite the scale of the human movement, “there is no confusion. Things seem to work, they are orderly. This is curious. How in a country with so many people things work so well, ”says the academic.
The Council of State, the Chinese executive, said this year expects nine billion internal travels during Chunyun, which will be a record for a country with a population of 1.4 billion.
“I think China has this magic,” he says with a smile Charlotte Yuan Tian, ​​married 11 years ago with a Portuguese. “It sounds like chaotic, but then things work. Even on the streets, it seems very confusing, but then things are walking. ”
Charlotte plans to her homeland, Chengdu, the capital of Sichuan Province, in southwest China, but still has memories of train travel during the Lunar New Year at night to visit grandparents in a rural area.
“The carriage was full, full, full, nor could we set foot, we had no place to sit, but I don't know how, my mother got a place and had to go to her lap, already big, nine years old ”Recalls the teacher, today based in Macau.
More than 30 years later, China has the fastest trains in the world, but certain things have not changed.
“The crowded trains of people, standing, bags and children everywhere. Those unfoldable stools. Children to eat instant pasta. This is one of the images I have from the Chinese New Year, ”says João Simões.
Still, since in 2014, the teacher has been practically every year to spend this period to the woman's homeland. “It's not even anything else, it's like going to Christmas to Viseu,” he explains.
The Lunar New Year is usually compared to Christmas in Western countries, but João Coimbra Sampayo says the importance of the main party of Chinese families "is amplified to the fullest."
“In Portugal it is very easy for a person to go home anytime of the year. In many cases, in China this is impossible. It is impossible for the family to gather, the man with his wife, children and parents, other than in the Chinese New Year, ”says Sampayo.
“Therefore, they are very strong feelings. There are a lot of rice brandy, talk a lot ”, because many of those who travel“ were their land to work for cities and do not have the hukou of these cities. Therefore, they cannot take the family, ”he adds.
Hukou is the Chinese residence system that, in practice, prevents migrant workers from rural areas from having access to health and their children from attending schools in large cities.
The return to homeland is also taken advantage of to offer the so -called 'Hong Bao' ('Lai Si' in Cantonese), red envelopes with money, which are usually given by the elders to the youngest.
But in rural areas, it is sometimes the children who work in the cities that give Hong Bao to their parents, says Charlotte Yuan.
The rapid aging of China's population has placed greater pressure on the already fragile social security system, with a growing number of Chinese to refuse to pay for the pension system, which has long been sub-financed.
“If parents don't have a large renovation, they depend a little on this money that their children will send,” explains Charlotte.
This is the case of John Simões's in -laws: "They are in their 70s, they have no reform, they have nothing."
"At the time of the Chinese New Year, children take the opportunity to deliver a larger amount of money, which is to give them to live for a while," adds the teacher.
 
Jtm with Vítor Quintã, journalist of the agency Lusa, text edited</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ipim only approved 12 requests for residence last year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipim-so-aprovou-12-pedidos-de-residencia-ano-passado/</link><description>In 2024, the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macau (IPIM) approved 12 initial requests for residence authorization, being the overwhelming majority (11) in the category of specialized leaders and technicians. This is a break of about 66% compared to 2023, as this year was given “green light” to 35 orders. Throughout the year, the body received 41 requests from staff and specialized technicians, of which only 27% were granted. According to the statistics released by the IPIM, of the approved requirements, six said respect to specialized managers and technicians in the area of ​​education; Following the health area of ​​social action (two requests), thick trade and retail (two orders), financial industry (one order) and entertainment and game (one order). In addition, there was only one request to set residence for relevant investments and investment projects to receive “green light” in the area of ​​Grosso and retail, the IPIM had received three requests. The body arrived at 66 requests for renewal, and followed by 64; and five in the family, two of which were granted. In the general calculation, IPIM sued 115 requests.</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Life Hope Line” registered a 50% increase in support requests</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/linha-esperanca-de-vida-registou-subida-de-50-nos-pedidos-de-apoio/</link><description>Caritas's “Life Hope line” received more than 15,000 requests for help over 2024, which translates into a 50% increase over the previous year, the institution's secretary general told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau. The number of suicide -related support requests has registered an annual rise from 30% to 178. Paul Pun said that Caritas intends to optimize this year the online counseling segment of the line, so that this service is more professional

Last year, the “Life Hope line” of Caritas de Macao, which is intended to support people with emotional or psychological problems or even vulnerable to suicide, has registered more than 15,000 requests for help. This number reflects a significant increase of 50% compared to 2023, the year the line received "a little over 10,000" calls to request support, said the secretary general of Caritas.
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Paul Pun also said that in 2024 there was an annual increase of almost 30% in the number of requests to help the “Life Hope line” related to suicide, which totaled 178. According to the person responsible for Institution, among these cases, those involving young or adolescents recorded a higher increase percentage than other age groups, exceeding 30%.
According to Paul Pun, both in 2023 and last year, the users of the line sought maintenance mainly due to psychological, emotional or study problems.
For the secretary general of Caritas, the significant climb of requests for help will also be associated with the reinforcement of the line of the line and the institution itself. In this aspect, he mentioned that Caritas has been able to make free dissemination actions on this emotional support channel at an establishment in the McDonald's chain in the tape.
“It is not known if it was the pandemic that led more people in Macao to ask for help in terms of mental health. But in fact, we started to see relatively many situations with young people or adolescents wanting to end life. All parties need to attribute attention and importance to this issue, ”said Paul Pun.
On the other hand, it revealed that last year, Caritas received “very few” requests for help in the line segment in foreign language (English). “They (citizens of foreign nationality) rarely called us. Usually, they prefer to move to our social equipment, the Welanser Center, to receive support, ”he said.
Although the “Life Hope Line” has suffered a notorious addition of calls, the secretary general of Caritas understands that the number of users in the last year was not high for a service that, on the other hand, continues to have a number Reduced from personnel. Still, Paul Pun stressed that this year the line will remain open for 24 hours, and that to answer the calls, "there must be, at least one worker who knows how to speak English every day." In fact, he said, the service has already had foreign nationality volunteers.
Paul Pun expressed the desire to widen the service, namely in terms of foreign languages, but admitted that it would be necessary to gather many resources. "In the long run, to expand the coverage of the service, it would make sense that the line would also provide services in the languages ​​Nepalesa, Filipina and Indonesia," he said.
However, there are still no conditions for Caritas to expand this segment of the line, as the institution has to channel resources to other services. In this sense, this year, the institution intends, above all, to maintain the current conditions of the “Life Hope line” and optimize the online counseling segment, to raise the professionalism of this service.
“On the computer, staff cannot immediately analyze whether help applicants are in crisis. For example, if you come to say on social networks that you want to die, the team cannot send personal soon to intervene. We need to observe and analyze, so we will reinforce the training, ”said Paul Pun.
Regarding mental health, the secretary general of Caritas believes that “there is room” for the local population, especially young people and adolescents, to improve the ability to support stress. “All residents should give greater importance to mental health, rest, sleep and do more exercise. It cannot be considered that this is only a responsibility of government or society, as the population itself must do something. In turn, it is obvious that if the government increases the piped resources for mental health, it will also be beneficial to people's general health, ”said Paul Pun.
Authorities have been appealing to citizens so that, in case of need, they call the “Life Hope of Caritas” line (2852 5222), which also has a foreign language segment (2852 5777).</description><pubDate>2025-01-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Absence of social networks feeds “parallel reality” in Turquemenistan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/ausencia-de-redes-sociais-alimenta-realidade-paralela-turquemenistao/</link><description>“We know that Facebook, Instagram and Youtube exist, but we have no access. Here, everyone is blocked, ”says byashim Ishanguliyev, a fruit salesman in Turquemenistan, one of the most closed countries in the world, where the state dominates the internet almost completely.
Passing over these prohibitions in this Central Asian Soviet Republic, rich in hydrocarbons, is a true race of obstacles.
"Some people can connect to a VPN, but it is temporary (why) it will also be blocked," he told AFP Ishanguliyev, 19, in a market in the capital, Ashgabat. “The internet is slow, so if someone can download a video, a clip or an interesting movie, we all watch together” with friends, explains the young man.
However, for the president of the country, to be BerdyMujamedov, these drastic measures are not enough. Last year, the leader announced his intention to “reinforce the country's cybersecurity,” following the steps of the predecessors imposed - his father Gurbanguly Berdymujamedov and the late Niazov Saparmurat.
Main messaging services are prohibited in the country: there is no WhatsApp, Viber, Signal or Telegram. Alternatively, the government created an application, Bizbarde, under its control.
For online videos, authorities have launched Belet Video, a kind of alternative to Youtube filtered from any content that can reveal the world outside Turkomens, whether news or entertainment.
“There is no media panorama,” summarized the writer of the TurkmenNews Information Site, Ruslan Miatiev, whose portal is forbidden in his country.
Turkoman only see “propaganda to promote the personality worship of the BerdyMujamedov,” explained the journalist, who currently resides in the Netherlands. "And to prevent this parallel reality created by the media collapsing, the rulers block the internet," he said.
The Turkoman media, all state -owned companies, only disclose official information, with a special emphasis on thanks and praise to the country's authorities.
Yusup Bakhshiyev, a 38 -year -old ashgabat employee, had access to more foreign channels via satellite. However, it says it is now impossible.
"Chamber employees came to my house and told me to remove the antenna because I spoiled the city's architecture," he said.
Then Bakhshiyev registered on Turly cable television. “With this, the state controls the information and receives revenues with the signature,” he notes.
Some western networks such as France 24, BBC and Euronews are authorized, but their audience is scarce in a country where English is little spoken.
Every day, the Turkomena watch programs in which BerdyMujamedov rebuke ministers, plants trees in the desert, or receives applause. His father Gurbanguly, "Hero Protector" (Arkadag) and "Chief of Turkomana" with great prerogatives, becomes increasingly eccentric with the worship of his personality.
The American Non-Governmental Organization Freedom House, which analyzes civil and political freedoms, classified Turquemenistan in the “worst” category with a score of 2 in 100, even smaller than North Korea, with 3. It also occupies one of the last positions in the ranking of press freedom of Reporters Without Borders.
But none of this worries Oksana Shumilova, an employee of an Ashgabat builder, who is delighted with the country's stability. Subscriber of the newspaper “Turkmenistão Neutral”, with the inevitable photo of the president on the cover, she assures AFP that she feels a “feeling of stability and tranquility” because “has no critical articles or negative information”.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-01-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>