<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Training, towards social reintegration,” is one of the priorities of the new chain</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/a-formacao-rumo-a-reintegracao-social-e-uma-das-prioridades-da-nova-cadeia/</link><description>The broad and modern facilities of the new Macao prison establishment, which make it one of Asia's most advanced gender complexes, have been working in the middle of nine months, next to the Ká-Hó dam in Coloane, and, according to its director, added “quality” in all slopes to the services that were already provided before. In an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the chain's director said that the training of prisoners remains one of the priority tasks. Lam Kam Sau addresses the main issues of the government's correctional policy, which point to resocialization, safety, health and decent conditions for prisoners. This includes investing in education, professionalization and psychological support programs, as well as, simultaneous

Victor Rebelo
 
⁃Themates are currently at the prison of Macao, Coloane, and what is the maximum capacity?
Upon July 31, 2025, they were serving penalty 1,292 people, 1,071 male and 221 of the female. These numbers are still far from the maximum prison capacity, which is 2,704 beds.
 
⁃ In relation to 2024, there is a decrease of 48 prisoners. Do you find any explanation for this?
-Idens that the main reason has to do with the improvement of the general security of Macao, including the installation of cameras throughout the city. In addition, citizens are more aware and the government has also done a lot of work in terms of security, with the police to constitute an important part in this regard, so that there is a decrease in the number of prisoners.
 
⁃With the entry into operation of the new prison establishment, what are the main changes to register?
-Foundly, the large changes are at the level of internal, wider and more modern structures, that is, the perimeter of the chain increased, which is reflected in the conditions that are given to all, but especially to prisoners. We can say that the new chain added benefits and quality to the service provided to prisoners. Regarding the prison itself, we have an optimization regarding its functioning and also the environment of the prison. On the other hand, with this move to a larger place, we have more room for training different types for prisoners. In this sense, we can provide more learning and training opportunities for those detained here, as well as offering a good environment and increasing work efficiency. In short, formation towards the social reintegration of the prisoners is one of our priorities.
 
⁃ Was specifying some of the introduced improvements?
-A of these benefits is at health level. We began to implement in the former prison establishment an electronic clinical registration system for the prisoners, having scanned the processes that were on paper. Now, here, we are improving it. This can help the efficiency of prison clinical service. On the other hand, as the Correction Services Directorate works with the Conde São Januário Hospital Center, another service was launched together, the external video consults at a distance. This can also help alleviate the workload of the master guards in the escort and the transfer of prisoners to hospitals to be attended.
 
⁃What other benefits brought the new building?
There are also differences in the infrastructure of the cells. This new prison adopts a modular design in each block. In addition to cells, there are other facilities, or rooms, for, for example, meetings with social workers and medical appointments. Given these conditions, prisoners leave cells less frequently, which can also help save human resources from master guards. As for surveillance and control, the new chain has facilities that facilitate the provision of service of the guards.
 
⁃What projects have you ever been able to realize?
-It of all, as long as I assumed the responsibility of the management of the Macao Prison, the first objective was the realization of the change of facilities. Since 2021 we have been preparing this change, prioritizing the formation of the guards and the inspection of the facilities. To do this, we did several simulacros, which provided good results to make the change successful, which really happened, since the prison has a new ambience. Fundamentally, this was one of my main projects for this first phase of the prison establishment.
 
⁃What does the challenges of the future, in the short term?
-The from a change, we reviewed what had been done so far and set off for the improvement of work processes, especially at the level of prisoners. However, for prison guards, in terms of teaching and professional training, since our facilities are higher, we also seek to create more opportunities for this learning to do in the best way.
 
⁃What type of training is given to prisoners?
-Nós tentamos ajudar os reclusos a partir de três aspectos: individual, familiar e social. At the social level, we conducted correctional counseling and, in prison, we organize recurring teaching programs, for example, extension courses, social assistance, management and business administration, among other types of diversified training. The aim is for prisoners to acquire new techniques for when they leave prison. Regarding your personality, we do a kind of teaching, starting by addressing the return to work and the future contact with the community. For this, we provide various types of work to prepare. In addition, families' help is always important to make their reintegration easier in society.
 
⁃What results have arisen with the implementation of this program?
-In 2024, there were a total of 998 people who participated in individual or group counseling, and 582 were involved in our training plans. In the academic year 2024/2025, 36 inmates signed up for recurring education programs. In addition, 27 participated in university courses.
 
⁃Not on the families of prisoners and the general community, how do you deal with this communication and interaction?
-To help and facilitate the relationship between the penitentiary and families, we have developed some actions that I consider important. For example, marriage and marriage parties, which strengthen the relationship between families, children and prison. This also helps strengthen people's confidence and determination. I add that the arrest greatly values ​​the care and support to the family members of the prisoners, organizing every year activities on the eve of some of the festivities, such as Mother's Day, Father's Day, Children's Day, Lunar Cake Party, among others, without forgetting events such as Chinese New Year and Christmas.
 
⁃What type of collaboration are with Macao entities?
-The direction of correctional services also contributes to the Institute of Social Action in the development of some plans, one of which is called 'Family Out of Prison', to support local prisoners and to help them solve family problems. In addition to this program, we have yet another directed to prisoners who are residents of Hong Kong, offering support so they can strengthen their trust, determination and self -knowledge as well.
 
⁃ How is the meeting with social workers and families?
We disagree with a mechanism so that social workers can have a meeting every month. There are a certain frequency of visits that they have with the prisoners, to find out about the situation of serving the sentence, etc. At least once a month they come to prison.
 
⁃ Is there rooms for this and also for medical assistance and family visits?
-In another prison there were already rooms for doctors, social workers and family visits, but now the conditions are frankly better. In each block, there is a room for doctors to see the sick and for the meetings with the social workers. Reclusos do not need to move to other sites to have the consultations. It's all focused on the same block.
 
⁃What is the concern with food?
-In relation to food and its quality, we always have in mind, first of all, the issue of hygiene, having its own committee for the purpose. Food is made by a company and we also consulted nutritionists, who have created a specific menu that can ensure the quality of foods ingested by prisoners. In addition, the Macao Prison Establishment also consists of the issue of religion, those who are vegetarians and other situations, such as arrested with certain health conditions, so we offer five varieties every day. There are, for example, cow -free menus or pig. They can choose, as happened in the previous chain. [Now the distribution is made directly in the cells, which have their own space].
 
⁃In female part, when mothers have still quite small children and need to have them, what conditions are there?
-According to the penitentiary regime, minor children may stay with their mother until they are three years old. When a woman comes pregnant to prison, he goes to the hospital to give birth and then here we take care of the mother and the baby, in medical terms, feeding, breastfeeding and other aspects, with special cells for this purpose.
 
⁃How children are there at this moment living with the mother in the prison establishment?
-Test time we have only one.
 
How many prison guards do you have? Are they enough for current needs?
-We currently disagree with 671 prison guards, 547 residents of Macao and 124 non -resident workers, especially from Nepal and Vietname. Recently, 55 guards and instructs began to perform functions, which helps alleviate the situation of lack of human resources, but are now enough.
 
⁃ How is the recruitment of these guards done?
-We were recruiting taking into account the vacancies, the limit of vacancies, and provided we have authorization from the hierarchical superiors, we held a public tender to hire.
 
⁃ How was the distribution of the guards to move to this location?
-In relation to this situation of human resources, we reorganized and optimized this distribution reasonably, to ensure normal functioning.
 
⁃ How many cameras are there in this new building? How is new technologies being used?
-In the moment, within the public space of this direction of services where many of the master guards are found, surveillance chambers were installed. As for the interior of the prison, usually only in special cells, there are cameras, in order to ensure the privacy of prisoners. [Unlike corridors of the old chain, new cells are arranged in a circle space, allowing for faster and more effective surveillance].
 
⁃What do the most committed crimes by convicted prisoners in the prison?
-In the first place are the fraud, and there are now 420 sentenced to serve penalty for these crimes. This follows drug trafficking (243) and illegal immigration (127).
 
⁃For what nationalities?
-Thá 27 nationalities in total. I can highlight the three countries that have the largest number of prisoners here: Vietname (51), Philippines (44) and Indonesia (15).
 
-How final note, what balance makes these first months of operation of the new prison establishment?
-It's just that has worked well and we are satisfied. A director always has in mind the development of society and considers the service provided to prisoners, counseling, training, etc., as the main priorities, so that it can facilitate its social reintegration, and, on the other hand, seeks to ensure the prevention of recidivism. It is also important to continue to reinforce collaboration with other public services, non-governmental institutions and companies, so that we can provide more learning opportunities for prisoners, helping them in what is fundamental in correctional politics, reintegration in society.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Duty of confidentiality” does not allow sharing examples of null votes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dever-de-sigilo-nao-permite-partilha-de-exemplos-de-votos-nulos/</link><description>The President of the General Court of Legislative elections invoked the “duty of confidentiality” to explain the fact that examples of invalid votes have not been shared, unlike previous elections. Cheong Kuok Chi also did not comment on the fact that there was a large number of invalid votes, arguing that such assessment is not the “competence” of the General Courts Assembly
 
Pedro Milheirão
President of the General Legislative Election Assembly, Cheong Kuok Chi, justified the fact that no images of invalid votes of these elections have been shared with the "duty of confidentiality." Asked why in these elections were not shown the bulletins -contrary to what happened until 2021 -Cheong began to invoke the law, saying that "the vote must fulfill the duty of confidentiality."
Given that this was a usual practice during the legislative elections at least until four years ago, the same responsible was questioned if the authorities of MSAR have been violating their duty over the years. To this question, Cheong Kuok Chi replied that he did not comment on previous qualifying work.
In addition, journalists also observed that the vote is secret, that is, unidentified, so it would not be compromising confidentiality. To which Cheong replied, "Before doing the work work, we never know how they are the voting newsletters, so taking into account this consideration, we chose this way to do our finding work."
Speaking during a press conference about the work of counting votes, the same responsible also clarified that, during the number of votes, candidates from the lists or officers may be present. "During the procedure, we also prepared some screens or monitors so that the representatives of the lists can see the situation of the votes," he said.
In previous years, during the final count, the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) used to show the null votes with a projector on the wall, to realize why they were considered invalid. In 2021, bulletins appeared with some political messages, such as the letters “DQ”, referring to exclusions, protest words or insults.
However, this time, in addition to Caeal, he did not show the bulletins, he also posted a sign of prohibition to photograph the voting newsletters. It is recalled that this year were disqualified two lists and a total of 12 candidates, including former deputy Ron Lam, from the race to elections. In these were the first elections under the Electoral Law, the authorities intend to reinforce the principle "Macao governed by patriots."
On the other hand, about the reason for a considerable number of invalid votes, Cheong asserted that this is not the “competence” of the general finding assembly, explaining that there are “various reasons”. "According to the Electoral Law of the Legislative Assembly, our work is to verify the statistical data we get and reach a decision on the invalid votes and the contested votes," he said.
In the MSAR, so many blank votes had never been accounted for (5,987) and null (7,077), corresponding to increases of 90% and 242%, respectively, compared to previous elections. Following the disclosure of the results, Seng Ioi Man, president of Caeal, also refused to comment on this exponential increase, only said that "in all data related to elections there are numbers to rise or descend."
 
24 votes began to be considered valid
At yesterday's conference, Cheong Kuok Chi also announced that, after completing the work of determination, the previously considered invalid votes were validated 24, all related to direct suffrage. According to guaranteed, such “did not harm the order or result” of the elections, he guaranteed. Of these, eight were contested votes and 16 had been considered null.
"At each [vote] assembly, after the vote is finished, the table has a preliminary decision on the votes," he said. "Some can be decided immediately as invalid votes. There are also representatives of each list present to see if it is necessary to protest or not," he reiterated.
The rate of participation in the last legislative elections was 53.35%, in direct suffrage, an increase of nearly 11 percentage points compared to 2021, when the highest abstention rate was recorded in the history of MSAR. Even despite the constant government's appeals, the poll to the polls was the third worst since 2001. In total, 175,272 people, a new maximum, voted last Sunday. This was also the year when most voting registered (328,506) were.
It is recalled that the list “Nova Esperança” was the big winner of these elections, with three seats, by José Pereira Coutinho, Chan Hao Weng and Che Sa Wang. This was followed by the list led by Song Pek Kei, linked to the Fujian community, which also secured three seats in the hemiciclo. The remaining four lists - linked to the workers, "Kaifong", the Jiangmen community and the "women" - got only two seats each.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pedonal Zone will be born next to the Jardim das Artes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zona-pedonal-vai-nascer-junto-ao-jardim-das-artes/</link><description>Metal platforms to facilitate pedestrian crossing between Zape and NAPE will be installed in the accesses of the lanes of the Jardim das Artes parking lot. The project also includes widening the pedestrian passage on Avenida da Amizade

From mid -October, it will not be necessary for pawns to get around the outer of the Jardim das Artes, as a pedestrian space will be created in one part of that zone, and can then cross Avenida da Amizade and Rua Cidade de Sintra direct pedestrian line. The optimization works have already begun, and should be completed 16 of next month.
With a view to improving the pedestrian environment, after interdepartamental coordination, metal pawns metal platforms will be built, in the access of the parking park lanes on both sides of the Garden of the Arts, some trees from the garden to another place and some recreational and sports facilities and a monument in the garden area.
It will also be implemented, to 12 meters, from the passage to pedestrian, on Avenida da Amizade, next to the Jardim das Artes, in order to create a easy pedestrian access and optimize the crossing environment.
At this time, given the limitation of the surrounding road environment, if the pedestrians near Avenida 24 de Junho or Cantão Street want to travel between Zape and Nape, they need to circumvent temporary access, separated by water barriers, next to the Garden of Arts, lacking walking. These barriers of water will be removed, as will be implemented the circulation of vehicles in the four tread.
According to a joint statement from the Directorate of Public Works, Directors for Traffic Affairs and Institute for Municipal Affairs, the new space will “increase the safety and accessibility of pedestrians and traffic”.
The achievement of the project results from the evaluation and interdepartal coordination in the place and the release of the opinions of the Advisory Board for the municipal affairs, the Advisory Board of Community Services and the representatives of the industrial and commercial sectors, as well as the associations of the respective zone.
To articulate with the respective work, part of the Garden of Arts area will be prohibited, according to the execution period. The rest of the garden will remain open. Additionally, from 9:30 am to 5:30 pm, every day, between September 16 and 30 and October 9 and 15, the circulation of vehicles will be subject to traffic conditioning, in the sections of Friendship Avenue, near the Hotel Presidente, and Rua Cidade de Sintra (in front of the Seng Vo building).
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rare artifacts illustrate silk route exchange</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/artefactos-raros-ilustram-intercambio-da-rota-da-seda/</link><description>An exhibition that aims to deepen the ties between China and the West will be inaugurated on the first day of October, at the MGM Poly Museum, integrated on the birthday of the initiative “One Range, a Route”. The show releases the cultural heritage of the Silk Route and is framed by the intangible cultural legacies of the East and the West. The exhibition encompasses four thematic chapters and more than 200 rare artifacts



















Victor Rebelo
 
The intangible cultural legacies of the East and the West will be in evidence in the exhibition “Rotas da Seda Beyond the Borders”, which inaugurates on October 1, at the MGM Poly Museum, inserted in the celebrations of the 12th anniversary of the initiative “Um Track, a Route”.
The show features four thematic chapters and more than 200 rare artifacts, illustrating “vividly the grandeur of millennial civilizational exchange along the silk route”, as a note from MGM says, which adds that the display “incorporates the fundamental values ​​of the silk route, such as peaceful cooperation, opening and inclusion, mutual learning and shared benefits, underlining the lasting relevance of the cultural exchange ”.
Using live performance as a cultural medium, the exhibition gives life to the stories of the Silk Route, combining dynamic staging with static exhibitions of cultural relics. “These immersive night excursions offer a multisensory trip through time, intertwining the rich narratives of the silk route civilization in an experience that transcends time and space,” reads the game operator's text.
Through thematic spaces, the exhibition explores “systematically the history of exchange, the achievements of integration and the future view of the silk route”, narrating the travels of the former pioneers of the silk route and the fundamental role of trade and the exchange of information in maintaining the prosperity of the route along millennia.
Additionally, it highlights material culture, specifically silk weaving, ceramic, lacquer, metallurgy, glass manufacturing and enamel, which promoted “mutual learning and shaped daily life in oriental and western civilizations”.
Likewise, and according to the promotion text, the exhibition explores the spiritual and aesthetic integration of the silk route through images, sculptures and music, along with philosophical reflections found in classical scriptures and texts, demonstrating its deep role in promoting a deeper human dialogue.
Presenting the work of generations of artists, including the Chinese painter known as the “Dunhuang Guardian” Chang Shuhong and his daughter, Chang Shana, the exhibition highlights over 80 years of efforts dedicated to preserving the art of Dunhuang.
Ancient Seda Route's old musical instruments are also presented, such as Konghou with Phoenix's head, five -string kite and rebound kite, “meticulously restored over years of research” by the Chinese musician of world renowned Tan Dun. “Combined with modern symphonic arrangements, these instruments relive the 'silk route sounds' to the contemporary public,” says the disclosure document.
The Poly Museum encourages the public to find out how the material and spiritual heritage of the Silk route enriches contemporary art and supports the creation of a shared global future, rooted in mutual trust, interconnected commerce and intercultural understanding.
Since its inauguration, in November 2024, the MGM Poly Museum has been focused on cultural relics and works of art from countries and regions of the initiative “a track, a route”. Through innovative curatorial approaches and flexible spatial design, the space integrates academic knowledge, educational involvement, artistic expression, entertainment and interactivity, as well as, according to the operator, having established as a cultural milestone in the great bay and a link between oriental and western cultures.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Israelite tanks invade city of Gaza</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/tanques-israelitas-invadem-cidade-de-gaza/</link><description>The Israeli army yesterday began a major terrestrial offensive in the city of Gaza, after the US Secretary of State Marco Rubio warned Hamas that remains a few days to reach an agreement. A month ago, Israel intensified attacks against the main city of the territory, which presents as one of the last strongholds of the Palestinian Islamist movement.
“The main offensive in the city of Gaza began last night. We know that there are thousands of Hamas terrorists,” between 2,000 and 3,000, a military commander said by AFP. “We are moving to the center” of the city, where hundreds of thousands of people still live, he added.
A few hours earlier, Israeli Defense Minister Israel Katz said the largest urban core in the devastated Palestinian territory was "flames" after attacks. "We will not give in and we will not retreat until the mission is accomplished," he said.
Witnesses told AFP “intense and relentless bombardment over the city of Gaza”, which has been largely in ruins after almost two years of war since the fatal attack of Hamas on October 7, 2023, which triggered the conflict.
Before completing his visit to Israel, Rubio promised the “unshakable support” of the US to Israel to eliminate Hamas in Gaza. The guarantee was given in a meeting with Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, who ordered the army to conquer the city of Gaza.
The Secretary of State stated that the diplomatic solution that includes the demilitarization of Hamas is preferred by Washington, but "sometimes when it comes to a wild group (…), this is not possible."
The European powers have unsuccessfully asked Israel to interrupt the new campaign in Gaza, warning of the humanitarian crisis in the territory, where the UN determined last month that one million people face a situation of hunger, a conclusion rejected by the Israeli government.
Yesterday, an independent UN investigation commission accused Israel of committing a "genocide" in Gaza with the aim of "destroying" the Palestinians, blaming Netanyahu and other Israeli leaders. Israel criticized the report, classifying it as "biased and false."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Praised role of Macao and Hengqin in the growth of the great bay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/enaltecido-papel-de-macau-hengqin-crescimento-da-grande-baia/</link><description>The development of the great bay and the cooperation between Macau and Hengqin were the themes of the executive's head at the Industrial and Commercial Conference for the development of the region. Sam Hou Fai said that the two parts are assuming themselves as “the new level” driving the construction of the great bay and encourages the investment of “companies of excellence”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The head of the executive spoke, in a virtual format, at the inauguration ceremony of the 3rd Industrial and Commercial Conference for the development of the Great Bay, and pointed out that “Macau + Hengqin” is assuming “the new example” of the enrichment of the application “a country, two systems”, “the new level” driving the construction of the great bay and “the new platform” to concretize the opening of the country to high quality.
In this sense, he stated that all “excellent companies and quality projects are welcome to invest in Macau and Hengqin, and to share benefits from the development of the region”.
The Government of the Government has revealed that the construction of the Great Bay “is a large planned national strategy, coordinated and promoted by President XI Jinping”, adding that since the publication of the “General Planning for the Development of the Great Bay” have been performed “useful explorations”, which played “a positive role” in the areas of collaboration between Macao and the inland cities to “attract foreign investment”.
In addition, it stressed the importance of promoting “articulation of rules and mechanisms”, reinforcing “infrastructure connectivity”, boosting “integration and innovation of regional transfrances”, dissemination of the “synergistic development of supply chains” and the construction of the Guangzhou-Schenz-Hong-Hong-Hang-Hanging corridor.
Sam Hou Fai also stressed that, with the objective of integration between Macau and Hengqin, the reinforced promotion of the construction of the deepened cooperation zone is an “indispensable component of Macau's deep participation in high quality development of the large bay, being a key point to resolve the development of the proper diversification of Macao's economy”.
In his speech, he also spoke of government plans to launch a set of iconic and important works projects that “freak out driving effects”, namely the construction of the University City, an international tourist and cultural neighborhood, an international air transport hub on the west of Rio das Pearls, and an industrial park for macao sciences and technologies, so that “they become essential components of the high quality development of the large quality. Bay ”.
The seminar, which took place in Canton, is an industrial and commercial event subordinate to the theme of the construction of the Great Bay, created together by the Chinese Council for the promotion of international trade and the governments of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Air Macau joins Airasia online agency</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/air-macau-adere-a-agencia-online-da-airasia/</link><description>Airasia joined Air Macau on the Move Platform, Low-Cost online travel agency, in the context of a direct partnership that perspective the capture of more passengers in Southeast Asia, namely Malaysia
 
Air Macau has become Airasia Move's latest direct partner, online travel agency created by the low-cost carrier that offers several offers, both regarding flights and hotels reserve, transfers to the airport, “duty-free” purchases.
According to the Malaysian group, to celebrate this partnership, Move users will be able to take advantage of flying with Kuala Lumpur Air Macau to Macao through the Airasia Move application, paying only 470 ringgits (almost 900 patacas) by traveling until February 7, 2026.
“Macao is a destination that offers truly unforgettable experiences with its mixture of culture, gastronomy, entertainment and heritage. Having Air Macau on the Move platform as a direct air partner allows us to offer travelers not only convenience, but also the opportunity to explore this incredible city with the best quality-cherry relationship,” said Nadia Omer, CEO of Move, mentioned in an Airas. "We are excited to make Macau more accessible to our users, contributing at the same time to the city's tourist goals," he added.
In the same vein, Howard Zhu, Director-General of Air Macau in Kuala Lumpur, argued that this partnership will allow you to attract Macau more visitors from Malaysia and Asean (Southeast Asian Nations Association) as it will facilitate travel planning in a single application.
Passengers were bound by Air Macau's departure card to enjoy “privileges” on the MSAR, from discounts on restaurants, shopping vouchers and other special resort benefits to special offers on Macao Tower Skypark.
In addition to maintaining direct partnerships with more than 70 airlines worldwide, MOVE has about 700 other carriers through authorized suppliers on its platform. Move was elected in the “World Travel Awards” as “Asia Leading Online Travel Agency” for two consecutive years since its first appointment in 2023.
 
A321neo reinforces fleet of Air Macau
Air Macau has reinforced its fleet with another Airbus A321neo, a model known for the high efficiency. According to the Capa Portal, aviation specializing, the aircraft was delivered to Air Macau on August 29 as part with Air Lease Corporation (ALC), a “leasing” aircraft company that has collaborated with the Macau Air Macao fleet, thus encompassing 22 airbus, all manufactured by Airbus.
 
China Eastern Airlines connects mashed to nanchang
China Eastern Airlines has launched a new route between Macau and Nanchang, the capital of Jiangxi province, operating three calls a week with national production C909. The Chinese company is the only regular operator on this route. The inaugural flight, held last Wednesday, brought to 85 passengers, indicated the society of Macao International Airport (CAM), stressing that the opening of the route marked the first time that a Chinese manufacturing aircraft was used on commercial flights for the MSAR. The weekly flights are held every Wednesday and Fridays and Sundays.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Wynn expands Jingdezen's “charm”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/wynn-expande-charme-de-jingdezhen/</link><description>Under the Macao International Art Biennial, Wynn added new works to its special exhibition “Hello China, Hello Macau - The Porcelain Jingezen Odyssey”, in order to enrich the public experience. The operator hopes that residents and tourists can continue to “experience the charm” of the porcelain Jingezen



















Wynn introduced new works at the special exhibition “Hello China, Hello Macao - Porcelain Jingezen Odyssey: A Macao's Heritage Trip to the World”, inserted in the Macao International Art Biennial program. Some of the artists whose works were already on the show presented new pieces “to offer visitors an artistic experience enriched”, according to a press operator press release.
Master Liu Wei's “Fisherman in the Land of the Pessegueiro Flower” reveals “the diverse and deep beauty of nature” through a “textured interpretation of the landscape”. “Crossing the river with a reed” and the “Guanyin statue” are pieces of blue and white porcelain, made by master Huang Jingzang. Both reflect “superb sculpture techniques” and “the traditional beauty of blue and white porcelain”. Finally, the “mountains and distant waters” vase and the ceramic painting “clouds in pine, Master Liu Wenbin, will leave the audience with“ a stunningly colorful impression ”.
For Wynn, the works “not only demonstrate the contemporary innovations of Jingezen's porcelain art”, but also “invite visitors to reflect on the integration between traditional handicraft and modern art, leading them to a reflective exploitation of cultural origins”. The operator invites "residents and tourists to explore these art treasures and to experience the infinite charm of the porcelain Jingezen", in a show "where history and modernity converge."
In addition, the Qing Dynasty Vessels set, with Taoist and Buddhist symbols that represent “prosperity and longevity” and demonstrate the use of artisanal technique “ormolu”, which consists of gold finishes. Even these porcelain artifacts have already belonged to Elizabeth Montagu, 3rd Duchess of Buccleuch, according to the operator.
The Penva da Paz, the inaugural national gift of Master Chang Shana offered to China, also continues on display. In addition to constituting a symbol of “peace and friendship”, it also represents “China's confidence on the international stage”, integrating traditional Chinese cultural elements into a “powerful fusion between art and culture”.
The show “Hello China, Hello Macau - The Porcelain Jingezen Odyssey”, “has attracted the attention of many art enthusiasts,” since it was inaugurated, according to Wynn. In the same note the operator states that she intends to present "more iconic exhibitions" to give residents and tourists "a more in -depth experience of the fascinating porcelain of Jingdezen."
Wynn's special exhibition includes pieces and sets of more than 30 masters of contemporary Chinese ceramics, such as Lui Ru, Ning Gang and Xu Lan, among others, in a demonstration to the world of “Inheritance and Innovation of Jingezen Porcelain Art”. The free admission show will remain patent on “Illuminarium” and Wynn Palace's “Palace Reserve Club Gallery” by next month.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young site among the award -winning “International Film Camp”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovem-local-entre-os-premiados-international-film-camp/</link><description>The second edition of “International Film Camp” is over, and Jane Zhang was Macao's only participant among the eight winners. Among the selected projects, two came from mainland China and two from Hong Kong



















The Asian Film Awards Academy announced the eight winning short films of the second International Film Camp (IFC), in a closing ceremony that took place at Londoner, according to a press release. Jane Zhang, with the movie "After her," was Macao's only representative among the winners. Participants included 18 young filmmakers from Macau, from the interior of China, Hong Kong, South Korea, Vietname, Bangladesh, India and Kyrguistan.
The list of winners included Hong Kong's Kong Ho Yan and Lam Lo, with the projects “I don't want to grow” and “The Elephant in the Room”, respectively. From the interior of China, they beat Xu Hangcheng with "terrestrial breeze" and Han Tianchu with "The Night Journey." Also selected were the projects “Death in Tokyo” by Phạm Hoàng Minh Thy, Sreeram Pattathil and “Forgive Me, Tynystan Temirzhan,“ forgive me, “forgive me,”.
Under the theme “My Best Friend”, the participants created short films, taking advantage of individual sessions of mentoring, seminars and masterclasses. Each of the eight selected filmmakers received $ 300,000 from Hong Kong to produce their shorts, and the organization will guide the authors of the selected films and promote the projects chosen at international film festivals. In addition, the company “Shaw Studios” will assist winners in post-production work.
According to Sands China, "this year's camp has received an enthusiastic response, and the quality of the scripts and creative proposals presented by the candidates was exceptionally high." During the camp, competitors exchanged ideas and experiences between them, having participated in courses that cover the realization, writing of scripts, financing, distribution, post production and 'pitching'.
Wilfred Wong, president of “Asian Film Awards Academy”, recalled the inaugural edition in 2024 that “produced encouraging results, with several short films shown at festivals throughout Asia and abroad”. "IFC is a true launching platform for aspiring filmmakers," he said. The 18 young filmmakers “gave them all at this year's camp” and “demonstrated a remarkable talent and determination,” he said.
In turn, Grant Chum, executive director of Sands China, stressed that "film art not only captures the essence of beauty and life, but also has the potential to introduce the public to explore new destinations." "We believe that, through the power of cinema, we can attract visitors to Macau to experience their charm as the world center of tourism and leisure," he added. Before congratulating participants, he said that the cultivation of “various artistic talents” could “boost the sustainable growth of the film industry in Macao”.
Hong Kong filmmakers John Chong and Stanley Kwan, as well as veterans Roger Garcia, Anthony Chen, Chan Hing Kai, Mabel Cheung, Brillage Mendoza and Meng Xie were some of the mentors who joined the "camp."</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Renowned jury at the Galaxy Short Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/juri-de-renome-festival-de-curtas-da-galaxy/</link><description>Filmmakers who have left marks in Cannes, Berlin and Venice, and even Oscars, are part of the 2nd International Macao International Festival in Macao that runs until September 21, organized by the Cultural Institute and Galaxy Entertainment
 
The second edition of the Galaxy Entertainment International Film Festival, organized by the Game Operator in conjunction with the Cultural Institute, started on Sunday and lasts until September 21, offering film projections, an industry forum, theme workshops and “MasterClasses”.
The schedule and selection of films are led by an international advisory board, chaired by Jason Anderson, short consultant from Jason Anderson Jason Anderson Anderson Cinema de Toronto International Festival. The advice also includes Gaia Fundo, artistic director of “Giornate Degli Author” (Venice Days), Shen Yang, China's interior curator and producer, Jeremy Chua, curator of the Singapore International Film Festival, Sung Moon, curator of the Jeonju International Film Festival (South Korea) and Giovanna Fulvi, Winnie Lau and Mike Goodridge, curators with experience in film events.
This edition of the festival consists of five sections, which will be evaluated by a “remarkable” jury, according to IC. The "Short Macao" section will present 10 local productions: Chao Koi Wang's "Chuc Chuc"; "Ho Cheok Pan Family", Ao Ka Meng's "Box of Raposa", Teng Kun Hou "Girl with Amen," Pirate 3: Typhoon again "by Ho Wai Tong, Jarvis Xin's" Hand Hand ", Chan Chon Sin, Ho Keung Un," The Performance "by Keo Lou and Waves Under The Sea ”by Chan Si Ieong.
The jury includes Icelandic-German director Gunnur Martinsdóttir Schlüter, whose Fár movie received a special mention at the Cannes Film Festival and won the best short film award at the first edition of the Macao International Film Festival; Danish filmmaker Lsese Lyskjær Noer, named Oscar for best short film with “Knight of Fortune”, and Ben Vandenda, an experienced Belgian short films with over 200 films featured at renowned international festivals such as Berlinale, Cannes and Venice.
In turn, the “New Voices of the Horizon” section will display 26 works from around the world completed between 2024 and 2025, with various themes and encompassing the genres of animation, experimental, fiction and documentary, and which will compete for four awards (best short film, special jury mention, better innovative director and narrative). The jury of this section includes Isabelle Glachant, French international producer and “Unifrance” representative in Greater China; Yov Moor, French colorist, who collaborated with directors, photography directors and producers in works regularly shown in Cannes, Berlinale, Venice, Oscars and other important cinema festivals; and Phạm Thiên an, Vietnamese director who won in the “Fortnight Director” section in Cannes.
The festival will also mark the debut of the “Panorama East Asia” section, with 10 short films that reflect the remarkable cultural dynamism and the unique identity of this region. “This section highlights the role of Macao as 'East Asia City of Culture' and its creative vitality,” says the IC, adding that the jury will be chaired by Wang Muyan, programmer of the performer of the filmmakers in Cannes.
The “Featured Director” section will feature classic films by Japanese filmmaker Nobuhiro Yamashita, including the commemorative screening of the 20th anniversary of “Linda Linda Linda”, while the “Special Sessions” section encompasses “Non -Competitive Works, Rich in Artistic Innovation and Cultural Depth”.
In addition to film screenings, the festival program includes lectures and professional workshops led by renowned director and industry experts.
The films will be shown in the movie theaters of Galaxy Macao and Cinemateca Paixão. Tickets are on sale at the “Enjoy Macao” ticket office (Ticketing.enjoymacao.mo).</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge surpassed 90 million passengers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ponte-hong-kong-zhuhai-macau-superou-fasquia-dos-90-milhoes-de-passageiros/</link><description>The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge has facilitated more than 90 million passenger trips since its inauguration in October 2018, the Xinhua agency reported, citing data from the infrastructure border inspection unit. By Monday, the port of Zhuhai da Ponte had already received almost 18.7 million vehicles. Traffic registered robust growth, with passenger volume reaching 27 million by 2024. This year, the bridge has received 21.2 million passengers, a homologous rise of 19%. Chinese authorities predict the number of trips exceed 30 million by 2025, establishing a new annual maximum. The expansion of individual travel plans from the continent to Hong Kong and Macau significantly boosted tourism through the bridge, refers to Xinhua, noting that since the early 2025 more than nine million residents of the continent have traveled the bridge. The bridge significantly reduced travel time between Hong Kong and Zhuhai, from three hours to just 30 minutes, making it increasingly popular with residents of Hong Kong and Macau for tourism, business, studies and family visits. Trips made by residents of Hong Kong and Macau increased from 4.5 million in 2019 to 16.2 million by 2024, with the figures of 2025 to exceed 12.7 million. Projections for the whole year point to over 18 million trips.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Patane lifting station enters the test phase</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/estacao-elevatoria-patane-entra-em-fase-de-ensaio/</link><description>The construction work of the elevator and box-Cults of the Northern Patane Basin was completed, and there is a survey and rehearsal work, “with a view to obtaining the best result in terms of operation,” according to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI). The body believes that the enterprise will contribute to relieve flooding in the areas of Fai Chi Kei and Lam Bad, caused by heavy rains. The project is divided into three parts, namely, the 170-meter-long box of Patane's northern basin of Patane Basin along the 268-meter-long dock street section, connecting to the rainwater shower on the marginal avenue of Lam Mau. Rainwater in the Box-Culvert in case of heavy rain and its unloading in sea strength, thus relieving the pressure of the drainage systems of Fai Chi Kei, Lam Mau, San Kio and Horta and Costa, ”says AMI. The goal is to reduce floods in those zones, caused by torrential rain. The station also has the function of wastewater interception, simultaneously improving the problem of pollution of coastal waters in the northern basin of Patane. AMI took the opportunity to build another marginal leisure zone, with an area of ​​2,200 square meters and various functions, such as fitness spaces, children's interaction and an observation platform. The area is already open to the public and, at the same time, is linked to the leisure zone of the northern Fai Chi Kei Bay.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/arranca-recolha-de-opinioes-sobre-lag-de-2026/</link><description>Put up collection of 2026 lag
The Government of MSarns is conducting the Governing Action Report for 2026, so today it will begin a collection of opinions, for a month, until October 17, with the aim of obtaining “comprehensively the opinions of all sectors of society and gather social consensus,” says a statement from the Communication Office. Residents may present opinions through the single account and the electronic page (www.mo.gov.mo). "The active presentation of opinions by the population (…) is very meaningful in promoting the stable development of the economy and the constant improvement of the quality of life of the population," says the note.
 
New public roads opened in zone a
New transit measures were implemented on the connecting roads between the peninsula and zone A and on the streets of Zone A, due to the opening of public roads, and the A2 access route has been operated, with circulation in both directions. Similarly, the main arteries of Zone A are open to traffic, namely Tai On Avenue, a part of Doctor Ma Man Kei Avenue and Avenida do Mar de Mirror, among others. There were also traffic lights on Avenida de Tai on. With regard to buses, two new stops near public housing in zone A will be activated with the first match tomorrow, serving three existing careers: 101x, 102x and 103 (previous 103x).
 
Value of currency reserves exceeds 253 billion
MSAR currency reserves were cheered at 235.4 billion patacas in late August, representing an increase of 0.7% compared to rectified data from the previous month, indicates preliminary estimates of the monetary authority. At the end of August, foreign exchange reserves corresponded to about 11 times the monetary circulation. On the other hand, the effective exchange rate of Pataca grew 0.62 points compared to the previous month, but fell 2.44 points within one year.
 
Registered descent in the housing price index
Between May and July, the Global Housing Price Index at MSAR has dropped 1.1% compared to the full period (April to June) and retreated 10.4% in annual terms. According to statistics and census services, the numbers recorded in the peninsula (191.6) were lower than the mud and coloane (203.6), with decreases of 10.3% and 10.6%, respectively. In terms of built housing, the index fell 2.5%, while in the construction year table of buildings there was a decrease of close to 3%.
 
Correios celebrate 76 years of the implementation of the RPC
To mark the 76th anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China, the Directorate of Post and Telecommunications services will have a temporary post on October 1, with the commemorative stamp “celebration of the 76th anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China”. According to CTT, the post will be installed at the central station's filately store from 09h00 to 14h00. In the same place, will be for sale commemorative envelopes to the unit price of five patacas.
 
Hospital das Ilhas organizes Academic Week
The Islands Hospital will hold, on September 27 and 28, its 2nd Academic Week, with the registration is open. More than 1,500 vacancies are available. This edition will be attended by “several renowned hospital directors and famous scholars from China and abroad”. 10 thematic forums will be organized to promote academic discussions around pancreatic diseases, rare diseases, clinical diagnoses, nursing care, development of the Big Health industry, among others. The idea is to “boost technological innovation and clinical research in the medical sector of Macao, thus contributing to the training of specialized medical professionals and Macao medical students, as well as to increase their abilities”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>London inaugurates permanent exhibition space on the life of David Bowie</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/londres-inaugura-espaco-de-exposicao-permanente-sobre-vida-de-david-bowie/</link><description>A permanent exhibition space dedicated to the British rock legend David Bowie opened its doors on Saturday in London, with the ambition to explore the life and work of the artist who died in 2016.

Located in the vast building of the new headquarters of the “Victoria and Albert Museum” (V&amp;A), the space brings together almost 90,000 pieces coming from the personal archives of the singer and composer. Among the objects are garments, sheet music and photographs, as well as valuable letters that document the years when the musician began his artistic career.
Only 200 objects will remain exposed to the public, but visitors have the possibility to consult, if they request, other parts conserved in the archives.
"I don't think I could stand all the setbacks he suffered and keep smiling, still full of trust and combativity," wrote artist's father, Haywood Jones, in a letter sent to a company Bowie expected to work.
Another correspondence, dated July 1968, sent by Apple Records to the artist, demonstrates the rejections he suffered early in his career.
"As we claim on the phone, Apple Records is not interested in hiring David Bowie. We don't consider that he is looking for the moment," says the text.
The exhibition also includes material that documents the influence of the “Let’s Dance” singer on other artists.
“I feel that my whole career was an artistic appeal for you to note,” wrote in a letter to American Pop Star Lady Gaga.
Other documents reveal projects that have never come true, including an adaptation of George Orwell's book “1984”. The artist also included creating a musical inspired by the 18th century London.
Character costumes like Thin White Duke, Ziggy Stardust or guitars were also included in this immersion in the artist's universe.
"We were very lucky that (the file) arrived in a really well organized state," Sabrina Offord told V&amp;A to AFP.
In the 1990s, Offord explained to AFP agency, David Bowie “sent material to his team to include in the file, with notes explaining the context from where this material came and where he thought he should stay,” he added.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-17 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>