<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>“Various problems” identified in DSAT's supervision to special taxis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/identificados-varios-problemas-na-fiscalizacao-da-dsat-aos-taxis-especiais/</link><description>A report from the Audit Commissioner reveals failures by the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs, in Speaking to Special Taxis Services. First of all, there was “non -compliance” in relation to the minimum number of vehicles in circulation, a problem also visible in the taxi call service. Another issue indicated concerns the taxi driving monitoring system. CA has left a number of recommendations to the government organism. Both DSAT and the Radio Taxi Services Company pledged to apply improvements
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) did not properly perform its inspection functions to the Macao Taxi Radio Services Company, according to an Audit Commissioner Report (CA). The data collected, referring to the period from January 2023 to February 2025, reveal “various problems of supervision of special taxis services by DSAT”.
According to the document, “there was a non -compliance with the 'minimum number of vehicles in operation', (…) during this period there was no day when the criterion had been met, particularly serious was the situation during the end hours: the failure rate reached 100% between 8h00 and 8:59 and about 99% between 17h00 and 17:59”.
The concessionaire claimed that "the aging of vehicles was affecting its operation", and the DSAT adjusted the calculation parameter of the "minimum number of vehicles in operation", adopting as one of the elements of the calculation formula the 'minimum number of vehicles able to operate in the month' instead of the 'number of licenses issued' ".
The CA interpreted that this new calculation constituted a “less demanding criterion than that stipulated in concession contracts”. In addition, there were no documents that demonstrated "any formal approval" of the relaxation of the criterion, which was "implemented only in practice." Still and by way of example, during January this year, the adjusted criterion was only fulfilled in a single day.
The Commissioner proceeded to a new analysis based on the adjusted criterion and, in the 783 days analyzed, the blue taxis fulfilled the criterion by just nine, while the red taxis fulfilled only one day. "The number of days needed to comply with the criterion in question was lower than that required in the concession contracts," may be read.
Given that the concessionaire was still in breach of the new criterion, DSAT decided to make a second adjustment, adding that "as long as there were vehicles" waiting ", this would be sufficient to consider that the needs of the population were satisfied."
"The CA consulted DSAT's daily bulletins prepared between January 2023 and February 2025 and found that every day they were registered with regard to the 'minimum number of vehicles in operation', there were certain vehicles 'waiting'." Since “daily newsletters indicated that 'needs were satisfied'”, also “there were no sanctioning procedures for breach of the 'minimum number of vehicles in operation',” the commissioner noted.
 
Problems in Red Taxis Calling Services
However, according to inspection data, when the population proceeds to the immediate call of the special taxis service, the failure rate is quite high, "which means that available" in wait "vehicles do not yet satisfy the demand." "CA randomly examined the red taxi call records for the month of January 2025 presented by the concessionaire to DSAT and found that the average immediate call failure rate of special taxes at different times was over 50%, having even exceeded 90% in the period between 18h00 and 18:59," says the report.
The CA found that "although the passenger is notified that the marking was successful, the dealership does not guarantee, at this time, the attribution of the taxi." In order to resolve this situation, "DSAT required the concessionaire to create a fleet to provide the marking service, and it did not consider that it was not expressly stipulated in concession contracts."
In addition, “DSAT did not sought to guarantee other improvement measures” and the body's inspection “was not proactive, depending only on the monitoring of complaints, rather than using operational records presented by the concessionaire”. The very effectiveness of inspection has been compromised by the “deficiencies in operational records”.
Finally, CA also found that DSAT followed the installation and operation of the “behavior monitoring system and the taxi drivers”, “the installation of this system in a part of the fleet was only completed a year after the operations began”. Of the 200 red taxis with this installed system, "50 were having problems at the level of data loading the alerts to the dealership system."
The CA urged DSAT to take steps to “exploit the special taxis service to be performed in accordance with contractual provisions”, and to resolve the problems with the monitoring system and data use and use. In addition, services should also become aware of the “global situation of passengers who made the successful marking” and for which taxis were not available. The Commissioner also recommended an “exhaustive analysis of the provisions of the current concession contracts and their execution”.
 
Dsat and Radio Taxi ensure improvements
DSAT has pledged to “actively improve, the inspection mechanism” in response to the report. The services are “calculating the 'minimum number of vehicles in operation' based on the operating ratio at different times stipulated in the concession contracts” and will “intensify supervision” and proceed to the sanctions provided for in the contract, assured in a statement.
In addition, DSAT has installed waiting points for special taxis and required the concessionaire “the elimination of the self-established geographical zone for taxi call” and that it “complied with the special taxi service marking procedure”. On the other hand, it indicated that the company has already been sanctioned for the delay in the operation of the special taxis safety equipment.
Ensuring that he will perform “random and proactive checks” of the “behavior monitoring system and the state of driving”, the body also clarified that in May, it identified “44 red taxis with incomplete data load”. DSAT also stated that conductors subject to mandatory training “should increase the formations with testing”, and “additional personnel will be highlighted to treat and reinforce supervision” and an exhaustive revision of concession contracts will be held.
In turn, the Radio Taxi Services Company acknowledged that there are “insufficiency” in the company's services and said that in the future it will be taken into account the expectations of citizens. It will also continue to try to "improve the mechanism and optimize services in accordance with the requirements of the Government of MSAR."
Stressing that over the past eight years, it has made several adjustments to its operational model, the company has admitted that the “current model continues to reflect a growing difference with the evolution of times”. In this sense, "the company will continue to hear the opinions of society, in a humble attitude, and to embrace the challenges."
 
Secretary establishes internal investigation
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, revealed that an internal investigation procedure will be “instituted”, stressing that the direction of services for traffic affairs (DSAT) “assumes full responsibility for the incident”. In a note published by Raymond Tam's office, it is also said that DSAT has already been instructed to “proceed with a comprehensive review of all current procedures, regulations and regimes related to the supervision of the special taxis service”. Tam accused Dsat of presenting "failures and disabilities in the process" and ensured that "the matter will be treated with absolute rigor without any tolerance." In order to correct the “identified deficiencies” and ensure “safeguarding the public interest”, “practical and effective measures will be adopted to strengthen and improve the oversight of the operation of special taxis”, promised the secretary.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao at the top of the 10 “most satisfactory destinations”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-topo-dos-10-destinos-mais-satisfatorios/</link><description>For the first time, Macau occupies the first place in the ranking of the “10 most satisfactory destinations for Chinese tourists on foreign travel 2024”, released by the China Tourism Academy. The territory has risen two places since the last evaluation
 
Macao was the first classified in the list of “10 most satisfactory destinations for Chinese tourists on foreign travel 2024”, released by the China Tourism Academy, after the previous year the territory occupied third position. The destination was especially praised in the categories of “Entertainment and Leisure” and “attitude of local residents”.
The release of the ranking occurred in Beijing, where activities such as the dissemination of research results, thematic lectures and dialogues in the round table were disseminated. "These initiatives allowed the exchange of ideas about the trends of demand for travel abroad and the innovative development of destinations in the New Age," according to a note from the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD).
The subdirector of STD presented the current situation of tourism in Macau, highlighting the intersectoral integration of the concept “Tourism +”, the combined (online and face -to -face) training directed to the sector professionals and the quality tourism assessment program, which has “supported and encouraged the sector to improve the quality of tourist services in the territory”.
Jennifer Si Tou also underlined the role of Macao's courtesy campaign, which encourages residents and sector professionals to receive visitors with "hospitality", reinforcing the image of Macao as a "welcoming" destination.
According to the Academy report on the “10 most satisfactory destinations”, Macau is followed in the classification by China, Singapore, England, New Zealand, Spain, Hong Kong, France, Australia, Malaysia and Argentina.
In the document released, STD states that it will continue to launch measures to “promote the integration of tourism with other sectors”, among which highlights the “diversification of tourist supply”, including the organization of more events, the “promotion of community tourism”, and the “projection of the image of Macau as a city of hospitality and courtesy”.
The China Academy of Tourism, subordinate to the Ministry of Culture and Tourism, is a specialized organism in the investigation of policies and theories related to the sector. It also plays a crucial role in studies on the integrated development of culture and tourism and in the elaboration of statistics and data analysis on both areas.
 
Seminars on retail promote professional level
A series of seminars under the theme “Quality retail sales services 2025” will be promoted between June and the second half of 2025, presenting a total of four lectures. The organization belongs to the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), the Consumer Council (CC) and Sands China, with target audiences to retail sales and tourism -related sectors, including certified stores. Seminars intend, in line with sector development trends, promote the improvement of the level of Macao professionals to raise the degree of satisfaction of residents and visitors in the shopping experience, “generating more tourist consumption”. At the launch ceremony, CC president Leong Pek San stressed that "the exploitation of business with honesty and the provision of quality services are not only crucial to gaining customers' confidence, but also serves as the basis for the healthy development of the sector." For her part, head of the STD Quality Training and Quality Control Department, Doris Leong, pointed out that quality retail and confidence sales services “create a favorable image of Macau as a tourism city and solidify their positioning as a world center of tourism and leisure”.
 
“Feeling Macao” campaign was shown in Hong Kong
Hong Kong received at the weekend the tourist promotion “Feel Macau”, with the theme “Explore Macao in a vibrant summer”. The event was part of two display zones with stage shows and interactive games. The opening ceremony took place at East Point City shopping center. Highlight for the action of Macau singer Vivian Chan, who made known the cultural attractions in fashion in the masters. The program also included a dance performance starring young artists, accompanied by Mak Mak, the Macau Tourism Mascot. Na ocasião, a directora dos Serviços de Turismo, Helena de Senna Fernandes, disse que as duas regiões têm sido “destinos populares entre os seus residentes há anos”, sublinhando que, entre Janeiro e Maio, a RAEM recebeu 3,03 milhões de visitantes provenientes de Hong Kong, com uma média diária superior a 20.000 pessoas.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Psychological support platform under construction later this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/plataforma-de-apoio-psicologico-em-construcao-ainda-este-ano/</link><description>Health services have advanced the plan to start creating the 24 -hour mental health support platform between October and December this year. In addition, this year, also the single account will be integrated in the mental health, depression, anxiety and sleep health
 
It is planned to start in the 4th quarter of this year the construction of the 24 -hour mental health support platform, a project that had already been announced by the secretary for social affairs and culture within the government lines. The information was advanced by Health Services (SSM), explaining that, with the platform, the number of financial support vacancies for psychological counseling will increase and the diagnostic capacity and psychological treatment of health centers will be reinforced.
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Nick Lei, the SSM also said that, this year, mental health, depression, anxiety and sleep health tests, currently available on the “Electronic Mental Health Information Page”, will be integrated into the “My Health” section of the single account. In addition, information on mental health and support for users will be released.
In general, the body has promised that it will reinforce their dissemination and promotion so that more residents can know the channels of access to mental health services in Macau.
On the other hand, according to the SSM, the Institute of Social Action will introduce in day care the project of generalization of education on cognition and management of emotions, intending to see all the work of the project in 2026. The idea is that the work of emotional education begins to be implemented in the services of day care centers.
According to the answer, the preliminary concepts of this project would be presented to the sector this month. Then, through preliminary training, day care workers can master the applied knowledge and techniques. In addition, professional institutions will be charged, in the 4th quarter of this year, to provide advanced formations, as well as to elaborate the manual for education in the systematic plans for activities for the development of emotions of children, the guidelines of assistance and complementary information for the use of day care centers.
In terms of professional personnel linked to mental health, the body led by Alvis Lo renewed the promise of continuing to form more medical psychiatry specialists and reinforce the construction of the mental health team. According to the SSM reiterated by 2024, 16 psychiatry specialists and 25 superior psychology technicians were recorded at the SSM, as well as six psychologists in other public services; Already in the private sector, there are three doctors specialists of psychiatry and 58 psychologists.
In total, there are currently 108 mental health professionals in the territory, who, in collaboration with different parts, can meet the needs of residents in the context of mental health services, the SSM assured.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Gastronomy Party brings together 34 creative cities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festa-da-gastronomia-reune-34-cidades-criativas/</link><description>More than 30 cities in two dozen countries will be present at the International Festival of the cities of Gastronomy, which will take place between 11 and 20 July at the fishermen's dock. The Director of STD mourned the absence of the Portuguese city of Santa Maria da Feira
 
Subordinate to the theme “Expertise and Aromatic Herbs”, the “International Festival of the Cities of Gastronomy, Macau 2025”, organized by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), will take place from July 11 to 20, at the Fisherman's Dock. The event will bring together 34 creative cities of gastronomy from 21 countries distributed by six continents, seven cities in other creative areas and two candidates for the interior network of China, along with two designated as “East Asia Cultural City 2025”.
At the party's press conference, STD director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes lamented that the city of Santa Maria da Feira, in Portugal, decided not to join the festival. Agenda incompatibilities will be at the base of the decision, which thus leaves Portugal outside this event, which has a budget of 27.8 million patacas, more 7% than in 2024.
Brazil will be represented by four cities: Florianópolis, Belém, Paraty and Belo Horizonte. In Brazil there are "only four cities" recognized as creative cities in gastronomy of UNESCO and "all of them will be here," said the director of STD.
Chefs from 28 creative cities of gastronomy will hold more than 60 culinary demonstrations for the public in the Roman Coliseu Square and the Legend Boulevard of the Macao fishermen's dock. This year's edition will focus on the role of spices and aromatic herbs as essential ingredients in the world's cuisines.
"There will be more than 100 newsstands, of which 25 from the interior of China (including Chengdu, Shunde, Yangzhou, Huai'an and Chaozhou), nine from Asia (including Phuket, Thailand; Hatay, Turkey; Buadia, from Saudi Arabia, and Iloilo, Filipines) and 52 from Macau with local gastronomy," he said. the STD. This year were also added 11 newsstands from Portuguese -speaking countries (including from the four cities of Brazil) and six game operators.
In addition, lectures from the International Gastronomy Forum will be held on the 14th, under the theme “The Flavor of Life: Macao Culinary Connections”.
The international party will have five meal zones with a total of a thousand sites sitting, an annual increase of 42% of the capacity, to be able to welcome more visitors and residents. There will also be exhibitions on the three stages of the event, including Portuguese folk dances, music groups, rope jump and street dance, along with interaction with puppets, magic tricks and clown balloon modeling.
Macao has been recognized as a creative city of gastronomy by UNESCO since 2017. At the time, the organization underlined the “important experience” that Macau has in the holding of large -scale cuisine -related events, such as “the Macao Gastronomy Festival; a striking event that brings together local and international chiefs and the main stakeholders of the entire sector of all to Asia and Europe”.
"Other important festivals are the Lusofonia Festival, which promotes and exchanges cultural knowledge between the countries and regions of Portuguese Language, and the Myanmar and Southeast Asian cooking and culture festival," said Unesco.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cesl Asia Children's Contest challenges “future urban planners”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concurso-infantil-da-cesl-asia-desafia-futuros-urbanistas/</link><description>Cesl Asia again promotes another children's drawing contest, entitled “Future Urbanists” to inspire the next generation to project a sustainable and dynamic future for Macau
 
In order to encourage creativity and imagination among the younger ones, and simultaneously increase awareness of sustainable development, Cesl Asia, in collaboration with the Macao Youth Art Association, launched the 2025 Children's Design contest - “Futures Urbanists”, whose inscriptions are open until 1 August. With this year's theme, young people between eight and 14 years are invited to put themselves in place of urban planners of tomorrow.
“The contest challenges them to reimaginate the urban environment of Macao, perspecting a sustainable city that integrates ecological spaces, intelligent city technologies and a community-focused urban design, materializing a vision where innovation, nature and people coexist in harmony,” says a note by Cesl Asia.
“We hope to inspire children early in thinking about sustainability and considering better urban design and engineering can bring lasting benefits to society. This drawing contest is more than an art competition, it is a platform to stimulate young minds and encourage the next generation to participate in the construction of a dynamic future for Macao,” said António Trindade, president and CEO of Cesl Asia.
This edition marks a remarkable milestone, as it coincides with the 25th anniversary of Cesl Asia's social investment initiative (CSII), a pioneering impact investment program launched in 2000. To cultivate Cesl Asia's fundamental leadership capabilities, CSII highlights the company's contribution to the development of local talents and the growth of a more resilient, inclusive and innovative community.
The children's drawing contest became an emblematic activity of CSII, using creative education to increase awareness among children on social and environmental issues. The event is supported by the Macao Technology Productivity and Technology Transfer Center, IPOR - Portuguese Institute of the East, Macau - Professional Services, Limited, University of São José, the sponsorship of McDonald's Macau, and has as its partners the Jornal Tribuna de Macao and Macau Daily Times.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pop Mart activity has already yielded 600 million</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/actividade-pop-mart-ja-rendeu-600-milhoes/</link><description>Near 470,000 users participated in offline consumption and their raffles in the scope of “Pop Mart Macao Citywalk” activity. In total, a consumption of about 600 million patacas has already been registered. The campaign is about to enter the second phase, in which different prizes will be launched
 
Pop Mart Macao Cirtywalk intellectual property activity, launched by the Tourism Services Directorate (STD) at the beginning of June, recorded, by the 24th, a total of close to 470,000 users, who consumed over 600 million patacas.
The 108 -day program, which will end in September, will enter the second phase, "in which different gifts will be provided for raffles," according to the STD director.
Making the point of the situation of the activity, Helena de Senna Fernandes points out that part of the amount raised may serve to support the Zape zone in the program intended for community tourism, assigned to “travel by macao”. He also added that he is being discussed with travel platforms from the interior of China the launch of hotel campaigns in this area, as well as discounts for guests.
Regarding the forecast for this year of the volume of visitors, which pointed to 39 million, emphasized that "if the results are satisfactory between July and August will be possible the total number of visitors in 2025 returned to the level recorded in 2019".
The STD director considers that Macao "needs more types of consumption" and expects, in the future, "more diverse and cultural and creative elements for high standard consumption can be introduced in the future."
For example, he said that, currently, every 100 patacas spent by a visitor, about 45 were used to shop, 23 for accommodation and 23 for meals, which means that, for another type of consumption, the money spent by tourists "represents a relatively low percentage."
On the other hand, it has revealed that authorities have already begun planning intellectual property cooperation projects for next year, intending to do so diverse, in various periods of the year and in different zones, with the aim of “stimulating new types of consumption”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>17 hotels receive “green” prize</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/17-hoteis-recebem-premio-verde/</link><description>The “Hotel Green Macau 2024 Award” distinguished the “Environment Friends” measures adopted by 17 projects
 
Seventeen hotel units were rewarded by the efforts and contributions in the environmental promotion and in the realization of the “double carbon goal”, under the “Hotel Verde Macau 2024 Award”. Six gold prizes were awarded (MGM Macau, Nuwa, Morpheus, Countdown, Sands and Okura), two silver (Grand Emperor and Broadway) and four bronze (Riviera, Legend Palace, Waldo and Crowne Plaza).
The list also includes two Merit Awards (Yoho Treasure Island and City Viva), two “Green Pension” (Holiday Inn Express and I Fu) and a “Basic Measures Certificate” (City Pension).
According to the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA), since the creation of this initiative, in 2007, the number of awarded hotels has risen from eight to current 58, “effectively boosting the sector to implement environmental management and reduce carbon emissions”. The body also stressed that, in total, the electricity consumption of participating hotels has dropped about 370 million kilowatts hour, the equivalent of 220 million kilograms of reduced carbon emissions and the volume of carbon absorbed annually by 10 million trees.
"Almost 60% of award hotels have already conducted carbon audits and developed decarbonization strategies based on the analyzed results. Some extended the scope of audits to suppliers and business partners," said DSPA in a statement.
Some hotels have promoted the use of clean energy to “raise environmental efficiency”, namely changing to natural gas and installing photovoltaic solar panels. At the same time, they foster the use of electric vehicles and have increased electricity charging facilities.
So far, the “green” hotels have already installed, in total, close to 540 charging places (including moped and electrical motorcycle facilities), representing a climb more than 80% compared to last year. Some hotels also already have moped battery cabinets and electrical motorcycles for exchange.
Regarding the reduction of waste and resource recycling, several award hotels no longer provide bottled water in disposable plastic bottles in the rooms. Even some have created lines of water production bottled in glass bottles that can be reused.
In addition, it emphasizes DSPA, all award -winning hotels have implemented resource recycling, including paper, plastic bottles, aluminum cans and batteries. The total accumulated volume of recycling reached about 82,000 tons, which is equivalent to the weight of 20,000 small buses. More than 60% of award -winning hotels implemented the recycling of food waste and part of them installed machines to treat food remains.
The candidacy period for the “Hotel Verde Macau 2025 Award” takes place between July 1st and August 15th. The prize is valid for three years.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More 150 graduates from the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-150-graduados-pelo-instituto-de-enfermagem-kiang-wu/</link><description>Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, the LAM, at the undergraduate ceremony of the Kiang Wu Institute of Macao of the school year 2024/2025.



In the school year 2024/2025, almost 150 students from the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute graduated. In a speech given on this occasion, the secretary for social affairs and culture stated that the government will continue to improve the nursing framework system
 
About 150 students graduated from the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute of Macao in the school year 2024/2025, 87 of which undergraduate, Master's degree and 39 graduates of the course for the formation of dementia care managers.
At the undergraduate ceremony held on Saturday, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, said that in the future, the government will continue to support the development of the institution and to improve the nursing framework system, in order to create a better environment for professional development and career ascension.
Noting that, with the deepening of the construction of the large bay, the nursing sector gained new development opportunities, the secretary also encouraged the Institute's students to actively integrate into the development of the region, showing the talents on a wider platform and realizing their dreams.
In addition, LAM praised the institution for continually innovating the teaching model, closely monitored the most up to date development of international nursing education, and created a multilevel and comprehensive nursing -centered curriculum system and coordinated with other health courses. Generally speaking, the ruler stressed that the institution obtained “remarkable results” in teaching, scientific investigation and the provision of services to society.
Also in this ceremony, Lau Veng Seng, Chairman of the General Council of the Kiang Wu Nursing Institute, gave a speech, in which he stressed that the Institute will launch interdisciplinary courses in line with international standards, in order to cultivate comprehensive nursing and gerontology talents corresponding to the needs of an aged society and the development of intelligent medicine.
In turn, Van Iat Kio, president of the institution, stressed that the institute will actively integrate artificial intelligence technologies in nursing education, providing strong support for the promotion of the “Big Health” industry and the construction of the healthy city by the Government of MSAR.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SYNO-LUSOPHONE BACKGROUND ACCESS will have “more flexible” rules</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/acesso-fundo-sino-lusofono-tera-regras-mais-flexiveis/</link><description>Economic cooperation between China and Lusophone countries depends on governments, stressed the Secretary-General of the Macao Forum in an interview with Lusa, stiving that the body “is not a promotion agency”. Ji Xianzheng also stressed that the cooperation fund created in 2013 will have “more flexible” rules and “more diverse” forms of application ”
 
The Secretary General of the Macao Forum imputes to national governments the responsibility for conducting development and economic cooperation policies. In an interview with Lusa, Ji Xianzheng attributes criticism to the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries to an wrong interpretation of the body's mission, stressing that "the forum is a cooperation mechanism between central governments."
"A lot of people think it is to the secretariat that it is up to the policies, but we have a limited number of people," he added.
"The secretariat has no investment projects, it is a mechanism for preparing the ministerial conference, connecting with governments, not a promotion agency. It has not been thought of, connects with the promotion agencies. We are four people sent by China and one delegate for each country," he said.
At the last ministerial conference, in April 2024, then Portuguese Economy Minister Pedro Reis argued that the Portuguese Language China-Parais Cooperation and Development Fund should bet more on small and medium enterprises (SMEs). The Cooperation Fund was created in 2013 by the China Development Bank and the Macao Industrial and Commercial Development Fund, with a thousand million dollars, of which about 60% have already been invested, according to the secretary general.
Ji admitted that SMEs are "a difficult theme for any government" and that "international cooperation for the promotion of development and cooperation of small and medium enterprises is even more difficult. It is a theme that is being debated daily worldwide." But admitted, "here, little."
"But it is stipulated in the action plan [2024-2026]. It is up to central governments and commerce chambers, promotion agents, to work together to do this. The secretariat assumes responsibility as authorized by the central governments, specifically, in the activities program," he said.
Politicians from various countries have appealed to a change in the rules of the fund candidacy. The current rules require, for example, that candidate projects have a minimum investment of $ five million, and the fund only covers 20% of total investment, referring the rest to governments or companies.
The new direction of the Fund “is committed to promoting a broader investment, with better coverage for all forum countries, [relatively] to projects that have a strategic or significant impact on the socioeconomic development of participating countries,” said Ji.
According to the secretary general, "the terms of application [of the rules of access to the background] will be more flexible and the forms of application will also be more diverse." “Instead of being just direct investment, they are also studying ways to apply the fund, in cooperation with other funds or with other financial institutions,” he gave as an example.
"This fund has an operation according to market rules. It is not a humanitarian aid fund. Therefore, it has to guarantee the minimum benefit return. But on top of that, they are very open to study, in this case, the conditions of each project," he added, but to give examples of "flexibility of rules."
 
Forum did not discuss Hispanic countries
On the other hand, Ji Xianzheng said the Macao Forum “never discussed” to create an entity to widen the Hispanic countries to promote economic cooperation similar to those who provide the China-Parais Lusophone connection.
The official acknowledged that, "in society, there were some conversations to discuss or address the possibility of promoting more contact and cooperation with Spanish -language countries, but at the Forum level we have never addressed this theme."
The Executive of the MSAR announced in mid -April the intention to create a center to promote economic services between China and the countries of Portuguese and Spanish languages ​​in Hengqin. The idea is to provide companies in Hispanic countries services in the “linguistic, legal, fiscal, verification of compliance with norms, formation, arbitration and mediation”, according to the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong.
Days earlier, Macao Government leader Sam Hou Fai had also announced the intention of “promoting exchange and cooperation” through Macau, between China and Spanish -speaking countries.
Although Macau wants to widen focus to Castilian -speaking countries, "the forum will remain the Forum for China and Lusophony countries," Ji said, clarifying that the institution he directs "can contribute to Macao's greater opening in international cooperation," as the intention announced by the New Government of MSc.
Personally, he said he had “all the pleasure of working with all parties”, but stressed that this is a “decision that is up to central governments to make” and that the forum has never been contacted in this regard.
“I worked in Latin America, Spain, nine years in Madrid and Caracas. But this is not a decision of personal interest, it is up to politicians to make the decision,” he said, explaining that the idea will be to promote the relationship between Macao and Brazil and then to other Latin American countries, as well as expanding the relationship with Portugal to Spain.
"There is no limit. The Macao Forum is complementary. It does not restrict any promotion of the cooperation of the other parts," he said.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Six projects in a “race” from Macau to Venice</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seis-projectos-numa-corrida-vai-de-macau-veneza/</link><description>Six teams were selected for the “Local Curator Project” of the Macao Art Biennial, being also pre-qualified for the 2026 edition of the Venice Biennial
 
The “Local Curator Project” contest, one of the most important programs of the 2025 Macao Art Biennial, attracted 34 proposals, six of which were eventually selected by the jury, composed of Feng Boyi, main curator of the Biennial, Wang Xiaosong, executive director of the Suzhou Contemporary Art Museum, Song Dong, conceptual contemporary artist, Marcel Feil, Dutch Independent Curator, and Van Pou Lon, Head of the Division of Development of the Visual Arts of the Cultural Institute (IC).
In addition to being presented at the Macao Art Biennial, the exhibitions proposed by the six teams were directly qualified for the preliminary selection with a view to participation in the Macao collateral event of the 61st International Art Exhibition of Venice, which will take place between May 9 and November 22, 2026. The CI will create another jury to choose the proposal that will represent Macau at the event in Italy.
Involving a total of 35 artists, the list of chosen proposals includes “genetic duration”, curated by UNG Vai Meng; “Behind the Eastern Garden,” by Cheong Weng Lam; “Language Sea: He Yan Jun and Zhang Ke's Linguistics Program; “An enunciable position for women,” by Cheong Cheng We and Wang Jing; “Under the Wetware Peninsula,” by Daisy Di Wang and Wong Mei Teng, and “Jacone Tower”, curated by Feng Yan and NG Sio Ieng.
According to the IC, "the selected proposals exploit the relationship of dialogue between Macao's historical memory and globalization, encompassing a wide range of aspects such as cultural genes, linguistic landscapes, women's narratives, as well as technology and ecology." The jury considered that this year's proposals have “good quality, with experimental and insightful curatorial methods, fully corresponding to the theme of the Biennial, 'Hello, what do you do here?'”.
Under the secretary's sponsorship for the social affairs and culture of MSAR, organized by the IC and co-organized by the Directorate of Tourism Services and the six game operators, the Macao Art Biennial is divided into six sections: “Main Exhibition”, “Public Art Exhibition”, “Special Exhibition”, “Local Curator Project” and “Collateral Exhibition”.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural Fusion at the German Institute in Lisbon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fusao-cultural-instituto-alemao-em-lisboa/</link><description>José Joaquim Monteiro Júnior at the German Institute. Photo Kathine Cheong_Macau / Experimental Theater



The “Goethe-Institut” of Lisbon welcomed, last Thursday, the third journey in Portugal from “BPM”, a cycle that crosses makeshift music and poetry in several languages. With an event that remembered the hybrid spirit of Berlin, the “Macau Experimental Theater” (“small town” experimental theater group) led to Lisbon poets from Macau and Europe. Names like Li I, Si Tou Chi ü, J. J. Monteiro and Heiner Müller had their voices, present and evoked, with the organization promising an experience of "transfrontic listening."
In the presence of Jana Binder, director of the German Institute, Cheong presented Tertulia as "an affective intertwining between Berlin, Macao and other listening geographies." "The strength of the meeting lies in the urgency of respecting and celebrating the multiplicity of tongues-not as a mere music, but as a living and political matter of contemporary feel," said the project co-cure.
Accompanied by the guitar of Alcides Miranda, the first session was starred by Li I and Si Tou Chi ü, authors of Macao who first acted in Europe in the context of “BPM”. In a performative recital, the two young poets read excerpts from their tales “Bones Without Master” in Mandarin and “Dannie de Souza” in Cantonese.
“Bones Without Master”, first published in the newspaper or Mun in 2023, reports as a feminine “self” runs away from a friend, which becomes a melancholy search for itself and by lost memories in the city of Shanghai. In turn, “Dannie de Souza” tells, in the first person, how an old student had a passion not corresponded by a Luso-descendant Macanese teacher, addressing desires, memories and separation.
The “Dannie de Souza” tale was selected for the Macau Foundation's official literary anthology and 2021 and 2022 Cultural Institute, exclusively for Chinese language works.
Reiterating the curatorial concept of “translingualism”, Cheong recited a poem in a language mixed in German, French, English and Portuguese, generated by AI from the history of the authorship of Si Tou Chi ü. Marta Stanisława Sala, set scenographer of the two meetings, presented an unprecedented translation of the Cantonese poem “The Umbilical Cord (a set of poems)”, also of Si Tou Chi ü.
 
J. J. Monteiro sung by his son
In the late afternoon of the second session, J. J. Monteiro was the target of tribute. The author was represented by his son, José Joaquim Monteiro Júnior, “doctor by profession and man marked by a singular cultural and personal heritage”, reads in a brochure offered to the public.
Admirer of his father's work declared, in Portuguese, “Teresa”, a husband's poem-plating for his wife's death, expressing pain, longing and the hope of a reunion in eternity. If I'm back to recite a Cantonesa version.
José Joaquim Monteiro Júnior also sang “The City of Macau”, a letter created in 1939 by the “Soldado Poet” Muroseiro and Macaense, adopting the song “March of Alfama”. Marta Sala, a Berlin -based Polish artist, presented a version that mixes several European languages, including Polish.
Under the theme “dialogue”, the public participated in the “without stage show” with the sonnets of Camões and the verses not only of Jose Régio or Junqueiro War, but also from the German playwright Heiner Müller or the Serbian poet Siniša Gavrić. Li I made a point of highlighting, in English, the literary work of Brazilian poet Maria Giulia Pinheiro, with whom she became “good friend” through “BPM” in Lisbon.
“It gave me goose bumps,” Cheong Kin Man confessed at the end of the event, “Gonçalo Pinto's Electronic Music, who interacted with this meeting to gather the ancient and modern macaus, to interconnect the traces of the many ways that could not even imagine.” "It was powerful to hear voices in so many languages ​​in such a constellation that transcends the borders," he concluded.
Held at the Garden of Germany's Cultural Representation in Lisbon, the two events had the support of the MSAR Culture Development Fund and the “Goethe-Institut Portugal”, as well as a Babel-Cultural Association disclosure partnership.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>First simulacrum in the new prison, it took place with “Success”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/primeiro-simulacro-na-nova-prisao-decorreu-sucesso/</link><description>Coloane's new prison was received a large -scale emerging incident simulacrum under the name of code “Joint Operation - Lightning 2025”. This was the first large-scale interdepartal emergency exercise carried out since the change of facilities to Ká-Hó had 419 people and, according to Unit Police services, took place with "success."</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2425/</link><description>Police dismantle network of telephone burlas
Macao and Hong Kong authorities dismantled a network of telephone burla, which has been using the disguise of customer support service staff, and nine fraudulent messaging points were dismantled. In Macao, the Judiciary Police (PJ) detained a total of seven members of the group and dismantled four illegal points. In addition, 68 message issuing machines, 24 mobile phones, more than 5,000 mobile cards and video surveillance cameras were found. The PJ believes that in Hong Kong and Macau the burlans made 168 victims, which will have lost more than 22 million patacas. At Raehk, police received at least 20 complaints.
 
84 candidates in the race to direct suffrage from AL
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) posted on Saturday the list of candidacies to the election of September 14. The eight lists are composed of 84 candidates, who will compete for the act in the field of direct suffrage. With regard to indirect suffrage, and there are two lists of the work sector, for the other sectors only one was presented. On July 15 will be released the results of verification of the applications based on the opinion of the State Security Commission. Regarding the decision on the process of verifying the definitely admitted lists, it will be published between July 18 and 31, said Caeal.
 
New Round of subsidy for vulnerable families
The Institute of Social Action (IAS) will accept, between 1 and 21 July, requests to assign the second phase of the special subsidy of the “Community Inclusion and Harmony Program” for 2025. The program is intended for three types of families in vulnerable (single, with disabled members and chronic) families who receive regular allowance or have a salary not exceeding a certain multiple of social risk value. The beneficiaries of the regular subsidy of IAS and the 1st phase of this program do not need to submit the request. According to IAS, the values ​​of granted subsidies range from 2,650 to 10,100 patacas, respectively, for families with a member and with eight or more people.
 
Hengqin clinic can already accept health valleys
Health Services (SSM) authorized the adhesion to the “Health Care Reimbursement Program” of a doctor with a clinic in the deepened cooperation zone, in the first case of the genre after the government decided to extend the scope of health valleys to Hengqin. According to the SSM, all residents of Macao can already use health valleys in that clinic through the single common access account. Acceptance of health valleys in hengqin implies that clinics in the cooperation zone are consisting of MSAR residents who hold, individual or jointly, in accordance with the relevant interior of China.
 
Temporary housing open to visits in the black sand
The temporary dwelling project in the Plado Sand Lot has been completed and is currently in the final survey phase. According to Macau Urban Renewal, the model's visits to model apartments have already been opened, allowing the public to personally explore the spatial configuration and support facilities for temporary housing. Visits can be made from tomorrow, taking place between 09h00 and 13h00 and between 14:30 and 18h00, from Monday to Saturday, and should be scheduled at least two days in advance. Composed of eight towers, with heights ranging from 37 to 50 floors, the venture has 2,803 units and offers a variety of recreational and leisure facilities.
 
Sarau of the 25 -year -old from the award -winning manda in Shanghai
The show “Macau sings with joy for the future: Cultural Sarau in celebration of the 25th anniversary of the return of Macau to the Fatherland”, organized by the government and produced by China Media Group, won the special award of the 30th edition of the Shanghai Television Festival. According to the organizing committee, through various art forms such as songs, dances, instrumental music, Chinese opera, martial art, narratives and musical theater, among others, the exhibition “demonstrated the voices of love to the homeland and the macao of all the sectors of the territory”. The Sarau director said the program took over a year to be produced. "In the future we will continue to recall the responsibility and mission of cultural and artistic workers in the New Age and work to create more high quality cultural and artistic programs and programs," said Zhang Ji.
 
Hou Kong School in Hengqin increases number of students
The Hou Kong School Hungqin School of Affiliate Hou Kong will increase, in the teaching year 2025/2026, the number of places for students from 200 to 600. The director of the school, IAO Tun Ieong, revealed that classes will be opened for the first three years of primary education, and for both the level of primary and children, the school will make available a teen. classes.
 
UMA Campus may have intelligent border
The possibility of building a new intelligent border post of the University of Macao campus in Hengqin, as well as the creation of a Macao Airport terminal at Hengqin, were some of the projects discussed at the first group meeting exclusively for the innovation and development of cooperation between Hengqin and Macao stations and the facilitation of border tickets. Both parties reached an agreement on the constant optimization of Hengqin's infrastructures. According to it was revealed, the proposals discussed obtained a broad consensus, and several new projects were defined, including the acceleration in the implementation of border passages of people without document presentation and the expansion of the border.</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China launches first 4 year course on pets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/china-lanca-primeiro-curso-de-4-anos-sobre-animais-de-estimacao/</link><description>China's Agricultural University (CAU) launched China's first company -focused undergraduate program to satisfy the growing need for animal industry talents, CCTV News said.
Offered by the Faculty of Animal Science and Technology of the China Agricultural University, the program will last four years, with graduates receiving the degree of Bachelor of Agricultural Sciences.
It covers courses on genetic improvement, nutrition and metabolism, feed processing, reproductive physiology and welfare and behavior of company animals. In 2025, the program will have 50 undergraduate students.
"Company animals, who live with humans, maintain close communication and emotional exchanges, and bring happiness to people's lives, so they are often called pets. That's why this program is commonly called a specialization in 'pets'," said Professor Liu Guoshi, vice-rector of Cau's Faculty of Animal Science and Animal Technology.
Professor Liu said the new specialization is aligned with the needs of the market. The pet industry has become a new driving force of animal science, with a huge demand for professionals with experience in company animal care.
"In addition, there is a growing demand for pet -related professionals at universities, research institutions, veterinary clinics and relevant management departments," he added.
A member of the CAU Faculty of Animal Faculty and Technology team said the program's curriculum focuses on animals such as cats, dogs and horses. Graduates are expected to have access to pet-related companies and equestrian clubs.
Previously, CAU offered programs similar to the “pets” course, including a master's degree in Company at the Yantai Institute in Shandong Province, and a high school science high school, both always well received.
Research shows that by 2024 the urban pet consumption market (dogs and cats) in China exceeded 300 billion yuans, with an annual growth rate composed of 11.9% in the last decade. In addition, there are over 500,000 pet -related companies across the country.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>