<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Public projects represent 74% of environmental impact reports</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/projectos-publicos-representam-74-dos-relatorios-de-impacto-ambiental/</link><description>DSPA received 14 environmental impact assessment reports in 2024, an annual increase of six that contradicts the decline recorded in 2022 and 2023. Since 2009, 191 reports have been presented, with public projects representing 74% of the total
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Throughout 2024, they entered the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA) 14 Environmental Impact Assessment Reports (AIA), six more than the previous year. This increase interrupts a two -year break cycle, as this type of studies decreased from 17 by 2021 to 13 by 2022 and only eight by 2023.
According to official data published on the DSPA Electronic Page, between 2009 and the end of 2024, 191 projects for environmental impact assessment were submitted, representing an annual average of 11.9. Within 16 years, about 74% of the total environmental evaluations involved public entities, with the remaining 26% integrated into the private sphere, reveals the body, stressing that this panorama proves the “initiative” of public services to promote studies of aia in the projects they develop.
The lowest number of AIA dates back to 2009, with a total of five reports, before entering a phase of ups and downs: 14 in 2010, 11 in 2011, seven in 2012, 13 in 2013, eight in 2014, 12 in 2015 and six in 2016. This environmental protection tool gained a new momentum in 2017 (16 reports) and 2018 (18), eventually reaching the peak in 2019 (22). However, in 2020, the first year of the pandemic, there was a break at just seven.
DSPA presented in 2011 a “exploratory text” for the creation of an environmental impact evaluation regime and, two years later, released a list of types of projects subject to AIA, which was tested on public projects. After a new review of the evaluation list, in 2017 the reports also started to cover private projects.
On January 1 this year new rules were adopted, in order to make the AIA list “more operational and closer to Macao's development situation”. According to DSPA, the new adjustments took into account the experiences of the interior of China and neighboring regions, as well as the opinions of public services, associations and related sectors.
By organizing a new relevant/expansion/expansion construction plan for the existing project (including demolition, if applicable), the entity promoting the contract will have to determine whether or not there is the need to prepare an evaluation report of the Environmental impact, in accordance with the AIA list. According to DSPA, relevant/expansion remodeling refers to “the demarcation of the area, plant or changes in the design of the project that may eventually cause significant environmental impacts in places with high ecological value”, or when, in the lack of Mitigation measures, pollutant emission is likely to cause “serious adverse impacts on the environment”.
The new list is divided into three parts: projects of establishment (new buildings or large remodeling/expansions); demolition projects; and establishment projects in a given zone (which include new buildings or large remodeling/expansions). The projects contained in the first two parts are subject to the evaluation of the environmental impact, however, in the third part, “the promoter must first present a brief description and data from the project, for the competent authorities to determine whether or not the need to evaluate the environmental impact ”.
In general, the AIA report is "elaborated by an independent (third) entity, specialized and believed, in order to represent its independence and credibility." Technical evaluation should cover factors related to air and water quality, noise, ecology in general, solid waste and soil pollution.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Domestic workers expect government to “open the dialogue”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/trabalhadoras-domesticas-esperam-governo-se-abra-ao-dialogo/</link><description>Jassy Santos, president of the progressive union of domestic workers in Macau, expects the new government to hear the "voice" of domestic workers and can open to dialogue. This after sending a letter to DSAL with seven suggestions to improve the working conditions of maids and the government organism has said that rights and interests are already guaranteed by law
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The president of the Progressive Union of Domestic Workers in Macau, Jassy Santos, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that he expects the new government, led by Sam Hou Fai, to “open the dialogue” - this after almost at the end of last year Having received a non -response from the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) after sending a letter with some suggestions to improve the conditions of these workers in the territory. Orders included, for example, that households can only work a maximum of 12 hours a day, a minimum wage of 5,500 patacas and compulsory medical insurance.
“With the new government, we liked to hear our voice and open to the dialogue. Our role is to suggest and we are looking forward to sitting with the authorities and discussing what is happening to domestic workers, ”said Jassy Santos, stressing that it would be important that his work be" recognized. " “We need social welfare. We hope this can happen in the near future, ”he added.
In the letter sent to the Dsal released by “All About Macau” and to which this newspaper had access, the association also claimed standard and legal contractual conditions, as well as a housing, food and transportation allowance, worth 1,000, 1,200 and 300 patacas, respectively. It also asked for at least four days off per month and the right to mandatory holidays and annual holidays.
In addition, it asked that in the case of termination of a contract without just cause, article 70 of the Labor Relations Law, which provides for the calculation of compensation, and that the period of the written contract applicable to non -resident workers ( TNR) was applied to households. This contract “must include a stipulation that workers must enjoy 13 months salary and that after the termination of the contract, the remuneration of domestic workers must be calculated in the same way provided for in article 70”, may be read.
In response, Dsal stated that domestic workers in Macau are already protected by law. Regarding working hours, the body said that employers and domestic workers may sign an agreement, but the 30 -minute rest of 30 minutes and a rest time of 10 consecutive hours or total time not less 12 hours a day. "If agreements are not signed, domestic workers should not work more than eight hours a day or more than 48 hours a week," he said.
Regarding the issue of dismissal without just cause, DSAL stated only that, according to the law, employers have an obligation to pay compensation. He concluded that, "in the future the government will listen carefully to opinions regarding the revision of the Labor Relations Law and will consider the issue in accordance with the real situations of society."
Given the answer, Jassy Santos said, quoted by the “All About Macau”, was “dissatisfied and disappointed”, understanding that the body only chose to repeat the legal provisions that are already known to the workers. He also noted that Dsal did not fully respond to seven suggestions.
Jassy Santos has lamented that, even if, according to the authorities, rights are guaranteed by law, the truth is that there are situations in which “the support provided by DSal is usually not enough to solve the difficulties” of TNR. In this sense, he continued, workers "feel many times they were ignored."
To the Macao Tribune, Jassy Santos said that in January he met the Consulate General of the Philippines, having delivered the same letter with seven suggestions. “They said they are willing to help… but without promises,” said the associative leader.
Compared to this year, Jassy Santos says he will continue to fight for domestic workers of foreign nationality in Macau to be more recognized in society and have more legal guarantees. It will also strive to achieve the minimum wage and the maximum limit of working hours.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IPIM travels to Portugal and Brazil in April</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ipim-desloca-se-portugal-ao-brasil-em-abril/</link><description>Portugal and Brazil will receive, in April, a team from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment, which will perform “a series of business promotion activities, with the aim of reinforcing mutual benefit cooperation between Chinese and Lusophone companies”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
A team from the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) will move to Portugal and Brazil in April, revealed the director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah. In this visit to the two Lusophone countries, it is planned to organize the "roadshow" pre-activities, in order to "attract more Lusophone companies" to participate in the 2nd China-Paraís Economic and Commercial Exhibition of Portuguese Language (Macau)-CPLPEX, "" creating more opportunities for in -depth cooperation between the intervening parties. ”
The second edition of CPLPEX will take place in Macao in October this year, aiming to invite companies from the Great Bay dedicated to electrodomers and manufacturing sectors, “to bring their quality products, technologies and services to the event site,” added Yau Yun Wah , in response to a written interpellation of Mrs Song Pek Kei.
According to the director of the body, the IPIM team "will move to Portuguese-speaking countries to carry out a series of business promotion activities, with the aim of reinforcing mutual benefit cooperation between Chinese and Lusophone companies."
In particular, it referred to the participation, together with the services of trade in the municipality of Beijing and other entities in the “Meeting of Entrepreneurs for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries”, which is mid -year in Equatorial Guinea. The purpose of the meeting is to help companies in the interior of China and MSA to better know the business environment in Portuguese -speaking countries, at the same time promoting, with Lusophone companies, the opportunities for the development of Macau and Hengqin.
In parallel, through the service of the “China-PLP Trade Conduct”, the “Portal for Cooperation in Economic, Commercial and Human Resources between China and the Portuguese-Speaking Countries” and the “Exposure Pavilion of the Platform Services for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries ”, IPIM“ will give strong support to Chinese and Lusophone companies to explore the market to deepen cooperation bilateral economic and commercial and commercial, it can be read.
The body's director also stressed that IPIM is dedicated to playing the role of Macau as a service platform for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, exploring greater cooperation space between China and Portuguese -speaking countries in Several areas, such as trade, investment and different industries.
On the other hand, Deputy Song Pek Kei had argued that the authorities should advance with a discussion with the interior of China so that “more convenient” policies and measures were adopted in favor of greater cost reduction and simplification of processes in the context of Participation of Macao companies in Sino-Lusophone Economic and Commercial Cooperation. At this point, Yau Yun Wah remembered only the measures already implemented and ensured that "the Government of MSar will continue to promote more facilitation measures, supporting even more local companies in exporting quality products to the interior of China."
In relation to the SINO-Portuguese qualified staff, Song Pek Kei considers that it is necessary for the authorities to do more in relation to the capture of these paintings and the formation. Now, also in this context, the authorities remember the measures already taken so far. By way of example they speak in the “Portuguese Language Learning Initiation Program”, launched in 2023/2024. Regarding this initiative, it is said that the direction of youth education and development services will “optimize the initiation program, supporting students to continue their studies in Portugal”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Restaurants propose subsidy in the face of price increases</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/restaurantes-propoem-subvencao-face-ao-aumento-de-precos/</link><description>Alongside the new round of the “large consumption award”, the director of the Union of Associations of Restoration and Beverage Owners expects the government to equate reinforce the degree of support for the community economy and the consumption of the local population, even considering, including , the hypothesis of assigning a subsidy in the face of price increases
 
In the opinion of the Director of the Union of Associations of Macao Restoration and Beverages Owners, the launch of a new round of the “big consumer award” between March and June corresponds to the expectations of traders and will bring hope to the market. Still, Fong Kin Fu (in the photo) considers that the budget of the MSAR and the government lines of action are essential to stimulate the community economy.
Specifically, he suggested to the Executive to expand the degree of support for the community economy, even considering launching a subsidy in the face of price increases, to strengthen residents' confidence in consumption. At the same time, the associative leader expects commercial establishments to articulate with the beneficial government's policies, improving the quality of service.
In addition, according to the Chinese language press, Fong Kin Fu argued that to boost the community economy, authorities can also explore the historical and cultural resources of different zones, leading more tourists to participate in cultural visits, as well as launch exclusive measures With a view to “rewarding” tourists by the act of consumer, such as raffles and immediate discounts. He stressed, the new round of the “great consumption award” has caught the attention of many traders, especially in the field of restoration.
In turn, Kou Seng Man, director of the Institute of International Academic Investigations (Macau), said the new consumer incentive round will allow clients to commercial establishments located in various community neighborhoods and stimulate residents to consume in the territory, thus boosting the economic growth of masters.
However, the academic expects some details to be optimized, including increasing the amount of immediate discounts, re -assigning consumer cards, raising the likelihood of winning in the draws, abolishing the deadline that limits the validity of the measure, reinforcing inspections regarding Chaotic price increases, as well as intensify campaigns with the elderly to prevent them from being deceived by burns.
In the long run, Kou Seng Man suggested more economy incentive measures, which includes residents' use, improving the business environment, supporting companies, and promoting sustainable development of the local economy.
On the other hand, according to the government, during the initiative, the elderly can also obtain immediate discount benefits, in the amount of 300 patacas, upon loading of the “Macau Pass card to the elderly”. Representatives of various associations have ensured that they will reinforce campaigns on the measure and provide services to help the elderly to exchange cards and raise the immediate discount benefits.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Zara shows “scoring vein” in Hong Kong football</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zara-mostra-veia-goleadora-futebol-de-hong-kong/</link><description>Hong Kong's women's football received this season the first Portuguese in its history. Zara Matos is advanced and wears the Rangers jersey of the II Division, for which she has so far scored 14 goals in 11 challenges. The 19 -year -old, born in England and resident in Macau, has been sighted in her speed and physical power, and has been approached to join next season in the main league of the neighboring territory

























Victor Rebelo
 
“Fish daughter knows how to swim,” is a popular saying that she applies perfectly to the young Portuguese Zara Matos, daughter of a former Macao football player. The Portuguese, who turned 19 in January, became at the first Lusa player to join Hong Kong women's football, being representing the Rangers of the II Division.
Born in England, so double nationality, the young woman has been sight in her speed, physical power and ease of invoicing, scoring 14 goals in 11 challenges.
Student of the 12th grade of the Portuguese school, it does not yet know its future in academic terms, but the possibility of coming to study at a university of Kong Kong can open other doors to her player career, that she herself would like to be professional .
Daughter of Paulo Conde, who played in Macau until he was 43, Zara Matos has her father's speed. He only “lacks” his left foot, but it has not prevented it from being considered as one of the revelations of Raehk's II Women's Football Division.
He started playing at Sporting de Macao when he was only 13 years old, in 2018, a time when the first championship for women came up, in the variant of seven, in the synthetic of Campo D. Bosco. A few years later, Zara Matos had the possibility of training in Hong Kong through her father's contacts.
“It was an excellent experience at Kitchee, a great prestigious club in Hong Kong and who is the current champion of the Main Women's Football League,” he began to tell the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
Despite being highly praised by the technical staff and leaders, the athlete could only train, since there were many difficulties to be inscribed in the association, because it is a minor, foreign, without residence and without passport of Raehk.
He later moved to the Hong Kong Football Club, where he also only did training. But last year, he was fortunate to be registered by Rangers of the II Division, because he had already turned 18.
“When I started at Rangers I felt that my evolution, especially in technical terms, was already at levels far higher than those I had when I acted in Macao football,” said Zara Matos, to whom the periods she trained at Kitchee and HK Football Club provided you with great progress.
"My coach says it is not normal for a player to have the speed I have, so I have contributed to some good results of the team, which makes me very pleased," he says.
Rangers occupies fourth place in the classification, with no big chance of ascending to the main league. At the club also acts Alexa, another athlete from Macau, former Sporting, taken by Zara to also try his luck in Hong Kong football. There are still two other foreigners on the squad, coming from Nepal.
Next season will be unknown to the Portuguese footballer, because it doesn't know your future in academic terms. “I haven't decided with my parents yet what I'm going to do, but, on the one hand, it would even be advantageous for me to study for a university in Hong Kong and thus be closer to the training site,” expresses Zara, who has had one Sacrifice life, moving to Hong Kong to train and play, often coming at dawn to Macau.
"It has not been easy, but as I really like playing football I just accept and endure well, although I have to get up early to go to school," he acknowledges, assuming he has the dream of becoming professional soccer player. "Yes, I would like to pursue a career."
 
Invitations have already emerged for next season
The young woman has been highly praised by coaches of various teams and received invitations to play next season, one of whom is Kitchee, who already knows her qualities and now has the advantage of being able to subscribe to the main league.
For his father, who only began to truly believe his daughter's potential when he first saw her playing Macao's Sporting team, Zara Matos had a huge evolution. Being a physical trainer of the Men's team of Rangers, which participates in the Hong Kong Premier League, Paulo Conde has been committed to giving private training to his daughter and notices his great evolution.
“She began to improve her eyes from the moment she went to train for Hong Kong, knowing how to position herself on the field and play with 11 players. All of this had to learn, along with the sessions made with me, on the beach and at the gym, that made their technique and muscle mass increase, ”he says.
For Paulo Conde, who acted in the selection of Macao and in teams like Black Red, Lam Pak, Ka I and Benfica, the possible reentry in Kitchee would be for the player an asset, since the club has a gym with excellent condition . "If it is confirmed, she will have everything to follow up on the progress she has done so far," he says, adding that "it will depend on her will."
Kitchee is well positioned to become a champion in Hong Kong women's football and this will mean the participation, for the second consecutive year, in the Asian Champions League of the category. “This would give Zara a huge opportunity to show its skills at the international level,” concludes Paulo Conde.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost four thousand infringements to the anti-tabagism law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-quatro-mil-infraccoes-a-lei-anti-tabagismo/</link><description>Last year, authorities detected 3,941 cases of illegal smoke, and restaurants and casinos were the places where the laws were most infringed. Regarding the control of alcohol, 47 cases suspected of violation of the regime that controls consumption by minors
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Smoking prevention and control regimes and alcohol consumption by underage people have led health services (SSM) to perform successive inspection actions in collaboration with law executing services last year. In total, the SSM made 259,081 inspections to establishments, which perfect a daily average of 708.
Regarding smoking control, the SSM, together with the Public Security Police Corps, the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the Directorate for Game Inspection and Coordination (DICJ) and customs services, detected 3,941 cases of illegal smoke and 138 of transportation of electronic cigarettes at the entrance and exit of Macao. Official data also includes 126 suspected cases of violation of other provisions of the smoking prevention and control regime, including the non -posting of smoking forbesting indoctics in the places provided for by law and the prohibition of prohibition of sale of tobacco products to minors 18 years old.
Statistics point to the fact that the restaurants were the spaces where there was a larger number of smokers in forbidden places, with a total of 604 cases (15.3%), followed by casinos that recorded 531 illegal situations (13 , 5%). The DICJ, in collaboration with the SSM, made 709 inspections to the casinos. In parks, gardens and leisure zones, 361 cases were detected, ie 9.2% of the total establishments or spaces.
On the other hand, in 2024, authorities detected 47 suspected cases of violation of the prevention and control of alcoholic beverages by minors. Among these, 11 involved the sale or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors, and other cases are related to various sales establishments or availability of alcoholic beverages that did not afford the prohibition of sales or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors.
In addition, the inspections noted that there are also commercial establishments that provide self-service services that do not clearly indicate or indicate the areas of alcoholic beverages and non-alcoholic beverages or advertising to alcoholic beverages, nor have warnings in Chinese, Portuguese and language languages ​​and English.
Pursuant to the law of the prevention and control of alcohol consumption by minors, their availability, both commercial and non -commercial purposes, is illegal and can be punished with a fine up to 20,000 patacas. The SSM recalls in the statement that if thebistics are not posted by commercial establishments according to the law, the penalty can reach higher values, specifically up to 200,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Saved” 906 thousand plastic bottles per year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/poupadas-906-mil-garrafas-de-plastico-por-ano/</link><description>Since the end of 2018 and until December 2024, Macau managed to spend 5.44 million plastic bottles less, under the campaign launched by environmental protection services and promoted the installation of drinking fountains in various areas of the city
 
In six years, Macau managed to “save” 5.44 million plastic bottles, an average of 906 thousand per year, according to the data provided by the Directorate of Environmental Protection Services (DSPA). The reduction of the use of plastic bottles in the territory has been made under a campaign launched in 2018 by the body subordinate to the protection of transport and public works.
Reducing the use of these disposable bottles has been through the installation of drinking fountains all over the city-since 2018, there are 82. These facilities thus allow anyone to fill a reusable bottle that brings with them home, A practice that has been gaining fans all over the world in the face of environmental concerns.
DSPA ensures that "it will continue to cooperate with more public services to install more drinking fountains in appropriate places to reduce the production of plastic bottles."
The reduction of plastic use has reached several areas, such as cases of cutlery, dishes and non-bodegradable and disposable glasses, as well as spherovitis trays for food products. According to a preliminary investigation, DSPA estimates that, per year, about 10 million knives, 25 million forks, and 40 million spoons - all non -biodegradable and disposable plastic products. It is also estimated that 300,000 plates, four million glasses and six million spherovitis trays are also estimated to be brought to the territory.
In this sense, and to promote with citizens the reduction of the use of disposable table utensils, to “reduce waste production from the source”, also launched in 2018, the “Reducing Plastic is very easy” campaign. Since its launch, “it has been supporting the population and traders,” says DSPA. According to the campaign, the campaign has been attended by over 250 local restaurants and drinks and “Take-Away” stores-a number that has been stable over the last few years.
By the end of December last year, the number of acts of “Plastic Reduction” had exceeded 2.8 million, and it is estimated that they could contribute to the reduction of about 6.1 million sets of disposable table utensils, Refers to the body on its electronic page.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>"Made in Macau" products for sale in supermarkets</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/produtos-made-macau-a-venda-nos-supermercados/</link><description>More than a hundred “Macao Quality Products” “Macao Ideas” are entering the big supermarkets located in community neighborhoods, and simultaneously sold and sold in online and offline. The exhibition runs until February 27
 
The Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment (IPIM) is organizing until the 27th, Thursday, an exclusive session of exhibition and sale of “Macao Ideas”-“Macao Quality Products”, which has the Participation of a dozen exhibiting companies and more than a hundred Macao products to three “premieres”. The news is the launch in large supermarkets located in the community neighborhoods of the territory, the availability of products in online stores of these supermarkets on the food delivery platform and the simultaneous online and offline exhibition and sale.
The event, extended this year to the community neighborhoods of Taipa and to the online supermarket, to facilitate contact with the new client sources, is held at the headquarters of the Grand Mart Department Store Ltd. da Taipa, where the categories of product and sale products are diverse.
More than a hundred “Macao Quality Products” include crackers, snacks, pasta, swallow nest, dry shellfish, healthy tea, wines, health supplements, bathing products and pet items, among others, by in order to satisfy the purchasing needs of different customer groups.
On site, there is a “offer of gifts with check-in”, which will give the opportunity to gain a limited edition memory of “Macao Ideas” when sharing the indicated footage and taking in loco photography. Due to the limited number of memories, they will be offered in the order of arrival.
In 2024, the exclusive session of exhibition and sale of “Macao Ideas” - “Macao Quality Products” introduced, for the first time, the companies exhibiting “Macao Ideas” in the great supermarkets of Macao, namely the “New Yaohan establishments ”, In Praia Grande and Cotai. Subsequent negotiations between stakeholders allowed a portion of the products to have been placed for sale in such retail spaces, “highlighting a successful example of promoting long-term sales cooperation through exposure, sale and experimentation Short -term products, ”according to a note from IPIM.
The “Macao Ideas” encompasses more than 100 exhibiting companies and about 1,700 brands and design products from Macao. All locally manufactured, products are promoted through online and offline exhibitions, display in large national and international fairs and exhibitions and commercial contact bags, among other initiatives.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Two residents assisted in the hospital after fire in the Lake Building</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/duas-moradoras-assistidas-hospital-apos-incendio-edificio-lago/</link><description>Two residents of Block 5 of the 79 and 51 -year -old Lake Building were submitted to first aid at the hospital after they inhaled thick smoke following a fire that launched in the fraction where they live on the 7th floor. Both were in weak consciousness when they were rescued. The fire also led 20 people to be removed from the site. The case occurred at 7:40 am, with the fire to be extinguished at 08:55 and the cooling work to be concluded at noon. According to the Fire Department, the fire was caused by the short circuit of a television. In the operation, 54 firefighters and 12 ambulances were mobilized. In the affected fraction, an area of ​​400 square feet was fully destroyed. Already a neighboring fraction got the door burned, the same happening in the corridor of that floor. The Institute of Social Action (IAS) sent to the site social workers, accompanied by workers from various social work institutions in the mud, with the aim of providing emotional support, counseling and other supports according to the needs of the residents of the economic housing in question. According to IAS, at this time, there are no residents who need temporary accommodation service. On the other hand, a fraction in the Mong Sin building of the Social Housing of Mong-Há also registered a fire on Sunday morning, considered preliminarily as a fire case given by the Judicial Police. The fire, which has not caused injured, had originated in cigarette beatas lying next to an air conditioner hanging on the outer wall of the fraction in question.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Accident caused 12 minor injuries</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/acidente-causou-12-feridos-ligeiros/</link><description>An accident on Seminar Street, not far from the Largo de Santo Agostinho, caused 12 minor injuries, all extras in a filming that was taking place. The filming team was working on that street when a worker eventually lost control of a driving car, running over 12 people, including four children aged five and six. According to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP), the accident occurred at 2:30 pm, when the car was circulating on that street, which was prohibited. After losing control, he reached a seal and eventually entered the sidewalk of Francisco António, where the injured were resting, waiting for the next footage. According to CPSP, the driver is a resident of the interior of China, is 62 years old and holds a driving license issued by the continent, but is allowed to drive in Macao. He passed the alcohol test, and the police are still ascertaining the video surveillance chambers, the filming process and the driver's physical state. In addition, it is inspecting the vehicle to see if it has mechanical problems. The cause of the accident continues to be investigated by CPSP. The injured, three men and nine women, are between five and 61 years old. Two are residents of Macao, nine holders of safe conduct and a Singapore passport holder. For the site, six ambulances were mobilized. The Fire Department indicated that all injured were transported to the hospital. The direction of tourism services was notified of the accident.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM students win interpretation contest in the Portuguese Language category</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-da-upm-vencem-concurso-de-interpretacao-na-categoria-de-lingua-portuguesa/</link><description>The third edition of the International Remote Interpretation Contest “Yunshan Cup” had as winners, in the Portuguese Language category, first introduced students from the Language Faculty and Translation of the Polytechnic University of Macau (UPM). The distinctions fell to Zhao Qichao (champion), Wang Xiaoyu (runner-up, advisor teacher: Wang Xiaoyan) and Mok Man Sam (second award). According to a UPM note, students "fully demonstrated their excellent abilities in the area of ​​Chinese-Portuguese interpretation." In addition to the Language of Camões, the race covered 15 more languages ​​and attracted more than 4,000 participants from various universities from countries in Europe, Asia and the USA. UPM Language and Translation Faculty Director Gaspar Zhang stressed that, through systematic learning, students can consolidate their professional linguistic knowledge in various areas, “becoming high-level professional interpreters and translators”. The UPM also recalled that registrations are open for the Master's degree in Chinese-Portuguese translation and interpretation of the same faculty. Interested parties can register online until May 15, on the UPM Electronic Admission Page.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2349/</link><description>Administration Human Resources will be the target of an audit
The first working meetings of two groups created by the Chief Executive have already been held: the leadership of the Public Administration Reform and the group to promote the construction of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin. Both were chaired by Sam Hou Fai. The group dedicated to management reform “plans to boost a cooperation between the audit commissioner and the direction of administration and civil service services to perform the audit of results in the area of ​​human resources, in order to ensure its reasonable use”, indicates A press release released by the Social Communication Office. At the meeting, the members discussed various topics about the continuity of raising the capacity of governance and the level of services to the public, namely the optimization of rights, responsibilities, functions, structure and regime of public services personnel; the improvement of management and leadership personnel management; the deepening of the construction of the electronic government and the expansion of electronic services. Sam Hou Fai stressed that the reform of the civil service team "is important to adapt to Macao's economic and social situations and to respond reasonably to development needs in all areas." As for the group dedicated to the cooperation zone, the leader of MSAR instructions to the secretaries to understand and “seriously” the requirements left by the Hong Kong and Macao affairs director with the Council of State, Xia Baolong. For example, it indicated that they should focus on “further” a convenient circulation of qualified, capital and goods in Hengqin, joining the new strategic positioning of “Macau + Hengqin” and promoting the completion of the second “high quality” with “high quality” with “high quality” phase of the cooperation zone.</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive “must look a little more” to the elderly population</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/executivo-deve-olhar-um-pouco-mais-para-populacao-idosa/</link><description>Support for the elderly has been considered by the new government as one of the priorities of policies to be implemented in the coming years and the president of the General Assembly of the Macao's Retired, Reformed and Pensioners Association, and that this is a reality. "It is necessary that the speeches have consequence, that is, that one can see the fruit of these promises," Jorge Fão told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Among other proposals, the associative leader suggests that social housing follow Singapore's model, providing broader fractions, allowing them to live parents, children and grandchildren. Understands that, in this way, the reduction of birth can be avoided
 
Victor Rebelo
 
In the context of the Government Action Lines (LAG), members of the Macao government have been arguing opinions and receive suggestions on a journey by various associations linked to the most diverse areas. Support for the elderly is one of the themes of this policy of approximation to the aged population, based on the social layer to which they belong, the economic capacity of survival and their physical conditions.
In this sense, the Association of Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners of Macao (Apomac), for the voice of its President of the General Assembly, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao to expect the issue of the elderly to be one of the government's priorities in LAG.
Jorge Fão states that the executive “must look a little more to the old class” and that, in addition to the guarantees that have already been said about government availability, “discourses must have consequences, that policies are realistic, or that is, the fruit of these promises can be seen. ”
The leader expresses that, “in this matter, the government has to work a little more”, giving an example of measures to be implemented. "In the case of economic and social housing, I suggest that the government follow the model that exists in Singapore, which opts for modern and effective solutions."
Realizing the idea, Jorge Fão says that, “while in Macao houses of small spaces are constructed, many of which have only one couple in Singapore are widening the houses so that two or three generations can live there, parents, parents, children and grandchildren ”.
The President of the General Assembly of Apomac is of the opinion that "these measures facilitate human reproduction." This may be one of the reasons, he points out, "for the reduction of birth in Macao registered in recent years, and this year, records in terms of low birthday will be beaten."
Jorge Fão notes that "no one has time to take care of his children and the burden is high." Therefore, he argues, the government must create conditions for these children and young people to be more accompanied by grandparents. Hence, it reinforces, "the reason for the need for intergenerational dwellings to facilitate human reproduction."
 
APPLICATION INCREASE MONTHLY PENSION
In other aspects of governance, and in view of improving the quality of life of the older age population, Apomac leader expects the government to increase the pension to the elderly, at least to 4,000 patacas. “We think it is not to ask that much, beyond an increase in the elderly allowance,” he says. On the other hand, it considers the subsidy given by birth of a child (just over 5,400 patacas).
“These are situations where the government speaks, propagates ufanly, but then, in my view, more voices than nuts, as the popular saying goes,” laments Jorge Fão.
In short, Apomac's member of the Apomac managing bodies expects the current government to "devote more attention to these policies, such as birth, education, also trying to realize the reason for the high number of suicides in Macao." The executive “has to be transparent in all matters”, he stresses.
Referring to Sam Hou Fai's speech at the meeting that the Chief Executive kept with the Macanese community, Jorge Fão says he had “liked to listen”, since the government leader's words highlighted the role of the community, “having -manifested available to support, in order to keep the Macaense community alive ”. But, insists the Apomac leader, "it is necessary that these intentions are put into practice, to move on, to materialize."
The associative leader considers that Macau “needs critical mass”. "And in my case, what I point out is done in a constructive way."
 
Old clinic will give way to the multipurpose room
Regarding the role played by Apomac and the support given by the government in the implementation of benefits to its members, Jorge Fão regrets that this help is only through the Macao Foundation subsidies, although they usually arrive with some delay. "We always had, but besides there are no other official financial aid."
Reminds the clinic closure. "We were forced to end the space, because the subsidies did not arrive to keep the clinic open."
The leader said that, where the clinic worked, Apomac will now start works in order to install a multipurpose room there to be able to perform his usual lectures. "The house is not ours, it is from the territory, so we should not be us to endure the expenses when the works are of public utility," he reiterated.
To fund these improvements at its headquarters, Apomac has some savings. “Fortunately, we have instituted a reserve fund for a few years that allows us to meet certain expenses that are not accounted for through subsidies, or whose funds of the Foundation has not yet arrived,” explains Fão, adding that these supplementary expenses, A which he calls eventualities, "they are increasingly frequent, have become almost permanent due to the needs."
 
From the tours to China to health lectures
Speaking of Apomac's activities scheduled for this year, Jorge Fão wants to keep what has been done in recent years, which is the organization of tours to China, with the support of the connection group, and the holding of lectures. Last week, the association received two Hong Kong doctors who came to Macau to talk about issues that affect the health of the elderly, such as thrombosis and dysphagia, which is a difficulty in swallowing food.
For this year, in October or November, a walk to Yunnan is planned, where there are many ethnic minorities. "The purpose of these travels is to show our associates the development that China has suffered in the last 30 or 40 years, as well as the Chinese culture that many do not know," he says.
In addition, Apomac continues to support the resolution of the bureaucracy that implies the obtaining and renewal of pensions ensured by Caixa Geral de Portugal. “This is a very hard work that occupies us a lot, but we do with all the taste to solve various problems to our associates,” says Jorge Fão, for whom the life proof of life is one of the most complex situations that in the last years is made through the mobile phone.
Jorge Fão stressed that he has already contacted the entities in Portugal, specifically the finances, suggesting that it is possible to prove the documents through the Macao Single Account. "They could use our unique account for life proof and so it would not be necessary to resort to so much bureaucracy, because the system in Macau is reliable and the data could be sent there," he says, hoping that one day there will be an agreement in this regard.
Apomac, which celebrates 25 years in 2026, will have elections “probably in the middle of the year,” according to the President of the General Assembly. “Me and Francisco Mannão, who is the president of the Board, let's define deadlines,” he says.
Regarding his continuity, Jorge Fão says he would like to make way for others, younger, but recognizes that "volunteering is increasingly difficult in Macau, because people have other priorities." If you do not appear candidates, it ensures that you will continue in Apomac managers.</description><pubDate>2025-02-24 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Egypt announces the first discovery in 100 years of a pharaonic tomb</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/egipto-anuncia-primeira-descoberta-em-100-anos-de-um-tumulo-faraonico/</link><description>The Ministry of Antiquities of Egypt announced the discovery of the tomb of Tutmés II, the first ancient royal tomb found since that of Tutankamon in 1922.
Tutmés II was the son of Tutmés I and his minor wife, Mutnofret, who was probably daughter of Ahmés I. He was therefore a minor son of Tutmés I and chose to marry his royal sister, Hatchepsut, to ensure his royalty . As Mutnofret was a princess and Tutmés I was a commoner, they probably married only after Tutmés became king, so his son would be born after his father's coronation, and probably after half sister Hatchepsut, who was the daughter of Pharaoh with your primary wife.
This would mean that Tutmés II was in early adolescence when it became Pharaoh. Although he successfully repressed rebellions in Nubia and the uprising and defeated a group of nomadic Bedouins, these campaigns were carried out specifically by the king's generals, not by Tutmés II himself which is often interpreted as evidence that Tutmés II was Even under age when it took over the throne. Tutmés II generated Neferure with Hatchepsut, and Tutmés III, with a smaller wife called ISET.
Some archaeologists believe that during the government of Tutmés II Hatchepsut was the true power behind the throne, due to the similar internal and external policies that were later adopted during his reign and because of his claim that he was his father's intended heiress. It is portrayed in several relief scenes from a Karnak portal dating from the reign of Tutmés II, both together with her husband and alone and later, became Pharaoh several years after the young successor of her husband, Tutmés III; This is confirmed by the fact that "the queen's agents have replaced the king's name in some places with his own."
Now the tomb of Tutmés II was found near the Valley of the Kings in Luxor, southern Egypt, a few kilometers from its imposing funeral temple, erected on the western bank of the Nile.
It is “one of the most important archaeological discoveries of recent years,” celebrated the Ministry of Antiquities.
According to preliminary studies, the tomb, excavated by an Egyptian-British joint mission, was emptied in antiquity, leaving the tomb without royal mummy or the golden splendor associated with the discovery of Tutankamon.
Its entry was first located in 2022 in the mountains of Luxor, west of the Vale dos Reis, but the experts believed it led to the tomb of a royal wife.
The team then found “fragments of alabaster vessels with the name of Pharaoh Tutmés II, identified as the 'deceased king', as well as inscriptions with the name of his main royal wife, Queen Hatshepsut,” details the ministry.
Shortly after the king's burial, the water flooded the funeral chamber, damaging the interior and fragmenting a plaster coating decorated with extracts from the book of Amduat, an old funeral text over the beyond.
Also found in the grave were some funeral furniture that belonged to Tutmés II, the ministry said.
According to mission chief Piers Litherland, quoted by the Ministry of Antiquities, the team will continue their work in the region, hoping to find objects that were originally in the tomb.
This announcement occurs at a time when Egypt intensifies efforts to boost tourism, an essential source of foreign currency for the country's economy. Last year, Egypt received 15.7 million tourists and this year expects a visit of 18 million, especially thanks to the expected inauguration of the great Egyptian museum, at the foot of the Giza pyramids.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-02-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>