<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Analysts expect lag directed to support for the population and SMEs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/analistas-esperam-lag-direccionadas-para-apoios-a-populacao-pme/</link><description>The first lines of government action of the executive led by Sam Hou Fai will concentrate today the attention in Macau. For various sectors of society, the environment is of expectation around the measures that the leader of MSAR intends to implement, in order to meet the demands of a recovering economy and the welfare of the population. Listened to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, experts in different areas, such as Leonel Alves, IP, António Félix Pontes, António Monteiro, Joe Chan and Glenn McCartney have suggestions that they believe to be important for the development of the field



































Victor Rebelo*
 
Sam Hou Fai will present today in the Legislative Assembly the report of the Government Action Lines (LAG) to 2025, five months after taking office as Chief Executive. The measures to be implemented are generating natural expectation in the various sectors of society, and areas such as economy and social welfare are on the list of priorities for this year, according to experts heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
Leonel Alves, a member of the Executive Board and former deputy to the Legislative Assembly, stresses that the budget for 2025 and LAG should include "measures that guarantee the stability of Macao's economic and social development, especially in times of world crisis, whose evolution generates fears and uncertainties." Therefore, he says, "it is essential to adopt cautious financial measures, avoiding excessively optimistic perspectives."
The member of the National Committee of the Chinese people's Political Advisory Conference points out that "good financial management is an important condition to generate a sense of security among residents and provide internal and external investments."
Continuing in his analysis to LAG, the lawyer by profession states that “the negative impact of the covid-19 pandemic, the consumption tendency of residents to be diverted to the cities and locations of the Great Bay, as well as the spectrum of the current deep-scale profound crisis, do not allow major initiatives for the implementation of important financial support measures to companies they need most”.
Even so, he expects, "at the bottom of the tunnel," innovative ideas will emerge to "alleviate the crisis of small and medium enterprises, the real estate market and the unfavorable situation of late -defendant credits."
Leonel Alves is waiting for more governmental government actions "to take an important step forward to reinforce the role of Macau as a service platform for commercial cooperation between China and Portuguese-speaking countries," as well as "The First Steps to extend this role to Latin American countries."
On the other hand, perspective measures to improve the efficiency of governance, "through administrative reform aligned with the characteristics of this government, considering previous experiences and the need to improve relations between public services, citizens and investors."
In this sense, the MSAR should have an administration "to resolve the difficulties of people and companies, rather than perpetuating them and finding no way of solving them." If it is necessary to change procedures, Leonel Alves wishes to be “actually modified”, and “if it is indispensable to adjust the law or create new standards, that is realized”.
Within the scope of economic diversification and greater use of the advantages and opportunities provided by the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin, the executive board member expects “concrete ideas on interaction between these two territories, as well as the point of situation of mutual cooperation policies”.
For Leonel Alves, the existence of a convergent project between Macao and Hengqin, including the legal and judicial cooperation area, “interesting to facilitate and provides more security and protection to those who want to live and invest in hengqin, simultaneously, simultaneously changing what is needed for Macau reaches a higher level of their right and justice”.
 
Opportunities for families and young people
In the social area, I IP IP, Director of Services of the Coordinating Cabinet of Social Services Sheng Kung Hui, warns of the recent “constant changes in the social conjuncture”, specifically the trade war, which caused “many factors of uncertainty”. In this context, it considers that the first lag of the current government may have as its main objective "to ensure stability and at the same time seek progress."
At the level of social services, I can IP believe that the executive will give importance to the economy stabilization and guaranteeing the welfare of the population, which means "a more corresponding orientation to the current economic scenario."
Despite the economic improvement verified after the pandemic, the same responsible warns that "some families in Macao have still faced several degrees of difficulty." "Therefore, we think that in LAG the government should focus on improving the economy, as well as giving more opportunities to families and young people, so that they have better financial conditions," he emphasizes.
Regarding the functioning of social services, Sheng Kung Hui leader maintains that, first of all, “it is necessary to maintain the basic guarantees for families with financial difficulties and to evaluate concrete situations of these families to optimize support”.
Considering that Macau “continues to register inflation”, the director of services of the social body expects the government to address LAG especially the issue of “revision of social risk value” and, in general, “maintain the basic benefits for residents, evaluating the right measures to make support more accurate”.
In addition, I can utter the government to discuss the issue of support for families, when it is known that often both spouses work, and mention in the lag “to policies and concepts to support residents in family care”.
On the other hand, it, “beyond children, many elderly and family members with less good physical conditions also need care.“ Hence we hope that the authorities can support companies so that they reinforce family policies, ”he says, convinced that this subject deserves to be discussed,“ because it can contribute to stabilizing society ”.
Thirdly, Sheng Kung Hui says he always values ​​the issue of young people's growth, “especially those who have little conditions” and acknowledges that, from the outbreak of the pandemic so far, “the emotional health of young people has been one of the most important points of government work”, but intends more support. "Not only as a prevention of emotional problems, but also for improving mental health in general, because some young people are in a less good mental state," he says.
Advocating a faster intervention by the authorities, I can ask for “more spaces and resources to promote physical exercise, beneficial to young people's health”, while “it is good to convey more information for young people to learn some self-care techniques”.
In addition, Sheng Kung Hui's office leader argues that more platforms should be created in society so that young people can show their talents and, consequently, feel valued.
"The social atmosphere is for us very important, but if there are less satisfactory situations regarding the emotion of young people, if there is a little more support for parents, both advice and medical system help, families will be able to find this help earlier to deal with the problem of emotional instability of young people," he says.
In the fourth point of his suggestions for this year's lag, I can address the theme of new technologies, noting that social service institutions “have also felt this impact”. It then suggests that the authorities consider ways to encourage Macao social service institutions "to know more and make good use of the development of new technologies, including their respective paintings and equipment, to become more modernized."
 
Rethink SME support model
In the sector of the economy, Antonio Félix Pontes considers that the current and future political-economic context, which is characterized by an abnormal and growing uncertainty and volatility, and alignment with the central government's guidelines, will constitute the main guiding bases of lag.
These guidelines should be based on six fundamental axes, the economist understands, starting by stating that “the government should continue the '1+4' economic diversification plan, namely in the areas of intelligent technology, modern finances and health tourism (in this case, in view of the capacity of the islands hospital, which must be equipped with state -of -the -art equipment and highly qualified doctors).
In addition, he argues, it will also be important to “rethink the Small and Medium Enterprise Support scheme (SMEs) to the new geopolitical framework and the huge financial difficulties felt by these economic units in the rent chapter and online competition and physics of neighboring markets”. In his analysis, Felix Pontes advocates greater efficiency in the economic and financial relationship with Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP) and the role attributed to masters in the large bay, including hengqin.
The launch of credit lines from the monetary authority to the central banks of the Portuguese-speaking African countries (Palop) and Timor-Leste is also understood by the economist as a means of development, “effectively, for exports and re-exports of MSAR to these countries, whose movement has been very small, or even null”.
In addition, the former member of the board of directors of the monetary authority, supports the creation of a public capital credit insurer, “with the aim of coverage of commercial and political risks to local companies that export or re-export to Palop and Timor-Leste, or that make investments, or for new markets (South America and Africa, for example), for the new geopolitical world framework”.
The expert hopes that Sam Hou Fai and his team will develop and perform “a realistic strategy”, in view of “maximizing” the role of Macau in the Great Bay, including Hengqin, “based on the objectives of leveraging their potential to in fact, a worldwide tourism and entertainment center and to reinforce their action as a platform for the commercial and financial relationship between China and PLP”.
 
Raise amounts from subsidies
Speaking of the improvement of social welfare, Felix Pontes suggests “raising the amount of subsidies for the elderly population and other vulnerable groups and promoting policies to support family and unemployed young people”.
In professional formation and improvement and talent attraction, it requires reinforcement of support for these continuous education programs, namely for “subjects relevant for economic development and diversification” and, “based on the experience obtained in the application of local legislation on talent attraction and the similar system in the Special Administrative Region of Hong Kong, to review this legal framework”.
Infrastructures also deserve the economist's reflection, which suggests the acceleration of relevant projects in the infrastructure area.
It also underlines the need to take conducting measures “to change the third-world landscape 'landscape' in certain areas of Coloane Island (including Ká-Hó), for the construction of a new market, the destruction of informal constructions (vulgar tents), part of which they serve as a deposit, uncontrolled and eventually illegal, solid waste of all dimension and species”.
In short, the economist wants to see an environmental policy implemented, in line with the standards established in the United Nations Environment Program (UNEP), “with a view to promoting sustainable development (ban on non -biodegradable plastics, faster renewal of old vehicles and promotion of electric or hydrogen vehicles)”.
Its last theme is the modernization of the functioning of public administration, asking for the acceleration of the development of intelligent governance, in the one hand, to “give greater transparency and speed to the process of administrative decision making” and, on the other, “increasing accountability and fostering the collaboration and participation of stakeholders (citizens and companies).
At the same time, it suggests that the executive takes “anti-bureaucracy effective, legislative or other, as well as promotes the acceleration of the pace regarding the progress of court proceedings and revising the traffic law and the improvement of the pedestrian network”.
 
Diversification and Medical Tourism
Glenn McCartney, an integrated resort management expert, told this newspaper that “economic diversification in relation to tourism will remain LAG's main focus”, anticipating “many subthemes to diversify tourism”. "One of the issues that are putting themselves has been having these major investments from the six game dealers, there are several thousand millions of dollars, so I think it is an opportunity to get greater involvement with integrated resorts, a public-private collaboration (…) in the scope of medical tourism, for example, where this collaboration is really needed," he defended.
The professor at the University of Macao recalled that the diversification of the economy is an old topic, so we need to reflect: "We are advancing to a trajectory of diversification, but why are we not advancing faster?".
Regarding medical tourism, McCartney points out as a fundamental issue the creation of a collaboration between the public and the private sector. "There are many interveners, such as medical industry, tourism, hospitality, transport and the public sector, who have to legislate and write policies that contribute to success," he said, stressing that it is important to "accelerate some policies if we want to move forward with these sectors." "You need to have tune policies, not four or five years later [to be created]."
In his opinion, the “opportunity” of the in -depth cooperation zone must also be “enjoyed” as regards the tourism sector. "Economic diversification will undoubtedly be a key area, but also collaboration with Hengqin and the dissemination of this collaboration in the Great Bay area, because, in terms of resources, Macau can really benefit from this collaboration," he said.
Another aspect that has been widely spoken by the government is the attraction of more international visitors to the territory. In this context, Glenn McCartney emphasizes that it is necessary to "have more data and understanding of travel markets." “We need to understand our regional markets and competition, because there is regional competition ... So we have to understand what attracts visitors and tourists today, families, young people, etc.,” he continued.
The academic says, on the other hand, that the “brand of the city” is also “very important” to attract international visitors. "When people travel, they have many options, many destinations (…) and many places concentrate a lot of energy and emotion in building their image of destination-they do so through traditional media, social networks. Once again, I underline the importance of the city's image." “How do we promote Macau and how do people perceive it?” He asked.
Finally, Glenn McCartney referred a third aspect: the transport. "Of course you can bring more international visitors, but it takes more transportation options. It takes connectivity," he said.
 
Understand culture and local history
António Monteiro, president of the Association of Young Macanese (AJM), says that the “youngest portion in particular and the general population continues to have difficulty leasing a home, including high prices and unstable variations in goods consumption”.
In finding that the population prefers to go the other side of the border to buy goods instead of Macao, the leader feels that "there is anything wrong on this side." In this situation, "it is obvious that young people" run away from marriage and do not want to have children and this will certainly contribute to greater aging of the population, "which adds" the problems of maternity leave, where 70 days does not favor Macao ", compared to neighboring or international regions."
In the preview of LAG, António Monteiro points to education as the successful key to forming young people in the direction of Macao's objectives, especially in the area of ​​economic diversification. “Understanding local culture and history are fundamental to transmit correct content to the desired diversification, it is essential for younger people to have this training,” he says, indicating that access to schools and universities “can also be access to knowledge and linguistic, cultural, historical, business, with opportunities for internships in public services, game concessionaires, private entities, etc.”
It suggests, therefore, “a governing guidance to society in the appropriate preparation for younger people to achieve objectives to the work of diversification of Macao, guiding the increase of their regional and international competitiveness.
Culture and language are aspects that the president of AJM understands to be equally important. In this domain, I would like the government to promote more auscultation with the various communities in Macao, specifically Macaense and Portuguese, "where they are also children of the earth and residents and part of Macao's success." It also mentions that, at cultural, historical, academic, teaching and business, “the two communities may be an important contribution to the integration of Macau in the Great Bay, but also essential in the international connection and with Portuguese -speaking countries”.
These communities, Macaense and Portuguese, “are the true window platforms abroad to bring knowledge and international business to Macau,” he says.
António Monteiro, who is also secretary general of the International Institute of Macao, points out that the Portuguese language "can not only be an official language applied in public services, but also a vehicle for the tourist, educational and business and cultural platform between China and Portuguese-speaking countries."
 
“Political courage” to review the laws
One of the lines of action for this year indicated by Macaense, “may be the strengthening in the formation of Portuguese and Chinese to the non -speaking residents of these respective languages, creating new linguistic actors in various exchanges (not only being applied to the formation of translators in Macau)”. To this end, it understands that “there will be political and diplomatic courage for the review of laws for the recruitment of outdoor trainers or educators (in the teaching of the Portuguese language in particular)”.
António Monteiro also advocates “the guarantee of more media for television and media for the formation of new communication talents, creation of actors and artistic talents, soap opera production, programs for the dissemination of Macao products, local cinematic world, in view of the promotion of territory abroad and greater projection in the teaching of Macaense and Portuguese cultures, to achieve a greater cultural exposure of Macau and the Great Bay”.
On the other hand, it believes that bet on culture and language in the business domain can ensure the development of new products. "The proper use of Macaense and Portuguese cultures in the creation of products (including tangible and intangible heritage), in the arts, gastronomy and music, will provide new windows, both business and cultural."
Thus, António Monteiro exhorts the executive to promote auscultation sessions to civil society and macanese and Portuguese cultural associations to define “more transparent guidelines and ensure means to achieve common objectives for the development of Macao in the future”.
In conclusion, the leader of AJM speaks of the importance of Hengqin, which, “given the limitations of space in Macau, can be an opportunity for the creation of more solid sports structures (stadiums), motor circuits or karting at the tourist level, themed parks and attractive structures to families and bring large -scale international concerts, ensuring greater circulation and integration to local residents in the cooperation zone Deepened ”.
 
Recycling policies and reduction of plastics
In the environmental field, the president of the “Green Students Union” association expects this year to “be prohibited to import more plastic utensils, probably other small plastic objects such as spoons and forks”. But for Joe Chan "it would be great if the government could actually reduce the consumption of containers and plastic glasses of unique use, as they represent the largest section of plastic waste."
Pointing out that the ecopoints in Macau are “just a decoration”, because “most of the trash inside is contaminated and mixed with unwanted objects”, the environmentalist regrets that there are no regulations or rules that oblige citizens and visitors correctly. "It turns out that 80% of the waste placed in the recycling ecopoints ends up in the incinerate," he continues, in statements to this newspaper.
Joe Chan argues that, for example, the plastic bags used for fruits and vegetables, which are currently not paid, are taxed, "since the final goal is a free -use plastic -free society." The worldwide trend of the “paying polluter” is thus for the associative leader the way to follow. "In the short term, the government should also regulate the use of plastic bags through higher taxes, promoting the awareness of people to take their own bags," he added.
“As an international leisure tourism city, tourism brings us fortune, but at the same time many environmental charges. Macau should become not only a city-friendly city, but also a model of environment friendly. We should attract our visitors for our hospitality, history and sustainability,” he said. Joe Chan later gave the example of Singapore, which is famous for being a garden city, but also an exquisite city. "Tourists and citizens are educated to worry about the environment. Japan, Singapore, Korea and Taiwan adopt a very effective policy of waste recycling. We can have them as a reference," he said.
On the other hand, the president of Green Students Union considers that "the problem of electronic waste remains a taboo in the policy of the direction of environmental protection services, given the high cost of their treatment and elimination." Joe Chan is also concerned about eliminating lithium batteries, pointing out that more and more electric cars and power banks are used. "If they are incorrectly eliminated, they are toxic and dangerous to society," he warned, hoping that there may be policies related to these subjects.
 
*With Catarina Pereira</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Association of journalists concerned with the form of communication of the government</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacao-de-jornalistas-preocupada-forma-de-comunicacao-governo/</link><description>More than 100 days after the new executive took office, the Macao Journalists Association is said to be "seriously concerned" with the possibility of the government's "passive and retrograde" communication being able to become the new normal. He says, there are more and more events at the closed door, and more than 90% of the government -related news arrive by press release or speeches. AJM asks the government to “maintain its commitment to the rule of law and to repose, as soon as possible, the provisions related to the news coverage”
 
CATARINA PEREIRA
 
The Macao Journalists Association (AJM) says it is “seriously concerned” about the possibility of the government's communication approach, which describes it as “passive and retrograde, to become the new norm” in the territory. Pointing out that the government led by Sam Hou Fai took office over 100 days ago, the association states that "it has been noting the growing number of official events held at the closed door, which has significantly reduced the opportunities for journalists to interview directly the chief executive, secretaries and other high employees."
According to a statement sent yesterday to the newsrooms, AJM stresses that "over 90% of the government -related news is now disclosed through press reports or discourses after the events, which is exactly that this is the will of the government - with the promised" diverse "communication channels - to propagate the news, replacing any forms of live interaction with the press."
“Once again, we exhort the Government of the Misreo to honor its promise of respect for freedom of the press, taking concrete measures: dialogue with the public and the media with more confidence, so that the community has a better understanding of its policy and vision,” can read.
Citing comments collected from the media sector, AJM indicates that "an abnormal standard has arisen with regard to the provisions related to the press since the new administration has taken office." Although the restrictions imposed by the pandemic have already been raised and the normality resumed, the association says that some of the boss's main visits "were not open to the coverage of the average, as traditionally happened." For example, he speaks at the Guangdong-Macau Cooperation Joint Conference and Hengqin's inspection visit earlier this year.
"In addition, during the visit of the Chief Executive to the Community on the fourth day of the Lunar New Year, only two media with narrow calls to the government were notified for news coverage," he adds. On the other hand, in several sessions of advisory councils and events in which the secretaries participated, "no invitation to the media was made." “This scenario has no precedents in more than two decades of existence of masters,” he laments.
AJM also again says that “government continues to refuse, irrationally, that local monthly magazines and online media” will cover certain events. According to the social communication office has been trying to justify with “unconvincing explanations”, such as “Limited Space”, and even advised journalists to watch the live transmission. "These answers raise serious doubts about employee integrity and their understanding of the role of journalism, and reflect a lack of knowledge of international norms for an open government, eventually undermining the credibility and public image of the Masters," argues the association.
"An exhaustive analysis of the recent evolution would reveal a systematic deterioration of the press device organized by the authorities. The situations described above are not isolated incidents, nor are they limited to certain media," said AJM, noting that, on January 14, Sam Hou Fai clearly stated that freedom of the press is fully protected by basic law and press law.
AJM thus says expecting "the government to maintain its commitment to the rule of law and to repose, as soon as possible, the provisions related to news coverage, in order to prevent the public right to be informed to be continually imposed."</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing credit returns to “low tide”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-a-habitacao-volta-a-mare-baixa/</link><description>The new mortgage loans for housing fell 45.4% between January and February, marking the fourth break in five months, according to official data
 
The value of new mortgage loans for housing approved by local banks was led by 724.09 million patacas in February, reflecting a monthly descent of 45.4% and an annual rise of 5.5%, the Macao Monetary Authority (AMCM) announced. The loans granted to residents corresponded to 98.3% of the total.
After increasing 31.4% in January, in monthly terms, the new housing credit thus suffered the fourth sequential descent in the last five months. Between December and February, the monthly average of these loans reached 1.02 billion patacas, less 14.2% than in the previous period (November to January).
According to AMCM data, at the end of February, the non -housing credit debt ratio involving delays of more than three months in interest and or capital payments of loans, maintained the same level as the previous month (3.6%), but advanced 2.6 percentage points compared to the same period of 2024.
The gross balance of mortgage loans for housing stood by 216.86 billion, translating reductions of 0.4% and 4.8%, compared to the previous month and at the same period of 2024, respectively. Of these loans, 96.6% were granted to residents.
In turn, the new commercial loans for real estate activities totaled 1.53 billion patacas, which illustrates a monthly increase of 4.4% and an annual growth of 61.3%, with residents absorbing 82.5% of this type of credit. Between December and February, the monthly average of these loans increased by 21.1% to 1.22 billion, in relation to the previous three months.
In credit for real estate activities, the unpaid debt ratio (5.4%) did not suffer monthly fluctuations, however, rose 2.1 points within one year. The gross balance of commercial loans for real estate activities (149.88 billion) fell 0.2% compared to the previous month and 5.3% in the annual variation.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Table Tennis Elite returns to the Galaxy Arena</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/elite-tenis-de-mesa-regressa-a-arena-galaxy/</link><description>Macao hosts from today the international table tennis elite for the World Cup. The competition is intended for the category of singles, male and female, with the presence of 96 athletes, and will be stage the galaxy arena. The leaders of the respective rankings, the Chinese Lin Shidong and Sun Yingsha are confirmed. Portugal will be represented only in the women's test, by Jieni Shao



















The best players in the world of table tennis will act in the World Cup, which takes place at the Galaxy Macau Arena for the second year in a row. The race will feature 96 athletes, equitably distributed to the categories of male and female singular.
The tournament starts this morning, with the qualification phase, in a group system of three players each, taking place until the 20th, Sunday. The race again brings to the territory of high level mesatenists, from the outset with the presence of the leaders of the respective rankings, Lin Shidong, in men, and Sun Yingsha, in women. In the male picture, Lin Shidong, who will be 20 years old during the territory competition, is already a certainty in the landscape of the sport, relegating for secondary positions the compatriots Wang Chuqin and Liang Jingkun, respectively and fourth on the world list.
In the middle, in the third place of the ranking, is the Japanese Tomokazu Harimoto, also considered as one of the candidates for the title in the Macao Tournament. With ambitions in the first places, Brazilian Hugo Calderano (5th), Frenchman Felix Lebrun (6th), Swedish Truls Moregard (7th) and German Patrick Franziska (8th).
Contrary to what happened in 2024, with Marcos Freitas and João Geraldo, Portugal will not have any representative in the male condition.
In women, Luso table tennis features 31 -year -old Jieni Shao. The veteran Chinese-born player, born in Anshan, moved to Gondomar in 2010 and in 2015 became a Portuguese citizen, having participated in the 2016 Olympic Games in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. It currently ranks 52nd in the ranking.
In this class of women, Macao's audience will have the opportunity to see Sun Yingsha and Wang Manyu, who occupy the first two places on the world list, which played in the final of last year, with the victory of the first, as well as two more accrediting players of the Popular Republic of China: Wang Yidi (3rd) and Chen Yingtong (4th).
Moreover, in the female board of the MSAR Tournament, they will also play the Japanese Hina Hayata (5th), Miwa Harimoto (6th), Satsuki Odo (8th) and Mima Ito (9th), Chinese Kuan Man (7th) and South Korean Shin Yubin.
The World Cup is organized by the Institute of Sport,
Galaxy Entertainment and “World Table Tennis Management Group”, and co-organized by the Macao General Ping-Pong Association, with the supervision of the International Table Tennis Federation (ITTF).</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Commercial duel becomes a war between US and China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/duelo-comercial-transforma-se-em-guerra-entre-eua-china/</link><description>China has responded to US President Donald Trump's last tariff blow, who remains convinced that his commercial coping works “really well”, an idea increasingly questioned by investors and consumers. Markets avoid the US dollar, debt and actions, in a widespread wave of distrust that tends to occur with emerging countries, but not with the world's main power. Jamie Dimon, director of JP Morgan, acknowledged on Friday that the economy faces "considerable turbulence." In a message on his social Truth platform, Trump defended his strategy on Friday, stating that his government is “doing it really well,” but avoided pronouncing Beijing's announcement that he has increased his customs tariffs on American products to 125%. "The president made it very clear that he is open to an agreement with China," White House spokeswoman Karoline Leavitt told the press. "It's optimistic," he added. The Republican believes that China wants to negotiate, but the statements of the Chinese Ministry of Finance indicate another departure. “With this level of tariffs, US products exported to China are no longer viable on the market,” and if Washington continues to increase rates, “China will ignore,” he warned. Uncertainty presses the dollar, which reached the lowest level on Friday in over three years. European bags are again in red and in Wall Street volatility is on the agenda. In addition, income from 10 -year -old US government titles are rising, which means the US must pay more to get into debt. And consumer confidence in the country fell dramatically in April, according to a barometer from the University of Michigan. This is a “widespread and unanimous [in trust] fall, regardless of age, income, educational level, place of residence or political affiliation,” said research director Joanne Hsu. The American federal reserve says it is “absolutely prepared” to act and stabilize markets if necessary. Is this instability sufficient to force Trump to give in? On Wednesday, the Republican retreated in the protective offensive by temporarily pausing for 90 days customs tariffs for dozens of business partners, except China, which has been in force other overcrowders and a universal minimum of 10%. Europeans continue under cross fire: under pressure to negotiate with the US and forced to reach an agreement with China. At a meeting with Spanish Prime Minister Pedro Sánchez, in Beijing on Friday, Chinese President Xi Jinping asked the European Union to “remain united” against Trump's trade war. Sánchez called for a “rectification” of the commercial deficit with China, but without “hindering the potential for growth of relationships” with Beijing. French President Emmanuel Macron warned that the break is "fragile" and asked Europeans to be "strong." The EU suspended the planned contracted and European Commerce Commissioner, Maros Sefcovic, travels today to Washington. If negotiations with the US fail, the European Commission may apply taxes to US technology giants, it threatened the president, Ursula Von der Leyen. In this battle of the great powers, the UN warned about the possible consequences for poor countries such as Lesoto, Cambodia, Madagascar and Myanmar. They are “the most vulnerable” and “less equipped to adapt,” says Pamela Coke-Hamilton, the executive director of the United Nations International Trade Center and the World Trade Organization.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reduction of excavations requires private cooperation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reducao-de-escavacoes-requer-cooperacao-de-privados/</link><description>At a meeting with construction and engineering sectors, the secretary for transport and public works requested cooperation with the aim of “reducing the need for repeated excavations on public roads due to new enterprises”
 
The Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, asked the private sector to collaborate to reduce repeated excavations on public roads due to the construction of new enterprises. The Working Group for the optimization of the Coordination of Road Works held a meeting with representatives of the construction and engineering sectors, having discussed the theme of pre-reserved conduct.
Raymond Tam stressed that all entities must include, in the initial phase of the project, the arrangement of underground conduct, seeking to ensure that future bonds of the new buildings are limited to the interior of the respective workshops, as a statement of the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) can be read.
According to he said, "the pre-restraint of conduct is one of the fundamental elements for the optimization of road works." In addition to the support and cooperation of public interest entities, “the active collaboration of private prosecutors is also necessary, especially in the project phase, and should take into account the location of pre-reserved conduct,” he said.
In this sense, the Secretary for Transport and Public Works requested the cooperation of the construction and engineering sector with the guidelines of the Working Group, coordinating well the projects and preliminary provisions, in order to reduce the need for repeated excavations on public roads due to new enterprises.
According to the press release, representatives of the various sectors expressed availability to “actively collaborate, striving to coordinate and optimize the project and execution of the works”.
At the meeting were, for example, members of the Macao Architects Association, the Macao Engineers Association and the Macao Engineering Consultant Association, among others.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSA and Guangdong will improve judicial and legal cooperation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-guangdong-vao-aprimorar-cooperacao-judicial-juridica/</link><description>A delegation headed by Guangdong Attorney General was at MSAR, having met with the chief executive, the prosecutor and the corruption commissioner. Both regions intend to improve judicial and legal cooperation
 
Macao “will constantly improve the exchange and cooperation with the interior of China, especially in the court and legal areas of Guangdong Province,” said the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, in a meeting with the party secretary and attorney general of Guangdong Popular Attorney, Feng Jian. The two were at the Government's headquarters, where they approached precisely the reinforcement of interaction and exchange in the judicial area between the parties.
According to the note of the Social Communication Office, Sam Hou Fai spoke concretely in the promotion, jointly, of the “optimization” of the commercial conflict resolution mechanism, as well as in the encouragement of integrated legal services development, “providing safeguarding the rule of law in the creation of the great bay and in -depth cooperation zone”.
The leader of the MSAR added that by promoting the implementation of the principle “a country, two systems” with “singular characteristics of Macao”, “Macao's judicial body has always rigorously played its functions according to the law and demonstrated its important role in resolving social disputes, safeguarding the rule of law, promoting socioeconomic development and ensuring the global stability of society”. It also guaranteed that "the government will continue to govern in accordance with the law and promote the progress of the rule of law."
On the first day of the visit to the MSAR, the Guangdong delegation visited the Public Prosecution Service (MP), where it was received by prosecutor Chan Tsz King, who promised to continue to “firmly fulfill the principle 'a country' and to take advantage of the 'two systems', playing their role as a communication bridge between the inland China and the public ministries of Portuguese -speaking countries, in order to increase the influence of the state international scenario ”.
Already Feng Jian indicated that Guangdong Attorney's Offices and the Macau MP could reinforce the exchange, “articulating better with the construction and development of the great bay”. In addition, he considered that the two parties can deepen judicial cooperation and foster interaction between the staff of the two regions.
Also the commissioner against corruption, to Ieong Seong, met with Feng Jian, having exchanged opinions on investigation cooperation between the Attorney's Office and the execution of the law of the two parties and the investigation procedures. In Ieong Seong's view, Guangdong and Macao "have a close relationship and there is a large space for cooperation between the judicial and law enforcement of the two regions, and steps can be taken to address cooperation in exchange and personnel formation."</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Casinos concentrate 15% of illegal smokers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casinos-concentram-15-dos-fumadores-ilegais/</link><description>Macao authorities detected 1,262 cases of illegal smoke in the first quarter of this year, with casinos outstanding the most infringered locations, according to health services. Until March, six cases suspected of breach of the prevention and control of alcoholic beverages by minors were reported.
 
Between January and March, health services inspectors (SSM) made 62,410 inspections to establishments related to regimes of prevention and control of smoking smoking and alcohol consumption, which makes a daily average of 693, having discovered a total of 1,370 cases of offenses, according to data released by the body led by Alvis Lo.
The SSM, the Public Security Police Corps, the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games (DICJ) and Customs Services detected 1,262 cases of illegal smoke, 71 electronic cigarette transport to the entry and exit of Macao and 31 suspected violation of other provisions of the anti-tabage law, namely the non-postering of timelessness and notices Prohibition of smoking and selling tobacco products to children under 18.
Casinos appeared as the places with the largest number of people smoking in forbidden areas, registering 194 cases (15.4%of the total), followed by restoration establishments, with 186 (14.7%), and bus stops, with 139 (11%). Together, the DICJ and the SSM made 212 inspections to the casinos between January and March.
On the other hand, six cases suspected of violation of the alcohol consumption prevention and control regime, three of which involving the sale or availability of alcohol to minors. The other three cases were related to the non-posting of sales for sale or availability of alcoholic beverages to minors and the fact that establishments that provide self-service services not clearly defined the areas of exposure or advertising to alcohol, without warning in Chinese, Portuguese and English languages. According to the SSM, the cases have already been instructed for proper follow -up.
If in doubt about the age of buyers, establishments must request the presentation of an identification document. In case of refusal, it is assumed that the subject is lower, and the sale must be rejected to him, otherwise a fine of 20,000 patacas should be applied. In addition, the supply of alcoholic beverages for minors for non -commercial purposes can be punished with a fine between 1,500 and 20,000 patacas. Establishments that do not affix the destics, according to the law, incorporate fines of up to 200 thousand patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vitória Clube in focus on the hockey championship</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vitoria-clube-em-foco-campeonato-de-hoquei/</link><description>The Macao Roller Hockey Championships came to an end, which joined three categories, with Vitória Clube won two titles and Lusitania one. The race also served to give the players of the selections competitive, in view of the Easter tournament in Taiwan and Asia, in South Korea
 
The Macao Skating Association (APM) has again organized the Roller Hockey Championships with three teams, Vitória Clube, FC Porto and Lusitânia Sport Club. The competition is intended for three categories, two Open, male and female, and one for under16.
Vitória Clube stood out by winning the titles in the younger and Open Ladies class, while Lusitania won in Open Men.
Regarding the tournament of male senior players, Lusitania, oriented by Nuno Antunes, secured first place with the triumph in the last round against FC Porto 5-2, ending the championship with 10 points, against five from Vitória and one of the portistas. The best scorer was Alfredo Almeida, with 11 goals scored, against five by José Sousa, Nuno Antunes and Augusto Fernandes.
In Open Women, Vitória, guided by Augusto Fernandes, won all games, adding 12 points. FC Porto and Lusitania were classified, both with three. Cao Chi Cheng was the championship scorer, with nine goals, followed Kira Fernandes with four.
In the race for young people under 16, Vitória also did not give any point, closing six in front of Lusitania. FC Porto did not score.
In the list of best markers of this rank, three players got the same number of goals (three): Hoi Ka Seng, Wong Weng Chon and Mário Fernandes. Cedric Correia pointed two.
These roller hockey championships, which took place during six days in the northeastern Taipa pavilion, belonging to the former University of Macao, served to give competitive pace to the players who make up the work of the selections, in view of two events to perform this year.
Between the 18th and 20th of this month, the Easter tournament will take place in Taiwan (Nanta-Taichung), where Macau will feature three teams, two seniors, men and women, and one from the U19 category. The race will also feature Taiwan's main selection and the regional formations of Taipei, Taichung and Kaoshiung.
In July, it will be the turn of the Asian in South Korea, in which the MSar will be represented by the same formations.
By the end of the year, and according to information provided by APM President António Aguiar, are also planned games against Guangdong (Interport) in October or November, and at the New Year tournament in Zaoqing in December.
Meanwhile, Macau will be the scene of two roller hockey courses, one for national referees in May and another for coaches given by Portuguese technicians in June.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Technology intersects with nature in the hostel</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/tecnologia-cruza-se-natureza-albergue/</link><description>The SCM hostel will host the exhibition “Verses da Rain in late spring”, organized by the Circle of Macao Culture Friends. Multimedia works will be presented by five artists who include the “relationship between technology and nature”

























The Circle of Macao Culture Friends (CAC) will present more than 10 multimedia works on the art exhibition of the new media “verses of rain in late spring”, with free admission. The opening ceremony will take place at 6:30 pm at Gallery A2 and the D1 pavilion of the SCM hostel, with works by Cindy Ng Sio Ieng, Kit Kit Kit Ka Ieng, Wang Tou Kun, Chon Iap Lam and Xiaoqiao Li.
Sponsored by the MSAR Culture Development Fund, the exhibition will present multimedia works, in which modern technological methods such as digital photography, interactive digital sound installations, computer painting and invisible paint are used, in a reinterpretation of “ecological wisdom embedded in the 24 solar terms as a vocabulary of technological art,” says the organization.
The works simulate effects of natural light and shadow through virtual lighting techniques that create the “aesthetics of spring beauty”, according to CAC. At the same time, real -time sound data is used to allow the public to “experience the pace of coexistence between all living beings”.
“This interdisciplinary creation breaks with traditional narrative forms in art,” can be read in the press release, and explores issues of technology and sustainable development. The purpose of the show is to provide the public with a cyclic philosophical experience of “rain nourishes all grains” and encouraging “contemplation of the relationship between technology and nature while appreciating art”.
Created in 1985, CAC is committed to promoting culture, arts, heritage, architecture, literature and other cultural activities of Macao, exposing the creation and talents of Macao. Founded by Carlos Marreiros, Mio Pang Fei, Kwok Woon, Un Chi iam, Ung Vai Meng and Victor Marreiros, CAC organizes events such as exhibitions, lectures, study visits and seminars to foster cultural exchange between Macao and the world, presenting works by international artists.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Photographs of the “Invisible” in the Portuguese Bookstore</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/fotografias-invisivel-na-livraria-portuguesa/</link><description>The Portuguese Bookstore Gallery presents tomorrow the exhibition “Remains of the City, by artist Pedro Paz. The 33 photographs are a“ visual exploration of the city of Macau ”that reveals the“ invisible in the visible ”

The Cultural Association of Ascens Macau will open tomorrow, at 18:30, at the Portuguese Bookstore Gallery, the photography exhibition “Remains of the City”, by Pedro Paz. This initiative, which marks the solo debut of the author, is a “visual exploration of the city of Macao presented from a unique and unique perspective” composed of three series (“You've Got Mail” and Framing the Invisible ”and “Where Chaos Meets Color”), which reveal traces and memories of a city rich in history and contrasts, according to the association's statement.
The exhibition, which will be evident until May 6, proposes a pictorial view, without human presence, inviting the public to reflect and observe the urban daily life of Macao otherwise, where “the details that often pass us unnoticed into poetic compositions of aesthetic impact”.
The 33 color photographs, in digital PVC format, were captured by the chamber of a mobile phone. The author's work immortalizes fragments of reality, giving them depth and highlighting details of everyday life "that escape the hasty look from the inhabitants of the city," says the association.
The author reveals the "invisible in the visible" and proposes a reflection on the deep layers of reality, "where the banal and ephemeral are eternalized." The photographs offer an “experience that goes beyond the look”. Each image invites the audience to rediscover the meaning and beauty of the small things of everyday life.
Through this work, the artist intends to create a bridge with the observer and reveal that the territory and its history offer an important platform for the exchange of cultures and the creation of their own identity.
Pedro Paz was born in Lisbon in 1979, and is a degree in history, with a minor in art and heritage. He lived in Macao until 1997 and returned to the city in 2012. By revisiting the streets and historical alleys that marked his childhood, he rediscovered “elements of a distant past” and recorded urban landscapes, textures and “unlawful” places.
The exhibition has the sponsorship of the Fund for the Development of Culture of MSAR and the support of the Portuguese Bookstore. The gallery is open every day from 11:00 to 19:00, with free admission.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Exceptional works” yield 30,000 Patacas at the Visual Arts Show</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-excepcionais-rendem-30-mil-patacas-na-mostra-de-artes-visuais/</link><description>Between May 9 and 11, the applications will be open for the collection of works for the “Annual Exhibition of Macao Visual Arts of 2025 - Chinese Painting and Caligraphy category”. The reception of works will take place in the “Art Space” of the Cultural Center of Macau, between 10:00 and 19:00, the Cultural Institute (IC) informed, challenging all local artists to present works of “traditional Chinese painting, handwriting, sinetes and experimental ink”. 10 prizes will be awarded for “exceptional works”, each worth 30,000 patacas. The winners will also be invited to participate next year in an exhibition organized by IC in cultural and museum institutions outside Macao. The works will be selected by a jury consisting of five artists from the interior of China, based on the “criteria of originality, creativity, content and expressiveness,” says the IC. Competitors must be adult residents, which may have only one original work, or a set of up to four pieces, which has been completed between 2023 and the current year. Applications must be made in person, presenting the registration form duly completed, a copy of the BIR and the respective work. The exhibition regulation and the registration form can be discharged on the site or obtained at the IC Visual Arts Development Division in Tap Seac Square. Through this initiative, the body aims to “promote the inheritance, innovation and sustainable development of traditional Chinese painting and handling in Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young volunteers have received 3,300 awards since 2014</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-voluntarios-receberam-3-300-premios-desde-2014/</link><description>The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) delivered 582 prizes under the “Youth Volunteer Incentive Plan” of the last year, including 48 platinum, 112 gold, 99 silver and 323 bronze. Since 2014, the year in which the plan has been implemented, more than 3,300 awards have been awarded, says a DSEDJ statement. The ceremony brought together more than 450 people, which included DSEDJ subdirectors, Teng Sio Hong and Wong Ka Ki, Youth Council vowels, public institutions and services representatives, social associations and schools, as well as a group of young volunteers. According to DSEDJ, the award -winning young people contributed a total of more than 120,000 hours of service in sports, educational and community health, international exchange for young people and rehabilitation services, among others. You can apply for young prizes that accumulate over a year more than 100 hours of volunteering. DSEDJ guarantees that it will continue to actively promote the participation of young people in volunteer work, “injecting positive energy into the Macao society”. Interested parties can apply to the DSEDJ website.</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Dextinction” of the “Terrible Wolf” revives controversy among scientists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/desextincao-lobo-terrivel-reaviva-polemica-entre-cientistas/</link><description>A magnificent white wolf printed the cover of the magazine "Time", accompanied by a headline announcing that the species "returned" from the extinction and images of three offspring flooded social networks, after the animals were presented by an American company as a success of genetics that resurrected a prehistory animal. However, the scientific community is divided between skepticism and enthusiasm.



















The Colossal Bioscience Start-up, headquartered in Texas, has caused a furor in recent days by release photos and videos of what it has described as three young “Aenocyon Dirus”, originating from North America and extinguished for over 12,000 years. "For the first time in the history of humanity, Colossal successfully recovered an extinct species, through the science of decay," he said on his website.
“This moment represents not only a milestone for us as a company, but an advance for science, conservation and humanity,” celebrated Colossal Bioscience on social networks.
The company explained that it changed the DNA of a modern wolf (“canis lupus”) with selected genes of fossils of wolf. This modified genetic material was used to fertilize an egg of sinzing wolf and inseminate a bitch. The result was three "wolves", according to Colossal.
“I find these statements extremely exaggerated,” commented molecular biology expert Alan Cooper, who participated in a prior study of the Wolf-Terrible DNA. "It's like I put some Neanderthal genes on someone, which would give her more hair and muscles, and then I called him Neanderthal. This is millions of kilometers from Neanderthal. It would be a hairy human," he said, quoted by AFP agency.
"This is not a terrible wolf. They have created an animal with phenotypic characteristics of a Terrible Wolf," said ecologist Lisette Waits, a professor at the University of Idaho, admitting, however, that this is an important advance.
Quoted by the BBC, zoologist Philip Seddon of the University of Otago, New Zealand, also argued that these animals will actually be "mild wolves, genetically modified."
Paleogeneticist Nic Rawlen, also from the University of Otago, argues that the old DNA of the prehistoric wolf extracted from fossilized remains would be very degraded and damaged to be copied or biologically cloned. "Ancient DNA is as if we put fresh DNA in a 500 degree oven. It comes out fragmented, like shards and dust. We can rebuild it, but it's not good enough to do anything else with him," he said.
Instead, Rawlence adds, members of the “Despite” team have employed a new synthetic biology technology, using old DNA to identify key code segments that they could edit in the DNA of a living animal today, a gray wolf in the case. "So what the colossal has produced is a scrub wolf, but it has some characteristics similar to those of the prehistoric wolf, such as a larger skull and white hair. It is a hybrid," he said.
To raise the animal, the colossal analyzed the DNA of the "wolf" from two fossils, and compared it to that of the sink wolf. In concrete, he extracted genetic material - which holds information on the characteristics of a living being and instructions for the body to work - from a 13,000 -year -old tooth found in Ohio, USA, and a piece of 72,000 -year -old skull in Idaho, also US.
The company determined that the two species were "99.5% identical," Beth Shapiro, chief scientist of the project, told AFP.
The differences in DNA were also analyzed to identify the genes responsible for the size, muscle structure and color of the certible wolf. With this information, the company has changed the genome of the sinzing wolf by inserting these genes of the extinct animal.
In total the company has made 20 editions in 14 genes using a manipulation technique known as CRISPR-CAs9, also used in human genetics. With this, it would be possible to obtain some characteristics of the Terrible Wolf: White, larger hair, open shoulders, wider head, more muscles in the typical legs and vocalizations of the species, marked by howls and whimpers.
It is a small number of modifications, which does not include all variations between species. "The more we limit the number of changes, the more possibilities we have to get a healthy animal," explained Beth Shapiro.
After the edition of the genes, the experts transferred the core of this cell - where the entire DNA is kept - to an egg whose nucleus itself had been previously removed. In turn, this egg was cultivated to become an embryo, which was implanted in the womb of a domestic dog. The dog had a normal pregnancy and, on October 1, 2024, were born the alleged "wolves".
About whether animals are "wolves-terrible" or only genetically modified wolves, the scientist said it is "semantic debate," noting that it will never be possible to "create something that is 100% genetically" to an extinct species: "This was not the goal. Our goal is to create functional equivalents of these species," he said.
Two of the wolves were baptized from Rómulo and Remo, a reference to Roman mythology, and the third is called Khaleesi, inspired by the success series "Game of Thrones", which honors the majestic "Wolf-Terrible".
According to BBC, Romulus, Remo and Khaleesi are kept in a large private reserve in the US whose location was not disclosed to protect animals. There is no prediction that they may be released in nature or crusaders to produce a new generation.
 
Dodós and mammoths
Colossal Biosciences plans to replicate the procedure with at least three more extinguished species: Dodós (“raphus cucullatus”), endemic birds of the maurious islands, lane mammoths (“mammuthus primigenius”) and the Tasmania wolf (“Thylacinus cynocephalus”). In early March, the company published photos of hairy rats, with a genetic composition of mammoth, causing controversy immediately.
For some scientists, this goal is simply impossible and at the same time dangerous. Others describe as an ambitious initiative that would help combat biodiversity collapse.
Waits, a conservation expert, believes that the technique “could help save endangered species” due to the lack of genetic diversity caused by the small number of individuals. With its ambitious promises, Colossal raised more than $ 200 million, an amount that would probably not have been invested in other conservation efforts, according to Waits.
However, the technical prowess of the Texan company raise ethical questions about the welfare of animals, the rules and the foundation of the proposal. "I don't think people will say," We can let these animals disappear because we can bring them back later, "he told AFP Ronald Sandler, director of the Northeastern University Institute of Ethics, warning, however, that it is necessary to not lose sight of what really matters, which is to face the deep causes of extinction, and the loss of animal habitat.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-04-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>