<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Simon Vong returns to AMCM to replace Henrietta Lau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/simon-vong-regressa-a-amcm-para-substituir-henrietta-lau/</link><description>Macao's monetary authority again undergoes changes in the structure of the Board of Directors, leaving the current substitute president, Henrietta Lau, and entering her place Simon Vong, former administrator of the body and so far director of statistical and census services, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao found. Vong will start roles on July 1, for a period of six months. Henrietta Lau returns to the place of AMCM administrator
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin Yip, will promote changes in the board of directors of the Monetary Authority of Macao (AMCM), hoping that the respective order will be released soon in the official bulletin.
According to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau with a knowledge -source of the case, the current substitute president, Henrietta Lau, will return to the position of AMCM administrator, entering the presidency of the body Simon Vong Sin Man, who ran Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). It will start functions from July 1 and for a period of six months.
Those who will soon be officially designated Effective President of AMCM had already held the position of member of the administration for four years after being appointed by Lionel Leong, at the time secretary for the economy and finance. Simon Vong had taken office in June 2018 and since 2020 also held the position of president of the Institute of Financial Training.
Degree in Business Management from the East Asia University of Macao, Simon Vong completed masters in Economics from the University of Jinan and in Public Administration from the National Institute of Administration of China and the University of Beijing. Between 1983 and 1989, he was auditor of a private company, and journalist of the Chinese language newspaper Va Kio, between 1986 and 1989.
During the Portuguese Administration, he held the positions of Deputy Technical, Technical and Superior Technician of DSEC. In June 1999, he was promoted to the head of the Division for Promotion and Information Diffusion of the same organism, a position he held until 2002.
In February 2002 he was appointed aggregate coach and advisor to the Secretary's Office for Economics and Finance, which remained until 2018, the year in which he joined the Board of Directors of the Monetary Authority. After the departure of AMCM in 2022, Simon Vong was executive vowel of the Board of Directors of the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment of Macao.
Already Henrietta Lau had been appointed Substitute President of AMCM in March this year, as the Jornal Tribuna de Macau said, taking the place of Benjamin Chan, after taking office as an administrator for the bank.
In June 2024, the then Secretary for Economics and Finance, Law Wai Nong, had renewed the appointment of Benjamin Chan, as president of the AMCM Board of Directors for a period of a year, with practical effects from August 26. At the same time, the secretary also renewed, also for a year, the nominations of Henrietta Lau and Esther Law as vowels of the AMCM Board of Directors.
In addition to Simon Vong, who will then be the new president of the AMCM Board of Directors from next month, another new element, whose name we cannot find out, will integrate the structure of the Administration, which will thus have five members.
The changes were communicated during a meeting held at the AMCM facilities last Wednesday by an element of the Secretary's Office for the Economy and Finance.
JTM also knows that Simon Vong will be accompanied by four people of his confidence to occupy positions in the body's structure.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Restoration of the courtyard of eternal happiness partially completed in 2026</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/restauro-patio-da-eterna-felicidade-parcialmente-concluido-em-2026/</link><description>The courtyard of eternal happiness has gained advances in restoration and revitalization, with the general project predicting the contract in two phases. According to the IC, in the first phase, the buildings above the stairs in the courtyard will be restored. The work costs 10 million patacas and is expected to end in the first half of next year. As for the second phase, the constructions below the stairs in the courtyard will be repaired, and the presentation of the project regarding the 2nd phase of restoration will be underway

Last year, the Cultural Institute (IC) concluded the elaboration of the General Restoration Plan of the Eternal Happiness Courtyard, located near the ruins of São Paulo, and the project was divided into two phases. According to the IC, in the first phase, restoration works will be carried out in buildings 8 to 10 and No. 16 to 18, located above the courtyard stairs.
In a response sent to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the body revealed that the first phase of the courtyard's restoration project involves expenses of 10 million patacas. According to anticipated, the endeavor must be completed in the first half of 2026. Regarding the second phase, which consists of restoring the constructions located below the stairs in the courtyard, the IC pointed out that the project presentation procedures are underway.
According to the IC, the project mainly implies the structural repair of the constructions, according to the revitalization and use of the courtyard needs. In addition, infrastructure will be added such as modern water supply and drainage systems, electricity and fire prevention.
In the same answer, the body led by Leong Wai Man also assured that the IC has continuously promoted the restoration project of the courtyard of eternal happiness.
At the same time, in the third quarter of this year, the work of installation of a barriers without barriers in the Beco dos Faitião, to connect to the courtyard of eternal happiness and St. Anthony Street, as part of the pedestrian system improvement. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the elevator design will be in “harmony” with the style of the historical buildings of the eternal happiness courtyard, with elements of gray brick.
It is recalled that, as a Chinese-style courtyard in better preservation and the largest in Macao, consisting of 13 buildings with unified architectural style and high continuity, the courtyard of eternal happiness was received by IC in 2019.
After the reception of the courtyard, recovery and revitalization work was carried out, being open to the public some buildings such as temporary exhibition spaces, in which reinforcement works were carried out. For example, the courtyard has already welcomed an exhibition about life in courtyards and alleys and still displays another about Lingnan's traditional architecture.
According to the IC, the courtyard recovery project - which took into account the intangible cultural heritage and the elements of the creative industry - cost 1.7 million patacas.
In general, the IC will cooperate with Sands China to take advantage of the geographical advantages of the courtyard of eternal happiness and the Street of Estalagues, in order to inject different artistic elements to enrich the urban cultural atmosphere. Specifically, Sands plans to transform the courtyard of eternal happiness into a place of creation and exchange for contemporary artists, reinforcing the atmosphere of arts appreciation and the community connection with the adjacent streets, such as Street of Estlagentes.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Joey Lau leads list of Jiangmen countrymen</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/joey-lau-lidera-lista-dos-conterraneos-de-jiangmen/</link><description>Representatives Zheng Anting and Lo Choi in are out of the list of candidates from the Jiangmen Country Association team, who yesterday presented a list of 14 candidates, betting on a “new combination” for the race to the album for direct suffrage. As a head-to-head, is the former deputy named Joey Lau, followed by the director of the Ouri-Aisarias Association, Lee Koi Ian
 
Yesterday, the last day for the presentation to the Electoral Affairs Committee (Caeal) of the candidacy for the Legislative Assembly (AL) elections, the Union of Macau-Guangdong, team of the Jiangmen Association of Counseling, submitted a list of 14 candidates for direct suffrage and the political program.
The list has as a head-rist Joey Lau, former deputy appointed and current director of the Macao Economic Association. Lee Koi Ian, director of the Macao Goldsmith Association and president of the Macao Youth Entrepreneurs Association, is number two. Following is NG NGA FAN, vice president of the Jiangmen countryman's Association.
The new structure of the list means that the current deputies linked to the “Jiangmen countrymen”, Zheng Anting and Lo Choi In, will not compete for al. Zheng Anting has been elected deputy for direct suffrage since 2013, while Lo Choi In is also elected by Via Direct since 2021.
O mandatário, Chan Sio Cheng, presidente da Associação dos Conterrâneos de Jiangmen, referiu que a equipa vai candidatar-se pela quinta vez no campo do sufrágio directo das eleições para a AL. According to he described, the team bets on a "new combination", "new actions" and "new atmosphere".
Joey Lau pointed out that the “fundamental mission” of the candidacy is “making Macau happier”, so in the future will boost the government to realize a more dynamic economy and the pension for elderly linked to the value of social risk. As stressed, at the same time, the team will also work for the governments of Guangdong and Macao to allow the elderly to enjoy medical services, pension and subsidy for the elderly, when they live in cities in the interior of China that are part of the great bay.
Lee Koi Ian pointed out that the team expects to boost the government to launch more economy stimulation measures and favorable to the transformation and update of small and medium enterprises (SME). In addition, he stressed that the team will continually follow the issue of community economy. At this point, it expects the government to beautify the old areas to attract more tourists to consume.
On the other hand, it has ensured that the team will seek to make the stabilization policies of companies, employment and well-being of the “more detailed, profound and realistic” population, and at the same time will promote cooperation between Macau and Guangdong, so that the large companies of the Great Bay can help Macao to develop abroad and so that young people of the field can gain greater development space.
In turn, NG NGA Fan said the team will urge the government to create a comprehensive service system directed to the studies, employment and entrepreneurship of young people.
For al scheduled al schedules for September 14, Caeal received a total of eight lists of candidates who will compete for direct suffrage and six lists linked to the indirect pathway. Caeal will affix the list of applications tomorrow.
 
A dozen deputies are not renowned
Presented that all lists are to the direct suffrage of the elections for the Legislative Assembly, it is observed that three of the current deputies will not re-apply: Zheng Anting, Lo Choi In and Ma Io Fong. In addition, Si Ka Lon, currently elected by the way, starts to compete in the field of indirect suffrage. As for the 12 deputies elected by indirect suffrage, the change is more evident, and only five advance with master's. Among those who do not re -apply are Kou Hoi In, Chui Sai Cheong, Chan Chak Mo, Vong Hin Fai, Chan Iek Lap, Law Chan U and Wang Sai Man. On the other hand, two appointed deputies - MA Chi Seng and Iau Teng Pio - are in list of candidates for indirect suffrage. It is recalled that there are then seven deputies appointed by the Chief Executive.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>First case of “space oil” trafficking</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/primeiro-caso-de-trafico-de-petroleo-espacial/</link><description>A non-resident worker was arrested by the Judicial Police (PJ), in the first case of “ethomidate” trafficking, as long as it was included in the list of controlled substances. Sit Chong Meng, PJ's director, said the body acquired emerging drug detection equipment, including rapid tests to detect “space oil”
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Judicial Police (PJ) discovered, on Wednesday, the first case of “ethomidate” trafficking, also known as “space oil”, since the alteration of the drug combat law. A man, of Vietnamese nationality and non-resident worker, was arrested on suspicion of trafficking, in a fraction where he resided, according to PJ.
The agents found several bottles with “ethomidate”, totaling 635 grams and evaluated at 37,000 patacas, as well as electronic cigarettes and a “large amount of packing tools”. According to the authorities, the man began trafficking “space oil” three weeks ago, with compatriots at MSAR and at a price of a thousand patacas per dose. The suspect refused to collaborate with the investigation.
The PJ director explained that at the beginning of the year, the body acquired emerging drug detection machines, including rapid “ethomidate” kits, which allow the test to be completed in three minutes. In order to respect human rights, the tests are performed inside the police facilities.
"The PJ has become very aware of the situation of 'ethomidate' infiltration in schools and community neighborhoods," said Sit Chong Meng, so in recent years, a drug prevention training plan has been developed.
Last year, police discovered two young traffickers of “space oil”, 16 and 18 years old. Prior to the change to the list of prohibited substances, and since 2023, the MSAR registered five cases related to "ethomidate". Four were accused of involvement of other substances, already included in the control list. In the other case, evidence of “ethomidate” was found in electronic cigarettes.
The PJ director also reiterated that since the revision of the smoking control law in 2022, "Macao has already managed to control the problem of electronic cigarettes." Asked how authorities can more effectively combat covert drug cases, Sit Chong Meng explained that "PJ focuses on gathering information on cases in community neighborhoods, hoping to obtain criminal information at different levels to investigate."
In order to mark the “International Day of Combating Drugs”, PJ yesterday inaugurated the “Drug Fight Week”, with the purpose of bringing drug combat information to community neighborhoods, “so that residents and students know the damage of drugs.”
It also stressed that, between 2014 and 2024, the number of trafficking and drug use cases decreased. According to the director, 94 trafficking cases and 111 consumption were established in 2014. Last year, 49 trafficking and 15 consumption cases were counted, less 48% and 87%, respectively, representing “notorious reduction rates”, he said.
Since the beginning of the week, 24 substances, including “ethomidate”, have been included in the list of substances controlled by the authorities, under the anti-drug law. The "ethomidate" is an intravenous hypnotic of short action, indicated for the induction of general anesthesia. The substance has been used by young people for consumption through electronic cigarettes.
In 2024, the total number of drug consumers recorded in the territory was 148, an annual increase of 24.4%, according to data from the “central registration system of toxicode dependents”. Of these, seven were young people under 21 years old (two more in annual terms). On the other hand, 446 requests for detox support were verified, of which about 16% were new cases.
According to the World Drug Report, published yesterday by the UN, cocaine traffickers are being able to penetrate new markets, including Asia. According to the organization, cocaine supply has grown in areas where demand and consumption were often low, such as China.
Another trend that the UN has checked in almost all regions is Nitazene consumption, "which can be sold like other drugs, such as heroin, or added to other drugs." While in 2020 trafficking and consumption of Nitazene was exclusive to North America and Europe, between 2023 and 2024 the substance was also located in Asian countries, including China.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>André Couto returns to the tracks with two races in Zhejiang</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/andre-couto-regressa-as-pistas-duas-corridas-em-zhejiang/</link><description>André Couto returns this weekend to compete, running in one of the rounds of the China Tourism Car Championship, in the Zhejiang circuit. The Macao driver was invited by an unofficial Honda team, which could mean “good prospects” to start thinking about a possible presence at the Macao Grand Prix in November this year. Couto has been linked to the formation of young Formula 4 pilots on the continent

Victor Rebelo
 
The return to André Couto's tracks, after half a year of absence, takes place this weekend at the Zhejiang circuit, where the Macao driver will crew a Honda, with the MacPro Racing team, in the two races scheduled for the third round of the China Touring Car Championship (CTCC).
"I've tested the car, which seems to be in good condition," Couto told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, adding that the first official tests, but not yet qualification, will be performed today. "Then we can get times and get an idea of ​​what we can do on Saturday and Sunday," he said.
The pilot already knows the Zhejiang track, located in the city of Shaoxing, saying it was a new 3.2-kilometer-long circuit, where he ran a few years ago when he also participated in CTCC races, having obtained a second place.
About the presence in the remaining journeys of the championship, Couto pointed out that "may not be possible", since the team in which he will run in Honda is not official. Therefore, “economic support is not much, which should not allow me to take more evidence this season,” he says.
"It's very good for me and it appears as an excellent opportunity to go back seriously," he said, admitting the return to other races "that may lead me to be present in any of the Macao Grand Program events," which will take place in November.
It is recalled that the Portuguese pilot has not left the track, at the end of last year, when he participated in the world finals of the Lamborghini Super Trophy, which was played in Jerez de La Frontera, Spain, after several rounds throughout the year.
For this new season, Couto hoped to be able to repeat his performance at the Lamborghini Championship, in the GT category, but on the start of the start of the season everything changed. "Everything indicated that I would run through the same team of last year on this Lamborghini trophy, but two days from the cars to go to Australia, stage the first round, my team canceled the presence and I had no place," he said.
André Couto states that after that, it was complicated to enter another team, since "the places were already busy", so without competing.
Even without serious races, “but always waiting for possibilities like this that happens this weekend at CTTC, the pilot failed to maintain a strong connection with motoring, now in another function, that of“ coaching ”, through a management company that has several pilots.
Formula 4 and Formula 1 Academy gives you this new phase of your career, having the opportunity to train young people of those monolos, but also GT. "I have had a lot of work in these functions," he said. “While I dedicate myself to training amateur pilots and 'Gentleman Drivers', Formula 4 is more seriously because they are kids who have a dream of reaching Formula 1 and want to shorten the learning course, so we help in this process,” he attests.
Last week he was in Zhuhai with an 18 -year -old who asked him to be his coach, in a GT 4. “I always end up taking a little back in free training, to get the idea a little of what the car can do and the pilots go after this reference,” he says.
Regarding Formula 1 Academy, the now coach has been guiding a 16 -year -old Australian, Joanne Cicconte, who participates in the races of this category, after sighting in Karting tests in his country.
F1 Academy is an exclusively female racing class created by Formula 1 in 2023, with the aim of developing and preparing young pilots to advance to higher levels in motorsport, such as Formula 3, Formula 2 and, finally, Formula 1. The category offers track time, as well as technical, physical and mental support, with all 16 and 25 years.
André Couto's career is now slightly different from the past, but the pilot remains attached to motorsport. "Apart from the races I may make, for which I am always available to accept invitations that come to me, like this in the championship in China."
The curiosity is, in this same weekend, André Couto having his son Lucas, 12, to play for the first time a serious race of the Karting Championship of Macao, a modality that launched him in the international wanderings of motorsport. It remains to be seen if, with time and track experience, the popular saying is confirmed, "son of fish can swim."</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Victory in the Sino-Japanese War marked with various activities</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vitoria-na-guerra-sino-japonesa-assinalada-varias-actividades/</link><description>Macau will mark the 80th anniversary of China's victory in Sino-Japanese World War II with a series of activities. Among the events, highlighting a solemn session, with the presence of young students, as the Military Parade is taking place at Tiananmen Square, in Beijing, on September 3
 
A series of activities in Macao will mark the 80th anniversary of China's victory in Sino-Japanese War, which began in 1937 and extended until 1945. To mark the ephemeris, the Government of MSar people planned several events, including a commemorative solemn ceremony, on September 3, a military parade in Beijing, at Tiananmen Square.
The event will be attended by students from the territory and associative representatives, who will attend the direct transmission of the parade, and can also “hear President Xi Jinping's speech,” according to the secretary to social affairs and culture, LAM, at a press conference, during which the agenda of initiatives to organize was released.
In addition to the solemn session, the government will promote a thematic exhibition on the war in the forum complex, between the second half of August and the same period of September.
Regarding education, exclusive didactic content will be prepared on the subject, as well as develop studies to tell the context, the process of the main war and the important wars, as well as the history of the heroes of Batalha, “so that students can know this part of history systematically and comprehensive,” said the secretary.
At the same press conference, the director of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ), Kong Chi Meng, said the body will launch, with elementary and secondary students, complementary didactic manuals about the war.
At the same time, the government will support associations and different sectors in the realization of cultural and artistic shows, exhibitions, contests, or film promotion activities related to ephemeris.
LAM also revealed that sessions will take place for “discovery of historical data on Macau's participation in the war”, as well as will be promoted thematic seminars, directed to academic and cultural sectors.
In addition, the patriotic cultural resources that exist in Macao will be organized and improved, such as the former residence of General Ye Ting and the Xian Xinghai Memorial Museum. The objective, stressed the secretary, is "to make these spaces important to mark China's victory in the war and at the same time the elements of patriotism throughout the sins."
These activities will be the subject of general planning and reorganization, to constitute resources that can serve for thematic tourist itineraries on patriotism and itineraries for study visits.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Competition in Macau will reward Palop and Timor-Leste Startups</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/competicao-em-macau-vai-premiar-startups-de-palop-timor-leste/</link><description>The fifth edition of the “929 Challenge” competition in Macao will include an award for the best startup of African Portuguese-speaking (Palop) and Timor-Leste countries, the organization announced yesterday.
Marco Duarte Rizzo, co-founder of the “929 Challenge”, told Lusa that the 'Future Builders' award was created to encourage participants in the least developed Lusophone countries. "We have a common language, but the level of economic development of each of the countries is completely different," explained Rizzolio, on the sidelines of a press conference.
The latest edition of the Chinese startups competition and Portuguese -speaking countries recorded a new maximum, with over 1,600 participants in over 320 teams. However, in 2024, the “929 Challenge” did not receive any projects of Timor-Leste or Sao Tome and Principe.
With the new prize, RizzoLio said he hoped that this year's edition there will be 'startups' of all nine Lusophone countries. "The goal is that, encourage, but it is also helping ... If they can win that award, it is already motivating for them, so that they can develop the project," he explained.
The Portuguese startup IPlexmed, which develops fast genetic diagnostic devices, won last year's edition, while also the Portuguese NS2, which provides intelligent solutions to monitor water quality for sustainable aquaculture, was third.
The only time a Palop and Timor-Leste team arrived at the finalists was early in the first edition, released in 2021, in the middle of Covid-19 pandemic, then only directed to college students. A project from the Guinea-Bissau Lusophone University to install solar panels in the Gabu region of the east of the country, was in second place.
“In the end, those who win are often teams that already have mature products, mature services,” explained Rizzolio.
Registration is open until September 30, for both companies and university students.
Rizzolio, also a professor at the City of Macau, recalled that the competition has new partners, including Startupporto, Cape Verde Digital and Eduardo Mondlane University in Mozambique.
The best 16 plans - eight from companies and eight university students - will have 10 minutes to convince the jury of the “929 Challenge” and potential investors in the final in November.
The other co-founder of the competition, José Alves, stressed that the competition “is not a success yet” because so far it has not been able to attract projects to open doors in Macao.
"We need to identify the best startups, invest in them and bring them to the mainland China market, or take them from China to Lusophone countries," the professor explained.
The contest is co-organized by the Forum for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries (Macau) and various MSAR institutions, including all universities.
The Deputy Secretary General of the Macao Forum, Danilo Afonso Henriques, reiterated at the press conference that "establishing" startups "in Macau requires continued support." "With no collective and sustained efforts, this view runs the risk of remaining, reducing the efforts and hard work of so many," warned the Timorese.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Telephone harassment punished with six months in prison</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/assedio-telefonico-punido-seis-meses-de-prisao/</link><description>A man who called the wife's ex-husband several times at dawn after arguing with him was convicted by the TJB to a six-month prison sentence, suspended in execution for two years, and the payment of compensation. The TSI upheld the decision, also considering that the defendant's objective was to “disturb” the victim's rest
 
The Court of Second Instance (TSI) dismissed the appeal of a man convicted at first instance for crimes of violation of home. In addition to being convicted by the Base Judicial Court (TJB) for the commission of two crimes of violation of home to six months in prison suspended in execution for two years, he was also forced to pay compensation to the victim-the wife's ex-husband-worth 4,000 patacas.
The case happened in 2021, when, "because of everyday conflicts with the companion," the defendant called the woman's ex-husband at dawn to complain. The ex-husband asked the man to stop the calls, being being disturbed and even changed his phone number to avoid contacts. Still, the man was aware of the new phone number and contacted him again.
Segundo um comunicado do Gabinete da presidente do Tribunal de Última Instância, na madrugada de dois dias diferentes de 2023, o homem efectuou “três chamadas telefónicas consecutivas” para a vítima, tendo uma delas sido feita depois de o visado desligar a chamada. The action was seen by the TJB as "having" the purpose of disturbing the tranquility of the private life of the woman's ex-husband. Segundo o Tribunal, o homem “sabia bem” que era possível que, naquele período em específico, as chamadas “perturbassem o descanso” da vítima, “mas manteve uma atitude indiferente”.
Disagreeing with the decision, he appealed to the TSI, claiming that the TJB "could not prove the existence of the subjective intention of disturbing stability or tranquility." However, the TSI understands that the court of first instance "in the face of two different versions of the statements made" and taking into account other witnesses, "carefully analyzed the possibility of the two versions and made a logical analysis."
He then recalls that, that year, the man often called his wife's former partner, leading him to change number “to avoid harassment”; Later, in 2023, he again called what he demonstrated that "it had the aim of disturbing the rest and tranquility of the other party."
The victim's testimony may be read, "was proved by the existing documentary communication records and the testimony of another key witness." In addition, as he gave testimony, the convict's wife "also expressed that, whenever she argued with [her husband], she called at dawn to harass her mother and other family members, and often telephone to her ex-husband, as a means of retaliation against [she]."
In the Court's opinion, the TJB “has already explained in detail the grounds that led to its conviction, including the explanation of the reasons not to accept the content of the declaration provided [by the defendant] and to accept the version presented [by the victim]”, concluding that the conduct in question “fills the objective elements of the crime of violation of Outrem”.
Moreover, the TSI stresses that the penalty of “corresponds to the requirements of general and special prevention of the crime, and there is no excess manifest.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Residents invest more in titles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/residentes-investem-mais-em-titulos/</link><description>Macao residents' investments - including individuals, government and other legal persons, but excluding MSAR currency reserves - in securities issued by independent non -resident entities, calculated at market prices on December 31, 2024, reached 1,204.3 billion patacas, reflecting an annual increase of 14.3% and a semiannual increase of 2.7%, announced Monetary Authority (AMCM).
According to AMCM, investments in representative capital securities (including mutual funds and “trusts”), long-term obligations and short-term obligations were encrypted at the end of last year at 316.5 billion, 750.7 billion and 137.1 billion in market value, translating annual increase of 11.2%, 8.2%and 81.7%.
The Asian region continues to absorb the largest slice of the resident's external investment portfolio, with 46.4%of the total, the remainder being applied mainly in North America (19.6%), Europe (15.9%), the North Atlantic and Caribbean (14.4%) and Oceania (1.6%).
Official data also show that investment in securities issued by entities in the interior of China (including listed in scholarships abroad) continued to be predominant, representing 28.4% of the external investment portfolio applied by MSc residents. The respective market value rose 22.6% to 314.5 billion patacas, within one year. These investments included 59.5 billion in capital representative titles (18.8%of the total of the respective category), 174.3 billion in short term obligations (23.2%) and 107.7 billion in short term obligations (78.6%).
In turn, the investment portfolio quota issued by Hong Kong entities dropped from 11.0% to 9.0%, with its market value to fall 7.3% to 107.8 billion. AMCM emphasizes that investments in capital representative securities and long -term obligations have reached 38.6 billion and 54.0 billion patacas, respectively.
The investment of macao residents in securities issued by entities in the US entities ciphed at 250.6 billion patacas in market value, an annual rise of 33.6%, with the respective weight in the investment portfolio growing from 17.8%to 20.8%. On the other hand, the share of investment in European securities has retreated a percentage point to 17.6%, although its market value increased by 21.1% to 212.2 billion patacas. Among the European countries, investments in Ireland, the United Kingdom and Luxembourg represented the largest weights, with market values ​​of 72.4 billion, 38.0 billion and 36.3 billion patacas, respectively.
In the titles issued by countries located along “one track, a route” (excluding China), detained by residents of Macao, the market value (100.3 billion) dropped 3.8% and represented 8.3% of the total investment portfolio abroad. In turn, investments in Lusophone countries totaled 948.3 million, involving titles issued by entities in Portugal and Brazil.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Works by 10 local artists at Beijing Biennial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-de-10-artistas-locais-na-bienal-de-pequim/</link><description>Ten artists from Macao present 30 works at the Visual Arts Biennial in Beijing until the end of July. Visitors will be able to know paintings, photographs, digital images and facilities, among others, under the theme “Not Macau, but it's called Macau”

The Hong Kong and Macau Visual Arts Biennial is evident in the Western Gallery of the National Center for Performative Arts, in Beijing, until July 31. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), the exhibition will present “the contemporary cultural panoramic and the artistic spirit of the three regions”. Under the theme “Integration and dialogue”, the Biennial covers visual arts, intangible cultural heritage, design and technological innovation, among others.
The Macao section has as its theme “Not Macau, but it's called Macau”, with oil paintings and acrylic combinations on screens, photography, multimedia, video, dynamic digital images, installations and immersive experience spaces. The 30 pieces and contemporary art sets on display reveal "The Ties and Emotional Links of Artists with" Macao ". The 10 local artists who participate in the show include Ricardo Filipe dos Santos Meireles, Cai Guo Jie, Ieong Wan Si, IM Fong, Lam im Peng, Lo Hio Ieng, Lou Kam Ieng, Ng Sang Kei, Sit Kat and Xie Yun.
The IC expects Beijing to provide “a vast stage for artistic creation”, in which “artists from Hong Kong, Macau and the interior of China can collaborate to promote Chinese culture and increase international influence”. Ho Hong Pan, Substitute Vice President of the IC, highlighted the role of Beijing as a “national cultural hub and fundamental platform for artistic development”.
He also stressed that the show "is a crucial window for macao artists to present their works to a wider audience." For Ho, the Chinese capital will have “a glimpse of the contemporary context of the arts of Macao and the multicultural dynamism and humanistic spirit of the city”, stressing the “fruitful and longtime cooperation” between the two cities.
Kong Lun, subdirector do Gabinete de Intercâmbio e Cooperação Internacional asseverou que os artistas de Hong Kong, Macau e do Interior da China demonstraram “de forma expressiva, a vitalidade e o dinamismo da criação artística contemporânea” durante a passagem da Bienal por Hangzhou e Nanquim, para os mais de 70 mil visitantes. The inaugural ceremony in Beijing was attended by eight artists from Macau. After the Chinese capital, the exhibition will still pass through Canton and Shenzhen.
The “Hong Kong and Macao Visual Arts Biennial” has been held since 2008 and has become “an important link between artistic communities” between the two RAE and mainland China and “an emblematic event of cultural exchange”. The Biennial is co-organized by the Ministry of Culture and Tourism of the Republic of China, the Department of Cultural and Leisure Services of the Government of Raehk and the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture of MSAR.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cotai Received National Tennis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cotai-volta-receber-nacional-de-tenis/</link><description>The Cotai Tennis Academy will be the stage, for the fifth consecutive year, of the final phase of the China Professional Championship, where the national and female -and -female unique and unique titles will discuss. The test takes place in the first week of December
 
Some of the continent's best tennis players will discuss in Macau the national titles of the sport, in the singular, male and female categories, in a tournament that will take place at the Cotai Tennis Academy, between 1 and 7 December. This is the fifth time that the masters receives the competition sponsored by the Macau Games Society (SJM), divided into “SJM Final of the CTA Professional Circuit” and “National Tennis Championship”.
The final phase of the season happens after several rounds, made in several inland cities, in a tournament that started in April in Huzhou.
In the territory will be the 16 best players on the continent in the categories of singular and eight pairs in peers. The system is from a first group phase, followed by the qualifiers to the finals, where the 2025 champions will be found.
The event's press conference featured, among others, with the presence of the former Grand Slam women's peer champion and Bronze Medalist at the 2008 Beijing Olympic Games, Zheng Jie, currently vice president of the China Tennis Association.
At the time, the president of the Institute of Sport (ID), Luís Gomes, said that the championship in Macau "will further publicize the sneakers", in addition to promoting the integration "sport + tourism" and contribute to "the moderately diverse economic development of Macao".
Daisy Ho, SJM Resorts Administrator, said, for its part, that “being the national platform of professional competitions”, the CTA circuit plays a “fundamental role in the discovery and formation of potential Chinese athletes, promoting the continuous rise of national tennis in the international panorama”. The annual final in Macao in December, “will continue the popularity of national sport triggered by the national games, allowing athletes and viewers to continue participating, and will further consolidate Macao's strategic position in the sports landscape of the Great Bay,” said the SJM official.
Zhou Bing, director of the tournament, considered that Macao's interest in the organization demonstrates "once again the goal and determination to build a sports city."
On the sidelines of the tournament, a series of activities will also be held, including the invitation to celebrities who like to practice tennis. Spectators will be able to use their tickets to play for free in the event's “Games Area”, visit and check in on the “cultural and creative area” and enjoy various discounts on tourism, gastronomy and shopping in Macao.
In addition, the “Interactive Campaign of the Special Olympics” will again take place, the “Dialogue with Featured athletes” sharing sessions and the “National Tennis Tournament by the Family Cup invitation”, as will be held for the “Zheng Jie 2025 Cup”, founded in 2010 by the former player herself. The test aims to promote the popularization and development of the tennis in the level of the young layers, becoming “in a important platform for the reserve of national youthful tennis,” according to Zheng Jie.
At the time, the “national” technical team, led by itself and by Zhang Yu, will provide students with professional experience in training. “They will also be invited to participate representatives of young athletes in Macao”, in the sense of “exchanging experiences and learning with elite athletes from all over the country”, reveals the organization.
Ticket tickets will be available on Damai and Go Out Mall platforms. To celebrate the 5th anniversary of the event, there will be 50% off for “Early Bird”, residents and students from Macao.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Military Club welcomes piano and accordion concert</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/clube-militar-acolhe-concerto-de-piano-acordeao/</link><description>The Military Club will host the “French Touch” show today at Stanley Ho Hall, with performances by pianist Freeman Lok and Nazar Tabachyshyn on the accordion
 
The “music journeys” will have a “French touch” at the Military Club today. The concert program, with Nazar Tabachyshyn in the accordion and Freeman Lok on the piano, starts at 19:00.
Nazar Tabachyshyn is a “multi-talented artist,” according to the Military Club. In addition to conductor and event organizer, he is also a master of music, having taught and directed popular instrument orchestras at the National Academy of Tchaikovsky Music and at the Ternopil School of Music in Ukraine. He founded the vocal ensemble of the Ukrainian Catholic Cathedral and won the 2008 Ukrainian Musical Contest, the International Music Contest in Italy in 2010, and the International Music Contest in the Czech Republic, Lithuania and Estonia, from 2011 to 2013.
Tabachyshyn started playing accordion at five and a year later went to study music. He has resided in Hong Kong since 2014, where he co-funded the tango band “Café 852” and the duo “Jennie and Nazar”, and also participated in various China music festivals, such as “Jazz on the Lake” in Hangzhou and “May French”, among others.
Freeman Lok started playing piano at the age of five. Initially he learned to play classical music and gained several local and international piano awards. He studied music at the University of Cambridge, where he licensed “with distinction” in 2022. During this period, he developed an interest in jazz, having acted in high -level concerts, including a performance for King Charles III.
In the last year, he focused on jazz and became one of the young pianists of the gender "most active in the city". Freeman's trio was invited to play at the 2024 Hong Kong Freespace Jazz festival. Versered in many genres, since Jazz classical music and pop music, Freeman worked with artists such as Vivian Woo, Jill Vidal and Cy Leo.
Tickets for the concert, with cocktail, cost 120 patacas or 330 patacas if they include dinner.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Korean brand opens aesthetic clinic at Wynn Palace</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/marca-coreana-abre-clinica-estetica-wynn-palace/</link><description>The first medical center located inside a resort in Macao was inaugurated. The “Blanc de Vie” will bring sophisticated medical services to Wynn Palace to attract “new tourist markets”
 
Wynn Palace inaugurated the “Blanc de Vie” medical center, a South Korean brand of luxury aesthetic clinics. According to Wynn, this is the "first and only medical center located inside a resort in Macao." With the introduction of sophisticated medical aesthetic services and chronic disease management methods at MSAR, the operator aims to attract new tourist markets, aligned with the government's diversification strategy.
For the game operator, this project will facilitate the growth of the local 'Big Health' industry and the position of the city as a health tourism destination, in line with the intersectoral integration of “Tourism+”. At the inauguration ceremony were present Linda Chen, president of Wynn Macau, and Jun Choi, CEO of the “Blanc de Vie”, among others.
Headquartered in Seoul, the “Blanc de Vie” is recognized for being a leading dermatological institution in the country's aesthetic care sector and has participated and contributed to national and international conferences over the years through investigations, exchanges and presentations. Through the “high quality” services, it was able to win numerous customers, the statement says.
Wynn “is dedicated to promoting the growth of the 'Big Health' industry in Macao” and says it has continually improved exercise services at its facilities, and even inaugurated the first center of health and integrated well-being in a spa in the MSAR.
This type of initiatives not only injected “vitality” in the city's health industry, but also provided “a greater variety of health care options for residents and tourists”. In the future, “Wynn will continue to leverage its international resources” to boost the development of the sector, contributing to the diversification of the local economy.</description><pubDate>2025-06-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The popularity of the plates in a glass remains strong in South Korea</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/popularidade-dos-pratos-em-copo-continua-forte-na-coreia-sul/</link><description>With the change of stations, a new trend of “Bingsu in a glass” is gaining popularity among Koreans who prepare to survive the summer notoriously humid and hot.
Offered mainly in low -cost coffees, such as Mega MGC Coffee, Compose Coffee and Ediya Coffee, the innovative dish brings all common features of the snack in a plastic cup normally used for drinks: frozen milk or cream, sweetened red beans, small rice dumplings, syrup to choose from, and of course, the piece of shagged ice that makes it one of the summer snacks more summer popular here.
Bissu in cups is just the latest of a long line of snacks and popular meals packed in a glass.
What can sound like a dystopian Wall-E Dystopian nightmare is actually a very pleasant and accessible form of food in South Korea, expanding its traditional instant pasta for the Bap (rice), Cup Tteokbokki (spicy rice dumplings) and, apparently, practically anything, in the palm.
Bissu is rarely considered a dessert for a person due to its price and size. Sulbing, one of the most popular Bingsu restaurants, offers its most basic, Injeolmi Bingsu (bean -covered rice bingu) by 9,900 wons (almost 60 patacas). Served in a large cup, it is an ideal snack to share with a friend.
The price of the instant Bingsu is usually located in the range of 4,000 wons (about 25 patacas), rarely exceeding 6,300 wons (38 patacas). This makes it an ideal snack to taste alone.
In South Korea, the accessibility of an individual dish has been the main attractive of the plates in the glass since the ancestor of the meals in modern glass, the Cup Ramen, was introduced in Japan. Momofuku Ando, ​​Taiwanese-Japanese that made and lost his fortune in World War II, invented the famous instant Ramen and packed him in a cup-known as Cup Noodles - To attract the international market.
In 1972, the Korean company of Samyang Foods food and beverage launched the first local version of South Korea Cup Noodles, which quickly gained popularity over the next few decades, especially with the introduction of convenience stores franchises in the mid -1990s.
Another popular glass plate is the Cup Bab, a roofed rice version that emerged as street food in Noryangjin-Dong in Dongjak district in Seoul. In the 2000s, Noryanjin had its peak as a center for aspiring civil servants, with numerous private gyms to offer courses for the public tender.
The students of the preparation courses sought cheap and fast dishes, which was attended by the street vendors who sold Cup Bab. Since rice is the main source of carbohydrates for Koreans, the BAB Cup was sold by about 2000 wons (12 patacas) and was a welcome change from the traditionally consuming cheap sandwiches and hamburgers.
Today's Noryangjin Cup Bab sellers are neither far nor close, as prominent as before, but the once popular dish found its place in convenience stores. The BAB Cup is now sold in cup packaged containers, which can be stored longer and instantly heated for consumption.
At the same time as adult students ate Cup Bab, their youngest colleagues filled their belly with Tteokbokki Cup. Restaurants and street vendors started selling the popular snack in small portions to children with little money, but since then found their place in the official menus.
Perhaps the more unusual cup food is nothing less than sushi, such as the “cold soup of sashimi with meat tartar” offered by local franchising. The plate of small portions is a limited time offer, only for summer, although the price is questionable for a meal of 13,900 wons (82 patacas).
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-06-26 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>