<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>All EPM finalists placed in higher education</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/todos-os-finalistas-da-epm-colocados-ensino-superior/</link><description>Students who completed the 12th grade at the Portuguese School of Macao and presented candidacies for higher education in various universities, especially in Portugal, saw the process approved in full. The EPM director told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the rate of 100% "means the school is on the good way." Acácio de Brito congratulates the 22 students, but also teachers and parents for success. For the new school year, which started a week ago, the EPM records double enrollment in the 12th grade, being a total of 48, which will lead to a "growing" of candidates for higher education of 2026/2027
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Portuguese School (EPM) successfully registered all students who applied for higher education and will continue their studies at universities in Macau, Portugal or other countries and regions. There were 22 students who guaranteed access, 18 will attend educational establishments in Portugal.
First congratulating students for the work done, the director of EPM also welcomes teachers and parents for the success achieved. "This is something that makes all those who daily toil for the best education for our young people," Acácio de Brito told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, noting that "last year, this did not happen."
After the second phase of the competition for public higher education candidates in Portugal, “100% of our students were placed”, which means, according to the official, that “the school is on the good way”, adding that “if we have improved the physical conditions of the school, it is also for continuous improvement”.
Acácio de Brito considers that the curriculum also helps that this success be realized. "Our curriculum is very robust and allows adequate preparation for students," he says, emphasizing that "through an external assessment process, which are the exams themselves and the question of the candidacy, this has to actually continue to work to continue to have this success, so they are all congratulations."
In the first phase, he stresses, "a student had, for reasons of her choice, was placed, and at this time she entered the Faculty of Fine Arts, in Porto, as well as a student who had competed, but requested the transfer, went into Aerospace Engineering at Instituto Superior Técnico in Lisbon."
The EPM tells of the 2025/2026 academic year, which started on September 9, with 48 enrollment in the 12th grade, or twice last year. Meanwhile, also in secondary education, there are 50 students in 11th and 51 in the 10th.
"The trend is to increase in the coming schools," attests the EPM director, anticipating a "growing" of students who will reach the last level in the coming years, then heading to universities. “Probably this was a fruit a lot of pandemic reflexes, since at the time there was many students to Portugal and other places,” he says.
On the other hand, the same responsible informed that the issue of English discipline, given the non -approval of the teacher's quota by the education and development services of youth, is already being resolved through readjustment for this first period of classes. We are redistributing the disciplines, because we have to solve this type of situations immediately, hence that, at this moment, it is resolved, ”he expresses, stressing that“ then we will see ”.
Regarding the non -use of mobile phones in the school space of the school, he said that "there are already cliffs, placed by us, for this purpose." "Students are adapting well, at least I don't have disagreement feedback, taking place at this time, with about a week of classes, a process of evaluation, monitoring and readaptation, which we hope to run in the best way," he said, noting that "many students no longer bring even the phone."
For the 2025/2026 school year, the EPM has 810 students enrolled, 37 more than last year, which means an increase of 5%. With regard to classes, there is no change, remaining 39 in total, distributed by 15 in the first cycle, nine in the second, 10 in the third and six in the secondary.
At the level of facilities, the beginning of the school year in the educational establishment is marked by some improvements, one of which at the level of the restoration space and bar, just at the entrance of the building, on the opposite side of the secretary, whose objective is to offer better conditions to students and teachers.
In addition, the recreation area has been increased and there is to register the renewal of the resorts with the Sports Pavilion, with more showers for both sexes, now in a total of 15 in each sector. The music room was also remodeled, as well as the teacher room diverted elsewhere.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Feeling Macau” returns to Lisbon tomorrow</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sentir-macau-regressa-amanha-lisboa/</link><description>Tomorrow begins the campaign “Feel Macau Roadshow in Lisbon”, organized by the Tourism Services Directorate. By the end of the week, the Commerce Square will be the scene of Ruem Street Promotion, in an attempt to capture more European tourists. The event schedule includes shows and exhibitions, as well as promotional offers
 
The tourist promotion campaign “Feeling Macau Roadshow in Lisbon” starts tomorrow, in an effort of the Tourism Services (STD) direction to promote mashes in Europe as a “ideal tourist destination”. The initiative extends until Sunday, in the Portuguese capital's Square, with “technological elements” and “three thematic areas of exhibition”. The promotion will be integrated in the “Rua” of the Lisbon City Council, “in order to develop synergies and widen advertising,” according to a press release.
The areas of the event will be made up of a main stage and a show zone, a multimedia exhibition and the “window to the great event of the guide” exhibitions, where “the rich tourist, cultural, sports, economic, commercial and entertainment of Macao will be displayed. In addition, there will also be a stand in the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, in order to promote the region's cultural and tourist resources.
Tomorrow, the inaugural ceremony will feature a night fire and drones at night show, DST said. In addition, all other nights will have “light drones” with projections that will represent “the coexistence of various cultures and the urban vitality of Macao”, in a “immersive audiovisual show”.
In partnership with the “Abreu” travel agency, STD also launched a set of tourist promotions with macao packages and multiple destinations, including the interior of China, Japan, South Korea and Hong Kong. Offers will be available through various sales channels, including social networks, until February 2026.
The tourist services of MSA will also take the opportunity to visit Portuguese tourist projects and meet the Portuguese Association of Travel and Tourism Agencies and the Lisbon Equipment and Cultural Animation Management Company. STD aims to “further develop the role of Macao as a bridge in the interior of China and Portugal, and reinforce exchange and cooperation with Portuguese -speaking countries”.
This initiative marks the return of STD promotional activities in the Portuguese city, “after the success of the first promotion in Europe after the pandemic in 2023”. Between tomorrow and Sunday, the body hopes to “show the European market the diversified charm of‘ Tourism +’”, attract more visitors from Europe and expand the markets of international visitors.
STD invites all those in Lisbon to participate in this event. Interested parties can consult more information about street promotion and their activities on the body and social networks of the body.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Elections showed “atmosphere” of “high quality democracy”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/eleicoes-mostraram-atmosfera-de-democracia-de-alta-qualidade/</link><description>The Office for the State Council RAE matters considers that the elections for AL have shown "the healthy, positive and vibrant atmosphere of a high quality democracy." The central government's connection office on the MSAR argued that “the 26 elected deputies are convinced patriots, committed to serving society and capable of taking responsibility”.
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL) have demonstrated “fully the healthy, positive and vibrant atmosphere of a high quality democracy,” says the Hong Kong and Macao's affairs of the Council of State. For the organism spokesman, the electoral act “marks another milestone in the full implementation of the Macao principle governed by patriots' by masters and promoting a high quality democracy in line with the real conditions of Macao,” can be read in a note.
The urgent rate of the ballot box in Sunday's elections was 53.35%, a notorious rise of nearly 11 percentage points, compared to 2021, when the highest abstention rate was recorded in the territory. However, and despite the appeals to the authorities' vote, the participation rate was the third worst since the creation of the MSAR. In total, 175,272 people -a record -of a universe of 328,506 voters voted.
The blank votes and null votes, in turn, also reached a new maximum, having totaled more than 13 thousand.
Like 2021, this year there were also disqualified candidates from the race to the elections, allegedly "not defending the basic law or not being faithful to MSAR," including former deputy Ron Lam.
In the cabinet note for MSAR affairs, it is said that the review of the electoral law came to “improve and refine the qualification standards and the mechanisms of selection of candidates”, reinforcing the implementation of the “Macao Governed by Patriots” principle. In addition, he considers that a "just, impartial, open and honest election was guaranteed."
"With solid institutional safeguards, the democratic rights of the electorate in general were fully exercised and the electoral participation was supported and encouraged," adds the spokesman.
It is also said that "civil servants took the lead in the fulfillment of their civic duties and voted universally." A week before the elections, the Chief Executive sent a letter to the civil service workers to say that going to vote was a demonstration of "fidelity to the masters." According to Lusa, the employees were also questioned by the bosses about whether they intended to vote and were required justification when they said no.
"The broad public participation, the high enthusiasm of voters and the unprecedented electoral participation strongly demonstrate the healthy development of democratic participation in the political landscape of Macao," he added, saying that the "success" of elections resulted from the joint efforts of all sectors of society. It also states that "the comprehensive qualities of newly elected deputies were widely recognized by society."
The cabinet also believes that "the population is pleased to see that many exceptional people, especially young talents, with strong positions, solid skills and a good image, emerged from this election." The “general quality” of deputies “is at their highest level ever”, he says.
In the same vein, the central government's connection office in the MSAR expressed contentment for the “success” of the elections. Remembering that it was the first electoral act under the new law, the spokesman stressed that this was "an important event in Macao's political life."
He also made a reference to the participation of civil servants in the elections, who “assumed the leadership in the exercise of their democratic rights and in the fulfillment of their civic obligations, encouraging all sectors of Macao society and the general public to pay attention to elections and to vote actively”.
For the connection office, "the 26 elected deputies are convinced patriots, committed to serving society and capable of taking responsibility", considering that "the general structure of deputies was optimized, materializing a transition between the old and the new."
Both offices also made praise for the Chief Executive and the Government of MSAR for fulfilling their "responsibilities" and organized the elections "in an orderly and legal way".</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Illegal exchange crimes with “more hidden” methods</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/crimes-de-cambio-ilegal-metodos-mais-ocultos/</link><description>An Employee Counts Hong Kong One-Thousand Dollar Banknotes at the Hang Seng Bank Ltd. Headquarters in Hong Kong, China, On Tuesday, April 16, 2019. The Hong Kong Dollar's One-Montic Volatility Climbed to the Highest Sincere Early Februarie as Traders Were Whiplashed by the Currency's Price Swings Aimid Declining Liquidity. With the Central Fact City Bank Having SPent $ 2.8 Billion in March to Defend the Peg to the U.S. Dollar, Hong Kong's Aggregate Balance has dropped and interbank rates have soared. Photography: Paul Yeung/Bloomberg



Despite considering that the space of action for the crime of illegal money exchange "has been lower in recent months", the secretary for security warns that combating these activities should be "as a long term challenge". According to Wong Sio Chak, “some of the individuals who are dedicated to this activity have adopted more hidden methods to commit the crime,” which makes the work of the authorities difficult. Since October last year, the PJ has detained almost 600 people involved in illegal exchange
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Secretary for Security argues that the Judiciary Police (PJ) "has achieved considerable results, reducing the margin of 'illegal money exchange' crimes, however, it warns that it is predictable that the fight against illegal exchange activities" remains as a long term challenge, with no space for incuria. "
This is because, explains Wong Sio Chak, in the monthly message that is published on his office's online page, "some of the individuals who dedicate themselves to this activity have adopted more hidden methods to commit crime, such as carrying out vehicle transactions or the number of cash transport in them, in an attempt to escape investigation." At the same time, he points out, the existence of these activities is due to the search for cash by tourists, "some of which ignore the illicit nature of this exchange and the associated criminal risks, therefore continuing to perform this type of transactions."
Despite considering that the space of action for this type of crimes “has been lower in recent months”, the secretary says that it is necessary to not neglect the crime. And he recalls that, in recent years, with the continuous increase in the number of tourists, the number of individuals who have the “illegal money exchange” in the casinos and their nearby has also increased, “which not only disturbs public order, but also contributes to the practice of serious crimes”.
In this sense, it ensures that the PJ will continue to review the application of the legislation, improve police work and adjust strategic implementation. “Through solid, uninterrupted and accurate actions, it will continue to combat the illicit exchange rate and transionic crimes, with a view to reducing the risks of public safety derived from 'illegal money exchange', safeguarding society's tranquility and public security, thus creating a safer and more ordered environment for Macao's socioeconomic development,” can read in the message.
Prior to the entry into force of the illicit play crimes in October 2024, which criminalized “illicit exchange exchange exploration”, the “illegal exchange of money” was only an administrative offense. For this reason, "it was difficult to grasp the capital involved, due to insufficient punitive measures, which limited the deterrent effect."
Since the law came into force and by the end of July, PJ detained 597 individuals involved in 387 cases of “illegal money exchange”, having seized more than $ 56 million from Hong Kong (HKD) and more than 15 million HKD in game sheets, Wong Sio Chak said.
The secretary also recalls that PJ maintains information exchanges with the execution services of the abroad law, "having created specialized teams to investigate the criminal groups that are behind these activities." Through the adoption of “comprehensive measures, the illicit exchange is completely eradicated,” he added.
Last year, as part of joint operations with China's interior police, several clandestine banks and transfronist criminal groups involved in “illegal money exchange” were dismantled. Already with the operation “Ant removal”, 13 individuals involved in “illegal exchange of money” were sent to the judicial agencies.
This year, the PJ returned to cooperate with the interior police of China, and two joint operations were carried out that culminated in the dismantling of three criminal groups associated with this type of crime. “The law of execution of the law has proved effective,” noted Wong Sio Chak.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese “monopolized” titles on table tennis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chineses-monopolizaram-titulos-tenis-de-mesa/</link><description>Wang Chuqin and Sun Yingsha won the WTT champions tournament on table tennis, held at Macau Dome. Unsurprisingly, the players on the continent, classified among the first places in the world ranking, surpassed Brazilian Hugo Calderano and Wang Manyu, respectively in male and female singles

Victor Rebelo
 
The final journey of the WTT champions tournament, in table tennis, attributed the titles to the Chinese Wang Chuqin, in singular men's, and Sun Yingsha in female. The latter confirmed its top status of the world ranking of the current, while Chuqin emerged in Macao in the second place on the international list, behind compatriot Lin Shidong, who was surprised in the quarterfinals by Danish Anders Lind, 19th in the ranking.
In the challenges that determined the winners of another edition of the MSAR WTT, the 25-year-old left Wang Chuqin had an easier task than expected, given the opponent, Brazilian Hugo Calderano, four years older, ranking room, had surprised in the Anders Lind semi-finals and everything pointed out so that he could discuss the title to the end.
The partials of the 4-0 (9/11, 11/7, 9/11, and 11/4) result mirror the superiority manifested by the Popular Republic table of China (RPC), in a match where the South American has been holes below previous installments and drumming at crucial times.
Chuqin, much supported by the local public, with good assistance in the Sports ship of the Macao East Asia Games (Dome), still felt some resistance from the opponent, but the consistency of his game at the end of the end of the triumph.
In the remaining "sets", Chuqin did not allow the Calderano so much balance, although in the third the Brazilian approached the result, only failing in the last moments of the challenge. In total, the "duel" lasted just over 36 minutes.
Chuqin, who had surpassed the South Korean Jang Woojin, 30th, 28th in the world ranking, became Macao's WTT champion after being first classified in 2023.
In the discussion of women's title, another RPC representative in focus, this time Sun Yingsha, best in the world of today. The 24 -year -old athlete, had to push two compatriots away from the final part of the tournament to reach the first position. In the semi-finals eliminated Kuan Man, fourth in the ranking, and in the final, Wang Manyu, 26, second on the world list.
Unlike men's game, the confrontation of female singles was more exciting and extremely balanced, as there was alternation in "six sets", forcing the black woman in the seventh. Sun Yingsha managed to win 4-3, with the partials of 11/8, 13/15, 9/11, 9/11, 5/11, 9/11 and 9/11, bringing the viewers present in the pavilion in a game that lasted an hour and 16 minutes.
The first "head-of-head" was losing 3-2, but operated a turnaround in the last two "sets" to reach the title of champion, thus revalidating the trophy won in 2024.
In this category of female singles, the mashes presented its best performer, Zhu Yuling, seventh of the world, who resisted to the quarter-finals, when it was eliminated by Wang Manyu 4-0.
The tournament was co-organized by the Sports Institute, the “World Table Tennis” and the Galaxy, having distributed monetary awards total of $ 800,000, about 6.42 million patacas. Each winner, in men and female, amelled a $ 35,000 check, close to 280,000 patacas.
After the games of the finals, followed the awards ceremony to the first classifieds, in which the secretary's representative for social affairs and culture of Macao, Alex Vong Iao Lek, WTT executive director Steve Dainton, WTT Event Director Mounir Bessah, and Galaxy Entertainment Corporate Affairs Director, were attended. Buddy Lam.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau Brands praised in Wuhan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/marcas-de-macau-elogiadas-em-wuhan/</link><description>Wuhan's audience showed great interest in the brands of MSAR and Lusophone products, which were presented throughout the “Macao Week” in the interior city of China. For exhibitors of MSAR, sales “exceeded expectations,” according to the Institute for the Promotion of Trade and Investment
 
The exhibitors of the masters who participated in the four days of the “Macao Week in Wuhan, Hubei” said that “their products were very well received by the local public”, read on a press release. This year's edition was held for the first time in the Central China region, with a roadshow format, which brought together 28 MSAR companies, including 14 brands “Halal” certification, 17 with “M-Mark” Macao Quality Certification and 550 selected products.
According to the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), some visitors mentioned that the event knew how to capture “the characteristics of Macau”, through demonstrations that promoted both companies and technological modernization of MSAR. The great interest in Macao products and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP) resulted in sales that “exceeded expectations,” says the note, with multiple locals praised “the richness of the contents of the exhibition area”.
The “MinM Exhibition Area - Macao brands and made in Macau” and the PLP product display area combined consumer rewards and live broadcasts, among other “fun elements”, with an “integrated online and offline approach”. At the time, the gastronomic, shopping and entertainment experiences of Macao were presented.
Even a company that made its debut in “Macao Week” believes that “the constant flow of visitors significantly increased the company's visibility within China”, with customers to react “positively” to their food products. In addition, throughout the contact scholarship sessions, the company has achieved a cooperation intention with a local Wuhan supermarket.
According to Ipim, the event “not only promoted a profound exchange between companies” but also highlighted “The Macao Charm”, in a boost to economic and cultural ties between the two cities.
The “Contact Stock Exchange between Hubei and Macau” was attended by different representatives of companies from the trade, retail and restoration sectors. In particular, a wine -selling company in Wuhan hopes that this type events can result in a narrower relationship with the MSAR, hoping to be able to use “the Macao platform to expand even more in the international market”.
Between the “Contact Stock Exchange between Hubei and Macau” and the ““ Mice2 Macao x Hengqin ”brand promotion session, more than 350 representatives of government, business and conventions and exhibitions from participating regions were gathered. The initiative also contributed“ to the deepening of a new collaborative development paradigm of the Macao and Hengqin industries ”, Ipim said.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Curb organizes “pedaling” by Ilha Verde</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/curb-organiza-pedaladas-pela-ilha-verde/</link><description>On the 27th of this month, Curb - Center for Architecture and Urbanism will organize a new edition of the “On The Move” bike rides, on a visit to the neighborhoods of Ilha Verde. The two programmed routes will start from the University of São José
 
Curb - Center for Architecture and Urbanism will organize the seventh edition of the “On The Move” initiative, a project that combines bike rides and the display of a documentary. According to a press release, on September 27, the excursions will explore different neighborhoods of Ilha Verde, with the courtyard of the University of São José as a starting point.
The trips will be commented in English by the architect and president of Curb, Nuno Soares, who usually makes observations about architecture, the history of the neighborhoods, as well as to tell some curiosities.
Participants can choose between two itineraries: the Fai Chi Kei route and the toi San route. The first will have a session between 10h00 and 11h00 and another from 16h00 to 17h00, while the second will happen from 11:30 to 12:30 and again between 14:30 and 15:30.
Each session will be limited to 10 people, and participants will have to be of age and have the “necessary bicycle driving skills”. The organization will provide equipment such as helmets, reflective vests and audio receivers.
The images and audio captured throughout the tours will be used to create a documentary film, whose place and date of display will be announced later, said Curb.
As a non -profit institution, Curb aims to “promote research, teaching, production and diffusion of knowledge in urban architecture, urbanism and culture”. Active at regional and international level, especially in Asia and Lusophone countries, brings “local issues to a global audience”, read in the note.
Being a “exchange platform between academia, civil society, professional practice and government institutions”, Curb seeks to serve “the interests of the community in general through research studies, workshops, conferences, exhibitions, competitions and other initiatives”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost 700 non-residents with repatriation processes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quase-700-nao-residentes-processos-de-repatriamento/</link><description>The police authorities of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau performed a joint operation called “Thunder 2025”. Surveillance actions were intended to repress transionic organized crime and achieved “significant” results, thus ensuring “the social stability of the three regions”. Highlight for the detection of a hundred smuggler and the repatriation process of almost 700 non-residents
 
Maintaining public order and tranquility, preventing and combating organized transfronic crime was the objective of a joint operation of the police authorities of Guangdong, Hong Kong and Macau, called “Thunderstorm 2025”.
According to a Unit Police Services (SPU) statement, the operation lasted just over a month, between August 4 and September 6, and allowed to suppress the transfronic organized crime, having achieved “significant results”, thus ensuring the “social stability of the three regions”.
In Macao, the coordination belonged to the SPU and was carried out jointly by the Customs Services (SA), Public Security Police (CPSP) and Judicial Police (PJ).
The operation focused on inspection and identification on public roads, coastal areas and maritime area under the jurisdiction of the sinhers, borders and cargo ports, as well as in various fun facilities, specifically in night clubs, casinos and adjacent zones.
625 inspection actions were made at 1,533 locations. The SA mobilized patrol vessels 34 times, while SA, CPSP and PJ made available in a total of 8,756 agents.
In the balance sheet, 48,155 individuals were subject to identification and 1,393 taken to the police for investigation. Among the investigated, 551 would be referred to the judicial bodies for accusation for involvement in a total of 443 cases. Highlight for the fight against smuggling, developed by the SA, where 314 people are accused of administrative offenses for violation of the “Foreign Trade Law” and “sanitary and phytosanitary control”, among which 101 are non-resident workers.
During the operation, the authorities also discovered eight acts of criminal association, and 13 individuals and 85 records related to 100 detainees were intercepted and 62 cases of exploration of illicit exchange exchange rate with 100 arrests.
Finally, 669 non-residents were referred to the authorities for the due process of repatriation, namely for committing crimes, illegal immigration, excess permanence, illicit exchange, prostitution, employment-related offense, illegal work or activities that did not fit the quality of tourist.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Renewed by 2027 CTM and MTEL operation licenses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/renovadas-ate-2027-licencas-de-operacao-da-ctm-mtel/</link><description>The Macao Telecommunications Company (CTM) and the limited Mtel Telecommunications Company have become renewed licenses to install and operate a public telecommunications network and provide licensed services. The concession is extended for another two years, in the period between October 1, 2025 and September 30, 2027, and is inserted, according to the order of the Chief Executive, published in Official Bulletin (BO), under the installation and operation of public networks of fixed telecommunications. Recently, it is recalled, Derby Lau, director of the Director of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT), had said that all preparatory work for license renewal were already completed. At the time, Derby Lau explained that the renewal would be "a little different", with the deadline but "too long". Given other planning, new contracts are not just a simple renewal, Derby Lau stressed, adding that the procedure is expected to bring “clearer” provisions to future operators or for reforming the telecommunications sector. However, the Chief Executive delegated to the Secretary for Transport and Public Works, Raymond Tam, all the necessary powers to sign, in representation of the MSAR, as a grantor, the additional contract to the interim review of the public telecommunications service concession contract, to be celebrated with the CTM.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing Credit fell 17% in a year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-a-habitacao-caiu-17-num-ano/</link><description>The amount of the new mortgage loans for housing approved by Macao banks reached 1.05 billion in July, reflecting an annual break of 16.7% and a monthly decrease of 0.3%, reveals data from the Monetary Authority (AMCM). In July, the credit contracted by residents represented 98.6% of the total. Between May and July this year, the monthly average of new housing loans were 1.02 billion, 5.9% more than in the previous period (from April to June). According to AMCM, at the end of July, the debt ratio unpaid on housing credit, which encompasses delays of more than three months in interest and or capital payments of loans, was 3.7%, corresponding to a monthly increase of 0.1 percentage point and a decrease of 0.5 for the homologous period of 2024. Housing totaled 211.21 billion patacas, translating down 0.6% and 5.5%, in monthly and annual terms, respectively. On the other hand, the new commercial loans for real estate activities ciphed at 284.24 million patacas, marking down 84.9% and 85.2% in one month and one year, respectively, and 96.4% of the total amount was granted to residents. According to AMCM, the monthly average of new real estate business loans fell 31% to 912.45 million, in relation to the period between April and June 2025. In the credit segment for real estate activities, the unpaid debt ratio (5.4%) has not changed 1.5 points in a year. The gross balance of commercial loans for real estate activities (145.48 billion) maintained the same level as June and dropped 5.3% in the annual variation.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT promoted cybersecurity workshop</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctt-promoveu-workshop-sobre-ciberseguranca/</link><description>The auditorium of the headquarters of the Macao Technology Productivity and Technology Transfer Center recently welcomed the “Cybersecurity Vulnerabilities Workshop”, organized by the Directorate of Post and Telecommunications Services (CTT). According to a statement, with “a large number of registrations and active participation”, the graduates were able to know the “basic concepts, recommended processes and practices for cybersecurity vulnerabilities”, beyond problem identification techniques, evaluation criteria and repair methods. The CTT expect the initiative "can reinforce the capacity of trainees in identifying vulnerabilities in computer and computer equipment." Reinforcing the cybersecurity of local organizations will reduce “the occurrence of cyber attacks”, argues the body. In this sense, it will continue to perform “relevant” formations, in order to improve the “technological level of cybersecurity of private operators of critical infrastructure and small and medium -sized workers”. The stable development of the sector will be the formation of more paintings in the area of ​​cybersecurity, the CTT reiterated.</description><pubDate>2025-09-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Hope and Fujian list ensure three seats each</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-esperanca-lista-de-fujian-asseguram-tres-assentos-cada/</link><description>There was “surprise” and a “historic frame” for Jose Pereira Coutinho's New Hope, who was the big winner of the night, when he got the largest number of votes -a large distance from the rest -and elect three deputies. Secondly, the list led by Song Pek Kei, linked to the Fujian community, also secured three seats in Hemiciclo. Faom, "Kaifong", the list linked to the community of Jiangmen and the "women" got only two seats each
 
Catarina Pereira
 
List 2, “Nova Esperança”, led by José Pereira Coutinho, and list 1, “Association of United Citizens”, whose head-to-head is Song Pek Kei, were the great winners of the electoral night by ensuring three seats in the hemicicle. The New Hope got 43,361 votes (26.73%), having elected Pereira Coutinho, Chan Hao Weng and Che Sa Wang. It was the most voted list, a large distance from the second.
To journalists, the president of the civil service workers' association said that “this was undoubtedly the biggest victory of the new hope”, stressing that over the years the list has always been adding votes and never losing them. "I think a lot of people were surprised by this result, because we did it too," he continued. "It's a historic landmark."
Pereira Coutinho stressed that the result “is not individual”, but “set”, the result of the effort and work of many people. "We are very pleased. We know that in the future we have a huge responsibility to follow up on the constant promises in our electoral program, but we have confidence and willpower," he added.
Despite admitting that he did not expect to elect a third deputy, Pereira Coutinho said that Che Sai Wang was placed in third position "as a driving force, because he also has a very strong substrate in the community, although he is a bit modest." "But the result is in sight, made a great contribution, the strategy worked," he said.
The deputy argued that the result is of special importance "at this time we live in the MSAR": "As a resident citizen in Macau, with a Portuguese name, having this result is extremely satisfactory." He then promised to “continue fighting for the rights of the Macaense and Portuguese community and all other communities in Macau”.
In the last elections, it is recalled, the New Hope list had been the third most voted.
It should be noted that of the more than 175,000 voters, only more than 162,000 were considered validly expressed votes, with more than 13,000 to be blank and null votes [see text on page 3].
Already the group linked to the community of Fujian reelected deputies Song Pek Kei and Nick Lei, having still got a place for a third candidate: rookie Chan Lai Kei. It achieved 29,459 votes, the equivalent of 18.16%. The list repeated the feat four years ago, when it also made hat-trick.
Song Pek Kei noted that in this edition the list obtained more votes, which "proves that the works done by the team were recognized by the citizens." Being “satisfied” with the result, he asserted that he will fulfill the promises, especially to promote economic development and industrial diversification. Already Nick Lei stressed that he will try to realize the increase in the pension for the elderly and the implementation of guarantees for the use of residents.
The “Union for Development” was followed, list 5, with a total of 27,431 votes (16.91%). Thus, he managed to reelect Ella Law and Leong Sun Iok, like what happened four years ago. In the reaction, deputies linked to the Macao Workers' Associations Federation thanked voters for their support, stating that in the next four years they will continue to promote, with priority, solutions to employment problems and linked to the welfare of the population.
In the same line, list 3, “Promoting Union for Progress”, linked to the union of Macao residents' associations (“Kaifong”), managed to elect two deputies, receiving 21,745 votes (13.41%). They remain in the hemicycle Leong Hong Sai and Ngan Iek Hang. Facing the result as “satisfactory”, Leong Hong said stressed that the proportion of an increase in the number of votes obtained by the list corresponded to expectations.
In turn, the “Union of Macau-Guangdong”, list 4, obtained a total of 21,461 votes, equivalent to 13.23% of the total. Thus, it is a return to the Legislative Assembly for Joey Lao, now as a deputy elected by direct and not appointed suffrage, while Lee Koi Ian will take office for the first time. In the reaction, Joey Lao, whose list has links to the Jiangmen community, has promised to do a good job over the next four years, presenting suggestions for issues such as economy, population welfare, young people.
In the last position was the “Good Home Alliance”, list 6, but still managed to secure two seats in the hemiciclo. With 18,751 votes (11.56%), the list linked to the General Association of Women was able to elect Wong Kit Cheng and Loi I Weng. After scrutiny, Wong Kit Cheng described that reelection reflects “public recognition” regarding his work. It also asserted that it will comment by citizens in the hemiciclo and ensure the rights and interests of more families and women.
Among those elected by direct suffrage, there are four premieres at Al: Chan Hao Weng, Lee Koi Ian, Loi I Weng and Chan Lai Kei.
On the other hand, in the indirect suffrage were already automatically assigned 10 of the 12 seats: four at the Electoral College of Industrial, Commercial and Financial Sectors (José Chui Sa Peng and IP Sio Kai, Si Ka Lon and Kevin Ho, which debuts); Three from the professional sector (Iau Teng Pio, Vong Hou Piu and Wong Chon Kit, the last two also rookiers); one of the sectors of social and educational services (Ho Ion Sang); and two of the cultural and sports sectors (Angela Leong and MA Chi Seng).
The two seats of the work sector was missing, as they applied two lists. Each one eventually ensured a place, and Lam Lon Wai remains (obtained 484 votes) and Leong Pou U will debut as deputy (got 578 votes). The Chief Executive will also appoint seven deputies within 15 days after receiving the general investigation.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Influx rose, but it was the third smallest</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/afluencia-subiu-mas-foi-terceira-menor-de-sempre/</link><description>The poll to the polls in the elections for the Legislative Assembly was 53.35%, a notorious rise of almost 11 percentage points, compared to 2021, when the highest abstention rate was recorded in the territory. However, and despite the appeals to the authorities' vote, the participation rate was the third worst since the creation of the MSAR. In total, 175,272 people -a record -of a universe of 328,506 voters voted. The blank votes and null votes, in turn, also reached a new maximum, having totaled more than 13 thousand

Catarina Pereira
 
Yesterday's legislative participation rate was 53.35% in direct suffrage, an increase of nearly 11 percentage points for 2021, when the highest abstention rate was registered in the territory after the disqualification of more than two dozen candidates by the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal). However -and despite the persistent appeals of the authorities -, this year's polls of the polls turned out to be the third worst since the creation of the MSAR.
They voted, 175,272 people, from a universe of 328,506 voters. At this point, a new maximum has been reached, as there had never been so many voters before, since the number of voters was higher.
The blank and null votes also hit a record. According to Caeal statistics, 5,987 blank votes were accounted for and 7,077 null votes, translating 90% and 242% increase compared to 2021, respectively. These were, moreover, the highest accounts since the creation of the MSAR.
It is recalled that this year also disqualified 12 candidates from two lists, allegedly “not being faithful to masters or not defending the basic law”, including former deputy Ron Lam.
After the disclosure of the results, when asked what is the reason for the exponential increase of blank votes and null votes, CAEAL President Seng Ioi Man refused to comment. "In all data related to elections there are numbers to go up or down, there are many reasons, so Caeal will not comment," he said.
In the indirect suffrage, they voted 6,645 of the more than 7,500 voters, a participation rate of 88.12%, slightly higher than four years ago.
Hours earlier, Seng Ioi Man had thanked those who went to vote. "It was in fact a little hot day, we thank the population for going to the voting assemblies; not only to the voters, but to all the workers who helped," he said.
Asked if he was satisfied with the participation rate and which he considered the main factor who led people to vote to greater strength, Seng Ioi Man declined, saying that it was necessary to do "some studies, some analyzes."
Four years ago, after the first wave of disqualification for the elections, the MSAR registered the highest abstention rate of 57.6%, and more than 5,200 people voted blank or null.
This time, the authorities endeavored that abstention (46.65%) did not reach such low levels. Last week, it is recalled, the Chief Executive sent letters to civil servants, saying that the vote was a way of demonstrating "fidelity to the masters."
In addition, Sam Hou Fai met with the directors of services and holders of high positions, appealing again to the vote. On this occasion, he argued that "leaders in the management level should assume a role of connection between superiors and subordinates", and should promote "compliance with liability".
Civil servants, who asked not to be identified for fearing reprisals, confirmed to Lusa that earlier last week they were asked if they intended to vote. After apparently informal conversations, written justifications were required to admit that he did not plan to vote.
The workers - some of whom with decades of service in entities and public services - confirmed that this was the first time they were questioned about whether or not to participate in elections.
Yesterday, Seng Ioi Man said that "no one can oblige another to reveal the intention to vote, that is, which list they want to vote," but as to the issue of civil servants said nothing.
In recent days, companies and other entities in the territory have intensified appeals to residents to vote. In addition, authorities introduced various measures to encourage and facilitate suffrage, including public transportation.
Some of the largest employers, such as game operators, have also made available free buses, meals and early departure times in the coming business days, according to Macau News Agency.
When he was inspecting the voting assemblies, Seng Ioi Man considered that “the preparation work, the facilitating measures and the good time” encouraged to vote. Later, he indicated that the voting places were operating within the normal range, with only one case in which a voter tried to use the mobile phone in the voting assembly.
 
Boss did not comment on letters
Sam Hou Fai voted yesterday morning at the Salesian Institute of Immaculate Conception. At the time, he said he exercised "a political right" and fulfilled a "responsibility." He also argued that these elections were taking place "in a good climate" and that there was an "enthusiastic participation of the whole society."
Refusing to comment on the document sent to civil servants, the chief executive preferred to stress that the vote "is a civic duty" and that "voters must actively participate in the elections and use the right to vote."
He also noticed that, during the election campaign, “society expressed great interest in participating” in the suffrage. "Once again I appeal to voters to vote, with valid votes, on the lists that deserve your confidence," he added.
The day before the elections, Sam was to inspect the voting assemblies, and reiterated that the candidate lists for direct suffrage "have wide representation".
Yesterday, after going to vote, the Secretary for Administration and Justice also made no comment, either in relation to the executive's head circular, nor on interrogations to civil servants. "We hope that citizens, public services workers and private companies will exercise their right to vote," said André Cheong, who ensured that there was no goal for abstention.
The calls to the vote were also bound yesterday by several holders of high positions, including the five secretaries, and service directors, as well as the president of AL, among others.
 
Chief enhances “fair, impartial and whole” electoral environment
With the “joint efforts from all over”, the elections “successfully took place, according to the law and in a fair, impartial and whole environment,” said the chief executive, after the preliminary counting of votes. In an official note, Sam Hou Fai congratulated the elected deputies and thanked voters who participated in the elections, as well as the staff highlighted to the voting places, civil servants, security forces, schools that provided spaces and entities that adopted measures to facilitate electoral participation. Exalting the organization and planning “well done” by the Commission on Electoral Affairs, he considered that the election “has been ordered” at a time of “deep meaning” because it was the first for the Legislative Assembly (AL) since the change of law in 2024. Ensuring that the government will continue to “maintain close communication and mutual cooperation” with Al, Sam Hou Fai said “Deputies News take forward the spirit of patriotism and love to Macao, actively participate in political affairs and return the support of the electorate with concrete work. ” The leader of the MSAR believes that the new AL will continue to “work hand in hand” with the government to “reinforce the economy, fight for development and to improve resident welfare, with a view to the joint creation of a brighter future for Macao”.
 
CCAC received 15 complaints on election day
The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) received 15 complaints and 34 requests for information on election day. Since early March and until yesterday, 143 complaints and 145 requests for information have been received, "26 criminal investigation cases have been instructed, four of which are related to electoral corruption and other illicit acts," the body said. When he was voting, the Commissioner, to the Ieong Seong, said that yesterday were found "about 10 occurrences, involving citizens with clothes showing number or denomination of the candidacy lists and other objects, so all were subjected to verbal warnings."</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea erases traces of Kim after meeting with Putin in Beijing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/coreia-norte-apaga-vestigios-de-kim-apos-encontro-putin-em-pequim/</link><description>After North Korean leader Kim Jong-un reunited with Russian President Vladimir Putin in Beijing, those responsible North Koreans carefully cleaned the objects played by the country's supreme leader, when analysts say they are part of a set of security measures to fight foreign spies.
Even with the appearance of a growing friendship between Kim and Putin, the 3 September images showed the extraordinary measures of the North Korean state to hide any track over Kim's health.
In a publication on Telegram, Kremlin reporter Alexander Yunashev shared images of Kim's team to meticulously clean the room in the Chinese capital where Kim and Putin met for more than two hours.
The backrest and arms of the chair were rubbed, and a coffee table next to Kim's chair was also cleaned. Your glass has also been removed.
"After the end of the negotiations, the team accompanying the head of the RPDC carefully destroyed all the traces of Kim's presence," said the reporter. RPDC is the abbreviation of the official name of North Korea, Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
After conversations in the living room, Kim and Putin left for tea and said goodbye warmly.
As with previous trips to the foreigner, Kim took his own living house in a green train that took him to Beijing to hide information about his health, said the Japanese newspaper Nikkei, citing South Korean and Japanese information agencies.
Such measures have been the standard protocol since Kim's predecessor era, his father, Kim Jong-il, said Michael Madden, a US-based North Korean leadership expert.
"The special bathroom and the necessary garbage bags with debris, waste and cigarette tips are for a foreign intelligence agency, even friend, does not get a sample to test it," said Madden.
"This would provide information on any medical conditions that affect Kim Jong-un. This may include hair and skin marks."
In 2019, after a Hanoi summit with US President Donald Trump, Kim guards were seen blocking the floor of their hotel room to clean the room for hours and remove items, including a mattress.
Kim's team was also seen to clean items meticulously before he used them. During his meeting with then South Korean President Moon Jae-in, in 2018, North Korean security guard sprayed a chair and a disinfectant table and cleaned them before Kim sit down.
According to Reuters, in another Summit with Putin in 2023, Kim's security team cleaned the disinfectant chair in advance and vigorously checked if it was safe, with a security guard using a metal detector to scan the seat, as a video showed.
 
JTM with Western Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>