<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Santa Casa provider proposed birth subsidy of 30 thousand patacas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/provedor-da-santa-casa-propos-subsidio-de-nascimento-de-30-mil-patacas/</link><description>In a meeting with the secretary for social affairs and culture, the provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia proposed several measures related to birth and population aging. One of them was the increase in the birth allowance of current 5,418 Patacas, a value that considers “derisory” to 30,000 patacas. As for aging, he gave the idea of ​​turning the lower floors of the residence into an elderly
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia proposed a series of births and aging measures to the secretary for social and culture affairs, Lam. Increased birth allowance, free day care and use of residence for the elderly to create a home were the ideas transmitted By António José de Freitas, who expressed concern with the phenomena of the low birth rate and the aging of the population in an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
“I proposed that the Macao government should increase monetary support to encourage the birth rate. In Hong Kong there are 20 thousand for every child born and it is good not to forget that there are over seven million inhabitants. Macao doesn't even have 10%. Macao gives 5,418 patacas, which is derisory. Last year, only 3,000 children were born, ”noted António José de Freitas.
In this sense, in a meeting with LAM, where members of the social sector of the Electoral Commission of the Chief Executive were present, the Holy House provider made a proposal in this context: “I suggested the secretary that the value, at least, should be 30 thousand Patacas. Every 1,000 children who are born only represent 30 million patacas. ” "It's nothing," he said, pointing to the revenues of 6,300 million from MSAR.
In the same field, he noted that “it is a luck for children” to be 15 years of free education in the territory, “something that does not happen everywhere”, however, argues that it takes more. “The government should also exempt children who need preschool, that is, the day care. Because whether families have money or not, they have to pay a monthly fee, ”he said.
As for the reaction of the secretary, António José de Freitas said it was “good”: “I think that, by her reaction, this will move forward. The birth subsidy will not be 5,000 Patacas for sure, ”he said in a preview of the government lines.
With the low birth rate in the territory, day care centers are already impacting. With two day care centers -one in Nape, subsidized by the government, and another on Avenida da República, the Lara Reis day care center -the Santa Casa was also affected, with these two spaces accounted for “losses” last year, due to decreased number of babies.
The oldest daycare in Nape has a capacity of 258 children, currently counting less than 200. “And according to the numbers of the Social Action Institute, our day care is one of the highest occupancy rate. There were day care centers that had to close rooms, ”said the provider. The Lara Reis day care center, with space for 70 children, welcomes, at the moment, 24. "All this is derived from the low birth rate," he noted.
Recently, the Deputy Director of Health Services (SSM), Kuok Cheong U, predicted that the MSAR should register less than 3,500 births in 2025, a number that would be the lowest since 2004. After visiting the first babies born in the lunar year of the serpent, He said he hopes that the birth rate "continues to fall" and added that "it will be good" if the number of births reaches 3,500.
If Kuok's forecast is accurate, this will be the least fertile year since 2004, when Macau registered 3,308 births. According to official data, 3,712 births were 43.5% than 10 years (6,571) and out of a maximum of 7,913 set in 1988, which was a lunar year of the dragon.
 
Residence for the elderly must host home
On the other hand, the tendency of aging of the population that will only be aggravated in the coming years also worries António José de Freitas. For this reason, it was also one of the topics he addressed with the secretary for social affairs and culture. The provider took official data from the Institute of Social Action, according to which 1,800 people were waiting to enter the homes of the elderly.
As this newspaper reported in January, there were only about five hundred hundred homes in elderly homes, and the waiting list was quite extensive. Vago places did not even cover a third of the people who were waiting to enter these spaces, which totaled about 1,800.
“I said 1,800 are many beds. Doing the math, a home with a capacity of 100 beds is already a very good home, has to have some space. We need 18 homes to be able to satisfy these requests. This is now, but in some time it will be worse, because the aging of the population gradually worsens, ”he said.
Stating that there is always talk of the home that is being built in zone A of the new landfills, the provider argued that it cannot be expected. “Why not enjoy the residence for the elderly, whose occupancy rate is too low? This has 37 floors, each floor has nine autonomous fractions… ”, he continued, saying that the idea would be to“ enjoy the lower floors ”.
In your opinion, taking advantage of that space to create a home would be "a perfect idea," because "when they enter the residence for the elderly, people have no guarantee about the future." According to the rules, people who can live in those fractions have to be independent. “The elderly who enter now have total independence, but in 10 or 15 years from now they are dependent, it is the law of nature. And then? They have to go back to the place of origin and have no guarantee of taking place in the elderly homes, ”he lamented.
Thus, the idea would be that, after being dependent, these seniors will pay, instead of the income of the residence for the elderly, the tuition of the home - which would be on the lower floors of that building. "It is a quick, effective solution and we enjoy the space that is already created," he said.
Home of Misericórdias, of Santa Casa, has 129 beds, currently welcoming 95 elderly. The space never fills because the third floor is dedicated to independent people, and 98% of the elderly who are admitted are bedridden and dependent.
Asked if it believes that in the lines of government action will be announced measures in this context, António José de Freitas said that there will be "a major revision regarding the distribution of benefits to the needy people." "And I think the consumer card will be an announced thing," he added.
 
Santa Casa with positive balance of 34.5 million
The Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao ended 2024 with a positive balance of 34.5 million patacas, “thanks to rigorous management,” said the provider, António José de Freitas, to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, indicating that Last year, all tenants of commercial spaces again paid the incomes, after several years of pandemic in which the amounts were cut, resulting from the economic situation that lived. The revenues “collected” by the Brotherhood ascended 102 million Patacas, a 6% increase in 2023. Most of the lace earnings of stores (42% of the total), in a value of 43.7 million; Following the subsidies of the Institute of Social Action and Health Services, of 17.6 million (17.4%), and interest on time deposits and the Order was worth 17.6 million (17.2%). As for the expenses, they totaled 67.6 million, and the spending on the staff were the ones who had the most “weight”, a total of 50 million patacas. Asked if this year there will be an increase in salaries, António José de Freitas said that no now, but "probably next year." In 2023, Santa Casa rose the salaries of employees by 5%.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Real estate sector wants land auctions to invert crisis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-imobiliario-quer-leiloes-de-terras-para-inverter-crise/</link><description>The president of the Macao Real Estate Entrepreneurs Association considers that the sector is living the “worst scenario in the last 40 years”, having recorded only an average of 3,000 transactions of housing fractions in the last three years. To inject vitality to the sector, Ung Choi Kun suggested, for example, that the government has been auctions of land to erect housing for exchange in urban renewal
 
The real estate sector of the territory is experiencing the “worst scenario in the last 40 years,” warned Ung Choi Kun, president of the Macao Real Estate Entrepreneurs Association, pointing out that, according to data from the Finance Services Directorate, 3,057 were registered. Transactions of housing fractions at MSAR last year. The average number of house transactions has reached only about 3,000 in the last three years, it has accentuated.
On the sidelines of the Spring Lunch organized by the Association, Ung Choi Kun also pointed to the constant increase in old buildings built over four decades in Macao. Given this context, he suggested to the authorities to advance with land auctions to build housing for exchange in urban renewal, in order to give more opportunities to the real estate sector.
According to the Chinese language press, the associative leader hopes to see various measures to counteract the crisis panorama, including the “deep integration” between the “1+4” industries and the real estate sector. In this respect, it has exemplified that the development of traditional Chinese medicine and Big Health requires modern industrial parks, laboratories and advanced equipment, as well as cold chain storage and logistics facilities. However, he warned that the current conditions of factories in Macao "can no longer meet the requirements for the development of modern industry."
In addition, Ung Choi Kun proposed to the government to take the initiative to erect a “complex with the nature of former libris”, encouraging the financial and banking sectors to support the participation of real estate industry in this project.
On the other hand, it stressed that small and medium -sized SME (SME) currently face “multiple challenges” related to capital, technical and market. Therefore, it expects a “high-tech industry incubation center to be built, which provides“ One-Stop ”SME services including offices, technical support and financing services. In your opinion, this solution will not only strengthen the competitiveness of SMEs, but will also foster more leases and investments for the real estate sector.
At the same time, Ung Choi Kun asked the authorities to launch “favorable and facilitating measures for the population” as a “one-stop” measure to open commercial establishments to stimulate internal demand and strengthen investor confidence .</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal has recorded 1,333 minors to work in recent years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsal-registou-1-333-menores-trabalhar-nos-ultimos-anos/</link><description>Between 2022 and 2024, 667 cases of hiring of minors were reported, involving 1,333 minors, according to data from the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs. Most work on hotel and restoration sectors, as well as thick and retail trade. According to the body's director, Wong Chi Hong, 21 lawsuits were instructed in the same period
 
Between 2022 and 2024, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) was notified to 667 cases of hiring minors, involving 1,333 minors. The information was advanced by the director of the body, Wong Chi Hong, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U.
Employers were mainly dedicated to “hotel and restoration” and “thick trade and retail”, while smaller workers in question was mainly “table employee” and “retail sales employee,” said Wong Chi Hong.
In the same period, 21 processes related to minors were instructed. According to the director of the government organism, they were "mainly related to the violation of minor admission requirements and the disqualification of employers' duty to communicate." The DSSA proceeded, in accordance with the law, “the monitoring of the offenses committed”, and Wong Chi Hong advanced details.
According to the Labor Relations Law, the minor who works must have completed the minimum age of admission, to have the physical and psychic capabilities appropriate to perform the functions to be performed, proven by written medical certificate, as well as the written authorization of their legal representatives.
In addition, the employer must communicate the hiring of the minor to DSAL within 15 days of the conclusion of the contract, and the copy of the contract, the medical certificate and the written authorization of its legal representatives, except in the situation of Hiring to work during the summer school holidays.
The director of DSAL also recalls that, in the current law, special guarantees related to the minor worker are plasma, and for example there are “prohibited and conditioned works”. In addition, there are also requirements regarding health protection, among others.
To increase public knowledge about the labor rights and interests of minors, DSAL has been conducting disclosure actions in various formats, as well as conducting exclusive clarification sessions in schools. Surveillance actions and special inspection actions are also carried out during summer school holidays.
“Dsal will, in articulation with the needs of socioeconomic development, continue with the attention given to the situation of law enforcement, as well as to continue to hear from the various quadrants of society the opinions and suggestions regarding a more adequate protection of rights and interests Workers, ”said Wong Chi Hong.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game in the phase of “stabilization”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-em-fase-de-estabilizacao/</link><description>Casinos' results after Chinese New Year holidays were “better” than they were feared, when they hit an average of 725 million patacas, according to the investment bank JP Morgan
 
Gross Macao game revenues totaled about 7.4 billion patacas in the first nine days of this month, which is equivalent to a daily average of 822 million, the JP Morgan investment bank said, stressing that “solid” demand At the end of this period it helped compensate for the “weakness” of the results achieved on Chinese New Year holidays. The recipes “stabilized after the Lunar New Year,” said DS Kim, Mufan Shi and Selina Li analysts.
Between February 1 and 5, the casinos raised 900 million patacas a day, but were a little short of the expectations of analysts and investors.
After the golden week, which took place between January 28 and February 4, the billing has been “better than it was”, translating an average of 725 million patacas, JP Morgan experts revealed. In general, monthly performance “remains within expectations, although it is at the lower end”, they noted, noticing that the daily average until February 9 is in line with its previous predictions (between 800 million and 850 million patacas) .
In estimates for the general taxpayer, the trio of analysts opt for caution, pointing to a wide margin, between 18.3 billion and 19.4 billion of patacas. In annual terms, this interval oscillates between a 1% break and a 5% increase.
As the first two months of 2025 may reflect an annual decrease of 2% or a growth of 2%. “This implies that gross game revenues in 2025 can grow only in a low digit, about +1% to +4% in annual terms,” says the report, stiving that the “consensus” of initial projections perspective an increase in about 5% compared to 2024.
This week, Citigroup has already reduced its forecast on the growth of macao casinos revenues in 2025, now anticipating an annual rise of 3%compared to the previous projection of 7%.
According to the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, the game's revenues were on 18.25 billion Patacas in January, translating an annual break of 5.6% and equivalent to 73.2% of the same month of 2019. On the other hand, 0.3% grew in monthly terms.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting “repsched” remains in the Elite League</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sporting-repescado-mantem-se-na-liga-de-elite/</link><description>The new season of the 1st Macao Football Division starts on the 19th and will rely on Sporting's participation. Leonine formation ended the past season in the penultimate place, so it was unpromped, but it turned out to be “repaired” due to the withdrawal of Mount Carlo. The decision was made by the soccer association, which thus confirmed the presence of the “white green” in the draw that takes place today. The associative leaders also revealed that women's football will have a championship of the eleven variant
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The 2025 season of the Macau Football League will start on February 19, with the first rounds to be held on the pitch of the Canidromo Campo. The race will feature 10 teams, as last season and in the same system, that is, a single turn of “all-Contra”, followed by two with the first five classifieds to play the title and the remaining to fight for maintenance in the main level.
This year's race will not have Monte Carlo, as the Jornal Tribuna de Macao had already advanced, which represents a loss of enormous meaning, as it is a historic club in the territory. To fill the vacancy left open by the “blue and yellow” club, the Macao Football Association (AFM) decided to “reply” Sporting, which finished the 2024 elite league in the penultimate position, ahead of Ka I. Decision arose following the same policy used in similar cases, according to this newspaper the secretary general of AFM told.
"When these situations happen, we have always given priority to the teams that would come down, thus providing them with permanence, which I think it makes perfect sense," said Chan Keng Hou during the traditional Spring Lunch, in which AFM gathers with the media and promotes the program for another time of football.
The leader reported that the elite league draw will take place today in the late afternoon, knowing the departure of the matches for the first hours of the competition, which will take place, not on the lawn of the Taipa stadium, as it would be desired of the clubs and intention of AFM, but in the field of the canhy.
 
Unavailable stadium “takes” games to the canidrome
Chan Keng has regrets that the floor of the Taipa Stadium is not at this time in condition, requiring some time so that there can be held back games of the championship. "We don't have great alternatives, so the Canidromo field is again our only option at this time," he said, hoping that "within perhaps a month or two the Taipa stadium can already host the elite league challenges." .
In addition to the absence of Mount Carlo in the Elite League, because it does not intend to continue the senior football project, the descent of the II Ka I division, another prestigious club at the local level, also stands out. Ka I and Monte Carlo have titles won throughout their history and have already been part of their plants of good quality players, not only from Macau but abroad, with emphasis on Brazilian professionals.
Unlike previous years, in which two teams were unpromped, this time only Ka I descends from division. In the opposite direction, the League of Elite is the champion of the 2nd Division of 2024, Shao Jiang, who promises to bet on "high flights" after the superiority manifested in the last year's race, and Ivo Chiba, a club that is given great importance to the development of young players.
In this sense, the elite league that is about to start generates some expectation, trying to compensate for the important absences of Monte Carlo and Ka I.
 
Women's football will have proof in the eleven variant
AFM, which has been represented by virtually its entire staff, including the coaches of the selections, released the activities plan for 2025, where a Women's Football Championship of the 11 variant will be charged for the first time, when the race will until now the test It was held in the D. Bosco field with seven athletes.
“This is a strong bet we intend to make,” said Chan Keng Hou, for those who “have been time to give women's football the dimension that deserves through this world and to provide women to play 11 elements games on the field , which so far had not yet happened at a local level and did not allow them to develop that it is necessary to implement. ”
Macau has been organizing a championship for at least six teams for several years, but in the variant of five players on each side and the synthetic floor of the D. Bosco field. This has created difficulties when the Macao female selection moves to international competitions to carry out Asian findings.
“The progress of women's football can be much greater,” expresses the leader. About the Women's Championship system, Chan Keng Hou has not given details, because "we are still discussing the best model."
"We will probably have to reduce the number of participating teams, as there are not so many athletes available, but the intention is to make a league with several laps so that they can compete as much as possible," he says.
According to the planning of AFM, the female football team will be able to hold friendly meetings in April, May, July, October and November, which will confirm will give the team a greater competitiveness.
 
Higher training frequency for the main selection
The year of Macao football will also bring a project of “greater intensity” regarding the frequency of the work of the selections, especially in the main formation. For this, AFM has a plan already stipulated by the new Kenneth Kwok coach, which points to more training periods.
The coach, born in Hong Kong, who has been responsible for some teams from the 1st neighboring territory and directed Raehk's main selection at the Jakarta Asian Games in 2018, told the Tribuna de Macao newspaper that “young players in the territory They have a lot of potential. ” "And that is what I intend to enjoy, giving them the possibility of training in the field, but also in theoretical sessions outside the lawn," he said.
Kenneth Kwok considers it "indispensable" that the main selection of MSAR is progressively assimilating the arrival of young elements, so that "there is a renewal and Macao football can ensure higher quality."
The representative team of MSAR has scheduled some international challenges of preparation, about four or five throughout the year, but not yet established or chosen opponents.
For the month of March, the first friendly challenge of the year is planned, but it will have to be out of Macao, as the Taipa stadium should not yet be in a position. “Later, yes, we will have our selection to receive some opponents in games included in the so -called FIFA window and scheduled for June, October and November,” said Chan Keng Hou.
However, in September, the under-23 Macao selection will participate in the Asia Championship qualification phase of the category. The respective draw will be held in June, so the adversaries are not yet known, knowing that, in principle, they will leave the geographical zone of East Asia and ranking similar to the MSAR.
Another aspect that the association intends to develop is the arbitration area. The president of the AFM Board said yesterday that a campaign was launched in schools and along with young people with soccer, so that there is an interest in attending referee courses. Thus, after the first attempt, AFM has already had the registration of nine students for arbitration sessions that will begin soon.
Lao Pak Leng also emphasized other courses, such as coaches, following the plan presented by the Kenneth Kwok coach, which aims for greater contact and joint learning, through various local stages with technicians not only of the selections, but also with those of the teams of the Elite League.
 
Disciplinary punishment Stephen Chow can be “some games”
The Disciplinary Commission of the Macao Football Association (AFM) has not yet made any decision regarding the punishment that should be applied to Stephen Chow, former President of Must CPK, following aggressions recorded at the end of a sub-sub-championship challenge 16. According to Chan Keng Hou, AFM Secretary-General, "the process is underway and has been longer because there have been many incidents and aggressions after the challenge is over." However, "as the images released on video are not fully enlightening whether or not there was aggression from the then CPK responsible, as stated in the police report, the punishment is likely to be summed up to some suspension games," said the manager. It is known, however, that the parents of Benfica's 15-year-old, apparently assaulted by Stephen Chow, did not file a complaint to the authorities. The former CPK president has already been replaced in office.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Green Island residents deliver petition to the Chief Executive</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/moradores-da-ilha-verde-entregam-peticao-ao-chefe-executivo/</link><description>In order to request the government changes to the new planning plan of the Green Island and the improvement of fire prevention measures, a group of residents of that city zone yesterday submitted a petition to the Chief Executive.
 
At the government headquarters, a group of residents of Verde Island yesterday handed a petition to the chief executive. In the document, they ask for changes to the new planning plan of Ilha Verde and the improvement of fire protection measures in that area of ​​the territory.
Regarding the new urban planning plan, residents began to regret that, although the government has underlined the importance of safeguarding the Green Island Hill and the maintenance and restoration of the convent, “there was no effective advance ”In this regard.
Fiting the planning of the green island as “challenging”, the petitioners appealed to the executive to create an exclusive interdepportional group to properly treat procedures for the expropriation of the Green Island Hill and the respective compensation. They argue in particular that the "real realization of the planning plan" will only be possible "if land throughout the hill are actually controlled by the government."
On the other hand, the plan expects to download the maximum height ceilings of the buildings in the lots influenced by the view of the visual corridor on the south side of the hill. According to the group of residents, the new top limit of height will affect the Fok Tak San Chuen building where several five -floor blocks have no elevators.
In this sense, residents are concerned about the risk that the reconstructed buildings are unable to welcome elevators due to height restrictions, because they are not foreseen, in the planning plan, measures to lodge affected residents. In the petition, the government also installed the restrictions to the height of the constructions in the lots influenced by the visual corridor, to enable the construction of buildings equipped with elevators.
Regarding the issue of fire safety, according to the Chinese language press, a petitioner pointed to the recent occurrence of a fire in a shipyard on the new road of Ilha Verde, where “after the fire, no prevention measures have not yet been taken measures. fires ”.
As there are many obsolete vehicles parked on Verde Island, residents are afraid that inappropriate treatment of these vehicles causes fires. In addition, they warned of the number of old trees in the area due to the impact of termites and for landslide signs on the slopes of some roads. Therefore, the petitioners have asked the government to optimize fire prevention measures, so that the safety of old and residents is better protected.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT resumed sending orders to the US</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctt-retomaram-envio-de-encomendas-para-os-eua/</link><description>The post office of Macao and Hong Kong announced the recovery of small packages and orders to the US after five days of suspension. In a statement, Macao's Post Office and Telecommunications Directorate says that it is already accepting “all mail objects” for the US.
The CTT recalled that the suspension "may have originated a correspondence, which will possibly result in delays in the delivery of shipments to the US." "Additionally, the possibility of any changes in the Postal Services of the United States cannot be excluded at any time," they warned.
Hours earlier, Hong Kong's post office had said they were "formally notified" by the US Postal Service (USPS) that US authorities "currently do not impose additional fees on postal articles with goods."
On January 5, the company said it had been notified by USPS that it could only send packages or orders that customers had registered with customs and the protection of US borders (CBP). The registration would require “the necessary import documents and the payment of fees made through a customs dispatcher,” added the Hong Kong Post Office. After the suspension of shipping, the company "continued to negotiate" with USPS.
On the 4th, USPS announced that it would temporarily stop accepting orders from China and Hong Kong (without any reference to Macao) “until new order”. But hours later, USPS reversed the decision, without justifying, just stating that it was going to work with the CBP to implement a collection process for the new rates imposed on Chinese goods in order to avoid interruptions in delivery.
The new US president has increased customs rates on imports from China by 10%after retreating in plans to charge tariffs to Canada and Mexico. The vast majority of goods sent from China arrives outside the mail system, but Donald Trump's order has eliminated exemption for low value products, acquired directly by consumers and sent through postal service. This exemption encompassed articles of less than $ 800. The USPS measurement could block or delay orders made through Chinese Electronic Trade platforms Shein and Temu.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing credit suffers third consecutive break</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-a-habitacao-sofre-terceira-quebra-consecutiva/</link><description>The value of new mortgage loans for housing approved by Macao banks was 1.01 billion patacas in December, marking a monthly decrease of 17.9%, although it risen 8.8% in annual terms, indicate monetary authority data (AMCM). In December, the loans granted to residents (1.18 billion) corresponded to 96.6% of the total.
This was the third consecutive monthly break in housing credit, after the 57% descents in October and 5.3% in November, which had contradicted the 142.1% increase between August and September.
Between October and December, the monthly average of new mortgage loans for housing reached 1.18 billion patacas, less 36.5% than in the previous period (September to November).
According to AMCM data, at the end of December, the debt ratio unpaid on housing credit, which involves delays over three months in interest and or capital payments, rose 0.1 points to 3.5% , compared to the previous month, and 2.7 percentage points compared to last year's same period.
Already the gross balance of mortgage loans for housing was located at 218.14 billion in late 2024, reflecting decreases of 0.5% and 4.9%, compared to the previous month and the same period of 2023, respectively. Of these loans, 96.6% were granted to residents.
For its part, the new commercial loans for real estate activities totaled 685.51 million patacas, an amount that translates a monthly decrease of 22.7% and an annual decline of 21.1%. Between October and December, the monthly average of these loans retreated 13.6% to 738.25 million, in relation to the previous three months.
In the credit segment for real estate activities, the unpaid debt ratio (5.3%) advanced 0.5 points in a month and 2.3 points within one year. The gross balance of commercial loans for real estate activities (149.92 billion) fell 0.7% compared to the previous month and 5.5% in the annual variation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Atletico veterania was added value on the way to the 1st division of the ball</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/veterania-atletico-foi-mais-valia-na-subida-a-divisao-da-bolinha/</link><description>With a majority of players over 40, Portuguese, Atletico de Macao managed, for the first time in the club's history, the rise to the main rank of the ball championship. In eight challenges made, the team only lost in front of champion Gala. For coach Pedro Ferreira, the championship was “very difficult”, in a race with several candidates. “It was worth our experience, which made a difference,” said the coach
 
A beautiful birthday gift, for its 10 years of existence, to complete two months from now, had the Atletico de Macao Club by reaching one of the great objectives since it was formed, the rise to the 1st division of the seven football championship, or Ball as it is popularly designated. The team guided by Pedro Ferreira won seven of the eight meetings held in the season, being the only defeat, already in the semi-finals, against the one who would become the champion, the gala.
In a competition in which the top three ranked climbing, Atlético achieved this dream in the third and fourth-classifieds game, that is, in the “duel” among the semi-finals losers, beating San Heng 3-1 .
Already in 2022, Atletico reached the final of the tournament, but this year there were no climbs, by decision of the Macao Football Association. "We have now achieved what we have proposed, knowing that it is not easy to reach the earlier phase of the race," the Tribuna de Macau newspaper the coach of a team with a overwhelming majority of veteran players, over 40 years of age.
"It was always this desire to face teams with younger players than us who moved us in this ball championship and so we finally got the climb, after we arrived at the quarterfinals in 2020," said the coach, who will leave The team's command next year, giving the place to Manuel Cunha.
For Pedro Ferreira, the “hard core” of the team, ie the oldest, was crucial for good results. “It was worth our experience, which made a difference,” he admitted, adding that the team has players who acted in many federated teams in Macau and so, despite their age, “made this experience in the field, before some opponents who performed With professional players from Hong Kong, but also Japanese, Brazilians and other nationalities, much younger than us. ”
In the midst of veterania of elements such as João Pegado, Ricardo Pinheiro, Tiago Assunção, Pedro Pereira, Daniel Melo, Henrique Ferreira, Ricardo Sá Carneiro (this one, 60), among others, Atletico told only this year with Two young people.
"Next time, with greater responsibility and difficulty that we will naturally find in the 1st division, we intend to renew the team a little, to get at least three or four young players to balance the squad," said the coach.
Clube Atlético de Macao, whose main founder was Pedro Ribeiro and Castro on April 29, 2015, also participates in football of eleven, having ended in the previous last post of the classification of the II Division, and is waiting for a possible “recap” to keep up in the echelon. However, the Macao Football Association has not accepted the pretensions of the Luso club, so Atletico will participate in the III division of the 2025 season.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Henry ma exposes China's paint sketches at Creative</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/henry-ma-expoe-esbocos-de-tinta-da-china-na-creative/</link><description>Until March 11, Henry Ma presents at Creative Macau three dozen pieces of his outdoor ink ink in recent years

An exhibition of paintings, by Henry Ma, presents about 30 works that are outdoor ink sketches outdoors in recent years by the artist, which applies western painting techniques in Chinese art and has also incorporated Chinese handwriting as a medium of expression. The exhibition was inaugurated yesterday at the Macao Creative Industries Center (“Creative”), where it will be evident until March 11.
This is one of the rare appearances on the painter's solo exposure, which reports, in statements regarding the launch of the exhibition, that their sketches, "although they cannot be considered as great works of art," may be a revision of the their research and development phases. "In fact," he acknowledges, "there are still many flaws that need to be improved." Henry Ma points out having tried "in many ways, but the effect was not significant," so he returned "to the starting point with outdoor sketches."
At first, the artist designed with handmade paper fiber pens, then passed to China's paint on rice paper. In the initial phase, he stresses, "he could not deal with the reaction between ink and water, but after years of practice, I gradually understood the interrelationship between these two means." Thus, he notes, "over the years to the present, I still think and constantly seek the way to express me in my own works of art."
Henry Ma, born in Macau, began working for the government shortly after his return to the territory, after the degree completed in Canada and was in charge of Fine Art exhibitions. Since then, he has organized only to others and occasionally participates in joint exhibitions to show some of his own works, “which does not reflect the scope of my artistic creation,” he says.
MA is a doctorate in archeology and museology from the University of Beijing and Master in History from the University of Jinan. He is currently director and member of the Macao Teledifusion Executive Committee (TDM).
The artist taught in institutions such as the Universities of Beijing and Science and Technology of Macao, and published a book entitled “A Research on Blue and White Porcelain Wares of the Ming Dynasty Unearthed in Macau”, along with articles in various academic magazines. His art, including paintings, photographs and Chinese calligraphy, was exhibited in Canada, mainland China and also in the MSAR.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AI will improve children's area in the city of Flores City</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-vai-melhorar-zona-infantil-jardim-da-cidade-das-flores/</link><description>The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) began on Monday the works of optimization of the children's fun zone of the Garden of the City of Flores. According to AMI, the reordering project is justified by the fact that the facilities and the floor rugs are already “aged” after many years of use. The new facilities are “adequate” for children aged between the two and 12 years, being installed “diversified” fun equipment for this age group, such as climbing and balance, the body explained. In addition, “a seamless safety rug and barriers without barriers will be installed to connect the children's fun zone and the garden of the city of Flores, as well as washing for children, in order to optimize the leisure space of the leisure Citizens, making it more convenient for the use of adults and children, ”says the AMI statement. The execution period of the work is about 150 days, but may be extended "due to time and other factors." The children's fun zone will be closed during the endeavor.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau wins Bahrain in ice hockey at winter games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-vence-bahrain-em-hoquei-gelo-nos-jogos-de-inverno/</link><description>Macau's ice hockey selection ended its participation in the winter Asian Games with a 4-3 triumph of Bahrain after extension after 3-3 at the end of regulatory time. The mashed team, oriented by Ho Chon Nin, had lost all three challenges in the regular phase of the tournament that runs in the Chinese city of Harbin, having achieved the challenge with Bahrain avoiding the last position in the sport. The finding meeting of the 13th and 14th places of the competition was very balanced, having left for the second period of the departure of the Harbin University Arena at a disadvantage by 1-0. In the second 20 minutes, the set of mashes reached equality through Shinoda Katsuyoshi and won in the third period 2-1 (Edison Sou and Ho Yieng goals), forcing a extension. In extra time, Macau was happier and scored for Hermínio Cheng Chon. The delegation of the mashes, which participated in the winter Asian Games only in this mode of hockey, thus closed its participation in the “Ice City”, after having endorsed defeats compared to Turquemenistan (26-0), Hong Kong ( 26-0) and India (4-2). The games will take place until next Sunday and, in the middle of yesterday afternoon, the entourage of the Popular Republic of China had already won a total of 54 medals, 21 of which of gold. In second place follows South Korea, with 30, and third of Japan, with 17.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2341/</link><description>Woman from the continent drowned in Hotel do Nape
The Judicial Police (PJ) announced yesterday the death of a middle-aged woman from the interior of China, who drowned in the pool of a hotel in the Nape area. In the afternoon of Monday, according to PJ, the body of Victim was found by family members, who asked the staff of the hotel unit. The woman was eventually rescued by hotel employees and submitted to first aid, but died. In the body were not found suspicious injuries. The case will continue to be investigated.
 
11 thousand anti-gripe vaccines acquired urgently
Health services (SSM) acquired 11,000 doses of urgent flu vaccines, taking into account the “evident increase in the demand for vaccination”. The doses arrived last night. According to the body, from today there will be more vacancies to mark vaccination, however, the elderly 65 years or older and residents aged six months and nine years are exempt from marking. The SSM also stressed that, between 2024 and this year, already acquired 225 thousand doses of the flu vaccine, plus 45 thousand doses compared to the amount acquired at the previous time. By February 10, 204 thousand doses of the flu vaccine in Macao have already been given, compared to 167,000 administered in the same period last year, thus registering an increase of 22.2%.
 
Canton helicopters take off in the middle of the year
According to the Canton press, a heliport is being built in the Pazzi zone, specifically in the so-called modal center of the Hong Kong and Macau passenger transport terminal, and, according to the contract, the infrastructure may enter into operation in mid -year. At the time, aerial routes will begin between Canton International Airport and Hong Kong and Macau airports. The Canton-Hong Kong trip could last 26 minutes, with the tickets between 450 and 620 Renminbis. As for Macao, this type of information was not available. A volume of 150 trips per day is planned.
 
Seak Chio Law took office as a subdirector of the DICJ
Seak Chio Law took office as a subdirector of the Directorate of Inspection and Game Coordination (DICJ), at a ceremony chaired by the substitute director, Lio Chi Chong, and witnessed by the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP. Lio Chi Chong praised Law Seak Chio, stating that "the vast experience and professional capacity will bring new ideas and dynamics to the DICJ, and will help reinforce the effectiveness of surveillance." Master in Public Administration, Seak Chio Law began his career in the civil service in 2005, in the services for labor affairs, where he has been so far.
 
Coffee will be able to cost in the coming months
IP Sio Man, president of the Macao Suppliers Union Association, warned that coffee prices increase over the next three to six months in the territory. Speaking to the newspaper “or Mun”, the associative leader said that, due to the impact of extreme time, the price of coffee raw materials has been rising around the world. Specifically the cost of importing coffee from Brazil and Colombia tripled, he said.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Côa Museum takes children traveling at the time of the paleolithic to the present</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/museu-coa-leva-criancas-em-viagem-tempo-paleolitico-a-actualidade/</link><description>The Côa Museum Living Science Center has launched a challenge to the students of the 1st cycle of the Côa Valley, who, from 2022, takes them on a time trip, from the upper paleolithic to the present day. This adventure, which has already covered about 600 students from various schools in the Côa Valley region, begins in the prehistoric and tries to demonstrate, to the long of various learning phases, the evolution of hunter communities and superior paleolithic residents, which They occupied the territory 25,000 years ago, to the 21st century scientists. Foz Côa, Guarda, January 29, 2025. (Accompanies Lusa text of February 03, 2025). Francisco Pinto/Lusa



The Côa Museum Living Science Center has launched a challenge to students of the 1st cycle of Vale do Côa who, from 2022, has taken them on a time trip, from the upper paleolithic to the present day.
This adventure, which has already covered about 600 students from various schools in the region of the Côa Valley, begins in the prehistoric and tries to demonstrate, to the long of various learning phases, the evolution of hunter communities and superior paleolithic recollectors, which They occupied the territory 25,000 years ago, to the 21st century scientists.
Speaking to Lusa, the coordinator of the Côa Museum School of Living Science, in Vila Nova de Foz Côa, explained that, over a week, workshops, visits, 'workshops' and laboratory activities, in which children, are tinned. They explore the various activities of the time, such as hunting, fire production, manufacture of household items, rock recording techniques, among others, until finally they play the role of the archaeologist among other scientists.
“Children for five days will belong to tribes of the same camp and are performing activities, until they return to the course of thousands of years, starting as hunters and recollectors of the upper paleolithic and ending this venture as 21st century scientists, who They take them on a time trip, ”said Vera Lúcia Carvalho.
On this time trip, Vasco, a student of the 1st cycle of the Lieutenant Colonel Adam Carrapatosa group in Vila Nova de Foz Côa, did not hide the anxiety in learning to build spears, a rudimentary wood and silent weapon, but a great discovery for The Communities of Hunters of the Superior Paleolithic.
“I would like to learn to spears, just like primitive men, who served to hunt for food to tribes and family. (…) The lives of prehistoric men was very difficult, because they had to fire with stone or make their clothing to wrap themselves from the cold, ”said the 8-year-old student.
Maria Dias, a student of the same school and the same age, considered this trip in the time made at the Côa Museum very rewarding, after all that she saw and lived and who could observe and experiment.
"I am enjoying it a lot and what caught my attention was this time trip, in which we tell us stories with representations of 25,000 years ago," said this 3rd year student who did not hide the excitement of the journey.
Other of the aspects that caught the attention of Mary were the scenes of the daily life of the Paleolithic communities that are represented in the engravings inserted in the rocks of the Archaeological Park of Vale do Côa (PAVC), which were revealed in a class of experimental archeology.
"I was very fond of learning these pickup techniques to make prehistory engravings," he said.
“I had never done it, but I was very fond of learning. They represent images that seem to move, giving the idea that they move their heads to one side to protect someone. It seems to me a story of the comics of 25,000 years ago, ”noted the future scientist.
In another room, there was another group of children who began their discovery in the scientific area, through small experiences of great significance regarding the behavior of matter.
At this stage of the didactic path, simple materials are used that allow children to see the behavior of matter in the face of simple chemical reactions. For this case an egg was chosen.
Joana, an 8-year-old student, was aware of the behavior of the egg that turned into a “bouncing ball” after her peel softening and becoming more transparent and malleable. Others of the experiments was to make the egg foam, with the addition of a simple chemical formula.
“These are simple things that can change the world. By accompanying this chemical reaction, I noticed many fixed things on the behavior of matter and this experience taught me a lot, because I saw how the elements can become different things, ”said the little student.
One of the objectives of this class, explained archaeologist Marta Mendes, from the Côa Parque Foundation, is to give students the opportunity to know the raw materials and the materials that were used in hunting weapons.
The project began in 2022, and is funded by funds from the recovery and resilience plan.
 
Jtm with Francisco Pinto from Lusa Agency</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>