<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Food Bank has already supported more than 2,800 residents this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/banco-alimentar-ja-apoiou-mais-de-2-800-residentes-este-ano/</link><description>In the first seven months of this year, Caritas de Macau accepted requests from 2,841 residents to receive support from the food bank. According to Paul Pun, secretary general of Caritas, on average, about 900 residents raise food attributed under the weekly food bank. On the other hand, the institution continues to make a temporary food supply service available to foreign citizens in Macao, and has been distributing bread to approximately 250 per week
 
Between January and July this year, 2,841 residents successfully requested the support of Caritas de Macao under the food bank, a number similar to the same period of 2024 (2,848 accepted requests), Paul Pun, Secretary General of the Institution, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
In terms of a weekly average, about 900 residents receive food at food bank service stations, being sufficiently raised for an entire week, Paul Pun said. The weekly number is equivalent to the accounted for in the same period of last year.
The beneficiaries of the food bank are residents or local families of low income, not included in the subsidies network of the Institute of Social Action.
The short-term goal is to help alleviate the difficulties of these residents in life and make them physically and mentally more resilient. In the long run, the institution expects that, through the Food Bank project, the public provides more attention to the problem of poverty in local society and demonstrates more solidarity with others.
As for foreign citizens in the territory, Caritas also provides a temporary food supply service from pandemic. According to Paul Pun, the institution has received new food donations in the last two months, but as the amount is not very large, it has ceased to distribute them to foreign citizens on Sunday. However, it maintains the distribution of bread on weekdays, having served about 250 foreigners per week.
 
Home service for elderly with “remarkable” results
On the other hand, Caritas will organize the “Charity Race” at the University of Macao, on September 28, waiting for 2,000 participants. Paul Pun clarified that the funds raised through the race will be used to cover the expenses of the “We Connect” project, a new service launched by Caritas in March to provide support to the elderly at home or in designated places.
The “We Connect” service currently works with five helpers, all non -resident workers, and featured about 140 users in July. Currently, monitoring in the medical appointment and at night are the most sought after types of support by the We Connect users.
"This service has already begun to give very remarkable results. Some family members of the elderly want our support a lot. But on the other hand, the service costs 100 patacas per hour while that similar government subsidized only 100 patacas for eight hours of service. So we need to gradually broaden users of this new service," Paul Pun acknowledged.
In this sense, funds raised through race will help partially subsidize some users who actually require a longer duration of this service, but have been restricted by financial limitations.
"Some seniors have money deposited on the bank, but they don't want to get it up, because they only keep this money for use after you die. And there are others unable to raise money, which may also be some of our home support users," Paul Pun noted.
In general, the Secretary General of Caritas stressed that an amount of 300,000 Patacas, equal to the range of last year's race, will not be sufficient to support the respective service for a long time, because the management of this company by residents, the necessary means of transportation to travel to the hospital, among many operational details imply costs. On the other hand, he found, most people needed in this context continues to preference to the government's subsidized service, so the reinforcement of the disclosure will be one of the institution's important tasks.
Earlier next year, Caritas may need to increase the “We Connect” assistant team. Usually a helper can provide service to three seniors, and the five workers currently assume 50% of normal working volume. When they are not working, helpers are subject to training and other psychological works.
 
New home should take “a lot of time”
Already on the new elderly home of Caritas, with 40 beds, which will be located on Coronel Mesquita Avenue, Paul Pun revealed that the cultural institute “verbally” agreed with the design of the project. However, as there are divergent opinions between various government services, the project “may face many problems” and “it should take a long time”.
Regarding the institution's clinic, in Areia Preta, whose opening was scheduled for July 2024, the secretary general of Caritas revealed that the direction of soil services and urban construction recently approved the project project. After obtaining another document from this organism, Caritas may already require license from health services, and license issuance usually takes a few months. After this stage you can start recruiting doctors.
Maintaining the plan of three consultation rooms and three Western Medicine doctors, including a dentist, as well as the non -profit nature of the clinic, Caritas has supported an income for the occupation of space. “The preparation took a long time,” lamented the official, hoping that the procedures around the clinic will gain speed.
In addition, the Caritas Bakery, in the São Lázaro neighborhood, also did not go into operation according to the scheduled calendar - in April this year. Paul Pun explained that he has already obtained a license and the decoration was completed, and the institution was acquiring clothing equipment. Despite having resorted to different channels, Caritas has not yet been able to find a advisor, who, besides needing to make bread and cakes, must be “a loving person”. At the same time, it is necessary to seek sponsorship.
Four or five people with disabilities are intended to work at the bakery per day, each one or two hours a day. Bread sales will start when the master is found. On the other hand, Caritas intends, through the bakery, to offer birthday cakes to children.
 
Inclusive Travel Agency in “Stable Development”
In turn, Caritas Travel Agency Kin Hang, which promotes inclusive excursions, dedicated to people with mobility difficulties, “has maintained a stable development”, although it has not organized a high number of excursions. "People with disabilities still do not have a strong motivation to participate in paid tourist excursions," said Paul Pun.
Still, the official emphasized that the travel agency has the main objective "to give one more option to the disabled to leave home" and provide "an opportunity to their families to show affection". Normally, the agency serves families with members with disabilities or social groups that seek to promote a different way of social inclusion, through the organization of tours or sponsoring excursion rates.
According to Paul Pun, the agency's next excursion will depart in October with at least a dozen visually impaired tour, and can spend a night in the interior of China.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended pedestrian areas in Zape</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidas-areas-pedonais-zape/</link><description>Like several restoration traders at Zape, Leong Chon Kit, a vowel of the Central Zone Community Services Advisory Board, suggested pedestrian zones in that area of the city. In turn, another member of the Advisory Body, Lao Sio Cheok, proposed the regular holding of cream and “Bubble-Tea” pastel festivals at Zape
 
At a plenary meeting of the Central Zone Community Services Advisory Board, vowel Leong Chon Kit suggested the creation of “own characteristics” pedestrian zones at Zape. In the same vein, some traders who operate restaurants in Zape also proposed the transformation of some streets in this part of the city into pedestrian areas to improve the overall image of Zape.
Listened to the newspaper “or Mun”, traders appealed to the government to enjoy the gastronomic, cultural and creative fair, which will start on Zape on the 15th, to transform, for example, Beijing Street into one of the pedestrian zones. The idea has as reference the projects of community revitalization of Shanghai and Hong Kong.
Assuming that they will support and collaborate with the gastronomic fair, through the launch of discounts for consumers, retailers argued that any pedestrian zones could facilitate the displacement of residents and visitors to Zape, make young tourists more familiar with the area and enrich gastronomic elements through the attraction of different types of restaurants. According to the traders, the lack of cooking diversity in Zape has been the subject of comments among the public.
For vowel Leong Chon Kit, it would be advisable to create incentives for Zape restaurants to require Esplanade licenses to promote the transformation of commercial establishments. In addition, it expects community facilities to be perfected in the area, namely awnings, adjusted to the distribution of parking spaces and bus careers to become “more reasonable”.
Leong Chon Kit also requested a health center, spectacles and sports at Zape, as well as long -term community dissemination actions, with the aim of seeking sustainable development and the economic transformation of that part of the territory.
In turn, another member of the Advisory Board, Lao Sio Cheok, asked that new scenarios of cultural and tourist consumption will be fostered at Zape. In concrete, he suggested regularly holding a “cream festival” and a “Bubble-Tea Festival” at Zape, with a view to stimulating consumption.
Alongside this, this vowel proposed the “deep exploration” of the connotation of Flor de Lotus Square and the Kun Iam Ecumenical Center, and the integration of the respective elements into intellectual property brands, Chinese fashion and tourist activities of immersive experience.
On the other hand, Lao Sio Cheok has suggested to the government that “officially recommended” tourist tour of tourist tour and careers of free tourists to tourists, in order to bring more visitors to Zape, promoting sustainable development.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>More arbitration in the disputes between consumers and traders</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mais-arbitragens-nas-disputas-entre-consumidores-comerciantes/</link><description>Consumers and merchants have appealed more arbitration to resolve disputes, dismissing consensus resolutions between both parties, according to consumer board data. Since 2016, commercial operators have also been overcome more cases against consumers, contrary to the trend verified between 1998 and 2015
 
Pedro Milheirão
From 1998 to the end of 2024, 791 cases of dispute between consumers and traders have been established, involving a total amount of more than 4.9 million patacas. Of these processes, 426 (53.9% of the total) were resolved with consensus and 241 (30%) resorted to arbitration. However, according to data from the Macao Consumer Council, fewer and fewer cases have been resolved by conciliation, without the need for arbitration in recent years. From 2015 to 2019, in 105 instituted cases, almost half (51) was resolved by consensus. However, between 2020 and 2024, although more processes were established (156), only 15 were resolved without arbitration.
In recent years, cases resolved with arbitration have also given favorable opinions more often to commercial operators. From 1998 to 2015, consumers won 101 disputes (56.1%), more than half of the 180 cases arbitrated during this period. On the other hand, from 2016 to 2024, the commercial operators earned 41 of the 61 arbitrated cases, representing more than two thirds (67.2%), indicating a turn to the merchants.
Of the total proceedings filed, five were suspended and 109 archived. It should be clarified that, exceptionally, in the year 2021, 107 of the 114 instituted cases were filed and involved disputes related to “membership of members to other services”, without additional information. It is necessary to reassemble to 2008 to find another year in which there was more than a hundred instituted cases (129), with 110 of these was resolved by consensus. Adding the processes resolved by reconciliation (426), with those resolved by arbitration (241), as well as the suspended or archived (114), there are 10 instituted cases on which no information is available.
Between 1998 and 2020, 403 of the 647 cases involved goods or products, which translates into a proportion of 62.3%, compared to service disputes. Since 2021, the year when the Consumer Council began to use a new categorization of the established cases, and until 2024, the services began to represent 84% of cases. Of a total of 144 lawsuits, 121 concerned services. However, if we exclude the 107 cases filed in 2021, in 37, most conflicts (23) continued to be related to goods or products.
 
Evolution of products and services
Over the course of more than two decades, computer and telecommunications purchases have been the typology of goods that have generated the most conflicts, resulting in 95 disputes (14.7%) of the total cases between 1998 and 2020. In the following four years, from 2021 to 2024, with the new consumer council designations, there was only one case (0.7%), highlighting a significant breakage.
On the other hand, jewelry and craft pieces remain products that often result in disputes. From 1998 to 2020, they originated 54 cases, or 8.3% of the 647 of this period. In the last four years, these same articles have resulted in eight of the 144 disputes (5.6%). The cases related to clothing went from 29 (4.5%) from 1998 to 2020, to 3 (2.1%) from 2021 to 2024. In the first period, laundries gave rise to 92 cases (14.2%), and from 2021 to 2024 none was recorded.
In the interval from 1998 to 2020, 48 instituted cases were related to tourist services (7.4%). Between 2021 and 2024, only one case was registered in the same sector. Between the two periods analyzed, feeding products fell 89%from 18 cases to two. There have been 15 processes -related processes related to vehicle acquisitions, from 1998 to 2020, and none from 2021 to the end of 2024. Cases on transportation services have also fallen from four cases between 1998 and 2020, to just one in the last four years.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lack of infrastructure and talents restricts metaverse in the MICE sector</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/falta-de-infra-estruturas-talentos-restringe-metaverso-sector-mice/</link><description>The MSAR is not prepared to integrate the metaverse in the convention and exhibition industry, according to a study involving researchers from the Macao University of Science and Technology. For the authors, the infrastructure needs to be updated, it is necessary to find qualified professionals and the government itself must play an active role in the development of the metaveverse
 
Pedro Milheirão
Outstanded infrastructure and scarcity of qualified professionals and policy by the government are some of the problems that prevent the growth of a technology that could boost the MSAR tourism sector -the metaverse -according to a recent study.
The authors of the article “Factors inhibitor affecting conventions in Metaveveiro in Macao” interviewed academics and experts from the industry areas of information and information technologies. The investigation group includes Songhong Chen, Chunhui Cai and Jian Ming Luo, from the Macao University of Science and Technology, and Lam Fai, editor of Macau Convention &amp; Exhibition magazine.
Researchers have observed that, despite having an “established and prosperous” tourist sector, the MSAR needs to intervene in various parameters if you want to establish yourself as a leader in the convention industry. Macao has faced some obstacles, particularly in the “emerging field” of the metaverse.
Some of the respondents expressed concerns about the ability of facilities related to traditional tourism, considering them “too old-fashioned” and needing renewals. For one of the interviewees, "many of Macau's large convention sites have been in operation for many years, and numerous facilities no longer meet the current technological demands."
Similarly, another inquired stated that "the conventional reasoning process behind Macau convention industry can be unable to keep up with technological advances." Network conditions, the authors report, are also considered “a significant restriction on the development of Metaverse convention tourism in Macao”. “The main technological pillars that support the metaverse include Artificial Intelligence (AI), networks, blockchain and the Internet of Things,” they indicate.
Several respondents pointed to "problems such as unstable connections" and "internet speeds that didn't align with 5G claims." In addition, the high cost and limited options of internet services in the territory can be obstacles to "the high standard operational requirements of the metaveverse."
"The development of the Internet as a platform allows transfer without discontinuities of incorporeal assets, such as knowledge and culture, which transcend traditional limitations because they have decreased the importance of physical location. The metavevers is a technological advancement for conventions, providing universal access to individuals and allowing conventions to occur without geographical and time restrictions," read in the study.
"With the widespread adoption of metaverse technology and the accumulation of experience, other industry participants can also emulate and get cost benefits. Although the early stages may require substantial capital investment over time, investment costs can gradually decrease with technology proliferation," the authors say.
In other words, “increasing technology adoption can generate economies of scale, reducing long -term costs,” which requires, however, cooperation between government and private sectors to balance risks and returns and optimize resource allocation.
 
Metaverse requires active role of the government
At the same time, “Macao is experiencing a professional talent deficit in areas related to metaverse, particularly in technology, design and marketing, which are essential to successfully performing metaverse conference tourism”, which can restrict sector growth.
In the case of an “emerging industry with the potential to cultivate and develop talents”, the MSAR government “must support the reeducation and formation of the current workforce”. For the authors, "the government has the task of providing a favorable political environment and ensuring that these policies adapt to the characteristics and demands of emerging technologies." In this sense, "Macao government efforts can potentially create more opportunities for the development of metaverse conference tourism."
In turn, the integration of the metaverse could help the government diversify the economy, for which "Macau is favorably positioned." Diversification is "especially important for small economic entities such as Macau, as excessive dependence on a single economic field (for example, the game industry) can increase economic vulnerability."
"Under the action of multiple stakeholders, leveraging technological innovation capabilities can improve the efficiency and quality of the construction of metaverse scenes, continually enrich the innovation of the model, improve tourist consumer experience and continually achieve structural innovation, increasing the general competitiveness of the metavers.
Generally speaking, respondents believe that the metaverse can renew the tourism sector, grow service exports, and attract more investors. The government and relevant entities should consider investment and coordination of the necessary infrastructure construction, such as network coverage, data centers and hardware devices. The search for physical devices of augmented reality and virtual reality, essential to the metaverse, has been growing.
"The effective adoption of the metaverse requires hybrid governance models that balance a decentralized innovation with centralized regulatory safeguards." On the other hand, “stakeholders are also concerned about negative impacts on privacy and safety, as well as the potential negative effects on mental health and social relations,” the authors say. It is essential to follow the double principles of “adherence to the autonomous rules of the metaverse and timely intervention”. Government intervention must respect the rules achieved by consensus, maintaining a “reasonable and legal basic order” that encourages private entities to actively innovate and explore the construction of the future of the metaveverse.
This study was based on qualitative data from a limited number of interviews with industry professionals, so they may not represent the prospects of all relevant potential interveners.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Summit between Putin and Trump pointed to the "next few days"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/cimeira-entre-putin-trump-apontada-para-os-proximos-dias/</link><description>Donald Trump and Vladimir Putin will meet "in the coming days," Kremlin said yesterday, adding that the two parts have a "principle" agreement about the summit site, which will be announced later. Putin pointed out, however, that the meeting could take place in the United Arab Emirates.
"The approximate date has been set for next week, but the parties are preparing for this important meeting and it is difficult to predict how many days will take the preparations," said presidential counselor Yuri Ushakov, quoted by the Russian official news agency Tass.
This summit will be the first among US and Russian acting presidents since Joe Biden met Putin in Geneva in June 2021. The meeting is part of Trump's efforts to end Russian military offensive in Ukraine.
The three direct conversations rounds between Moscow and Kiev organized so far have not generated advances for a ceasefire and the parts seem to be very far from the end of the conflict, which began more than three years ago. Putin has so far rejected the reiterated appeals of the US, Europe and Kiev for a ceasefire. During direct conversations in Istanbul, Russian negotiators demanded partially occupied Ukrainian regions and that Kiev gives up from the NATO adhesion project, unacceptable conditions for Ukraine.
The summit announced came a day after the US envoy Steve Witkoff with Putin in Moscow. Witkoff proposed a trilateral meeting that would also include Ukrainian President Volodimir Zelensky, but Russia did not respond to the proposal, according to Ushakov. "The Russian part left this option completely without comment," he said.
Zelensky and German chancellor Friedrich Merz praised Donald Trump's “mediation efforts”. Russia should “end its war of aggression, which is contrary to international law,” said the German government, one of the most fervent supporters of Ukraine, while Zelensky urged Europe to participate in peace talks between Ukraine and Russia.
“War is happening in Europe, and Ukraine is an integral part of Europe (…) Europe must therefore participate in the process” that aims to end a war that has been dragging on since 2022, said the Ukrainian President after a telephone conversation with Merz.
According to Zelensky, it is crucial that Europe is present in the business process with Russia that Trump tries to promote. "Ukraine and Germany share the view that war should end as soon as possible, with a dignified peace, and the parameters for the end of the war will shape Europe's security horizon in the coming decades," Zelensky wrote on social networks.
The Ukrainian President said he was still scheduled for yesterday a remote meeting between the security counselors of the leading European and American leaders to coordinate positions against the next events.
Zelensky reaffirmed his willingness to meet with his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, regardless of whether or not leaders from third countries. "Ukraine is not afraid of the meetings and expects the same brave posture of Russia. It's time to put the war end," he concluded.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Deputy wants “Data Security Law”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/deputado-quer-lei-da-seguranca-de-dados/</link><description>BusinessWoman Use Laptop, Analytics and Financial and Bank Technology Concept, Chart from Computer Laptop, Business Growth Concept



Deputy Hon Ion Sang urged the government to assess whether it is necessary and feasible to create an exclusive “data security law” for Macau, and to introduce an audit mechanism related to government data security
 
Given the increase in the number of cyber espionage attacks or acts to Macao's critical infrastructures to 6,200 per day in 2024, Deputy Ho Ion Sang warned that the phenomenon not only threatens the personal privacy of residents, but can also impact the socioeconomic security and international reputation of MSAR, affecting even national security.
In this sense, in written interpellation, Ho Ion Sang urged the executive to comprehensively evaluate the need and feasibility of creating a “data security law” specifically for Macao. The goal is to protect the data from Macau more completely, he said, recalling the approval of a law on matter in China as early as 2021.
For the deputy, the Government of MSAR should reinforce consciousness to danger, since, in the face of unstable changes in the environment of international cyber security, "the improvement of data security protection has been urgent."
In your opinion, the framing of internet data processing supervision has to be improved, in order to be able, in addition to ensuring the privacy of residents, promoting the orderly flow, development and use of data. "What will be the prospective measures that authorities will take with a view to strengthening the protective resilience of critical infrastructure, thus preventing the risk of cyber attacks and large-scale data leakage?"
In addition, Ho Ion Sang argued that, with the aim of ensuring that the integrity, availability and confidentiality of government data meet international and local requirements, there must be an interdepartal audit mechanism regarding government data security. Through this, authorities can periodically verify the compliance and safety of public services in collecting, processing, storing and transmission of data, as well as taking the initiative to identify and correct security gaps, with independent audit and risk assessment.
On the other hand, the deputy expects the government to reinforce education with the public about data security, through lectures, school courses, business training, in order to lead more residents to “fully know the important meaning of data security management”, and gain greater identification and protection skills, thus fostering a social atmosphere of “personal data protection and cyber security safeguard”.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ESTABLISHED SCHOOLS ELIMINATING MOSQUITES</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/escolas-instadas-eliminar-mosquitos/</link><description>Higher education schools and institutions were bought to carry mosquito elimination actions before the beginning of the school year. Education services also appealed to the reinforcement of surveillance
 
The Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) urged territory schools and higher education institutions to consolidate cleaning work on campus to prevent dengue fever and chikungunya fever. "The summer vacation period is crucial to reinforce preventive measures against mosquitoes and to reduce the risk of disease transmission," the body said in a colloquium with 120 representatives from local institutions.
At the same time, DSEDJ appealed to schools to reinforce surveillance and strictly follow the instructions for preventing dengue and chikungunya fever for secondary, primary and child schools, as well as higher education institutions. Specifically, he urged schools to materialize preventive measures and to pay “high attention” to the most up to date information on health services (SSM).
On the other hand, institutions should “try to increase awareness of teachers, students and parents for prevention” against mosquitoes, in order to jointly ensure a healthy environment in schools and community neighborhoods.
The SSM have ensured, in turn, that they will continue to closely monitor the evolution of the disease. At the same time they will resort to interdepartmental cooperation to protect public health. In general, DSEDJ and SSM have renewed appeals to schools and community neighborhoods to intensify measures to prevent and eliminate mosquitoes.
The Colloquium intended to help schools gain “greater capacity” of chemical elimination of mosquitoes. DSEDJ stressed that it will continue to communicate with schools to ensure a safe and healthy school environment for teachers and students.
Macau has so far registered two local cases and six imported cases of chikungunya fever.
However, the authorities have already said that the territory is at a crucial phase of disease transmission prevention. In this sense, awareness campaigns have been done.
The SSM, together with the Macao Workers' Federation of Associations, the General Union of Macao Residents Associations, the Macao General Association of Macao, the Vietname Friendship Association in Macao and the Indonesian migrant workers organization, formed 29 promotional groups with more than 130 people.
Disclosure groups moved to Rua do Manduco Praia, namely Kuong Ho, Weng Fong, Weng Fong, Tin Si Kok, Son SENG, Chun Ieng, among others, to perform health awareness and education actions with residents, including the presentation of chikungunya and dengue fever symptoms as well as the source of transmission.
In both actions, more than 4,200 dwellings were inspected and awareness of about 1,400 residents were visited, and about 530 homes were visited, “where many stagnant water and larvae containers were found”.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief reiterates the aim of fusing more public services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-reitera-objectivo-de-fundir-mais-servicos-publicos/</link><description>The government “is orderly to rationalize the organic structures of public administration and the functions of various public services”. The Chief Executive asked all the tutelage to merge public services with the same functions and optimize the personnel structure
 
The merger of more services and the control of workers' quotas in public bodies are two of the government's objectives, reiterated the chief executive at the second work meeting of the Public Administration Reform Leadership Group. Sam Hou Fai stressed that the project of renovation and optimization of public administration must be “pragmatic” and “respond reasonably to the real needs of Macao's economic and social development”.
"As for the organic structure, it is necessary to define criteria for the maximum limit of the dimension of the structure, to review the distribution of functions and merge public services with related functions. Regarding the management and control of the number of workers' quotas, optimization should be done through, namely, standardization of functional areas, study of a career access mechanism and establishing basic criteria of staff affectation of all levels," He explained, according to a note from the Social Communication Office.
According to said, the government "is orderly to rationalize the organic structures of public administration and the functions of various public services, proactively promoting the detailed management of human resources and public resources."
In addition to being discussed the distribution of functions of public services, the simplification of organic structures, the management and control of the number of workers' quotas, the regimes related to personnel mobility and professional counterplane, topics such as computer infrastructure of public services were also addressed.
Sam Hou Fai thus asked all the tutelage to achieve the scheduled work, "in order to effectively increase the effectiveness of the functioning of the public administration." Administration and Public Function (SAFP) services must also, according to the guidelines defined by the leadership group, “reinforce collaboration with the compliance with the audit”, gradually promoting the simplification of the structure of public services and the optimization of the personnel structure, “taking into account the reality of each public service”.
Based on the principle of centralized management, the mechanism of hiring and management of public services will be optimized, ensuring the rational use of public resources ”. The chief executive also ordered that, under the premise of not affecting daily operation, all public services should gradually improve the computer system, to further increase the risk prevention capacity.
All five secretaries attended the meeting.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>STD ponders introduce halal certification in mashed restaurants</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dst-pondera-introduzir-certificacao-halal-em-restaurantes-da-raem/</link><description>Tourism services have been in discussions with different Hong Kong Muslim Associations to introduce a halal certification in Macau, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes revealed in response to a written interpellation of Ho Ion Sang
 
Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes stated that the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) is in conversations with Hong Kong Muslim Associations, about the introduction of Halal certification in the MSAR. In a response to a written interpellation presented by Deputy Ho Ion Sang, the STD director states that the body intends to “support restoration and drink operators in Macao in the application and obtaining” of the approval.
In late June, Ho Ion Sang questioned the government about the plans to attract and "improve the experience of Muslim visitors." At the time, the deputy urged the authorities to “promote and support more restoration companies” to “increase the amount and types of halal food products” and to provide prayer facilities in various public spaces in the city, as well as accommodation services aligned with Muslim religious norms.
In turn, the STD director stated that the services have “appreciated and authorized, under the law, the requests for licensing of hotel industry and restoration establishments, and there is no restrictions on the installation of a prayer room and the equipment that satisfies the Halal standards”.
Ho Ion Sang added that the government should also "elaborate plans for the organization of more festive activities and themed itineraries suitable for Muslims." The deputy considers that “cooperation between the respective sectors and the local Islamic community” should also be reinforced, taking advantage of mosques, resorts and historical constructions such as Macao's World Heritage, among others.
STD official explained that “the building of the Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services, Casa Moosa, the Calçada do Gaio Building No. 6 and the building at Rua de Silva Mendes nº 1” were classified as “immovable heritage” because they had “elements of Islamic culture”. He also stressed the support that the Cultural Institute has given to different associations, in the organization of festivities such as the “Exhibition on the Culture and Heritage of the Six Macao Religions” and the “Concert of Appreciation of Music of the Six Macao Religions”.
Finally, Ho Ion Sang asked if STD was considering creating “a specific column for Muslim friendly tourism” on the tourist services website. Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes recalled that STD has already launched the “Halal Travel Guide”, having added a part of “Halal food” to the “Gastronomy” section of the MSAR Tourism Promotion site, with information about certified restaurants. The official also said that, in the future, "more thematic pages will be launched on Muslim tourism."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MSAR team discovers new species of bacteria in Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/equipa-ligada-a-raem-descobre-novas-especies-de-bacterias-em-portugal/</link><description>A team of academics, led by André Antunes, acting director of the Institute of Science and Environment of the University of São José (USJ), recently made a publication on the isolation and characterization of new bacteria species from samples collected in Rio Maior Saline, Portugal. The article was published in the “International Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology”, the Reference Journal for the Publication of New Microbial Genreos and the Official Publication of the International Procaryotes Systemics Committee and the Applied Bacteriology and Microbiology Division of the International Union of Microbiology Societies. The team also included other Macao researchers, namely Macao University of Science and Technology, Marta Filipa Simões, from Portugal (University of Minho; Ligia Rodrigues) and from Spain (University of Seville; Rafael de La Haba). The publication resulted in the establishment of the new "Fodinibius alkaliphilus" species and also includes the reclassification of a species previously known in the same genre (such as "Fodinibius salipaludis"). “This publication highlights the strengths of Macao in articulation with partners of Portuguese and Spanish -speaking countries and their growing position in the domains of biodiversity and biotechnology,” says USJ in a statement. According to the note, other samples from these places are being investigated and in the coming months new publications will be published by describing other new species.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>FOAM violated duties in the scope of financial support in health</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/faom-violou-deveres-ambito-de-apoios-financeiros-na-saude/</link><description>The Federation of Macao Workers Associations (Faom) has violated the duties of the beneficiaries of financial support granted by health services (SSM), reveals information on the protection of social matters and culture published on the public dissemination platform for public financial support information. According to the data, they are channeled to the recovery center of the General Association of Macao Workers. As for the specific violation situation, it is the association is accused of “not planning and organizing, prudently and reasonably, canceled activities or projects”. As a result, health services have decided to “partially cancel the financial support granted and to demand from the beneficiaries the refund of their respective financial support funds”. The situation happened last year. Looking at the list of support granted, it can be observed that the Faom Recovery Center, which provides rehabilitation nursing services, had to restore 4,770 patacas that had been attributed to it for the month of April, under the financial support plan to provide community health care services. Over the past year, Faom received a total amount of over 74 million Patacas under health supports, representing 10% of the total, more than 752.7 million patacas. From the money he received, he had to repay 4,770 patacas for violation of duties.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2450/</link><description>Autopsy request to the driver of deadly accident
The Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) will ask for an autopsy examination to the body of the young driver who was driving in the rugged vehicle on Monday and which caused three deaths. The objective, the authorities explained, is to realize if the case involved driving under the influence of alcohol. According to the CPSP, through the cameras it was possible to realize that the seven people who followed the vehicle entered a bar and bought alcohol. Alcohol consumption has already been confirmed in other injured. The three survivors remain in critical condition. The case has already been referred to the prosecutor. Remember that one of the deadly victims was soccer player Leon Ng Lai Teng.
 
PJ Alerts to Burla after losses of 28 million
The Judicial Police (PJ) launched “strong appeals” to the population, asking for caution with the advertising of investments in social networks. The warning came after last month, PJ received complaints from at least 18 people who claimed to have been deceived. The victims registered losses greater than 27.89 million patacas. PJ explained that in these cases the burns begin by establishing friendship or dating relationships, with the purpose of instigating victims to invest in valuable or cryptocurrency actions, metals. In this sense, the authorities asked for the resolution of citizens. However, in another case, a young woman from Macao suffered damage of about 1.14 million patacas, following being circumvented by a fake civil servant who was passed by police from the interior of China.
 
GROUND TWO SUPPLIES OF PREGNANT SUPPLIES
Two lots of pregnant supplement “PRENATAL VITAMIN DHA Softgels”, produced by “Earth’s Creation Usa”, were collected, the Institute for Supervision and Pharmaceutical Administration (Isaf) said. This is because "black spots were discovered in the capsules." "Taking as a preventive measure, the importer concerned has decided to voluntarily collect the affected lots of the drug that were imported to Macau," added the Isaf. The affected lots of the drug “were supplied” to the Conde de São Januário hospital center, health centers, polyclinics and community pharmacies, and these places suspended use and sale.
 
Launched Olympic medals for disabled
Tongxinnuan's “Tongxinnuan” medals of the special Olympic Games for the disabled were launched. According to the preparatory office for the organization of the National Games in Macao, the medal means "affective hearts", being associated with the medal of the 15th edition of the National Games, with the idea of "Tongxin". "It also demonstrates the spirit and willingness of joint collaboration between athletes, coaches, volunteers and all social sectors to achieve excellent results, as well as the idea of integration of all," he adds.</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Planned inclusive model for all day care centers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/planeado-modelo-inclusivo-para-todas-creches/</link><description>The Institute of Social Action plans to create a “operational model” of support and monitoring of children with special needs, so that it will be implemented in all day care centers in the territory, gradually. There are currently three kindergartens with inclusive services, which have already served 70 children with development difficulties
 
Catarina Pereira
 
By addressing inclusive day care centers, the president of the Institute of Social Action (IAS) revealed that the body plans to “establish an operational model of support and monitoring of children with developmental difficulties for day care centers, with a view to implementing it progressively on all Macao day care centers”. However, Hon Wai was no use details about the plan.
The information arises in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U, who had questioned whether the “day care center development plan for the years 2026 to 2030” would be reinforced inclusive services to support needy families.
On the other hand, law chan u asked how many day care centers provide inclusive services to children with slight special needs and what is the point of situation about this support. In this context, the president of IAS indicated that there are currently in Macau three subsidized day care centers who provide inclusive services, having already served 70 children with development difficulties.
“These services allow children with developmental difficulties to receive day care cautions together with other children of the same age, promoting their happy growth and, at the same time, helping to alleviate parents' pressure on their children's care,” explains Hon Wai.
Regarding the “day care center development plan for the years 2026 to 2030,” he says he aims to “provide adequate child care for families”, “support parents in the participation of child care and education” and “establish a quality day care management system”, in order to “further improve day care care services, relieving pressure on family care and encouraging young people to have children”.
Currently, IAS is “summarizing the experience” of implementation of the plan that began in 2023 and ending this year, “presenting to the sector the conceptions of the next phase of the plan and collecting opinions, with the aim of finalizing the plan during the year 2025”, read.
In written interplies, law chan u also wanted to know how authorities will reinforce personnel formation and resource allocation in this area. At this point, Hon Wai states that, since 2023, the body he directs has been training both to professionals and parents of children. "By the end of 2024, about 220 day care professionals and 250 parents completed the training," he said, adding that during this year they will continue to allocate resources to make approximately 500 training vacancies.
"In the future, training and support actions will be developed according to the needs, aiming at the continuous improvement of the day care center service system," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-08-07 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Students from Nagasaki and Hiroshima play the role of “messengers for peace”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/alunos-de-nagasaki-hiroshima-assumem-papel-de-mensageiros-pela-paz/</link><description>Hiroshima and Nagasaki secondary students participate annually in the initiative “Messengers for Peace”, which aims to preserve and disseminate the testimony of the survivors of the atomic bomb around the world. The initiative has already collected more than 2.5 million signatures to request the abolition of nuclear weapons.
"Our actions can be small, but not insignificant" is the motto of this movement, which began in Nagasaki in 1998 and has since been present at the United Nations headquarters, conferences on disarmament and non -nuclear proliferation and meetings with world leaders.
This is one of many initiatives launched by the only cities in history to be attacked with an atomic weapon, seeking to keep alive the 'Hibakusha' experience. It assumes special relevance in the 80th anniversary of the attacks and as the number of bombing survivors decreases.
“We are the last generation who has heard the story of the 'Hibakusha' firsthand. We need to spread this message; for me, it is a responsibility we have to the world,” said Ye Seoji, student at Nichidai Secondary School in Nagasaki, at a press event in June.
“Many of my friends do not follow the news and believe that nuclear weapons are a thing of the past. But I am very concerned about the fact that there are more and more weapons in the world,” says Yuka Ohara of Nichidai Secondary School in Nagasaki, quoted by EFE agency.
Both are among students aged between 15 and 18 years who are annually designated as “peace messengers” through a public selection process. They perform their activities in Japan and abroad, with contributions from local governments and private donations.
Ohara decided to participate in this program after growing up listening to stories of her grandparents' bomb horrors, survivors of nuclear attacks. “Soon, it will not be possible to hear your experiences,” he laments.
After Hiroshima signed on Wednesday the 80th anniversary of atomic bombing, Nagasaki will also mark the ephemeris tomorrow. According to the latest official data, the remaining number of 'Hibakusha' descended to 99,130, falling below 100,000 for the first time. Its average ages is 86.13 years.
“It may seem strange, but to me these activities are my hobby, such as playing basebol or video games are for my friends. I'm proud of what I do,” confesses Kenji Takada, another student of Nagasaki participating in the program.
“New generations need to learn the lessons of bombing so that they never happen again,” says Takada, also admitting to "fear" of the possibility of a country resorting to atomic weapons in one of the current global conflicts.
In 2001, 14 “Messengers for Peace” began collecting signatures in favor of the abolition of nuclear weapons on the streets of Japan, with the aim of gathering 10,000 signatures. In this first year, they collected 28,000 signatures and, given their success, decided to continue the campaign, which now has 2,626,714 signatures 24 years later.
Every year, students participating in the program travel to the United Nations headquarters in Geneva to present their signatures, which are recognized by the international organization for their contribution to global sensitization on nuclear weapons.
More than two thousand young Japanese have been involved in this initiative since their creation, and travel to other countries around the world to participate in international conferences, charity events and meet other students. Its actions offer some hope for the future, in the midst of a renewed global rearmament, with growing tensions and open confrontations in different regions of the world, and even some leaders openly threatening to use atomic weapons.
 
Peace Museums attracted record of visitors after the Nobel Prize
The Peace Museums of Hiroshima and Nagasaki received about three million visitors in 2024, a record number after the atomic bomb survivors won the Nobel Peace Prize in 2024 and while the country has a tourism growth.
Only the Hiroshima Peace Memorial Museum received more than two million people in the Japanese fiscal year of 2024 (from April this year to February 2025), a record number. Last March, it has also reached the mark of 80 million visitors since its inauguration.
"Due to the devaluation of the yen, an environment has developed that facilitates foreigners coming to Japan," Toshihiro Toya, the agency's deputy director, told EFE during a press trip organized in July by the Japan Foreign Press Center.
Toya hopes that those who travel to Japan will visit not only large cities, such as Tokyo, Kyoto and Osaka, but also Hiroshima, “a city that boasts two world heritage: the atomic bomb dome and the Itsukushima Sanctuary (on Miyajima Island)”.
Japan welcomed 21.51 million visitors in the first six months of 2025, a new record. To maintain this trend, it could reach 40 million by the end of this year, compared to 36 million of 2024.
Toshihiro Toya believes that the trend has also increased between those “who want to learn about peace” and Hiroshima's atomic bomb.
Located next to Marco Zero, where the bomb was launched in the Japanese Western city center, the Hiroshima Memorial Museum, inaugurated in 1955, exhibits belongings of the victims, photographs of the consequences of radiation, destroying the time and a reproduction of the device used, ‘Little Boy’, among other artifacts and documents. The center seeks to convey the horrors of nuclear weapons in the first city to be the target of an atomic bomb.
The leaders of the so -called seven group (G7, made up of Germany, Canada, USA, France, Italy, Japan and the United Kingdom) visited the museum during their stay in the city's summit in 2023, as well as Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky, who attended this meeting. The visit of the leaders also had an attraction effect, resulting in an increase in the number of monthly visitors to the center.
The number of visitors to the Nagasaki Atomic Bomb Museum in the 2024 fiscal year exceeded 800,000 for the first time in more than two decades, an increase of 6.9% over the previous year and the first time this number has been reached since 2001.
The museum registered its largest number of visitors in the 1996 fiscal year, when it was inaugurated, with approximately 1,135,000 people. Since the 2002 fiscal year, the annual number has been consistently kept between 650,000 and 750,000 visitors, although it has dropped dramatically to approximately 230,000 by 2020 due to the pandemic.
The Municipal Peace Promotion Division points to the increase in cruise ships in Nagasaki as one of the factors behind the increase.
"The current tense situation in the world and the attribution of the Nobel Peace Prize may have increased global interest in nuclear weapons," admitted an area authority in statements to EFE.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-08 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>