<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>EPM starts classes with an increase of almost 5% in the number of students</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/epm-inicia-aulas-aumento-de-quase-5-numero-de-alunos/</link><description>New spaces and rules that prohibit the use of mobile phones - these were some of the news on the first day of return to class at the Portuguese School of Macau. The canteen, located just at the entrance of the facilities, gives a more modern image and is the most notorious change resulting from the works. In this new school year, the educational institution will have 810 students, plus 5% in annual terms. For now, there will only be missing an English teacher. According to the director, Acácio de Brito, "only the DSEDJ authorization is missing, but this should be resolved soon." In addition, according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, psychology and guidance services will suffer “some restructuring”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
With the improvement works of the facilities completed and ready to show the Portuguese Prime Minister, Luís Montenegro, who visits the educational establishment today another school year at the Portuguese School of Macao (EPM), on a first day only for the reception of students by the holder teachers and the class directors. Today it will be more seriously, with the beginning of classes themselves.
For the new school year, students and teachers will soon have better restoration conditions, as the new space, which is now just at the entrance of the facilities, is large, modern, in “Open Space” style and integrates a bar. In addition, the recreation area has been increased and there is to register the renewal of the resorts with the Sports Pavilion, with more showers for both sexes, now in a total of 15 in each sector. The music room was also remodeled, as well as the teacher room diverted elsewhere.
These improvements will be shown to Luís Montenegro and Foreign Minister Paulo Rangel, who visit the school this morning.
For 2025/2026, the EPM is maintained the growth tendency of the number of students in recent years, now 37, more than the previous school year. There is, therefore, an increase within 5% in the number of enrollments.
With regard to classes, and according to data provided by the director of the school, there is no change, remaining 39 in total, distributed by 15 in the first cycle, nine in the second, 10 in the third and six in the secondary.
The reception to the students was made between 9:30 am and 1:00 pm, with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao witnessing the usual Aishaphama, both students and parents, with them to queue to address issues related to the students.
One of the parents heard by this newspaper said he hoped the school “can maintain the quality of education”, however, congratulations on the remodeling of some facilities. "They are frankly better," he said.
On the issue of teachers, he said that "last year there was a lack of teachers, but this year apparently is resolved." On the other hand, he stressed that “a fixed school calendar”, believing that “everything can go well, that there is a good start of the school year, to maintain the quality of education and that the school has more representativeness in Macao”.
Another of the parents who was waiting for a time to deal with matters at the Secretariat expressed votes that "students are happy and learn a lot." Pedro Santos Silva and his wife of Chinese ethnicity, who have been in the territory for seven years, have their daughter to study at EPM since the primary. "She loves this school and like her mother - who speaks Mandarin to her, while I talk in Portuguese - she did training in Portugal, we wanted our daughter to come here, because it is the ideal to perfect the Portuguese language," he said.
Meanwhile, the hundreds of students enrolled for this year were distributed throughout the facilities, and may be seen, at the entrance, some conviviality between old colleagues and friends, who proved after another long vacation period. And also those who first knew each other for the first time, that is, the little ones, 5 or 6 years old, who left the kindergarten to attend the EPM for the first time.
In the case of primary education, all classes are in a two -story block, separated from the remaining cycles, which are in a different wing.
Our newspaper was one of the small rooms of the little ones and listened to Professor Lia Dalte: "Being with these classes is a challenge that has their charm and that we hug with all the pleasure, because it's all new, from children to families." The teacher hopes that "above all Portuguese language and culture prevail, as is the Chinese and Macaense, making the possible to incorporate and articulate these cultures."
Going down to the outdoor main courtyard, there were many of the older students to adapt to a new life-free life, following the decision of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) to prohibit the use of telephone appliances within schools.
As all students have to leave smartphones in the cliffs at the school entrance, the conviviality environment was completely different. Football and games, as well as running among the little ones now replace the addiction that has entered the young people. At least in schools this changes radically with this measure, which seems to gather consensus, or at least acceptance by students.
All students, from the second cycle, heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau recognize that the decision is positive. "We can do more things together, which is important," said one of them. "It's a little strange to be at school without using mobile phones in the break, but this will favor our conviviality," said another. "I think not everyone accepts this measure, because it has advantages and disadvantages, but the essential thing is that we can live more, this is the reality," said another student. “From now on I will play soccer so as not to think about the mobile phone,” said one more.
 
English teacher awaits DSEDJ authorization
Regarding the start of the school year, it is known that almost all subjects have attributed teachers, even though there is an English teacher, with special license, who has not yet seen authorized by DSDEJ their inclusion on the list of 86 teachers that the school houses. "We hope this will be resolved quickly," Acácio de Brito told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, stressing that, otherwise, "there was a positive response to all special licenses requested."
In prior to another academic year, the EPM official expects “everything to run for the best”. Regarding school results, he points out that "if we want to compare it with last year, we had good results, when it has been a practice in the EPM, measured by internal assessment, which the school classifies, and external, which is caused by exams."
The director notes that "almost totality entered the first option, and only one student did not have the possibility of completing secondary education and another did not enter the first phase, but I think it will enter the second." On the other hand, he stresses, “we had good results in a discipline that I think is important too, that it is Portuguese, and therefore we are on the good way”.
Regarding the new year, the official says that the school wants to "develop areas that are more marginal, namely the appreciation, and so we have the new facilities to support the most needy, namely who have some special education situations."
In addition, it reinforces, “we will also serve in pedagogical terms to the valuation of that program we started last year, in the sense that all students until the 4th grade will benefit from one hour per day of Portuguese, so that they reach 5th grade and are able to solve problems”.
"Often students have difficulties, but if we do a strategic analysis of these difficulties we find that the problem is mainly in communication, that is, the non -dominance of language often makes a good result impossible for some disciplines," he says, stressing that "this work is being done and there is a process of continuity."
Acácio de Brito also talks about “reinforcement in some structures that have to do with the mastery of Portuguese and also some processes that will still be subject to some restructuring”, specifically psychology and guidance services. "At this time there is a new responsible for this service and soon we will launch a contest to hire a psychologist," he said.
About Montenegro's visit, Acácio de Brito says that "it is always good," adding that the head of the Portuguese government "will have the opportunity to see, because it will be accompanied by the Minister of Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel, who was here a few months ago, significant improvements in school." The Prime Minister will also find that the EPM "will always be a lighthouse space of a certain sense of portugality, being a school in China, but also cultivating the values ​​of culture and Portuguese language."</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China wants to reinforce “strategic” communication with Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/china-quer-reforcar-comunicacao-estrategica-portugal/</link><description>Prime Minister Luís Montenegro (D) during the meeting with the President of the Popular Republic of China, XI Jinping (E), which took place at the Great Palace of the People, in Beijing, China, September 9, 2025. António Cotrim/Lusa



China and Portugal are countries with a “deep historical heritage” that share “a spirit of openness, inclusion, initiative and autonomy,” said Chinese president in Beijing, in a meeting with the Portuguese Prime Minister, reiterating that the two nations resolved “the issue of Macao through friendly negotiations”. In recent years, cooperation in various areas has achieved “important results”, establishing “a model of mutual respect and reciprocal gains between countries with different social systems and different national realities,” said Xi Jinping, quoted by the Xinhua agency.
Noting that this year is the 20th anniversary of the establishment of the comprehensive China-Portugal strategic partnership, Xi assured that “China is willing to reinforce strategic communication with Portugal, to guide bilateral relations in the right direction, to make good relationships even better and to contribute even more to the prosperity and progress of both countries and the world through solidarity and cooperation”.
The Chinese leader maintained that the two countries should “continue traditional friendship, confidence and mutual support”, “deepen the alignment of development strategies”, “expand practical cooperation” in the domains of innovation, environment, oceans and pharmaceutical sector, among others, and stimulate “cultural, educational, tourist and scientific exchanges”. At the same time, he stressed the importance of “taking advantage of the unique role of Macau as a bridge and fully using mechanisms such as the Economic and Commercial Cooperation Forum between China and Portuguese -speaking countries, to achieve a higher level of mutual benefits”.
"The more turbulent and interconnected the international panorama becomes, the greater the need for China and Europe to reinforce communication, reinforce mutual trust and deepen cooperation," he said, appealing to Portugal to work with Beijing for sustainable, stable and healthy development of European China-Union relations.
In this context, he insisted, China is available to "strengthen multilateral cooperation with Portugal, to truly practice multilateralism, safeguard the UN authority, defend the free trade system, and promote the construction of a fairer and more reasonable global governance system."
 
Compliments to Guterres, Durão and Costa
According to the Lusa agency, at the beginning of the meeting at the Great Palace of the People, Xi stated that “Portugal is a good friend of China”, and praised the international role of previous prime ministers António Guterres, Durão Barroso and António Costa.
Xi began by saying that it is "a pleasure" to know the prime minister. “Welcome on the visit to China. I remember that in 2018 I made a state visit to Portugal, which left me a beautiful impression, and deep,” he said, taking the opportunity to ask Montenegro to transmit “sincere greetings” to the head of state, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa.
“Portugal plays an important and unique role on the international stage,” he said, highlighting that he has “good relations” with UN Secretary-General António Guterres, European Council President António Costa and former president of the European Commission Durão Barroso.
"Portugal was also the first country in Western Europe to sign with China cooperation acts under the" One Rota, a Route "initiative, and the first country in the euro zone that issued titles" in Chinese currency, he said.
In turn, Montenegro stressed that, in the international context, Portugal and China have maintained "on many occasions a base of cooperation and sharing of values." "China has a key role in the global and international context, a permanent member of the United Nations Security Council and we expect your contribution to build bridges between peoples, bring some of those who are in conflict, promote peace, promote multilateralism, promote respect for human rights," he said.
Montenegro began by mentioning that “it is very tasteful” that he makes this official visit to China and transmitted to Xi the greetings of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa.
The prime minister expressed agreement with Xi's words about how the transition from the Macao de Portugal administration to China in 1999 took place. “We had in the transition from Macau a good expression of the way we were able to converge and managed to ensure the cultural identity and the relationship between the special administrative region of Macau, Portugal and China,” he said.
 
Ukraine motivates Portuguese appeal
On the other hand, Montenegro took the opportunity to tell Xi that he has his close relationship with Russia so that it is possible to “build just and lasting peace” in Ukraine. Later, on a visit to the forbidden city, he was confident that this Ukraine appeal will not be ignored.
"I believe that the appeal, coming from a friendly country, coming from a European Union country, coming from a country, such as Mr. President XI Jinping also emphasized, who has an identity of values ​​and route, will not fall into a rotor bag," he said.
Saying not being able to answer for the Chinese president, Montenegro has manifested convinced that Portugal has done what is required for this conflict. "My conviction is that, to our dimension and without any kind of pretentiousness, we do what is required to a nation with history and the international respectability that Portugal has. We are builders of bridges, we are protagonists of the approach between peoples, we are advocates of peace, defenders of values, respect for people's rights," he said.
Montenegro considered that, at the meeting with Xi, it was limited to “being frank, loyal and direct in the appeal” so that China's ability to influence can be developed and “bring practical results” to Ukraine.
"We have an active diplomacy that gains credit so that I can speak on behalf of the country, appealing to this sense of collective responsibility on a global scale," he said, emphasizing that the country has a Portuguese who is the United Nations Secretary-General, another who is president of the European Council and another that was 10 years chairman of the European Commission.
The prime minister stated that Portugal "maintains an open dialogue" with China, which he classified as "partner" in many domains. "I have no problem saying this, while I guarantee Portugal and our fellow citizens that we are a country with a position and intervention within the European Union, our NATO partners, and today also within the GOOD WILL coalition that seeks to ensure just and lasting peace in Ukraine," he said.
Montenegro argued that “regardless of many differences” that Portugal has with “some perspectives of China”, this country “and its president have affirmed values ​​such as multilateralism, values ​​such as respect for international law”. "With this also meaning respect for human rights, respect for the access of all citizens to levels of fulfillment, development, which are in line with the values ​​we advocate in Portugal," he said.
Montenegro's agenda in Beijing began in the morning with the deposition of a wreath in the monument to the heroes of the people, in Tiananmen Square, accompanied by the wife and Paulo Rangel, Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Manuel Castro Almeida, Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion, and Graça Carvalho, Minister of Environment and Energy. In addition to the meeting with XI, Montenegro first met with the President of the National Popular Assembly of China, Zhao Leji.
After visiting the forbidden city, he went to a meeting with Chinese counterpart, I read Qiang before heading to Macao. On Thursday and Friday, will make an official visit to Japan, with tickets for Tokyo and Osaka.
 
Montenegro thanks Chinese support during the financial crisis
Luís Montenegro thanked Xi Jinping for China's support to Portugal during the financial crisis. "At the level of our bilateral economic cooperation, it is my duty to tell you that we do not forget, on the contrary, we have very well present and respect the bet that China has developed in the Portuguese economy, in one of the most critical moments of our country, when the financial crisis," said the Portuguese prime minister at the beginning of the Chinese president. As had been highlighted moments earlier by Xi, Montenegro also considered that in recent years the two countries have reinforced ties "in various sectors of the economy, from energy to bank, from health to water supply." "Our conviction is that we can continue to follow this path on the basis of trust," he said.
 
Portugal “is a reliable and confident country” for investments
The Portuguese Prime Minister said that, in his visits to China and Japan, he wants to bring the message that Portugal “is a reliable and confident country” for economic investments. Asked if you will be able to get the message to the potential Chinese investors although the program does not include an economic seminar -as happened at the previous visits of the then Prime Minister António Costa, in 2016, or President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, in 2019 -Montenegro rejected this perspective. “I believe that the statement that this program is quite short is only referring to the temporal dimension, because from the point of view of content, this program is vast,” he countered, in statements to journalists, highlighting the importance of direct contacts with Chinese leaders. He also pointed out that Portugal is already “enjoying several investments that originate in China and have been levers for the transformation and economic development of Portugal”. "It is our intention to contribute to our coming here so that we can also open doors to which more Portuguese companies can find in the Chinese market the destination of their products and, therefore, also increase our export share for this geography," he said.
 
Jtm with Lusa and Xinhua</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“We will fight for the rise of the birth allowance”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lutaremos-pela-subida-subsidio-de-nascimento/</link><description>List number 6 highlights the objective that policies that advocate continue continuity. In an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the Good Lar Alliance promises to “strengthen, with full force, the Macao's birth and family support system”, concretely so that the birth allowance will increase to 20,000 patacas. Also defends more benefits to consumption
 
What reasons led to the covenant list of good home to apply for the Legislative Assembly?
- List number 6 - Good Home Alliance (GLA) is led by the General Association of Women and constituted by the educational, industrial and commercial, youth, professional and social services sectors. Assuming the idea of ​​candidacy centered on “fighting for the rights and interests of women and children, and the happiness of families, building platforms for young people and creating a future for Macao,” our list competed for two editions of legislative elections and got direct suffrage seats.
Over the course of eight years of course in which our team has participated and discussed policies, as well as pronounced for the people, ABL always remembers fulfilling the promises left in the candidacy for the elections. We have already achieved the realization of the “childhood assistance allowance” in the monthly value of 1,500 patacas, the continuous increase in birth allowance to 6,500, the launch of the “reimbursement program in the treatment of medically assisted procreation”, the realization of the “conciliation regime for the causes of family”, the regular implementation of the “subsidy for caregivers”, the optimization of leisure zones and installations Children's fun in various zones, among other policies and beneficial measures for residents in general and support for family development.
However, the low rate of birth and population aging remains. In addition, under the impact of the complex internal and external economic environment, among other factors, the sustainable development of society faces challenges. ABL will strive to realize the perspectives and desires of residents for a better life. Our political program continues to focus on the rights and interests of women, children and families, the benefits for the elderly and needy groups, and the effective increase in the sense of happiness, safety and gain of residents. At the same time, it focuses on boosting the government to make efforts in many ways to improve employment and business environment in community neighborhoods, raise the effectiveness of governance and improve urban construction, to build a good home for residents, that is prosperous, harmonious, happy, dynamic and healthy.
 
- How is this candidacy from the rest?
- GLA values ​​diversity, having brought together a team of participation and discussion of policies composed of representatives of various sectors. Our candidates are from different professional areas, have already held several professions, have participated in society for a long time and do practical things for the people. On the other hand, the list includes members of various MSAR advisory bodies, with vast professional, social and political experience, which provides the team a more solid base for political participation, and allows our team to transmit, even more scientific and rationally, social conditions and public opinion, as well as further residents.
ABL is a young and dynamic team, having long valued the formation of young political and social services. We have actively formed young cadres for the principle of “Macao governed by patriots”, which reflects our idea of ​​“building platforms for young people”. The average age of the team is about 39 years and we have several candidates born in the 1990s, with the younger candidate only 26 years old. This demonstrates a team full of dynamics.
ABL does practical things for the people, serves the needs of residents, humbly auscultate public opinion and actively convey the voice of the people. For a long time, we have worked deeply in the community through different platforms. Regularly adopting inquiries, studies and community activities, the team knows the current situation of society and what residents think, using this information as an important basis for making suggestions to the government. For example, when we successfully fight for maternity leave, creation of paternity leave and childhood assistance allowance, and housing policy in five scales, we always adopted, first, questionnaires, on -site visits, among other measures, to collect opinions, in order to transform public opinion into viable and viable and viable policies. This shows our professional and pragmatic attitude, oriented to the people with the heart, and to serve society.
 
- What are the priority problems and what solutions do they propose to solve them?
- The family is the core of society. ABL attributes importance to family development, presenting good solutions to low birth rates and population aging. We will fight for the rise in the birth allowance to 20 thousand patacas, extension of the childhood assistance allowance for children aged six, extension of maternity leave to 90 days, increased paternity leave to 10 days, as well as creation of children's care and prenatal care. We expect, through “laws and subsidies working simultaneously, and the social costs to be supported together”, reinforce, with all the strength, the system of support for birth and family.
Regarding the elderly and vulnerable groups, we advocate the continuous increase in the value of the pension for the elderly, the subsidy for the elderly, the disability pension and the disability subsidies and for caregivers. In addition, we advocate the increase of resources for early treatment and special education services, and the rapid review of the “regular social security adjustment mechanism” so that social benefits meet the real economic environment more and fully ensure the quality of life of the elderly and needy groups.
To boost the professional rise of young people, we will try to stimulate the accreditation exams of qualified frames to 10,000 patacas. In addition, we will work to provide diverse training on entrepreneurship, in order to take advantage of businesses started by young people to create more jobs for young people. We will boost beneficial housing policies oriented to young families and the acceleration of the realization of the economic housing exchange regime, to create, with full force, a system of support for “studies, employment, entrepreneurship, professional career and home acquisition” of young people.
ABL knows that “guaranteeing the economy” means “ensuring employment” and “ensuring the well-being of the population”, and good economic development is support for social benefits. Given the lack of clarity in the community economic environment, we will continue to fight for the launch and reinforcement of various consumer benefit measures, to reduce residents' living costs and give “running water” to small and medium enterprises. At the same time, we will boost the accelerated creation of “Community Community Areas with its own characteristics”, development of embellishing and revitalization work, change to various commercial regulations, and simplification of the licensing process, to facilitate the investment of more capital and resources for the development of the community economy. Moreover, in order to promote the healthy development of the labor market, we will boost the widening of professions and the increase in the number of employment vacancies within the “specific employment plan + training”. At the same time, by improving the non-resident workers management regime, and improving the policies to support unemployed residents, looking for employment and changing employment, we will be fully committed to ensuring employment, stabilizing the economy and contemplating the well-being of the population.
 
- What are the expectations in terms of elections? How many seats do you expect to win at the Legislative Assembly?
- GLA is convinced that it will be struggling to participate and discuss policies. Each vote is very important, so our team will do as much as possible to obtain the recognition and support of voters, safeguard the voice of GLA in the hemiciclo, continue to serve residents and fully strive to build society, so that policies advocated by GLA can gain continuity. Let's build a good home and a good future together!
 
JTM and Electoral Act
In accordance with the electoral law, the Jornal Tribuna de Macao continues to cover the campaign for legislative elections on September 14. Like previous years, we will adopt a model that aims to inform our readers about the ideas defended by the various candidacies, under the premise of granting the same journalistic treatment to all competing lists in direct suffrage. Without prejudice to any general reports about the elections, never focused on specific lists, we present today the last of the interviews with the different candidacy teams, which were entitled to a page until the campaign is closed, naturally without any charges for the lists, as a way to provide a public interest service to readers.
In this sense, we sent a fixed set of questions to all applications, whose answers have been published in the last days, in increasing order of the numbering of the lists in the voting newsletters.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>One hundred invests in the decarbonization of the electrical network</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cem-investe-na-descarbonizacao-da-rede-electrica/</link><description>The Macao Electricity Company appears to invest a total of 839 million Patacas this year, about a quarter less than the value actually invested in 2024. On the other hand, it continues to make efforts to decade the electricity grid network
 
Pedro Milheirão
For 2025, the Macao Electricity Company (CEM) has budget 839 million in investment, minus 24.35% (270 million) of what the company effectively invested last year (about 1.11 billion), according to the CEM annual report. The data consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao indicate a decreasing trend, if we consider that 1.27 billion patacas were invested in 2023. This year, investments for the transport network represent about 62.57% (525 million patacas) of total expenses, and investments related to energy production constitute 16% (134 million).
The construction and optimization of the network includes the project of the Tai On Substation, in the new urban area A, which will be completed and placed on this year. The substation “will provide energy to public housing, government buildings and public facilities in the zone, as well as provide energy to the dedicated 22kV network for the macao light meter system”, predicts the company.
CEM also plans to build an integrated storage and loading system of solar energy in the Tai Substation, in order to “feed the substation and store energy during periods of solar production peak, reducing network energy consumption by substation and contributing to the reduction of carbon emissions”.
In this sense, “fixed photovoltaic devices will also be installed on roofs and pavilions”.
The concessionaire also foresees to expand the East Parking Park of the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge Border, “to meet the loading needs of transfronist electric vehicles”. “To meet the future growth of demand, the loading infrastructure in this parking lot is prepared to expand to accommodate up to 300 loading spaces,” explains the concessionaire. It also plans to develop the use of fiber optic among public parking parks “to reinforce data transmission between loading stations”.
In addition, “to improve the level of intelligence of the electricity grid, CEM has launched an investigation project on the Macao Electric Network Development Plan in the context of carbonic neutrality. This project focuses on the analysis of the business factors and the long-term vision of the CEM, exploring in depth the needs of updating and transformation of network facilities in the process of decarbonization, digitization and intelligence”.
 
Reached full coverage of smart counters
In 2024, "CEM reached the full coverage of smart counters in Macao, officially launching a new energy management model. The smart accountant system system has successfully collected data from over 280,000 smart counters." "With the full coverage of smart counters throughout the territory of Macao, CEM will continue to use this technology to optimize operational monitoring functions and data collection data from the power supply network."
The hundred predicts that total energy consumption will increase 3.3%to 6,443 GWh this year, also projecting 6,222 GWh. The company also expects this year, “the management of the network's vulnerability will become part of Macao's laws and regulations”.
"Building a smart, green and low-carbon macao is the aspiration of the government and, as the city's only electricity company, we are fully committed to supporting the development of Macao's Baixa-Carbono," said the company, quoted by Macau Business magazine. However, one hundred recognizes that to achieve carbon neutrality, "it is necessary to update and optimize technology throughout the electrical system industry chain."
“Looking to the future, the CEM will closely follow the strategic guidelines of the central government and the Government of Mashes in the construction of a society of reduced carbon footprint and the achievement of 'double carbon' goals,” read the report. "We will fully promote sustainable development, technological innovation and digital transformation, continuing to make efforts to optimize infrastructure, improve service quality and ensure energy supply stability."</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Shaquille O'Neal among NBA legends for event in Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/shaquille-oneal-entre-lendas-da-nba-para-evento-em-macau/</link><description>Ancient American professional basketball players, such as Shaquille O'Neal and Tim Hardaway, will be present at the first edition of “NBA House” in Macau. The interactive event for adherents will take place between October 8 and 12, during which time two NBA preseason games are scheduled, which will face the current teams of Brooklyn Nets and Phoenix Suns

Victor Rebelo
 
Five days of interaction with former players of the world's leading professional basketball league will allow fans of the sport in Macau to participate in the first edition of “NBA House”. The free event, promoted by NBA China, will take place in the venetian, between October 8 and 12, bringing to the past names of the past, such as Shaquille O'Neal, Tim Hardaway Sr, Stephon Marbury, Shawn Marion, Mitch Richmond and Deron Williams.
This is an “immersive basketball experience that celebrates the convergence of game, music, fashion and technology,” according to a National Basketball Association (NBA) statement.
During the activities, clinicals and games of the sport will be organized in real enclosure, including an interactive half court, consisting of “an unprecedented LED basketball source”, which, through a thematic tunnel, “combines NBA elements with sculptural patterns inspired by Chinese classic art in Macao's urban landscape,” says the promotional text.
In addition, a NET -themed photographic cabin will be installed, made up of “Three Infinite Rooms”, where fans can take pictures and buy products from the team. A Suns Tennis Vault will also offer the opportunity to gain tennis. On the other hand, an experience will be made available at the Replay Center NBA, providing fans to “get into the skin” of an NBA referee, as well as an inflatable NBA theme will be intended for children's fun.
In the presentation of the NBA House, NBA Director-General for Asian Continent, Wayne Chang, said the event will be "an immersive celebration of culture and technology involving the current game."
The US Professional Basketball League promotion program moves Macao for the first time, after having passed other stops, such as Brazil, Canada, France, India, Mexico, the United States and the United Kingdom.
These interaction sessions with local fans, whose inscriptions are already open to interested parties, will take place in the same period of the preseason games as Brooklyn Nets and Phoenix Suns teams will play in the territory, with the matches having the venetian arena. The first meeting will take place on October 10th and the second two days later.
The Nets currently feature German Dennis Schröder, the Golden Medal of the World Championship Fiba 2023, the American Cam Johnson, a member of his country's team, and NBA's Australian Ben Simmons. On the suns squad are Kevin Durant, four times Olympic gold medal and NBA champion on two occasions, Devin Booker, also with two gold medals at the NBA Olympic Games and four times Bradley Beal.
The NBA has not played pre-season games in China since 2019, when Daryl Morey, then Director-General of Houston Rockets, demonstrated on social networks support for old protests in Hong Kong. NBA commissioner Adam Silver refused to punish Morey, but Chinese state television CCTV stopped broadcasting NBA games, a hiatus that the US league said it cost $ 400 million in lost recipes.
The last time the territory audiences watched a NBA pre-season challenge was in 2007, with Orlando Magic and the Cleveland Cavaliers, also in that gaming operator, which has a capacity of 14,000 spectators.
The agreement for the NBA return to the MSAR, secured for the next five years, had been signed last December between Sands and the race director, Mark Tatum, and the one referred to at the time that the partnership is “a significant milestone in the continuous global basketball growth”, namely in China, “which has some of the world's most fervent supporters”.
Also according to NBA vice-compensation and operations director Mark Tatum, the Nets and the Suns will present “an exciting mix of established and rising stars,” an initiative that also aims to “involve supporters, aspiring players and the local community in these games and a variety of interactive events, youth development programs and social impact initiatives”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Montenegro wants to “take further” cooperation relationship with Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/montenegro-quer-levar-mais-longe-relacao-de-cooperacao-macau/</link><description>In the short time in Macao, the Prime Minister of Portugal met with the Chief Executive having addressed “various subjects”-one of which the restrictions on the assignment of residence to Portuguese citizens. Luís Montenegro was confident that this “embarrassment” may be overtaken, but it was no use details about what the solution will be. Out of the conversation with the leader of the MSA was the arrest of former Deputy Au Kam San. "It's a subject - this and others - we follow and that we promote with the necessary discretion," he said. The important thing in the context of the visit, Montenegro, was reiterated the “firm purpose” of “taking the relationship of cooperation further”. As for the Portuguese in the territory, it praised the role they play and asked to be the “ambassadors” of the country



















Catarina Pereira
 
She was just a noon and a half when the Portuguese Prime Minister arrived at the consular residence for the reception to the community-they expected him to dozens of people, from handcans, in the face of the heat he was felt. With the room full, “the Portuguese” and “march of volunteers” were heard, then followed a brief speech, in which Luís Montenegro praised the role of the Portuguese in Macau.
“I mean that we attribute special importance to those who are here in the most varied activities, which bring the values ​​of Portugal, transport and preserve Portuguese culture and tradition, being a link between our countries and our peoples, and may be further away from the concrete result of the various areas in which we have come to cooperate. Approach factor, ”said the head of the Portuguese government.
Montenegro then observed that the activity of the Portuguese community in Macau “is very multifaceted”. “Culture of those who like to do well, those who like to do more, those who like to bring their effort to achieve new results, who is always unhappy and who fights every day to overcome and to be able to overcome society,” he continued.
However, the truth is that since August 2023 that Macau has not accepted new requests for residence for Portuguese for the “exercise of specialized technical functions”, allowing only justifications of family reunion or previous connection to the territory. A matter that the part of the part of the part of the part have addressed and was back on the table at the meeting between Luís Montenegro and Sam Hou Fai, confirmed the prime minister in statements to journalists.
Montenegro was, in fact, optimistic about this matter. "I believe things will be referred so that we can have the consecration of a more agile, easier, more expedition regime and therefore that this embarrassment may be overcome, which we know exists," he said.
Since restrictions on residence attribution were imposed, the Portuguese who arrive in the territory remains the issuance of the “Blue Card”, limited authorization to the work bond, without the benefits of residents. The alternative to get BIR is the application for qualified frame capture programs.
"It is a concern that we have regarding the visas of residence of all those who go to this territory with desire to work and to help the institutions can do their work," admitted Luís Montenegro. Asked what type of regime will be adopted, in terms of rights, the Portuguese ruler did not detailed, pointing out that the objective is “not discouraging this mobility, which is positive mobility”.
Noting that procedures for obtaining residence “are often determinant, for the choice of people looking for professional activity” in Macau, the prime minister stressed: “We are talking about people with various qualifications that seek to help develop here many of the activities in which our community has relevance”.
In this sense, he ensured that the authorities on both sides “are in contact” and “it was combined following” the dialogue already started in late March, when the visit of the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel.
 
Au Kam San detention deserves “Discretion” and “Rebate”
Although they were discussed "various matters" with the chief executive, when asked if the arrest of former deputy Au Kam San was one of the themes, Luís Montenegro admitted not. He even said that in relation to this issue, it is "necessary discretion" and "some concentration."
It is recalled that Au Kam San, a Portuguese citizen, was arrested in late July on suspicion of having violated the State Security Defense Law. It was thus the first case in Macao under the law that has been in force since 2009, but was revised in 2023.
At the time, the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Portugal told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that it was “following this issue, through the Portuguese General in Macao”. Paulo Rangel's office also assured that the case would deserve “the best attention of the Portuguese authorities, from the outset in future meetings at the political level, in the spirit of the joint statement”.
The case was not part of the meeting of the meeting between Luís Montenegro and Sam Hou Fai, but the Prime Minister assured that he is not forgotten. "It was not the subject of our conversation, but it is a subject - this and others - which we follow and that we promote with the necessary discretion," Montenegro told journalists.
"There are some matters that also deserve some modesty in treatment and this is one of them," said, along with Minister Paulo Rangel.
Asked if it has already been or will be provided with some support to Au Kam San, Montenegro chose not to "particularize". "We are not discussing this case," he reiterated, threading after the important thing is "cooperation." "In this context of the visit, what I want to reiterate is our firm purpose in bringing our cooperation relationship to the most varied levels and the preservation of a connection that has been fruit, despite having its problems. It is part of the history of sharing that we have been materializing over the years," he replied.
Previously, Montenegro had said that the joint statement "assigns responsibilities to all, and we will be up to our fulfillment and, of course, to request compliance with others." He said he also considered that Macau "is a good example of how it was possible to organize a transition process, to safeguard the most relevant interests in presence and contribute to economic and social development."
"The numbers, although they do not express everything, are a good instrument for us to be able to assess the success, economic and social success, of this route and this process," said Montenegro, admitting, however, that "it is not exempt from tensions, not exempt from obstacles." "[This is what] impels us to be proactive, to be diligent, to be present, and that's what we came here to do," he said.
 
Boss visit to Portugal “at the first opportunity”
Regarding the visit of the Chief Executive to Portugal -who was scheduled for the period between 16 and 20 of this month, but was then postponed -the Prime Minister indicated that “at the first opportunity, so it will be as fast as possible”. "The chief executive reiterated that his first visit abroad will be to Portugal, this also has a very special symbolism," he continued.
In addition, Montenegro assured that Sam Hou Fai proved to be “highly cooperative and sensitized” so that the relationship between the parties can be deepened, “either at the level of teaching Portuguese, or at the level of the exchange between educational institutions, or at the level of the relationship between our governments, this predisposition was very tied”.
In a statement issued by the Social Communication Office on the meeting of Luís Montenegro and Sam Hou Fai it is said that the two parts “exchanged opinions on how to enhance Macau's unique role in the process of consolidating and reinforcing friendly relations between China and Portugal, and the continuous strengthening of exchange and cooperation between Macao and Portugal”.
The leader of the MSA stressed that the government "has always attributed, throughout its development, great importance to the protection and respect for the rights, customs and cultural traditions of the Portuguese residents of Macao, proactively promoting the teaching and diffusion of the Portuguese language." In addition, bilateral cooperation with Portugal has been “increasingly” consolidated.
He also pointed out that "the friendship between the Chinese and Portuguese peoples is long and lasting, and the two countries have been established for 20 years a broader strategic partnership, with a special emphasis on the use of the Macao platform in promoting exchange and sino-Portuguese cooperation." Sam Hou Fai also stated that the MSarns is “committed” to build a commercial service platform between China and Portuguese countries, contributing to “deepening relations between China and Portugal”.
On the other hand, he said he believed that Macau and Portugal "will continue to deepen mutual trust and cooperation, increase friendly exchange, benefit people more and promote bilateral exchange and cooperation to a new level."
Still according to the same press release, Luís Montenegro “praised” the “successful implementation” of the “a country, two systems” principle in Macao and the “huge advances made” since the transition. He also praised the “preservation” of cultural diversity in Macau, including Portuguese culture.
 
“We count on you to be our ambassadors”
Still at the official residence of the Portuguese consul in Macao and Hong Kong, during his speech, Luís Montenegro had asked the Portuguese community to be “ambassador” from the country in the territory.
“We count on you to be - our diplomats do not harm me - our privileged ambassadors on the ground, those who represent our values, our interests, our ambition to be more productive, to build our society more prosperously and also to help the other peoples of the world to find the way for justice and for equal opportunities,” said the Portuguese ruler.
"It is with this spirit that corresponds to our history of almost nine centuries of universal vocation that brought us here, that does not let us get out of here and projects to the future," he added.
It also assured that the community can count on the government of Portugal. "We also count on you. We also have the Chinese and Macanese authorities and each and each of those who are our community here," he concluded. Time later for the usual selfies with the various members of the community.
 
Mixed Commission runs between February 4 and 6
The Portuguese Prime Minister, Luís Montenegro, said that the meeting of the Portugal-Macau Joint Commission, which “has many years late”, will be held in the territory between February 4 and 6 next year. "One of the objective results of conversation and interaction [with Sam Hou Fai] was precisely this," he added. This will be the first meeting of the Joint Commission to be held since 2019.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Promised “commitment” to solve needs of the Portuguese school</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prometido-empenho-para-resolver-necessidades-da-escola-portuguesa/</link><description>At the end of the visit that he made yesterday morning to the Portuguese school, the Prime Minister of Portugal considered that the institution “is a very important active”, to which Portugal attributes a “great strategic relevance in the promotion of teaching Portuguese”. Luís Montenegro heard the Portuguese anthem sung by students, entered classrooms and observed some recently renewed facilities before meeting with school representatives. Neto Valente, president of the EPM Foundation, stressed that the prime minister “promised all the commitment” on issues such as the coming of teachers from Portugal and that he would “keep contacts open” to the school to transmit his needs

Victor Rebelo
 
The few hours of permanence in the Portuguese Prime Minister's sons had a full program throughout yesterday morning. After the meeting, at the government's headquarters, with the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, Luís Montenegro paid a visit to the Portuguese School (EPM), in a stop considered almost compulsory whenever a Portuguese ruler moves to the territory.
The entourage Lusa, who also joined the Minister of State and Foreign Affairs, Paulo Rangel and the Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion, Manuel Castro Almeida, was received at the entrance of the building by the School Director, Acácio de Brito, and the president of the EPM Foundation, Jorge Neto Valente. A student with a branch of flowers welcomed the prime minister, wife and elements of his entourage.
With the facilities devoid of any students, “closed” in classrooms, for safety reasons (they have been in the interior of the school, including vigilance on the terrace, very close to four dozen security elements, including three polic dogs), Montenegro began by listening to the hymn of the Popular Republic of China and then the Portuguese republic, played by the third-year-olds who performed, properly perphilated, Uniform in shades of blue, under the guidance of a teacher. The prime minister listened carefully and in the end clapped, thanked the "performance" and made a point of telling them, "Very well, they were tuned."
From there, the visit to various areas of the school began, with Cicerone Acácio de Brito, which explained the operation of the facilities, especially multipurpose, library, teacher and canteen room, among other spaces, some of which were recently completed improvements.
One of the high moments of the trip to the interior of the school was the entrance of Luís Montenegro and Paulo Rangel, in a group where consul-general Alexandre Leitão and the director of IPOR, Patrícia Quaresma, in two classrooms, one that houses the little ones, aged 5 and 6 years, which yesterday had the real starting year and their lives yesterday, was included in the first cycle rooms. academic at EPM, and the other of the 4th grade.
Montenegro took some time, questioning some students of Chinese origin were spoken Portuguese and wanting to know with others if they liked the school and which subjects enjoyed more.
The visit to the facilities lasted about 45 minutes, which followed a meeting with representatives of the school and the EPM Foundation, and the president of the Association of Parents and In charge of Education, Filipe Figueiredo, and the president of the Student Association, Diana Antunes. At the end of the meeting, the prime minister signed the Honor Book and received some signs, one of which EPM's 20th anniversary commemorative by Edite Silva, former director of the school and current member of the Foundation.
The first statements of the Prime Minister have followed since he had arrived in the territory, claiming, first of all, that he had been “positive” the encounter with the chief executive, with whom he could “project a joint work that aims to strengthen our friendship and cooperation relations”. He stressed that this cooperation is made to “various levels, economic, social, administrative and also cultural”.
In this (cultural) field it referred to the EPM, stressing that “it is a very important active, to which we attribute a great strategic relevance in the promotion of Portuguese teaching”. On the other hand, he stressed, "also in the possibility of giving conditions of training and qualification to many hundreds of young people every year, with a view to qualifying them to build their projects, to access a higher level in their academic pathways, whether here in Macao, China, Portugal or in Lusophone countries."
He added that "the interest of the Portuguese government will always be to support the preservation of our identity, our culture, our projection in the world."
Montenegro argued that Portugal's presence in Macau “is, moreover, enlightening and synonymous with our universal vocation, our perspective of looking into the world and contributing to the development of all geographies, meeting the valorization of people, the idea of ​​progress, development, which promotes peace, social justice and respect for people's rights”.
 
Neto Valente regrets “interference” from DSEDJ
In the balance of the visit of the Luso ruler to EPM, Jorge Neto Valente linked the importance of the act. "It is not common to have visits from the Prime Minister of Portugal, so for us it is an honor, but it is above all an opportunity to make known our situation as a Portuguese Language and Culture School and establish better relationship ties with the Portuguese government," he said.
The president of the Foundation stressed the importance of the Portuguese government, "responsible for the existence of the school, for its survival and, above all, for the support it gives." And, he stressed, "not only in financial terms, but also, above all, in defining the curriculum, in the granting of special licenses for teachers to teach in our school."
He considers this "very important", having found "opening" by Montenegro. "What depends on Portugal, the prime minister promised all the commitment and said he would keep the contacts open so that we could get our needs there," he says.
Speaking of other issues that concern the Foundation's leaders, but they are not about Lisbon, Neto Valente lamented that there is no response to the attribution of BIR to teachers from Portugal to teach in the EPM, within the development of qualified talent and pictures. "We have done steps and have no answer yet, but I think this will be accelerated, because everyone complains about the delay in solving this problem, and for us this is a problem, because these frames are selected among the best, validated with many years of experience."
On the other hand, he used the term “divergences” by referring to the way teachers' skills and competences by education services, not agreeing with what he considers to be “interference in our pedagogical autonomy”.
"There is no one better qualified than EPM, and the responsible entities of Portugal, to appreciate the quality of teachers," he said, adding "who has to say which are the competent and qualified teachers to give the Portuguese curriculum in Macau is the school, not local education services." "Each one at its place is what we want to happen, and that's what we have had some difficulty in making recognizing it," he lamented.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief reiterates appeals to the vote within the civil service</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-reitera-apelos-ao-voto-seio-da-funcao-publica/</link><description>The chief executive had a meeting with leaders in the direction and higher level, appealing again to the vote in the legislative elections. At the meeting, he argued that "leaders in the management level should assume a role of connection between superiors and subordinates", promoting "compliance with liability". He further reiterated that the suffrage demonstrates “the defense of the basic law of masters and the fidelity to masters”
 
After sending a letter to civil servants to appeal to the vote, saying that suffrage is a right, but also a duty, and that it is a way of demonstrating “fidelity to the masters”, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, met with leaders at the level of direction and higher to address “the work and facilities prepared to allow the elections to the Legislative Assembly (AL)” next Sunday. The leader of the MSAR has again stressed that the vote "constitutes not only a right, but also a civic duty."
In this sense, he again appealed “to all voters, including civil servants, to actively participate in the legislative elections as a way of exercising the right to vote in choosing their representatives,” according to a statement from the Social Communication Office. At the meeting -where the main holders of the Government of the MSAR, the directors and counselors of the Chief Executive and the main holders, as well as the leaders in the level of service director -SAM Hou Fai will have explained that the letter sent to the civil service workers “represents an appeal, as members of the Governance of the MSAR, to actively respond to the Call of the Electoral Affairs Committee of the Electoral Affairs. in order to diligently fulfill their duty to vote and to encourage it to family and friends. ”
Pointing out that these are the first elections to be held after the review of the Electoral Law to the Legislative Assembly, which has as one of the main objectives “reinforcing the implementation of the Macao principle governed by patriots,” the chief executive added that this is “a political event of enormous importance for the MSAR and a major political task for the current government since its inauguration”.
Thus, he again said that "all public services should facilitate the displacement of employees in service to vote on election day."
Understanding again that the elections for Al “are a great political event,” Sam Hou Fai said that “leaders in the management level should assume a connecting role between superiors and subordinates, promote compliance with liability, jointly support electoral work, [and] actively vote on election day”. All this to support “with a practical action, the fulfillment of the competence of the Government of MSAR according to the law, which constitutes a basic requirement of the ethical and moral principles of civil service” and, thus, “the defense of the basic law of masters and the fidelity to masters [by the] civil servants”.
At the same time, it encouraged all public services and entities to cooperate, support, communicate with each other during the electoral process, “to join, together, the order and security of the elections, ensuring that they take place in a cool, fair, impartial and whole environment”.
At the meeting, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, and the Secretary for Security, Wong Sio Chak, presented the provisions of voting and security work to be done for election day.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Excessive times of teachers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/denunciados-horarios-excessivos-dos-docentes/</link><description>Ng Wan Hei, a subdirector of the Association of Youth of People, warned of the working conditions of non-superior teaching teachers, stressing that they have suffered a “significant pressure” in their duties, resulting from more hours of work. Moreover, it considers that the current structure of contributions to teachers' reform is inadequate
 
Pedro Milheirão
The Association of Youth People warned that many teachers have been feeling “significant pressure” in their work, due to an excessive workload, according to a statement issued yesterday, under the teacher's day. The group noted that, in addition to classes, which need to be planned by the teachers themselves, they also have to develop performance reports and perform various formations, among other extracurricular activities.
Ng Wan Hei, subdirector of the association, noted that several teachers reported daily journeys “over 10 hours”, when the “general framework of teaching staff of non -higher education schools”, in force for 13 years, stipulates a maximum of 18 weekly teaching periods. The subdirector added that many teachers have been meaningful "unable to deal with the situation."
In addition, NG Wan Hei stated that additional tasks add an average of eight to 12 hours a week to teachers, and some of them continue to have a disproportionate remuneration for workload as well as years of service.
At the same time, the subdirector of the Association of Youth of People warned of the “inadequate retirement provisions” of teachers. Although there is a mandatory regime of a Providence Fund for teachers of private institutions, "the absence of explicit criteria for the calculation of contribution rates resulted in an effective gap, in terms of protection," criticized NG Wan Hei.
"The remuneration structure in most private schools in Macao is made up of a base salary complemented by various subsidies," continued the responsible. "When contributions are calculated exclusively taking into account the base salary, the real amount of the contribution is significantly below the reasonable levels, making it difficult to achieve the goal of ensuring the quality of life of teachers in the reform."
In the first measure, Ng Wan Hei argues that the regulatory framework should be reviewed, establishing "minimum contribution rates for schools and teachers without reducing the standards of existing benefits." In addition, a subsidy “by antiquity and echelons” should be introduced.
As a second measure, it proposes to reduce the “scientific” workload and review support measures. At the same time, it suggests the application of artificial intelligence tools to assist teachers. The third measure focuses on the improvement of existing psychological support channels for teachers and the inclusion of the right to rest in school assessment indicators.
For ng wan hei, "teachers constitute a life force in social development, contributing significantly to the formation of talents and the advancement of social progress."
The official urged the government to “re -evaluate measures to alleviate teachers' workload and adjust their remuneration, establishing a tripartite warranty system”, between teaching staff, schools and government, as “sustainable pillars for the future development of Macao”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Biennial curators and artists discuss “face -to -face” public art</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/curadores-artistas-da-bienal-discutem-arte-publica-presencial/</link><description>Inserted in the Macao International Biennial Program, the lecture “Conversation and Dialogue: The Public Nature of Public Art” will be held. The initiative will bring together curators and artists participating in the Biennial, in a reflection on new ways of addressing “face -to -face public art
 
Pedro Milheirão
At 7 pm on September 24, the “conversation and dialogue: the public nature of public art” will take place in the 1st floor auditorium of the Macao Art Museum. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), the session will focus on “ways to cultivate a new, dynamic and vibrant approach in the context of 'face -to -face' public art” and will be moderate by curator Wu Wei. The discussion will involve artists Ann Hamilton, Yin Xiuzhen, Jason Ho and Assembly, as well as Feng Boyi, main curator at Macao's International Art Biennial, and co-cure Liu Gang.
The lecture will be held in English, and with simultaneous translation in Mandarin. The session is a complementary initiative to the Biennial Public Art Exhibition, which aims to “integrate art into urban space and everyday life”. At the end of the month, Ann Hamilton, an American artist, will reconstruct the “historical memory of sino-western commerce” at the Dom Pedro V Theater, in a project called “Hands borrowed”, using multimedia art. Already the contemporary Chinese artist Yin Xiuzhen will present the installation of interactive video “non -terminal”.
In turn, the British group "Assemblies" will introduce the work "goods and warriors", in a reflection "on the relationship between earth and people". The set is known for “revitalizing urban spaces through community collaboration and creative design”, says the IC. In addition, Jason Ho will continue with the “Community Co-Creation Project and mutual aid from San Mei On”, which began between July and August, in order to “encourage community connection”, with artistic projects and interactive workshops.
Under the theme “Waves and Paths”, the public art exhibition brings together five projects of nine renowned authors, including “The Tower of Time”, created by a trio of artists from China, South Korea and Japan and on display at the Cultural Center Square. The different artistic works share the objective of “imagining the new possibilities of public spaces in movement and permanence” and “weave collectively the emotional texture of the city”.
Feng Boyi is an independent and critical curator of contemporary Chinese art, while Liu Gang, founder of a creative brand, develops a “rooted in the local, but with international vision” curatorship. Wu Wei is dedicated to investigating contemporary artistic practice and “the evolution of artistic language in transcultural contexts”.
The lecture will be open to public participation, and interested parties should be residents aged 13 or over. Registrations will be open until September 19th through the Single Account.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SPU in Tokyo for the fight against money laundering</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/spu-em-toquio-em-prol-combate-a-lavagem-de-dinheiro/</link><description>The Financial Information Office sent representatives to Japan, as part of the annual meeting of the Asia-Pacific group against capital bleaching. The occasion served to share observations on the group's resource planning, mutual assessments and new financial crimes trends
 
A delegation, coordinated by the Financial Information Office (GIF) of the Unit Police Services (SPU), moved to Tokyo to the annual meeting of the Asia Pacific group against the bleaching of capital (APG, in the English acronym). According to a statement, the meeting focused on the mutual evaluation reports of two jurisdictions, the new mutual assessment calendar and the group's resource planning, as well as the new trends in capital laundering and terrorism financing, among other matters.
The GIF representative presided over the discussion of one of the reports, before finalizing the mandate as co-president, says the statement. The body has been co-crashed the APG Mutual Evaluation Committee since 2013. The MSar has been praised for contributing, over the years, with personnel in the participation of the various works of the organization.
The SPU have reiterated that the MSAR “has actively participated” with international institutions and ensure that GIF will “continue to coordinate the participation of working group members in meetings and training actions”, in order to be “about new international standards against capital laundering”.
In addition to the GIF itself, the staff organized by the cabinet was composed of the member services of an interdepartal working group, which included the commissioner against corruption, customs services, the Judiciary Police, the Public Security Police, the Macao Monetary Authority, the Directorate of Games and the Directorate of Technological Development Services.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Young people with moderate level of adherence to voluntary services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jovens-nivel-moderado-de-adesao-servicos-voluntarios/</link><description>The proportion of young places who have already been volunteers and the frequency of their participation in this type of activities reach moderate levels, according to an inquiry from the Macao Youth Christian Association. More than 50% of young people and adolescents responded that “helping needy people” was the reason that led them to provide volunteer services. On the other hand, they pointed to “lack of time” as the main factor that can restrict their adherence to voluntary activities
 
Between February and June, the Association of Youth Christians of Macao (YMCA, in the English acronym), inquired 313 youth and adolescents from Macao, with the purpose of perceiving the “Macao Volunteer Growth Pathway”. According to the results of the recently released inquiry, the proportion of young places who have already participated in volunteer services and the frequency of their involvement in this genre of activities are at moderate levels.
Still, the Association notes that, in general, all respondents recognize the importance of participation in voluntary services. And they are satisfied with their experience as volunteers, convinced that participation in such initiatives can contribute to reinforce their personal ability.
On the other hand, more than 50% of respondents pointed out the intention of “helping needy people” as the main reason that led them to participate in volunteer services. However, they have recognized that they can reduce their level of participation due to "lack of time."
In addition, according to YMCA, there are differences between different groups of respondents, with regard to the content and the target of their volunteer services. Specifically, male respondents prefer to participate in voluntary activities that serve young and adolescents and educational activities, while female young women value the feeling of satisfaction they can get in emotional terms and interpersonal relationships.
In addition, interviewed college students face participation in volunteer services as a channel that can contribute to improving their experience and curriculum. In turn, respondents who have already entered the job market expect participation in voluntary actions to enrich their free time, so they prefer flexible and simple initiatives, such as visiting activities.
Given the results of the inquiry, YMCA suggested continuous dissemination of the services provided by young volunteers and the launch of appropriate and attractive voluntary activities for different youth groups. It also advocates the periodic collection of opinions with the young volunteers, so that the content and forms of activities can be adjusted in due course according to the degree of satisfaction of the participants.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Five special careers for elections</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cinco-carreiras-especiais-para-eleicoes/</link><description>Next Sunday, 37 polling stations will be available to the Legislative Assembly, with 38 voting assemblies for direct suffrage and five for indirect suffrage. There will also be five special careers that will connect four border posts to the Macao Forum, as well as the University of Macao to the Taipa Olympic Sports Center
 
The Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal) will prepare 37 voting places, where 38 voting assemblies will be available for direct suffrage and five for indirect suffrage. Voters will be able to vote from 09h00 to 21h00, according to the statement.
At the same time, 29 service stations will be available from 08h00 to 21h00, in various streets and areas of park and leisure near the voting places. In these posts, employees will “provide information on elections, voting assemblies, transport facilitating measures, and assistance required for elected specific needs and transportation,” according to the Communication Office (GCS).
In addition to free public transport services, there will be five special bus lines. Four will connect the border posts of the doors of the siege, Qingmao, Hengqin and the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge to the Macao Forum. The lines will be free and will work in both directions, "to facilitate voters whose registered addresses are out of the border." In addition, another connection will connect the University of Macao (one) and the Taipa Olympic Sports Center, with a view to “facilitating the travel of voters teachers and university students”.
The first buses will rip off the border stations and one at 08:30, with intervals of 15 to 20 minutes. The latest careers of the Macao Forum and the Olympic Sports Center will leave at 9:30 pm, towards the borders and one.
Throughout the course of the special calls, signs and staff with orientation signs will be installed. Special nominations will serve to guide and facilitate the departure of careers in traveling to voting assemblies and the points of waiting of buses after voters make their vote. "Employees on site will be aware of drivers who make parking to wait, and possibly affect the traffic order near the voting places."
 
Identical voting assembly for inmates in coloane
Caeal visited the Voting Assembly of the Coloane Prison Establishment on Tuesday to learn about the work carried out by the Directorate of Correctional Services (DSC), in order to guarantee the right to voters voters who are arrested.
According to a statement, "the provisions of the voting meeting, the voting procedures, the opening hours and the regulations on confidentiality are identical to that of other general voting assemblies." In addition, “all voters who are not deprived of political rights have a right to vote,” said the GCS.
In addition, so that voters who are serving time to have access to the programs of the candidate lists, Caeal and DSC reported the prisoners about the “bases of the political program of the candidates”, how to vote correctly and the vote secret. The attributed electoral information was "practically identical to those of the general population."
Caeal President Seng Ioi Man, thanked DSC for the “collaboration and supportive support” in electoral work.
 
Detained suspected of vandalizing poster
A 40 -year resident was arrested on suspicion of vandalization of a campaign poster of a candidate for the Legislative Assembly, the Public Security Police (CPSP) said. CPSP did not specify the list, but it seems that it is the one led by Pereira Coutinho. The detainee claimed that he was a “unleashed” and denied having committed the act with political intent or to defame any candidate. The case occurred on the night of the 1st of this month, on General Castelo Branco Avenue. The inspection of the firefighters indicates that the burning was caused by a cigarette beata and was found cigarettes of the same brand at the suspect's home. In the fraction where he lives, was also found the clothes he wore on the night of the crime. The CPSP said the suspect's conduct could incur at a maximum penalty of three years in prison. The case was referred to the prosecutor.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Prince Hisahito reaches adulthood in the midst of succession crisis in Japan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/principe-hisahito-atinge-maioridade-em-plena-crise-sucessoria-japao/</link><description>Japan announced the majority of Prince Hisahito with a ceremony elaborated in the Imperial Palace, where a succession crisis is formed. Emperor Naruhito's nephew and second in the line of succession after his father, the 19 -year -old received a black and lacquer silk crown, which marks the beginning of his royal adult life.
“Thank you so much for giving the crown at the age of majority,” said Prince Hisahito, wearing traditional yellow costume for minors, bowing before Emperor Naruhito and Empress Masako, who smiled at him.
"I will fulfill my duties, aware of my responsibilities as an adult member of the imperial family," he told parents at the ceremony in Tokyo, which was attended by several members of the royal and family family.
Although the Emperor has a daughter -Princess Aiko -the 23 -year -old was part of the royal family's succession rules, who predict that only men can continue the imperial lineage -which, according to legend, dates back to 2600 years -, opinion polls show a high public support on the climb of a woman to the throne.
"For me, it makes no difference whether a woman becomes an imperative or a man," said Yuta Hinago, Tokyo barista.
The 33 -year -old believes that there may be “space for more flexibility” in the rules of succession.
"The genre doesn't matter," he told AFP Minori Ichinose, 28, a part-time counter, adding that he supports the idea of ​​an imperator.
Japan has debated the real succession for decades, with an important government panel to recommend in 2005 to pass to the eldest son, regardless of sex. This seemed to pave the way for the Emperor's daughter to rise to the throne of chrysanthemum, but the birth of Prince Hisahito the following year silenced the debate.
Politicians have been slow to act, “postponing the issue” and a solution in view of the young Hisahito, said Kenneth Ruoff, director of the Japanese Study Center at Portland State University.
Traditionalists state that the “uninterrupted imperial line” of male succession is the basis of Japan, and major changes would divide the nation.
According to the postwar constitution, the royal family has no political power. With the daughters of royalty forced to abandon the family after marriage, a modernizing proposal would oblige them to continue their public duties after marriage.
Conservatives, in turn, press for the royal family to bring distant relatives back to the group. But it is not clear if these men would be willing to give up their careers and freedom to continue the lineage.
Prince Hisahito said in 2025 that he “had not yet deeply reflected” about his own prospects of marriage, which could be challenging.
Historically, women who marry royal members face intense pressure to have boys and become a constant target of rumors.
Empress Masako, a former high -level diplomat, fought for years against a stress -related disease after joining the family, which some attributed to the pressure to have a child. Empress Emérita Michiko, mother of Emperor Naruhito, also suffered from diseases caused by stress.
Prince Hisahito's sister, Mako, married her university boyfriend Kei Komuro. It has faced intense tabloid coverage of the allegations that Komuro's family would have faced financial difficulties, leading the former princess to develop a complex posttraumatic stress disorder. The couple left for the US, where he recently had a baby.
Despite the broad public support for changing the rules of succession, far from pomp, people are focused on other issues, such as increased inflation, royal historian Hideya Kawanishi told AFP.
"If the people who usually support (the imperators) become a little more expressive, politicians can become more serious," said associate professor Kawanishi, who tends at Nagoya University.
"But when the ceremonies end, society, including the media, calms down and moves on," he noted.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>