<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Local economy “well positioned” for “sustainable growth”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-local-bem-posicionada-para-crescimento-sustentavel/</link><description>Encouraged by tourism and increased game -related investments, and “the lasting support of the central government”, the MSAR economy “is well positioned for sustainable growth”, considers the monetary authority. “Macao's economy is expected to advance a moderate pace this year, the body in the first report of“ monetary and financial stability ”of 2025, also anticipating a“ slight ”rise in inflation and maintaining“ slight ”monetary stability and the maintenance of“ slight ”and the maintenance of“ the maintenance of “the maintenance of“ resilience ”of the labor market. AMCM also believes that Macau will consolidate its role as a financial service platform between China and Lusophone countries
 
Sérgio Terra
 
The sons “is prepared for greater economic recovery, driven by sustainable tourism and increased game -related investment”, maintains the monetary authority of Macao (AMCM), convinced that external demand will remain “strong” in a context of “enrichment” of tourist facilities as a way of responding to “changes in consumer preferences”. "In addition, with the stimulus policies introduced by the central government last September, it is expected that consumer feeling gradually improve in mainland China, which will be conducive to the Macao tourist sector," he says, highlighting the positive impact of the Measures that, since January 1, facilitate the visits of residents of Zhuhai.
The combination of these factors will “support the impetus of external demand and consolidate the territory's economic recovery”, anticipates the AMCM Department of Studies and Statistics in the first “Monetary and Financial Stability Review” report of 2025, also reiterating that “OS Solid Fundamentals of Macao in terms of budgetary and external balances will protect against adverse repercussions from global economic uncertainties. ” "Since the base effect will normalize after rapid recovery in the last two years, Macau's economy is expected to advance a moderate pace in 2025," says the body, without risking numerical projections on the annual increase of the product Gross internal (GDP).
The latest official data indicate that the Macau GDP grew 4.7% in the third quarter of 2024 and 11.5% in the first nine months last year, in real homologous terms, illustrating new sequential slowdown, partially imputable to higher comparative bases , but also to the slowdown in the recipes of the game between July and September. In the first nine months of 2024, GDP was on about 301 billion patacas, corresponding to a resum of 86.3%, compared to 2019. In October, reviewing the previous projections, the international monetary fund estimated that the economy of Macao could grow 10.6% by 2024 and 7.3% in 2025.
On the other hand, AMCM believes the consumer price index will “slightly” this year, after the inflation rate retreated from 0.94% by 2023 to 0.74% by 2024. Internal inflation pressures in 2025 grow modestly in conjunction with increased aggregate demand, while external pressures will remain moderate, ”read the report.
At the same time, it expects the labor market to demonstrate "continuous resilience in the midst of favorable economic conditions." In this domain, the body insists that "imported workers, which aim to supplement local labor, will provide sufficient protection for policy adjustments."
It is recalled that the global level of unemployment in the MSAR performed by 1.8% in the general calculation of 2024, noting an annual decrease of 0.9 points and the lower percentage since the 1.7% recorded in 2019. The unemployment rate of the residents dropped a percentage point to 2.4% compared to 2023.
Generally speaking, AMCM stresses that "with the lasting support of the central government, Macau's economy is well positioned for sustainable growth." With the Executive of MSA committed to promote the strategy “1+4” to diversify the economy and stimulate the transformation of traditional industries, “a synergistic development” is provided with the deepened cooperation zone to “optimize resource allocation for both The regions ”, while the“ vast industrial space ”in Hengqin will be able to foster“ entrepreneurial activities, creating more high -value jobs and generating a new momentum for growth ”.
At the same time, the monetary authority understands that “the greatest interconnection with the continent” will allow to “broaden the business field of the financial industry of Macau, especially in the areas of the obligation, heritage management and business in Renminbis, thus consolidating the role of Macao as a platform de serviços financeiros entre a China e os países de língua portuguesa”. “With a wider range of growth engines and continuous optimization of the industrial structure, these efforts will not only anchor macroeconomic stability against external shocks, but will also conduct Macao to a more sustainable development trajectory,” says the report.
 
Financial system reveals “continuous resilience”
AMCM also emphasizes that the monetary stability of the MSAR has been sustained by a “credible” currency stabilization background system and the “strong budget position”. “Macao currency reserves have been consistently maintained at a enough level to fully cover monetary responsibilities in Patacas,” he says, also noting that “the budget position has been reinforced along with the continuous expansion of the financial reserve, providing the government of MSAR a Ample political space to anchor macroeconomic stability and at the same time keep your status free of debt. ”
Nesse contexto, “o sistema financeiro de Macau tem demonstrado uma resiliência contínua, sustentado por posições sólidas de capital e liquidez”. Embora a Reserva Federal dos EUA tenha procedido a três cortes nas taxas de juros desde Setembro do ano passado, a AMCM adverte, porém, que os custos de financiamento ainda são “elevados” e, caso assim se mantenham, “poderão continuar a ser um Burn the rendibility of Macao benches ”.
For now, the body asserts, "the capitalization and liquidity position of the bank sector remains solid, providing robust support to financial stability and sufficient resources to respond to future credit demand." However, it is clear that “the uncertainties on the pace of future cuts of FOMC [US Federal Reserve Federal Reserve Federal Market Committee] require vigilant credit risk management by Macao banks and an agile response to changes in macrophinance conditions ”.
Last week, the US Central Bank decided to keep interest rates unchanged, thus stagnuting a cycle of three consecutive reductions and resisting the pressure by US President Donald Trump, who wanted a new cut to boost economic activity. According to AMCM, the FOMC "aims to relieve the containment of monetary policy over time, but the rhythm will remain uncertain, as it needs to find a balance between the promotion of growth and the containment of risks of rising inflation."
On the other hand, in Macao, the AMCM -compiled financial indicator of financial stability, reached 0.54 in the third quarter of 2024, below 0.61 of the same period of 2023. This fall is associated with the decline of income Local banks, whose operational profits fell 38.8% to 5.6 billion patacas in the first 11 months of 2024, in homologous terms, as a result of the 21.5% reduction in interest margin and increased operating costs. In particular, banks' provisions for credit impairment, which accounted for 39.5% of operating costs, rose 11.1%.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Analysts foresee slight climb of the game in February</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/analistas-preveem-ligeira-subida-jogo-em-fevereiro/</link><description>After the game's recipes suffered a 5.6% annual break in January, JP Morgan analysts, Deutsche Bank and Seaport Research Partners expect improvements in February, although with distinct optimism levels, ranging from a residual homologous rise to one increase of 11%. In common, the conviction that the joint results of the first two months will give more clues about the performance of casinos in 2025
 
Consultants and investment houses that regularly follow the game sector in Macau reacted with caution to the announcement of the results of the first month of 2025, taking into account the pre-Anan Chinese seasonality factor and the differences in the calendar of the festive season face to 2024. Although January revenues have been below the initial expectations, the general feeling points to the sense of improvements in February and the belief that homologous comparisons will be more enlightening when data from the first two months of the year are gathered.
It is recalled that the current “golden week” extends from January 28 to February 4, while the 2024 Lunar New Year began to be celebrated in the second week of February.
According to the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, Casinos gross revenues ciphed at 18.25 billion patacas in January, translating an annual decrease of 5.6% and equivalent to 73.2% of the same month 2019, the pre-pound year. On the other hand, they increased 0.3% in monthly terms.
For February, forecasts already released by several analysts have an ascending curves in annual terms, although with significant differences, based on values ​​that oscillate between 18.5 billion and 20.7 billion patacas. These estimates represent up between 0.1% and 11.4% compared to February 2024.
The JP Morgan Investment Bank, which expected an annual break between 3% and 4% in January, after initially anticipated a 5% decline, classified last month's result as “weak”. “According to our checks, there was a very remarkable slowdown before the holidays this year, with a trailer in traffic since the past weekend, particularly affecting the large enterprises,” which led “to the deficit of gross revenues from I play, despite the strong performance in the first half of the month, ”said DS Kim, Mufan Shi and Selina Li, JP Morgan.
In a more positive record, the investment bank stresses that mass market revenues will have grown more than 10% in January, compared to the same month of 2019, offering the slow resume of the VIP segment, estimated at about 20%. The two percentages of recovery are “similar” to those recorded in the fourth quarter of 2024, the same report says, also stressing that the visitors' entries in Macao “recovered sharply” from January 31, the fourth day of the “golden week”, and the hotel reserves “look solid”.
DS Kim, Mufan Shi and Selina Li stress that it is now important to realize "if the January error was a temporary setback or indicative of a lasting trend."
“We believe that the maximum value for billing is set at about 800 million to 850 million patacas per day for gross game revenues between February 1 and 9, which implies a daily rate of over a billion during peak Of the holidays, ”he added, predicting that this month's accounting could close with about 19 billion or more, which would mean an annual increase between 3% and 5%. In this scenario, the revenues of the first two months of 2025 "will remain stable," despite the "relatively difficult comparison."
JP Morgan experts continue to believe that game's revenues can rise 5% by 2025, "probably accelerating growth rates in the second half of the year," benefiting from "easier comparisons."
Seaport Research Partners' Vitaly Umansky analyst, on the other hand, predicts February to be “slightly better” than last month, with revenues of 18.5 billion patacas, signaling increases of 0.1% and 1.3% in annual and monthly terms, respectively. "If our estimates are confirmed, the agreed period from January to February will fall 2.8% over the previous year," he said.
Carlo Santarelli, an analyst at Deutsche Bank, also reduced estimates for the first two months of 2025, but remains the most optimistic when betting on an annual increase of 11.4% in February, to about 20.69 billion Patacas. Initially, Santarelli had risked a growth of 3.9% in the first two months of this year, but now it foresees a homologous rise of 2.7%.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Denied 31 requests for subsidy for caregivers of intellectual disabled</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/negados-31-pedidos-de-subsidio-cuidadores-de-deficientes-intelectuais/</link><description>As part of the Caregiver Support allowance, IAS received 111 requests linked to people with intellectual disabilities, of which 80 received “green light”, with the remaining 31 (28% of the total) being rejected for several reasons, explained the president of body. Hon Wai also made it clear that, for now, the government will not change the requirements for the request for support
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Since the Subsidy for Caregivers was implemented in November 2020, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) has received 111 requests related to people with an unconnected intellectual disabilities, of severe or deep degree. Of these, "80 gathered the assignment requirements, and the rest was rejected," said the body's president.
It means that 31 of these requirements or 28% of the total have been denied. Hon Wai explains the main reasons: the people in question did not have the corresponding degree of deficiency, were not approved in economic assessment or self-care capacity, among others. The information arises in response to an interpellation of Deputy Song Pek Kei, who called for the flexibility of the caregivers' allowance requirements.
The support, which has become permanent in December 2023, is directed to people who need continuing and intensive care of third parties in their daily lives. Thus, we include permanent beds unable to perform sitting and lifting actions without help, people with intellectual disabilities, with autism and motor disability, "all of a severe or deep degree (including those without grade assigned)." This allowance covers families of low performance caregivers.
“Currently the subsidy for caregivers can basically cover their respective low -performance caregivers families, thus allowing them to benefit from another economic support to live in the community. Moreover, it refers that families of caregivers who do not have enough economic resources to face the basic needs of life can still require IAS subsidies, ”says Hon Wai, dismissing the hypothesis of extending the requirements for the request.
It also recalls that, since this initiative was implemented, the range of recipients has been gradually extended, having become a permanent measure not long ago. “At this time, the Government of MSAR maintains the current regime of assignment of the subsidy for caregivers, continually paying attention to the execution regarding this allowance, as well as support people with disabilities and families of caregivers through different types of services to meet the needs felt by them, ”he added.
 
Sufficient vacancies
On the other hand, the deputy questioned the government about vacancies in the integrated rehabilitation facilities for people with intellectual disabilities and also for these people who are already in the elderly. In this context, IAS indicated that “currently, there is a total of 13 social equipment in Macao with the host service to the disabled people, which can provide about 1,060 vacancies, which basically can meet the needs of the services concerned ”.
According to data referring until November 2024, a total accumulated of 44 people with intellectual disabilities who requested the reception service in care molds for rehabilitation. “Once the requests were considered, it was found that the majority of the applicants do not have the immediate need to enter the rehabilitation homes with the receiving service, and that these people and families receive the daytime rehabilitation and temporary reception service that It is data in the community can effectively maintain and balance the relationship of dependence among family members, ”said Hon Wai.
Regarding the needs of families of two elderly people with intellectual disabilities, IAS states that in 2019, coordinated the elderly home and the rehabilitation home of the Pai Van Seac Zone to organize, with priority, cases of parents and children to receive the corresponding home care service. Through the coordination of both homes "there was an increase in the number of times of visits that leads to a better maintenance of the relationship of parents and children of families of two elderly."
Already last year, “it was deepened” the coordination at the rehabilitation home of the Mong-Há zone, so that the same-sex parents and children can receive services within the home. Through the program, and at January this year, “there was only the entry of a pair of mother and daughter at the Elderly Home and the rehabilitation home of the Pai Van Seac Zone, which enjoyed the ease of visiting and visits and live close to each other ”.
Hon Wai also points out that the government plans to create a home that can make available for elderly and people with disabilities in Zone A to respond to demand. “Currently, home planning is still in a preliminary phase,” he says, pointing out details for later.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Pedestrian zone in the mud “has kept good order”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zona-pedonal-na-taipa-tem-mantido-boa-ordem/</link><description>Today the pedestrian zone in the mud, which has been operating since January 29. The authorities consider that they have “worked well”
 
The pedestrian zone in the mud, operating since January 29 and which is closed today, “has worked well and maintained good order”, consider the various government organisms. That area opens daily at 12:00 pm and ends at 19h00, aiming to “optimize” the flow of people and traffic management due to the celebration of the Chinese New Year.
The initiative also aims to “balance the needs of residents, traders and tourists, in order to ensure the ordered circulation of pawns and vehicles in this area and create a comfortable and safe environment”, report the economy services, in a joint statement with the direction of Services for traffic affairs, the Public Security Police body, tourism services, the Cultural Institute and the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI).
Thanking the support and collaboration of residents and traders, the Interdepartamental Group said it will synthesize the opinions collected and proceed to an assessment “to further improve the organization of the work” next time.
The pedestrian zone in the old district of Taipa is located between the intersection of Rua de Fernão Mendes Pinto with Rua do Supico (in front of the Pool of the Carmo Pool Street) and the intersection of Correia da Silva Street with Governador Tamagnini Street Barbosa (Museum of History of Taipa and Coloane), covering the section between the sidewalk of the barracks and the avenue of Carlos da Maia.
During the implementation of the measure, the authorities maintained close communication with the associations, traders and residents of the old neighborhood of Taipa, cooperating to promote and realize the various works, overseeing the situation and continuing to hear the opinions of all parties To continually optimize the work, a press release indicates.
The AMI highlighted more workers to reinforce the cleaning of streets and public bathrooms and accelerate garbage collection work, while more workers of economics services were also available to answer the doubts of tourists and residents.
At the same time, to enrich the festive elements of the pedestrian zone, a series of activities and shows, such as a fair, a meeting with “Mak Mak”, street performances, music bands, among others was made available. Today is the last day this pedestrian area is working.
 
Golden Week has already brought more than 1.15 million visitors
Between January 28, the eve of the Chinese New Year, and at 5 pm yesterday (7th day of the golden week), Macau received more than 1.15 million visitors, according to data from tourism services and the compiled public security police body by this newspaper. In the general calculation of the first six days, in which just over one million visitors were counted, there was an annual break of 6.1%. In the first three days there were annual breaks, but from the fourth day of the Golden Week (January 31)-which also marked the peak of visitors, with the arrival of almost 220 thousand-there were always increases. . In concrete, on January 31, 219,092 visitors (+9.1%) arrived, on February 1, were 218,367 (+11.7%) and on February 2 total 189,123 (+6.9%). Yesterday, until 5 pm, 142,277 visitors entered the territory.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CPK turbulence causes the club's president to leave</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/turbulencia-cpk-provoca-saida-presidente-clube/</link><description>The CPK is in difficulties following the case of the aggression of President Stephen Chow to a young player at the end of a challenge of the U16 championship. Must, the main sponsor, which ensures the salaries of the senior squad, will have required the resignation of the CPK president to continue to support the collectivity. With the departure of the manager, the university decided to maintain the support, but with a much lower budget, having reevaluated all contracts with the players. One of them, Niki Torrão, did not accept the conditions and abandoned the team
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Changes in the top of the structure of Chao Pak Kei (CPK) have already been operated, one of the main soccer clubs of Macao, as a result of the “bad image” caused by the case of the aggression of then -President Stephen Chow to a young man minor, in End of a game of the under-16 championship in mid-January this year.
With the dissemination of a video on social networks, in which the confusion that was generated after the challenge made at the university stadium was finished and in which the sudden entrance of Chow was glimpsed in the lawn and the apparent aggression by him, the apparent aggression, the CPK's main sponsor, the Must (University of Science and Technology), which ensures senior squad salaries, will have intended, according to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, to end the bond to the collectivity.
However, some CPK leaders were able to demo the Must to cancel financial support as Chow had been, however, deprived of the position of president. In this condition, Must decided to continue to support the team, but with a much smaller budget than had been registering for several years, which can complicate the quality of the squad.
For now, the most sounding output is that of Niki Torrão. After several years at CPK, the Portuguese striker declined that his departure has to do with the club's restructuring. However, the reassessment of the contract in December was certainly one of the reasons.
"I do not mean that it was directly because of this, but what is certain is that I was placed another contract in front, with less favorable conditions, and I did not accept," he said.
The 37 -year -old will sign for Benfica, where he has been for several years, as a senior and in the young layers. "I am very happy to return to a house where I was always very happy, I was part of my training and where I won several titles in the Elite League," he says, stressing to be "eager to start working with the team."
Another footballer who was a CPK reference for 11 times, the Brazilian Diêgo Patriota, will stop playing. Not for the same reasons as Niki, but because, according to JTM, he preferred to “bread his boots” as an athlete, taking a place in the technical structure. "I thought I should leave the career as a player, giving way to a renewal that CPK needs," said the now deputy coach, his compatriot Leonardo, who led Shao Jiang's formation last season.
Patriot is also responsible for the CPK Academy (soccer schools), which remains in activity, despite rumors that pointed to difficulties in its continuity.
The Jornal Tribuna de Macau knows that, within the CPK, there were many voices of indignation that rose, due to the negative image that affected the club, after the above events.
The new president of the club has not yet been officially disclosed, which should happen briefly, given the urgency that the CPK will have to try to undo the negative image caused by the apparent aggression to Benfica's “kid”, perpetrated by the maximum club's guardian and Considered the "soul" of the football team for tens of years, having been one of the workers of entry into Asian competitions. One of the names pointed out to replace Stephen Chow in CPK's lead is Domingos Kong, currently leading and responsible for Shao Jiang football, champion team in the II Division, which will be this year in the elite league, a competition that is expected to start in March.
Regarding a possible disciplinary sanction, Chow is awaiting a decision of the Macao Football Association Council. "We are following the case and we will disclose the punishment within a few days," he told JTM Kong Cheng Hou, secretary general of the body.
The CPK is another club to go through moments of instability, after another history of local football, Mount Carlo has recently decided not to continue their senior team.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Bachará tables at Sands and Wynn 100% “Intelligent”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mesas-de-bacara-na-sands-wynn-100-inteligentes/</link><description>After MGM China and Galaxy Entertainment Group, Sands China and Wynn Macau are already 100% “intelligent” when it comes to the mass segment tables, according to Citigroup analysts according to
 
Sands China and Wynn Macao's pasta -segment tables are already 100% “intelligent”, according to the latest observations from Citigroup analysts, cited by “Inside Asian Gaming” (IAG) magazine. It means that Sands and Wynn are the third and fourth game operators to do so, after MGM China and Galaxy Entertainment Group have completed the installation of this type of tables on their casinos.
Although not all tables are working, and their online placement gradually is expected, IAG has confirmed that the installation of intelligent tables is actually completed.
Citigroup analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau also said they saw “62 new smart tables in the City of Dreams and 63 in the Grand Lisbon [SJM]”, pointing to the two dealers who have not yet completed the launch of these equipment .
“It is worth stressing that intelligent tables can help increase the speed of the game [more games can be distributed per hour] and this is one of the important factors in our forecast of gross recipes in the Macao game from another 7% for the Fiscal year 2025 ”, they stressed.
Last November, Craig Billings, CEO of the Wynn Resorts group, said during a teleconference that Wynn Macau expected to complete the installation of "smart tables" on its two casinos until the Chinese New Year, which started last week. A promise that was fulfilled.
It is recalled that in March last year, the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate and the Judicial Police met with the Safety Departments of the six game dealers to discuss video surveillance and “smart” game systems, namely tables with radio frequency identification. The two organisms "have asked the gaming operators to continue to update surveillance systems in their spaces" and develop "more comprehensive management with technology," including "Increased smart game tables."
Billings then acknowledged that “intelligent” tables offer operational advantages, at the level of security, human error prevention and marketing aspect, “mainly due to the abundance of very accurate data, bets on the bet”.
The latest study of Citigroup on the tables also suggests that Wynn may be recovering some market share in the premium mass segment, based on analysts' observations. “Although Sands (26%quota) and Galaxy (24%) continue to lead in terms of total bets observed in our premium mass study, it was Wynn (24%) that seems to have recovered a significant quota of significant market (compared to January), mainly reflecting great 'whales' [great gamblers] we witnessed that day, ”they wrote.
"All three operators have premium mass rooms that are at the top of our premium mass survey in terms of average bet/player." Although Citigroup said it conducted its investigation on a day when players were just starting to get in Macau after celebrating the Chinese New Year with their families, the average 'premium' player of 26,224 dollars player Hong Kong was still classified as the fourth highest, while there was a "solid increase" in the number of "whales" seen with an average bet of 210,000 dollars of Hong Kong. "The results of the Chinese New Year's inquiry suggest that this year we will probably have a solid gold week," analysts say.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Crossing works start tomorrow on Avenida do Nordeste</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-de-travessia-arrancam-amanha-na-avenida-nordeste/</link><description>The construction works of the pedestrian crossing along Avenida do Nordeste start tomorrow and during its execution will not affect the flow of traffic in the area, guarantee the authorities. The structure will be 600 meters long and will have 13 accesses along the route. The objective is to separate vehicles from pedestrian in a housing area of ​​high density
 
The construction contract of the main structure of the pedestrian crossing along Avenida do Nordeste starts this Wednesday, and will be made by zones with progressive sealing and phased. Its area will also be expanded for execution purposes in order to avoid excessive prohibition and concentration in the execution of the work.
According to a note jointly widespread by the directions of public works and traffic issues, with the advancement of the work, the tracks sites on Avenida do Nordeste and the roads around them will be gradually narrowed, by the measures of Transit according to the concrete situation of the work, in order to respond to the public's travel needs.
The first phase consists of the execution of prospecting on the ride on Central Rua da Areia Preta next to La Baie du Noble, in the Jardim da Areia Preta and the Green Central Seputer of Avenida do Nordeste to determine the location for underground pipes.
In addition, the partial prohibition of tours and the construction of provisional locations to cross pedestrians in order to create the conditions for the execution of stakes and underground structure of the next phase (scheduled from March 2025).
During the construction will be implemented the conditioning to traffic on the partial roads of Central Rua da Areia Preta and Avenida do Nordeste, maintaining normal functioning to the public a part of the zone for dog tour situated next to the fuel supply station next to the black sand garden.
The pedestrian crossing on Avenida do Nordeste will have a length of about 600 meters, with the width free of its pedestrian passage (board) not less than 4.0 meters and the free height inside about 3 to 3.5 meters, with 13 accesses along the way.
Upon completion of the work, citizens can move directly to the residence to the elderly on Avenida do Nordeste, from the Mong Son building on Avenida de Venceslau de Morais. The crossing will allow you to separate vehicles from pedestrian, improve the level of pedestrian safety and the flow of traffic on the ground floor, as well as relieves traffic pressure on that high density housing zone.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Delta Bridge has reached a new daily travelers record</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ponte-delta-atingiu-novo-recorde-diario-de-viajantes/</link><description>The Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau bridge registered a significant increase in the number of travelers during the early days of the Lunar New Year, according to authorities, with the number of people who passed through the port of Zhuhai to establish a new daily record on Friday , reported the official Chinese agency Xinhua. On January 31, the third day of the serpent, the Zhuhai Ponte post accounted for 156,000 trips, between entrances and exits, the highest number since the inauguration of the 55-kilometer mega infrastructure in 2018. Border inspection authorities in Zhuhai, there were more than 454,000 passenger trips between Tuesday and Friday, marking an increase of 22% compared to the same period last year. On the other hand, in the same comparative interval, the number of vehicle trips grew 32% to more than 69 thousand. Hong Kong and Macao residents were responsible for over 60% of the total passenger flow using the bridge during this period. Official data also reveal that the daily flow of passengers at the Zhuhai Bridge border post has exceeded 100,000 in 50 days last year, reflecting an increase of 10 times compared to 2023. Over the past year, the authorities have accounted for more Of three million trips from vehicles with Hong Kong or Macau enrollment through the bridge, representing 55% of total traffic.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2335/</link><description>Game inspection has a new sub -director
Seak Chio Law was appointed, in a service committee, to hold the position of subdirector of the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate. The secretary's order for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, says that Seak Chio Law will perform the functions for a year, starting on February 10. Lei Sek Chio thus leaves the head of the Department of Occupational Security and Occupational Health of the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs, roles since 2023. Law Seak Chio has been a degree in Engineering Management from the University of Huaqiao, and has a master's degree in Business. Public by the National Institute of Administration of China.
 
Appointed administrator of the Society of Parks
Wu Jianfeng was appointed to hold the position of Administrator of the Society's Board of Directors for the development of the Macao Industrial Parks, limited, after being dismissed in the same order as the Chief Executive, as chairman of the Board of Directors of Macau Investment and Development, S.A .. The new function of Wu Jianfeng will be held until May 2, 2025. In turn, Vong Sin Man was dismissed, in his request, from the position of administrator of the Board of Directors of the company for the development of Industrial Parks of Macao.
 
Salaries in construction suffer little descent
In 2024, the average daily salary of construction workers was 763 patacas, 2.7%less in annual terms. Eliminated the effect of inflation, the average real salary index of those workers (92.6) in the year under analysis lowered 3%, compared to 2023. While this and according to data provided by statistics and census services, the material price list Construction of housing buildings corresponded to 123.6 in the last year, 1.2%less, in annual terms.</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Executive wants to preserve trade with centenary history</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/executivo-quer-preservar-comercio-historia-centenaria/</link><description>The promotion of the community economy and the business environment, as well as the hell of the concerns of traders, were at the basis of the executive's head and the secretary to the economy and finance to old neighborhoods of Macao. According to Tai Kin IP, the government intends to establish a plan that boosts the development of SMEs, which covers elements that preserve the centenary stores
 
Victor Rebelo
 
As part of the community economy revitalization policy that has been followed by the Macao government, with the support of tourism and leisure companies, the secretary for the economy and finances took stock of the visit to some old zones of city.
Tai in IP, who accompanied the Chief Executive to travel to the Streets of the Herbarians, Tercena and Five of October and off the bazaar pagoda, revealed that the government is committed to preparing a three -level plan that boosts the development of small ones and medium companies, which covers elements that preserve trade establishments with centenary existence.
The guardian of the economy said that, for several years, support for small and medium enterprises have been granted to increase their ability to explore business. At the same time, he said, the government "has also paid attention to the experience of residents in community neighborhoods."
Tai Kin IP indicated that centuries -old stores in community neighborhoods “have good techniques for next generations to inherit”, and they are elements that must be preserved and maintained by Macao as an international city.
That member of the Sam Hou Fai team was optimistic about the economic development of the territory. In addition, he said that the government will be aware of the general situation of the economy and will study and evaluate the trends of macroeconomic evolution from abroad, "to proceed with a full consideration based on sustainable development."
In this trip to the community neighborhoods, the Chief Executive also took the opportunity to greet the passers -by and talk to some traders and tourists. Sam Hou Fai considered that "the business environment is being driven, given that the area is endowed with a very strong atmosphere in terms of creative culture." Traders took the opportunity to continue the launch of support measures to revitalize the local economy.
Then the Chief Executive and the entourage moved to the mud, to observe the temporary pedestrian zone installed in the old neighborhood of Taipa.
One of the tourists, from the inner Mongolia, told Sam Hou Fai that Macau has “a very strong environment alluding to spring festivities”, which has “a traditional Chinese party atmosphere”, and that the city is “very prosperous and excited ”.
He added that staff in trade establishments "shows a great hospitality," and therefore considers that Macau "deserves to be visited more than once."
 
Improve business environment
However, days earlier, the secretary for the economy and finance continued the series of meetings with commercial associations and “Think Tank” cavity institutions, in order to exchange opinions and collect suggestions for the definition of the government lines.
Responsible for various industrial and commercial associations have spoken about improving the business environment, labor needs, consumption incentive measures, reinforcing tourist attractiveness and strengthening the support for Modelnization of SMEs via digital instruments. ”
On the other hand, they suggested the intensification of brands promotions, the best use of sources of visitors attracted by major events to streamline the community economy, financial support measures, the simplification of administrative procedures concerning the beginning of commercial activities and revitalization of community neighborhoods.
According to an official note, other associations point to stories that cover the improvement of the digital economy business environment, the promotion of the digital development of companies, the valorization of the advantages of the Sino-Madphone platform, the incentive for young people in knowledge of digital economy and dedication to work positions or entrepreneurship in this area.
Proposals on the development of tourist products, tourism with community characteristics, financial support for small and medium enterprises, the development of electronic trade, the operational situation of the restoration sector and the measures to incentive consumption were also presented.
In response to the various suggestions and opinions he received, the secretary highlighted those that concern the themes of society's focus of attention, such as the operation of companies and the use of residents. Tai Kin IP said it will be “accelerated the improvement of Macau's business environment through interdepartamental collaboration” and specific measures will be launched, safeguarding the environment favorable to the “honest operation of local stores in conjunction with the sector” and reinforcing the “dynamism of the market economy”.
The ruler also pointed out that during his tutelage, the role of “infallible contact agent” will be played for Portuguese -speaking countries. The objective, he said, is to “increase the internationalization level and international influence and attraction of Macao, for the provision of services and contribution to a higher standard opening of the country abroad”.</description><pubDate>2025-02-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Golden Week has already attracted close to 990 thousand visitors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/semana-dourada-ja-atraiu-perto-de-990-mil-visitantes/</link><description>The serpent “brought” close to 990,000 visitors to Macau in the first six days of the golden week, accounted for January 28, according to data from tourism services and the Public Security Police body. The peak went on January 31, when almost 220,000 visitors arrived in the territory. Throughout the city, the festive spirit makes it feel, with a series of activities



















Catarina Pereira
 
The Golden Week associated with the Chinese New Year, made up of eight days of holidays, has already brought to the territory near 990,000 visitors. Doing an analysis of the flow of entries in this period, accounted for by the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) from January 28, entered the territory, until February 1, 821,016 visitors, a number that translates into a break of 8.6 % compared to the same period of 2024. According to STD, during this period, most visitors, in a total of 606,231 (-11.3%), came from the interior of China; and Hong Kong arrived 158,191 (-4.4%).
The total visitors for yesterday was not yet available at STD statistics, however, gathering preliminary data from the Public Security Police (CPSP) by 5 pm on Sunday, is expected to be around 989,838, in the first six days of the golden week.
Given only the Chinese New Year's days (which began on January 29), the data point to a total of 742,048 visitors in the first four days, and by joining the tourist flow accounted by CPSP until 17h00 yesterday ( 168,822 people), totals 910,870 visitors.
A more detailed analysis points out that the peak was Friday, January 31. That day, almost 220,000 visitors entered Macau - 219,092, more specifically. According to STD data, there was a 9.1% increase over the same day of the last year. The siege doors absorbed about 40% of the starters, totaling 86,663, followed by the Delta Bridge, where 51,343 visitors arrived (23% of the total) and the Hengqin post, which was chosen by 37,377 visitors to arrive to the MSAR (17%).
Saturday, February 1, has not been far from the highest volume so far accounted for 218,367 visitors, according to STD statistics. In this case, there was an increase of 11.7% in annual terms. The border of the doors of the siege was again the place of passage of election, and there entered 85,125 visitors (39% of the total). Second and third places were the Delta Bridge and the Hengqin Post, which absorbed 52,872 and 35,530 visitors, respectively, the equivalent of 24% and 16% of the total.
Already on the 29th and 30th arrived in Macao 131,856 and 172,733 visitors, and was registered of 19.3% and 20.6% compared to the same days of the previous year, refers to STD. In turn, on January 28, the eve of the Chinese New Year, 78,968 visitors entered the territory, less 34.9% in annual terms.
Due to the increase in the number of tourists walking the city streets, CPSP was forced to take multitudes control measures several times. Yesterday afternoon, along with the ruins of São Paulo, the measures were activated, with several agents to give indications to those who passed by. Before, they had been implemented twice, on different days.
However, taking into account the holidays, the Institute for Municipal Affairs mobilized personnel to reinforce hygiene inspection in several areas, increased the number of cleaning workers and rubbish crates in the busiest areas and reinforced the frequency of cleaning houses. -De-public. At the same time, he installed more than 200 indicative signs of toilets "to facilitate the use of residents and visitors." Also the Cultural Institute (IC) and the firefighters inspected more than 40 temples.
 
Animation in the city
On the first day of the Chinese New Year, the 238 -meter -long giant dragon traveled the city, along with 18 lions, the god of fortune, the three gods of happiness, longevity and prosperity, pair of boys, the zodiac of the snake and Mak Mak, offering “votes for a good new year lunar to residents and visitors” and distributing “gold ingots”.
The serpent's parade of the year took place on Friday, but will return on February 8 (11th New Year), in the central and northern areas of the city. Already the fireworks will return the sky again on February 4 and 12, at 21:00, in the riverside area in front of the Macao Tower.
On the other hand, the six game operators organized activities in the city's historic areas. Melco organizes, in Fortaleza do Monte, until February 12, cultural activities related to the Chinese New Year, including traditional costume photographs service, a workshop on costumes and make -up of the Tang Dynasty, an auspicious lanterns wall, an interactive experience From divine, as well as the “exposure of cultural relics of the dynasties Zhou, Qin, Han and Tang”, in collaboration with the Macao Museum. There is also a gastronomy fair, performances of the Chinese Youth Orchestra of Macao and live bands.
In Barra, MGM presents the “Lucky Market of the Barra da Barra”, until February 25. It has Creative Workshops for New Year's Impressions of the Prince Kung Palace Museum, exclusive collaborations and exhibitions by Japanese illustrator Shinri Murakami, popular Hong Kong, Macau, Taiwan and China, a fashion market, and and popular musical performances, and a fashion market, and Local dishes produced by Barra da Barra, a special pop-up coffee from Bookand.
Sands China, in turn, presents until March 15 “The artistic visit of Philip Colbert in Macao”. In the former Panchões Factory IEC Long and the Houses of Taipa will be seven themed art sculptures and two giant sculptures.
At San MA Lo, until February 12, SJM features street shows at Largo do Pagoda do Bazar, destic writing workshops and gift bag painting, in collaboration with the Youth Art Association. In addition, the “Kam Pek Mercado” brings together several restaurants of Chinese, Portuguese, Japanese, Thai and Taiwanese specialties. During this time there will be music shows and writing of destics.
Until the 4th, Wynn organizes the “Chinese New Year Market” at Rua da Felicidade. “If the amount spent on the small and medium -sized companies in the zone reaches a certain amount, customers will have the opportunity to participate in games and receive Chinese New Year gift bags,” says the IC. There are street performances and flash Mob performances, as well as the “god of fortune”. Lai Chi Vun shipyards also received a fair with over 15 stands, organized by Galaxy.</description><pubDate>2025-02-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sam Hou Fai enhances “indispensable role” of the Macanese community</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sam-hou-fai-realca-papel-indispensavel-da-comunidade-macaense/</link><description>Exalting the “important contributions” given by the macanese since the implementation of the MSAR, namely in the role of bridge between China and Lusophone countries, Sam Hou Fai has ensured that the government will continue to help this community “advance to a new level in all aspects ”
 
Since the process of socio-economic diversification to the successful application of the “country, two systems” principle, the Macaense community, as a “member of the large family” of Macau, “plays an indispensable role and makes important contributions”, acknowledged the head of Executive at a dinner offered to Macanese representatives. “The support and participation of the Macaense community are indispensable for the good performance of the role of Macau as a platform for economic and commercial cooperation services between China and Portuguese -speaking countries,” said Sam Hou Fai, according to an official note.
Note that the Government of MSA has “given importance and supported the Macaense community” in the development of initiatives in the areas of education, social services, cultural activities, restoration and law, among others, in addition to the meeting of the macanese communities, whose last edition took place Between December 1st and 6th last year, the Chief Executive has asserted that "as always, it will continue to help the Macaense community advance to a new level in every respect."
When speaking at dinner, held last Monday, Sam Hou Fai recalled that, despite having studied in Portugal when he was young, he works and has lived in Macau a few decades ago, so he has known many of the participants in the event since the 1980s, Since all this allowed him to “better understand” the Macanese community. Macao is “the home of the macanese”, the “place where the macanese constitute family and make dreams come true,” he said, ensuring that he is “willing to work, together with all representatives, to safeguard and improve this home”, giving “continuity to the Development ”so that the mashes will be“ even more prosperous ”.
In a more general analysis, the Chief Executive considered that, currently, "the society of Macao is experiencing a stable and harmonious conjuncture, presenting a positive tendency for economic development, a scenario of well-being of the population and the splendor of multicultural wealth." For the leader of MSAR, all of this demonstrates "the great superiority and strong vitality" of the principle "a country, two systems."
Sam Hou Fai also took the opportunity to remember that, in the recent visit to Macau, Chinese President Xi Jinping, met with representatives of the various social sectors, including from the Macanese community, thanking them the contributions to the maintenance of prosperity and Macao stability in the long run, and urged them to continue working together to reach “new successes” for Macao. "As President Xi Jinping said, anyone who supports 'a country, two systems' and love Macau as his home, is a native who 'took water from Lilau' and a positive force that contributes to the development of Macao." , emphasized the chief executive.</description><pubDate>2025-02-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Birth can reach lower level in 20 years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/natalidade-pode-atingir-nivel-mais-baixo-em-20-anos/</link><description>The number of births in the MSAR could be this year the lowest of the last two decades, according to predictions of health services
 
Kuok Cheong U, Deputy Director of Macao Health Services (SSM), predicted that the masters should record less than 3,500 births in 2025, a number that would be the lowest since 2004. According to the Chinese channel of TDM, Kuok Cheong U He reported the record of 284 newborns in both hospitals in the territory until Monday, 17 less than in the same period of 2024.
After visiting the first baby born in the lunar year of the serpent, which began on Wednesday, the SSM subdirector said he hoped the birth rate "continues to fall" and added that "it will be good" if the number of births reaches 3.500 .
If Kuok's forecast is accurate, this will be the least fertile year since 2004, when Macau registered 3,308 births.
According to official data, in 2023 there were 3,712 births in Macao, 43.5% less than 10 years ago (6,571) and out of a maximum of 7,913 fixed in 1988, which was a lunar year of the dragon.
Considered a symbol of royalty, fortune and power and the only mythical figure among the 12 signs of the Chinese Zodiac millennial, the dragon sign brings together a set of characteristics that traditionally leads couples to plan to have children during this period.
By the way, the father of the first newborn at Kiang Wu Hospital, nicknamed Yip, told the press that his son was born later than expected and that the couple was telling that it was still "a Dragon Baby."
Although 2024 was considered an auspicious year, Tao Xuemei and Wong Chio Fan, a young couple, told Lusa that the personal and Chinese coffers do not allow this step.
“We are concerned to have children because of national debt, due to economic recession. The option for motherhood really depends on the country's economic capacity and the debt payment capacity, ”says Tao, 28, to work as a school advisor.
“We don't want to have children just to pass them [our] debts,” adds Wong, a 35 -year -old contractor.
The economic growth of mainland China has reached the 5% goal of Beijing by 5%, but some economists claim that the economy is expanding at a slower pace than indicated in official estimates. Nicholas Chen, Creditsights analyst, told Lusa that the company of the Financial Notation Agency Fitch group expects a slowdown to 4.7% this year, in part due to weak private consumption.
During the election campaign, the new head of the Executive of MSAR admitted that one of the biggest long -term challenges is low birth, which in 2023 reached a historical minimum of 0.59 births per woman. Sam Hou Fai said it is necessary to “create conditions in terms of education and employment” to rise birth and promised to study the extension of the maternity leave, currently fixed in 70 days, and the creation of a compulsory central action fund.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Beyoncé and Kendrick Lamar triumph in the Grammy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/beyonce-kendrick-lamar-triunfam-nos-grammy/</link><description>EPA11871592 US SINGER BEYONCE ACCEPTS The Grammy For Best Country Album During the 67th Annual Grammy Awards Ceremony at Crypto.com Arena In Los Angeles, California, USA, 02 February 2025. EPA/Caroline Brehman



Beyoncé won the Grammy to the album of the year, for the first time in his career, by "Cowboy Carter" at the 67th edition of the awards, held at Crypto.com Arena in Los Angeles. "It's been many years there," said Beyoncé, referring to the time he waited to receive the 'Crown Jewel' from the Hands of the head of the Los Angeles Firefighters, Anthony Marrone.

This Grammy makes Beyoncé the first black woman in 26 years to win in this category since Lauryn Hill in 1999 and the seventh artist winning the award for a country album. Beyoncé also triumphed in the categories of best country album and country performance, thanks to the duet with Miley Cyrus in ‘II Most Wented.”
Named for the maximum award awarded by the US National Academy of Arts and Sciences were André 3000 (“New Blue Sun”), Sabrina Carpenter (“Short N 'Sweet”), Charli XCX (“Brat”), Jacob Collier ( “Djesse vol. 4”); Taylor Swift (“The Tortured Poets Department”), Chappell Roan (“The Rise and Fall of A Midwest Princess”) and Billie Eilish (“Hit Me Hard and Soft”).
"Cowboy Carter", the eighth album of Beyoncé's career, is the long -awaited 'second act' of the work "Renaissance", released in 2022.
In addition to Beyoncé, who had 11 nominations, a number that raises the total in his career and makes her the artist with the largest nominations in history, Kendrick Lamar, with the Grammys for the song and the album of the year by “Not Like Us, ”Shakira, Billie Eilish, Chappell Roan, Doechii, Sabrina Carpenter and Charli XCX scored among the stars of the night, which was attended by Will Smith, Stevie Wonder and Janelle Monáe in a tribute to the deceased and legendary producer Quincy Jones.
The ceremony, led by comedian Trevor Noah for the fifth consecutive time, was filled with political scraps directed at the new US administration and particularly marked by the recent memory of the three weeks of devastating fires in California.
Shakira dedicated Grammy to best Latin pop album with her 12th studio album, “Las Mujeres Ya No Lloran”, to the US immigrant community that Donald Trump's new administration brought headlines around the world again, due to Promise of the greatest deportation of Latin Americans in history on American soil. “I want to dedicate this award to all my immigrant brothers and sisters in this country. You are loved, you are worth it and I will always fight with you and with all the women who work hard every day to advance your families, ”said the singer.
The surprise of the night was Californian singer Kendrick Lamar, the artist with the most awards at the 67th edition of Grammy as he received five distinctions, with the song “Not Like US”: in two of the main categories, album of the year and song of the year, and Best rap interpretation, best rap song and best music video.
Lamar recalled in his speech the fires in California and, in particular, in Los Angeles County, which he considered “a true testimony” that the city will continue to be collectively restored. Also here an allusion to Trump's threat to condition federal aids to the recovery of areas affected in the Democratic State.
Lady Gaga and Bruno Mars also honored the victims of the fires by playing "California Dreamin", an ode to the Golden State, before winning Grammy for better pop duet performance by "Die With a Smile." Gaga took advantage of the microphone to claim the rights of transgender and the power of music to unite people.
Alicia Keys, who received Grammy by the global impact, referred to Trump's executive order on the unique two-genre recognition: male and female, leaving aside the trans community. "Diversity, equity and inclusion (Dei) is not a threat, but a gift," he said.
Taylor Swift left empty hands, despite the six nominations for the album “The Tortured Poets Department”, like Billie Eilish, who was a favorite of the year. British Charli XCX has won three Grammys by "Brat". Chappell Roan was crowned best new artist, in a list that also included Sabrina Carpenter and rapper Dochii, and in a powerful intervention demanded that the publishers dignified the conditions of emerging artists.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>