<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Ron Lam and 11 other disqualified candidates from the race to elections</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ron-lam-outros-11-candidatos-desqualificados-da-corrida-as-eleicoes/</link><description>A total of 12 candidates, from two lists, did not pass the evaluation by the State Security Defense Commission, for “not defending the basic law or not being faithful to MSAR”, so they are out of the race to legislative elections. Among them is the current deputy Ron Lam, who was elected in 2021. The president of Caeal, Judge Seng Ioi Man, announced yesterday the decision, who said he was taken "considering the facts." However, it did not reveal the concrete reasons for the exclusion of these candidates, invoking "confidentiality." The decision does not fit a complaint or litigation appeal. Now only six lists in direct suffrage
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Twelve candidates for legislative elections - including the current deputy Ron Lam - were disqualified following the issuance of the Opinion of the State Security Defense Commission (CDSE). According to the appreciation made by that body, the candidates "do not defend the basic law or are not faithful to the Mashed people of the People's Republic of China." In this sense, the Commission on Electoral Affairs (Caeal) "has made the decision that the individuals concerned do not have the ability to be candidates."
The president of Caeal, Judge Seng Ioi Man, stressed that "the opinion issued by the State Security Defense Commission is binding, and the decision of Caeal that a candidate does not have the ability to be a candidate, based on the respective opinion, there is no complaint or litigation."
At stake are two lists: "Power of Synergy" and "Popular Liveliod Force in Macao." All candidates on the list headed by Ron Lam, that is, Ian Heng Ut, Che I Kei, Sio Iek Weng, Chan Chon Meng and Cheong Iek Chong were excluded from participation in the elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL), scheduled for September 14. It is recalled that Ron Lam was first elected in 2021.
The other list, which ran for the first time, also saw all his candidates - Alberto Wong, Leong Sio Iok, Che Meng Lam, Chow Chi Fai, Ngai Ka Fong and Fong Kai Hou - to be away from the Race to the Hemicicle. The seventh candidate of the list, Hong Wai I, had already presented the withdrawal of the race, according to Seng Ioi Man.
The president of Caeal said that the decision was taken "taking into account the facts" and argued that "it should not be doubted of the authority and specialization" of the committee, pointing out that the opinions issued "have a clear and sufficient legal foundation." "Data and information regarding their work have to remain highly confidential, otherwise there may be risks to national security," he said.
Asked how the population may know how to violate the law, given that the concrete motives were not explained, and urged to clarify which criteria - of a total of seven that were included in the new electoral law - motivated the decision, Seng Ioi Man re -mentioned the question of “confidentiality” of CDS -related works. "Caeal has no more information to provide," he added.
After the announcement, the State Security Defense Commission indicated, in a statement, that, when a candidate is excluded for not being patriot, the other members of the list are also considered “not defenders of the basic law” or “not faithful to MSAR”.
The seven criteria that candidates have to comply with include: defense of the constitutional order established in the constitution of the RPC and the basic law, not organizing or participating in activities with the intention of overthrowing or harming the fundamental system of the state; Defense of the unity and territorial integrity of the State, not practicing acts that endanger them; There is no collusion with “anti-china” organizations, associations or individuals; Respect for the political system enshrined in the constitution of the RPC and the Basic Law, “not attacking in bad faith, denigrating, slanderizing or outraging the RPC or the masters”; Respect for the competences and decisions of the National Popular Assembly; Do not practice acts against national sovereignty and security, nor against state security; and do not provide assistance or facilitate the practice of these acts.
 
Six lists for 14 seats
On the other hand, Seng Ioi Man indicated that the remaining six lists of direct suffrage "have no ineligibility situation of candidates or other irregularities." Therefore, “these applications and their candidates were admitted” by Caeal.
Thus, they remain in the race to elections the “Association of United Citizens of Macao”, linked to the community of Fujian; the “Union for Development”, of the Federation of Workers' Associations; and the “Promoting Union for Progress”, linked to the General Union of Residents' Associations. They also compete for the seats of the “Good Home Alliance” of the Women's Association; The “New Hope”, linked to the Macao Public Function Workers Association, and the “Union of Macau-Guangdong”, linked to the province of Jiangmen.
Since the establishment of the MSAR, this will be the time when there are fewer lists to compete for 14 seats for direct suffrage. With disqualification, it means that lists linked to traditional associations will get more space in AL.
In 2021, it is recalled, Caeal disqualified, for the first time, candidates for legislative elections-five lists and 21 candidates, 15 of which pro-democracy. This year, Macau then registered the highest abstention rate of 57.6%.
Asked yesterday, what impact expects on electoral participation, taking into account the decision and the fact that no details were disclosed about the reasons that led to disqualification, the president of Caeal stressed that “vote is a right, but also a duty” and promised to be aware of any acts of incitement to blank or null. These acts began to be punished with prison sentence, with the entry into force of the new law.
In the indirect suffrage, CDSE accepted all six lists of candidates.
 
Ron Lam of “Quiet Awareness” says he was not notified
The Jornal Tribuna de Macau tried to contact Ron Lam yesterday to get a comment on disqualification, but it was not possible. In a publication on his Facebook page, the deputy thanked the "concern" and said he had not received any notification: "I only learned of the information when I saw the broadcast of the news." Ron Lam said he was "calm" and "clean consciousness." "My original intention about Macau will not change. I believe the sun always comes after the wind and rain," he added, apologizing for not being able to continue to serve the population. The deputy also thanked the partners who have accompanied him and the supporters. This newspaper also tried to reach the speech with Alberto Wong, but it was equally impossible. The candidate also said on Facebook that he was not notified of the decision. "It will not change my position of loving the homeland and loving Macau. I will be faithful to masters as at the beginning," he said, apologizing to the supporters.
 
Government and connection office demonstrate “strong support”
Shortly after the announcement of the disqualification of 12 candidates, the Government of the MSAR issued a statement demonstrating “strong support” to the decision of the Assembly Electoral Affairs Committee, based on the opinion of the State Security Defense Commission. For the executive, "it is a correct measure for the full implementation of the fundamental principle" Macau governed by patriots ", can be read in the staff of the media. It is also said that "the defense of the basic law and the fidelity to the Mand of the People's Republic of China are the legal duties and the most fundamental political ethics than the deputies to the Legislative Assembly must observe." "Under the constitutional order established in the constitution of the RPC and the Basic Law, the people who are part of the masters' governance structure must be those who firmly love the homeland and Macao," the government. Also the central government connection office on the MSAR commented on the decision, supporting it "firmly." The spokesman argued that the deputies “must be convinced patriots” and stressed that, according to the laws in force, these decisions “have absolute authority and are unquestionable and unquestionable”</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao's historic center “materializes” “unique paradigm” between civilizations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-historico-de-macau-materializa-paradigma-impar-entre-civilizacoes/</link><description>Leong Wai Man highlighted the fundamental role of the Historic Center of Macau, which allowed to establish a dialogue between eastern and western cultures, during the commemorative ceremony of the 20th anniversary of the registration on the World Heritage list. The president of the Cultural Institute also underlined the efforts that have been developed within the scope of the safeguard of cultural heritage
 
Pedro Milheirão
"The" Historic Center of Macao ", as a strategic and crucial nucleus of the Seda Maritime Route, opened the doors to the East-Cultural Cultural Dialogue," said Leong Wai Man, during the inaugural ceremony of the 20th anniversary of the registration of that historic set on the World Heritage List, which took place at the Dom Pedro V. Theater.
For precisely two decades, “this cultural jewel born of a unique history” has been recognized by UNESCO and “became the first 'visiting card' at the global level, allowing the world to recognize the unique position and exceptional contribution of the territory as the confluence of eastern and western cultures,” said the president of the Cultural Institute (IC).
Leong Wai Man highlighted the fact that, for more than four hundred years, “Chinese and Western cultures have shone with mutual enhancement and harmonious coexistence, where Lingnan temples rise side by side with baroque churches, and Portuguese sidewalks serpen among Chinese courtyards. Like a tridimensional epic, this heritage, this heritage, this heritage Materializes a unique paradigm of peaceful coexistence and mutual enrichment between civilizations, ”he continued.
Since 2005 the government has been following the “concept of development and protection” of heritage. Collaborating with all sectors of society, it has sought to ensure “preservation and inheritance” and “innovative use” of the historic center. For this purpose, several initiatives were implemented, such as the construction of the legal system, the monitoring, repair and protection of science and technology, among others, accentuated the president of the CI.
These measures intend to establish an “effective barrier” to safeguard the Macao Historic Center, focusing on the revitalization and appreciation of heritage, the education of youth, social promotion and the creation of a cultural protection system that involves the entire population. “The safeguard of cultural heritage is a continuous civilizational legacy of perpetual transmission,” said Leong Wai Man.
"Today, in a new stage, we reaffirm our commitment to history and culture, guided by respect for the past and the valorization of heritage, reverence for history and love for culture. Based on the preservation of the historical and cultural roots of our world heritage, we will expand and streamline resources so that we can benefit society in general."
“We will strive to develop the singular role of the 'Historic Center of Macau' in promoting exchange and mutual knowledge at the international level, reinforcement and dissemination of Chinese culture abroad, building communication channels and sharing between different contemporary ethnic groups, to continue writing a new chapter of reciprocal permutations and learning between the Chinese and Western civilizations of Macau,” said the same responsible.
 
A “treasure” of humanity to continue to shine
The president of the IC also recalled the words of President XI Jinping, who praised Macau as "a bright pearl stuck on the banks of the Southern Sea of China" and a "precious part of the grandijosa homeland." He also appealed to the population to make efforts to protect a "cultural treasure that belongs to all humanity."
"We will guarantee that the essence of the dialogue between East and West, which is part of the Macao World Heritage, continues to shine and illuminate a future of peace and integration for all humanity," he concluded.
The celebrations at the Dom Pedro V Theater continued with a performance of the Chinese orchestra of Macao, which presented three songs, including an interpretation of the theme “Lisbon, Girl and Girl”. The occasion also served to launch the program “WORLD HERITAGE TOURS”. The event was also attended by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM.
In a response sent by the body to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the IC had already stressed that the inscription of the Historic Center allowed Macao to demonstrate to the world "its exceptional position and contribution to cultural exchange between China and the West, increasing their trust and cultural pride." He also stressed that over the two decades, "Macao cultural enterprises have recorded great progress." "World heritage has become an important resource for promoting cultural creation and innovation in all sectors and boosting diverse social development."
The feat also established "a solid base for the construction of Macao as" a base of exchange and cooperation for the promotion of multicultural coexistence, with a predominance of Chinese culture and a "World Center for Tourism and Leisure". The IC also acknowledged the “great support of the central government and the joint public efforts of the general public”, as well as the creation of the World Heritage safeguard law in 2013, and the Historic Center safeguard and management plan last year.
"The Government of MSAR always maintains an open attitude in the height of different opinions of all sectors of society, at the same time alarming the opinions and suggestions of the National Cultural Heritage Administration, the World Heritage Committee and professional protection institutions of World Heritage Protection, in order to do protection work well."
The body chaired by Leong Wai Man considers that "the revitalization of world heritage also fueled the spiritual and cultural life of residents, increasing the feeling of happiness in society and forming a consensus and public awareness of the protection of historical and cultural heritage."
The set of buildings that is now registered on the UNESCO list includes the Fortress of the Monte, the A-Má Temple, the Senate Largo and the Holy House of Mercy, the Dom Pedro V, the Ruins of São Paulo, the Temple of Na Tcha, the Sam Kai Vui Kun Temple, the House of Mandarin, the Sir Robert Ho Tang, the Library of Lilau, the Church of St. Lourenço, Casa Garden, the Fortress of the Guide, the Protestant Cemetery, the Church and Seminary of St. Joseph, the Church and the Largo de São Domingos, the House of Kou Kau and the Sé Church.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PORTUGUESE SCHOOL STUDY VISITS AWARE STUDENTS FOR HERITAGE</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitas-de-estudo-da-escola-portuguesa-sensibilizam-alunos-para-patrimonio/</link><description>Study visits to historic center places have been increasingly valued in the curriculum content of the Portuguese School of Macau. Working as an integration of content in the curriculum of Portugal, these activities are a call for attention to topics such as the arrival of the Portuguese to Macau and have aroused the interest of both students and teachers. Deolinda Santos, professor of the EPM History discipline, told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that these travels have contributed to “raising students to raise students to the importance of heritage protection”



















Victor Rebelo
 
Although they did not have the regularity that teachers would want, the study visits that students from the Portuguese School of Macau (EPM) have made some places in the Historic Center are considered of great importance for knowledge about the existing architectural heritage in the territory. The building of the former loyal Senate, current headquarters of the Institute for Municipal Affairs, was one of the last examples of visit by students of the 8th grade of the EPM, inserted in an outlined route when planning the school year made by the respective history teachers.
“Since the publication of our Macau-China manuals that we have worked on these contents and then we apply with the visits,” he began to tell the Jornal Tribuna de Macau Deolinda Santos. The teacher of the discipline says that these visits serve to “sensitize students to the importance of heritage protection”, at a time when Macau celebrates the 20th anniversary of the historic center's registration on the World Heritage Site list of the United Nations Education, Science and Culture (UNESCO) and which was designated as the 31st China World Heritage Site.
This inclusion, on July 15, 2005, also contributed to the conservation of the city's historical and architectural heritage and, in a broader context, represents an important part of China's history.
Although not only the immediate intention of marking the anniversary date of the registration of Macau as a World Heritage Site, “this type of initiatives is quite interesting and pleases students, who thus know the places of the historic center and some of the buildings that symbolize the first institutions of Macao,” says the teacher who has coordinated these travel to iconic places of MSc.
The teacher has the hypothesis that the ephemeris is highlighted in the next study visits. "In July or September we established the plan next school year and this is a good suggestion, remembering the 20 years of entry into UNESCO World Heritage," he said.
"The last time we were in the Leal Senate, but we had already visited other points of the historic center, such as the Santa Casa da Misericórdia, the former college of São Paulo and the Museum of Sacred Art, where we explained that there are small excavations, which were the Jesuit cells," said the teacher.
In addition, the study visits included the building of the former Hospital of São Rafael, currently the Portuguese General Consulate at Macao, and the Diocese of Macao. “It was very nice to have done all this route on foot for about an hour and a half,” he realizes.
The result of these programs is always published in the EPM school newspaper, Tempus &amp; Modus, in which students expose photographs and write small articles about the experience felt and they seized from the teacher's explanations, which served as a guide.
 
Contents inserted in the Portugal Program
Students, specifically those in the 8th grade, which are those who study the discoveries in the sixteenth century and the arrival of the Portuguese explorers in the following century, have a pre-stressed guide. “We plan the Portugal Program and we insert the contents of Macau-China, integrating them in due historical time,” he says, adding that it is curriculum adjustments, that is, an integration of content in the Portugal curriculum, “but only until 9th grade,” he recalled.
Participants in the study visits have a script, applying these travels to the tests they later do or in work they produce. “A few years ago, they did beautiful things like 3D models, which I think are in the school library, but now time is scarcer,” he says.
Deolinda Santos would like to, therefore, that these initiatives to take students to the street to learn more about the historic center and feel how important the protection of heritage is, or even visiting exhibitions, if they were more often.
"About hour and a week for a few school years and almost two hours for others is very little for so many content and so there is no time to do more study visits, because I think this in the spot knowledge of the first institutions of Macau, either Portuguese, and Chinese," he continued.
The teacher, who is one of the oldest to teach in the EPM, performing uninterrupted functions since 1993, considers that these initiatives are also important to their own “personal and professional valorization”.
Deolinda Santos recalls that there is a discipline of History and Geography imposed by the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ). “Then I also have to approach these themes, but it is different, it is not the arrival of the Portuguese to Macau, but the globalization, the role of China in the world, the first dynasties, which is also an interesting program,” he explains, adding that there are also exits from students, since, in this case, there is greater flexibility. “We have been, with the eldest students, from the 12th grade, to Sun Yat Sen's house, as well as visited the Seda Route exhibition on MGM,” he recalls.
As a support element for these study visits, DSEDJ has edited some small books, “very good,” notes the teacher. "These are publications that have helped us a lot, about the history of China, but more and more also about Macau, which was little accessible when I arrived here," he concludes.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau will have “Reading Festival”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-vai-ter-festival-de-leitura/</link><description>???????



To “stimulate the interest” of more citizens in reading, the Cultural Institute plans to launch a “reading festival” later this year. In addition, Leong Wai Man revealed that programs will be launched to promote reading in day care centers, elderly and companies
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Cultural Institute (IC) plans to launch, in the second half of the year, a new festival dedicated to reading. Titled “Macau Reading Festival”, it will combine book fairs, lectures, as well as cultural and creative fairs with outdoor reading activities, revealed the body's president, Leong Wai Man, in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Ma Io Fong. The objective is to “stimulate the interest of many more citizens in reading, to achieve the aim of promoting reading with community neighborhoods and reinforcing the dissemination of the 'reading city'”.
Regarding the “Baby and Children Reading Program”, launched in 2023 and directed to babies and children under two, IC is thinking widening it. Currently the materials are dedicated to content ranging from illustrative reading to the training of thought and tactile exercise, among others, being the appropriate books for autonomous reading and also for parents and children together.
"IC is reevaluating the species and amount of books in reading bags and studying the viability of widening the program to children aged 3 to 5, so that many more children have the opportunity to participate, seeking to further promote the generalization of reading culture and joint reading between parents and children," read.
He also recalled that the IC and the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services collaborated in the implementation of various reading plans in schools. In addition, in collaboration with the Institute of Social Action, “the promotion of reading to day care and elderly care will be widened, creating a reading atmosphere for people of all age layers”.
Later this year, a “parent -child reading cooperation program in day care centers” and a program for “libraries in community neighborhoods” will be launched, “in order to extend reading resources to the care institutions to the elderly, day care centers and companies, in order to promote reading culture with people of all ages”.
Leong Wai Man also assured that the IC will continue to implement the concept "to be based on the population and reading of all age groups", from the construction of spaces, distribution of resources to the extension to community neighborhoods, generally promoting the culture of reading to the entire population, "towards the construction of an inclusive and innovative" city of reading ".
In the same response to Ma Io Fong, the president of the IC also recalled that the body has been optimizing library facilities and enriching online collections and resources.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chinese economy grows 5.2%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/economia-chinesa-cresce-52/</link><description>The Chinese economy grew 5.2% in the second quarter of the year, according to official data that coincide with analyst predictions, thanks to the good performance of exports and despite the US trade war. In view of the previous quarter, the world's second largest economy expanded 1.1%, according to the National Statistics Office (GNE).
In the first semester, China's gross domestic product grew 5.3%, in homologous terms.
One of the main engines of growth was exports. On Monday, authorities announced that sales abroad increased 5.8% in June, compared to the same month of the previous year, accelerating the 4.8% registered in May. Temporary relief from punitive tariffs on Chinese products in the US, as part of the resumption of commercial negotiations between the two countries, led to a sudden increase in orders by companies and consumers.
Chinese companies have also sought to diversify export destinations and reinforce production in other countries as a way to mitigate the impact of the tariffs imposed by Washington.
“Generally speaking, with the application of more proactive and effective macroeconomic policies, the national economy maintained stable growth, with good dynamics, demonstrating resilience and vitality,” reads the GNE report.
Chinese leaders set a growth target of 5% for this year, in line with the expansion recorded in 2024. However, the resuming of US tariffs, which can reach 245% if Washington and Beijing do not reach a new trade agreement until August 12, could compromise export recovery.
China's industrial production rose 6.8% in June, a percentage point above the amount recorded in May, according to data released yesterday, widely exceeding analysts' predictions, which anticipated a slowdown to 5.6%. Among the three major sectors, the largest expansion was recorded in the transforming industry, with a growth of 7.4%, followed by mining sectors (+6.1%) and the production and supply of electricity, heating, gas and water (1.8%). In the accumulated 2025, industrial production has a rise of 6.4%.
The GNE also highlighted the strong growth of specific segments in the first half, such as the production of 3D (+43.1%, in homologous terms), electric vehicles (+36.2%) and industrial robots (+35.6%).
On the other hand, other indicators point to signs of weakness in domestic consumption and investment. Retail sales, a barometer of families consumption, grew only 4.8% in June, retreating to 6.4% in May and being below the forecast of 5.6%.
The official urban unemployment rate remained stable in the 5% for the second consecutive month, in line with expectations.
Investment in fixed assets, in turn, grew 2.8% in the first half, below 3.7% accumulated until May and below stability estimates or slight increase.
By sectors, the investment in the transformative sector rose 7.5%, the infrastructure increased 4.6%, while the real estate sector worsened the retraction, with a drop of 11.2%, after retreating 10.7%between January and May, reflecting the prolonged crisis of the sector.
Sales of commercial real estate, measures through the area of construction, fell 3.5% in homologous terms until June. In a separate report, the GNE revealed that the prices of new housing in 70 large cities retreated 0.27% between May and June, registering the 25th consecutive month of falls.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Firefighters for fire decreased 10% by June</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/saidas-de-bombeiros-para-incendios-diminuiram-10-ate-junho/</link><description>In the first half of this year, the number of fire departures registered breaks in several strands, including in cases of fires, which lowered about 11%
 
Between January and June this year, the Fire Department (CB) performed 406 exits due to fires, which corresponds to a reduction of 49 cases or 10.77%, compared to the same period of 2024, the corporation released yesterday.
Specifically, 321 fire exits did not involve the use of hoses, representing 79.06% of the total number. On the other hand, there were 78 cases of burnt food.
According to statistics, the main causes of fires included forgetting to turn off the stoves, non-fully extinguished flames, burning incense and candles or votive papers, short circuit of electrical installations and mechanical or equipment failures, totaling 255 cases, either 62.81% of total fire exits.
On the other hand, the CB accounted for 22,388 cases of ambulance departure for first aid in the first six months of this year, which reflects a decrease of 3.53% (less 819 cases) compared to the same period of 2024. According to the corporation, the breakdown should be mainly reduced in the cases of mild fever and breathing difficulties. In general, help situations involved mainly cases of dizziness, abdominal pain, respiratory difficulties, vomiting, fever and various types of injuries.
In total, 25,966 fire departures were recorded between January and June, which reflects an annual break of 6.1% (1,688 less cases).
At the same time, firefighters also dealt with 833 rescue operations (-9.06%) and provided 2,339 special services (-23.96%).
In the context of fire safety work, the CB made 4,197 inspections in the first half. Regarding the punishments, 50 cases of the administrative sanctioning procedure were completed during this period, which involved the motorcycle parking lot and the placement of objects in evacuation paths. In addition, in eight cases administrative sanctioning procedures have already been developed.
Simultaneously, in the “Fire Security Manager Training Course”, the CB formed 11,715 individuals until June this year. On the other hand, it also carried out 3,382 Dangerous Substance Security Inspection Actions.
In the chapter of awareness, in the first half of this year, the corporation performed 18 stages of fire fighting, with 689 participants, and 55 evacuation and incident simulacres, with the participation of 15,021 people, with the purpose of strengthening citizens' ability to respond in case of emergency. It also organized 307 disclosure activities, including 86 leaps on fire protection, disaster prevention, emergency medical knowledge and fuel safety, which had the participation of 6,944 individuals.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau and Hong Kong reinforce data protection bonds</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-hong-kong-reforcam-lacos-na-proteccao-de-dados/</link><description>The authorities responsible for protecting RAE's personal data signed an agreement to foster cooperation in the digital age, within the large bay
 
The Directorate of Personal Data Protection Services (DSPDP) and the Commissioner for Personal Data Protection (PCPD, English acronym) have signed a memorandum of understanding in the domain of personal data privacy protection.
Cooperation between the two bodies covers “the exchange of work experiences and good practices in the fields of law execution” and the “collaborative promotion of the ordered transion and personal data insurance in the Great Bay, as well as the provision of mutual support within the investigation or execution of the law”, can read in a statement.
DSPDP director Yang Chongwei has asserted that the agreement “not only promotes healthy and ordained development of the digital economy of Hong Kong and Macao”, but also “fully exploits the potential of data and injects a new dynamic in the economic and social prosperity of the great bay”, under the “guarantee of personal data protection”.
Ada Chung Lai-Ling, the PCPD commissioner, said that the signing of the memorandum of understanding "can further reinforce contacts between the supervision entities of the two regions, fully play the 'contact super agent' and 'surplus' super-agent' roles."
Collaboration with the MSAR entity aims to face “challenges brought by the digital age to protect personal data privacy,” added Ada Chung Lai-Ling. This understanding will also allow “promoting, together, the development of the digital economy in the large bay, contributing to the high quality development of the country”.
 
Creation of data spaces
However, DSPDP received a visit from the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the “International Data Spaces Association” (IDSA), Reinhold Acetz, and his entourage. According to a press release, the two parts discussed the prospect of "promoting the creation of data spaces and the exchange between the two parts to jointly face data governance challenges in the global digitization process."
Yang Chongwei presented the work developed at the areas of supervision, coordination and promotion of the Personal Data Protection Law, and emphasized that a balance between personal data protection and the promotion of data flow safely and ordered should be maintained.
Currently, the concept of data spaces is consolidating in China and Europe, while in Macau is yet to develop, he noted. Yang Chongwei said he hoped that, through this meeting, he could explore the viability of creating reliable data spaces in Macao to reach "a more perfected and more mutual confidence for the worldwide data exchange."
Reinhold Acetz praised the efforts and results obtained by DSPDP and said that the creation of highly interperoper and safe data spaces and the application of transfers transfer technology “play a key role in promoting digital economy and innovation”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>USJ and Catholic launch online degree in Data Science</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/usj-catolica-lancam-licenciatura-online-em-ciencia-de-dados/</link><description>The Degree in Data Science and Technology launched by the Portuguese Catholic University and the University of São José is intended for “students from any part of the world”. The course is fully taught in remote and English regime

The Portuguese Catholic University (UCP) and the University of São José (USJ) launched the degree in Data Science and Technology, which is fully taught under e-learning. The course is intended for “students from anywhere in the world”, has a duration of three years, and will be taught in English, from the Electronic Platform of the Faculty of Philosophy and Social Sciences of UCP, according to USJ.
According to José Miguel Vilaça, a professor at UCP, the candidacies are already open and anyone can compete "regardless of their location, as long as they meet some basic criteria." These include “English proficiency”, “minimum qualifications equivalent to secondary education” and online “specific access tests”. Miguel Vilaça added that students need “only an internet access computer”, “good English knowledge” and “a strong motivation to interact and learn”.
The program combines “a avant-garde curriculum and an innovative teaching methodology” and “stands out as an ideal choice for those who want to be on the front line of emerging data processing technologies by strongly using artificial intelligence,” according to the statement. The diploma will be issued by the Portuguese institution, with recognition “in Portugal and Macau, all over Europe (Bologna space) and in virtually everyone”.
Adérito Fernandes-Marcos, professor at USJ and coordinator of the institution's participation in the program, stressed that the “course represents an international collaboration of extreme relevance”. For the teacher, "Macao has the potential to establish himself as a global center for knowledge dissemination," which includes participation in distance learning models that combine "exceptional quality and alignment with the highest international standards."
Providing a “flexible and affordable” educational experience, the degree is “a unique opportunity to dive into the world of science and data technology, a rapid rise area,” you can read. Want students to “start an exciting career” or “explore new professional horizons”, the course is “a passport to a future full of possibilities and innovation” that will prepare a “path to the most desired professions of the digital age”, according to universities.
 
Prison Study Program has already benefited 69 inmates
A total of 24 prisoners from the Coloane prison recently completed the 2024/2025 school year under the program created by the University of São José (USJ), and certified to 19 of them were assigned. "At USJ, we believe in growth potential and second occasions," said the dean of the higher education institution, Stephen Morgan, quoted in a statement. The program began in 2009, and then interrupted and resumed again in 2018. Since it exists, it has benefited a total of 69 inmates, the USJ said in a statement. “As an institution in, and to Macao, USJ takes its responsibility for sustainable development and improvement of the society of Macao. This program is a key element in the fulfillment of its duty to the society of Macao,” reads a statement issued yesterday. The program has been coordinated by Professor Helen Lio.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lecture, Workshops and “Illusions Gemeas” inaugurate Art Biennial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/palestra-workshops-ilusoes-gemeas-inauguram-bienal-de-arte/</link><description>For the inauguration of the Macao International Art Biennial, the Cultural Institute will organize a lecture and two workshop sessions at the Macao Art Museum. On the same day, the exhibition “Illusions Gemeas” will also be presented

The Cultural Institute (IC) will launch two special events next Saturday “to expand artistic dialogue”, under the opening of “Macau Art: International Art Biennial of Macao”. At 3 pm, the main curator, Feng Boyi, will moderate a lecture that will bring together curators Liu Gang and Wu Wei and artists Song Dong and Xue Feng. The discussion will be held in Mandarin, with an English translation at the Macao Museum of Art (MAM), according to the IC.
During the lecture, guest speakers will dissect the Biennial, "to discuss exposure themes, concepts, implementation details, resulting discrepancies and results." The dilemmas and questions that "curatorship currently faces, as well as thought, strategies and solutions involved."
In turn, artist Chan Hung-Lu will lead two workshops, under the theme "Exploration of Interior Aliens." Chan will make use of the exposed works and guide participants to "mentally visualize the other aliens through the mobile phone." Workshops will be conducted in Mandarin and want participants to reflect "on origins and differences through meditation practices and image generation technology for artificial intelligence."
In the MAM, the exhibition “Games” by the German artist Gregor Schneider, an exploration of the “simulation phenomenon through contextual overlap” will also be evident. According to the statement, the museum has already started recruiting volunteer groups, "preferably twin brothers." Candidates must be of age of the same genre and have "a high degree of physical and height similarity." Registration is still open, and the admitted candidates will receive training to participate in the performance of the exhibition.
Registration for other biennial activities are also open and can be done in the single account. “The occasion invites the sharing of ideas and experiences between local and international and public artists, in a fertile dialogue between concepts and artistic practices,” can read.
This year's Biennial is dedicated to the theme “Hello, what do you do here?”. The main exhibition, patent until October 19, brings together 46 artists from 13 countries and regions, with about 80 works on display. The pieces and sets of works will be distributed in 20 spaces in the MAM. The museum will also have “unconventional exhibition spaces and transition zones between pavilions” and “miniatures of visual art that transcend time and space”. Visitors will have the opportunity to “feel and experience the cultural diversity of the world and Macau”.
The event will be divided into six sections, namely the “Main Exhibition”, the “Public Art Exhibition”, the “Pavilion of the City”, the “Special Exhibition”, the “Local Curator Project” and the “Collateral Exhibition”, with about 30 art shows.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CCM receives “auspicious arrival”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ccm-recebe-chegada-auspiciosa/</link><description>“Auspicious arrival” marks the end of this season of the Chinese orchestra of Macao. The concert will take place at the Macao Cultural Center on July 26, with the participation of Jinghu Master Wang Caiyun, Yangqin Liu Yinxuan and Soprano Cui Rui soloist
 
The Chinese orchestra of Macao will present the last concert of this season, entitled “Auspicious Arrival”. Scheduled for July 26, at 8 pm, the show will take place in the large auditorium of the Macao Cultural Center, the Cultural Institute said.
Under the baton of the orchestra music director and main conductor, Zhang Lie, the concert will be attended by Jinghu Master Wang Caiyun, Yangqin soloist Liu Yinxuan and Soprani Cui Rui, “featuring an exciting program that intertwines classics of Chinese music and the legendary essence of Beijing Opera, in order to make the public know the public to the public of reputable musicians ”.
The concert will bring together several artists of excellence, says the body, indicating that they will interpret several timeless classic works. Yangqin soloist Liu Yinxuan will interpret the concert for Yangqin “Rapsódia” by the renowned composer Wang Danhong, which, according to the IC, “highlights the infinite expressive possibilities of the instrument through the use of varied execution techniques and great musical expressiveness”.
Jinghu Master Wang Caiyun will perform, along with the orchestra, Beijing's Spirit, a Wu Hua work, "which requires a masterful technical domain of the Jinghu and reveals the artistic charm of the instruments." In turn, Soprano Cui Rui will play Goodbye, My Concubine, a Guan Xia National Symphonic Poem, which recreates the epic history of Xiang Yu and the Consort Yu with a vocal approach inspired by the Chinese opera, "giving this Chinese cultural treasure a new life."
Organized by the IC and co-organized by the limited Macao Orchestra Society, the Macao 2024-2025 Chinese Orchestra Concerts season also has the support of Banco da China (Macau). Tickets for the closing concert are for sale at the Macao online box office at 380, 250, 180 and 120 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Art Space” of the Taipa presents “Fan Paintings”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/art-space-da-taipa-apresenta-pinturas-de-leques/</link><description>The “Art Space” of Taipa village today hosts the exhibition “Paintings of Chinese Folding Fatcans” by artist Chao Iok Leng. The works will be on display until September

The Vila da Taipa Cultural Association inaugurates this Wednesday the exhibition “Paintings of Chinese Folding Fats” by Chao Iok Leng, in “Taipa Village Art Space”. The show will be evident until September 17, between 12:00 and 20h00, with free admission. According to the organization, Chao brings a "refreshing approach" to the tradition of Chinese Fan painting, with a "masterful use of Chinese paint in a rare intersection of art and beauty."
These accessories “are unusual treasures in the agitation of contemporary urban life”. The exhibition aims to increase the “appreciation of beauty and tranquility through the display of these precious objects rooted in the former Chinese culture”. Folding fans emerged in Asia to refresh their users, and they also functioned as “ornaments, status symbols and personal taste expressions,” the press release says.
The Chinese tradition of painting fans began during the Tang Dynasty, during which artists were inspired to “think creatively” and paint “with precision and great mastery”. The application of Chinese paint, developed more than two thousand years ago, requires “meticulous attention to detail” as it is quickly absorbed by the thin paper of the fans, which makes any retouching or correction difficult.
Chao Iok Leng, from Guangdong, lived in Macao most of his life, having developed a "deep and expansive interest" for art from an early age. In the 1970s, the artist studied with Guan Wanli and learned to paint flowers and birds. Later, he studied Western painting with Li Lun. At the end of this decade, he moved to Hong Kong, where he continued to study flower and bird painting, as well as landscapes, with Lui Zuishan. He also learned handwriting from Liang Zijiang.
Returned to Macao, he studied Chinese and Western painting with Zhao Weifu and, in the 1980s, studied Lingnan painting with Zhao Shaoang. In Beijing he developed his painting of flowers and birds with Xu Junxiu. Chao held his first exhibition at the Luís de Camões Museum in 1987. In the 1990s in Vancouver, he studied floral painting and landscapes with Song Weyuan. In 1996, the Directorate of Tourism Services invited Chao to present “The Charm of Leisure”.
He is currently vice president of the Yi Un Caligraphy and Painting Association, a member of Macau Artist Society and advisor to various local associations. João Ó, president of the Vila da Taipa Cultural Association, said that Chao interprets “skillfully the beauty of range leak paintings in different living elements that are not necessarily obvious, but, however, feed our lives”.
The Association promises to continue to make efforts to display art works by local and international artists in Vila da Taipa.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mandar confirms record delegation of national games</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-confirma-delegacao-recorde-dos-jogos-nacionais/</link><description>Macau wants to send the largest delegation ever to China's national games, which will take place in November, with the territory to host evidence of five modalities, the Institute of Sport (ID) indicated, thus confirming the intention expressed in May by the president of the body in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau. In a statement issued on Monday night, ID said the MSAR intends to have athletes in 23 modalities and teams in 14 modalities of the 15th edition of the National Games. The last games have taken place in the province of Shaanxi, in the northeast of the country, in September 2021, involving more than 12,000 athletes in 35 modalities, and ended with 12 new world records. The ID stressed that it “attributes great importance” to the games - the main Chinese sports event, which takes place every four years - because Macau will be “one of the hosts”. Macao will welcome all 3 × 3 table tennis and basketball tests, five-year-old men's under-18 basketball competition and the women's volleyball tournament, as well as an amateur karate competition, open to the entire population. The 15th edition will take place between November 9th and 21st and, for the first since its inception, in 1959, will include evidence outside the mainland China. In addition to being, the games will take place simultaneously in Hong Kong and Macau. Macao will also host two Badminton events, for people with physical or hearing disabilities and for people with intellectual disabilities, under the Special Olympic Games of China, which will take place from December 8 to 15.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Economic Association foresees a 2.8% GDP rise in the 1st semester</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacao-economica-preve-subida-pib-de-28-1o-semestre/</link><description>The Gross Domestic Product (GDP) of the MSAR will have grown about 2.8% in the first half of 2025, in annual terms, anticipated the Macao Economic Association. Considering only the second quarter, the association points to a 7%homologous growth. "In the first half of the year, although Macao's economy suffered from the impact of the weak external demand, the volume of visitors, the hotel occupancy rate, the total number of the active population and the unemployment rate, among other indicators, stable, with the support of the country, which generally shows some resilience," the association under the most recent study of the field economic perspectives. Although they warn of the persistence of “many external uncertainty factors,” the authors of the report believe that with continuous central government support, the local economy will remain stable in the second half of this year. Regarding the third quarter, the association's analyzes indicate that the economic perspective index may be between 5.8 and 5.9 points. In the study, the association again appeals to joint government and market efforts, in favor of optimizing the business environment and promoting industrial diversification, given that “Macao's economy is in an essential phase of transformation and development”. Thus, it is convinced that the local economy will gain greater integrated competitiveness and realize sustainable development. In addition, the economic perspectives for May and June reached 6.1 and 5.9 points, respectively, maintaining a “stable” level. Among the positive aspects, the study emphasizes that the impulse of concerts contributed to macroeconomic performance in May and June exceeded market expectations. However, it also recalls that, in the same period, consumer confidence and demand continued to be weak. It is recalled that, according to official data, Macao GDP retreated 1.3% in annual and real terms in the first quarter of this year, equivalent to 85.2% of the economic volume of the same period of 2019. The amount also represented a decrease of 6.1% compared to the last three months of 2024, marking the sixth consecutive quarter of slowdown.</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Worse than pandemic’: Searches for immigrants paralyze trade in Los Angeles</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/pior-pandemia-buscas-por-imigrantes-paralisam-comercio-em-los-angeles/</link><description>Nayomie Mendoza was used to seeing a line of customers graduate at her restaurant at lunchtime in the Los Angeles Fashion neighborhood, La Fashion District. But the migratory operations of Donald Trump's administration have emptied their tables.
"Our sales fell 80%," he told AFP Mendoza, responsible for Cuernavaca's Grill, a colorful Mexican restaurant in the popular commercial neighborhood.
"What saves us is that we have a lot of home shipments, about 20%," said Mendoza, explaining that many are afraid of going to the streets in the region.
In the heart of Los Angeles, La Fashion District is a vibrant neighborhood with numerous clothing and accessories stores, but with a predominant Latin labor, it has also become the target of Trump's anti-immigration offensive, with factories operations and other Los Angeles commercial points.
Now its sidewalks are empty, even this beginning of summer, when tourists fill the Californian city.
The Trump administration increased pressure on Los Angeles, a declared "sanctuary" of protection for immigrants by its democratic authorities as opposed to the Republican President.
With a third of the population of foreign origin and an estimate of hundreds of thousands of people in irregular situation, the federal investment against immigrants enraged the inhabitants, who took to the streets to protest last month.
The Trump government, however, does not seem willing to retreat.
"It's better for us to get used to us, because it will soon be normal. Let us go everywhere, when we want, in Los Angeles," US Fox News Gregory of the US Border, warning that "the federal government will not leave Los Angeles."
But Nayomie Mendoza states that operations not only reach foreign or without document, but also entire industries, at a time when traders try to recover from a difficult beginning of the year after the voracious fires that hit the Los Angeles region in January.
Due to the lack of customers, Mendoza closes the doors at 15:00. A contrast with last year, when working until night due to demand. "This is probably worse than pandemic," he said.
Manuel Suárez, owner of a toy store on a street near the restaurant, agrees. "Now it's worse because in the pandemic, although it was pandemic, there was sales," said Suárez, who has been working in the popular neighborhood for 35 years.
"It is now completely in crisis," he lamented, explaining that many traders have decided to close the stores as a precaution as the operations intensify in the city.
Others reduced the number of employees due to the drop in sales.
 
“The cat and the mouse”
The operations “sowed fear in our Latin community,” said Jose Yern, Anita’s Bridal Boutique, specializing in debutante dresses.
"People are afraid of coming (to the district), but if they come, they go to a specific store, do what they have to do and then come home," the merchant added, while in the past, potential customers walked among the colorful dresses exposed on mannequins.
Fear is palpable on the streets: any siren sound fires the alerts. Traders communicate with Walkie-Talkies and notify any noise, helicopter, or uniform presence on the nearby streets to warn those who have no documents.
Some even watch the roofs and give the warning signal to the cry of "The Migra".
"It is unfortunate that the government does not understand that when it attacks us, we all lost," said a seller who preferred not to identify himself. "But let's not leave. What will happen here is that we will be playing the cat and mouse. Let's see who gets tired first."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>