<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Taxi sector “earned” more than 350 million in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-dos-taxis-ganhou-mais-de-350-milhoes-em-2024/</link><description>The taxi sector closed the 2024 accounts with a positive gross surplus of 354 million patacas, 4.2% less in annual terms. In urban public passenger transport services, which include buses and the Metro, the final balance fell by around 27% to 313 million, according to official data
 
SERGIO TERRA
 
Last year, the taxi sector's gross surplus (revenue plus changes in stocks, minus expenses) amounted to 354.2 million patacas, a figure that represents a decrease of 4.2% compared to the 369.9 million recorded in 2023, revealed the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC).
According to official data analyzed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, in 2024, 995 taxis and similar establishments were in operation – including vehicles registered in individual names -, which translates into an annual drop of 226 or 18.5%. Still, the number of workers in the sector fell just 1.5% to 2,334.
Revenue from taxis and similar establishments reached around 1.15 billion patacas, maintaining the same level as in 2023, however, expenses rose 2% to 794.1 million.
The six companies providing public urban passenger transport services (buses and light rail) employed 3,102 individuals (+3.3%), collected revenues of 2.72 billion patacas (-6.1%) and incurred expenses of 2.36 billion (-6.1%). Thus, the gross surplus of this sector fell by 26.7% to 313 million patacas.
In turn, the gross surplus of the 21 cross-border and border bus operators grew by 25.6% to around 194.6 million patacas. These companies, which had 442 employees (+15.4%), recorded revenues of 532.8 million patacas (+23.3%) and expenses of 338.5 million (+22.1%), with DSEC associating these variations with the increase in the number of passengers who traveled between the SARs via the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macao Bridge.
Overall, revenues from land transport companies (5.55 billion patacas) increased by 0.6% in the space of one year and revenues fell by 1.1% to 4.44 billion patacas, leading to a positive gross surplus of 1.06 billion (-0.9%).
Among companies dedicated to the road transport of goods, revenues reached 854.2 million patacas (+0.6%) and expenses decreased by 9% to 684.7 million. Therefore, the gross surplus grew 73.4% to 168.7 million.
On the other hand, the gross surplus of the 972 establishments with ancillary and auxiliary transport activities increased by 26.3% to 1.58 billion, driven by the 11.6% increase in revenue (9.54 billion), including 5.44 billion from travel agencies (+7.5%). General expenses in this transport sub-branch amounted to 7.96 billion (+9.1%), with travel agency expenses totaling 5.08 billion (+5.6%).
Data from 2024 also points to a gross surplus of 112 million in maritime transport (-14.9%), with revenues (1.21 billion) and expenses (1.10 billion) increasing by 5.9% and 8.5%, respectively.
In turn, air transport recorded revenues of 5.36 billion (+21.4%) and expenses of 5.38 billion (+26.9%), generating a deficit of 17 million, after ending 2023 with a positive surplus of 181 million.
The DSEC survey also involved the sub-branch of telecommunications services, whose gross surplus reached 2.58 billion patacas (+17.7%), signaling revenues of 6.37 billion (-0.5%) and expenses of 4.13 billion (-0.8%).</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Simplification of issuing licenses meets restoration requirements</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/simplificacao-da-emissao-de-licencas-satisfaz-exigencias-da-restauracao/</link><description>Before the AL approved the proposed law that aims to simplify the licensing procedure for catering establishments, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, Wong Sio Chak, assured that the new rules have “broad coverage” and can meet the sector’s demands
 
Unanimously, the Legislative Assembly (AL) approved yesterday, in general, the proposal for the “Law on the activity of restaurants and beverages and related establishments”. According to Wong Sio Chak, Secretary for Administration and Justice, the revision of the law allows the time for issuing the restoration license to be shortened from the current 40 working days to just two working days.
Under the diploma, catering establishments installed in autonomous units with a useful area not exceeding 120 square meters and which, before opening, only require simple renovation works, or which do not require any works, can register, instead of licensing. The registration certificate may be issued two working days after receipt of complete documents.
According to the Secretary, currently, 31,000 catering establishments in the territory, 91% of the total, have a useful area of ​​no more than 120 square meters, while around 2,200 restaurants with licenses issued by the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM), more than 60% of the total, have an area equal to or less than that limit, which means that the new rules have “broad coverage”. Furthermore, Wong Sio Chak assured that the changes will meet the sector's demands.
In the discussion, the deputy elected by indirect suffrage Kevin Ho asked that the simplification of the licensing procedure be extended to restaurants with a larger area. Wong Sio Chak responded that it is impossible for the measure to be applied without limits, warning that, otherwise, safety in restaurants would not be properly guaranteed. As he added, the limit of 120 square meters is based on the legal regime for urban construction.
The diploma also recommends that there are only two types of licenses – “restaurant and beverage establishments”, supervised by the IAM, and “dance halls”, whose supervisory entity is the Directorate of Tourism Services. Chao Wai Ieng, chairman of the IAM Board of Directors, indicated that, in order to “allow the sector to start operating more quickly”, both the license and the registration certificate can be requested through a standardized electronic platform, without the need for face-to-face processing of applicants.
Furthermore, the Secretary stressed that the simplification of the assessment procedure constitutes the spirit of the law review, yet the authorities will not relax in supervising food, health and construction safety. The change is based on the fact that, in the future, the competent entity will carry out the inspection after the restaurant opens. "If problems are detected, the restaurant in question, even if already open, will have to be subject to correction, complying with the requirements, and temporarily close its doors. It will only be able to reopen if it meets the requirements again", stressed the Secretary.
Overall, Wong Sio Chak concluded that the revision of the law represents a “drastic simplification” of the technical requirements, which, in the future, will be defined to be “simple” and “minimally necessary for a catering establishment to operate”. “And in terms of service experience, it is believed that operators will try to make as much effort as possible to guarantee the comfort and safety of their customers”, continued the government official.
Furthermore, according to the Secretary, a transitional plan will be defined regarding the transfer of old restaurants.
On the other hand, nominated deputy Lam Fat Iam warned of the risk of the “World Heritage style becoming out of control”, taking into account that the diploma provides that works to modify and repair the exterior appearance carried out in buildings “outside the published picturesque streets or on lots not immediately adjacent to classified properties or in the process of being classified do not require the prior opinion of the Cultural Institute (IC)”.
According to Choi Kin Long, vice-president of the IC, even so, the IC will issue an opinion on reconstruction and construction works, in order to control the volume and height of buildings in the buffer zones.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss presents LAG on November 18th</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-apresenta-lag-dia-18-de-novembro/</link><description>On November 18th, the Chief Executive will go to AL to present the Lines of Government Action for 2026. A day later, Sam Hou Fai returns to the Hemicycle to answer questions from deputies. The sectoral debates then begin on November 21st, with Administration and Justice, and end on December 1st, with the Transport and Public Works portfolio
 
The Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, will present the Governing Action Lines (LAG) report for 2026 on November 18th, at 3 pm, at the Legislative Assembly (AL). A press conference will then follow, scheduled for 5:30 pm, at Government Headquarters, during which Sam Hou Fai “will answer questions from the media”, according to a press release.
One day later, November 19, the Chief Executive returns to the AL plenary to answer questions from deputies about the LAG report for the next financial year.
The LAG sectoral debates then follow, starting with the Administration of Justice portfolio, now in the hands of Wong Sio Chak, who will go to the Hemicycle on November 21st. The Secretary for Economy and Finance, Tai Kin Ip, will present his ideas to deputies on November 24th.
The LAGs in the Security area, now headed by Chan Tsz King, will be announced on November 26th. The former Public Prosecutor, who was also a Commissioner against Corruption, will make his debut in presenting the LAG to the deputies.
Secretary O Lam, in turn, will go to AL on November 28th, to present the proposals within the scope of Social Affairs and Culture. Finally, it will be Raymond Tam's turn, Secretary for Transport and Public Works, to report on his portfolio's projects for next year. The meeting with deputies is scheduled for December 1st.
According to the Social Communication Office, the presentation session of the LAG Report, the press conference and the plenary meeting will be broadcast directly on TDM (Television and Radio). The public will also be able to watch the broadcast via the internet, in real time, by accessing the Macao SAR Government portal, and the pages of the Office of the Chief Executive, the AL, the GCS, as well as the page on the LAG Report or through the applications “Office of the Chief Executive” or “Macau Government News”, as well as on the exclusive YouTube channel of the Office of the Chief and the GCS and on the GCS Facebook page.
In addition, the GCS Facebook page, in Portuguese and English, will also publish information about the LAG for 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kong Chi returns to the dock</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/kong-chi-volta-ao-banco-dos-reus/</link><description>Former deputy prosecutor Kong Chi and two other defendants in the case returned to the dock yesterday. For more than two hours, the judge of the Court of Second Instance read the indictment, according to which Kong Chi committed almost 80 crimes
 
Former deputy prosecutor Kong Chi and two other defendants were again present in court yesterday, due to accusations of bribery and malfeasance. In addition to Kong Chi, the first defendant, lawyer Ho Kam Meng and businesswoman Choi Sao Ieng were also present. In turn, lawyer Kuan Hoi Lon was absent.
According to the Chinese-language press, the judge of the Court of Second Instance (TSI) spent more than two hours reading the indictment, according to which, for example, Kong Chi and Ho Kam Ming were jointly accused of ten crimes of accepting bribes to commit illegal acts and 56 crimes of malfeasance. Ho Kam Ming was also accused of participating in or supporting a criminal organization.
According to the indictment, between 2008 and 2022, Kong Chi and the rest formed an organized group, conspiring with internal and external people to receive payments ranging from tens of thousands to hundreds of thousands of patacas per case. They will have facilitated the “withdrawal of charges” against individuals under investigation in several criminal investigations, with the majority of cases subsequently dropped. According to the judge, this allowed the suspects to escape prosecution and avoid sanctions.
In February this year, Kong Chi was sentenced by the Court of Final Instance (TUI) to a single sentence of 21 years in prison, a legal maximum. This sentence represented an increase in the 17-year sentence imposed by the TSI in January 2024 in a case in which Kong was accused of helping people escape justice in 30 cases. At the time, he was found guilty of dozens of crimes from passive corruption to an unlawful act, abuse of power, malfeasance and violation of judicial secrecy.
The TUI considered at the beginning of the year that Kong Chi was also guilty of the crime of association or secret society, validating the Public Prosecutor's thesis. According to the indictment, the main defendant received bribes, in collusion with the business couple Choi Sao Ieng and Ng Wai Chu, to interfere in several criminal investigation cases, illegally close the processes and collect the seized assets. Choi and Ng's sentences were also increased by the TUI, from 14 to 16 years and from six to 10 years in prison, respectively.
It should be remembered that, in June, Kong Chi was formally dismissed from his duties, as published at the time in the Official Bulletin. The Public Prosecutor's Council imposed “the defendant Kong Chi, who performed the functions of deputy prosecutor, the penalty of dismissal”, which was authorized by the Chief Executive. Dated June 4, the notice was signed by Council Chairman and Public Prosecutor Chan Tsz King.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Legends Li Na and Conchita Martínez at the MGM Masters Tournament</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lendas-li-na-conchita-martinez-torneio-masters-da-mgm/</link><description>The third edition of the Tennis Masters Tournament, promoted by MGM, brings two tennis legends to the territory this year, Chinese Li Na and Spanish Conchita Martínez, former Grand Slam champions. The competition is scheduled for December 27th and 28th at the Forum pavilion

VÍTOR REBELO
 
The Chinese Li Na, already retired from competitions since 2014, will be one of the main attractions of the Tennis Masters Tournament, in the men's and women's categories, which will take place on the 27th and 28th of December, in the Forum pavilion. Another legend of the sport who will be present is the Spanish Conchita Martínez. The two veterans will face each other in a game as captains of their respective teams.
Li Na, currently 43 years old, was world number two in 2014, the year in which she won the Australian Open, beating Slovak Dominika Cibulkova in the final. Previously, in 2009, she won the Roland Garros Open, defeating the Italian Francesca Schiavone. Conchita Martínez, 10 years older, was also second on the international list in 1995, having won the Wimbledon Open in 1994.
The remaining participants in the Macao SAR competition are still active and some are rising stars, such as 18-year-old Russian Mirra Andreeva, who has climbed several places on the “World Tour”, reaching fifth place this season, the best of her career. The young woman won titles in Indian Wells and Dubai, defeating top opponents such as Iga Swiatek and Aryna Sabalenka. He reached the quarter-finals at Roland Garros, Wimbledon, Rome, Madrid and Bad Homburg.
Meanwhile, 20-year-old Filipina Alexandra Eala has been equally in the spotlight. He trains at the Rafa Nadal Academy, won his first WTA title in Guadalajara and reached the final in Eastbourne. Meanwhile, she reached the semi-finals at the Miami Tournament, defeating names like Jelena Ostapenko, Madison Keys, Paula Badosa and Swiatek on the way.
On the men's side, the Macau Masters will include 20-year-old Chinese left-hander Jerry Shang, who recently returned to the circuit after recovering from foot surgery at the beginning of the year. Shang made history as the only player from China to win an ATP title on national soil, after triumphing at the 2024 Chengdu Open.
The British Jack Draper, known as “JD” or “Drapes”, won in Indian Wells, in what was the main title of his career, having eliminated Carlos Alcaraz, Ben Shelton, Taylor Fritz and Holger Rune. Draper also reached the semi-finals in Madrid and Doha and advanced to the round of 16 in Australia and Roland Garros.
At 1.96 meters tall, 20-year-old Jakub Mensík is another of the names in focus for the territory's test. It occupies 16th place in the world rankings. This year, he surprised Novak Djokovic in the final of the Miami Tournament, defeating Fritz and Draper along the way.
The first day of the event will include a challenge between captains, two men's singles matches and a doubles game, while on the second there will be another captains' match, as well as a women's singles match and two men's singles matches, followed by the closing ceremony and prize giving.
Details of the Tournament were announced at a press conference held at MGM COTAI, which was attended by Li Na. The former WTA player said that her team didn't win the last time, in 2024, so she assured that she will be “even more determined to change things this year”.
She added that she has never played against Conchita Martínez, but is “ready” to face her in Macau, “captain against captain”, adding that the Spaniard “did an excellent job training Mirra Andreeva”.
Catarina Lio, senior vice president of MGM's Marketing Department, stated that, “at a time of city-wide excitement about the National Games, we are pleased to announce the return of this great tennis event”.
Luiz Carvalho, tournament director and senior vice-president of the Mari Group for tennis events, said that the response from fans has been very positive. “When we brought professional tennis to Macau three years ago, we knew this city had something special, and the response from fans has been incredible.” The MGM Macau Tennis Masters “has become part of the city's festive DNA, a celebration of sport, friendship and energy”, he expressed.
Co-organized by MGM and MARI Group, the tournament has the support of the Sports Institute, the Tourism Services Bureau and the Macau Tennis Association.
Tickets are now on sale and can be purchased through the MGM website, and also at Kong Seng Ticketing, Damai, Maoyan, UUTIX and Ctrip. Daily tickets are priced between 230 and 580 patacas for VIP seats, while two-day passes cost between 360 and 1,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>AL budget “sufficient” for possible overtime</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/orcamento-da-al-suficiente-para-eventuais-horas-extra/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly (AL) yesterday approved the Project for a simple plenary deliberation regarding the LA Private Budget Proposal for the economic year 2026. The essential content stipulates that the budget will have an annual increase of 2.81% to 224 million patacas.
According to the document, there will be a reduction of 1.94 million patacas in “personnel expenses”, mainly due to the retirement and separation of workers from the service. AL president, André Cheong, explained that retirements in 2026 are mainly related to advisors. Even so, he noted that, with the change in personnel in the Hemicycle, including the president, new advisors also came.
Furthermore, André Cheong highlighted that the Bureau will fully consider the needs of the AL, including in terms of the team of advisors, other types of support staff, the AL website and the reinforcement of cybersecurity, to increase the number of employees in these areas.
The president of the AL assured that the Budget Proposal is “sufficient” and “flexible” to respond to possible needs for increased expenses due to the payment of overtime and the improvement of the IT system.
If this is necessary, the AL “will propose the respective budget revisions, in a pragmatic manner”, he stated, highlighting that he hopes to make full use of existing human resources to increase the efficiency of current work.
On the other hand, the Budget Proposal points to an increase of 7.64 million patacas in “operational expenses”, due, for example, to the replacement of the air conditioning and conference and interpretation systems in the Plenary Room, which have been in use for several years.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Green light” for IAM restructuring</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/luz-verde-para-reestruturacao-iam/</link><description>The Legislative Assembly also gave the “green light” to the proposal to revise the law “Creation of the Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM)”, with all 32 votes in favor. In the discussion, several deputies expressed attention to the objectives of the restructuring of the IAM foreseen in the diploma and to the issue of adapting the 150 employees who will be transferred to transport and public works services.
The Secretary for Administration and Justice highlighted that the revision of the law aims to optimize the functions and reinforce the efficiency of the IAM's functioning.
The diploma will come into force on June 1, 2026. After that, the IAM structure, currently comprising 12 departments and 36 divisions, will be simplified to eight departments and 19 divisions. Thus, the administrative efficiency of the IAM will register a “substantial increase”, highlighted the Secretary, noting that, on the IAM Administrative Council, the number of vice-presidents will be reduced from two to one and the number of members will be reduced to three.
At the same time, the IAM's private staff status will be revoked, which will be governed by the general civil service regime. With this change, 1,600 employees will have to sign new contracts, noted the Secretary, noting that, with the resolution of the problem of overlapping functions, the IAM “will then be able to dedicate more energy and resources to its other seven functions”.
Furthermore, it noted that the number of IAM employees has been reduced from 2,700 to 2,200 in recent years.
Regarding the 150 employees targeted for transfer, Chao Wai Ieng, president of IAM, stated that nine information sessions were held with the staff. He also promised continued coordination with transport and public works services, to ensure good adaptation to the transferred personnel.
Also in the discussion of this diploma, Wong Sio Chak said that “a series of restructuring” will be implemented in the public service over the next three years. “There will be many plans that will be implemented gradually and annually,” he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Electric vehicles represent 37% of new registrations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/veiculos-electricos-representam-37-das-novas-matriculas/</link><description>Although they represent only 6% of vehicles in circulation, electric vehicles increased by almost 40% between January and September, in annual terms, and corresponded to 37% of new registrations, according to official data
 
In the first nine months of this year, the number of electric vehicles (EVs) maintained a clear growing trend in Macau, despite their relative weight continuing to be small on local roads. At the end of September, 15,320 EVs were registered, which represents an increase of 4,342 or 39.6% compared to the same period last year, according to data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC).
The electric fleet thus corresponded to 6% of total vehicle registrations at the end of the third quarter, an increase of 1.7 percentage points. Since the beginning of the year, the number of trams has increased by 26.2%, or 3,178 vehicles.
According to official statistics, at the end of September, Macau had 253,515 registered vehicles, an increase of 1,706 or 0.7% in annual variation. The total number included 121,725 ​​light cars (+2.9%), 6,724 heavy cars (-0.8%), 65 industrial machines (-7.1%), 17,563 mopeds (-3.8%) and 107,438 motorcycles (-0.9%).
In the same period, the EV universe included 8,170 light cars (+44.1%), 3,830 motorcycles (+35.4%), 2,045 mopeds (+58.4%) and 1,275 heavy cars (+7.3%). The proportion of electric vehicles continues to be highest among heavy cars, with 19% of the total, followed by mopeds (11.6%), light cars (6.7%) and motorcycles (3.6%).
DSEC data also shows that the number of vehicles with new registrations fell by 10.2% to 8,522 in general between January and September, when compared to the first nine months of 2024, with trams (3,165) equivalent to 37.1% of the total (+7.1 percentage points). Considering only the month of September, it appears that new registrations decreased by 30.3% to 814 overall, while in the case of EVs they decreased by 27.3% to 247, corresponding to 30.3% of the total.
On the other hand, the number of road accidents fell by 8% to 1,243 in September, in annual terms, causing 465 injuries (+4.3%). In the first nine months of this year, there were 11,086 road accidents (-5.2%), causing 4,102 injuries (+0.7%) and four deaths (+100%), according to data from the Public Security Police Corps.
Between January and September, the movement of cars at border crossings (8,169,143) grew 22.5%, in annual terms, and the gross weight of containerized cargo entering and leaving by land rose 5.4% to 53,394 tons. On the other hand, transport statistics reveal that the movement of passenger vessels (57,884) and the number of commercial flights at Macau International Airport (40,797) decreased by 3.1% and 3.8%, respectively, compared to the first nine months of last year.
In September alone, the movement of cars at border crossings (932,644) increased by 18.4% and the number of commercial flights at the airport (4,256) grew by 2.6%, in the annual comparison. Conversely, the movement of passenger vessels (5,373) fell 12.5% ​​compared to September 2024.
 
S.T.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>15 thousand have already opted for smart passage in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/15-mil-ja-optaram-por-passagem-inteligente-em-hengqin/</link><description>More than 14,800 people had registered to use the smart border crossing system, as of 6pm yesterday, according to authorities
 
As of 6pm yesterday, 14,863 people had registered to use the smart ticket system with facial recognition, according to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP). According to the Macau Security Forces Services Directorate (DSFSM), expanding the group of people who can use this border crossing system will be studied. Furthermore, the Macao SAR intends to extend, in a timely manner, the measure to other border posts that meet the conditions, for example, the “single inspection” routes at the Qingmao Border Post and the Delta Bridge.
The smart border crossing measure was launched yesterday at the Hengqin Border Post, with the CPSP and DSFSM, in collaboration with the Zhuhai General Border Inspection Station and the Economic Development Services Bureau of the Deep Cooperation Zone, carrying out work to update the automatic full inspection channels.
The smart border crossing service adopts advanced facial recognition technology to verify identity, without the need for an identification document. This new model “simplifies the process and improves the experience of crossing the border, making cross-border travel increasingly convenient and efficient”, explained the CPSP and DSFSM.
Since “the interconnection between Macau and Hengqin is the key to coordinated regional development, increasing border crossing efficiency and facilitating the movement of people is the prerequisite for promoting regional integration”, argue the authorities. Next year, 46 automatic full inspection channels with intelligent border crossing functionality will be added at Hengqin Border Post.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Services fair helped explore international market</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/feira-de-servicos-ajudou-explorar-mercado-internacional/</link><description>The Institute for Trade and Investment Promotion (IPIM) organized the participation of a delegation, made up of around 20 representatives of companies and commercial associations from the big health, conventions and exhibitions, technology, finance and import and export sectors, at the 4th Greater Bay Services Trade Fair. The idea was “to help Macau companies explore international markets and better integrate into the context of national development”.
Under the theme “New service outsourcing engine, accelerating with digital commerce”, the Fair continued the “One Event, Three Locations” model, organizing several complementary activities, such as B2B contact exchange sessions, project roadshows, promotional sessions for investment capture services in the Greater Bay Area and study visits to the service trade industry in the Greater Bay Area, as indicated by IPIM in a statement.
This year's Fair featured, for the first time, an “Open Day to the Public”, to promote integration between trade in services and consumption in the culture, tourism and conventions and exhibitions sectors. At the same time, the GBA Next Humanoid Expo was held, providing intelligent support for the digital transformation of services trade.
At the Fair, topics such as opportunities in ASEAN markets, the empowerment of companies by AI in exploring international markets, and the high-quality development of the convention and exhibition sector were discussed. According to IPIM, the aim was to expand the connection channels between companies in the Greater Bay Area and the markets of Portuguese-speaking and international countries, build a platform for economic and commercial cooperation between China and abroad and promote the region's internal and external connectivity and its synergistic development.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Longer trading hours suggested during Games and GPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerido-horario-mais-alargado-comercio-durante-jogos-gpm/</link><description>The number of visitors who will travel to Macau during the month of November, to witness the National Games and the Grand Prix, could provide an improvement in the business of small and medium-sized companies, especially in community areas. Anticipating this possibility, association leaders suggest that the opening hours of commercial establishments and restaurants be extended, as well as proposing the launch of more tourist products that combine tourism and sport
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The sports industry has been an increasingly discussed topic, given the growing increase in events in that sector that Macau has organized. Concretely addressing the two poster events that will take place in the territory this November, the National Games and the Grand Prix (GPM), the program on Ou Mun Tin Toi (Chinese-language radio) gave a voice to some association members.
Noting that the sporting events will take place in various areas of the territory, Choi Chi Seng, deputy director of the Macau Quarters Youth Association, said that, “after the competitions, a certain number of spectators will consume in community neighborhoods, so it is advisable for traders to extend the opening hours of their stores or restaurants”.
The same leader predicted, on the other hand, that the cross-border cycling race of the National Games, which will connect the urban roads of Hong Kong, Macau, Zhuhai and the Hengqin Deep Cooperation Zone, via the Delta Bridge, will cause “inconvenience in citizens' travel”, but appealed to residents to understand the situation, as this type of event “will play a certain role in encouraging the business of small and medium-sized enterprises”.
Therefore, he suggests that more small-scale sports competitions be held in community neighborhoods, aiming to “stimulate the interest and participation of the public of various age groups in the local sports industry”.
In turn, Wong Fai, president of the Macau Tourism and Leisure Innovation and Services Association, proposes that the authorities analyze “how the level of participation of residents in the GPM can be increased”.
On the other hand, he pointed out that, in recent years, “more and more tourists have shown interest in tourist products with tickets for the GPM races, including many international visitors”, and, he adds, “the supply of this type of tourist products cannot satisfy demand”. In this sense, he suggests the launch of more tourism products that combine tourism and sport.
Meanwhile, Loi Hoi Ngan, member of the Macau Economic Association, proposes to the Government an assessment on “whether there are enough sports halls in the territory”. Furthermore, he argues that more personnel in the sports industry should be trained and more young people should be attracted to this sector. In the same vein, he also calls for community sports competitions to be held in the Macao SAR, “to make residents more accepting of the presence of the Grand Prix”.
 
Free entry to ID facilities until November 21st
The Sports Institute (ID) will provide free entry to its sports facilities between now and November 21st, in response to the 15th edition of the National Games. The objective, according to the organization, is to “encourage residents to practice physical exercise” and to “mark the big sporting event”. During the period of free use, the process for purchasing tickets and requesting space rentals will remain unchanged. In other words, residents will be able to continue to use the personal online reservation system (including the “Single Account”, the ID website and the application) or go to sports facilities in person. Alternatively, guests can visit the venue during opening hours to obtain tickets at the time, subject to availability.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Chinese Culture Shows” with productions from Beijing and Ningbo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/espectaculos-de-cultura-chinesa-producoes-de-pequim-ningbo/</link><description>January 2026 will mark the return of the Chinese National Opera to Macau, with the concert “Golden Lotus Flowers”, as part of the Cultural Institute’s “Chinese Culture Performance Season” program. In February, the China Coal Mine Artistic Troupe will provide a “festive and auspicious environment” for communities for Chinese New Year celebrations. In addition to several renowned works and artists from Beijing and Ningbo, the IC has programmed dozens of artistic exchange activities

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The National Opera of China returns to Macau in January next year, with the show “Golden Lotus Flowers – Concert of Vocal Works of the National Opera of China”, as part of the unprecedented “Season of Chinese Culture Shows”, which runs until March 2026. According to the Cultural Institute (IC), the concert will bring to several schools “masterpieces of vocal music, Chinese and foreign, with pieces rich music and exceptional artists.” Students will be guided “on a musical journey that crosses East and West”, indicates the press release.
Por sua vez, a Trupe Artística de Minas de Carvão da China realizará espectáculos de artes tradicionais de celebração do Ano Novo Chinês em vários bairros comunitários, nos dias 21 e 22 de Fevereiro. The “festive and auspicious atmosphere” of the celebrations will demonstrate “the charm of Chinese quyi”, says the IC.
In October, Leong Wai Man had announced that several Chinese opera classics would arrive in Macau between this month and March next year. According to the press release, Yu Kuizhi and Li Shengsu will lead “the best artists from the Chinese National Peking Opera Company to present two shows that explore the artistic expression of Chinese lyrical tradition”, namely “Meeting of Heroes” and “Invoking the East Wind”.
The dance and theater play “Mulan”, by the Ningbo Arts and Entertainment Group, will be directed by Zhou Liya and Han Zhen, fusing “modern scenic technology with oriental aesthetics, giving new vitality to the classical image”. Awarded with several distinctions, including the “Lotus Prize for Chinese dance”, the piece’s main focus is “filial piety, loyalty, courage and love, and ingeniously combines dance, martial arts, drama and technological elements”.
“The Passage of Huarong”, a traditional show and classic novel from the Three Kingdoms period, portrays “the confrontation of intellects and strategies between the brave, with great scenic tension”. Written by Tian Han and originally performed by Li Zigui, “The Legend of the White Snake” by the Chinese National Peking Opera Company will be performed by Li Shengsu and Chu Fengyi. This work, which has been perfected for more than 60 years, portrays “Bai Suzhen’s deep and unwavering love and perseverance.”
In “Farewell, My Concubine”, “eternal themes such as power, survival and responsibility are explored through multiple encounters and dialogues that cross time and space between consort Yu and Empress Lü”, the Chu–Han historical confrontation as the backdrop. The original story was created by Mo Yan, Nobel laureate in Literature. This immersive theater piece was produced and performed by the Beijing People's Theater and challenges “the traditional narrative structure of historical drama.”
The IC also programmed activities in schools and community neighborhoods, “in order to promote dialogue with the performing arts sector in Macau, presenting the richness of Chinese culture to the public in a new way”. These include eight exchange shows and around 50 activities, “such as community tours, school exchanges, dialogues with industry and workshops”.
The “Chinese Culture Performance Season” was developed from the previous “National Art Company Performance Season in Macao”. Using “Chinese culture as a connecting link”, the initiative aims to create “a cultural event that involves the entire population” and “promote emotional resonance and cultural transmission”, in order to “build a happy, beautiful and harmonious circle of life”, can be read in the note.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Markets and festivals show “tourism”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seis-mercados-festivais-mostram-turismo/</link><description>During this month of November, the Tourism Services Directorate (DST) will support six community activities, with a view to boosting the community economy. The idea is also to allow residents and visitors to experience “the rich and diverse charm of ‘tourism+’”.
The “San Kio Traditional Market Tour” will take place at Largo do Templo de San Kio, Jardim San Kio, Rua da Amendment and Rua da Erva, for six consecutive weeks, specifically until November 20, on Fridays, Saturdays and Sundays.
Activities include game tents, guided tours of community neighborhoods, weekend raffles, consumer benefits in the San Kio neighborhood, brief street performances, five themed fairs, workshops, limited figurative paintings and recreational parks in municipal markets, among others. For example, “the craft workshop will demonstrate the tie-dye technique, which is part of the intangible cultural heritage, and will offer an experience in making pins and brooches using this technique”, explained DST.
The “Ferreira de Almeida Festival” takes place throughout the month, in the Parish of São Lázaro. The event includes exhibitions, fairs, workshops, shows, exhibitions. Six of the activities include the Carnival of São Lázaro, a workshop on Macau with the Grand Prix as the theme, Horta da Mitra Municipal Garden series, mini-film screening, special exhibition of Corolla classic cars and an exhibition of photographs of the Grand Prix.
Until November 9th, the “Sports Carnival: National Games Celebration Party”, at the Rotunda of the Taipa Stadium, presents various activities, such as the 3×3 Golden League Youth Tournament, cultural and creative industries tents, gastronomy tents, cultural and artistic shows, gaming tents, characteristic points for taking photographs, a battle of interactive techniques between intellectual property characters, among others. Taking advantage of the opportunity of the 15th edition of the National Games, the event will enrich Macau's diverse “tourism +” sports content, considers DST.
On the other hand, between the 8th and 16th, the “15th National Games-Cheer Up! Community Fun Day” will bring sports-themed entertainment tents to the Fábrica de Panchões Iec Long, on Saturdays and Sundays: table tennis stands, 3x3 and 5x5 basketball, volleyball, karate-do and kung fu stands with the inflatable FATFAT doll and Large interactive outdoor sports area. Professional sports lectures and cheerleading shows will also be organised.
The “Roving Manduco – Street Life Festival”, in turn, takes place over four weeks, from the 8th to the 30th of November, on Saturdays and Sundays, covering Rua da Praia do Manduco, the Pátio da Restauração, the Doca da Barra Zone and the surrounding areas. The highlights are varied: market stalls with characteristic objects, theatrical and musical shows, guided tours and experiences of drinking tea on the street.
Between the 14th and 30th, the 25th Macau Gastronomy Festival returns to Praça do Lago Sai Van, bringing together more than 100 food and drink establishments, typical foods, stage shows and attractive games tents. To celebrate the anniversary, this edition will hold a series of activities under the theme “City of Gastronomy” on the ground floor of the Galaxy Macau International Convention Center, with two activities highlighted: the International Chinese Chefs Championship and the 1st International Exhibition of Intelligent Catering Equipment.</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Tourists return to Hoi An as clean-up continues after floods</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/turistas-regressam-hoi-enquanto-limpeza-prossegue-apos-cheias/</link><description>Tourists are returning to the ancient Vietnamese city of Hoi An as locals clear mud and debris to reopen the UNESCO World Heritage site following floods that devastated the central region and killed at least 35 people.

Tourism and services, driven by accommodation, food and ticket sales, constitute the backbone of Hoi An's economy and contributed almost two-thirds of regional income in 2024, with the city receiving more than 4.4 million visitors, including 3.6 million foreigners, according to official data.
From the beginning of this month, national and international visitors were seen strolling along the riverfront and visiting historic tourist attractions, although most hotels, lantern shops and restaurants were undergoing deep cleaning to prepare for full reopening ahead of the peak travel season.
Last week's historic floods submerged Hoi An's lantern-lit streets and centuries-old wooden houses, forcing hundreds of businesses to temporarily close.
Although no official estimates of financial losses were released, small traders reported high losses.
The neighboring city of Thua Thien Hue, also affected by heavy rain, reopened its iconic citadel to tourists on October 31st.
Authorities, however, continue to warn of rising river levels and the potential for new flooding, as prolonged rains are expected in the coming days.
The floods also left five people missing and flooded more than 16,000 homes and 5,300 hectares of crops. Around 75,000 people are still without electricity, the government disaster agency said in a report
Vietnam, prone to severe storms and flooding, often faces widespread property damage during the storm season, which typically lasts from June to October.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-11-06 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>