<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>New Hope and Fujian list ensure three seats each</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-esperanca-lista-de-fujian-asseguram-tres-assentos-cada/</link><description>There was “surprise” and a “historic frame” for Jose Pereira Coutinho's New Hope, who was the big winner of the night, when he got the largest number of votes -a large distance from the rest -and elect three deputies. Secondly, the list led by Song Pek Kei, linked to the Fujian community, also secured three seats in Hemiciclo. Faom, "Kaifong", the list linked to the community of Jiangmen and the "women" got only two seats each
 
Catarina Pereira
 
List 2, “Nova Esperança”, led by José Pereira Coutinho, and list 1, “Association of United Citizens”, whose head-to-head is Song Pek Kei, were the great winners of the electoral night by ensuring three seats in the hemicicle. The New Hope got 43,361 votes (26.73%), having elected Pereira Coutinho, Chan Hao Weng and Che Sa Wang. It was the most voted list, a large distance from the second.
To journalists, the president of the civil service workers' association said that “this was undoubtedly the biggest victory of the new hope”, stressing that over the years the list has always been adding votes and never losing them. "I think a lot of people were surprised by this result, because we did it too," he continued. "It's a historic landmark."
Pereira Coutinho stressed that the result “is not individual”, but “set”, the result of the effort and work of many people. "We are very pleased. We know that in the future we have a huge responsibility to follow up on the constant promises in our electoral program, but we have confidence and willpower," he added.
Despite admitting that he did not expect to elect a third deputy, Pereira Coutinho said that Che Sai Wang was placed in third position "as a driving force, because he also has a very strong substrate in the community, although he is a bit modest." "But the result is in sight, made a great contribution, the strategy worked," he said.
The deputy argued that the result is of special importance "at this time we live in the MSAR": "As a resident citizen in Macau, with a Portuguese name, having this result is extremely satisfactory." He then promised to “continue fighting for the rights of the Macaense and Portuguese community and all other communities in Macau”.
In the last elections, it is recalled, the New Hope list had been the third most voted.
It should be noted that of the more than 175,000 voters, only more than 162,000 were considered validly expressed votes, with more than 13,000 to be blank and null votes [see text on page 3].
Already the group linked to the community of Fujian reelected deputies Song Pek Kei and Nick Lei, having still got a place for a third candidate: rookie Chan Lai Kei. It achieved 29,459 votes, the equivalent of 18.16%. The list repeated the feat four years ago, when it also made hat-trick.
Song Pek Kei noted that in this edition the list obtained more votes, which "proves that the works done by the team were recognized by the citizens." Being “satisfied” with the result, he asserted that he will fulfill the promises, especially to promote economic development and industrial diversification. Already Nick Lei stressed that he will try to realize the increase in the pension for the elderly and the implementation of guarantees for the use of residents.
The “Union for Development” was followed, list 5, with a total of 27,431 votes (16.91%). Thus, he managed to reelect Ella Law and Leong Sun Iok, like what happened four years ago. In the reaction, deputies linked to the Macao Workers' Associations Federation thanked voters for their support, stating that in the next four years they will continue to promote, with priority, solutions to employment problems and linked to the welfare of the population.
In the same line, list 3, “Promoting Union for Progress”, linked to the union of Macao residents' associations (“Kaifong”), managed to elect two deputies, receiving 21,745 votes (13.41%). They remain in the hemicycle Leong Hong Sai and Ngan Iek Hang. Facing the result as “satisfactory”, Leong Hong said stressed that the proportion of an increase in the number of votes obtained by the list corresponded to expectations.
In turn, the “Union of Macau-Guangdong”, list 4, obtained a total of 21,461 votes, equivalent to 13.23% of the total. Thus, it is a return to the Legislative Assembly for Joey Lao, now as a deputy elected by direct and not appointed suffrage, while Lee Koi Ian will take office for the first time. In the reaction, Joey Lao, whose list has links to the Jiangmen community, has promised to do a good job over the next four years, presenting suggestions for issues such as economy, population welfare, young people.
In the last position was the “Good Home Alliance”, list 6, but still managed to secure two seats in the hemiciclo. With 18,751 votes (11.56%), the list linked to the General Association of Women was able to elect Wong Kit Cheng and Loi I Weng. After scrutiny, Wong Kit Cheng described that reelection reflects “public recognition” regarding his work. It also asserted that it will comment by citizens in the hemiciclo and ensure the rights and interests of more families and women.
Among those elected by direct suffrage, there are four premieres at Al: Chan Hao Weng, Lee Koi Ian, Loi I Weng and Chan Lai Kei.
On the other hand, in the indirect suffrage were already automatically assigned 10 of the 12 seats: four at the Electoral College of Industrial, Commercial and Financial Sectors (José Chui Sa Peng and IP Sio Kai, Si Ka Lon and Kevin Ho, which debuts); Three from the professional sector (Iau Teng Pio, Vong Hou Piu and Wong Chon Kit, the last two also rookiers); one of the sectors of social and educational services (Ho Ion Sang); and two of the cultural and sports sectors (Angela Leong and MA Chi Seng).
The two seats of the work sector was missing, as they applied two lists. Each one eventually ensured a place, and Lam Lon Wai remains (obtained 484 votes) and Leong Pou U will debut as deputy (got 578 votes). The Chief Executive will also appoint seven deputies within 15 days after receiving the general investigation.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Influx rose, but it was the third smallest</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/afluencia-subiu-mas-foi-terceira-menor-de-sempre/</link><description>The poll to the polls in the elections for the Legislative Assembly was 53.35%, a notorious rise of almost 11 percentage points, compared to 2021, when the highest abstention rate was recorded in the territory. However, and despite the appeals to the authorities' vote, the participation rate was the third worst since the creation of the MSAR. In total, 175,272 people -a record -of a universe of 328,506 voters voted. The blank votes and null votes, in turn, also reached a new maximum, having totaled more than 13 thousand

Catarina Pereira
 
Yesterday's legislative participation rate was 53.35% in direct suffrage, an increase of nearly 11 percentage points for 2021, when the highest abstention rate was registered in the territory after the disqualification of more than two dozen candidates by the Legislative Assembly Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal). However -and despite the persistent appeals of the authorities -, this year's polls of the polls turned out to be the third worst since the creation of the MSAR.
They voted, 175,272 people, from a universe of 328,506 voters. At this point, a new maximum has been reached, as there had never been so many voters before, since the number of voters was higher.
The blank and null votes also hit a record. According to Caeal statistics, 5,987 blank votes were accounted for and 7,077 null votes, translating 90% and 242% increase compared to 2021, respectively. These were, moreover, the highest accounts since the creation of the MSAR.
It is recalled that this year also disqualified 12 candidates from two lists, allegedly “not being faithful to masters or not defending the basic law”, including former deputy Ron Lam.
After the disclosure of the results, when asked what is the reason for the exponential increase of blank votes and null votes, CAEAL President Seng Ioi Man refused to comment. "In all data related to elections there are numbers to go up or down, there are many reasons, so Caeal will not comment," he said.
In the indirect suffrage, they voted 6,645 of the more than 7,500 voters, a participation rate of 88.12%, slightly higher than four years ago.
Hours earlier, Seng Ioi Man had thanked those who went to vote. "It was in fact a little hot day, we thank the population for going to the voting assemblies; not only to the voters, but to all the workers who helped," he said.
Asked if he was satisfied with the participation rate and which he considered the main factor who led people to vote to greater strength, Seng Ioi Man declined, saying that it was necessary to do "some studies, some analyzes."
Four years ago, after the first wave of disqualification for the elections, the MSAR registered the highest abstention rate of 57.6%, and more than 5,200 people voted blank or null.
This time, the authorities endeavored that abstention (46.65%) did not reach such low levels. Last week, it is recalled, the Chief Executive sent letters to civil servants, saying that the vote was a way of demonstrating "fidelity to the masters."
In addition, Sam Hou Fai met with the directors of services and holders of high positions, appealing again to the vote. On this occasion, he argued that "leaders in the management level should assume a role of connection between superiors and subordinates", and should promote "compliance with liability".
Civil servants, who asked not to be identified for fearing reprisals, confirmed to Lusa that earlier last week they were asked if they intended to vote. After apparently informal conversations, written justifications were required to admit that he did not plan to vote.
The workers - some of whom with decades of service in entities and public services - confirmed that this was the first time they were questioned about whether or not to participate in elections.
Yesterday, Seng Ioi Man said that "no one can oblige another to reveal the intention to vote, that is, which list they want to vote," but as to the issue of civil servants said nothing.
In recent days, companies and other entities in the territory have intensified appeals to residents to vote. In addition, authorities introduced various measures to encourage and facilitate suffrage, including public transportation.
Some of the largest employers, such as game operators, have also made available free buses, meals and early departure times in the coming business days, according to Macau News Agency.
When he was inspecting the voting assemblies, Seng Ioi Man considered that “the preparation work, the facilitating measures and the good time” encouraged to vote. Later, he indicated that the voting places were operating within the normal range, with only one case in which a voter tried to use the mobile phone in the voting assembly.
 
Boss did not comment on letters
Sam Hou Fai voted yesterday morning at the Salesian Institute of Immaculate Conception. At the time, he said he exercised "a political right" and fulfilled a "responsibility." He also argued that these elections were taking place "in a good climate" and that there was an "enthusiastic participation of the whole society."
Refusing to comment on the document sent to civil servants, the chief executive preferred to stress that the vote "is a civic duty" and that "voters must actively participate in the elections and use the right to vote."
He also noticed that, during the election campaign, “society expressed great interest in participating” in the suffrage. "Once again I appeal to voters to vote, with valid votes, on the lists that deserve your confidence," he added.
The day before the elections, Sam was to inspect the voting assemblies, and reiterated that the candidate lists for direct suffrage "have wide representation".
Yesterday, after going to vote, the Secretary for Administration and Justice also made no comment, either in relation to the executive's head circular, nor on interrogations to civil servants. "We hope that citizens, public services workers and private companies will exercise their right to vote," said André Cheong, who ensured that there was no goal for abstention.
The calls to the vote were also bound yesterday by several holders of high positions, including the five secretaries, and service directors, as well as the president of AL, among others.
 
Chief enhances “fair, impartial and whole” electoral environment
With the “joint efforts from all over”, the elections “successfully took place, according to the law and in a fair, impartial and whole environment,” said the chief executive, after the preliminary counting of votes. In an official note, Sam Hou Fai congratulated the elected deputies and thanked voters who participated in the elections, as well as the staff highlighted to the voting places, civil servants, security forces, schools that provided spaces and entities that adopted measures to facilitate electoral participation. Exalting the organization and planning “well done” by the Commission on Electoral Affairs, he considered that the election “has been ordered” at a time of “deep meaning” because it was the first for the Legislative Assembly (AL) since the change of law in 2024. Ensuring that the government will continue to “maintain close communication and mutual cooperation” with Al, Sam Hou Fai said “Deputies News take forward the spirit of patriotism and love to Macao, actively participate in political affairs and return the support of the electorate with concrete work. ” The leader of the MSAR believes that the new AL will continue to “work hand in hand” with the government to “reinforce the economy, fight for development and to improve resident welfare, with a view to the joint creation of a brighter future for Macao”.
 
CCAC received 15 complaints on election day
The Commissioner Against Corruption (CCAC) received 15 complaints and 34 requests for information on election day. Since early March and until yesterday, 143 complaints and 145 requests for information have been received, "26 criminal investigation cases have been instructed, four of which are related to electoral corruption and other illicit acts," the body said. When he was voting, the Commissioner, to the Ieong Seong, said that yesterday were found "about 10 occurrences, involving citizens with clothes showing number or denomination of the candidacy lists and other objects, so all were subjected to verbal warnings."</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MORNING OF LARGE INFLUXING IN SEAC PAI VAN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/manha-de-grande-afluxo-em-seac-pai-van/</link><description>A long line, about a hundred people, marked the morning of election day at the Seac Pai Van Assembly. It was the only exception in the quiet period of the morning. Moreover, in Coloane and the mud, the vote took place in an orderly manner, with short times of waiting, as referred to the various voters heard at the places of the voting assemblies by the Jornal Tribuna de Macau

























Victor Rebelo
 
According to the information that was being available shortly after the opening of the voting assemblies, through the website of the Commission of Electoral Affairs of the Legislative Assembly (Caeal), the Official Seac Pai Van school in Coloane, was, from all voting places, the one that registered a longer waiting time.
Already predicting the flow of voters in the morning, the voting assemblies located in that educational establishment, in a total of 22, two of which to vote on people with disabilities, opened slightly earlier, at 8:30 am. A measure to which it was not oblivious to the fact that it is a zone of large population density and where many elderly reside.
At 10:00 am on a very Solarenga and very hot morning, with the thermometers registering 32ºC, many people had to wait in line, albeit in the shadow, about an hour to exercise the right to vote. For many “it was an unexpected and unpleasant situation, because there was a line out of more than a hundred residents,” as the Tribuna de Macao newspaper referred to one of the support team's elements.
However, about an hour later, ie at 11h00, the expected waiting time went down to 10 minutes. "Quickly the situation has changed, perhaps because people had consulted the information available and decided to wait and come later," he said, confirming that from there "everything normalized."
This standardization was witnessed around 12:00 pm by the JTM report, which found the arrival of voters to the spot, not causing any waiting time outside the building.
Inside, before voting, "it was a few minutes," said one of the voters, named Luz, 50 years old, civil servant. The Macaense, who lives in one of the buildings in Seac Pai Van, was first at Mass and then went to exercise civic duty. "I have always voted since there are elections," he stressed, recognizing that the presence of deputies in Al constitutes "a positive aspect", being "very important to improve the lives of residents."
Berry, another of those interviewed by JTM, a 40-year-old civil service worker, had just voted when we found him to go to the supermarket adjacent to the Father Van Seac School. "I have put my vote and now I will do some shopping," he noted, adding that he voted for the fourth time in Macao. "Let's see now what the elected deputies will do, so I'm expecting."
Seconds after a gaming operator bus had left some people, presumably employees, to vote, we found a 36 -year -old, Chinese, nickname Kam, a finance service employee who responded in a fluent English. First I didn't mean whether or not it had voted, or if I would do it.
Then, during the short conversation, he let out "no, I won't vote, by the way, I never voted." About the reasons for abstention, the resident said it was not interested. “I have no great motivation for this, I usually have no interest in this kind of subjects and I think that,
Regardless of who wins, everything is in the same. ”He admitted, however, that" people here in Macau are already more mature and so many of them decide to vote for these elections, is a matter of option. "
In Seac Pai Van, there were several wheelchair residents and many elderly, most of the time accompanied by family members. In that place, and until 5 pm, therefore, four hours from the ballot box, close to half of the 6,605 registered voters had voted (3,099).
Before, and also in Coloane, our report had heard the environment that was lived in the youthful service facilities of the former Luso-Chinese school. Here people appeared in small numbers, spacingly, in a place with seven vote chambers, one of which for the disabled.
In the morning, it was in this space that voted the president of the last court. On the way out, in addition to appealing to the active participation of voters, Song Man Lei stated that the Legislative Assembly constitutes "an essential element in the political structure of Macao, and performs numerous important functions."
 
“Some distance to travel” at the stadium facilities
JTM then moved to the Taipa Stadium, where it was not allowed to capture photographs in the interior, contrary to what had happened in the previous places.
The complex, with two zones (A and B), had large installations, but with some distance from the entrance to the polling place. “I think it's a little far, there was some distance to go, since I entered until I voted,” said António Lagariça, renovated. In addition to this detail, “it was well organized and people voted quietly,” he said.
Regarding the work of the deputies, Macaense pointed out that "these days they are more active", hoping that "they will continue to present constructive proposals for the life of the population and not as happened before, in which the deputies entered al dumb and came out silent."
Professor Rui Martins also voted at the stadium, having chosen to move at lunch time after the mass. In the end, I told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau it was a quiet vote. "It was fluid, well organized, with two lines, so I expected little more than five minutes," he said.
For 33 years living in the territory, the Vice-Rector of the University of Macao (one) voted whenever there are elections and told this newspaper that "where there is the opportunity to vote, I think it should be vote," informing that the students of one "had at their disposal a bus to travel to the voting assemblies if they were interested."
Meanwhile, an indirect suffrage voter told the Chinese language press that before voting studied the political program of the candidates of the respective sector. The resident used a bus from black sand to the polling place at the Polytechnic University, considering that "the free public transport measure provided by the government was able to encourage more people to leave home to vote."
In addition, he stressed that the measure may allow residents to vote in different areas, but expects "in the future authorities to prepare more voting assemblies in the mud area."</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Voters manifest the desire to “improve” society</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/eleitores-manifestam-vontade-de-melhorar-sociedade/</link><description>Several voters have highlighted the fact that the voting process has taken place normal and organized in the peninsula. Between the late morning and early afternoon, there were no major queues for the entry of some voting assemblies. Most voters interviewed by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao stressed the importance of voting for Macao's improvement

Pedro Milheirão
The influx to the ballot box of the Macao Forum Vote was relatively calm, around noon yesterday. Police officers highlighted to the scene were escorting voters who landed in the special zone reserved for vehicles, while employees of the voting assembly helped other voters who arrived alone, mostly elderly and with reduced mobility.
After several attempts to talk to voters who abandoned the place, a young resident couple, who had just exercised the right to vote, agreed to make statements. To the 32 -year -old Tribuna de Macao newspaper, he explained that the voting process had been normal and had elapsed "in an organized way."
Despite voting for the third time, Xu confessed to considering that the vote is not a "very important" thing. "Regardless of voting or not, we cannot change the world, we cannot change the whole society. Just because it is Sunday and because I have time I came to vote," he said. Asked if he would exercise the right to vote in future elections, he replied that he would depend on “some reasons” without specifying which one. "Still I hope we can become in society we want to be," he said.
Shortly before 1 pm, when more than 92,000 voters had already voted on direct suffrage, the Colina da Guia Municipal Park recorded more movement than the Macao Forum, with several people exercising. Along the way, most people ran, while some stretched by the railing and the park equipment. At the entrance of the Flora Official School, the voting Assembly officials guided the few voters who arrived.
Near a group that played Jianzi, a 55 -year -old man and Chinese nationality, with his shirt wrapped over his shoulders. Resident and census in Macau, the man stated, in Portuguese, that he had not yet voted. When he was questioned by this newspaper about if he would intend to vote, the man replied that "yes, logical." “I go to the Luso-Chinese [technical-professional] school near my home. Citizens have the responsibility to do so, for the well-being of the city,” he said.
At the entrance of the Portuguese school, the voting Assembly staff approached some pawns that stopped in the restricted zone, asking them if they had come to vote and warning them that they could not stay in the areas marked with yellow tape. On the other side of the school, at the designated departure of the renovated Assembly, Teresa said the voting process "went well." Portuguese, who was born and lived in Macau, stressed that the vote is a “very important” act. "To have someone to help us."
In the same note, Ricky Mok, a 30 -year -old place, said he was going to vote for the second time in his life, to the Macao Polytechnic University, hoping to "make Macau even better." In the immediate vicinity of the TAP Seac multipurpose pavilion, another 42 -year -old said he had gone to vote and that the last time he had done it had been "a long time ago."</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mariza joins the Macao Orchestra for New Year concert</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mariza-junta-se-a-orquestra-de-macau-para-concerto-de-ano-novo/</link><description>Portuguese fadista Mariza will return to Macau for a New Year concert on 31 December, together with the Macau Orchestra
 
Mariza will act in the large auditorium of the Macau Cultural Center (CCM), as part of the Macao Orchestra Program for Season 2025-26, the Cultural Institute (IC) announced. The “Queen of the Portuguese Fado”, as described in the IC, will return to Macao's stages for the Orchestra New Year concert, scheduled for 8 pm on December 31, with tickets cost 180, 250, 300 and 400 patacas.
The program states that Mariza will present fado songs, accompanied by a symphonic version of the orchestra, conducted by local conductor Tony Yeh Cheng-Te.
Mariza was in the territory in November 2024, for a concert with the Chinese orchestra of Macao, under the last Macao International Music Festival (Fimm). It is recalled that next end has, for the third consecutive edition, with a fadista, since Cuca Roseta will act, also accompanied by the Chinese orchestra of Macao, on October 11.
The end returned to the stage in 2022, after a two -year interregnum due to the pandemic, with a program that included two shows with foreign guests, one of which from Portuguese António Zambujo, but only through recorded performances. The return of foreign artists took place in 2023, after the end of the restrictions on entry into the region, in a program that encompassed a concert by Gisela João.
The opening concert of the new season of the Macao Orchestra took place on September 6 at the CCM Grand Auditorium. Directed by the orchestra's main conductor and main conductor, Liao Kuok Man, the concert was attended by acclaimed South Korean violinist Leung In-Mo, who played the classic Mendelssohn violin concert.
Subordinated to the “One Step In” Theme, the new season of the Orchestra will lead the audience "on a trip through timeless music of different eras, finding musicians of antiquity and modernity, both Chinese and international, through their works," says the IC, adding that tickets are already on sale on the Macau Ticket network, with several discounts available.
 
Tribute to Mozart
Continuing the “Tribute Series to Musicians”, this season the Macau Orchestra focuses on the “Prodigy Boy” Mozart. Akiko Suwanai and Svetlin Roussev will present three concerts for Mozart violin, while renowned violinist Julian Rachlin will join Sarah Mcelravy and Macao orchestra to present Mozart's later symphonic concerts and the popular “Scottish” symphony of Mendelssohn.
The Macao Orchestra will also collaborate with German Daniel Müller-Schott to play the Elgar cello concert. In turn, Himari, the rising star of the violin who reached fame at 14, will debut in Macao, playing the concert for Sibelius violin. The closing concert of the season will feature the participation of Polaco pianist Rafał Blechacz, considered "Chopin's greatest interpreter of his generation."
For Valentine's Day, the orchestra bets on a “lively circus”, with classic opera, ballet and cinema works. Easter celebrations will take the audience on a spiritual trip with Bach's “Passion Second St. John” before the Holy Friday. Children's Day will also be marked, with the symphonic concert of a movie.
In addition, the Macao Orchestra will present the Special Concert “Symphony of the Stars”, with the Vanguardist “Time For Three”, winner of Grammys and Emmys, famous on the internet. “They will combine violin, double bass and guitar to play a diversified range of classical, country and pop classical music,” says the same note.
The season now started will offer “multiple platforms to support emerging talents in the music world”, also guarantees the IC, highlighting as “one of the high points” the “Hope for the Future” concert, with professional musicians from the Macao Orchestra, as well as local music enthusiasts and academic elites. “Florescent Arts” will present the winners of the Macao Young Musicians Contest.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public expenses reach 79% of revenues</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/despesas-publicas-atingem-79-das-receitas/</link><description>MSAR administration accounts registered a positive balance of 14.9 billion patacas at the end of August, with expenses falling 1.8% and representing 79% of revenues, which rose 3.5% in annual terms
 
The public expense of the MSAR fell 1.8% in the first eight months compared to the same period as 2024. According to data published on the Electronic Page of the Directorate of Finance Services, administration spending totaled 57.52 billion PATACA by August, which corresponds to 51.6% of the budget for the general calculation of the year.
Between January and June, public expense decreased mainly due to a fall of 4.4%, in annual terms, in spending on support and social subsidies, which were encrypted at 30.99 billion.
This although, in early July, the Legislative Assembly approved a government proposal to increase by 2.86 billion of Patacas in budget expenses, to reinforce social support. The review includes the creation of a subsidy, totaling 54,000 patacas, for children up to three years old, to raise the lowest birth in the world.
Also spending on the management's investment and expenses plan fell 2.4%to 10.98 billion patacas, in annual terms. On the contrary, personnel expenses (10.61 billion) and operation (3.14 billion) increased by 1.3% and 3.4%, respectively.
In the first eight months of the year, administration expenses equivalent to 79.4% of total public revenues, which increased 3.5% to about 72.42 billion, illustrating a budget execution rate of 64.8%.
Macao current revenue rose 3.4% in the first eight months of the year to 71.99 billion patacas. Growth was driven by an increase of 5.3% to 61.88 billion patacas, in tax revenues - representing 85.5% of total current revenues.
The six city game operators pay a 35% direct tax on game revenues, 2.4% for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development, and 1.6% delivered to the Macao Foundation for cultural, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic purposes.
Total casinos revenues exceeded 163 billion patacas in the first eight months of the year, more 7.2% than in the same period as 2024.
In April, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, admitted to fear a budget deficit in 2025, due to a slowdown in the recovery of the game's revenues, still below the levels reached before the pandemic. Still, Macao ended August with a surplus in public accounts of 14.89 thousand billion patacas, more 30.4% than in the same period last year. This value is more than double the government's initial forecast for the entire year of 2025.
Macao closed 2024 with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the one recorded the previous year.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Detained for enticing minors to take pictures without clothes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/detido-por-aliciar-menores-tirar-fotos-sem-roupa/</link><description>Police have detained a 33 -year -old resident who will have enlisted, on social networks, minor male students to perform sexual acts and take photographs without clothes, in exchange for money and material goods. According to the PJ, four victims were identified. With one of these victims, the suspect even made a “sexual transaction” in a public bathroom
 
A 33-year-old resident was arrested at his workplace by the Judiciary Police (PJ) on Friday, suspected of having enlisted, on the Internet, with money and materials smaller males taking pornographic photographs, as well as the practice of sexual acts in one case. The suspect was sent to the prosecutor.
So far, the PJ has discovered four victims, all male, who study in different schools. However, the existence of more victims is not ruled out.
According to PJ, in July this year, police began to notice that the suspect would have prompted on popular social networks, such as Instagram, X and Tik Tok, minor male students taking pornographic photographs. One victim claimed to have "sold" photographs taken to his thighs to the suspect, by 850 patacas and a bag for sports shoes of a well -known brand.
In addition, proofs were found that the suspect made a “sexual transaction” with one of the victims in a public bathroom in the central zone this month. According to PJ, the suspect made a short video with his mobile phone during this "transaction", and eventually paid 650 patacas to the victim.
The detainee has begun to commit sexual crimes last year, with the police investigating the amount of photographs and porn videos involved in the case. According to the PJ, the single individual has a special fetish for smaller students, and for now, no other criminal records of this suspect, nor female victims, were found.
The PJ has appealed to young people and adolescents that they are vigilant for online friendships, do not accept cybernauts' invitations and ask for help as soon as possible if they are damaged.
 
Young man tried to escape after driving driving
In another case, police detained a 20 -year resident on suspicion of driving under the influence of alcohol. The case occurred on the northern avenue of the Hippodrome at dawn on Thursday, when the young man tried to escape from an inspection of the Public Security Police (CPSP) to his vehicle.
On the other hand, the police warned the population because they re -detected telephone messages about alleged “road infringement fines” sent to citizens by burns who were passed by CPSP.
In addition, the PJ registered six more cases of telephone mockery related to false customer support employees of “TAOBAO”. Six residents suffered damage to the total of 310,000 patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital Challenges of the SMEs discussed within APEC</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desafios-digitais-das-pme-debatidos-seio-da-apec/</link><description>oznorcobr



Representatives of economics and technological development services attended a meeting of APEC's working group to present measures launched by the Government of MSAR to promote the digital transformation of small and medium enterprises
 
The South Korean city of Jeju welcomed the 60th meeting of the Small and Medium Enterprises of Economic Cooperation of Asia Pacific (APEC), which was attended by elements of the Directorate of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT) representing Macao as “invited member economy”.
During the meeting, the head of the Division of Support for Industrial and Commercial Activities, Chan Chi Ieng, shared the recent measures of the Government of MSAR to promote the digital transformation of small and medium enterprises (SMEs). According to DSEDT, the presentation included SME 2025 digitization services, which aim, through business digitization training, provide free business diagnoses and free solutions and fully enable SMEs to adopt appropriate digital tools to “realize their qualitative transformation”.
In addition, recalls the body, the government organized the “Digital Solutions Experience Day”, which allowed SMEs to personally experience applications of state -of -the -art innovative technologies.
The JEJE meeting focused on the exchange of opinions about the Working Group's strategic plan by 2028, and members presented the last developments and practical experiences of the project group projects, with a special focus on the challenges faced by SMEs and specific measures of innovation. At the same time, participants exchanged impressions on various subjects, namely the optimization of the Entrepreneurship and Operational Environment for the SMEs, the expansion of the scale and incentives for innovation through financing channels, the access to international markets, the integration in global value chains and the digital and ecological transition.
In general, according to DSEDT, the meeting aimed to “help SMEs in the realization of sustainable development in the context of the global economy, through in-depth exchange and practical cooperation with the economies of the Asia Pacific region”.
The body ensures that it will continue to participate, proactively, in APEC's relevant activities, to deepen the connection and cooperation with other economies. Thus, it believes that it will be possible to propel together a “sustainable and high quality development” of the Asia-Pacific SMEs.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau takes “Jacone Polyphony” to the Venice Biennial</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-leva-polifonia-de-jacone-a-bienal-de-veneza/</link><description>Created by curators Feng Yan and NG Sio Ieng, in conjunction with three local artists, the “Jacone Polyphony” project will represent Macao at the Venice Art Biennial in 2026

“Jacone Polyphony”, a project proposed by curators Feng Yan and NG Sio Ieng, in collaboration with local artists Fok Hoi Seng, the Chi Wai and Fung Ieng Law, was selected for the Macao Event of Macau integrated at the 61st International Art Exhibition of the Venice Biennial in May 2026, the Cultural Institute (IC), the initiative organized by Museum, announced the initiative. of macao art. The jury joined Feng Boyi, renowned curator and independent art critic, Hu Bin, vice president of the Academy of Fine Arts of Canton, and Tong Chong, IC representative.
Ensuring that the process of selecting exposure proposals for the collateral event was “in strict compliance” with the procedures stipulated in the regulation, the IC clarified that he invited prominent curatorial curators/groups that were distinguished in the “Macao Art Art” "Art International Art Biennial 2025" contest. "The proposals were evaluated based on criteria such as the degree of relevance in relation to the theme, the curatorial concept, the visionary, academic, original, innovative and unique, enforceability and operationality," the same note underlines.
The choice fell on “Jacone Polyphony”, which, according to the IC, “builds a multifaceted dialogue, which transcends time and space, between history and the contemporary era, around the creative path and cultural fusion explorations of the artist Wu Li (his Portuguese name is Jacone), who studied theology in Macau during the beginning of the qing dynasty, through narrative, through the narrative ‘Polyphonic’ ”. “Echoing this year's biennial theme, 'in smaller shades', the proposal explores the fluidity and fusion of culture, belief and spirit in a globalized context, taking ways to intercultural understanding and self -reflection, simultaneously preserving cultural uniqueness,” says the body, stressing that “this highlights the singular gene of Macao as an important center of the cultural exchange between the east West ”.
The jury praised the proposal for its approach, as it takes as its starting point the historical connection between Wu Li and Macau. Moreover, through its religious and cultural context, "resonates with the context of Venice", illustrating "the academic depth and originality." "The proposal not only reflects cultural fluidity and spiritual dialogue, but also highlights the historical presence and contemporary vitality of Macao multiculturalism," the IC also wins.
Curators Feng Yan and NG Sio Ieng have long acted in the field of contemporary art, while Fok Hoi Seng, Chi Wai and Fung Ieng Lei, are young artists from Macao who participated in various international exhibitions and art projects, emerging as experts in the “exploitation of cultural identity and transregional dialogue”.
Created in 1895, the Venice Biennial is the largest and oldest international contemporary art event in the world. Dedicated to the “smaller” theme, proposed by renowned curator Koyo Kouoh, the 2026 edition aims to create a great polyphonic artistic event, focused on several marginal voices and narratives in global culture. Since 2007, the Macau Museum of Art has actively participated in this international platform, “consistently promoting the singular charm and the creative energy of contemporary art from Macau to the world, offering important inspirations and expectations for both the artistic and public circle,” concludes the IC.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Victor Hugo Marreiros exposes digital art</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/victor-hugo-marreiros-expoe-arte-digital/</link><description>Works in Digital Art, with emphasis on works of historical and cultural diversity, will be presented today by Victor Hugo Marreiros in the Macao Tower. The artist says the title of the exhibition, "Coffee Tea", is "a slight way to say Western-Oriental"

























Victor Rebelo
 
Victor Hugo Marreiros inaugurates at the end of this afternoon an exhibition with 59 digital art works of his own. The show, entitled “Coffee Tea”, encompasses diverse works, which meet western and eastern cultures, highlighting Portuguese and Chinese cultures, as well as symbolizing historical aspects and events of Macao. The local artist told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the name of the exhibition “is a way of saying Western (Coffee) and Eastern (Tea)”.
In the pieces that will be on display at Galeria Articulate, located at the Macao Tower Convention and Entertainment Center, Victor Hugo Marreiros releases various digital art works that portray striking figures of literature, such as Camilo Pessanha, Wenceslau de Morais and Luís Vaz de Camões, heroes of the discoveries, such as Jorge Álvares and infant D. Henrique, without forgetting Fernão Mendes Pinto, Pinto, Pinto, Pinto, Explorer, Portuguese Jesuit merchant and missionary, or even fado singer Amália Rodrigues.
The digital art show also addresses aspects related to events in Macao history, especially the victory in the battle against the Dutch in 1622.
It is recalled that the designer has produced, since 1990, the visual identities of the “June, Portugal month” in Macao. These posters evolved to “cultural time capsules, reflecting common concerns, from pandemic masks and money trees during confinements to images that evoke peace, migration and global crises, all transmitted through their graphic delicacy,” says the curator of the exhibition.
William Chi-Kian Lam adds that "the city of Macao, forged over six centuries of sino-Portuguese interaction, is unique in its mix of Chinese traditions and Portuguese heritage."
Thus, "in the midst of such a rich cultural screen," he says that "few designers have had the ability to translate this hybridization into visual language as powerfully as it."
In the introduction of the exhibition, Victor Hugo Marreiros states that he grew up in Macao surrounded by the aromas of coffee and tea. “I was always attracted to what I see, and mix Chinese paint with the Photoshop brush, the irony with longing, and serving it all in a cup that sometimes burns, sometimes it smiles, it's all a matter of lines or… pleasure,” he said.
In the text of the event, it can be read that "Macau, often described as a 'microcosm', has been a meeting point between Chinese and Portuguese cultures for over six centuries." This unique confluence "gave rise to a distinct visual and spiritual landscape."
The artist, who is one of the founders of the Amaga Gallery, held the position of artistic director of TDM, in the 1980s. From 2003, he led the graphic department of the Cultural Institute.
In 1986, he won a scholarship to attend the Higher School of Fine Arts of Porto, in Portugal, deepening its mastery of modern design approaches.
It was honored by the Government of Macao in 1999, with the Medal of Professional Merit, in recognition of its significant contributions to culture and creative industries. That same year, along with Ung Vai Meng, he became one of the first Macanese designers to hold an out-of-door exhibition, entitled “Two Men from Macau”, at Osaka's DDD Gallery (1999), presenting visual works of local culture.
His graphic design and illustration work won several awards in local and international contests.
The exhibition “Coffee Tea” has the opening session scheduled for this afternoon, at 6.30 pm, being clear to the public until January 26, 2026, from 10h00 to 18:30, Monday to Sunday.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Neo-Realism Museum shows works of 14 artists on the Mand</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/museu-neo-realismo-mostra-obras-de-14-artistas-na-raem/</link><description>Two dozen works by 14 artists represented at the Neo-Realism Museum, in Vila Franca de Xira, are now available at the TAP Seac Gallery, under the Macau Art Biennial

The Neo-Realism Museum, in Vila Franca de Xira, brought 20 works by 14 artists to the Macao International Art Biennial with the exhibition “The Reinvention of the Real”. Inaugurated on Friday, the exhibition brings together pieces from the museum's contemporary art collection, selected in response to the Biennial Curatorial motto, "Hello, what do you do here?", According to a statement from the Vila Franca de Xira City Council, which protects the entity.
Patent until November 16 at the TAP Seac Gallery, exhibition is curated by David Santos, scientific director of the Museum, and the artist, curator and university professor José Apples of Carvalho, and includes works by Alice Geirinhas, Ana Pérez-Queiroga, André Cepeda, Carla Filipe, Fernando José Pereira and José Carvalho himself. Luciana Fina, Luísa Ferreira, Manuel Santos Maia, Miguel Palma, Paulo Mendes, Pedro Cabral Santo, Rita Barros and Valter Vinagre are the other artists represented in the exhibition.
The Macao Art Biennial opened on July 18 and takes place until October 19, with about 30 exhibitions of 46 artists.
For the mayor of Vila Franca de Xira, Fernando Paulo Ferreira, quoted in the statement, this international participation is “a huge honor” and “an opportunity to show not only the collection of contemporary art, but also the Tauromacic culture, the equestrian art, the gastronomy, the natural heritage, the immaterial heritage of the municipalities, the history and the traditions of the county”.
On the sidelines of the inauguration of the exhibition, Fernando Paulo Ferreira told Lusa wanting to take advantage of the presence at the Biennial to promote the municipality in China. The period of more than two months of exhibition represents “a hypothesis of being able to show the potential of our territory to a gigantic market, which is the Chinese market,” he said.
Vila Franca de Xira has prepared a program parallel to the exhibition that includes the trip to Macau from several artists to make workshops, including a cartoonist. “We will take the opportunity to show (…) some products that we have our territory and our traditions,” said the mayor.
A winemaker will talk about the “Encostas de Xira”, a wine produced by the municipality itself, and students of the “José Falcão” bullfighting school will come to Macau, where the last bullfight took place in 1997, still during the Portuguese administration.
Students will show the ballroom, “a show in which they demonstrate the techniques they use to grave on foot,” explained the mayor. “It is always an aesthetically beautiful show that, for those who do not know, is not used to, will certainly be delighted with this experience,” predicted Ferreira.
The mayor said the presence in Macao "is a window of opportunity that opens and that Vila Franca [de Xira] could not lose", for example to edge contacts with the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry.
David Santos explained that the artists were chosen for sharing “the kind of social and political concern” that characterized the neorealist movement.
In the late 1930s, it was “a very important movement in the history of art and literature and culture in Portugal, in the context of Salazar dictatorship, with an oppositional sense that marked several decades,” said Santos. The curator argued that the show is an example of how "art is a universal language, which opens perspectives and hypotheses of dialogue between peoples, between cultures, between nations."
The show explores the ability of art to “understand and transform society”.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cesl Asia had “productive” meeting with Portuguese minister</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cesl-asia-teve-reuniao-produtiva-ministro-portugues/</link><description>The Minister of Economics and Territorial Cohesion of Portugal, Manuel Castro Almeida received António Trindade, president and CEO of Cesl Asia, and the group's director of operations, Roland Schoorl, at a private audience during his visit to Macao, marked by the exchange of ideas on strategic cooperation in logistics, infrastructures and sustainability. During the “productive” meeting, the parties “discussed the potential of a contribution of high value from Portugal in the development of global logistics and industrial infrastructure, as well as innovative and sustainable solutions for renewable energy and agriculture in Portugal,” said Cesl Asia. According to the company, Manuel Castro Almeida also suggested holding a meeting later this month in Lisbon to discuss the development of such projects, in coordination with other relevant entities. Accompanying the minister was Philòmene Dias, director of AICEP - Portuguese Agency for Foreign Investment and Foreign Investment, Nuno Lima Leite and Bernardo Pinho, heads of AICEP's representation in Beijing and Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Libraries targeted by improvement works</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bibliotecas-alvo-de-obras-de-melhoramento/</link><description>The Cultural Institute (IC) will start this Monday a series of small improvement works in several public libraries of Macao, to “further improve the spatial quality and efficiency of facilities”. During the works, which should extend until mid-December, libraries will be open, so users may continue to use their services. According to the IC, the works focus on the “renewal and updating of infrastructures” of libraries, including pavement renewal, wall repair, thermal insulator installation and modification of doors and windows, so as to “comprehensively improve the comfort and usefulness of facilities”. In addition, in view of the specific needs of some libraries, restoration of wooden windows will be carried out and the installation of additional outlets. At the same time, the Taipa Library will make several improvements from the facilities, including the renewal of the reading zones for adults and bookshelves, and the replacement of soft rugs at the “Baby Book Club”. The IC promises to make all efforts to proceed to the works during the closing periods or outside the end hours, based on the specific circumstances of each library, with the partial closure of areas and the phased implementation of the work, in order to minimize the impacts on readers.</description><pubDate>2025-09-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>North Korea erases traces of Kim after meeting with Putin in Beijing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/coreia-norte-apaga-vestigios-de-kim-apos-encontro-putin-em-pequim/</link><description>After North Korean leader Kim Jong-un reunited with Russian President Vladimir Putin in Beijing, those responsible North Koreans carefully cleaned the objects played by the country's supreme leader, when analysts say they are part of a set of security measures to fight foreign spies.
Even with the appearance of a growing friendship between Kim and Putin, the 3 September images showed the extraordinary measures of the North Korean state to hide any track over Kim's health.
In a publication on Telegram, Kremlin reporter Alexander Yunashev shared images of Kim's team to meticulously clean the room in the Chinese capital where Kim and Putin met for more than two hours.
The backrest and arms of the chair were rubbed, and a coffee table next to Kim's chair was also cleaned. Your glass has also been removed.
"After the end of the negotiations, the team accompanying the head of the RPDC carefully destroyed all the traces of Kim's presence," said the reporter. RPDC is the abbreviation of the official name of North Korea, Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
After conversations in the living room, Kim and Putin left for tea and said goodbye warmly.
As with previous trips to the foreigner, Kim took his own living house in a green train that took him to Beijing to hide information about his health, said the Japanese newspaper Nikkei, citing South Korean and Japanese information agencies.
Such measures have been the standard protocol since Kim's predecessor era, his father, Kim Jong-il, said Michael Madden, a US-based North Korean leadership expert.
"The special bathroom and the necessary garbage bags with debris, waste and cigarette tips are for a foreign intelligence agency, even friend, does not get a sample to test it," said Madden.
"This would provide information on any medical conditions that affect Kim Jong-un. This may include hair and skin marks."
In 2019, after a Hanoi summit with US President Donald Trump, Kim guards were seen blocking the floor of their hotel room to clean the room for hours and remove items, including a mattress.
Kim's team was also seen to clean items meticulously before he used them. During his meeting with then South Korean President Moon Jae-in, in 2018, North Korean security guard sprayed a chair and a disinfectant table and cleaned them before Kim sit down.
According to Reuters, in another Summit with Putin in 2023, Kim's security team cleaned the disinfectant chair in advance and vigorously checked if it was safe, with a security guard using a metal detector to scan the seat, as a video showed.
 
JTM with Western Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>