<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Renewal of Macau Houses may reinforce interest in the meeting of young people</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/renovacao-das-casas-de-macau-podera-reforcar-interesse-encontro-de-jovens/</link><description>In addition to other activities that will perform throughout this year, the Association of Young Macanese starts now thinking about the best way to promote the next edition of the Macanese Youth Meeting, scheduled for 2026. Over a year away, António Monteiro told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that there are some criteria to take into account in the pre-pre-preparation of the event. One of the priorities is the contact with the current Chief Executive, "to whom the willingness will be transmitted to organize the meeting." Then “get financial support” by the Macau Foundation. The event, at the Optics of the leader, may serve to captivate younger people to participate in the actions developed by the Houses of Macao da Diaspora, believing in the "renewal". Regarding the Association's Event Plan for 2025, in focus will be an exhibition about Macaense sport
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Association of Young Macanese (AJM) has already defined the plan of activities for this year, after confirming the subsidies requested to the Macau Foundation, but, even more than a year away, also begins to prepare for another edition of the meeting of the Young Macanese, scheduled for 2026. The president of AJM believes that the event will be a reality, but there are some criteria to establish.
"First, we have to visit the new Chief Executive, which we have not yet had this possibility, to inform him of our intention to organize the meeting and ask for his support," he told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau António Monteiro, noting that the Macanese young meeting is organized by AJM, unlike the senior event, which is initiative of the Macanese Council of Communities and has a larger dimension.
"The separation of the two meetings, in terms of organization, does not mean that there is no connection between them, but on the contrary, but in our case we intend that the meeting of young Macanese is not just a simple conviviality, but have another type of activities, providing participants with some exploration, not only of Macanese culture, but also at the level of interests that may then come to Macau more often," he says.
The objective will be, reinforces, "not only integration in China, but also projecting externally Macao." The conviviality, however, is always a part of extremely important, because it is necessary to “that people explore their roots, to know families, to know that there is macanese culture, gastronomy, theater in Patuá”.
Second, "because probably some of their parents or grandparents have not passed the testimony to them," says António Monteiro, adding that "in a way, they, the young macanese, directly or indirectly, are linked to the roots of Macao and the meeting will provide this condition of finding themselves and know what their identity is."
 
Avoid aging of Macau houses
Already at the last meeting of the Macanese, promoted by the Macanese Council of Communities and which took place in late last year, the issue of the aging of Macao's houses around the world was very focused. António Monteiro notes this reality, but believes that there may be renewal.
"There are places, for example, Sao Paulo, in Brazil, where new people are appearing and this is what the rest have to seek to promote, this renewal, trying to avoid this phase of aging of houses, so that they are not just more museums," he says, "conviviality is always important, but the houses of Macao da Diaspora have to be more than that, otherwise young people do not feel motivated."
The meeting of the young Macanese can also serve to “show our usefulness before the Macao government, which makes me more sense to me,” attests the president of AJM, considering that “it is necessary to reinvent, for example, the writings”.
António Monteiro suggests that “more people write books, that there are people taking more photographs, or projecting their work at Macao Houses” through various means of publicity such as videos, or newsletters. "There is so much to spread the culture," says the leader, stressing that "it is in this sense that we have to go forward, not only the Macao associations, but also the houses around the world."
 
Macaense Relics on Exhibition
Leaving the theme of the young Macanese who, it seems to bring people from the diaspora in 2026, especially the new generations, AJM number one revealed to JTM that Macaense sport will be the subject of an exhibition, possibly taking place in September or October.
"As this year coincides with the holding of several sports events in Macao -and particularly the national games -it is time to gather some memories, some relics of local sports practiced by macanese athletes in different modalities, from football to hockey in the field, passing through roller hockey and the big prize," he said, stressing that he will talk to the Rui Cunha Foundation for those who were responsible for It is performed, "because there has been a great collaboration between the two organisms."
The show aims to “awaken the side of Macaense sport” and will feature, in addition to photographs and documents, also with objects such as sticks, equipment used in sports, facts of car and motorcycle races, among others.
“We will contact several people from the past, but also the younger ones, those who still practice some of these sports, to participate in the exhibition,” says António Monteiro. Regarding sport, he also indicated that there will also be the annual soccer tournament at the Portuguese school.
 
Qinghai is the destination of the annual tour
The associative leader also confirms another tour to members of the Association, which will be destined for the province of Qinghai, in the north of the continent, in July, once again with the support of the connecting cabinet once again
These annual trips of cultural exchange aim, according to the AJM official, to “make known the various Chinese regions”, in two ways, one formal and one informal. "The first allows us to maintain conversations with the authorities of these provinces and in some way establishes exchange contacts, of which cultural or business effects may arise."
The most informal road of the trip of about six days, for about 20 AJM members, "will make it possible to know these regions, in tourist terms, their attractions and even places where the common visitor has more difficulty in access." In 2024, the tour went to Jilin.
Meanwhile, the association goes to elections this year, all pointing out to take place in August. António Monteiro should continue as president, if there are no other lists. Macaense is available to face a second term, even though they liked that the board be led by someone younger. "I am already 40 and it was good that the lesser names would emerge and take the projects that AJM has to develop in the future," he said.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Global uncertainties and price records drop the goldsmiths</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/incertezas-globais-recordes-de-precos-fazem-cair-negocios-das-ourivesarias/</link><description>Suffering the impact of global and geopolitical economic uncertainties and the consequent increase in the price of gold, which continues to beat historical records, Macao's goldsmiths saw their businesses fall between 30% and 40% in annual terms, the Macao Ouri-Airisaries Association said. To the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Cheok Kuan Law explained that the sector faces a “dilemma” related to weak consumer buying and selling intentions, which have had “little confidence” in the market
 
Among the clouds of uncertainty caused by global financial instability and geopolitical tensions, the price of gold continues to beat historical maximum records, surpassing 3,051 US dollars yesterday afternoon. The effects of this phenomenon have been strongly felt by the goldsmiths and jewelery in Macao.
"The impact has been very strong. The price of gold so high shaking consumers will buy it unless the demand is rigid. Currently, consumers only decide to buy gold after clearly observed the point of situation in general," he began by describing the vice president of the Macao Goldsmills Association.
Heard by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, Cheok Kuan Law revealed that after the Chinese New Year, the turnover of Macao goldsmiths “fell dramatically”, and the break should have reached 30% to 40% over last year's same period. In addition, the associative leader pointed out that some goldsmiths recently recorded an even more significant decrease in business than those percentages, due to records of the price of gold.
As described in the past all “gold waves” recorded active transactions as to the purchase and range of sale. However, the conjuncture became this time “very strange,” he said.
“In the current 'gold wave', the public has been reliable, because they are not sure, worrying about the continuation of the price of gold after sale or with any price breaks after purchase. In a dilemma context, the businesses of goldsmiths and jewelery have come to fall strongly,” noted Law Cheok Kuan.
In addition, the associative leader lamented that, even as for rigid demand customers, that is, those who bought gold for marriage, the weakening of purchasing power also resulted in a “significant decrease” in the sector's revenues, which constitutes another face of difficulty. "For example, before, these types of customers bought one to two (about 37.4 to 74.8 grams) of gold, but now it is frequent just wanting to buy a golden product less than a tael," he said.
About the future of the sector, the vice president of the Ourives Association stressed that it is necessary to observe the global financial conjuncture, the geopolitical trends, as well as the evolution of “desceolarization”, whose rhythm “has been increasingly accelerated”. "If 'dedolarization' becomes increasingly accelerated and severe, it is possible the price of gold to record even more notorious fluctuations," he said.
For Cheok Kuan Law, in the current context, local goldsmiths should “redouble care” and prepare sufficient capital flow. "Otherwise, if the sale suddenly occupies the overwhelming majority of the sector's total transactions, and the goldsmiths were unable to receive the gold from sellers, then there would be a contradiction. So we want to appeal to the sector to be more careful about this," he said.
It is recalled that last Friday, the gold surpassed, for the first time in history, the mark of $ 3,000 per jaguar. Exactly a year ago, the price of gold was about $ 2,158 per jaguar, which means a 41.3% increase in the range of one year.
 
Increases the number of injuries by alliance store to 16
The Macao Consumer Council (CC) has already received 16 complaints of people injured by a wedding sales center. The complaints, which a few days ago, cipher in seven, increased significantly, with some complaints communicating cases to the police and asking for help from the CC. According to PJ, nine victims will have lost 120,000 patacas in total. To the Chinese radio show “or Mun Tin Tai”, a listener said that after buying the product, that store did not hand it at combined height. At the same program, the CC said it is a store registered in Macao by a Hong Kong company, but at this time is not operating in the MSAR. The body ensures that if the cases imply crime will forward them to the competent services.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand will create “better conditions” to attract Lusophone companies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-criara-melhores-condicoes-para-atrair-empresas-lusofonas/</link><description>The secretary for the economy and finance has ensured that “Macau will spend efforts necessary to effectively play his role” from a sino-illusophone platform, and one of the objectives is to create “better conditions” to attract Lusophone companies to settle in the MSAR. In a meeting with the ambassadors of Lusophone countries in China, they expressed the desire that new opportunities for cooperation can be explored ”
 
Economic and commercial cooperation in the areas of investment and financial sector and development of the role of Macao as a platform between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP) were some of the topics on the table, in a meeting between the secretary for the economy and finance, Tai Kin IP, and the delegation of PLP ambassadors in China. According to a statement from the secretary's office, Tai Kin IP intends to create “better conditions” to attract Lusophone companies to MSAR.
The secretary began by stressing that “over the years, Macau has been developing his role” by platform - and this way will be to continue next. He later pointed out that, in recent years, bilateral trade between China and PLP have increased stablely and cultural and humanistic exchange has also become more frequent.
Tai Kin IP also said that the focus will remain developmental positioning while “a center, a platform, a base”, and the “hard” participation in the joint construction of “a track, a route”. In addition, the idea is also to continue to “enrich” the platform content between China and Lusophone countries.
To this end, he continued, “Macau will spend efforts necessary to effectively play his role as a 'accurate interlocutor'” in order to deepen international cooperation and exchange, proactively participate in the construction of the in-depth cooperation and the large bay, as well as to promote “with all the commitment” the development of the main industries, “creating better conditions to attract companies from Portuguese-speaking countries to settle in the countries to settle in territory ”.
At the time, the ruler also took the opportunity to direct to companies in the interior of China and PLP an invitation to participate in the 2nd edition of the “China-Paraís Economic and Commercial Exhibition of Portuguese Language (Macau)” (C-PLPEX) this year, “aiming at the full potentiation of the role of Macau as a sino-sirophone platform and exploration of more business opportunities between China and PLP”.
For its part, the delegation of Lusophone ambassadors, and according to the statement issued by the Social Communication Office, praised the importance given to the partnership with China. He also appreciated the role of platform played by Macao, as a connection bridge in the economic and commercial promotion between China and the PLP.
"All parts also expressed the desire that, through the steps of the Macao Forum and the Macao Platform, more investment can be attracted, and at the same time, exploring new opportunities for cooperation in the fields of economic and commercial promotion and cultural and humanistic exchange, among others, fostering the implementation of initiatives and projects in both directions," he can read.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Verde Island Convent is still in the restoration phase</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/convento-da-ilha-verde-continua-em-fase-de-restauro/</link><description>The Cultural Institute told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the next stage in the Green Island Hill will be to promote, as soon as possible, the restoration work of the convent. On the other hand, the body led by Leong Wai Man ensured that hill safety at the level of cultural heritage and fire prevention, as well as its hygienic environment, no longer face urgent problems
 
Upon completion of the removal of the garbage accumulated in the Convent of Ilha Verde, the demolition of several illegal constructions and the repair of the stone stairs and the containment walls linked to the convent in early 2024, over the last year, the owner of the Green Island Hill and the convent “continuously advanced” with the project of the restor of the remaining spaces of the convent (IC).
According to an answer sent to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the IC said that in the next phase, it will continue to strengthen the coordination with the owner, in order to promote the restoration work of the “as soon as possible” convent. At the same time, he assured that he will intensify cooperation with public services of different skills to join jointly the protection of the Green Island Hill.
According to the Cultural Institute, currently, in Colina, the most urgent protection problems are already solved regarding the safety of cultural heritage, fire safety and hygiene environment.
Regarding the 29 ancient trees, IC has asserted that it will continue to coordinate the Institute for Municipal Affairs and the owner in the development of the protection and classification of these plants, in accordance with the cultural heritage safeguard law.
Regarding the hill development guidance for the future, the body led by Leong Wai Man stated that, in favor of safeguarding the historical and cultural value of Colina da Ilha Verde, IC will continue to coordinate with competent services and to issue technical opinions in the scope of cultural heritage protection.
It is recalled that, at the beginning of the last year, the problems were also solved, which existed for many years, from an obsolete vehicle park, and the accumulation of a large amount of waste, flammable and dangerous substances. Part of the green vegetation and open spaces were also recovered, which resulted in “significant improvements” in the hill and convent environment.
Before that, the problem of illegal occupation was resolved in mid-2023. At the same time, the owner presented a suggestion for the government to expropriate the hill, exchanging it to another terrain. At the end of the same year, the owner revealed a preliminary planning that predicted the construction of a hotel, two giant wheels and a cable car in that area. Specifically, he proposed that one of the "giant wheels" was called "Vira", inspired by "Vira do Minho".
On the other hand, in February this year, a group of residents of Verde Island handed a petition to the Chief Executive. In the document, he appealed to the government to create an exclusive interdepartal group to treat hill expropriation procedures and their compensation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UTM creates company in hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/utm-cria-empresa-em-hengqin/</link><description>The in -depth cooperation zone now has a company created by the University of Tourism and Macau, which is dedicated to consulting services in the areas of education, technology, among others
 
The University of Tourism of Macau (UTM) created, on the other side of the border, the “UTM Education Consulting Company in the in -depth cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin, Ltd.”, which, among other services, will provide consulting. UTM is the only shareholder, and the company has a social capital of 100,000 Renminbis, according to the information contained in the public disclosure platform for public capital companies.
The company created by UTM addresses consulting services in the area of ​​education; Technological services, technology development, technology consulting, technology exchange, technology transfer, technology promotion; Research on policies and regulations; as well as about conference and exhibition services.
According to the information provided, it is also dedicated to information consulting services, testing and evaluations in the field of education and education, business training and social and economic consulting services. In addition, other areas of action are the consulting and planning of tourism development projects, business management and organization of cultural and artistic exchange activities.
In January, it is recalled, the institution's dean, Fanny Vong, said, regarding the UTM campus in Hengqin, that the project was still on planning, and the university had not yet requested the terrain for this purpose. The Jornal Tribuna de Macao contacted UTM to realize if, however, the request has already been made, however, until the closing of this edition did not receive any response.
In December last year, the then Chief Executive, Ho Iat Seng, stressed that the new campus of the University of Macao (one) in Hengqin should serve as a "example" for other higher education institutions in the territory.
Last month, the Macao University of Science and Technology asked the government to extend the campus to Hengqin, as the institution lacks spaces for its development, rector, Joseph Lee Hun-Wei, revealed. The request was formalized at the end of last year.
On the other hand, Guangdong Hengqin a Higher Education Development Co. Ltd., created by UM to make investments across the border and provide consulting services, saw the capital of socially grow from 50 thousand Renminbis to four billion, according to information on the public capital companies platform. One is the majority shareholder (72.35%), with a limited (27.65%) to also have a stake. A limited tec was founded in 2006 and is a public capital company of UM.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China consumer plan should benefit game</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/plano-de-consumo-da-china-devera-beneficiar-jogo/</link><description>The Macao game sector should benefit from the recently announced consumption incentives for China, considers consultant Seaport Research Partners
 
The latest consumption incentive package announced by China is expected to favor the game industry in Macau - this is at least the conviction of consultant Seport Research Partners, who provides for an increase in consumer confidence and purchasing power.
"The Chinese government recently announced ambitious plans to boost consumption and improve consumer confidence," said Vitaly Umansky analyst, in a note published on Wednesday, adding that "these political initiatives should provide a positive wind for Macao's recipes."
The package of measures, announced on Sunday by the Central Committee of the Chinese Communist Party and Council of State (Executive), aims to revitalize internal demand and relieve consumer financial charges. It includes 30 measures distributed by eight areas, such as increased population income, support for purchasing power, improving the quality of service consumption and renewing durable goods. One of the central points is the promotion of family performance, especially the salary increase.
Although the specific details of the financing have not yet been disclosed, Umansky stressed the relevance of politics. "The importance of changing economic focus and prioritizing consumer economy is of critical importance to the future economy of China and for the purchasing power of consumers," he said, adding that policies to improve consumer demand were "expected", given "the government's concern about weak consumption."
"We hope that, in the medium term, these measures will help support the growth of Macao's demand," said the analyst, and then add: "The improvement of consumer confidence and the expansion of consumer portfolios should provide long -term support for the growth of Macao's mass customer base."
Although the Premium Games segment has shown resilience in postpandeia recovery, Seaport's report points out that the base market (composed of less spending players) remains weaker than expected. In concrete, the consultant estimated that this segment is still about 15% below 2019 levels.
Despite the immediate challenges, Umansky suggested that the latest China stimulus initiatives should support the growth of the Macao Casinos sector in 2025 and 2026. According to his observation, Beijing also seems to be positive political stance on Macau, giving as an example the expansion of various policies to facilitate the travels of mainland China.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Illegal guide case delivered to CPSP</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caso-de-guia-ilegal-entregue-ao-cpsp/</link><description>STD detected an illegal guide in Senate Largo, which was sent to CPSP for being involved in activities that did not correspond to the quality of tourist. The body states that it is “committed” to combat illegal guides
 
After receiving information from operators about the existence of an illegal excursion in Macao, the direction of tourism services (STD) highlighted staff to follow the case, having found the group in Largo do Senate. "After investigation on the spot, the notification against an individual suspected of the illegal exercise of the tour guide profession was raised, and the subsequent sanctioning procedures was established," said the body led by Helena de Senna Fernandes.
Since the individual was also involved in activities that did not correspond to the quality of tourist, the case was delivered to the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP).
Underlining that it has been “committed” to maintain order in the tourist industry, STD adds that it has continued to combat the activity of illegal tour guides. In concrete, he said that in 2024 he carried out 1,615 inspections at the border and sights, along with random inspections to the tour operators' work situation.
In addition, in conjunction with CPSP, he made inspections to combat the illegal activities of the tour guides, and the news records against 17 individuals suspected of illegally exercising the tour guide profession were raised.
Already between January and March 16 this year, STD made 314 inspections at the main points of tourist attraction and border posts. The body also states that it continues to maintain contacts with the tourism authorities in the interior of China, "and immediately report cases of irregularities, to reinforce the combat of illegal activities."
At the same time, it disseminates with the tourist excursions and operators in the interior of China that the Macao excursions organization has to follow "a certain way, including the need to be received by local receiving travel agencies and have legal tour guides."</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ecological Transformation Brand this year's edition of MIECF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/transformacao-ecologica-marca-edicao-deste-ano-miecf/</link><description>The Macau 2025 International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition (MIECF), which starts on the 27th, bets on the development of ecological transformation. The event will present three sessions of the “Green Forum”, which will bring together experts and academics from various countries
 
For three days, between March 27 and 29, the Macao 2025 International Environmental Cooperation Forum and Exhibition (MIECF) will discuss issues such as the development of ecological transformation, technological innovation and exchange and cooperation with the Rio das Pearl Pan-Delta region within the environment of environmental protection.
The MIECF, which will take place in Venetian, will have as its central theme “Innovation and Green Development - Solutions for the Construction of Beautiful Cities”, and along with the exhibition has programmed three sessions of the “Green Forum”, bringing together renowned experts and academics from the interior of China, Portuguese -speaking countries, Europe, Hong Kong and Macau, which will jointly explore new opportunities for exchange and cooperation jointly explore exchange and cooperation. environmental at the international level.
Among the sessions, highlight the “green transition driven by new quality productive forces”, which will take place on the morning of the second day of the fair.
"The promotion of eco -and -carbon ecological practices is essential for the high quality development of society, in an era characterized by rapid global economic growth and limited resources," according to a text by the organization.
The same statement adds that "emerging quality productive forces, which integrate advanced technologies, operational efficiency and high quality standards, are a new driving force that fosters socio-economic development towards ecological transformation."
For this session, national and international experts and academics were invited, including the Director-General of the Central Office of Supervision and Coordination of the Ecological and Environmental Protection of the Ministry of Ecology and Environment of the Popular Republic of China, XU Bijiu, the president of the Portuguese Environment Agency Board, José Carlos Pimenta Machado, the team of the investigation group of the Water Resources Research Institute. Hydroelectric from China, GAO BO, and the co-founder and director of Algaesys S.A.), James Lander. The host is the interim director of the University of Macao Cheng Yu Tung College, Wong Seng Fat, Alfred.
Speakers will present advice and suggestions on green development and explore the role of new quality productive forces in promoting economic growth and safeguarding ecological integrity, thus realizing a promising future of sustainable development.
In this year's edition, MIECF will continue to apply for professional certification for scheduled sessions and certificates of participation will be issued.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands launches book on Rua das Estlagês</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sands-lanca-livro-sobre-rua-das-estalagens/</link><description>The book Bilingual “In search of its roots - an illustrated story of Rua das Estlagês”, was released by Sands China, highlighting the past of the historic Macau Street and the beauty of its legacy. The author of the book is Siguo Chen



















The iconic Rua das Estalagens, where thousands of visitors passed daily, motivated the publication of a book by Siguo Chen, released by Sands China. “In search of their roots - an illustrated story of Street of Estalagins,” says the fascinating past of the historic Macau Street and the beauty of his legacy through the efforts of collaboration of the community.
The book, produced in partnership with the Macao Artists Society, was illustrated by Shirley Lu and compiled by a team of local professionals - from edition and interviews to pagination and illustrations.
With this publication, according to a text widespread by the game concessionaire, “local residents and visitors will rediscover the preciousness of the centenary stores and the cultural heritage of the street through legendary stories”.
The book, which is sponsored by the Secretariat for Social Affairs and Culture, aims to reintroduce the ancient and contemporary aspects of Rua das Estlagences to MSAR residents and visitors, “preserving the invaluable deeds of its inhabitants”.
Through conversations with guardians of associations, business entities and residents of the neighborhood, Siguo Chen “headed the characters and historical moments of the street past through oral history,” says Sands.
The publication has a digital version and was included in the Macao Public Library file. It is also available in secondary and primary schools, in the sense of “educating the next generation and promoting a sense of cultural heritage”, stresses the statement.
Leong Wai Man, president of the Cultural Institute (IC) stated that by publishing this book, Sands makes an effort to "widen the discussion around the preservation and revitalization of Rua das Estalagues, in order to include its broader meaning to society." The IC official hopes that the restoration of the street "inspires more people to learn about the historic neighborhoods of Macao and participate in its preservation, combining ideas and resources to ensure that the city's culture and history continue to prosper during generations."
In turn, Wilfred Wong, the operator's executive vice president, said that "Rua das Estlagês is a microcosm of Macao itself, a place where a rich story meets a modern future."
Sands China's revitalization plan for that tourist zone also includes the entrepreneur recruitment program, launched in April last year. This program, the company, “seeks to support the development of local companies and boosting the economy of the neighborhood”, while “encouraging Macao residents with innovative business proposals to help revive the neighborhood economy, revitalize the street and release the vibration of the past”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau loses with Hong Kong in the first game of the year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-perde-hong-kong-primeiro-jogo-ano/</link><description>Macao's football team was defeated by Hong Kong in the first 2025 challenge. The friendly meeting was held in the neighboring territory and Kenneth Kwok's formation was beaten 2-0, with goals to appear in the first part. In the second half, the MSAR has given some signs of improvement














Victor Rebelo
 
Macau held his first meeting in Hong Kong and was defeated 2-0, goals scored during the first part of the challenge that took place at the Mong Kok Stadium, in the presence of about 5,000 spectators.
The friendly match, integrated in FIFA's game period, had a greater mastery of the house's selection, which opened the marker on 25 minutes, through the Leon Jones defense, following a corner kick.
Five minutes from the break, the "eleven" guided by Briton Ashley Westwood rose the count, this time through Raphael Merkies, an striker acting on the Shandong Taishan Chinese.
In the second half, Macau improved the quality of his game and bet a little more in offensive terms, having even arranged some danger throws with Hung Fai Yapp goal. However, it failed to change the course of events.
Macao's selection used only one non-chinian player, Nuno Pereira, a passport holder of the MSAR, having stayed in the bench Amâncio Goitia.
The initial "eleven" integrated six elements representing the Must IPO, currently classified in the Elite League, behind the Leader University of Macao. Two title champion players, Benfica, were part of the coach's options for Wednesday night's match.
On the side of Hong Kong, the team has several naturalized players, namely Leon Jones, Oliver Gerbic, Everton Camargo, Fernando Pereira, Raphael Merkies, Benhaddouche Clément, Stefan Pereira, Nicholas Benavides, Awal Matawa and Christian Alexander.
This was the seventh consecutive victory for the selection of the neighboring territory and the challenge against Macau served as a preparation for the first meeting of the C Qualification Group for the Asia Cup, which will take place on March 25 in Singapore. In the confrontation history between the two selections, Raehk has a large advantage, having won 10 and lost only one in the 11 games made.
In the Kenneth Kwok era, Hong Kong-born coach, who succeeded Luso-Angolan Lazarus Oliveira, Macau has not yet won any challenge after being beaten in the late 2024 by Guam (2-1) and Brunei (1-0).</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Local team wins Great Bay Martial Arts Tournament</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/equipa-local-vence-torneio-de-artes-marciais-da-grande-baia/</link><description>The Macao Tower hosted about 500 athletes for the 1st Chinese Wushu Cultural Festival of Asia-Pacific and the 5th Academic Championship of the Great Bay Martial Arts, from which the Wushu de Macao General Association team won. The events were sponsored by SJM
 
The Wushu de Macao General Association won first place in the 5th Academic Championship of Great Bay Martial Arts, which took place at the Macao Tower with the sponsorship of SJM Resorts. The Macao North and South Martial Arts Association achieved second position, while Hong Kong's Wushu team and the Kung Fu Sanda Association of Zhaoqing ended, respectively, in third and fourth places.
This competition, as well as the 1st Chinese Wushu Cultural Festival of Asia-Pacific, was co-organized by the Tai Chi Youth Benefice Foundation of Hong Kong and the Macao Traditional Martial Arts Institute, with the support of the Government of MSAR. The event attracted about 500 athletes from the Great Bay and Asia Pacific, including from Japan, Singapore and Malaysia.
Daisy Ho, SJM delegate and chairman of the organizing committee, said that the success of the initiative resulted from the "perfect collaboration between the organization and support teams in Hong Kong and Macao." The competition captured the spirit of the initiative “Fitness for All, Healthy China”, he said, adding that the activities “enriched the competition, mixing health and well-being events with visits to UNESCO World Heritage sites” and “reinforced Macao Statute as“ World Tourism and Leisure Center ”.
Li Fai, president of the Tai Chi Youth Charity Foundation of Hong Kong and co-president of the Organizing Committee, said this event provides a “transformative experience” by incorporating “health practices such as Baduanjin and Tai Chi”. According to Li, “more than a vibrant competition, this event is a cultural legacy that connects generations and regions”, in which participants have the opportunity to discover “the joy and benefits of welfare” martial arts.
Among the guests present were the director of tourism services, Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, and Luís Gomes, president of the Institute of Sport of Mashera.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>RAE residents may require provisional safe conduct</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/residentes-das-rae-podem-requerer-salvo-conduto-provisorio/</link><description>Residents of Macao, Hong Kong, and Taiwan can now ask for a provisional electronic conduct if they have lost it, damaged or if they have forgotten that document and need to travel by plane or quick train inside China. The measure was announced yesterday by the National Immigration Administration of China, and the document is valid for seven days. According to the information provided, residents of the three regions can use the Government Services Platform of the China National Immigration Administration to request the provisional pass, which may be the target of verification by air and rail transport companies. The aim is to "help residents of the three regions in their travels in the interior of China, avoiding any delays." Another measure was also launched, in which if residents of the three regions need to make a connection between the safe conduct and proof of residence in a city in the interior of China can resort to the same platform to do so. It is also maintained the possibility of making the request in person, with the public security authorities equal to or greater than the village. Both proofs can be verified by companies and service entities, one that can have access to a national immigration administration identification platform.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Galaxy and SCMP Seminar brings together parents and education specialists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seminario-da-galaxy-scmp-reune-pais-especialistas-em-educacao/</link><description>The Galaxy Macau will host next Sunday, March 23, between 14:00 and 17:30, a seminar centered on education, in partnership with the “Learn” program of the newspaper “South China Morning Post” (SCMP). The “Engineer Your Child’s Future Path to Wealth and Success” seminar, which will take place at the Galaxy International Convention Center, aims to present strategies to parents so that they can prepare the long -term academic path of their children. The event will be attended by admission consultants, alumni of the Universities of Ivy League and directors of UK top schools, to talk to parents about an educational planning process that ensures the academic success of their children. Among discussions conducted by experts and networking opportunities, the theme of applications for the best educational institutions in the US and the United Kingdom will be addressed. A series of “Coffee Roundtables” will allow parents to dialogue directly with experts to “ensure their children's academic success in a rapid change world,” says the Galaxy Entertainment statement. The company invites parents interested in “creating exceptional educational opportunities for their children” to participate in the “event that will launch the foundations to draw future paths for teaching in world class institutions”. The seminar will be conducted in English, with simultaneous interpretation for Mandarin.</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese widow Aum Shinrikyo speaks 30 years after attack on the metro</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/viuva-culto-japones-aum-shinrikyo-fala-30-anos-apos-ataque-metro/</link><description>Just seven years after her marriage, Yuki Niimi first touched her husband-a morgue, where she collected her body after her execution, and kissed him in a coffin. Prior to that, a glass screen always separated her from her husband, Tomomitsu Niimi, a notorious member of the final judgment Aum Shinrikyo who for 30 years orchestrated an attack with a nervous agent in the capital of Japan.
On March 20, 1995, members of AME released Sarin in five Carriages of the Tokyo Metropolitan, killing 14 people and leaving thousands sick. "Until the end, he did not apologize to those who died. He did not regret what he did."
Yuki herself is a former member of an Aum's successor group that, despite her denials, has already been convicted of using intimidation to try to recruit an acquaintance for the sect. Given the magnitude of her husband's crimes, she believes that the death penalty was "inevitable" and that "paying refund" is the only way that the cultures of AM can do.
Under the domain of rebel -haired guru and almost blind Shoko Asahara, Aum's devotees believed that the Armageão was coming and saw the massacres as an altruistic way of raising souls to a superior kingdom.
Unhappy young people in Japan, including doctors and engineers who later manufactured toxins, found comfort in Asahara's doctrines. Among the most loyal pupils was Tomomitsu, which was behind bars when he met Yuki and when they got married in 2011.
His relationship consisted of letters and 15 to 30 minutes of conversation, almost every day, under the supervision of a guard. It all ended with its execution in the summer of 2018, along with 12 other AMA members, including Asahara.
After her death, the widow Yuki stroked the still hot body of Tomomitsu, whose neck was wrapped in a ligation to hide the mark left by the loop. He then spent the next three days, to the cremation, lying next to him at home. "He didn't seem to have suffered anything. He seemed to be sleeping," she said.
Tomomitsu, who died at the age of 54, is sometimes called Aum's “bloodiest” disciple - having helped perpetrate all seven group attacks on the group, including the previous strike of the meter he served as a driver.
The AUM cultists, who were isolated and were incommunicable in the pre-internet era, "believed in everything," Asahara said, and "honestly thought they were helping their act of salvation," Yuki said.
However, about a month before Tomomitsu's execution, she felt that her loyalty to the leader was finally crumbling. “He called him only 'Asahara'-this had never happened before in the 12 years or more we were together.
Then, in his diary, “in the last days of his life, he clearly expressed that 'I will not follow him anymore'” realizing that Asahara's teachings over Karma were a fallacy, Yuki said.
Also, despite Tomomitsu's lack of remorse, "I asked why Aum had performed the gas attack on the meter, and my husband clearly told me that the guru was sick, mentally ill," he added.
The poisoning in the metro shocked the world and led to an adjustment of accounts with extremism in Japan, with a repression of the Asahara Empire, which has had more than 10,000 followers.
Its successor groups continue to operate and recruit, with estimated numbers of 1,600 in the domestic market. Two of these groups, Aleph and Hikarinowa, openly operate in Japan, which, according to some experts, makes them easier to monitor.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>