<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Coutinho says that "maintaining a place" in the hemiciclo would already be "very good"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coutinho-diz-manter-um-lugar-hemiciclo-ja-seria-muito-bom/</link><description>By this time, it is still uncertain what will be the strategy of the new hope in the elections for the Legislative Assembly. José Pereira Coutinho referred the decision on the names to join the list to the ATFPM management, when asked if theist head will keep or can be Rita Santos. The deputy said he was also “reticent” about the conquest of two seats, pointing out that maintaining a place would be “very good”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Getting a seat at the Legislative Assembly (AL) in the next elections would already be “an excellent result” for the Nova Esperança list, says José Pereira Coutinho, who said yesterday that he is still open who could head the list. "[The place will be] for whom the Directorate of the Association of Public Function Workers (ATFPM) decides," he said, when asked whether to be for his own or Rita Santos, that he twice suspended his mandate as counselor of Portuguese communities, justifying the decision with the realization of the elections.
The deputy proved to be “quite reticent” as to the results of the elections, pointing out, without specifying, that “there is already movements in society in terms of offerings, tours, gifts”. "I already have some experience, in election time everything changes overnight and I must say, frankly and honestly, that keeping a place on the new hope list is already very good," he said, adding that it would be "important" have in the hemiciclo “a voice that dominates the Portuguese language and the Chinese language”.
As for Rita Santos, she noted that "she is a public figure, a person capable of performing any public office, both in public administration and in the Assembly." "It is committed, it is a good picture, valid," said the deputy, reiterating that "it will all depend on what the direction of ATFPM understands" and even the opinions of the Portuguese communities counselors.
It is recalled that in 1996, Rita Santos was a candidate for deputy of AL, having failed to enter the hemiciclo. In October last year, it temporarily suspended the mandate as an advisor to the Portuguese communities of the Circle of China, justifying the decision with the preparation of the election of the Chief Executive and with the participation in the elections for AL in 2025. Already in January this year, He extended the suspension for another 60 days.
Pereira Coutinho, in AL since 2005, recalled that he is already fulfilling the fifth term, being "one of the deputies with the most seniority". "We need to sacrifice ourselves, it is not easy to be elected deputy by the way," he said. "Performing an examination of conscience in the last five years, I have fulfilled the role it should fulfill, serve the population, serve the Portuguese community, I am at this moment the only one that is expressed in Portuguese," he defended.
Claiming to be “confident” of the work and commitment they are dedicating to the preparation of the elections, he stressed: “We need the support of the entire population of Macao, especially the Portuguese community”. In the last elections, the New Hope got two seats.
As for Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa's visit to Macau to mark June 10, the deputy said that “it is pleasant news”, pointing out that the Portuguese school will be a subject to be on the table, since it worries the Portuguese community .
 
Policies to “revive” the economy of the
On the other hand, he said he noted "a notorious difference in the executive's attitude" regarding the period of elections for the position, "when it was much easier to have access to him." "Now it is becoming increasingly difficult," he said, although he says that "the most important thing is that there is work and implementation of policies that can solve problems."
He said, he has "high expectations" about the lines of government action, hoping that there may be policies to "revive Macao's economy." “Macao's economy is not in good health. It takes measures that can increase jobs, ”he said. "There are many unemployed people, inflation is shooting, the inflation rate does not correspond to reality and it is increasingly difficult to find a job," he said.
In addition, he said, "we have a big problem with satellite casinos that has to be solved because, otherwise, if they are extinguished, it involves tens of thousands of jobs." The only solution, he argued, "is to extend the deadline for another three years to try to find long -term solutions."</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kou Hoi in anticipating “even more intense” works in the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/kou-hoi-anteve-trabalhos-ainda-mais-intensos-na-al/</link><description>In what is the last legislative session of the current legislature, Kou Hoi In anticipates that the works of the hemiciclo are “even more intense”, also because the sixth mandate of the government begins and will be presented the lines of government action. The president of AL assured that the agency will "optimize" the mechanism of legislative production. On the other hand, he said that the review of several laws related to national security gives “guarantees of a disciplinary framework applicable to the next elections” of AL, which are held this year
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The President of the Legislative Assembly (AL) foresees that the work of the “in the near future” agency is “even more intense”, since this year is the last legislative session of the current legislature, and the sixth mandate of the government begins . At the spring lunch offered by Al to the media, Kou Hoi In also took a balance of the work so far done.
Regarding legislative initiatives, he said that they were already approved by the plenary, being appreciated in the specialty in the three permanent commissions, nine proposals of law and a project of resolution. "On the other hand, the presentation of the first report of the government lines by the new government will also be presented, followed by the debate," he recalled.
In this sense, it has ensured that the hemiciclo will make “all efforts to be completed before the legislative session.” Kou Hoi In also stressed that the legislative agency “will continue to work for the welfare of the population, to vigorously promote the glorious tradition of love for the homeland and Macau, and to accurately adhere to the new mission and the new tasks attributed to Macao on the new journey of the new age of the country. ” "We will perform the functions entrusted to us, working together to improve diverse legislation, promoting the reform of public administration and optimizing the legislative production mechanism, in coordination with the government," he added.
For the future, he has ensured that Hemiciclo will “persist, as always, in the beginning of 'a country' and enhance the advantages of 'two systems', ensuring stable and lasting implementation of the 'country, two systems' principle in Macao, and raising the level and effectiveness of the governance of MSAR by the exercise of supervisory competence ”. In concrete, he stated that the commitment will be evidenced in the “improvement of the construction of the institutional system” and the promotion of the “high quality development of the works” of AL, “seeking to progress in a stable way”.
“We are going to work towards a new mandate leap in the conquest of new development milestones in all its enterprises, thus contributing to the successful practice of the 'a country, two systems' with Macao characteristics to be projected to a new level, ”said Kou Hoi In.
According to this legislature, "2024 was the year when the AL had the most overwhelmed agenda." Nevertheless, he pointed out Kou Hoi In, “all deputies, sharing an active and pragmatic attitude in the performance of their functions, have fulfilled their attributions under the law, with a high sense of mission and responsibility”, in cooperation with the government. In your opinion, this has allowed improvements in the “efficiency” and “effectiveness” of the hemiciclo, “ensuring that all works are developed and completed in a solid, orderly and stable way”.
With regard to national security, said Kou Hoi In, "we have always taken the defense of national sovereignty, and the safety and interests of state development as guiding principles of legislative work developed by the hemiciclo." In this field, and to “better” implement “Macau governed by Patriots”, recalled that Al concluded, in 2023, the review of the electoral law for the Chief Executive and, in 2024, of the Electoral Law to the AL and the Law of Oaths on the occasion of the act of inauguration.
“The approval of these three legislative initiatives was essential, to ensure, on the one hand, that the election of the sixth chief executive had been successfully completed under the law in 2024, offering, on the other, the guarantees of applicable disciplinary framework To the next 8th al elections, to take place this year, ”he said.
Kou Hoi In also mentioned President Xi Jinping's “important speeches” on the occasion of the anniversary of the masters.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended 90 days of maternity leave</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidos-90-dias-de-licenca-de-maternidade/</link><description>Wong Kit Cheng considers that one of the most important incentives to foster birth would be to extend the maternity leave to 90 days, with the government to finance the additional 20 days
 
In view of the low birth rate, Deputy Wong Kit Cheng expects the government to adopt, through administrative regulation, the increase in maternity leave from 70 to 90 days to all Macao women. At the same time, it suggests a subsidy plan for the compensation paid in the maternity leave, and the value of this support is equivalent to 20 days of the maturity of the workers.
Noting that, for the implementation of 90 days of maternity leave, it is necessary to review the Law of Labor Relations, Wong noted that no mechanism has not yet been activated, although “the possibility of the matter being addressed in the future by the Permanent Council of Social Concertation ”.
In this respect, the deputy understands that “a measure of provisional benefit”, through an administrative regulation, would be more viable to motivate companies to launch that “friend” measure of the family. In their opinion, the authorities will be financially capable of encouraging birth in this way.
“I hope that, in the coming lines of government action (LAG), birth incentive policies will be separated from any laws, being regarded as beneficial measures for the population. In addition, in monetary terms, the increase in birth allowance and the launch of a subsidy for child care would also contribute to relieve the financial pressure of families after the birth of babies. In the long run, improving child and child care services can also make Macau environment more favorable to children's growth, ”he suggested.
"If the government does not grant subsidies under maternity, paternity, company to sick family and child care, companies will remain hesitant," he said.
On the other hand, Wong proposed a new housing policy that allows families with newborns to replace their fractions with larger ones.
Still on LAG, the subdirector of the Association of Women has exhorted the government to reinforce measures to support the population, so that "residents can effectively enjoy the fruits of economic diversification." In addition to expecting “more concrete economic measures that also serve to solve resident employment and entrepreneurship problems,” the deputy wants to see mirrored in the lag “interaction” of MSAR with the development of Hengqin.
In addition, Wong warned of increasing requests for help to the Women's Association Psychotherapy Center. Therefore, it considers that resources in the area of ​​mental health should be reinforced, as well as support to institutions that provide psychological counseling services in the community and the number of vacancies for consultations in the psychotherapy centers, among other measures.
Wong also indicated that his team expects to "keep up" in the Legislative Assembly after this year's elections, so that "there are more deputies who speak to children and their families." Stressing that the defense of the rights and interests of women and children is a “priority work” of deputies linked to the Women's Association, the desire to see more deputies in the greater participation of young people and women in politics.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Buses in breaking in the evaluation of passengers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autocarros-em-quebra-na-avaliacao-dos-passageiros/</link><description>The numbers of the latest assessment of passenger satisfaction in Macau's public bus service show that users are less satisfied. In the statistics released by services for traffic issues, regarding the service offered directly by the companies, TCM remains at the head of Transmac
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The results of the assessment of bus services in the first half of 2024 reveal that passengers felt less satisfied compared to previous periods. According to data from the Directorate of Traffic Services (DSAT), 27 points were assigned, from a total of 40, a break from the first half of 2023 (28.8 points) and the second semester of the same year (28.1 points ). According to official data, as long as the score is made at the base of a total of 40 points, this was the lowest assessment.
Regarding the degree of passenger satisfaction regarding bus companies, the numbers maintain the indications provided at the end of the same period last year, ie, TCM got a better score, having received 27.4 points, against 26, 3 of Transmac. The TCM score is, however, lower than that that was reached in the second half of 2023, when the values ​​reached 28.3.
In the data now provided by DSAT, TCM has maintained the hegemony of satisfaction for several years, specifically since the second half of 2020, after the period before Transmac has obtained, a favorable score of a few tenths above its rival.
Despite the positive numbers now revealed and regarding the second half of 2024, the TCM this time received the lowest grade of the last six reviews.
Transmac has progressively descended from quotation in the opinion of people who use buses and this second semester assessment of 2024 is the worst of its last five semiannual reviews.
On the other hand, DSAT has attributed the C+ level to the transmac performance, similar to what happens since the first half of 2021. The values ​​mean that, if there is a scale stipulated from 0 to 100 points, the transmac would get a score between 77 and 80.
The TCM received B-, that is, between 80 and 83 points, worsening its installment, since in previous statistics, first and second semesters of 2023, had been quoted with C+. It should be noted that between 2015 and 2020 the maximum score was 10 and from 2021 became 40.
Other data provided by DSAT include improvement measures by bus operators. Concretely regarding the repetition of security problems or services, such as breach of safety or driving rules, as well as accidents, there is a possibility for drivers involved to be “persuaded” to dismiss or be dismissed.
The 2024 data show that 25 bus drivers were “persuaded” to fire, while 30 said goodbye to a total of 55 drivers. The number is equivalent to a climb compared to 2023, since this year only 32 were under these circumstances.
It is recalled that pursuant to the new bus agreement, which entered into force on 1 January 2021, the service evaluation regime indicators were adjusted for service and management indicator (30%), transportation means and equipment and security (30%) and passenger satisfaction (40%).</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public libraries record high use rates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bibliotecas-publicas-registam-elevadas-taxas-de-utilizacao/</link><description>An inquiry into the Macao Public Library shows that 80% of respondents are satisfied with the global services provided. The study, commissioned by the Cultural Institute to the Polytechnic University, also revealed that 73% of respondents said they had used public library services, which means a relatively high use rate. In terms of electronic reading, about 70% have this habit
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Residents in general, students, parents and children, and non -resident workers answered 1,200 questionnaires about the Macao Public Library. The results obtained in this study commissioned by the Cultural Institute (IC) from Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) show that the average score of the degree of satisfaction attributed by respondents was almost four points, on a scale up to five, and about 80% are satisfied or very pleased with the services provided by public libraries.
The positive answers of the participants in the inquiry were directed to the time of service, the distribution sites, attitude and efficiency of the service, among others.
In addition, the research conclusions revealed that 73% of respondents said they had used public library services, which means a relatively high use rate.
In terms of electronic reading, about 70% expressed that they have a habit of reading electronic books or other electronic resources. These data reflect that reading through electronic means is becoming increasingly popular in Macao.
The results of the inquiry conducted by the UPM, in which 1,006 valid questionnaires were obtained, showed that resident reading interests are mainly leisure and relaxation, as well as obtaining information. Almost 80% read books last year, with the annual volume and time spent on reading it was at an average level.
These data illustrate a relatively high rate of participation in the reading of Macao residents, constituting a good basis for the promotion of the construction of Macau as a “reading city”, considers the IC. On the other hand, the people who participated in the investigation generally recognized the important role of public libraries in promoting reading culture.
According to the IC, public libraries will in the future "optimize their development around diversification and digitization." Given the results of the inquiry, the body will continue to reinforce the promotion of the concept of the “city of reading”, “increasing the sensitization and participation of the public in reading and developing a promotional strategy that differentiates various groups, such as local residents, workers not residents, and students. ”
At the same time, the IC ensures libraries will enrich the resources of the collection, especially electronic books and electronic resources, improving digital services for public convenience and optimizing the experience of using library resources through the combination of technology and innovation .
“There will be diverse and international reading activities, facilitating cultural exchange and cooperation, creating an inclusive reading environment and promoting the transformation of Macau into an“ influential reading city ”, reinforces the body.
The final report of the inquiry is published on the Electronic Page of the Public Library of Macao do IC, and can be consulted and discharged by residents.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Ron Lam calls for “urgent measures” to “save” economy and employment</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ron-lam-pede-medidas-urgentes-para-salvar-economia-emprego/</link><description>Deputy Ron Lam hopes LAG will include “concrete measures that can quickly have effects” to “save” the economy and employment
 
Given that the economy of Macau “has suffered a macro impact”, the government must prepare short, medium and long term measures, defended yesterday Ron Lam. At the level of resolution of “urgent problems”, the deputy considers that the executive It should launch “concrete measures that can quickly have effects” to “save” economy and employment, and improve the benefits of the population.
Specifically, Ron Lam expects the government to include, in the lines of government action (LAG), consumption incentive measures such as consumer valleys or discount programs.
In addition, he urged the executive to take “effective measures” so that “certain jobs of in some large companies” stop absorbing unspent workers and thus provide “good job opportunities to residents”.
"If the government can implement these policies, residents will resume confidence in the executive's ability to respond to public opinion," he said. According to the deputy, after this stage, the government should advance with the promotion of the diversification of the economy and employment and the improvement of the benefits of the long -term population.
Ron Lam also exhorted the government to “prove” the intention of the monetary reimbursement. “If the measure is used to share bonuses to the residents, it will be enough to have a resident identity ticket to enjoy their check. But if the objective is to mitigate the difficulties, this benefit should be attributed to residents in the territory. This is a political choice and there is no right or wrong. If it is not proven in the future, the measure will only be controversial, ”he warned.
On the other hand, he stressed that he warned the new government to the problems encountered in the proposal to build a viaduct between zones A and B of new landfills. On this article, it even ensures that many residents prefer the viaduct to be replaced by a tunnel.
In addition, the deputy criticized the viaduct planned for not including a connection to the artificial island, so it will be "unlikely to divert the flow of traffic." Although he believes that the government will eventually “suspend” the viaduct, Ron Lam warned that he could collect signatures with the citizens if the authorities insist on the current proposal.
In addition, the deputy urged the Executive to resort to the legislature to prohibit the repetition of road excavations for many years, except in cases where the works are really necessary.
 
Weighted re -candidacy
Ron Lam assured, on the other hand, that his team has not yet started arguing whether he will compete again for elections for the Legislative Assembly, so there is no final decision yet. Promising that it will "actively and thoroughly" the matter, the deputy added that his team will advance with a reconditeration "if he has been able to help society and promoted more integration policies and favorable to sustainable development of MSAR."
On the other hand, the deputy stressed that it will be important that the new executive of MSar efforts to “change the bad feeling caused by the previous government” in communication with the media, namely dialoguing directly with the population and promoting “more interactive bidirectional communication” .
In his opinion, the current government “gives importance to issuance of information”, which is something “unidirectional” but “reasonable in the current phase”. "But even this warming should be more active and open," he said.
 
Chan Iek Lap fulfills last term
Deputy Chan Iek Lap is fulfilling his last term as a deputy to the Legislative Assembly, said yesterday, saying that he will not be recalled to office in this year's elections. Deputy elected by the indirect road since 2013, Chan Iek Lap, who is also a doctor, is fulfilling the third term. In addition to being a deputy, he accumulates positions in various associations, namely president of the Chinese Association of Medicine Professionals and the General Association of Macao Medicine Sector.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Malparado retreats 9% on credit cards</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/malparado-recua-9-nos-cartoes-de-credito/</link><description>Last year, non-compliance with credit cards dropped in all quarters, setting at 72 million at the end of December, according to official data
 
The total amount of the debt for paying for more than three months in credit cards issued by Macau banks was 72.1 million patacas in late December, which represents an annual decrease of 9.2%, or 7 , 3 million, although it remains far above 48.1 million noted in late 2019. On the other hand, it reflects a decrease of 4.3% or 3.3 million in just three months, according to data from the Monetary Authority (AMCM) , which point to breaks in all quarters of last year, contrary to the sequential increase of 9.3% registered in the last three months of 2023.
Already the debt with delays between three and six months reached 13.3 million patacas, retreating 20.4% in a year, despite rising 7.3% in three months and 0.8% compared to the end of 2019.
Between October and December, the unpaid debt ratio, measured based on arrears for more than three months against debt balance, lowered 0.2 points to 2.6%, compared to the end of September.
The credit limit related to cards (49.9 billion patacas) grew 1.1% in annual terms and 0.3% in three months, with the balance of debts settling at 2.8 billion. The “Rollover” balance (786.9 million) was equivalent to 27.9% of debts receivable.
According to the same data, the amount of credit used in the fourth quarter totaled 6.2 billion, with an annual decrease of 0.6% and a quarterly rise of 0.4%. The advance of cash (157.5 million) corresponded to 2.5% of the credit used.
The number of credit card transactions (12.7 million) grew 8.1% in three months and 14.7% in one year. The amount of the refund (6.2 billion), including interest and expenses, dropped 2.3% and 3.2%, respectively.
In debit cards (excluding cash surveys), the number of transactions (1.2 million) increased by 61.4% and 4.5% in annual and quarterly terms, respectively. The value involved (552.5 million) grew 0.6% and 3.2% in the same time intervals.
 
Mobile payments grow 24%
Between October and December 2024, the number of transactions with mobile payments at MSAR rose 24.3% to 100 million in annual terms, also illustrating a quarterly increase of 13.5%. According to the monetary authority, the value of transactions reached 8.2 billion patacas, translating an annual increase of 15.7% and a quarterly climb of 8.4%. The average value per transaction was encrypted at 82.4 patacas in the quarter under analysis. At the end of December, 108,905 devices accepted mobile payments and “QR code” supports in Macao, representing an annual growth of 6.6%.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Request reinforcement of raising on road rules</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pedido-reforco-da-sensibilizacao-sobre-regras-da-estrada/</link><description>Deputy Ella Lei considers that it is necessary to review and optimize some traffic facilities with which there has been accidents, as well as the reinforcement of road awareness with the visitors
 
Ella Lei defended yesterday that it is necessary to reinforce the awareness of visitors to the road rules in Macao, and it would also be important to do an analysis to the traffic facilities involved in road accidents. The deputy, who spoke to journalists on the sidelines of the Spring Lunch offered by the Legislative Assembly (AL) to the media, recalled that the road traffic law is still being discussed within the 1st Permanent Commission, which presides over.
“Regarding some road accidents that have caught the eye, I think it takes the concrete causes to be analyzed and to assess whether these accidents are related to the design of traffic facilities, for example, the treadmills. There may be some dead angles and, if confirmed, you will need to change the design, ”he said.
In addition, for Ella Law it is also necessary to “continue to perform awareness raising for road safety”. "For example, in San Ma Lo there are situations where pedestrians do not respect the law in crossing the treadmills, this is also dangerous for drivers," he noted. Thus, while the design of traffic facilities has to be “revised and optimized”, it is also necessary to “reinforce the sensitization of the subject with visitors who know little about the conditions of the roads of Macao”.
According to the commission recently sent a list of questions to the government about the proposal of road traffic law. “We are still waiting for the discussion by the advisors of both parties. And at the next meeting we will invite again government representatives to answer the questions, ”he added.
In addition to the driving license scoring system, the law also involves other issues such as the use of the seat belt and the rules for pedestrians in crossing the treadmills. "These points will also have changes, but there are still no final decisions, for example, how to cross pawns can become safer," said Ella Lei, adding that there is also no decision on measures to make against pedestrians that use the mobile phone when crossing the treads.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PSG Academy joined young people from the great bay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/academia-psg-juntou-jovens-da-grande-baia/</link><description>Young footballers from 28 teams from the Great Bay cities faced a tournament in the field of workers. The competition was organized by the Paris Saint-Germain Academy, which has "schools" in Hong Kong and Macau
 
A tournament for the lower levels of football, concretely under-9, under-11, under-13 and under-15, took place in the field of workers during the weekend. The competition showed new talents of the sport, which have evolved at the PSG Academy, a prestigious club in France and at the international level, which a few years ago installed in Hong Kong and Macau branches of their “soccer schools”, putting them in competition with teams from neighboring regions.
The “GBA Tournament for Youth of Macau 2025” featured 28 teams from the Great Bay, at an event that was supported by the Sports Institute (ID) and tourism services, in partnership with “Benenden Bilingual School Guangzhou” and “CTF Education Group ”.
At the opening ceremony, Yannick Ngassa, executive director of the PSG Academy Hong Kong and Macau, ”said French club schools have been dedicated to“ developing young talents through professional soccer training ”, with their coaches, certified By academia and UEFA, "focused on developing teamwork, sports spirit and the technical skills of young players." Through this competition, “participating teams have the opportunity to learn from each other,” he added.
The inaugural ceremony was also attended by ID president Luís Gomes, who began the tournament, as well as the director general of the PSG academy of Hong Kong and Macau, Joseph Jessel, and representatives of the Macao Football Association ( AFM).
It should be noted that the ID has been carrying out training throughout the year for several local football levels, providing schools of the sport, from a talent selection. In addition, some players from Macao who have evolved in this tournament, especially ages up to 15 years, are part of teams that participate in the MSAR Championship, organized by AFM.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Craft Fair returns to April 24</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/feira-de-artesanato-regressa-24-de-abril/</link><description>More than two hundred stands will be installed in another edition of the TAP Seac Craft Fair, between the end of April and early May. The event will also return to integrate workshops
 
The Craft Fair returns in April to Tap Seac Square, in an initiative of the Cultural Institute (IC) that takes place in spring and fall, aiming to make available to professionals of cultural and creative industries a platform for exchange, display and marketing of products. The event will take place in two periods, from April 24 to 27 and from May 1st to 4th, and the registration was already opened.
This fair aims to “support and encourage creativity and innovation”, promote the entry of Macao's cultural and creative products in the market and “contribute to the creation of a cultural and creative exhibition of the large bay brands”, according to an IC note stresses .
The spring edition will integrate a total of 220 craft and gastronomy stands. The registration for exhibitors runs until February 26, and the interested parties of Macau, Malaysia and Singapore may apply online, through the electronic page of the “Stand Operator Database of the Craft Fair”.
The detailed information about the registration of stakeholders from the interior of China, Hong Kong and Taiwan is available on the event's exclusive electronic page.
All products presented for sale should be of original design, with a minimum of 10 models available for this purpose, and may simultaneously include services of cultural and artistic experience. If the number of eligible candidates exceeds the number of stands originally fixed, the CI will assign them by draw.
In turn, the deadline for registration for creative craft workshops takes place until February 19, being selected and evaluated based on their score, which will be attributed according to criteria such as improvement, viability, aesthetics and the attraction of the plan, as well as the budget and the trainer's experience.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Citigroup reduces annual forecast on game</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/citigroup-reduz-previsao-anual-sobre-jogo/</link><description>Citigroup reduced its forecast on the growth of macao casinos revenues by 2025, now pointing to an annual increase of 3%, compared to the previous projection of 7%. In the first half, revenues could fall even 1% in annual terms, the banking group indicated in a report cited by the Ggraia portal. According to analysts George Choi and Timothy Chau, the results were “lower than expected” in January and in the first five days of February, with averages of 589 million and about 900 million patacas, respectively. Citigroup has attributed the “disappointing” Chinese New Year's performance to “some late cancellations of Macau travel by players”, near the end of the Golden Week, which lasted until February 4 and coincided with the tariffs imposed by the US President to Chinese exports. "These two data make us more cautious about the trends of gross recipes in the short term," analysts points out. "We believe the implementation of US tariffs against China on February 1 has reduced the search for the game at the end of the Lunar New Year's Golden Week, and we hope this impact will continue for most of the first half of 2025," they add. Citigroup hopes that "the feeling of players will begin to recover in the second half of 2025 as the impact of [US] tariffs is digested." In addition, the search could “re -race as big events return to Macao,” he said, giving as an example a concert in June at the Hong Kong Jacky Cheung Hong Kong Singer and actor. In the second half, casinos will be able to register revenues of 119.5 billion (another 6% in annual terms), also benefiting from the impact of summer holidays and the golden week of national day.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2340/</link><description>Costa Nunes registered collective case of gastroenteritis
A collective case of gastroenteritis was on Friday at D. José da Costa Nunes Kindergarten. According to Health Services (SSM), the case involved four patients who are students (two boys and two girls) from the K2A class. Since the 4th, they began to have symptoms such as vomiting and belly pain, some of which were treated in medical institutions. According to SSM, none of the children had critical symptoms or serious complications. It has been preliminarily discarded that the case was caused by food, and it is more likely to be caused by viruses.
 
Subsidized day care centers open in March
Registration of subsidized day care centers will be open between March 1 and 26, with the admission list published on May 2. This year, in addition to the four subsidized day care centers that accept face -to -face registration, the remaining registration will have to be done online. For more information, interested parties will be able to consult the “Child Care Service Information Network at MSAR” page, or call the IAS Children and Youth Services Division.
 
Vandilion license fees published
The government published in official bulletin the table of fees of the vendinon license. The issuance and renewal for newsstands with structure provided by the Institute for Municipal Affairs will be cost ranging from 2,000 to 2,600 patacas depending on occupation areas, ranging from 2.5 to 10 square meters. Regarding the vendin zone of Hac Sá beach, the price is 3,000 patacas. The duplicate issuance of the license costs 100 patacas.
 
Traditional Chinese medicine motivated visit to wan fao
The development of traditional Chinese medicine was one of the central objectives of a visit that a Macao delegation recently made Wan Fao in Guangdong province. Composed by the Wan Fao countryman Association and Macao Chinese Medicines Association, led by its president, Jorge Kuan, the entourage visited a medicinal plant park and addressed issues such as the formation of Chinese doctors and medical technicians and the creation of one Platform for exporting drugs abroad. Wan Fao is also known for the production of marble stones, an area that is seen to generate collaboration opportunities between Portuguese and Chinese entrepreneurs.
 
OPEN NECURITIES FOR RPC Medical Examination
Registration for the National Medical Qualification Exam in the Interior of China 2025 is open until 24h00 of 21 February, through the website of the National Medical Examination Network, the health services announced. Under the Cepa Agreement, doctors, Traditional Chinese medical dentists and doctors who are allowed to practice medicine in Macau, may apply for the exam, if they meet the requirements, in terms of academic degrees and the period of activity in the territory, which should be higher than one year.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Expecting associations to keep in contact with Marcelo on the visit to</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacoes-expectantes-para-manter-contacto-marcelo-na-visita-a-raem/</link><description>The President of the Republic, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa (D) Conversation with local sellers during a walk from foot from Leal Senate to the ruins of the São Paulo Church, this morning in Macao, China 1 May 2019. The President. da República, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa is from April 26 to May 1 on a state visit to the Popular Republic of China. Miguel A. Lopes/Lusa



The trip to Macao of the President of the Portuguese Republic, at the time of the celebrations of Portugal Day, Camões and the Portuguese communities, was received with great satisfaction. Associations want to take advantage of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa's time to stay in the territory to maintain contacts and address the real situation of the community. The Portuguese head of state will not be present at the ceremonies to be held on June 10, and should be moved immediately before or after that date
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Six years after he was in Macao, a two-day stop towards Beijing, inserted on a state visit to the Popular Republic of China, at the invitation of Xi Jinping, Portuguese President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa again traveling again to the territory. The objective of this time is the participation in the celebrations of Portugal, Camões and the Portuguese communities, which takes place on 10 June.
According to news released by the Presidency's Office, the dates of the visit are still unknown, and may be immediately before or after June 10, since precisely on this day Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will be presiding over the official celebrations, which this year will be held this year in the Algarve city of Lagos.
The novelty of travel to the territory was well received by responsible from some Portuguese matrix associations or entities linked to the Lusa community.
The Portuguese Consul General in Macao and Hong Kong told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that it is “an honor that the president decided this year to associate the Portuguese community of Macao with the June 10th celebration program”. For Alexandre Leitão, the choice of territory "is a huge joy for a career diplomat and it is always a great honor to work on the visit of a head of state."
The maximum representative of Portugal at Mashes is sure that the move of Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa will be seen by the Portuguese community as “a moment of recognition of its dimension, its relevance”. "That's why I think it's a very positive moment," he added.
About the program, the ambassador did not want to advance details, "because this will have to be worked with the embassy in Beijing and the Civil House of the President of the Republic, in the composition of the visit." As the president will come before or after, from June 10, it is possible that the reception to the Portuguese community will take place “by the time Marcelo meets in Macao,” says Alexandre Leitão.
The expectation of direct contact with Portuguese matrix associations is mirrored by Amelia António, president of the House of Portugal in Macau. The leader told JTM that “June, Portugal's month” has been systematically celebrated in Macao “with great commitment from the associations and the consulate, among others”, and is therefore the opinion that the coming of the Portuguese president “is A reinforcement and a way of giving credibility, strength and stimulation to an effort that has been done to make the work developed to highlight the presence of culture in Macao more visible. ”
Amelia António considers that the Portuguese president's direct contact with the associations is very important. "This will be fundamental for him to realize the real situation, because in Portugal there is often little the notion of reality," he noted. "Perhaps because Macau is far away, we have had evidence of the lack of knowledge that reveals itself in many attitudes by the Portuguese government and the lack of support for many important things," he lamented.
On the other hand, it states that Sam Hou Fai's visit to Portugal would be “a very important step, because with some of the measures that were taken, in the previous two years, I think it was essential to replace and highlight the importance of the Portuguese in the area of Knowing, culture, teaching, a number of things that are missing Macao and that a trip to Portugal may help to replace a certain balance that is being missed. ”
In turn, Jorge Fão, president of the General Assembly of the Association of Retirees, Reformed and Pensioners of Macao (Apomac), says he is “very good for Macau” and expects the Portuguese president, “who will also reform”,, also Go this time to Apomac. “Never has it been there and I think our around 800 associates deserve it, since it is a community that is not small,” he says.
 
Expected “synergies”
Miguel de Senna Fernandes, president of the Macanese Instruction Promoter Association, speaks of “development of synergies”, relating the trip of the Portuguese head of state to a territory led by someone who speaks the language of Camões. “It may be symbolic, but the fact that there is a maximum leader, who appears at a fantastic time to Macao, after the complicated pandemic years, communicating in Portuguese, that is a very large breath,” he says. "From then on synergies develop and this is important."
António José de Freitas also told JTM that Marcelo's visit is “a very special meaning”, recalling the passage of the Portuguese President in Macau in 2019. “It was a visit from which I keep intense memories, having had the honor of The The Honor Receive as a provider at the Host Casa da Misericórdia building, ”he recalled. At that time, it goes on, "we have signed its presence on the time of the 450th anniversary of our institution, with the unveiling of a commemorative tombstone."
In this second visit, “we will have the immense honor of receiving President Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa, if he provided herself,” he continued, talking about an “old friend of Santa Casa and Macau, with a relationship with our city that dates from 1980s of the last century, when he taught law at the University of Macao (then designated University of East Asia) ”.
The provider considers that “we are facing winds so will be favorable to reinforce the deeply rooted relations between Macau and Portugal and, in general, for the ties between Portugal and the Popular Republic of China, which celebrate, for these days, the 46th anniversary of the establishment of diplomatic relations, ”he concludes.
 
Evident sign of the relationship between Portugal and China
Paulo Canelas Castro, president of the Macao European Studies Institute, says it is this visit by Marcelo “a very significant act and a sign of the recognition of the community's role in maintaining the multisecular relationship between Portugal and China, centered on Macau, with more 500 years old, and which continues to deserve the dedication of the Portuguese community through history, even after the creation of the MSAR, ”he said.
The official of the Institute recalls that when Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa moved to Macau in 2019, said that he was always well informed about what is happening here. “He said he would go back here, which is interesting, so I say it's a symbolically very loaded act,” acknowledges Paulo Canelas Castro.
José Luís Sales Marques, chairman of the Organizing Committee of the Meeting of Macanese Communities, considers the visit “important to reinforce relations between Macao and Portugal and also at this particular moment between Portugal and China in an international context of very fast change and many uncertainties” . The economist points out that "the multisecular connection between the two sides has always been permanent, strong and stable, hence it is important to reinforce these links."</description><pubDate>2025-02-10 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Kinda Pregnant’ is quite good</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/kinda-pregnant-e-bastante-bom-jake-coyle/</link><description>Jake Coyle*
We have already used how some movie characters are able to do to maintain a good comedy story. But it is still a special achievement when Amy Schumer, playing a single woman crazy about babies who fits a pregnant belly in "Kinda Pregnant", is so desperate for maintaining fiction that stuffs a roasted turkey in the dress.
It may be thinking: this is very ridiculous. The filling, alone. But if we appreciated the "Some Like It Hot" or "Mrs. Doubtfire ”, I see no reason to question the structure of“ Kinda Pregnant ”, a funny and often insightful satire about motherhood, both real and imaginary.
"Kinda Pregnant", which debuted last week on Netflix, is a kind of retro comedy. Like “40-Year-Old Virgin” and “Wedding Crashers”, one can basically understand the film only by the title.
But, like any good high concept comedy, "Kinda Pregnant" is predominantly a far-fetched form of its star and co-argumentist, Schumer, talk frankly about his theme of election. Here, this is the wide range of pregnancy experiences - body changes, sex revelation parties, personal jealousy - all mixed with a healthy amount of pseudo pregnancy falls.
It has been a decade since Schumer was essentially released as a 2015 film star in “Trainwreck” by Judd Apatow. But "Kinda Pregnant", which Schumer wrote with Julie Paiva, almost as skillfully channels Schumer's comic voice - the one that made Sketches series "Inside Amy Schumer" excellent.
The opening of the movie recalls Lainy (Schumer) in a child playing with dolls and imagining a future mother. As middle-aged, however, Lainy, a high school teacher in Brooklyn, is nowhere near to realize this dream. At dinner, where she suspects that her longtime boyfriend (Damon Wayans Jr.) will make the proposal, he invites her to a throes to Trois. Back at school, Lainy's class about “Romeo and Juliet” becomes darkly cynical.
Things get even worse when Lainy's best married friend (Jillian Bell) reveals that she is pregnant. "Get rid of him!" Lainy lets out before apologizing. Later, when the couple go shopping in clothes, Lainy tries a disorder in the belly. The saleswoman is immediately friendly to her, offering a burrito and a foot massage. "Who is the father?" she asks. "Doordesh," Lainy replies before adding, "driver."
Much of the fun in "Kinda Pregnant" is to see Lainy inventing increasingly ridiculous lies while trying to pretend to be pregnant. (After accidentally choosing thanksgiving as the moment of its conception, Lainy Cava has an even deeper hole in suggesting that it happened in a “selling Black Friday's eve”.)
But the stratagem becomes harder when she, during a pregnant gymnastics class, meets a woman (Brianne Howey) who really likes and wants to be a friend. Even more complicated: Lainy begins to fall in love with another boy she knows in a cafeteria (Forte Will).
In a movie full of funny people (others include Urzila Carlson as an educational advisor and Alex Moffat as future idiot father), strong is an especially good presence in "Kinda Pregnant". For an actor of such a crazy nonsense, strongly fits in a remarkably natural way in a more romantic comedy scenario. It also has a wonderfully ridiculous occupation, even to the standards of the romantic comedy, leading a Zamboni in the Central Park.
Probably from here, you can imagine what Kinda Pregnant ”will be like. The director Tyler Spindel, nephew of Adam Sandler (producer of the film), does nothing to promote film comedy, a proposal failed in recent years, except rare exceptions in the great screen. But he gives artists a lot of space to be themselves, and Lainy's desperate desire to have a family looks exaggerated and genuine. If "Knocked Up" captured the comedy of unexpectedly pregnant, "Kinda Pregnant" personifies the pain of wishing it.
 
*Coyle has been a film critic for the Associated Press since 2013. He has lived in New York City.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>