<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Low -cost accommodation market share is the fastest growing</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/quota-de-mercado-de-alojamentos-de-baixo-custo-e-mais-cresce/</link><description>Macao visitors have increasingly opted for affordable accommodation to the detriment of luxury hotels. In the last decade, this most economical category of accommodation has been the largest quota in the market. Still, five -star hotels continue to attract more than half of the mashed tourists
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The number of guests in more affordable hotel establishments has increased to more than double in a decade, indicate official data. In 2014, three -star hotels registered more than one million customers, and last year they received about 2.4 million, an increase of 115.46%. In fact, it was the category of establishment that the highest market share gained over these ten years: if in 2014 they received 10.26% of 10,712,999 customers hosted at the last year, three-star hotel guests represented 16.43% of a total of 14,422,351, translated a growth of 6.16 percentage points, the largest among all categories.
Conversely, five -star hotels were those who lost the highest quota as the total of customers, in the same period of time, although they continue to represent more than half of the market. In 2024, they received 51.17% of the total guests (7,380,456), and in 2014 they received 58.61% (6,278,390), corresponding to a loss of 7.43 percentage points.
In terms of activity hotel units, more three -star hotels were also established compared to the other categories, according to data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC). In ten years, they went from 13 to 20 (+53.85%). Last year, there were 38 five-star hotels, 11 more than in 2014 (+40.74%). Four -star hotels, in turn, increased from 14 to 19 (+35.71%).
It should be clarified that the Law of Activity of Hotel Industry Establishments, in force since 2022, has reclassified pensions such as low -cost accommodation or two -star hotels, the latter increased 108.33%over the same time. By 2024, Macao already had more than double the two -star hotels in activity (25) than it was a decade before (12). Pensions, which were no longer recognized with the new legislation, were 32 in 2014. Low-cost lodges, approved from 2022, were 44 last year.
Despite a higher offer, the average three -star hotel occupancy rate fell 1.8 percentage points from 85.6% in 2014 to 83.8% last year. Five star hotels, in turn, were able to improve their occupancy rate from 87.5% to 88.5% within the same time. As for four -star hotel units, they were those whose occupancy rate was more decayed from 87.8% to 82%. In turn, two -star hotels had the highest occupancy rate by 2024 (89.6%), a 14.2 points from 2014 (75.4%).
The guest rooms of two and three -star hotels more than doubled in a decade. In the first, the number of rooms went from 815 to 1,984 and the three-star units had 6,528 in 2024, 4,002 more than the 2,526 in 2014. In addition, the latter places in three-star establishments more than tripled from 5,331 to 16,136, while in two-star hotels increased to more than twice, from 1,696 to 4,271 in the same period.
The number of bedrooms and beds in five-star hotels increased 31.64% and 30.70%, respectively. At the end of 2024, 24,194 rooms were available, 5,815 more than 18,379 in 2014. Last year there were 66,194 out of a total of 113,612 ladies (58.26%), and in 2014 there were 50,646 out of all 72,492 seats (69.86%).
However, considering that last year, for each place, the five-star hotels had approximately 112 guests, those of the four stars recorded 137, those of three stars 147 and the two star had 211, and considering the occupancy rates, the guests of luxury hotel units tend to stay longer, compared to the most economical establishments. In turn, more affordable hotel customers tend to stay less time.
According to DSEC, the accommodation rate rate related to accommodation was 148.61 points in 2024, and in 2014, the score was 169.52, indicating that the average price fell 12.34%, possibly driven by the significant growth of the amount of more economical offers.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inquiry reveals that 52% never used elderly support services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/inquerito-revela-52-nunca-usaram-servicos-de-apoio-idosos/</link><description>An inquiry developed by Macau's Economics Sustadement Alliance reveals that more than 52% of a total of 1,023 Macao elderly had never resorted to elderly support services. On the other hand, more than 50% of respondents live in non -modified fractions to adapt to the physical conditions of the inhabitants of the elderly
 
With the aim of studying policies and measures related to elderly services and housing, as part of the action for the development of the elderly support services, Macau's Sustadement Alliance developed an inquiry, with the responses of a total of 1,023 elderly from Macao.
The study points out that respondents, mostly with secondary education, live mainly depending on the salary or pension for the elderly. In addition, more than 52% of the elderly interviewed have never used any elderly support services, for example community centers and daytime care. The association found that, although there is a potential demand for community services and intelligent elderly support services, only a low percentage of the elderly ends up effectively resorting to this type of support.
Remember that in 2023, the society of Macao became an aged society, and from now on “the rhythm of population aging will accelerate”, according to the projections of statistical and census services. For the next twenty years, it is expected that the proportion of elderly (65 years or older) over the total population continues to rise, reaching 20.9% by 2041.
Community services have been one of the government's bets, and the president of the Institute of Social Action, Hon Wai, said in an interview with the newspaper Tribuna de Macao that in the elaboration of the new DECENAL plan, the use of technology would be one of the focuses.
On the other hand, the investigation points out that only 15% of respondents expressed a clear will to live in the residence for the elderly, which, for the association reflects that the public still prefers to observe the implementation of the respective policy.
Another conclusion is that more than 50% of elderly ears live in fractions that have not yet been modified to adapt to the physical conditions of the inhabitants of the elderly. For the support and economy alliance, security and housing convenience deserve to be one of the focus of future service policies for the elderly.
The inquiry also reveals that only 16% of respondents showed a clear intention to live the elderly within China. According to the interviewees, financial charges, inconvenient transport and the lack of connection between medical insurance systems on both sides of the border constitute the main obstacles.
In view of the results of the inquiry, the Association proposed the widening of the elderly access to the services directed to them, especially through the integration of intelligent elderly support services, which cover data tracking, distance medical services and community support.
In addition, the study researchers appealed to the optimization of housing policies and the improvement of the interconnection of resources for the elderly in the great bay, to increase the attractiveness and practicality of transfronting care policies to the elderly.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment is for Coutinho the great gap of today</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desemprego-e-para-coutinho-grande-lacuna-da-actualidade/</link><description>José Pereira Coutinho considers that “the priority of priorities” for the citizens of Macao, in times that run, is no longer housing and became the job. “We will have to face this big problem,” he says. In the balance of another four years of office in AL, the parliamentarian is also apprehensive about the workers of the satellite casinos. "In the medium or long term this will bring a new wave of unemployment," he said. Despite everything, Pereira Coutinho notes that, with this new government, "there has been any advance in resolving some concrete cases"
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The difficulty that young people finished licensing have to get their first job was one of the main topics addressed by José Pereira Coutinho, in the balance of the work of the last four years of his term in the Legislative Assembly (AL), along with the Chess WEng Benchmart. For the deputy, in the days they run, "the priority of priorities," regarding the needs of the citizens of Macao, "it is no longer housing and became the job, so we will have to face this big problem."
According to their accounts, there are about 4,000 young people to graduate per year, "many of whom continue to be unemployed for years and licenses at foreign universities give up their territory due to lack of job opportunities," he says, adding that "the courses they take, for example in public administration, or even in tourism, do not allow them to get jobs, because concessionaires are reducing."
Among other reasons that lead to the difficulty of young people to realize their first job, the deputy justifies with the “increasing number of positions held by non-resident workers”. He adds that the duo of deputies, both leaders of the Macao Public Function Association, asked the government "several times, to implement effective measures to reduce the number of TNR of large companies, facilitating the employability of young people and those of the Middle Ages."
Despite this problem, which he considers seriously, Pereira Coutinho says authorizations for non-permanent residents have dramatically reduced, "which means the government is paying attention."
Still in the theme of employment (or unemployment), Pereira Coutinho is concerned about a possible new wave of unemployed, resulting from the closing of the satellite casinos at the end of the year. “In the medium or long term, this will bring a new wave of unemployment in Macao,” he admits, stating that he and Che Sai Wang are one of the deputies who had the most of the casinos-satellite workers. "We found that many of them do not know where they will be allocated to the new dealership."
Even in the face of this possibility of being allocated, "workers will probably come across the situation of not being able to perform the same functions in which they have been working over the years, but in other positions, which will mean that in the medium or long term this will bring a new wave of unemployment."
About this, the parliamentarian adds that "the brief section may not happen". However, "the government will be eyeing the dealers, but in the medium and long term things are fading and then there may be more consequences."
Even so, it asserts, with the new government, "there has been any advance in resolving some concrete cases."
In other issues of balance, it stated that throughout the last legislature there were interventions in “matters of extreme relevance”, such as public health. In the context of the use of artificial intelligence, Pereira Coutinho points out that “nowadays, in this area, especially the serious diseases, such as breast cancer and others, early diagnosis is extremely useful for patients to be healed”. In this field, it mentions that robotic operations are increasingly common in adjacent regions, hoping that Macau can follow, by hiring specialized doctors.
Transport, road traffic, bullying, suicides, high bank interest, the need for electronic pages to be more “Friendly User”, the new regime for the acquisition of goods and services, support for the elderly, consumer subsidies, were integrated with a total of 401 interpeairs (371 writings and 30 oral).
In addition, there were 107 interventions “before the agenda” in the SA sessions and two proposals for debate, which join 90 missives regarding social affairs to the Chief Executive and the secretaries. These numbers marked the work of Pereira Coutinho and Che Sa Wang in the last four years of office.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dezanove candidates for “safeguard entities”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dezanove-candidatos-entidades-de-salvaguarda/</link><description>In the context of intangible cultural heritage inventory, 19 candidates submitted proposals to the Cultural Institute to become “safeguard entities”. The body's president, Leong Wai Man, expects more interested parties to present applications
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
A total of 19 candidates submitted requests to the Cultural Institute (IC) to become “safeguard entities” of the 70 demonstrations that make up the intangible cultural heritage inventory, Leong Wai Man said during a press conference. The president of the IC also assured that the government intends to support the entities, so that they can perform activities such as studies, promotion work or workshops related to their intangible cultural heritage, in a “joint work with the community”.
Applications concern demonstrations such as “beliefs and customs, macanese gastronomy, clothing and handicrafts”, having been submitted by religious associations, handicraft companies and some stores, among others, according to Leong Wai Man. The person also said to expect more submissions, emphasizing that each candidate can present more than one project, as long as it meets the conditions.
The body “has encouraged the entities, communities and groups involved in the transmission and safeguarding of the manifestations contained in the inventory of intangible cultural heritage,” said Leong.
The Cultural Heritage Council held a ordinary plenary meeting yesterday, which was chaired by Leong Wai Man. According to the IC leader, the situation of application and final reports of public consultations on the demonstrations to be registered in the list of cultural and intangible heritage and the 1st group proposed for the classification of movable property of Macau was presented. According to Wu Chou Kit, all board members approved the reports.
Asked if there have been candidates for the Fund for intangible cultural heritage, Leong Wai Man replied that the numbers will be released later.
Regarding the 12 demonstrations proposed by the IC, to integrate the list of intangible cultural heritage, the official said that a “final analysis” will still be made, and the final decision will be disclosed by order. It is recalled that the IC proposals collected about 70% of positive opinions, according to the final report.
Visual impact of lightning rays in the ruins of São Paulo
Regarding the visual impact of the rains of the ruins of São Paulo, Leong Wai Man clarified that several proposals were requested to the responsible concession entity and an opinion to the National Study Academy. "In addition to considering the visual factor, we also take into account the form of installation of the lightning rays," said the president of the IC. Not installing lightnings would be the “ideal”, to “reveal the beauty of the ruins of São Paulo”, but it is necessary “to take into account the safety of this cultural heritage”, he stressed.
"In the future, with technological advancement, if there is a better plan than current lightning installation, we can always change or update," he explained. Since it is a “non-invasive” solution, it will not create “any material impact on the ruins”, reiterated Leong, stressing that “it is necessary to protect the cultural heritage from the ruins of São Paulo during the storms”.
Regarding the study requested by UNESCO, about the viaduct project that will connect Zone A and B of new landfills, Leong Wai Man said that the IC will also deliver its "analysis report."</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Goa delicacies to enjoy at the Macanese Association</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iguarias-de-goa-para-apreciar-na-associacao-dos-macaenses/</link><description>The Macanese Association will receive the “Night of Goa” again, in a initiative in conjunction with the Goa, Damão and Diu Cultural Animation Center. The food will be made by cooks Maria Dias and Maria Antonieta, born in Goa. At the same time, guests can listen to traditional music and appreciate images of the gouge beaches. "Hopefully it has the same success of last year," he told the Tribuna de Macau Vicente Coutinho newspaper, president of the core
 
Goa, Damão and Diu's Cultural Animation Center again organize a “Goa night”, providing lovers of the gastronomy of that Asian region to appreciate some of their typical dishes. Dinner takes place tomorrow, Saturday, between 18:30 and 22h00, at the headquarters of the Macanese Association (ADM), which for the second time collaborates in the initiative.
During the transfer, participants can listen to traditional music by Goa Damão and IUD and enjoy videos and photographs of the beaches of those Indian cities. “Wonderful food and beaches,” emphasizes the core president.
Vicente Coutinho told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that he expects dinner to be "the same success as last year, held at the same place, at this point."
The leader revealed that Maria Dias and Maria Antonieta, born in Goa, will be responsible for making the dishes, whose menu integrates delicacies such as Sorportel (pig), Cofreal chicken, feijoada, baked steak in the oven, lung, light and fradinho beans.
As a starter, there will be no shortage of traditional Chamças, Vegetarians and Pork, as well as meat croquettes.
In desserts, Bebinca occupies a special place, but there is also coconut souffle, gosche (rice sweet goes) and the “Fruits Costard” cream, made of milk, cornstarch and fruits.
“The dishes are essentially goals, since this time we cannot count on Elias Colaço, which usually makes gastronomy of its land, daão, but also from Diu,” says Vicente Coutinho.
The absence of an association's headquarters leads this genre of events to be held at the ADM facilities, Vicente Coutinho notes, adding: "What we thank."
People interested in participating in dinner-converting will have to pay a 200-headed admission to ADM members, 250 for non-fields and 120 for children between three and 11 years old.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mande sees award -winning four tourism campaigns</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-ve-premiadas-quatro-campanhas-de-turismo/</link><description>Four tourism campaigns created at the MSAR were awarded under the Gold Awards in Thailand, where STD and tour operators took the opportunity to promote Macau Tourism
 
The Directorate of Tourism Services (STD) was, together with tourist operators, to promote Macau at the Pacific Asia Tourism Association Fair (Pacific Asia Travel Association - Pata Travel Mart 2025), which took place until yesterday, in Bangcoque, Thailand, “as part of the work to increase markets of international visitors”. From there, the MSAR brought four awards, from the main marketing award for the Gold Awards.
In concrete, the “Feeling Macau Edition” campaign launched by STD in collaboration with the six game companies received this award. The campaign has involved a series of promotional initiatives and prizes through an online interaction game.
In addition, other Campaigns conducted by STD and two tour operators to promote Macao through Hospitality Sustainability, Community Tourism and Intellectual Property Character Economics (PI) were also awarded.
Another campaign conducted by STD, “The New Standard of Excellence,” this time in collaboration with Fortune, received a Gold Award in the best marketing campaign in sustainability and inclusiveness. Through a series of documentary-format videos, interviews and editorial content for a target audience, the media campaign explored how Macau's integrated resorts sail the interception between luxury, environmental responsibility, and social inclusiveness.
On the other hand, Melco Resorts and Entertainment received a Gold Award paw in the best marketing campaign category - hospitality from “Sanrio Characters Studio City Carnival” to attract visitors through activities around Sanrio's popular characters. Sands China was awarded the best printed campaign in Marketing (industry) by publication of “In Search of ITS Roots: An Illustrated History of Rua das Estalagens,” as part of this zone's community revitalization program, STD statement says.
In this 48th edition of Pata Travel Mart, more than 1,000 delegates from over 50 countries and regions were gathered. STD director Helena de Senna Fernandes, in conjunction with representatives of 12 integrated resorts, travel agencies and Air Macau, went to Bangkok to attend the event.
Macau's promotion stand has released the diversity of “Tourism +” offers, from hotel to gastronomy, culture, among others, including a point for taking photographs with artificial intelligence technology with iconic attractions as a backdrop and a coffee with delicacies in the city. The exhibitor also served as a platform for STD and operators make contacts with partners from other parts of the world.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“New Stage” in the fuel deposit</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/nova-etapa-deposito-de-combustiveis/</link><description>A “new stage” began in the Macao fuel distribution deposit, with the parking lot of the Nam Kwong chemicals and oil company, the government stressed. The authorities guarantee that they will continue to oversee the compliance with the concession contract
 
The Nam Kwong Chemicals and Petroliferous Company has already officially parked in the Macao fuel distribution deposit, “marking a new stage in the standardization and safety of the Fuel Storage and Management System,” the Fire Department (CB), the Security Forces and the Public Security Police (CPSP) services in a joint statement.
Currently, the company “is actively coordinating with sub -rear reactions regarding change and subsequent management”, and public services will then “general change, in accordance with the attributions”.
According to organisms, “Nam Kwong oil” has already developed professional staff training and internal incident simulacrum, and CB and CPSP will perform fires in conjunction with it, simulating the process of response to sudden incidents and raising joint response capacity.
Currently the “Nam Kwong oil” is following the change of other commercial gas establishments and the use of fuel distribution deposit. In addition, their public services are also promoting “actively” the relevant work.
In a statement, government bodies ensure that they will continue to monitor “Nam Kwong oil” to comply with the concession contract, to ensure that its operation corresponds to safety standards, including the execution of irregular inspections and fires combat exercises.
According to the legal regime for controlling dangerous substances, which entered into force in 2023, the Chief Executive granted, in July this year, to the Company of Chemicals and Petrolers NAM Kwong the management and exploitation of the new fuel distribution deposit. "This important work related to the life of the population was driven through the model of 'government supervision, professional operation'," says the authorities.
The organisms further emphasize that "the government of MSAR persists in" security first and based on the welfare of the population ", building a safer and more standardized fuel supply safety system and creating a safe and habitable environment for residents by improving the installation of hardware, innovation management model and control of the control system."</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Government intends to invest in the arts and elite athletes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/governo-pretende-investir-nas-artes-em-atletas-de-elite/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai, gathers with representatives of the associations of work sectors, countrymen and social services



Several associations linked to sectors such as education, culture and work presented suggestions to the Chief Executive, in another round of meetings in the context of the preparation of the Government Action Report for 2026. The optimization of policies directed to young people and entrepreneurship, as well as greater support for the development of qualified staff in the scope of the arts and elite athletes were some of the topics approached. Sam Hou Fai emphasizes the executive's willingness to help “the young generation make their aspirations and demonstrate their talents”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Sam Hou Fai continues to arise opinions of associations and entities linked to various sectors of society, and yesterday received at the headquarters of the Government representatives of the educational, youth, culture, work, work and social services, as part of the preparation of the Governing Action Report (LAG) for the Financial Year of 2026.
Twelve associations presented suggestions to the Chief Executive on topics such as optimization of youth policies, support for entrepreneurship and the use of youth, continuous construction of the industry and education integration system and the response to low birth.
On the other hand, they disclosed proposals directed to the reinforcement of the mechanism of support for students, the promotion of scientific and technological education and the formation of qualified staff of scientific innovation.
Some of the associative leaders of the educational, youth, cultural and sports sectors also expressed the hope of seeing the government continues to “promote Macao's prosperity through education” and “build macao through talent formation”, in a continuous bet of developing an educational industry, and placing young people as a priority.
According to Sam Hou Fai, the suggestions presented will help your team and will continue to collect the opinions “broadly”, taking into account the general conjuncture, to “formulate the lag and plan the respective policies and measures”.
In addition to stressing that the Government attributes “great importance to the work of Macao youth”, striving to create better conditions for their growth, ensures that it will continue to “fortify” the power of the city in the field of culture and sport, “promoting the development of all physical facilities”. During this process, he points out, there will be a “strong support for the development of qualified staff in the scope of elite arts and athletes, in order to“ inject uninterrupted dynamics in the construction of the 'City of the Show' and 'City of Sport' ”.
The chief executive also listened to opinions and suggestions of representatives of the associations of labor, countrymen and social services, which addressed a variety of topics, namely support for the elderly and children, development of the economy, improvement of employment services and the protection of work rights, support for youth employment, among others.
On the table of concerns there is also the increase in administrative efficiency, the enrichment of the content of the “major consumption award in community zones”, the monitoring of consumer price index.
They want to further deepen the education of love for the homeland and Macau, a reinforcement of the training of health professionals and the promotion of traditional Chinese medicine.
The challenges of the low birth rate and demographic aging were other topics under analysis, and the associations suggested to the government to launch long -term measures and policies to raise the quality of life of residents, namely in relation to the aspects of social security subsidies, day care services, care for people with dementia and legislative work on barriers without barriers.
In the response, the chief executive indicated that these sectors encompass “aspects of comprehensive society and different social strata”, and the opinions presented “are covered by a wide and profound base of public opinion”. It is said that the government will continue to follow the philosophy of moving forward with "the notion of responsibility," and ensures that "all stakeholders fulfill their duties and responsibilities."</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DSEDJ wants active participation in the activities of victory in the war</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsedj-quer-participacao-activa-nas-actividades-da-vitoria-na-guerra/</link><description>At the working meeting on the new school year, DSEDJ suggested to schools to organize groups of students to actively participate in the activities of victory in the war against Japanese aggression, as well as to experience the replicas of the voting Assembly and to attend the competitions of national games. On the other hand, he asked that they pay more attention to the physical and mental health of the students, especially in the initial period of the new school year
 
In recent days, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) has held the working meeting on the new school year of non -higher education, to explain to the directors and representatives of educational establishments the subjects to which they must pay attention.
At the meeting, Kong Chi Meng, director of DSEDJ, suggested to schools to organize groups of students to actively participate in the various commemorative activities on the 80th anniversary of China's victory in the War of Resistance against Japanese aggression and anti -fascist World War, for example, the photographic exhibition about the Patent Eparis in the Forum Complex.
At the same time, it encourages schools to boost students to participate in voting assembly simulators for legislative elections, in order to increase the civic awareness of teachers and students.
In addition, the body expects educational establishments to organize students to attend in person to the competitions of the 15th edition of the National Games, which will take place in the territory.
Finally, schools were warned to pay more attention to students' physical and mental health, especially in the initial period of the new school year.
At the meeting, the body also presented the plans for the day of the academic year, works to support the physical and mental health of the students, reinforce the training of teachers and in charge of education, in the context of cooperation between parents and schools, elaboration of pedagogical resources on the “War of Resistance and Macao” together with local historians and professional institutions, as well as teacher education in artificial intelligence.
On the other hand, he indicated that he had invited health services to sensitize schools to dengue fever prevention measures and chikungunya fever, hoping to help establishments do preventive work.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM damage rose 12% in the first half</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prejuizo-da-sjm-subiu-12-primeiro-semestre/</link><description>SJM Holdings suffered net losses of 182 million dollars of Hong Kong (HKD) in the first half of this year, translating a 12% rise in the same period of 2024 (162.4 million), the company announced yesterday. Ebitda gains (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) fell 5.1% to just under 1.65 billion between January and June, in annual terms. According to data, total net revenues grew 6.1% to 14.64 billion HKD, with the operations of the game to contribute to 13.63 billion (plus 5.7%). SJM Holdings also reported that SJM Resorts has signed an agreement with STDM to purchase a part of the Lisbon Hotel for a total of 529 million HKD. The idea is to expand the operations of Casino Lisboa, which will host tables-satellite tables and game machines that will end by the end of the year.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2464/</link><description>Air Macau will launch flights to Harbin
Air Macao will inaugurate a new direct air connection between MSAR and Harbin city in Heilongjiang province, from December 18, according to a public travel agency advertising. According to information released, the route will have a trip and one return a day. This connection will be the longest flight to the interior of China operated by the Flag Company.
 
Burlons steal more than 7.7 million to 86 victims
Since the 11th of this month, 86 victims of a burlage scheme have been registered, in which criminals are passing by customer support employees of the Taobao and Alipay platforms, the Judicial Police (PJ) said. The total amount of the impaired losses of the burlads has already overcome the 7.7 million patacas, and the authorities renewed the appeals to citizens to remain attentive to potential fraud. The PJ indicated that, in the last two days, 13 residents warned the police, and in one case, a resident claimed to have suffered a loss of 184,000 patacas.
 
Tickets for Games at MSAR FOR SALE IN SEPTEMBER
Part of the National Games tickets are already on sale on the uniform platform created for this purpose. According to Pun Weng Kun, president of the preparatory cabinet for the organization of the Macao Competition Zone of the National Games, the competition tickets, of the seven modalities that will take place in Macau, will be sold in groups from mid -September, including tickets for table tennis competitions. The official's statements were made on the sidelines of the inauguration of the second official store of the Macao National Games.
 
1st interior boat arrived with sand to the airport
Recently, the first boat from the interior of China with construction materials for landfill came into Macao, as part of the expansion of Macau Airport. According to the gongbei customs, this vessel carried 4,400 tons of sand, having passed the Wanzai post and entered Macao through a fast inspection “green path”.
 
A case of “MPOX” and the 9th of Chikungunya fever
The Conde de São Januário Hospital Center diagnosed an imported case of “MPOX”, the third since 2023, the year the first two patients were recorded in the MSAR. According to a health services statement (SSM), it is a 29-year-old resident who had “high-risk sex during a trip abroad”. They said, the patient's clinical condition was "stable." The 9th imported case of chikungunya fever was also recorded, which involved a resident of Zhuhai, who works in Macao.</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested “special support” of the government for Macau-Portugal flights</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerido-apoio-especial-governo-em-prol-de-voos-macau-portugal/</link><description>CAM's marketing department director said there are some “difficulties” with regard to the creation of a direct flight between Macau and Portugal, but the company continues to try to encourage airlines to develop these routes. Eric Fong defended, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, that the Government of MSAR should create a "special support." In addition, he said, he should try to negotiate the assignment of subsidies, together with the Portugal Civil Aviation Authority, to the company so that costs can be reduced
 
Macau Airport Society (CAM) “has driven airlines to develop direct or transferred routes to Portugal,” said Eric Fong, director of the company's marketing department, but is not an easy task. "We still strive to work on the aspect of direct flights," he continued in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
However, about this ambition, Eric Fong pointed out that “currently there is still a certain degree of difficulties” and a “very long incubation period”, given the “very high costs”, the market and other commercial considerations. According to noted, there are no carriers interested in launching this long distance connection.
"Therefore, we suggest to the Government of Misremine to create special support. And we also propose that [the government] and the Portuguese Civil Aviation Authority negotiate to provide subsidies to the airline [operator] and passengers, to ensure that the company reduces costs as possible before the launch of flights.
According to the official, some passengers from Macao resort to the Inheon Route (South Korea) - Lisbon, operated by Korean Air. In addition, he said that Cam has kept contact with Air Macao, hoping the Flag Company of the Mother China Air China, to make a connection between Macau and Beijing and the transfer of daxing to Europe.
On the other hand, Eric Fong said that Cam also bets on the “unique ticket with luggage transfer to the final destination”, mainly through several large carriers, such as China Eastern Airlines, China Southern Airlines, Korean Air, among others. Under this model, the flights depart from Macau to Beijing, Seoul, Taiwan, Kuala Lumpur, Singapore, or Bangkok, and then take passengers to Canada, USA, Europe, Australia, Egypt and India, he explained.
"There are many passengers from Macao to go to Canada, with the volume of passengers recorded a certain increase… In addition, we have constantly promoted this service [bay flights] in the Great Bay, so that tourists from the great bay or European or American countries can travel to Macau this way," he said.
This year, Cam also has made several negotiations with Australian and European airlines, "especially with Turkish Airlines", to promote medium and long distance charter routes in Macao, through cooperation with carriers and travel agencies, pointed out Eric Fong.
“Regarding charter routes, it will be a little difficult to promote this area to depend only on the population of Macau. So we have negotiated with some travel agencies and large charter companies in the interior of China, to realize if they are interested in promoting, along with Turkish Airlines and Australian airlines. Macau Airport can attract people in this part of the Great Bay -such as Jiangmen and Zhongshan -from Macau to move to the Middle East. Airlines have already expressed this desire if we can connect all the supply chains involved, ”said the official.
According to exemplified, Cam is “quite interested” on Turkish Airlines, wishing to promote connecting flights from Turkey and, using codes, then transport passengers to the interior of China, Southeast Asia and Northeast Asia with Air Macau planes. In this aspect, Eric Fong stressed that Cam "has been hardworking" and that negotiations "never stopped".
On the other hand, the Civil Aviation Activity Law will come into force on February 1 of next year. According to Eric Fong, so far, no airline has expressed a clear interest in providing passenger air transport services in Macao, but some carriers have asked CAM information on operational issues and requirements. Among the companies that contacted Cam, "there are some traditional and some foreigners," he said.
 
Service Centers in Shenzhen and Zhongshan
In addition, the official noted that the Macao Airport Service Center in Zhuhai went into operation on July 2 in Gongbei, having mainly served passengers from neighboring regions and providing airplane ticket and flying information consultation services and border ticket.
Eric Fong said that two more service centers of his gender should go into operation in the 4th quarter of this year in Shekou, Shenzhen, and in the port of Zhongshan, being "negotiating some details" and "proceeding to the decoration". According to it, these centers will provide information about flights, but also provide the maritime and air transport transfer service between these maritime terminals and Macao airport.
“We will promote a service that will allow passengers to leave the Shekou terminals and the Zhongshan Port, after arriving at the mud terminal, catching fast buses linked to Macau airport and using the" one inspection "service to go directly to Japan or South Korea, for example. reembolso de imposto de 110 patacas e ver as bagagens directamente transferidas para o destino”.
The Campo and Air Transport Transfer Services Network will also include Wanzai Port, Zhuhai, and the Interior Porto Maritime Terminal, whose facilities and services were already ready in the first half of this year. ” However, the company currently continues to negotiate with China's interior authorities on “some details”, not providing a calendar for the launch of the service, in which the paid bus service of Macau airport will also be made available to passengers who reach the interior port terminal from the port of Wanzai. As this type of passengers enjoys tax refund, the service is “basically free,” notic Fong noted.
 
“Low-Cost” absorb 26% of passengers
Eric Fong also revealed that between January and July this year, 74% of Macau airport passengers caught flights from traditional airlines while 26% chose low-cost carriers. According to the same temporal interval, the “Low-Cost” flight occupancy rate exceeded 80%, while traditional airlines found an occupancy rate of about 75%. "Normally, low-cost airlines register a flight occupation rate between 80% and 85%," he added.
In addition, it also said that in the first seven months of the year, the total number of passengers at the airport registered an annual break of 4%, while the volume of flights was also below that verified in the same period of 2024. Regarding the origin of passengers, residents accounted for 11%, followed by those from the interior of China (57%), foreigners (17%), those of Hong Kong (1%) and those of Taiwan and those of Taiwan (14%). In this respect, he noted that the percentage of passengers on the Chinese continent fell two to three percentage points in annual terms. Still, he noted that the situation remained similar to the usual.
Eric Fong also said that in late September a route will be launched between Macao and the island of Phu Quoc, Vietnam, with two flights a week. And almost at the same time or early October, Macau will have a new connection to Sihanoukville, Cambodia, also with two flights weekly. Already in early November the Macau-Cheongju Route, South Korea, with four flights per week will be inaugurated.
In the interior of China, the official mentioned that, on September 10, flights will be started between Macau and Nanchang, capital of Jiangxi province, served by Comac C909 aircraft, with three flights a week.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched contest for superstructure work of the Central Library</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancado-concurso-para-obra-de-superestrutura-da-biblioteca-central/</link><description>The contest was launched yesterday for the construction work of the Central Library superstructure at the site of the former Hotel Estoril. The Directorate of Public Works Services states that this endeavor will have “immediate start” after the completion of the foundations and cellars. A base price was not defined, but as for the execution period is 620 days of work. The definitive security, in turn, is 5% of the total price of award. Proposals can be delivered until October 8
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The new Central Library, at the former Hotel Estoril, next to Tap Seac Square, will soon enter a new phase of construction. Yesterday, the Directorate of Public Works (DSOP) services launched the public competition of the construction work of the building's superstructure, whose project was the “Mecanoo” Dutch architecture office. Proposals can be delivered until 5 pm on October 8, and a base price is not defined.
In the announcement, published yesterday in an official bulletin, it is said that the maximum global execution period is 620 days of work, counted from the consignment of the work, with a mandatory goal: the completion of the coverage structure with a maximum period of 300 working days. DSOP states that "the work of superstructure will immediately begin, after the conclusion of the works of foundations and cellars."
For the assessment of proposals, DSOP will take into account several criteria, with the price of the endeavor to be the most weight (50%), followed by experience and quality in works (20%), execution time (15%), the execution program (10%) and the plan of the human resources program and the proportion of workers residing in management positions (5%).
According to the director of DSOP, Lam Wai Hou, “the award is made to the competitor with the highest total score and, if there is a tie in the higher total score, the award is made to the competitor with the lower price proposal”.
The announcement also informs that the provisional security is 7.8 million patacas, to be provided by cash deposit, bank warranty or insurance approved in the legal terms. The definitive security is 5% of the total price of adjudication, specifically, of the amounts that the contractor has to receive, in each of the partial payments, 5% are deducted to guarantee the contract, in reinforcement of the definitive security provided.
The new central library occupies an area of ​​land of about 2,960 square meters. According to the project, the library will have four floors in height, with a basement for storage purposes. The ground floor and top floors have an auditorium room, newspaper and magazine reading zones, adult libraries, children's library, youth library, meeting rooms, among other spaces.
Regarding the contest, there will be a visit to the place on September 3, at 10h00, being the meeting point the former Hotel Estoril.
It was three years ago, in March 2021, that it was known that the proposal of the office "Mecanoo" had been chosen for the conceptual project of the new central library, as it was "simple, rigorous, inspiring and multifunctional." It was the only one to support the change of symbolic mosaic to the interior of the library. The initial budget surrounded the 500 million patacas and at the time, it was expected that the space could open by the end of 2024, a goal that was already widely exceeded.</description><pubDate>2025-08-28 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>The love story between Taylor and Travis in five points</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/historia-de-amor-entre-taylor-travis-em-cinco-pontos/</link><description>It's official: the most famous couple in the United States will marry. Pop Taylor Swift superstar and the three -time NFL Travis Kelce Super Bowl winner announced the engagement on Instagram. Here are five facts about your love story:
 
- Taylor's version
Swift's way to become the world's largest pop star was full of adversity, not just for the mishaps in love that fed the successful songs until he met Kelce.
The music prodigy won the first Grammy at the age of 20, when he was dedicated to the country before making the jump to the pop.
With this, he had an overwhelming success, as well as needed to learn to live under the spotlight. Swift dealt with a very commented dispute with Kanye West and rewrite the initial catalog of songs to recover the property of a private capital company.
It had very commented novels with Hollywood actors and pop stars. In addition, it is rumored that Jake Gyllenhaal, Tom Hiddleston, Joe Jonas, Calvin Harris and Harry Styles are among the references in the lyrics of their songs.
Last year, he won the fourth Grammy album of the year, the largest number won by any artist, and completed the most lucrative shows of all time.
 
- A big NFL
Kelce's own path towards greatness in football also had obstacles. While playing university American football, he was suspended for marijuana consumption.
His older brother Jason pressured the coaching staff to give Travis another opportunity and again recommended it when Kansas City Chiefs selected him to play professionally in 2013.
Kelce played a key role as the chiefs went from a decay franchise to an NFL dynasty. Now it is considered one of the best in the history of this competitive sport.
He won three Super Bowls and lost two, including a painful defeat against Philadelphia Eagles in the year that ended the dreams of the historic "triplet" of the chiefs.
 
- How did you start?
During Swift's “Eras” tour, which raised $ 2 billion, distributing hand-made “friendship bracelets” with written messages became a much appreciated ritual among fans.
Kelce went beyond and tried to meet Swift behind the scenes of a show in Kansas City in 2023 and hand him a bracelet with his phone number.
But the plan was frustrated to find that Swift does not maintain fans dating - not even NFL stars - before or after the shows, "because he needs to take care of his voice," as Kelce regretted his podcast shortly thereafter.
Swift, however, was delighted to learn of the romantic trick. "We started leaving shortly after that," he told Time magazine.
 
- Controversy
Taylor Swift quickly became a usual presence at Travis Kelce's chiefs games. The audience and sale of tickets of this modality, immensely popular in the United States, fired as the cameras focused on the reactions of the POP star in the Games.
This caused criticism from the most radical football fans, who considered that the sport was becoming an entertainment show. Even the right -wing conspiracy theories appeared that their relationship had been invented as "Democratic propaganda."
In the end, the distractions seemed not to affect Kelce or the Chiefs, who beat the Super Bowl of that season.
 
- engagement
In a joint Instagram post, the couple showed a series of Kelce photos to propose to Swift in marriage kneeling in the middle of a garden decorated with flowers in tones of white and pink, and a photo of a large diamond ring.
The engagement occurs at a very busy moment for both: Kelce, between rumors about his retirement, is prepared for the beginning of the NFL season next month; While Taylor Swift has a new album, “The Life of A Showgirl”, which will be released in October.
For all that is said earlier, it seems clear that both will continue to succeed and that the marriage will eventually become a great promotional event of the brilliant careers of Taylor Swift and Travis Kelce.
Congratulations!
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-08-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>