<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Identification of elderly people alone “is no easy task and requires collaboration”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/identificacao-de-idosos-sozinhos-nao-e-tarefa-facil-requer-colaboracao/</link><description>Given the trend of population aging, the academic specializing in gerontology Jacky Ho and the secretary general of Caritas, Paul Pun, consider that "it is no easy task" to identify the elderly alone and argue that it is necessary "collaboration" between the different departments of the government, and it is necessary to be aware of the most diverse social contexts. For example, Jacky Ho says that public libraries and churches are places where social workers could be designated to find these elderly. They also point out that the government must create a home care team, as well as implement professionals to encourage professionals to dedicate themselves to this area

























Catarina Pereira
 
The aging rate in Macau has been registering a rise trend year after year and in 2024 reached 116.6%, the highest since 1990. With the elderly population, ie 65 years or older, to correspond to 14.6% of the total population, one of the concerns that has been raised is the fact that many live alone. In this regard, in the lines of government action for 2025, the government indicated that it will begin the survey and registration of the elderly and families of elderly living isolated. But this “is not an easy task and requires collaboration” between various departments, as well as attention to the different contexts of life in society, defend Paul Pun, secretary general of Caritas, and Jacky Ho, director of the University of São José Medical Sciences Faculty (USJ).
The academic specializing in gerontology from the University of Sidney considers that the difficulty is greater when talking about elderly 75 years or older. “This group of elderly people, compared to the younger ones, has less interaction with the social support network and does not regularly visit public services,” says Jacky Ho, in statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. "Therefore, to find them, a collaboration is necessary, for example, between the Institute of Social Action (IAS), statistics and census services and the direction of identification services. Thus a cross check can be done." "It is not an easy task, but it is a task that requires collaboration between government departments and also the associations that provide services," he said.
Jacky Ho spoke about some data provided to this newspaper by the Judiciary Police (PJ), according to which, over the past six years, 264 elderly people who lived alone were found at home. Last year there were 41 elderly, of which more than half (22) were between 71 and 81 years old. In 2022 and 2023, the numbers were higher, with 65 and 74 elderly to be found lifeless, respectively. In these cases, the teacher associates the highest numbers with the situation of Covid-19 pandemic. If we retreat until 2019, this year accounted for 25 cases, followed by 2020 with 27 cases and 2021 with a total of 32.
In the same line, and given cases of elderly people who are found lifeless, Paul Pun suggests that companies like Macau Water a hundred can play a role. "If the use of water decreases in some fractions where they live isolated elderly, they may have problems. The use of electricity is also a way of realizing the situation of the elderly living alone," he said.
In addition, banks should also strengthen the tracks, defended the secretary general of Caritas: "They can call customers to stop the pension accounts for elderly for a long time to demonstrate concern." On the other hand, "health entities can highlight staff to look for the elderly who do not attend follow -up consultations."
Paul Pun also pointed out two other contexts that can be aware of this most vulnerable group of the population. On the one hand, buildings management workers “can pay attention to fractions that are silent for many days”, on the other, yum cha restaurants, frequented by some elderly people, should also pay attention to usual customers who cease to appear, transmitting information to IAS.
In this context, Jacky Ho adds two more places: public libraries and churches. "According to a recent study we did, the data show that the elderly over 70 and 80 years old usually go to church or public libraries," he said, adding: "Perhaps we should designate social workers to be in these contexts, helping to break the lack of connection between the elderly and the social support network."
 
Men socialize less and ask for less help
PJ's statistical data also reveal that, in every year under analysis, there are always more men who were found dead at home than women. For example, last year, of the 41 cases registered, 28 were men (68%), while in 2023, 60% of the 74 cases, equivalent to 45 elderly, were male. Already in 2022, out of a total of 65 cases, 37 were men (57%). What can this data say to us?
“Our society is marked by an environment in which men rarely seek help and participate little in social activities. They prefer to be alone and few people care about them,” says Paul Pun, in the statements to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. In contrast, he adds, "the elderly people often seek help from their children at their own initiative." "Even if they fall or are sick, many elderly men prefer not to tell family members. There are risks in this regard," he warns.
Jacky Ho shares the same vision: "Men are not usual frequents of social services, they think it is only for women. On the other hand, men also have an average life of shorter life than women." The academic speaks after the examples of Korea and Japan, where he says, studies show that the man seems more likely to be abandoned, while the woman will be supported by her children.
In any case, whether men or women, “the elderly living alone constitute a group of the high-risk population,” says the secretary general of Caritas. From his perspective, "society must pay attention especially to the health of the people who live alone." You should think, for example, how to make this group aware of seeking help when you are sick, or what methods can be used to reduce falls at home. “This kind of situations has been increasing,” warns Paul Pun.
For Jacky Ho it is important for authorities to advance quickly with the identification work of the elderly isolated in the territory. First, "in the short term, we have to evaluate what kind of services need." "Perhaps they need to go to homes or maybe they need some kind of home care service," he said.
In the long run, it must be borne in mind that younger generations have less interest in building the traditional family structure. "Due to the new trends, there will be more people who will fall into this category of aging, living alone, or even aging, living alone with a partner," he noticed. Nevertheless, and by comparison, USJ academic notes that future elderly "have an advantage" as they have a higher level of education and are therefore "more aware of the different supports available in society."
 
Attract professionals and create home service team
The academic argues that the second step to be given, after identifying the elderly, is to create support services for the elderly that are provided at home. "I encourage the government to expand resources to create a home care team. At this time, the capacity we have is not enough," he says. Jacky Ho underlines: "You need to prepare professionals to face the challenges that get up and it takes time for the services people to get experience and develop desire to stay in the sector."
And right now “the sector is not attractive,” the USJ teacher wins, then enumerating what he considers essential to encourage professionals to embark this way. "We have to encourage training institutes to create a more systematic program and identify and attract more people to this sector. Then we have to create policies and even subsidized programs to attract people who work and stay in this area. And thirdly, we have to increase the amount of resources invested in building this home care network to prepare as society to face these challenges."
Jacky Ho believes that there is “a very wrong perception” in society regarding elderly care. “Society wrongly has the perception that a maid can be hired and pay 5,000 or 6,000 patacas to take over the elderly. I have observed that many maids, when they go to interviews and realize that they have to take care of the elderly do not accept. And it is natural, they can choose what type of work they want to do. In addition, they have not received vocational training in the area. The doing - and at this time, the options available in Macau are not enough, ”he concluded.
Paul Pun, for more than four decades in the service of others, corroborates: "It is currently very difficult to hire workers to take care of the elderly." "In the long run, we can encourage young people to be volunteers, so that, gradually, there are more and more people available to provide services to the elderly," he suggested, considering that they can try to provide services to elderly once or twice a month. "This experience can help them gain basic abilities." On the other hand, and in the long run, the secretary general of Caritas says that it is necessary to raise the salary of caregivers who work in the homes.
As for services directed to the elderly living alone, it argues that it is the health protection services that are missing the most. "Talking about health is a strategy. There are many positive recreational activities for health, but the elderly may not want to participate. Elderly need, for example, methods to relieve pain and dental health care. If they have teeth the deteriorated, they will lose their appetite.
In addition, it points out that IAS should encourage social services groups to organize activities for the elderly to be able to walk outdoors and reduce physical decline, and show concern about this group of the population. All of this will improve the lives of the elderly, emphasizes Paul Pun, who, however, is certain that what they need most is “attention and affection of family members”, in the case of those who have them. "If children and young people are awakened to devote more time to contact the elderly relatives, the lives of the elderly will become better."
 
NUMBERS
Isolated elderly found dead at home
2024 - 41 (28 men, 13 women)
2023 - 74 (45 men, 29 women)
2022 - 65 (37 men, 28 women)
2021 - 32 (21 men, 11 women)
2020 - 27 (19 men, 8 women)
2019 - 25 (17 men, 8 women)
 
In total, 264 elderly between 2019 and 2024 were found lifeless, and 167, the equivalent of 63%, were 71 years or older.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese community joins for Arraial de Santo António at EPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/comunidade-portuguesa-junta-se-para-arraial-de-santo-antonio-na-epm/</link><description>Two days of conviviality with music, dance, snacks and activities for adults and children, will mark another edition of the Popular Festival of Santo António. The village, scheduled for June 14 and 15, has the stage of the outer courtyard of the Portuguese school again and is organized by Casa de Portugal, under the program “June, month of Portugal”. The community needs this type of conviviality to be together, ”the Jornal de Macao told the president of the Portuguese Matrix Association. On the 13th, an allusive exhibition will be inaugurated to the popular saints, with ceramic work and other materials



















Victor Rebelo
 
As June is the month of Portugal, they could not miss the popular camps. The first is already on the 14th and 15th, dedicated to Santo António, patron saint of Lisbon, a typical Portuguese party that has been marked in Macau for three years.
In addition to music, dance, food and drink and fun activities for children and adults, the camp also means an opportunity for the Portuguese community to come together.
"The Portuguese need joy, to be together, with a whole dynamic that popular parties provide and that without them people come little, are very isolated," the president of Casa de Portugal told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
Amelia António considers that these moments of conviviality "are much missed for the well-being of the community."
The camp is back in the external courtyard of the Portuguese school (EPM), which happens for the fourth consecutive year, after a long period of interregnum. The revive of the party came shortly after the pandemic in 2022. "The popular saints were dead, in a way, and at that time we advanced with the organization of Santo António, because the Arraial de São João went through difficulties," said the leader of the House of Portugal.
Although two festivities currently exist, Amelia António reinforces the idea that "they have different foundations and expression, making sense to organize both." Also, he underlines, "St. Anthony is more traditional, ours, from Portugal, while St. John is an absolutely characteristic date of Macau, in which we have always participated and collaborated since we have always."
The first day of the village, which celebrates this year the Portuguese Catholic saint of the thirteenth century, will begin around 6:30 pm, extending until night, “as is tradition of the camps”, notes the president of the House of Portugal.
On Sunday, the party will start at 2:30 pm and will only take place until late afternoon. This day, which also has music and a variety of snack offerings, including traditional bifanas, is “especially dedicated to kids and families, with other games and other fun for the younger ones,” says the leader.
In terms of musical performances, the base belongs to the resident band of Casa de Portugal, which will be reinforced with two musicians from Portugal.
The organization of the village, which is sponsored by the Macau Foundation, does not neglect the possibility that, as happened last year, to be forced to implement a "plan B", if it rains. "We have all thought, because we know that this month is often rainy, so if the same is succeeded than in 2024, where we rained a lot, we will occupy the interior space of EPM," explained the president of the house.
About the collaboration that the school has given from the first hour, Amelia António understands that the school is the ideal place to perform the camp, “because we know that EPM wants to continue to have a greater connection with the outside, with the community, and therefore these events are also moments that provide this conviviality and this connection”.
As part of the “June, Portugal Month” program, the commemorative party of Santo António will also include a ceramic exhibition and other materials, with the theme of popular saints. It will be inaugurated on St. Anthony's own day, on June 13, Friday, at the glass house.
“We will have more than 20 pieces made in very different materials, with each artist making their creations within this spirit,” he said.
In addition, Casa de Portugal has been a series of initiatives throughout June, such as an exhibition of Portuguese puppets, from the estate of Elisa Vilaça, called “Objects with Soul”, which will be inaugurated on June 3 and will feature some workshops.
Two days later, the association promotes “Small Worlds in Solid state”, documentary and exposure by Claudia Falcão. In this event, to be held at the Portuguese Bookstore, the object photographs will be displayed in which the image arises influenced by the morphology of the stone, its color, textures and imperfections, ”according to the synopsis of the documentary.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and Catholic establish long -term cooperation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-catolica-estabelecem-cooperacao-de-longo-prazo/</link><description>An agreement was signed between the UPM and the Portuguese Catholic University, which aims to establish lasting academic cooperation and the joint realization of “innovative” research projects
 
The Polytechnic University of Macao (UPM) and the Portuguese Catholic University (UCP) signed a cooperation protocol “to establish long -term and friendly academic cooperation and the joint realization of innovative research projects”. All this in order to promote the development of scientific research and educational activities in China and Portuguese -speaking countries (PLP), the local higher education institution said.
To expand the role of Macao as a platform between China and Lusophone countries, UCP Vice-Rector Margarida Mano and a delegation that led the UPM, where they were received by the dean, Marcus Im. According to the press release, the two parts exchanged impressions on the exchange of higher education between China and the PLP, the formation of qualified staff and cooperation in scientific research.
At the meeting, Marcus Im presented the situation of the development of UPM scientific research in the areas of Artificial Intelligence and Health, as well as the results of cooperation with universities and research institutions of Lusophone countries. Marcus Im said he expects to deepen scientific research cooperation with the Catholic University, "in order to expand the role of Macau as a platform between China and Portuguese -speaking countries."
Margarida Mano, in turn, praised UPM's “excellent contribution” to higher education and scientific and technological cooperation between China and PLP. He also said he hopes that the visit could promote cooperation between the two institutions in the scientific research in the area of ​​health, thus creating a new milestone for sino-illusophone academic cooperation.
 
“Champions” students in knowledge test
On the other hand, the UPM student team became champion in the university category of the “GEG Macau Cup-17th National Education Knowledge Contest”. Under the theme “New Type of Industrialization and High Quality Development”, this edition of the contest covered two main areas: thematic knowledge and general knowledge about the national situation. The initiative attracted the participation of more than 15,000 students from eight higher education institutions and 26 secondary schools in Macao.
“After a close competition, the representative team composed by UPM Bao Guangyu students, Zhu Chule and Tang Ning, won the university champion, due to their solid knowledge and excellent immediate performance,” says UPM.
The competition was organized by the Association of National Conditions Education (Macau), under the guidance of the Department of Education and Youth Affairs of the Central Popular Government Cabinet in the MSAR and the Department of Public Information and Diplomacy of the Ministry of Foreign Ministry of RPC in the MSAR. It was also supported by Youth Education and Development Services, the Macao Education Association and the Macao Catholic Schools Association.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural Institute strengthens tufões response plans</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/instituto-cultural-fortalece-planos-de-resposta-tufoes/</link><description>自然災害及危機應變工作會議



The Macao Cultural Institute (IC) met with the managers of cultural spaces under its protection with the objective of “robbing prevention and response measures to disasters of different types of cultural facilities” and “enhancing the coordination capacity of their administrators”. "The mechanism of prevention and response to the natural crises and disasters of the CI requires that the various departments under the tutelage of this elaborate their own inspection and routine maintenance plans of their spaces and equipment," said the body in a statement, also highlighting the need to provide staff training, organize simulation exercises before the time of the typhors, analyze the risks of various disasters and review the plans of plans contingency.
At this year's meeting, which was attended by the Substitute President of the IC, Choi Kin Long, and leaders from the Institute's various departments, the Macao Cultural Center was pointed out as an example, presenting the response measures and the evacuation plan in case of fires. According to the same note, the importance of routine security inspections in facilities and enclosures, as well as the reinforcement of communication and coordination in the IC, was underlined.
In concrete, the body requires that facilities management departments will make safety inspections during tuffons and rainfall, including flood prevention and emergency response equipment, chunambo walls and outer walls, bamboo scaffolding, tin roofs, gardens and other equipment, outer gardens and other equipment Track and treat potential risks. ”
On the other hand, the IC ensures that, whenever necessary, the pruning of trees in the cultural spaces, temples and churches under their tutelage. At the same time, it provides support through the provision of drainage pumps, the installation of anti-importes and the aid in cleaning and clearance of leaks in temples and churches located in low areas, among other measures to prevent damage to cultural heritage and ensure the safety of residents.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting ‘Thanks’ Benfica's offer and reaches the double</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/desporto/sporting-agradece-oferta-benfica-chega-a-dobradinha/</link><description>EPA12135309 Sporting Players Celebrate with the Trophy of the Portugal Cup after Defeating Benfica During The Portugal Final Soccer Match Beteen Benfica and Sporting Held at Jamor National Stadium in Oeiras, Outskirts of Lisbon, Portugal, 25 May 2025. EPA/JOSE SENA GOULA



Gyökeres, Harder and Trincão gave Sporting the club's first 'double' in 23 years, in the victory in the Portuguese Football Cup final about Benfica (3-1), which can only complain about himself.

At the national stadium, after Kökcü gave advantage to the 'incarnated', on 47 minutes, Gyökeres, in the last play of the penalty regulatory time, redid the equality at 90+11, and Harder consumed the turnaround at 99.
With justice, as it was the most compact team in regular time, Benfica was second to win the cup, but Renato Sanches and Leandro Barreiro eventually ruined the afternoon to the emblem of Luz.
Sanches made a scused penalty on Gyökeres, in a play that had just been 'killed' by Barreiro. The Luxembourg International showed total lack of experience and intelligence as it should have knocked down at the beginning of the bid. If this had happened, now Benfica would be celebrating the conquest of the cup.
Sporting, which clearly arrived at Jamor of 'hangover' due to excesses at two -time championship festivities during the week, took advantage and eventually controlled extension to a completely demoralized Benfica. Coach Rui Borges ended up not surprising in the initial eleven of the 'lions', with Captain Hjulmand in return and St. Juste in place of the injured Diomande, while Bruno Lage launched unexpectedly Dahl and Bruma, leaving Di María again on the bench.
Sporting even came in better, but from the 15th minute the game began to be the 'incarnate', which practically didn't let the new champions come out of their midfield, forcing the mistake and the wrong passes. In one of these moves, Destast lost the ball in a forbidden zone and only a great defense of Rui Silva to the post prevented Pavlidis's goal in the first sign of danger.
There was a very dangerous new bid from the Greek striker, who this time failed the target, and Bruma, who still made some fans celebrate goal in Jamor. Just for this, and the full disappearance of the game's Sporting, Lage's team deserved to have gone to the break in advantage.
The second part practically started with the Kökcü goal, with the Turkish shifting outside the area, in a move where Sporting players were more concerned with contesting a non -existent foul on the chick. Shortly thereafter, throw practically the same, but this time Carreras even knocked down, before Bruma celebrated what would be Benfica's second.
As might be expected, the 'incarnates' have lowered the lines, always waiting to go out in quick attacks, while Sporting had more ball. However, the game eventually lived several breaks, such as Benfica players 'abusing' medical assistance, a situation that really had an impact on the 'lions' game. Rui Borges's team was well running the ball, but found no solutions, with Gyökeres, and not only, very erased in the match.
Already after Belotti, who had surrendered Pavlidis, had been close to the second goal, Trincão had a tie, but fired very weak against Samuel Soares, in the one that seemed to be the determining bid of the final.
Everything seemed pointed to a 'incarnate' triumph, with barreiro equally near 2-0, but the luxembourg and then Renato Sanches 'completely blurred the painting'.
In the last bid of regulatory time, Trincão drew from midfield, initially was pulled by Barreiro, but the midfielder gave up the play and Sporting came to the draw. Already with the ball in Gyökeres, the Swedish surpassed António Silva and, when he entered the area, suffered a misguided lack of Renato Sanches. As always, the Scandinavian was lethal of penalty and everything followed for extension.
Samuel Soares still prevented Gyökeres 'bis' with a great save, but Sporting even reached the second goal, with Harder to appear loose in the area and the right head after the center of Trincão.
The turnaround was consummated and now it had to be Benfica to try equality, something that was never close to happening. Lage also launched Di Maria and it was the Argentine who ended up bothering Rui Silva, twice, but always without giving much work to the Leonino guardian.
Already with the game completely broken, Harder started on the left, gave Gyökeres, ending the Swedish, at the entrance of the area, for watching Trincão to the goal that ended any questions in the club that would raise the Portuguese Cup 2024/25.
 
JTM/LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Elisa Ferreira opens cycle of “conversations in the consulate”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/elisa-ferreira-abre-ciclo-de-conversas-consulado/</link><description>At the invitation of the Portuguese Consul-General, Elisa Ferreira, former Minister of the Governments of António Guterres and former member of the European Parliament, will present in Masters a communication on the history and democracy of Portugal. Under the Conference Cycle “Conversations in the Consulate”, the presentation will be followed by a moderate question and answers session by Paulo Canelas de Castro
 
The “conversations in the consulate” conference cycle will open with an elisa Ferreira communication, former minister of the governments of António Guterres and former member of the European Parliament. “Portugal: From the successes of Portugal democratic to the crossroads of the present” is the theme of the session that will take place in the Stanley Ho Auditorium, at the invitation of the Portuguese Consul-General in Macao and Hong Kong, Alexandre Leitão.
The presentation will take place at 11 am on June 2 and will be followed by a moment of questions and answers with the public, moderated by the president of the Macao European Studies Institute, Paulo Canelas de Castro.
Degree in Economics from the University of Porto, where he was also a teacher, Elisa Ferreira is also a master and doctor in economics from the University of Reading. Throughout his professional life, he was vice president of the North Region Coordination Commission, vowel of the Board of Directors of the National Institute of Statistics and Vice-President of the Portuguese Industrial Association.
During the governments chaired by António Guterres, he also occupied the places of Environment Minister and Minister of Planning and Territorial Planning. He was also deputy to the Assembly of the Republic and the European Parliament. He passed by Banco de Portugal, as administrator and deputy governor, and was representative of Portugal in the Supervision Council of the Single Supervision Mechanism of the European Central Bank.
As a European Commissioner for Cohesion and Reform, Elisa Ferreira was responsible for “ensuring support for the regions most affected by digital and climate transitions”, for working with co-legislators to establish a legislative framework for cohesion funds in the European Union's long-term budget (EU), according to a note from the Portuguese Consul General Secretariat in Macau and Hong Kong.
He also supported regions and authorities in the preparation of programs, worked with the Member States “to ensure full and effective use” of the EU funds, supervised expenses and contributed to the revision of the urban agenda and a long-term view of rural areas, the statement says.
ELISA FERREIRA TELITELD ALSO THE GENERAL ADMINISTRATION FOR SUPPORTING STRUCTURAL REFORMS, IN TECHNICAL AND FINANCIAL SUPPORT TO REFORMS IN THE MEMBER STATES, coordinated technical support to the Member States in the adoption of the euro and worked with co-legislators, in order to obtain an agreement on the reform support program and the budgetary instrument of convergence and competitiveness to the euro area.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Talk at Sunset” will address Donald Trump's strategies</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/talk-sunset-vai-abordar-estrategias-de-donald-trump/</link><description>Talking about "noise" around Donald Trump's governance is the topic for another "Talk at Sunset" session, organized by the Macao International Advertising Association. Lawyer José Álvares Lawyer will share his perspective on the communication strategies and capabilities of the US president as a marketing professional
 
The theme “Donald Trump's communication strategies: beyond noise” will be discussed in another edition of “Talk at Sunset (“ Talk to Elder ”in the Portuguese translation), which will feature the presentation of José Álvares.
At the session promoted by the Macao-China International Advertising Association (IAA), which will take place tomorrow, between 6.30 pm and 8 pm, at Vasco Bar of Hotel Artyzen, the resident lawyer in Macau will share his perspective on Donald Trump's abilities as “Marketeer”, his leadership qualities and the global impact of his policies. The lecture will address the effects of customs tariffs, especially on the Chinese economy, and will explore potential opportunities for Macau and Lusophone countries.
In the presentation, followed by debate, José Álvares will talk about the examples of Trump's strategic communication, including the Panama Channel Declaration and the use of provocative rhetoric in Gaza to influence foreign policy.
By using Macau as “The Switzerland of Asia”, Álvares considers this city as a potential neutral center that can take advantage of its unique position and Portuguese ties to improve diplomatic relations.
“The world is undergoing colossal changes once by generation, so I invite everyone to discuss and try to understand the person behind this kind of revolution - I learn more every day, it's scary and fascinating,” says José Álvares, quoted in a statement.
“His unique view of Donald Trump's communication strategies and the broader implications for Macao and Portuguese -speaking countries promise to be clarifying and thought -provoking,” says IAA president. The discussion will explore “not only the intricacies of effective communication and leadership, but also highlight the opportunities that arise from global economic dynamics,” says Rebecca Choi.
For the leader, “Talk at Sunset” is intended “to be a key program for IAA to relate to all experts and sector leaders, as well as to serve as a platform to educate the new talents”.
IAA, founded in 1938, is the most influential global network of marketing and advertising professionals, covering 56 different countries and languages. The main business partners are international companies, including Google, Amazon, CNN, BBC, United Nations, among others.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>South Korean festival will pass through Macau</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festival-sul-coreano-passara-por-macau/</link><description>On August 9 and 10, the South Korean musical festival “Waterbomb” will be present in Macau, as part of a world tour of 2025. Raehk will also host the event again, two months later
 
The "Waterbomb", a South Korean summer music festival known for the mix of live shows and water battles, will go through Macau and Hong Kong, according to the South Korean newspaper "Korea Joong-Ang Daily". The concerts in Macau are scheduled for August 9 and 10, while in the neighboring region will take place two months later, on October 4 and 5.
The announcement comes at a time when the Waterbomb reveals plans for significant global expansion, with a 2025 tour that will cover 13 cities. The festival, which began expanding abroad in 2023 with shows in Bangkok, Tokyo and Nagoya, attracted more than 150,000 participants in Dubai, Hong Kong, Singapore, Tokyo and Fukuoka the following year.
In 2025, the Waterbomb will widen its international reach with new stops in Manila, Haião, Singapore, Bali, Ho Chi Minh, Taipei, Bangkok and Dubai. The Korean stage of the tour will be simplified, from nine cities to just three - Seoul, Busan and Sokcho (Gangwon Province). According to the South Korean newspaper, the organizers promised a more refined and engaging festival, with content adapted to each city.
Recognized by the unique concept that fuses music with interactive water battles and elaborate special effects, the WaterBomb has established a distinct niche in the summer entertainment calendar. After successful Hainão and Manila events, “the expectation of the global presence of tour and its role in the presentation of Korean entertainment on the world stage”.
"The enthusiastic support of fans in the country and abroad made this next step possible," said the festival organizers. "We are committed to presenting innovative content and continuing our global expansion to raise the WaterBomb brand," they said.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Launched two initiatives focused on the photograph</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lancadas-duas-iniciativas-focadas-na-fotografia/</link><description>We are! -Portuguese Language Communication Association and Halftone will launch two new initiatives under the contest “Images of Lusophony” and under the theme “The Man and the Divine”, whose exhibition will be inaugurated on Friday. In addition to a tour to capture the “local spirituality”, with the support of this year's contest winner, Marcos Júnior, a session on photographic techniques is also scheduled
 
Next Saturday, we are! - Portuguese Language Communication Association (Somos - ACLP), in a collaboration with Halftone, will organize the guided course “Photopiece in Macao - Sacred Place”, due to the sixth edition of the “Somos of Lusophony” contest and under the theme “The Man and the Divine”.
The script will include the ruins of St. Paul, the temples of Na Tcha, Tou Tei, Pau Kung and Kun Age, in a "collective discovery of diverse and creative ways to capture local spirituality." Participants will have the technical support of Marcos Júnior, Mozambican photographer and winner of this year's contest, and Francisco Ricarte, architect and president of Halftone, among others, the association said.
In addition to equipment, such as cameras or phones, the organization recommends participants to take water and sunscreen to the tour, which will be held from 10:30 am to 12:30 pm. In the end, each participant can send up to three photographs, accompanied by subtitles, to be published on Somos's website and social networks.
On the other hand, on June 3, at 6.30 pm, several local photographers will share experiences “about the capture of images in religious contexts and sacred ceremonies in Lusophony”. During the session “Photosteroses We are - Images of Lusophony x Halftone - With Marcos Júnior”, which will take place in Parisian, the audience will learn about photographic techniques of “image capture”, which intensify “characteristics of mysticity and transcendence”.
According to Somos, there will still be a reflection on the photographer/sacred dialogue, which will address the influence of the author's personal beliefs on photography and the power of religious and spiritual images in current societies.
The author of the image “Where there is faith, there is light that guides”, Marcos Júnior, will also be present at the inauguration of the photographic exhibition, scheduled for 6.30 pm on Friday, and the show will be evident to the public until June 28. This is the first time the association has a contest winner to the territory.
Curated by Francisco Ricarte, the show will display the winning photographs of the contest, as well as honorable mentions and images considered relevant by the jury in promoting “Portuguese language communication” and “dissemination of Lusophone traditions and characteristics”.
For Somos - ACLP, the objective of the initiative is to promote “the role of Macao as a bridge for the cultural exchange between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries” and the “intralusophone dialogue in the territory”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Betting houses and was focusing on the sports press congress</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casas-de-apostas-ia-em-foco-congresso-da-imprensa-desportiva/</link><description>Macao was present at the International Congress of the Sports Press, which took place in the Moroccan City of Rabat, through two representatives of the Association of Sports Journalists of MSA. The event received close to 100 delegations, having addressed various issues of the interest of the sector, especially the bookmakers and artificial intelligence

Victor Rebelo
 
Morocco was the host of the Annual Congress of the International Sports Press Association (AIPS), having participated in the event with two leaders of the Macao Sports Journalists Association (AJDM), created in 1998, currently with 50 members, and affiliated with AIPs. Fong Chi Kam, secretary general, and Tam Iao San, chairman of the AJDM Supervision Commission, participated in the work over the five days of Congress, in which about 100 delegations were involved, including Portugal, China, Hong Kong and Taiwan, and more than 300 sports journalists from the five continents.
For this forum, AIPS, which celebrated in 2024 a century of existence, annually invites representatives of international organizations, such as the Olympic Committee (IOC), FIFA and UEFA to present the next events they will hold. For example, the Milan Cortin Winter Olympics and the Youth Olympic Games in Dakar, both in 2026.
This year, the main topics were Artificial Intelligence (IA) and “content creators”, but also “women's challenges in sport” and “the investigation of illegal bets”.
Tam Iao San told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that the AIPS Annual Congress is important to Macau "to know the latest information in the area of ​​international sports media." After the event, added the TDM sports journalist, the representatives of the MSar will present a report to the AJDM and share the information with their members.
It should be noted that when the AIP elections, Macau is entitled to a vote.
The Asian continent also organizes an annual sports press congress, which is also part of AJDM, which will gather its members in Hong Kong, between the end of June and early July.
 
“Fake News” generate concern
In addition to the usual ceremony of delivery of awards of the written and photographic reporting contest, promoted worldwide, the Morocco Congress discussed various topics. One of them analyzed the danger of club betting houses, often involving minors to play, hidden from parents, which may result in financial losses for families.
Artificial intelligence (IA) also deserved attention from congressmen. One of the titles of dissertations- “Monster or really a great tool?” - launched the debate.
Morocco, Spain, France and India focused on discussions, considering that for the sports press, one of the biggest problems is the false news. The manifested concern is the possibility of “fake news” being received with manipulation of videos and images, “really doubtful origin news that can be confronted with the true information of the communication professional,” said the panel of the journalists present.
On the other hand, it has been pointed out that AI needs the “serious and responsible professional” to have true content.
"It will always be useful because it can have the source, do the interview, tell and record the history of their sport," said the interveners in the session.
Among other issues that filled the debates, one thrilled the participants when a presentation was made on “The Horror of Wars”, with official stadium and gymnasium numbers and press professionals killed in Palestine and Ukraine.
The "content creators" motivated equally strong discussions. Some participants have come to the conclusion that this is an accelerated way in the process of sports communication, speaking of famous reporters who are leaving traditional channels and depart for their own channel and content.
The panel of commentators has come to the conclusion that “there is no way to have room for the great chroniclers who do the work of registering the facts professionally”, hence the need for organizations such as FIFA, UEFA, COI, among others, implement rules that blend the “respect of old professionals with the new ones that emerge as content producers”.
AIPS President Gianni Merlo considered this congress as “one of the most striking” in the history of the body.
On the last day the participants visited several Moroccan sports facilities.
The next edition will take place in Lausanne, Switzerland, in 2026.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Students with autism exhibit 30 works that challenge stigmas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-autismo-exibem-30-obras-desafiam-estigmas/</link><description>Until June 7, will be on display at the Rui Cunha Foundation, the student art projects of the “Serpent Charm”, making known the imagination of young people with autism and intellectual difficulties. The 30 colorful works of participating students include paintings, designs, collages and handicrafts that challenge prejudice
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) inaugurates today, at 5:30 pm, the Student Art Exhibition “The Snake's Charm: Pursuing Dreams”, to make known the “imagination and creativity of the works” performed by young people with autism and intellectual difficulties. The projects will be patent until June 7, with free admission.
Promoted by the Association for Macao Intellectual Development Services (Asdim), this year's show will present 30 colorful works of art created by Kai Chi School Students, Kai Lung's Kai Chi initial training center, Kai Hon Center and Sam Meng Chi Snack House.
According to a FRC statement, the participants' age group was extended so that "more students could join the competition." The main exhibition brings together paintings, designs, collages and handicrafts aimed at “challenging difficulties, stigmas and prejudices” with young people with special needs.
The internal competition, which takes place with the annual exhibition, will have the title “You have a friend in me” and consists of creating partners for the asdim mascot, “Smart (Chi Chai)”. During the ceremony, the prizes will be delivered to the winners of the contest, which has 52 proposals.
Asdim was founded in 1986 to offer “early intervention services, special education and day -to -pedagogical activities” and employment support services for people with intellectual disabilities, according to the statement.
At the same time, the association has stimulated the learning of manual arts as a way of developing emotional and behavioral skills through self-expression. Workshops provide young people an opportunity to manipulate materials and a “sense of control of the creative environment”.
Associated schools and centers have been able to monitor the growth of these students, in terms of individual expression, social opportunities, self-esteem, well-being and happiness, can be read in the statement.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Amaga debut “Month of Portugal” with exhibition of 24 Portuguese artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/amagao-estreia-mes-de-portugal-exposicao-de-24-artistas-lusos/</link><description>The Amagao Gallery will host the first integrated event in the program “June, Month of Portugal”, with the inauguration of the exhibition “Portuguese Art - Dialogues of Creativity”. A total of 24 Portuguese artists present, from tomorrow, half a hundred painting and sculpture works. Júlio Pomar, Maria Leal da Costa and José Luís Tinoco are among the authors of the work that will be patent to the public by the end of June



















The Official Event Program inserted in “June, Portugal Month” already starts tomorrow, with the exhibition “Portuguese Art - Dialogues of Creativity”, which presents 50 works by 24 Portuguese artists.
The show releases an “exceptional selection of renowned contemporary authors, each bringing a unique and innovative perspective on the current artistic panorama”, according to a promotional note of the exhibition promoted by the amagao, in whose gallery, located at Hotel Artyzen, will take place the event.
Most of the works are in figurative and abstract painting of different approaches, but there is also a sculpture by Maria Leal da Costa. One of the highlights of the event is Júlio Pomar, renowned plastic artist and painter, who died in 2018, belonging to the third generation of Portuguese modernist authors, being responsible for multifaceted works.
In addition to those two artists, pieces will be represented by Abílio Febra, Alfredo Luz, Ana Cristina Dias, Ana Pimentel, André Pedro, Cunha Nery, Francisco Geraldo, Graça Morais, João Paulo, Jorge Francisco, Jose Luís Tinoco, Lara Roseiro, Luis Jesus, Madalena Pequito, Maria Dulce Martins, Maria João Franco, Number, Raquel Grail Bravo.
Some of the works, which will be exhibited until June 30, “are part of the collection of the sour and others expressly came to this exhibition,” he told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau Lina Ramadas, curator of the exhibition, but also founding and owner of the gallery, such as Victor Hugo Marreiros.
In the “June, Portugal Month” program, which is part of the celebrations of June 10, Portugal, Camões and Portuguese communities, this exhibition is considered a “vibrant celebration of contemporary art that not only illuminates the artistic scene in Portugal, but also provokes reflections on the issues that connect and differentiate us in current society”.
After already launched two exhibitions this year 2025, one that celebrated the anniversary of the gallery, and another with artists from 12 countries or regions, the love of two more shows.
In October, the initiative will cover Picasso and Miró posters, serving to celebrate Spain's Day. “We have a partnership with a Spanish gallery in Barcelona, ​​so it will be a different exhibition than usual,” says Lina Ramadas.
Later, in early December, “another unusual exhibition,” he emphasizes, in which he will be patent works in which two artists, Alexandre Marreiros and an Asian author will paint the same picture.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Forwarded to the MP after attacking agent with metal bar</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/encaminhado-para-mp-apos-atacar-agente-barra-de-metal/</link><description>The case of a 60 -year resident was sent to the prosecutor who assaulted a public security police officer on Sunday afternoon, reported Radio Macau. The incident, which took place near the Red Market, on Padre António Roliz Street, will have followed the police who reported the man he had committed an offense. According to videos published on social networks, the driver left the van with a metal bar and attacked the agent. According to a police source, quoted by the radio, the man also uttered insults. According to the information disclosed, the offense that will have committed was illegal parking, on Avenida do Ouvidor Arriaga. Police chased the driver after the illegal parking lot and asked him to leave the vehicle. It was at this time that the individual attacked the agent, and was later detained by another agent who was off and residents who were in the place. The wholesale agent suffered injuries to the arm. The man should be accused of various crimes.</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Centenary show brings together the last geisha in Tokyo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/espectaculo-centenario-reune-ultimas-gueixas-em-toquio/</link><description>On the gloss parquet floor of a room of a discreet Tokyo building, the latest geishas of the Japanese capital slide with millimeter steps to the rhythm of music and perpetuate an ancestral art in decline.



















Under the attentive look of his teachers, the geishas of the Shinbashi neighborhood, near the Imperial Palace, repeat these choreography daily to Azuma Odori, a dance show born a century ago.
Because of this centenary, between May 21 and 27, geishas from 19 regions of Japan shared the stage for the first time with their Shinbashi mates, now reduced to about forty women. These women are the latest guardians of an in danger art, heirs to an millennial tradition that Japan sometimes observes how something from the past, explains Hisafumi Iwashita, writer and expert of this theme.
“The Japanese themselves have difficulty understanding or not knowing the true reality of geishas,” he says to AFP.
The stereotypes are diverse. In the collective imagination they often consider them prostitutes. But in Japanese, the word "geisha" means "person of art," a man or woman graduated in the traditional Japanese arts.
The role of geishas goes beyond “simply dancing and singing,” insists Iwashita.
“We are there first to welcome and entertain customers in traditional restaurants called Ryotei,” confirms Koiku, a shinbashi geisha.
 
Postwar Renaissance
Dressed in a dark kimono highlighted by an obi (belt) with spring prints, Koiku decided to become a geisha to live on his passion for dance and music.
"In general, it takes 10 years to be considered competent," says this veteran that he has been participating in Azuma Odori for over three decades.
In this closed world, the show offers the general public a rare opportunity to appreciate this traditional art on the stage of “Shinbashi Enbujo”, a theater built with this goal in 1925.
In this centenary, the arrival of geisha across the country allows you to discover the typical styles and traditions of each region in two daily representations of more than one and a half.
In Kyoto, “dance is considered the main art, while in Tokyo, geishas differ by the skill with Shamisen [a Japanese string instrument] and the corners,” explains Hisafumi Iwashita.
At the beginning of the shows, the shinbashi geisha entertained in official banquets the new leaders arrived in Tokyo, which became the capital of Japan over the century in place of Kyoto. These women played an “essential role” in the definition of modern Japanese culture, says the expert.
The Shinbashi Enbujo Theater, inaugurated in the first edition of Azuma Odori a hundred years ago, was destroyed during World War II and rebuilt in 1948. After the conflict, the show was reborn and its scenography influenced the traditional Kabuki Theater. But, “she started losing popularity in the 1950s-1960s, because the public preferred simpler shows,” explains Iwashita.
Now, in the Rising Sun Archipelago, the art of geisha is threatened to disappear.
"A while ago, we were still 100, then 60 ... and the number continues to decrease," Koiku worries, for those who are "essential to find solutions" before "it's too late."
For Iwashita, the decline of geisha in the capital responds mainly to the disappearance of the wealthy clientele that previously supported the business.
One inflection point was in 1993, when Prime Minister Morihiro Hosokaw asked to end official dinners Ryote in a context of serious economic crisis. “A hard blow to the industry,” says Iwashita.
“The world has changed and, with it, how to receive customers,” laments Koiku. “Now, companies organize their receptions in their places or other places,” he continues.
The future of the profession is uncertain, warns Iwashita. "The fact that such a theater still exists and receives the centenary edition of Azuma Odori is a miracle."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-27 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>