<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>CCAC will propose a review of the law against corruption in the private sector</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ccac-vai-propor-revisao-da-lei-contra-corrupcao-privado/</link><description>The Commissioner against Corruption plans to study the Law on the Prevention and Repression of Corruption in the Private Sector, with a view to proposing an update to the legal framework, as stated in the body's Lines of Government Action for 2026. In addition, the CCAC will also present suggestions on the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly. In turn, the Audit Commissioner intends to “intensify” supervision of the management of public funds
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
In 2026, the Commissioner against Corruption (CCAC) will study the Law for the Prevention and Repression of Corruption in the Private Sector, which has been in force for more than 15 years, with a view to presenting, “in a timely manner”, “revision proposals considered relevant”.
In the Lines of Government Action for next year, consulted by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, the CCAC explains that, since the implementation of that diploma, Macau society has undergone “profound changes”, in addition to this legislation presenting “huge differences” in relation to “similar laws in neighboring regions” and various international conventions. According to the CCAC, in the process of combating corruption in the private sector, there are “many difficulties and challenges” in applying the law, the document states.
At the same time, the Commissioner intends to investigate and close cases related to the elections for the 8th Legislative Assembly “as quickly as possible”. Recognizing that the last elections were held after an “important review” of the Electoral Law for the Legislative Assembly, the CCAC will “seriously” evaluate the experiences gained and suggest improvements to the legislation to the Government.
Still within the scope of combating corruption, the CCAC will also “study the characteristics of public services and high-risk sectors”, adopting “specific measures”, and make efforts in dissemination and awareness-raising activities, in favor of “an honest environment in Macau”.
In addition to the review of the criminal legal system that will be led by the Government, the independent body also intends to “contribute to the improvement of the respective legal regimes”, such as criminal law and criminal procedural law.
Other planned measures include “raising the professional level of research staff”, “improving the cooperation mechanism” with authorities in Mainland China and Hong Kong, developing the “application of science and technology” in investigations and carrying out various awareness-raising and educational activities.
In the field of ombudsman justice, the organization states that it will reinforce the work of monitoring disciplinary processes. With the entry into force of the new version of the Fundamental Provisions of the Management Personnel Statute and the new version of the Macau Public Administration Workers Statute, the disciplinary regime has been optimized, which is why the CCAC emphasizes that “it will reinforce the supervision of disciplinary processes for public service workers, in order to better understand the disciplinary situation” under the new regime.
 
Intensified audits of the use of public funds
For its part, the Audit Commissioner (CA) will “intensify audits of the management of the application of resources and public treasury”. In the LAG for 2026, the CA plans to conduct “horizontal and vertical analyzes of public services” and deepen preventive inspection of the public service, in order to identify “deficiencies and potential risks”.
At the same time, it intends to reinforce communication with the Directorate of Finance Services and other competent public entities, to assist “the development of the legal system” and the public sector budget execution, “through a permanent monitoring mechanism”.
The integration of artificial intelligence and process automation are also other actions that the CA will consider, “with the aim of improving work efficiency”. In other lines, the organization also aims to increase awareness about the use of public funds and, like the CCAC, improve the professional skills of its delegates.
Finally, the CA plans to take advantage of the continued integration of the National Audit Office delegation into UN audit work, to “gain experience”, and remain in communication with counterpart authorities in neighboring regions.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Works with bamboo scaffolding have already started to suffer delays</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-andaimes-de-bambu-ja-comecaram-sofrer-atrasos/</link><description>The serious fire that occurred in the HKSAR has generated controversy surrounding the safety of using bamboo scaffolding, already causing an impact on the local sector, acknowledged the director of the Barraqueiros Association, in an interview with this newspaper. Under the current circumstances, some works involving this type of materials have begun to experience delays, revealed Chiu Tak Siu, also regretting that the sector lives with “too many rules” and difficulties in labor.
 
The tragic fire that left at least 159 dead, 79 injured and around 30 missing in the “Wang Fuk Court” housing complex in Tai Po, Hong Kong, has fueled discussions and controversies about safety standards in the use of bamboo scaffolding, including “unfounded comments”, said Chiu Tak Siu, director of the Macau Bar Association.
"Many people are unaware of the real situation in the sector and do not understand the differences between the materials used in the assembly and disassembly of bamboo scaffolding. The materials used are different in different regions. The materials we use are difficult to flammable", highlighted Chiu Tak Siu, interviewed by the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper.
According to him, the bamboo scaffolding and protective nets used in the sector in Macau comply with safety standards, and can provide many guarantees of safety when working at heights.
However, the association leader revealed that, under the current circumstances, some works involving bamboo scaffolding began to suffer delays, with the scaffolding having to be demolished. The delays are also related to customs inspections, which have been restricting the import of some materials related to the sector, noted Chiu Tak Siu.
The association leader acknowledged that the fire in the HKSAR is having an impact on the local sector, which “already lives with too many rules”. Faced with the added difficulties, Chiu confessed that, if the scenario remains, “even I wouldn't want to work in this field anymore”.
Hong Kong authorities propose replacing bamboo scaffolding with metal scaffolding. For the director of the Barraqueiros Association, if the Macao SAR Government follows the same guidance, the sector “will have to close its doors”.
According to the same person in charge, the prices of steel scaffolding are triple those of bamboo, so the eventual replacement of bamboo could increase the repair and maintenance costs paid by citizens, even forcing some to give up this type of work, which would increase safety risks and undermine the local situation for repair and maintenance of buildings.
"Bamboo and iron work differently, implying different occupations. If the use of bamboo scaffolding were now banned, and another case related to iron scaffolding occurred later, what material could the sector use? Everything has its danger", he highlighted.
In general, the association leader hopes that the Government will take scientific data as a reference and discuss with the sector in defining safety standards, taking into account the survival of the sector, which represents an item of Macau's intangible cultural heritage.
Chiu Tak Siu also revealed that there are currently only around 26 scaffolding assembly shops in Macau and there are only four dozen local workers in the sector, who are generally over 60 years old. There is no longer any “new blood”, much less young people entering the sector “because there are too many rules”, he criticized.
Yesterday, in a program on “Ou Mun Tin Toi”, Mak Tat Io, deputy director of Land and Urban Construction Services, said that, regarding the idea of ​​replacing bamboo scaffolding with metal ones, the Government will take an open attitude, as the organization, in fact, had already told this newspaper at the beginning of the year. Noting that both types of materials have advantages and disadvantages, the person responsible assured that the Government will communicate with the sector and society and will only move forward with the respective work when there is consensus.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Proposed Telecommunications Law integrates convergence of networks and services</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/proposta-da-lei-de-telecomunicacoes-integra-convergencia-de-redes-servicos/</link><description>The proposed law to revise the Telecommunications Law will include rules for the convergence of networks and services, said Derby Lau, director of the Postal and Telecommunications Services yesterday. The Government Action Lines for 2026 indicate that the legislative proposal process will be completed in the fourth quarter
 
PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The convergence of telecommunications networks and services will be regulated by the next Telecommunications Law, on which the Government will consult the sector this month, Derby Lau, director of the Postal and Telecommunications Services (CTT), told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper yesterday, on the sidelines of a press conference on the issuance of commemorative stamps. After years of advances and setbacks, according to the Government Action Lines (LAG) report for 2026, the conclusion of that legislative process is now scheduled for the last quarter of next year.
In 2019, although the Government consulted the sector on the new convergence regime, the proposed law was never presented. At the time, the administration explained that the new regulatory regime would “help create more development opportunities for the sector, allowing the offer of more diversified telecommunications services and increased competition in the telecommunications market”.
The presentation of the proposal for the new Telecommunications Law was also scheduled for the second half of 2021. However, at the time, the Government ended up separating the processes of 5G licenses, the convergence regime and the control of concession assets.
In December 2021, regarding the presentation of the LAG for the following year, Raimundo do Rosário, then Secretary for Transport and Public Works, had explained that, once the new Telecommunications Law was completed, the Government would issue the convergence license to operators. The LAG report for 2023 only mentioned that the proposal for the Telecommunications Law remained “under debate” and was scheduled for completion in the second half of that year.
The convergence regime aims to promote telecommunications convergence, the development of 5G and the evolution of next generation network technology, the improvement of the current mode of regulation and the sector's mode of operation, sharing and access to telecommunications infrastructures, the protection of users' rights and interests, among others.
 
CTT will launch two commemorative philatelic issues
On December 8th, CTT will launch the philatelic issues “Centenary of the Foundation of Yuet Wah College” and “30th Anniversary of Macau International Airport”. The first, by Tiago Lei, is a set of four stamps with images of Saint John Bosco, from the old school gate, the Versiglia Building and Jubileu Complex and the Dom Bosco Building.
The four airport anniversary stamps, by designer Vai Chi Hang, represent themes such as the “Airport Opening Ceremony”, “Contributions to Macau Tourism”, “Integration in the Development of the Greater Bay Area” and “Professionalism of Airport Workers”.
100 thousand units of each stamp will be available, with rates of 2.5, 4, 4.5 and 6 patacas. Each issue will also contain 100,000 philatelic blocks, worth 14 patacas each. On the 15th, the services will also launch a new reprint of the “Festejo” stamps.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CEM will have to compensate customers for electricity failures</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cem-tera-de-compensar-clientes-por-falhas-de-energia-electrica/</link><description>The new contract signed between Macao SAR and CEM, which comes into force on January 1st and lasts for 15 years, obliges the company to compensate customers in the event of electricity failures lasting more than 15 minutes. The contract extract defines staggered deductions depending on the number of power outages or the length of interruptions
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The Government renewed the public electricity supply service concession contract with Companhia de Electricidade de Macau (CEM) for another 15 years, starting from January 1, 2026. According to an extract from the contract, published yesterday in the Official Gazette, the company will have to compensate customers in the event of electricity supply interruptions lasting more than 15 minutes.
Specifically, 3% will have to be deducted from the value of the bill for the month in which the electricity supply failed, if the number of interruptions is three to five times; if it is more than six times, the deduction is 6%.
If the total accumulated duration of electricity supply interruptions exceeds four hours per month, the deduction of 3% of the bill value for the month in question will continue; the subtraction increases to 6% if the electrical failure lasts for more than six hours and to 9% if it exceeds eight hours in a month.
The contract extract also states that, within the same calendar year, the total accumulated compensation for each consumer is limited to an amount corresponding to 20% of the average monthly electricity bill paid to CEM during the previous year.
On the other hand, the contract sets a new limit for the company's profits. From 2026 onwards, CEM's investment profitability will be 8.2%. If the company obtains profits greater than this amount, the surplus will have to go to the “Provision for Tariff Stabilization” account. The amount to be transferred cannot exceed the balance of this account and if it is equal to or greater than 80%, CEM must communicate the transfer to Macao SAR in advance.
Furthermore, whenever the balance of the “Provision for Tariff Stabilization” exceeds 15% of the value of the sale of electricity in the previous year, one third of that value reverts to consumers who do not benefit from subsidized tariffs, in the form of a discount on the unit cost of the kilowatt-hour to be charged during the 12-month period following the date of approval of the company's accounts, as can be read in the contract extract.
Whenever the concessionaire requests an increase in electricity sales tariffs, the existing balance in that account “is used to reduce the impact of this increase, under terms to be agreed with the Macao SAR”. Macao SAR, in turn, may use the existing balance in the account to reduce tariffs “if deemed necessary for reasons of public interest”.
Also according to the extract from the contract, CEM is obliged to maintain a sufficient and diversified supply of electricity, as well as to “gradually improve” the electricity supply structure in the territory, “striving to reduce greenhouse gas emissions”.
You must also purchase energy produced through renewable energy installations, implement bidirectional tariffs and install the necessary electricity meters. Furthermore, it is obliged to carry out the expansion, extension, maintenance and renovation works of public lighting network systems, “necessary to respond to the development of the Macao SAR”, as well as the “design, installation, expansion, extension, maintenance and renovation works, necessary for public installations for the production of renewable energy, in accordance with the electricity supply diversification and low carbon policies”.
In the public interest and with the prior written authorization of Macao SAR, CEM may develop other activities related to the supply of electricity in the territory and in the Deep Cooperation Zone, in Hengqin.
In addition to the extension of the concession contract with CEM and the changes made, the concession contract for the public service for the management of technical galleries in Macao was also amended, which extends until December 31, 2040.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>UPM and UTM will spend 9.5 billion on new campuses in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/upm-utm-gastarao-95-mil-milhoes-novos-campi-em-hengqin/</link><description>The Polytechnic University and the University of Tourism each plan to occupy half of the same land in Hengqin, for the construction of their new campuses, which are expected to cost 9.5 billion patacas in total, deputy Ip Sio Kai revealed yesterday, citing university representatives
 
During the discussion of the 2026 Budget bill, university representatives revealed to the 2nd Standing Committee of the Legislative Assembly (AL) that the Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) and the Macau Tourism University (UTM) plan to jointly build new campuses in Hengqin, each institution occupying half of the same land.
Citing their respective representatives, Ip Sio Kai, president of the 2nd AL Commission, said that UPM and UTM have an estimated total budget of 9.5 billion patacas for construction, an amount higher than the 8.4 billion patacas planned for the construction of the new campus of the University of Macau (UM) in the Deep Cooperation Zone. The difference is due to the fact that the construction area is larger than that of UM, as he explained.
According to the Chinese-language press, Ip Sio Kai also said that, according to planning, in 2026, UPM and UTM will invest little in this area, with the budget mainly intended for preparations. Between 2027 and 2030, the two universities will invest 1.4 billion, 950 million, 950 million and 1.4 billion, respectively. Starting next year, UPM will start recruiting master's students for the new campus, while UTM has no plans in this regard yet. Currently, the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services leads the respective projects.
UM will invest, in 2026, around 634 million in the new campus project, work on which has already started. At the same time, the institution also began preparations for recruiting students. Between 2027 and 2030, UM will spend 2.276 billion, 2.857 billion, 630 million and 253 million, respectively, for the new campus.
Furthermore, Ip Sio Kai pointed out that the three institutions are promoting expansion to Hengqin through investment in shares.
At the meeting, university representatives also predicted that, in 2026, all three institutions will register an increase in revenue from teaching and training, given the increase in the number of students, especially non-local students.
Next year, UM will have estimated revenues of 1.137 billion, an annual increase of 19.1%, UPM will see its revenues grow 25.4% to 490 million, and UTM will see revenues of around 160 million patacas, an increase of 43%.
Consequently, the percentage of financial support from the Government will fall across the three universities. Currently, financial support from the Executive occupies 48% of UM's total expenses, 35% of UPM's total expenses and 50% of the money spent by UTM.
With regard to the size of students, all three intend to expand it. In 2026, the total number of UM students will reach 16,771, 1,000 more than in 2025, while UPM and UTM want an increase of 600 and 590 students, respectively.
As the review of its career status has not yet been completed, UTM does not intend to receive new formal employees in 2026, but will acquire services and hire part-time teachers. It is already known that, in 2026, UM will have 135 more employees and UPM 70 more.
 
Pension fund will suffer long-term losses
On the other hand, at the session, the Government explained that, following the decrease in the number of taxpayers and the continuous increase in retirees, the situation has worsened in which the Pension Fund's revenues are unable to cover expenses, predicting that this Fund will enter, in the long term, into a state of loss. According to Ip Sio Kai, the Government and the Pension Fund are actively studying solutions to ensure the stable functioning of the retirement system.
Citing the Government, Ip Sio Kai indicated that, in 2026, the Fund will record revenues of 3.22 billion (including 1.23 billion from the distribution of game winnings), expenses of 3.35 billion and, thus, losses of 130 million patacas.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Former Residence of General Ye Ting reopens today</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/reabre-hoje-antiga-residencia-general-ye-ting/</link><description>葉挺將軍故居開幕儀式



The former Residence of General Ye Ting will reopen to the public today, with the Cultural Institute (IC) highlighting that it intends to “expand the range of patriotic education resources”, as well as “highlight General Ye Ting’s notable contributions to the contemporary history of China”. For the reopening, the organization led by Leong Wai Man carried out work to improve the exhibition in that space.
The reopening ceremony, which took place yesterday, was presided over by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, by the director of the Publicity and Culture Department of the Liaison Office of the Central People's Government in the Macao SAR, Wan Sucheng, by the director of the Ye Ting Memorial Hall in Huizhou City of Guangdong Province, Qin Lan, and by the grandchildren of General Ye Ting, Yip Siu Yin and Ye Tiejun.
On the occasion, the IC president received a calligraphy work inscribed by Yip Ying, the General's grandson, in memory of Tiejun. The work will be displayed in the Old Residence.
This year marks the centenary of the founding of the Ye Ting Independent Regiment. During the ceremony, the bronze statue of General Ye Ting was unveiled, “which shows him standing in military uniform, with a fixed and determined look”.
The reopening of the space, together with other cultural and museum sites, including the Xian
The permanent exhibition is divided into “Childhood Years”, “Involvement in the Revolution”, “Victória in the North”, “Discreet in Macau” and “Prisoner's Song” - illustrating “in a comprehensive way the lasting achievements he achieved for the cause of national liberation”. At the same time, the recreation of scenes from the General's family's daily life highlights “the deep bond between the family and Macau”.
The space is open from 10am to 6pm, including holidays, closing on Wednesdays. On Sundays, at 12:30 pm, free guided tours will be available.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Almost half of the Metro East Line completed</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/concluida-quase-metade-da-linha-leste-metro/</link><description>Almost half of the construction project for the East Line of the Light Rail has been completed, according to the director of Public Works Services. Lam Wai Hou highlighted, on the other hand, that, at the end of the month, three new temporary outdoor parking lots should open to the public
 
The construction project for the East Line of the Light Rail is completed in almost half of its route, including a kilometer of underwater tunnel between Taipa and the Peninsula, which will have a total length of three thousand meters.
“In general, the progress of the works corresponds to expectations”, according to the director of the Public Works Services (DSOP) on the Chinese-language radio, highlighting that the Government will try to get this Metro line into operation in 2029.
Lam Wai Hou also revealed that preliminary soil exploration work is already being carried out to choose the location, with a view to Qingmao station on the Eastern Line. The person responsible said that, later, a public consultation will be carried out to present the respective information.
Remember that the entire Eastern Metro Line will be 7.7km long and have six stations. The work is divided into two segments. The northern part will be 2.9km long and consists mainly of the construction of three underground stations, three tunnels excavated by the tunneling machine and Mudflat planning. The southern segment, 4.8km long, will also include three underground stations and three tunnels, two of which are open-air.
On the same radio program, Lam Wai Hou also stated that three temporary open-air parking lots located on Rua da Cordoaria, in Coloane, in the D. Julieta Nobre de Carvalho Building, in Toi San, and next to the Piloting School, in Barra, will be able to open to the public at the end of this month. The auto-silos are expected to provide 194 spaces for light cars and 140 for motorcycles, with some of them equipped with electrical charging.
Lam Wai Hou highlighted, on the other hand, that, in relation to lots A3, A4 and A9 of Nam Van Lake, the Government will build a temporary public space, which should open in the short term.
Furthermore, the head of DSOP stressed that tenders will soon begin for the construction of recreational and sports facilities in Lots C8 of Nam Van Lake, BT7 of Taipa and B13 of Zone A of New Landfills, estimating that these works will be completed in the second half of 2026.
In relation to the two new Alegria environmental centers and a super charging station, the Executive has already started designing design and tender work.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coordination of road works with “significant” results</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coordenacao-das-obras-viarias-resultados-significativos/</link><description>The Working Group for the Optimization of Road Works Coordination took stock of the activities carried out in 2025, having recorded an increase of around 20% in the joint execution rate of contracts, compared to the previous year, with results considered “significant”. For 2026, the work has been integrated into 47 “coordination zones”, for which the Secretary for Transport and Public Works calls for rigorous supervision
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
The balance of activities carried out in 2025 by the Working Group for the Optimization of the Coordination of Road Works points to an increase of around 20% in the rate of joint execution of works, compared to 2024, with results considered “significant”.
The road works planned for 2026 were integrated into 47 “coordination zones”, defined according to their respective areas and execution periods, showing a reduction compared to the current year, according to a statement from the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT).
The Working Group met yesterday, in the presence of the Secretary for Public Works, Tam Wai Man, to evaluate the activities carried out since its creation. By the end of November, around 360 road works had begun, registering a reduction of more than 30% compared to the same period in 2024. Of these, around 120 were carried out jointly, representing approximately a third of the total, which reflects an increase of around 20% in the joint execution rate compared to the previous year and demonstrates the “increasing effectiveness of the coordination work carried out by the Group”, highlights DSAT.
Furthermore, members have already presented road works plans for next year, duly articulated and integrated into the 47 “coordination zones”, enabling the simultaneous execution of several works in the same area and contributing to reducing repeated excavations on the roads.
On the other hand, the pipeline reservation pilot project carried out at Rua dos Mercadores “was successfully completed”, highlights the organization, ensuring that it had prepared all phases in advance, from planning, publicity and execution to responding to unforeseen events and post-completion monitoring.
The objective was to ensure that the work was completed within the deadline and with the required quality, “establishing solid foundations for the future implementation of the duct reserve in other constructions”. After completion, the installation of ducts and drainage currently underway on Rua do Volong “also adopted this duct reserve solution”.
The Secretary required members to carefully analyze the experiences acquired in the Rua dos Mercadores pipeline reservation project, as well as in the rapid coordination in response to unforeseen situations, and should also examine, “from the perspective of efficiency”, the integration of the provisions relating to coordination zones and the approval process for works in the vicinity of gas pipelines, with a view to the overall improvement of administrative efficiency.
At the same time, he instructed the Working Group to adopt measures aimed at reducing the number of well covers on public roads to a minimum, with a view to guaranteeing the safety of motorcycle and moped drivers.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mariana Rocha “investigates” the paradoxical status of bamboo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mariana-rocha-investiga-estatuto-paradoxal-bambu/</link><description>Bamboo, considered a pillar of construction, is a theme in focus in the works of Portuguese artist Mariana Maia Rocha, which will be displayed, from December 8th, at Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia. The relevance of the exhibition lies in the critical analysis of accelerated urban transformations and the impact of globalization on local identity



















VÍTOR REBELO
 
“On the Threshold of Memory” is an exhibition that confronts the architecture of transience in the material and spiritual landscape of Macau. The works, designed by Mariana Maia Rocha, will be unveiled at the inauguration ceremony scheduled for December 8th, Monday, at 6:30 pm, at Albergue da Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macau.
The Portuguese artist uses her position as an observer of the diaspora and the experience of an immersive residence in Asian territory to investigate the paradoxical status of bamboo, a pillar of local vernacular construction, which “transitions from the utilitarian and profane to the domain of cultural heritage and the sacred, in the face of its imminent replacement by iron and concrete”, as can be read in the exhibition's introductory manifesto.
The relevance of the exhibition lies in its critical analysis of accelerated urban transformations and the impact of globalization on local identity, a scenario of particular resonance in Macau.
The exhibition is articulated through a juxtaposition of “symbolic materialities” that emphasize the Portuguese-Chinese “duality”. The dust (coal, graphite and ash of local origin) works as the “index of mortality, the fundamental substance of the universal memento mori”, says the Albergue’s statement.
Votive wax, common to Taoist and Catholic rituals, is used to mold ex-votos from the artist's shoes, configuring a procedural line that “metaphorizes the personal journey and the vulnerability of the body”. In addition, an “ephemeral urban intervention” with latex records the texture of the Portuguese sidewalk.
This “second tactile skin”, highlights the same document, “functions as a memory device”, alluding to the scaffolding protection networks and the Portuguese legacy on the verge of extinction, creating a “physical record of the cultural border and the negotiation of urban space”.
The exhibition aims to provide a “powerful dialogue about memory, mortality and the ephemeral structures we build”, says the exhibition’s curator, adding that the artist’s practice “navigates the tension between the permanent and the fleeting, cultural identity and the inevitability of disintegration in a territory of convergence and loss, echoing the complexities of a rapidly changing place”.
Mariana Maia Rocha is a visual artist and researcher whose interdisciplinary practice is part of the intersection between the body, memory and territory. His work, which predominantly integrates drawing, photoperformance and installation, addresses the conceptual and material boundaries of presence and erasure in the contemporary archive.
He has an academic career at the Faculty of Fine Arts of the University of Porto, where he completed his Masters in Fine Arts. She is a fellow at the Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, having been awarded the “Gulbenkian New Talents” Scholarship (2023/2024) and, in 2025, a PhD Scholarship to pursue studies abroad, as a reward for the research carried out last year. In 2023, he participated in the “Mirror Identity Drawings” project, signed by the UNESCO Charter.
The international dimension of his practice materialized during this year, through a program of artistic residencies, in São Tomé and Príncipe, in the context of the XI Bienal de São Tomé, and now in Macau, within the scope of the international program “Territories without Borders” (2025–2026), promoted by the Fundação Bienal de Arte de Cerveira.
Since 2018, his work has been presented in individual and group exhibitions at leading institutions, including the Chiado National Museum of Contemporary Art, in Lisbon, the Vila Flor Palace, in Guimarães, and the Júlio Resende Foundation and the Kubik Gallery, both in Porto.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Meet You There” shares works by two artists</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/meet-there-partilha-obras-de-dois-artistas/</link><description>Local artist Alexandre Marreiros and Indonesian Nyoman Suarnata will exhibit their first work together at Galeria Amagao. “Meet You There” is a creative encounter where visual language becomes an instrument of investigation

























In their first collaboration together, Alexandre Marreiros and Nyoman Suarnata will show, starting today, at Galeria Amagao, 35 works resulting from a fusion of perspectives and styles by two artists from different backgrounds.
“Meet You There” is an exhibition designed to be a “creative encounter”, where visual language becomes an instrument of investigation. Through “overlapping compositions, fragmented symbols and constantly shifting perspectives”, the authors “construct a territory that resists fixed meaning”, according to what can be seen in the exhibition manifesto, whose opening is scheduled for the end of the afternoon, at 6:30 pm.
The two artists, Marreiros, from Macau, and Suarnata, born in Indonesia, invite the public to participate in the “interpretive act, to adjust their lenses and to inhabit the multiplicity of stories that unfold within them”.
In the exhibition's promotional text, Alexandre Marreiros writes that the works reflect “layered compositions, fragmented symbols and changing perspectives, in constant displacement, transforming canvas and paper into a shared space where perception is fluid and the narrative pulses like a living organism”.
The artist adds that “this territory is populated by social, personal and environmental concerns, which metamorphose into characters, symbols and even superheroes”, highlighting that “they are not figures that save, but that reveal”, constituting “incarnations of urgency, empathy and resistance, challenging the viewer to reflect” and ask themselves: “what does it mean to care? Imagine? Act?”.
The exhibition's publicity note concludes that “Meet You There” presents itself as an invitation to participate “in a space where art is not static, but generative; where dialogue is not linear, but stratified; and where imagination is a form of engagement and participation”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reading Festival integrates art and leisure</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festival-da-leitura-integra-arte-lazer/</link><description>Casas da Taipa will host the Reading Festival, which includes a series of activities, including “Open Air Library”, “Night Cinema” and “Café and Cultural and Creative Products Fair”
 
The Reading Festival will take place between tomorrow and Sunday, at Casas da Taipa, announced the Cultural Institute (IC), organizer of the activity. Dedicated to the theme “Fun Reading Holidays”, the event offers a weekend that integrates, in addition to reading, art and leisure.
On the first day, activities take place from 5pm to 10pm, while on Saturday and Sunday they will take place from 3pm to 10pm. An “Open Air Library”, an “Art and Culture Book Fair” and “Night Cinema”, a “Café and Cultural and Creative Products Fair”, shows, a “Relaxing Space”, a “Serenity Corner” and games tents are planned.
According to the IC, two libraries in the Greater Bay Area were invited to set up tents, “promoting exchange and interaction between libraries in Guangdong province and Macau”. Festival photography facilities and a grand raffle will also be available at the venue, incorporating elements from the 15th edition of the National Games, the 12th edition of the National Games for People with Disabilities and the 9th edition of the National Special Olympics Games, with the mascots “Xiyangyang” and “Lerongrong” installed.
The Festival also includes a series of reading activities and therapeutic workshops, including the “Book Traveler” Shared Reading Activity and the “Spiritual Renewal Station” Workshops, creating a “joyful and innovative” reading experience, says the IC. In addition, the “Fairy Tale Character Cosplay Competition for Parents and Children” will be held. Teams of parents and children who register will take the stage to join other “book characters” and compete.
Before the event itself begins, there are already some activities prepared, such as the lecture “Read Alone for Self-Improvement – ​​The Path to Growth as a Life Hacker”, presented by the Science Center. It is scheduled for November 30th. The idea is for the public to discover “the relationship between personal growth and reading”.
“The Heritage of Chinese Classics – Special Exhibition of the Room of Ancient and Rare Chinese Works at the Sir Robert Ho Tung Library in Macau and the Hok Hoi Library in Hong Kong” will also be organized together with public libraries in the neighboring region. Centered on the Sir Robert Ho Tung Library's Room of Ancient and Rare Chinese Works and Hong Kong's Hok Hoi Library, the exhibition highlights the contributions that both libraries have made over the past century to the transmission of classical Chinese studies.
The Festival is organized by the IC, co-organized by the Bureau of Livelihood Affairs of the Deep Cooperation Zone, the Bureau of Education and Youth Development Services, the Institute for Municipal Affairs, the Bureau of Tourism Services and the Science Center, with the support of various organizations, including the Macau Youth Federation, the New Chinese Youth Association of Macau, the Macao General Chong Wa Student Association and the “Macau Youth Development Service Centre”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Bomb threat” simulation tested airport security</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/simulacao-de-ameaca-de-bomba-testou-seguranca-aeroporto/</link><description>Macau International Airport held in the early hours of yesterday, between 2 am and 4 am, a drill coordinated by the Public Security Police Corps (CPSP) which included the participation of various public services and civil aviation operators. The security exercise simulated a bomb threat, to test the effectiveness of contingency plans and the response capacity of personnel from entities participating in air security incidents. In the simulated situation, CPSP personnel found and intercepted an individual with suspicious behavior in the Airport Passenger Terminal. When fleeing, “the man was controlled by police officers and later said that explosives had already been placed at the airport”, says a statement from the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM). After receiving the alert, the Airport Police Division and its security guards blocked the location and began searching, and the airport immediately activated the contingency plan. “After the explosive materials had been destroyed and after the Judiciary Police agents had carried out an inspection of the incident site and verified that there were no other suspicious objects, the incident commander ordered the elimination of the crisis and the elimination of all blockages”, explained the AACM, highlighting that “the entire exercise went well and the expected results were achieved”.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2509/</link><description>Young man detained at the airport with 6.27 kilos of cannabis
An 18-year-old Malaysian man was arrested in Macau on suspicion of drug trafficking from the territory to Hong Kong. The Judicial Police seized 6.27 kilos of cannabis, valued at 6.27 million patacas. The young man was intercepted at Macau Airport on Tuesday night. In a suitcase, the drug was found divided into 12 packages. The suspect admitted to the police that he had received instructions to collect the drugs in Thailand and later bring them to Macau, stopping in the Philippines.
 
Motorcyclist died after collision
The Public Security Police Corps (CPCP) announced the death of a resident motorcyclist, who was injured in a collision with another motorcycle, also owned by a resident, on the Sai Van Bridge, towards Peninsula-Taipa, on the night of 30 November. The victim fell unconscious and was hospitalized, but died on Tuesday night. The police indicated that the cause of the accident is still being investigated, and information has been collected from video surveillance cameras. Police are appealing to potential witnesses to provide information about the case.
 
Shun Tak donated 10 million to fire victims
The Shun Tak group and management members, namely Pansy Ho, Daisy Ho and Maisy Ho, announced the donation of 10 million Hong Kong dollars to the “Wang Fuk Court” Building Support Fund, created by the HKSAR Government, to support citizens affected by the serious fire. The group says it will also fully support employees in participating in rescue aid actions, thus fulfilling the company's social responsibilities at a difficult time.
 
DSOP opens competition for Administration Offices
The Directorate of Public Works Services (DSOP) launched a tender for the “Construction Contract for the Office Building for the Administration on Lot Q-1d of ZAPE – Superstructure Work”. The maximum period for carrying out the work is 650 working days, counting from the date of consignment, and the roof must be completed within 350 days. Proposals must be delivered by 5pm on January 14th, at DSOP headquarters. The public opening of the proposals is scheduled for the morning of the following day. With regard to the assessment criteria, the price of the contract will be worth 50%, the execution time 15% and the experience and quality of works 20%.
 
Drones banned during Paralympic Games
Between December 8th and 15th, drone flights will be prohibited within 50 meters of the Sports Space of the Macau East Asian Games, informed the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM). The measure comes due to the 12th edition of the National Games for People with Disabilities and the 9th edition of the National Special Olympics Games in China. The AACM also asks citizens not to display drones, without written authorization from the organization, in the following locations: Taipa Maritime Terminal, Macau-Taipa Bridge, Wynn Palace, Pousada Marina Infante, England Marina Club Hotel and Marina Phantom Apartment Hotel. The fine to be imposed on those who do not comply with the order may range between 2,000 and 20,000 patacas.
 
Macao SAR will start receiving choy sum and taro from Yongzhou
The Interdepartmental Working Group on Foodstuff Prices visited Yongzhou in Hunan Province to explore new sources of vegetable supply for Macau. The delegation met with government authorities and the local sector, and went to several vegetable plantation bases supplied to Hong Kong and Macau. The group learned about the highly standardized plantation scale, the production process and the transport and logistics system. According to the Economics and Technological Development Services, after studies and negotiations, the sector will initially plan to import species such as “choy sum” and taro to supply the local market, with the first batch of these vegetables expected to arrive in the 1st quarter of next year.</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Film with Brendan Fraser portrays the Japanese business of renting a family</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/filme-brendan-fraser-retrata-negocio-japones-de-alugar-uma-familia/</link><description>Hiring a friend, relative or guest for a wedding is a very common service in Japan, a country where almost 40% of the population admits to feeling some degree of loneliness. This phenomenon has now reached the cinema with “Rental Family”, a film starring Brendan Fraser, an Oscar-winning actor.
Directed by Japanese filmmaker Mitsuyo Miyazaki, better known as Hikari, the film seeks to reflect the reality of this relatively common practice in her home country. “This business has existed in Japan since the 1980s, but people weren't aware of it,” explained the filmmaker to the North American magazine “Variety” during the film's presentation at the Toronto International Film Festival.
The film follows the life of Philip Vanderplug, played by Brendan Fraser, a foreigner who arrives in Tokyo looking for work as an actor and becomes involved in the industry of so-called “rental families”, where he has to pose as various relatives or friends to his clients.
Filmed in the Japanese capital, the film aims to show, as its director explained to the press, “the beauty of the chosen family”. O isolamento está a manifestar-se de todas as formas no arquipélago, onde 39,9% da população confessa sentir-se sozinha, segundo dados do Ministério da Saúde, Trabalho e Bem-Estar divulgados este ano.
More than half of those surveyed also stated that they do not participate in any specific social activity. This increase in social isolation is a cause for concern in Japan, where there is even a ministry dedicated to these issues.
The country already has record numbers of single-person households, which could become the most common type of housing by 2040, reaching almost 40% of the market, according to data from Japan's National Population and Social Security Research Institute.
The need for company is so great that some people hire these rental services simply to have someone to keep them company on a daily basis. This is the case of Shoji Morimoto, hired to “do nothing”, as he describes it.
“It’s about going to the indicated place, sitting down, eating what they bring me, listening and simply responding”, explained Morimoto at a press conference about his book “A Pessoa de Aluguel Que Não Faz Nada”, published in 2019, which brings together stories from his more than seven years of service.
In fact, Morimoto added that he only accepts requests where he can simply sit back and let others make the decisions. Simple tasks have prices that vary between 10,000 and 30,000 yen (approximately between 514 and 1,540 patacas), depending on the artist's mood that day.
“If I want more free time, if it's cold in winter and I don't want to leave the house, then I increase prices”, explained the Japanese artist, comparing his method of setting prices to techniques used in the hotel or aviation sectors, where prices vary depending on the season or weather conditions.
“We’ve all felt the desire to be part of something and we’ve had our nose pressed against the glass, trying to get in,” explained Fraser, during his participation at the Toronto International Film Festival. The actor sees this work as an unusual way of satisfying people's needs, and his only antagonist is the “apathy” of not understanding that, sometimes, doing nothing is what someone needs to not feel alone.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-12-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>