<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Subsidies approval enables plans of Portuguese matrix associations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/aprovacao-de-subsidios-viabiliza-planos-das-associacoes-de-matriz-portuguesa/</link><description>用色大膽的建築



In the opinion of the leaders of the Portuguese matrix associations, the subsidies attributed by the Macau Foundation are considered satisfactory and will allow, in general, all the activities scheduled for this year to be performed. Although the amounts were a little short of what was requested, "they will enable virtually everything to be done," he told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau Amelia António. "It was a little better than last year," said António Monteiro, while Miguel de Senna Fernandes emphasizes that the budget for the São João Arraial "is Magro", but the event "will be organized". Jorge Fão manifests himself equally satisfied with the approval of the supports, "fundamentally to pay employees." Meanwhile, there are organisms that dispense with subsidies, or gave up asking them
 
Victor Rebelo
 
All Lusa matrix associations contacted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao consider that the assignment of subsidies by the Macau Foundation (FM) corresponded generally to the expectations created. Although the requested amounts do not cover the total of the proposals presented -a situation that has happened annually, but already expected by the associative leaders -consider that the values ​​granted will allow programmed events to be held.
"With more or less money, the important thing is that all the activities we thought will be done," he began to refer to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau Amélia António, for whom "the concession of all intended subsidies is a sign of the recognition of work and the quality of what we have been doing."
The president of the House of Portugal says that the foundation now has "a kind of uniform criterion for certain activities, especially the exhibitions, with a more or less equal amount for all this."
The housekeeper states that, from now on, the events for which the association awaits the implementation of subsidies will begin to be organized, through the supports that exist. "We, in principle, carry out all that we schedule, as long as we have subsidies attributed," he says, adding that "the way to do them is that it can vary because of the amounts we have, and there is a need to proceed, in some cases, to certain adaptations."
Also António Monteiro, president of the Association of Young Macanese (AJM), was pleased with the subsidies granted to all scheduled programs, considering that "they were even a little better than last year."
In turn, Miguel de Senna Fernandes, president of the Macanese Association (ADM), speaks of general satisfaction for approval, without, however, “being so pleased by the attributed amounts”. Nonetheless, he says, "the supports cover the main activities," one of which is the São João village. About this popular party, the leader of ADM considers that "the budget is thin and a shadow of what would be fundamental," but the organization will still be assured "in the same way as last year in the Macao Tower."
Jorge Fão, President of the General Assembly of the Macao Retired, Reformed and Pensioners Association (Apomac), confirmed the approval of the monetary supports requested from the Foundation for most activities. "With the exception of some projects, of small importance, the rest had authorized subsidies, especially for what is necessary for the current expenses of operation, payment to employees and holding the annual events, such as the tours we usually organize," he says.
Regarding other needs, Jorge Fão regrets that FM has previously been negatively answered a request for financial support for the execution of processing works at the body's headquarters. "This is quite urgent and I will insist on an additional request, eventually even addressed to the Chief Executive itself," he says.
Knowing that the Foundation “has no rubrics to assign subsidies for this type of expenses”, Jorge Fão will ask the government to indicate which entity is most appropriate for this.
The installation where the clinic was located, some years ended for lack of financial support, should serve to organize lectures.
"Our request for subsidy for the works has its reason for being, on top of that because we have given a good part of the space as access so that the residents of that building could use our elevator," he expresses, adding that "the people who live in that building, who can, from now on, go down and go to the street through one of Apomac."
 
Coming from musician Paulo Soares is still uncertain project
Unlike Apomac, which has a lower flow of activities, Casa de Portugal has been developing diverse projects for several years. For 2025, and now that the subsidies were all approved, the association will seek reality everything that advocated, giving special focus to the exhibitions, to which it regularly invites people abroad, as well as other events, such as the Feast of St. Anthony.
“We have funds to stand once again this popular tradition, all pointing to the chosen place to be the Portuguese school in June,” says Amelia António.
On the other hand, and in addition to collaborations in the São João village and the Lusofonia Festival, as well as in the “June, Portugal month” - to which some of the program points have already begun - the Casa de Portugal intends to bring Paulo Soares to the territory, considered one of the most versatile guitarists in the Portuguese guitar panorama.
The musician's coming is (or was) initially foreseen in April, “but we still have no response to a request for subsidy of the Directorate-General for Consular Affairs and Portuguese Communities, since this type of support by Macao belongs to the Culture Development Fund, where we address the request, however denied,” explains Amelia António.
The purpose of this initiative is to mark the 100th anniversary of the birth of guitarist Carlos Paredes, who died in 2004. “We are already much on the date we wanted to perform the show, so it will probably have to be later, which implies more difficulties, such as the availability of the artist, who will be accompanied by another element, and the space where it will take place,” says the leader.
 
“Caretos” exhibition at the International Parade
While waiting for the achievement of this project, Casa de Portugal is currently committed to preparations for the Macao International Parade that will take place on March 23.
The association will have a representation of about 20 to 30 elements and the theme is the “faces”, consisting of masked characters of the Carnival of Trás-os-Montes and Alto Douro, Portugal, highlighting power. Este género de bonecos misteriosos será acompanhado por tambores e música ao vivo.
Amelia António makes a point of saying that all the “faces”, one of which giant, were produced locally by the School of Arts and Crafts. "The figures are naturally adapted to the culture of Macao, but while noting the Portuguese tradition," he says, praising the "tireless" work of people who do this kind of productions and other activities, "often with great difficulty in developing their works."
The leader regrets that he has not yet achieved another, more central place, for the school's work. "The situation was no longer famous, but now it's hell," he admits. "Those installations in the black sand are out of hand and people have difficulty, in access and lack of parking, to leave their children to the events we organize," he lamented.
Meanwhile, there are two associations linked to Macanese culture that do not need FM subsidies. They are the Brotherhood of Macanese Gastronomy and the Macaense Culture Studies Association (Macra).
Carlos Anok, president of the Brotherhood, told JTM that he gave up requesting support from the Macau Foundation. "We are not contemplated, because we only have people working voluntarily, hence, according to regulations, they cannot be paid." Therefore, “we gave up asking for subsidies,” he says.
About Macra, its main responsible, Elisabela Larrea, justifies with the fact that the association is relatively new. “We would like to learn first to do things step by step,” he explains.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Platforms accused of taking half of profit from restaurants</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/plataformas-acusadas-de-tirar-metade-lucro-aos-restaurantes/</link><description>The president of the Macao Restoration Industry Association “rocked” food delivery platforms in the territory, due to the absorption of “40% to 50%” of the profits of employee restaurants through the charge of commissions and other types of tariffs, as well as the “double charge” at delivery fees. Leong Leong appealed to the government to intervene, with policies, due to the “unfair market environment”
 
Almost nine years after the emergence, at MSAR, from food delivery platforms, the commissions charged by the platforms to employee restaurants rose from 18% of the price of each food order to “40% to 50%” of gross restaurants of restaurants. This, after the addition of other tariffs charged by the platforms, according to Law Iam Leong, president of the Macao Restoration Industry Association.
In a context marked by a “weak economy” and the “high value” of commissions, small and medium -sized restoration (SMEs) of the restoration sector “have suffered a lot”, lamented the associative leader, noting that, under the free market principle, many restoration establishments suffered from breach of business and eventually declared bankruptcy.
Quoted by the newspaper “or Mun”, Leong Leong also criticized food delivery platforms for “installing restaurants to participate in discount activities”, “using SME profits as a competitive capital”, which fostered an “unfair” operational environment.
As a result, some restaurants have chosen to offer 20% discounts to customers who move to the place to pick up the food, the associative leader noted. It has also revealed that in recent years they have opened “many small food stores” in industrial buildings or business centers to abandon, supporting relatively low incomes and thus able to participate in the respective “extreme promotional activities” of the platforms.
On the other hand, Leong Leong criticized the platforms for the “double charge” at delivery fees. According to it, "platforms first charge a delivery fee that is usually 20% of the price of each food order and then charge the same fee with consumers again." "If the merchant is available to give consumers discounts on delivery fees, they can occupy a better position in the ranking on the platforms," ​​he said.
For the president of the Restoration Industry Association, the sector "can no longer see a future." To reverse this scenario, Law AI Leong expects the government to launch policies to "intervene in the unfair market environment." Otherwise, he warned that the restoration SMEs "would have to sacrifice."</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vowel at ANP proposes Sino-Lusophone Universities in Hengqin</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vogal-na-anp-propoe-universidades-sino-lusofonas-em-hengqin/</link><description>In the farewell of the ANP session, Dominic Sio, representative of MSAR at the legislature, made another suggestion related to Lusophony. In order to deepen the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone, the vowel considers that the Chinese Ministry of Education can support China and Lusophone countries to jointly open higher education institutions in Hengqin
 
On the last day of the 3rd session of the 14th National Popular Assembly (ANP), Dominic Sio, Macao representative at ANP, delivered another proposal. He suggested to the Ministry of Education Chinese to support the opening of higher education institutions in the deepened cooperation zone, in a cooperation between China and Portuguese -speaking countries.
According to the Chinese language press, Dominic Sio argued that the formation and concentration of more paintings with “international vision” and “affection for local territory” corresponds to “urgent needs” to deepen the construction of the in -depth cooperation zone. In this sense, it emphasized that the solution to attract higher education institutions in the interior of China, Macao and Lusophone countries, as well as high levels to develop an “effective cooperation” in Hengqin can not only add more high -level frames corresponding to development needs, but also boost the internationalization of higher education in the cooperation zone. At the same time, he will make Hengqin a stronger role in exchange and cooperation between China and Lusophone countries.
Specifically, Dominic Sio proposed that hengqin captive courses and teachers in Portugal and Brazil through the advantages of the island at the level of fiscal policies and staff, to create an “Institute of Research under sino-illusion cooperation”, committed to developing international industry-in-coating cooperation.
In addition, it suggested the conception of a “laboratory or sino-sirophono setting center”, focused on agriculture, energy, marine sciences, among other domains, in order to promote the incubation and transformation of the scientific and technological fruits of Lusophone countries, also giving impetus to innovation and development of hengqin.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao will help China develop roller hockey</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-vai-ajudar-china-desenvolver-hoquei-em-patins/</link><description>The Macao Skating Association will sign cooperation agreements with some China provinces to develop roller hockey. The modality needs greater impetus on the continent and the MSAR can take on an important role in its disclosure, namely with technical support. In the exchange of collaboration, Macau can benefit from Chinese aid in "Skateboarding" and "Inline Free Style". The association was first invited to attend the Biennial Meeting of the China Skating Federation and had the opportunity to “start contacts for future partnerships,” the Tribuna de Macai newspaper António Aguiar told the newspaper Tribuna de Macao newspaper

Victor Rebelo
 
Macau roller hockey will be able to contribute to the development of the modality on the continent, having maintained contacts in this regard at the Biennial meeting of the China Skating Federation, which brought together the various provinces of the country. Throughout the work, for which the MSAR was first invited, the leaders of the Macao Skating Association (APM), António Aguiar (President) and Sónia Silva (secretary), who are also members of the “World Skate”, respectively for roller hockey and the “Inline”, were available to help boost Chinese skates hockey.
In this sense, during the two days of work in Shunde, area of ​​Foshan district, Guangdong Province, representatives of the territory promoted various contacts and negotiations with Chinese counterparts, in view of signing, in a brief stretch, of collaboration agreements, in addition to visiting sports facilities.
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, António Aguiar said the intention of partnerships serves both sides, that is, “Macau offers the strongest, which is roller hockey, and China helps us increase and reinforce modalities in which they are very strong, concretely‘ skateboarding ’and‘ Inline Free Style ’”.
The leader, who is also a member of the International Roller Hockey Committee, responsible for the mode in Asia-Oceania, stresses that the idea is also to “have regional competitions” involving several cities in the interior of China, Macao and Hong Kong.
Macau's skating has maintained collaboration mainly with a short, but intends to extend to other places in the province, as well as reinforce existing agreements. In addition to Guangdong, partnerships were previously established with Shandong, Hebei and Heilongjiang, as well as the Beijing Zone, "which is important," says Aguiar, highlighting the goal of "reinforcing these agreements and signing others."
According to APM number one, the first major realization will be Macau's participation in the co-organization of national skating championships in August, with the sports distributed throughout China cities.
In 2024 skates hockey was not integrated and now APM does “much” that the sport is present in those championships.
Macau applied to be the stage of the race, but it is not possible to have a national competition outside the continent. Thus, the association of the territory is available to organize the tournament in a city near the masters. “Zhuhai, for example, is a possibility that we are discussing, since they involve funds that obviously have to be sponsored, and there are also other places like Shunde,” says António Aguiar.
In addition, Macau intends to organize a championship, perhaps in 2026 or 2027, with Grand Bay formations. "This is being thought out for when there is team stability, four or five," says the manager of the territory skating.
 
Support exchange for hockey and skate
At this time, skateboarding is the most expanding skating in the interior of China, mainly because it is an Olympic sport, with many high -level athletes.
Already roller hockey needs to develop, with only four regions where it is practiced. "We want to widen the more provinces, but for this to be a reality, sponsors are required to finance the development of the sport, entering us with technical support," says the president of APM.
Macao currently has about half a thousand practitioners in traditional hockey and in line hockey, including skating schools, and in the first sport there are 200 athletes.
Regarding roller hockey, the selections will play the sports with Guangdong probably in October or November this year, but in the next Easter period, between April 17 and 20, the men's and female senior teams and the U19 boys, will participate in the Taichung, Taiwan tournament. This competition will be prepared for the Asian Championship, scheduled for South Korea, from 20 to 30 June.
At this time, the Macao Roller Hockey Championship, in three categories, male and female and under-16, with the participation of three teams: Lusitânia Sport Club, FC Porto and Vitória Clube.
In skateboarding there are only three or four athletes able to compete, with a club registered with APM and another who requested affiliation. In the discipline of speed, at this time there is no activity, since “there is difficulty in training on the street and Macao there is no specific place for it,” laments António Aguiar.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>PR hears parties with elections on the nearby horizon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/pr-ouve-partidos-eleicoes-horizonte-proximo/</link><description>EPA11958305 Portugal's President, Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa (R), Speaks with delegation from the Portuguese Socialist Party (PS), Led by Secretary General Pedro Nuno Santos (C), During a Meeting at The Belem Palace in Lisbon, Portugal, 12 March 2025. The President of Portugal Will to the Political Parties With Parliamentary Seats at the Belem Palace on Wednesday to Discuss The Political Crisis and the Scenario of Snap Elections.  EPA/ANTONIO COTRIM



Following the lead to the government's confidence motion (see page 8), the Portuguese president yesterday received political parties with parliamentary seat at the Belém Palace to discuss the political crisis and the scenario of early legislatures. Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa had signaled that if the confidence motion was rejected causing the government to fall, the “electoral calendar” would point to mid -May.
The president, who also called the Council of State for today, never explicitly referred to the anticipation of the legislatures, but after having dissolved the Assembly of the Republic about a year ago, after the dismissal of the previous Prime Minister, António Costa, following the influencer process, let him choose to choose the same solution again.
At the departure of the hearing with the head of state, the president of the PSD and prime minister argued that the solution to the political crisis involves the holding of early elections “as soon as possible”. “We should not anticipate the decision of the President of the Republic, but opening the possibility that there is a dissolution of the Assembly of the Republic and calling elections, we believe that there are all conditions for them to be held precisely on one of these two dates, or May 18. But there are all the conditions to be 11, ”said Luís Montenegro about the electoral calendar.
In turn, the PS secretary-general considered that early elections are “the only way” to clarify the political situation in Portugal and that “as soon as possible” should happen. Pedro Nuno Santos said he waited for the decision of the head of state and stressed that the elections were not the scenario "desirable to anyone."
 
PGR opens preventive inquiry on Montenegro and Spinumviva
The Public Prosecution Service opened a preventive investigation related to the Prime Minister and the company Spinumviva, from the family of Luís Montenegro, the Attorney General of the Republic announced yesterday. Amadeu Guerra explained that three complaints related to Spinumviva were received. "Of the elements we have collected so far, there is no foundation to open any inquiry," said the Attorney General, adding that, precisely due to the lack of elements, it was decided to open a preventive investigation.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dismantled “agency” of illegal medicines</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/desmantelada-agencia-de-medicamentos-ilegais/</link><description>Authorities seized 500 boxes of drugs that had not been registered and approved for imports. The discovery was made at a commercial agency in the siege gates, and the offender can be punished with a fine of up to 700,000 patacas. In case of aggravated circumstances, may assume criminal liability
 
The Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (ISAF) and customs services (SA) seized, in a joint action, more than 500 boxes of antiviral drugs for hepatitis B and hypoglycemic injections “that had not been registered and approved for imports”. The discovery was made at a commercial agency in the siege gates.
"The store was involved in supplying drugs without license and illegal importation of medicines," says the Isaf in a statement. The institute thus opened a process for investigation under the law, and the SAs proceeded to the prosecution against the store official regarding the violation of the provisions of product imports.
According to the note, the offender in question may be punished with a fine of up to 700,000 patacas and, to serious circumstances, may assume criminal liability. In accordance with the legislation in force regarding pharmaceutical activities, only license -granted establishments may provide medicines. In addition, the importation of medicines is also subject to prior authorization and import license granted by that institute.
Ensuring that it continues to collect information through and different channels, the Isaf has appealed to residents that they find establishments suspected of the exercise of illegal pharmaceutical activities to contact the ISAF licensing and inspection department. The complaint can be made by telephone (8598 3522), email ([email protected]) or through the institute's electronic page (www.isaf.gov.mo).
 
UPDATED STANDARDS FOR MEDICINAL PRODUCTION
However, ISAF recently organized three sessions to present “GCP's Good Clinical Practice” and “Good Sterile Medicines Manufacturing Practices” to be implemented on March 30. In the presence of representatives of medical and higher education institutions, trade associations and the pharmaceutical sector, Choi Peng Cheong, president of Isaf, detailed the basic requirements for CLINICAL DRIVERY TRAINS, FROM THE CONCEPTION TO IMPLEMENTATION.
The main objectives of GCP are to regularize clinical trials, protecting rights and ensuring the safety of the subjects, crediting science and increasing the international recognition of Macao in the field of drug investigation, according to the statement. Choi highlighted the active role of the government in the development of Big Health, through “continuous improvement and the elaboration of regulation for the pharmaceutical sector, promoting and guiding the healthy and orderly development of industry”.
In turn, NG Kuok Leong, vice president of the Institute, encouraged local drugs factories “constantly raising the level of production management and quality control” at the GMP, and “preparing well for the construction of their own capacity”, articulating with the strategy “1+4”. According to the statement, Isaf aims to give “technical guidance and necessary support” to manufacturers, during the transient period of five years, so that they meet the requirements of the new rules.
The vice president also hopes that MSAR drug factories reinforce its competitiveness in the interior of China and in international markets.
The ISAF intends that the rules encourage local industry to approach international standards. The GCP were prepared with reference to the guidelines of the International Council for Harmonization of Technical Requirements for Pharmaceutical Products for Human Use. The GMP were elaborated based on the standards of the World Health Organization.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Influenza and covid-19 stabilize cases</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/casos-de-gripe-covid-19-estabilizaram/</link><description>The situation of influenza and Covid is generally stable, with no serious cases, the health services reported. The body associated the decrease of influenza cases to rise in temperatures and increased inoculation rate
 
Recently, the covid-19 detection rate has reached about 16% of total breathing symptom samples, which reflects an increase tendency, Alvis Lo, Director of Health Services (SSM). On the contrary, the number of influenza infection cases has dropped, with the respective detection rate of 3% to 4%.
Although a tendency to increase COVID-19 cases have been registered, the official assured that, in general, the situation of the two diseases has been stable in the territory. In addition, recent cases have not involved serious symptoms.
According to the Chinese language press, Alvis Lo considered that the decrease in influenza cases is due to the rise in temperature and increased vaccination rate.
Regarding the flu, Alvis Lo stated that about 230,000 residents have already taken the vaccine, which contributes to “the constitution of a better prevention barrier in the community”. He said, currently there are still about 200 people inoculated a day. In total, the authorities acquired 245,000 doses of seasonal flu vaccine between 2024 and 2025.
Given the current epidemiological context, the SSM director called on citizens to wear masks if respiratory symptoms and to pay attention to personal hygiene. He also said he hoped that the elderly and people with chronic diseases will be regularly vaccinated against the flu to reinforce physical protection.
The SSM were recently notified for two cases of Covid-19 collective infection at the Nations School, which involved four students, and in the Chinese section of the Santa Rosa de Lima College (five students). In schools Cham Son and Secondary Pui Tou (Taipa) reported two cases of collective flu infection, involving four students each.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Boss planted tree on the track of the small mud</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-plantou-arvore-trilho-da-taipa-pequena/</link><description>The chief executive yesterday planted a "Machilus Chinensis" on the Taipa Small 2000 track on the occasion of the "National Tree Planting Day of China". The objective was “to promote the appreciation for vegetation, the planting of trees and the conservation of green spaces and, together with the population of Macao, to respect nature, contributing to their protection and to a coexistence in harmony”. At the same time, Sam Hou Fai inaugurated a sculpted tombstone with the inscription “from the same root the leafy branches sprout, from the same marrow grow the concentric circles”, which, according to an official note, “means that the homeland and macao have the roots and common origin, remaining in an intimate relationship, progress and prosper together, tracing China's concentric circles”. All heads of the Executive of the MSarbors planted a "Machilus Chinensis", native species of Macau, from the Lauracea family, in the "celebrity planting zone." Sam Hou Fai was accompanied, among others, by the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CC promises to “review and adjust” goods targeting price investigation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cc-promete-rever-ajustar-bens-alvo-de-investigacao-de-precos/</link><description>“Due to market change and consumer needs,” the Consumer Council will “review and adjust” the types and quantity of pricing assets and quantity
 
The Consumer Council (CC) regularly collects and disseminates retail prices of various food and first -rate goods, in order to “increase price transparency”. Without detailing a specific calendar, the body now said that products whose price is analyzed will be adjusted.
"The CC will review and adjust, in a timely manner and due to the change of the market and consumer needs, the species and the amount of goods that are priced research objects," said the director of Economics and Technological Development Services (DSEDT), Yau Yun Wah, in response to a question by José Pereira Coutinho.
The deputy had shown concern about the eventual increase in price, due, for example, to droughts and heavy rains, which impair food production worldwide. "The increase in the price of food goods will affect, above all, workers with smaller salaries (…) The sinhelms hardly produces food goods, it only matters, and it is important to implement measures, naturally coordinated with the interior of the continent, to ensure the stability of the prices of food goods," he said.
In the replica, it is also said that the CC will “continually optimize the means of disclosure of pricing information, in order to allow the consumer to perform directly a simple consultation of useful price and promotion information, to make a better consumer option according to their own needs”.
Yau Yun Wah also indicated that the Interdepartal Working Group for the prices of food products composed by DSEDT, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) and CC continues to maintain contacts with business sectors, to monitor fresh and living food price variations for sale in the market. This is to “move forward with work in various aspects, namely exploration of supply channels, increased points of sale online straight and raising price transparency”.
On the other hand, DSEDT ensures that it continues to oversee the situation of supply of main cereals and secondary foods, periodically performing surveys to suppliers and retailers. "The Government of MSAR also strives to encourage business sectors to largely exploit supply channels and introduce a variety of food types of different sources and markets to reduce dependence on a single source," he adds in response to Pereira Coutinho.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>ID looking for a suitable location for ice rink</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/id-procura-local-adequado-para-pista-de-gelo/</link><description>The creation of a place with the conditions for the practice of ice sports is part of the government's plans and the viability of building the venue "continues to be studied, in order to support the continuous development of ice sport."
In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Sun Lok, the president of the Institute of Sport (ID), Luís Gomes, states that, “in order to promote the development of this type of modalities, ID has maintained narrow communications with the General Association of Sports on Macao Ice and continued to invest resources to promote the respective modality”.
Among the actions developed in this field, ID stresses the recruitment of professional coaches and providing financial and technical support to athletes to participate in the events.
In addition, the body ensures that it has supported, through the Sport Fund, the athletes of the Teams of the Artistic Skating and Ice Hockey in internships in the neighboring cities of the interior of China, lasting between four and six days a week.
In the same response to the member of the Legislative Assembly, the ID ensures that it verifies “continuously the viability of opening more sports spaces in the existing facilities, seeking to perform studies and integration of spaces that are able to modify to host various modalities”.
Citing the direction of soil services and urban construction, ID indicates that within the planning of that body, the Macao Special Administrative Region Plan (2020-2040) provides for the maintenance and optimization of large existing recreational and sports facilities.
It is also planned to create new facilities directed to the generality of the population of Macao, with a view to increasing the offer of covered and outdoor sports facilities.
The multiple use of spaces was also proposed, namely the integration of these facilities into large housing complexes.
For example, the A9 Lot of Zone A of the new landfills, intended for recreational and sports facilities, had its plant of urban conditions issued a few years ago, and the respective construction works began. Lots B3 and C1 are also intended for soils for recreational and sports equipment, totaling an area of ​​approximately 34,000 square meters.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Suggested more wide screening for children's vision</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sugerido-rastreio-mais-alargado-a-visao-das-criancas/</link><description>Chan Peng Peng, a subdirector of the Macao's institution of institution, said he became aware, along with “many residents and parents”, the “serious myopia problem among primary students”, warning that children have difficulty describing the cloudy vision situation due to insufficient significant capacity and limited knowledge of eye problems. Quoting the database of Macao children, the associative leader warned that the prevalence rate of low visual acuity of students in the first year of primary education was 28.8% in the school year 2020/2021 and “has risen continuously”. Pointing out that the government annually sends health professionals to schools, in order to perform vision exams with students of the 1st year of primary education and forward abnormal cases to health centers or specialized outpatient services, Chan Peng Peng appealed to launch an annual screening plan for the vision of students who cover every year of primary education. In addition, he suggested to the government to cooperate with more private medical institutions to launch follow -up exam services. On the other hand, the subdirector of the Povo Alliance expects the authorities to implement an electronic file system on vision, through which they can periodically analyze the data regarding student vision in Macao and find out the tendency to change student vision. For the associative leader, you also need to create an open line and an online platform to make it easier to consult vision exam results and eye protection information.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing credit rose 31% in January after three consecutive breaks</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-a-habitacao-subiu-31-em-janeiro-apos-tres-quebras-consecutivas/</link><description>The value of new mortgage loans for housing approved by Macau banks ascended to 1.33 billion Patacas in January, translating up 31.4% and 11.1% monthly and annually, respectively, and interrupting a series of three consecutive monthly breaks, the Monetary Authority (AMCM) revealed. These loans had retreated 57% in October, 5.3% in November and 17.9% in December. The loans granted to residents represented 97.3% of the total in January. Between November and January, the monthly average of new mortgage loans for housing increased by 0.8% to 1.19 billion of patacas compared to the previous period (October to December). According to AMCM data, at the end of January, the debt ratio unpaid on housing credit, which involves delays of more than three months in interest and or capital payments, rose 0.1 points to 3.6%, compared to the previous month, and 2.7 percentage points in annual variation.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2358/</link><description>Chan Un Tong replaces Wong Chi Hong at Dsal
Chan Un Tong was appointed, in a service committee, by the Secretary for Economics and Finance to hold the position of Director of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL). The appointment, published yesterday in an official bulletin, has effects from March 18 and for a period of one year. Chan Un Tong, who has been a subdirector of the body so far, has entered the civil service in 2002, and now replaces Wong Chi Hong, which has been in office since 2012. Chan Tze Wai was named to hold, also on the position of subdirector of Dsal, for the same period. It has been since 2021 as a subdirector of economics and technological development services.
 
Delegate Coordinator of the MP retires this month
Kuok Kin Hong, coordinator of the Public Prosecution Service (MP), will voluntarily retire, from March 19th. Prosecutor, Chan Tsz King, made a praise and recognition of Kuok Kin Hong, “to whom they have filed the inquiry and intervention in a high-relief trial hearing”. In the career of more than 20 years, “fulfilled functions with professionalism in the legal area, meticulous and responsible attitude, diligent by the work of the MP”, can read, in an official bulletin. It also adds that Kuok made “contributions relevant to the formative work of local magistrates and jurists, for which he achieved great respect and recognition with the colleagues of the judicial and legal sector”.
 
Sold almost 100 economic fractions in the first week
A total of 98 fractions were sold in the first week of acquisition, under the 2019 Economic Housing Competition, the Housing Institute said. Most families, 65, chose units with three divisions. The fractions available in this contest are located in the Tong Seng building (lot B4), in the Tong Chong building (lot B9) and Tong Kai building (lot B10), in zone A of new landfills. They are, in total, 3,017 fractions. Note that in this contest, 2,993 selected acquirers met the requirements.
 
16 cases of arbitration involved 200 thousand patacas
The Macao Consumer Conflict Mediation and Arbitration Center opened 16 cases last year, which involved about 200,000 patacas. The balance was made by the President of the Executive Board, to Weng Tong, at this year's first ordinary meeting of the Center's new Board of Directors. Also presented optimization measures and the plan for digitizing the formalities related to the center services to 2025.
 
IC about to open registrations for music contest
The Cultural Institute (IC) is organizing the 43rd Macau Musicians Contest (CJMM), in the piano category, to be held between July 19 and 31. The IC will open the registration from March 27 to April 2. To apply, candidates must access the CJMM Electronic page (www.icm.gov.mo/cjmm), through the single account. The IC will make available a face -to -face consultation service at its headquarters at Tap Seac Square.
 
SAFP releases new version of the single account
Administration and Public Function (SAFP) services will launch today's 5.9.0 version of the single account. SAFP appeal to citizens to update mobile application before using electronic services. This update aims to “increase the stability of functionality and the safety of the single account,” according to the statement. Update only requires facial recognition for identity confirmation.
 
Programmed Health Accreditation Examination
The Council of Health Professionals (CPS) will hold the 4th edition of the Exam for Accreditation for 15 categories of health professionals, intended for graduates and finalists of courses in the area. Interested parties can consult the form of the exam as well as the necessary documentation for the application on the CPS Electronic page (www.cps.gov.mo). On March 29, CPS and Youth Education and Development Services will organize an exam presentation session at the Hippadrom neighborhood Youth Center.</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Marine ice coverage records record record in February</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/cobertura-de-gelo-marinho-regista-queda-recorde-em-fevereiro/</link><description>Marine ice world coverage registered a minimum historical index in February, the European Climate Observatory Copernicus announced, with temperatures up to 11 ° C above average near the North Pole, while the world continues with its persistent heat wave.
Global marine ice - the ocean water that freezes and floats on the surface - reached a record minimum extension of 16.04 million square kilometers to February 7, which was the hottest February ever recorded, according to data from the European monitoring service.
"February 2025 continues the series of record or nearly record temperatures, observed in the last two years," said Samantha Burgess of the European Center for Medium -term weather forecasts, which manages the copernicus climate monitor.
"One of the consequences of a warmer world is the melting of marine ice, and the record or almost marine ice coverage on both poles has led to the global marine ice to a historic low," he added.
Reducing ice coverage has serious impacts over time on weather, people and ecosystems, not just in the region, but globally. As snow and ice give their surface to the dark blue ocean, the same amount of solar energy that was once reflected back to space is now absorbed by water, accelerating the global warming rate.
Antarctic marine ice, which at this time of year, largely determines the global amount, was 26% below average in February, according to Copernicus.
The European service stated that the region may have reached the annual summer minimum at the end of the month, adding that if confirmed in March, this would be the second smallest minimum in the satellite record.
In the Arctic, where marine ice coverage usually reaches the annual winter maximum in March, minimums monthly records have been registered since December, with the marine ice coverage of February 8% below monthly average.
"The current low record extension of global marine ice revealed by the analysis of copernicus is a source of serious concern because it reflects major changes in both Arctic and Antarctic," said Simon Josey, professor of oceanography at the National Oceanography Center of the United Kingdom that added that warm ocean and atmosphere temperatures "can lead to an extensive flaw in the regeneration of ice" in Antarctica during the winter of the winter Southern Hemisphere.
At the international level, February was 1.59ºC warmer than in the pre-industrial period, according to Copernicus, adding that the period from December to February was the second warmest ever recorded.
Although temperatures were below average last month in parts of North America, Eastern Europe and large areas of East Asia, they were warmer than the average in northern Chile and Argentina, western Australia and southwest US and Mexico.
Temperatures were particularly high north of the Arctic Polar Circle, added copernicus, with average temperatures 4 ° C above the 1991-2020 average for the month, and an area near the north pole reached 11 ° C above average.
Sea surface temperatures were exceptionally high in 2023 and 2024. According to Copernicus, February readings were the second highest ever recorded for that month.
Climate scientists hoped that the exceptionally warm period around the world would decrease after the peak of the El Niño event in January 2024 and the conditions gradually moved to a phase of cooling of the La Niña phenomenon. However, heat has persisted at record levels or almost records since then, generating debate among scientists.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-03-13 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>