<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>September legislative elections with “very important meaning”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/eleicoes-legislativas-de-setembro-significado-muito-importante/</link><description>The elections for the Legislative Assembly are scheduled for September 14. The president of Caeal said yesterday that this electoral act has a "very important meaning", since it is the first with the new electoral law in force, which aims "a better implementation of the" Macao Macau ruled by patriots "principle. They are also the first legislatures after the disqualification of candidates, in 2021. On the other hand, the limit amount for the expenses of each application has already been settled
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The elections for the Legislative Assembly (AL) will take place on September 14, defined the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, in an order published yesterday in an official bulletin. In another order, the expense limit for each application, 3,549,622 patacas, was set, the same amount as in the scrutiny of four years ago.
It should be noted that these will be the first legislative elections after the disqualification of candidates, including pro-democracy deputies in 2021, and now under the new electoral law, which was reviewed due to the “new challenges in the national security”, and in view of “a better implementation of the 'Macao ruled by patriots' principle”. This was the chairman of the Electoral Affairs Committee of the Legislative Assembly yesterday.
Underlining that the review of the law aimed to improve the mechanism of verification of the qualifications of candidates for al “to implement well the principle of Macau ruled by patriots,” Seng Ioi Man added that “the defense mechanism of national security and the execution mechanism was also perfected”. It also reinforced the legal provisions regarding illegal conduct and improved electoral procedures, added to journalists after a meeting.
Given that the 2025 elections will be the first after the new law's entry into force, Seng Ioi Man said that "they have a very important meaning." “At the level of execution, the elections will strictly comply with the principle of 'Macau ruled by patriots' and electoral work will be implemented in accordance with the rules to take place with high quality. Electoral work will allow a fairer, impartial and more whole environment, ”he said.
Regarding the verification of the qualification of the candidates, he recalled that the cases will be analyzed by the State of the State Defense Commission. “In the last elections, there was no this rule. Caeal will coordinate this work with the Commission to implement the law well, ”he reiterated, noting that the candidates involved are prohibited from litigation.
The president of Caeal also argued that “voters' participation is also very important”, so several works will be performed to sensitize the public for the duty to vote. The total number of people qualified to vote for Macau rose to 333,391 last year. It is recalled that in 2021 Macau registered the highest rate of abstention in the elections for the AL, since it was created. The influx rate was 42.38%.
On the other hand, from Thursday, CAEAL will make the document available to the request for recognition of the constitution of the application committee. "The form must be completed before June 6 and be delivered to Caeal to confirm the application commissions," he said.
Seng Ioi Man also recalled that, according to the law in force, in direct suffrage, "each voter can only sign in a candidacy committee." “If the voter signs more than an application committee, all signatures will be considered invalid. This is an optimization of the electoral law to solve the problem of repeated signatures detected in the past, ”he said.
 
“Caution” with participation in associative activities
He also said that Caeal “assumes a very clear position that associative activities,” continued Seng Ioi Man. In this context, he recalled that the law defines the rules very clearly. “We understand that in the society of Macau is guaranteed the freedom of associative activities and many people are members of one or more associations, so we should not ban residents from participating in associative activities due to elections. But I want to reiterate that these activities, especially related to benefits, should not involve the election campaign. ”
In the constitution of candidacy committees, the president of Caeal said he considered that those interested in participating in associative actions are not necessary. "If the activity is intended only for the development of regular associative work, without involving campaign -related content, I see no need for the candidate to avoid participation in these activities," he said.
However, “if the person has already delivered the candidacy, he will have to consider his participation in associative benefit packet distribution activities,” said Seng Ioi Man.
Wong Kim Kim Fong, deputy commissioner against corruption, indicated, in the context of preventing and combating electoral corruption, that guidelines have already been issued regarding inspection work for legislative elections. "CAEAL and CCAC have created an online platform to submit complaints," he said, saying that it is possible to present photographs and documents to accompany the complaint. At the same time, a line that works for 24 hours to present the elections related to the elections (28997733) will be opened today.
Yesterday, Caeal issued an instruction, according to which the election campaign period starts at 00h00 of August 30 and ends at 24h00 of September 12. It also addresses the “duty of neutrality” of public entities and equivalent entities, as well as the prohibition of mobile phone use and other communication and recording equipment in the voting assembly and the prohibition to reveal the vote or voting intention.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>With São Lázaro discarded, Arraial should continue in the Tower</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sao-lazaro-descartado-arraial-devera-continuar-na-torre/</link><description>The difficulties in holding the São João village on the stage that the organization considers to be ideal, the São Lazaro neighborhood, should make the popular party return to the outer space of the Macao Tower. Miguel de Senna Fernandes told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau that informal contacts were made with some authorities, but the prospects are not in fact encouraging regarding the possibility of returning to St. Lazarus
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Having the Arraial de St. John in the outer space of the Macao Tower, as in 2024, is the most likely scenario for this year. Some contacts were made by the main responsible for organizing the popular party with authorities who in the past supported the event, but the reactions are not encouraging.
“Even in the informality of the contacts, it was told that it is practically impossible to make the camp in São Lázaro, because this decision went to the Culture Fund and I fear that the deadlines are over,” laments Miguel de Senna Fernandes, noting that the costs are also very high.
Thus, the president of the Macanese Association (ADM) believes that, for 2025, the tower becomes the strongest alternative. "The space is a good alternative, to evaluate the positive way as it ran last year, with many people to participate," he told the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
The leader insists on the idea of ​​“maintaining tradition”, which is the main priority. As for the place, he points out, "it is a matter of seeing, but I think we will return to the tower, even though I never give up trying to return to the origins, that is, to the São Lazaro neighborhood."
Among other options that can be considered if it is not possible to hold the party in the tower are the fishermen's dock, or very remotely the Tap Seac Square, but in this case "would involve a much larger logistics."
In one of the last meetings of the Advisory Board for Cultural Development, of which he is part, Miguel de Senna Fernandes raised the question of the Arraial in São Lázaro and obtained agreement of three counselors. "They have shown receptivity, which is already quite good, but it will probably not be possible this year to think about the return."
At the meeting, he stressed the importance of Arraial as an event of local traditions. “Formerly it was like a port party in Macau, but what is celebrated today is June 24,” he notes, noting that it is about to celebrate the one that became, at the time of the Portuguese administration, holiday of city day, or the patron saint of Macao.
The celebration also evokes the defeat of the Dutch imposed by the Portuguese of Macao, on June 24, 1622, which coincides with the date of St. John in Portugal - being the day of birth of St. John the Baptist celebrated by the Catholic churches. The victory was considered by the Portuguese as a blessing from St. John, which thus began to be venerated as patron of Macao.
 
Genuine tradition
For the importance he has for the city, Miguel de Senna Fernandes highlights the importance of being a genuinely festival of Macao, different from that of Portugal. "People wake up spontaneously and are not necessarily visitors from abroad, but the Portuguese and Chinese community, as has seen in previous editions," said the ADM leader, adding that "every year authorities are aware of the number of people who move to the party, and may prove that there are many people."
Given the period of celebration of the camp, the interest in traditions of this genre, "and because people are eager for parties," an event like this "has all the reason for being and is a date that concerns Macao," he said.
In this sense, Miguel de Senna Fernandes continues to argue that St. John should join the list of immaterial heritage. "For this year it will no longer happen, for a procedural reasons, but I hope that for 2026 this is a reality," he said, indicating that "continues on the waiting list" after the demonstration made in 2020.
According to the president of ADM, the conversations with the tower guardians will soon begin so that the preparations begin to be developed. "We have to get used to the idea that the Arraial de São João is celebrated in any space, provided there are minimum conditions to do it."
The subsidy request has already been made to the Macau Foundation and the leader expects to be granted. "We went back to a little over 400,000 patacas, but, as has happened, the foundation must again grant us about half, and it was with this money that we set the Arraial of 2024 standing," he explained.
For the organization of this year's São João Arraial, Miguel de Senna Fernandes intends to extend the collaboration of the associations. "Let's try to call more people," he concluded.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mand's vowels headed to Beijing with hengqin -centered proposals</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/vogais-da-raem-rumaram-pequim-propostas-centradas-em-hengqin/</link><description>Prior to the departure to Beijing to participate in the “two sessions”, several Macao vowels at ANP or CCPPC revealed that integration between MSAR and Hengqin will mark the theme of their proposals

To participate in the “two sessions”, 12 MSAR vowels at the 14th National Popular Assembly (ANP) and 27 Macao deputies at the 14th Political Advisory Conference of the Chinese people (CCPPC) moved to Beijing yesterday. The 3rd CCPPC session starts today in the Chinese capital, and will take place until March 10.
Before the match, several vowels advanced the themes of the proposals they lead. According to the Chinese language press, compared to ANP, the Ho Sut Heng vowel revealed that in the “two sessions”, he will pay attention to the development of the in -depth cooperation zone. According to said, a proposal that will present in Beijing aims to appeal to policies that can further facilitate the entrepreneurship, employment and life of residents of Macao in Hengqin. In addition, Ho Sut Heng will propose the optimization of the vocational training system, as it is concerned about the use of workers under the rapid evolution of artificial intelligence.
Already ng siu will focus on the issue of ease in border passages between Macau and Hengqin and the lives of residents in that area. In turn, Kevin Ho intends to ask the central government more support for the second phase of the construction of the cooperation zone, including “Innovative Laws directed to Hengqin, which better articulate with MSAR and international rules”.
Another ANP vowel, Vong Hin Fai, emphasized one of his approaches in the deep convergence of rules and mechanisms between Macau and Hengqin. Vong Hin Fai also stressed that Macau should take advantage of “a country, two systems” and economic and commercial exchanges with Portuguese -speaking countries, as well as consolidate the “a center, a platform, a base” to help the country in their respective work.
In turn, Lao Ngai Leong will suggest a new model in the Hengqin post that allows people to pass between the two sides of the border without reading identification documents or fingerprints.
How much to deputies at CCPPC, Mok Chi Wai said he will discuss how to make good use of the sinumphone platform of MSA to favor national development.
Frederico MA will also follow the progress of Macau's integration with Hengqin. To this end, it will submit proposals to reinforce cooperation between the two parts namely regarding the development of Chinese medicine and chip investigation. Alvis Lo will address the youth integration topics of MSAR in national development and “systematic and full promotion of the habit of regularly doing physical exercise among Macao residents”.
Also aware of the integration of hengqin masters, Lam Lon Wai will suggest a technical-professional school and a hengqin stage base. In turn, Lee Chong Cheng expects the central government to study the viability of the direct circulation of public buses from Macao to the cooperation zone.
On the other hand, at the CCPPC press conference, Liu Jieyi, a spokesman for this political advisory agency, said CCPPC will continue to support the construction of the great bay and help Hong Kong and Macau make better development by integrating themselves into the national development conjuncture. In addition, the spokesman praised the more than 230 RAE vowels at CCPPC for the “positive role” they play for the country's socioeconomic development and for the lasting prosperity and stability of the two regions.
 
Chief Executive present at the opening of the ANP session
Executive head, Sam Hou Fai, has moved to Beijing yesterday, and will be in the Chinese capital until March 6, with the purpose of attending the opening ceremony of the 3rd Session of the 14th Popular National Assembly (ANP), an event that will start tomorrow, March 5. During the absence of Sam Hou Fai, the Secretary for Administration and Justice, André Cheong, as an interim basis, as the executive It appears in an order published in an official bulletin.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Reserve investments yielded 30.95 billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/investimentos-da-reserva-renderam-3095-mil-milhoes/</link><description>The Macao Financial Reserve registered an income of investments in the order of 30.95 billion Patacas, reflecting a positive annual profitability of 5.3%, returning to the level of 2020. For this year, and given that Macau is “crucial period of economic recovery”, the monetary authority states that the government “must use and allocate public financial resources with caution”. The “safe, effective and stable” principle will continue to be followed in the scope of investment
 
Catarina Pereira
 
In 2024, the Form's financial reserve signaled an income from investments of 30.95 billion patacas, which translated into a 5.3%annual profitability. The monetary authority (AMCM) states that the scenario was due to “a diverse and balanced allocation of assets”. Last year's results reveal an increase compared to 2023, when the income was 28.98 billion and the profitability of 5.2%, and mark a return to annual profitability of 5.3% registered in 2020, the year in which a historical record of investment income was recorded (31.06 billion patacas).
According to AMCM, at the end of the year, the value of the financial reserve's capitals ascended to 616.21 billion of patacas, plus 35.74 billion or 6% in annual terms, with the basic reserve representing 153.39 billion and the extraordinary reserve 462.82 billion (+8%). It should be noted that the Extraordinary Reserve is equivalent to the remaining balances of the Financial Reserve after the satisfaction of the basic reserve, and can be taken to provide financial support to a possible annual budget deficit of the MSAR, as well as the necessary financial resources to favor socioeconomic development.
Last year, in the context of a “gradually controlled inflationary situation”, central banks from many countries have successively reduced political interest rates, “which favored the trend of financial markets,” says AMCM. However, "the variation of the growth pace of the main world economies, geopolitical complications and the gradual adjustment of market expectations regarding central bank interest rates have caused financial assets to retire from their maximums at the end of the year."
Although global financial markets continued to float this year, “the most diverse allocation of financial reserve assets played a complementary role, helping to balance returns and risks,” says the body. With the premise of maintaining the liquidity and safety of the general assets, it continues to AMCM, “the financial reserve focuses on allocation of high quality assets that can provide stable returns and lower risks, while moderately optimizing the structure of the license portfolio to achieve the preservation and appreciation of capital”.
 
Allocate “prudence” resources
Underlining that the Financial Reserve plays an important role in supporting social and economic stability, and given that Macao is, “currently, at a crucial period of economic recovery”, AMCM states that the government “should use and allocate public financial resources with caution”. "Entering 2025, facing geopolitical uncertainty, it is expected that the respective factors will continue to affect the prices of various types of assets, bringing challenges to the management of financial reserves in the current year," he warns.
Given the “uncertain environment of the financial market” and, to ensure that the financial reserve continues to play “an essential role in supporting the implementation of MSAR public policies and guaranteeing the capacity to pay long -term public finance”, the body states that MSc will join the basic “safe, and stable” principle when dealing with reserve. Especially highlighting “control of descent risks, detention of a higher proportion of high security and liquidity investment products and the timely adjustment of allocation in response to market conditions”. The objective in the medium and long term, he adds, is the preservation of capital and the appreciation of reserve assets.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Anora” dominates Oscars in a historic gala for Brazil</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/anora-domina-oscares-em-gala-historica-para-brasil/</link><description>Director Sean Baker, Producers Alex Coco and Samantha Quan and Cast and Crew Members Win the Oscar for Best Picture For "Anora" During the Oscars Show at the 97th Academy Awards in Hollywood, Los Angeles, California, U.S., March 2, 2025. Reuters/Carlos Barria TPX Images of the Day



Sean Baker's movie “Anora” was the winner of the 97th edition of the Oscars, triumpting in five of the six categories to which he was appointed, followed by “The Brutalist” with three awards, while “Emilia Pérez” was limited to two and Brazil celebrated its first statuette.

"I'm Still Here" by Walter Salles, took the Portuguese language to the distinguished, winning the Oscar for best international film, surpassing Magnus von Horn (Denmark), "The Seed of the Sacred Fig", by Iranian Mohammad Rasoulof (Germany), Gints, "Flow" Zilbalodis (Latvia), which won the award for best animated feature film, and French Audiard's own “Emilia Pérez” itself.
Walter Salles's film, which was also nominated for better film and best main actress, by the interpretation of Fernanda Torres, already awarded the Golden Globes, refers to the period of Brazil's military dictatorship (1964-1985), recovering the story of politician Rubens Paiva, who was arrested, tortured and dead, and his wife, the resistant Eunice Paiva.
“Anora” beat the Oscars for Best Film, Best Actress (Mikey Madison), Best Director, Best Original Argument and Best Assembly, bringing together four of the main awards, giving only Yura Borisov's appointment for the best secondary actor to Kieran Culkin, distinguished by “Real Pain”.
Baker's movie tells the story of an American stripper who marries the son of a Russian oligarch. The base of the plot has allowed the Oscar presenter, comedian Connan O'Brien, to make the only obviously political joke of the night: "I think Americans are excited to see someone finally face a powerful Russian."
Mikey Madison, who won her first Oscar, defended sex workers and reinforced Baker's appeals in defense of independent cinema. Madison surpassed Demi Moore (“The Substance”), which criticism and betting houses were favorite, Fernanda Torres, who had already won the Golden Globe for the performance of “I'm Still”, Cynthia Erivo (“Wicked”) and Karla Sofa Gasco (“Emilia Pérez”), who dictated the final luck of the most named films in this edition, with 'Tweets' of yours of racist and xenophobic character.
The musical “Emilia Pérez”, which totaled 13 nominations -a record for a non -English language movie -awarded at the Cannes Festival, saw the popularity fall mainly because of the actress's messages, after being criticized by the way the trans community represented, telling the story of a mexican drug cartel who made a genre transition. “Emilia Pérez” was limited to two awards: Best Song (“El Mal”) and Best Secondary Actress, Zoe Saldaña.
“The Brutalist,” Brady Corbet's postwar drama, was in second place with three Oscars, including the second best actor for Adrien Brody, as well as the best photography and best soundtrack awards.
The Oscar for best documentary was for the Israelo-Palestinian movie “No other Land”, which, almost without budget and without the support of a US distributor, avenged in the academy vote. Gints Zilbalodis's “Flow” won the Oscar for best animated feature film, the first for a Latto movie, and “Wicked”, with 10 nominations, got two statuettes: best production design and best wardrobe, distinguishing Paul Tazewell, the first black man to win a ospa in this category.
“Dune: Part Two”, with better sound and best special effects, also added two Oscars, while “The Substance” only managed to gain the best characterization. “Conclave”, which totaled eight nominations, including better film, got an Oscar for Peter Straughan for the best adapted argument. “The Complete Unknown,” which reads Bob Dylan's early years, had eight nominations, including better film, and no Oscar.
The gala opened with Ariana Grande to sing “Somewhere Over the Rainbow” and honored Los Angeles firefighters, calling the stage representatives from different corporations because of the January fires. The tribute to the film professionals who died last year took place to the sound of Mozart's “Lacrimosa”, and brought to the faces like Gene Hackman, Gena Rowlands, Teri Garr, Roger Corman and Kris Kristofferson.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Road Works Target of “Comprehensive Review”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/obras-viarias-alvo-de-revisao-abrangente/</link><description>The mode of coordination and supervision of major road works is being the subject of a “comprehensive review”, said the director of DSAT, pointing out that the objective is to “progressively increase the effectiveness in coordinating works and minimizing the impact on resident travel”.
 
“A comprehensive review regarding the coordination and supervision of road works of great wingspan” is underway, taking into account the limitations imposed by the conditions of the roads and the global traffic needs, among other factors, revealed the director of services for traffic affairs (DSAT), Lam Hin San. In response to an interpellation of Ella Law, the body's leader indicated that the review is guided by the principle of “continuous improvement and constant optimization”.
The idea, proceeds Lam Hin San, is “progressively increasing the effectiveness in coordinating the works and minimizing the impact on resident travel during their execution”. DSAT's director, yet, that, in recent years, the road works coordination group has introduced “improvements” to varying degrees in the procedures for the appreciation and approval of road works and the system, as well as the coordination between the entities responsible for the execution.
As for the works performed at the Institute's initiative for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), it is said that the body will, “through a regular communication mechanism, discuss the projects of work with the competent services and contractors, in order to reduce repeated excavations, to require the total presence of workers and machinery during the execution of the works, and to optimize the sealing plan of work areas”. For the critical sections of the works, when necessary, it will also be considered “the proper extension” of working hours.
"All measures aim to complete the works in the shortest possible time and minimize the impact on the displacement of citizens," can be read. In addition, with regard to other projects involving public road excavation for the installation of cables and pipes, “AMI will adopt the same criteria, controlling the deadline for excavation licenses and strictly overseeing contractors, to ensure that the works are completed within the deadline and that the prohibited area is minimized, thus reducing the impact on the displacement of citizens”.
Lam Hin San also indicated that the “uniform platform for road works” is only accessible to public bodies and public service entities, representing about 70% of the total requests. "It is expected that the platform is officially available to private entities during this year, with the aim of increasing the rate of orders made by electronic means to 85%," he adds, saying that DSAT will continue with the analysis of the viability of greater opening of the platform to the public and will continue to collect opinions from society.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SJM renews support to the social store</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sjm-renova-apoio-a-loja-social/</link><description>The Santa Casa da Misericórdia Social Store of Macao (SCMM) has made the distribution of property of primary need of March, sponsored by SJM Resorts. Cabazes, whose distribution was supported by more than 40 SJM volunteers, were delivered to 372 low -income families, including 150 of the General Union of Residents Associations (Ugamm), 150 selected by the Macao Workers' Associations Federation (Faom), 47 supported by SCMM and 25 referred by the Association of Parents of Defective Education Education Mental.

The support ceremony of support was held last week at the Grand Lisbon Palace, where SJM Executive Director Daisy Ho handed over António José de Freitas, provider of SCMM, a check worth 300,000 patacas. Also present were Angela Leong, SJM administrator, Ho Sut Heng, president of Faom, and Chan Ka Leong, president of the Ugamm Board.
According to Santa Casa, Daisy Ho stressed that SJM has been rooted in Macau for over 60 years and has always been concerned with society, committed to supporting disadvantaged groups. “This year marks the 13th consecutive year in which we support the social store project. We are very pleased to work side by side with this charity with hundreds of years of history to jointly promote philanthropy in Macau and promote harmony and social stability. We hope that, through practical actions, we can actively return to society and spread positive energy to local vulnerable groups, ”he said.
In turn, António José de Freitas praised the fact that SJM supported from the beginning the operation of the social store, fulfilling their social responsibilities and jointly contributing to “the inclusion of these needy families falling into the disguised poverty group”.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>2019 candidates can now choose economic fractions</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/candidatos-de-2019-ja-podem-escolher-fraccoes-economicas/</link><description>Family aggregates who applied for economic housing in 2019 and were accepted can begin today to choose the fractions, all located in zone A of the new landfills. IH indicated that this procedure is being done by different groups, which are being notified
 
Starting today, the first group of qualified family aggregates from the 2019 Open Economic Housing Competition can start choosing the fractions, the Housing Institute (IH) yesterday indicated. The body has been notifying, by groups, the various family centers, on this procedure, accounting for the discrimination tables for sales prices.
The Economic Housing Competition opened in 2019 was the last contest held under the former “Economic Housing Law”. Until February 24, and after substantial appreciation, 2,993 selected acquirers met the requirements.
Economic dwellings available for acquisition are located in the Tong Seng Building (Lot B4), Tong Chong Building (Lot B9) and Tong Kai Building (Lot B10), in Zone A of new landfills, totaling 3,017 fractions, including 760 T1, 1,000 T2 and 1,257 T3 apartments.
Zona A Economic Housing Fractions are located on the 2nd floor of the Mong Tak Mong Housing Building there are, with the respective typologies, materials used and similar delivery criteria, IH points out, adding that selected acquirers can pay a visit.
IH warns that household aggregates must be aware of the date and time indicated in the notification letter. They should then go to HI, along with this notification and the BIR originals of all aggregate elements or respective electronic identity tickets, and the signed statements originals, for the purpose of choosing fraction and treatment of formalities.
"After choosing the economic housing fraction, contractors must sign the Power and Selling Agreement and related documents," adds the IH. At the time of signing the promissory contract, no payment is required.
The body also underlines that it will “reserve enough time” for the treatment of formalities related to mortgage loans by aggregates and will later notify the prompts-compliances, through offices, for the payment of housing values ​​and the treatment of formalities related to the reception of fraction keys.
Acquirers can consult the catalog with the description of the fractions for sale (electronic version) and the situation of the sale of fractions on the electronic page (https://www.ihm.gov.mo/en/he2019-unit-sales-details).
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game recipes can accelerate in the second half</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/receitas-jogo-podem-acelerar-segundo-semestre/</link><description>Gross Macao game revenues could increase 6.5% by 2025, in annual terms, estimated consultant Seport Research Partners, predicting "a higher growth in the second half of the year." "Growth should be driven by increasing operators 'marketing efforts and improving consumers' feeling in China," says the report signed by analyst Umnsky, stressing that the eventual announcement of economic stimulation measures during the "two sessions" in Beijing (from the popular National Assembly and the Chinese people's political consultative) will represent a "positive wind" for the game sector in the game in Macao.
"With a growing tariff regime in the US, we hope China's political decision makers will look harder to expand consumption and improve house consumer confidence," he said.
The Seaport report was published following the release of the game results in February, the month when gross revenues reached 19.74 billion patacas, which translates up to 6.8% and 8.2% in annual and monthly terms, respectively, and equals 77.8% of the level of the same period of 2019. In February, the average daily revenue was about 705 million, a brand that, second Umansky, it was the highest since January 2020 and surpassed October 2024 by over 5%.
Investment Bank JP Morgan also noted that casinos exceeded analyst expectations in February. According to analysts DS Kim, Selina Li and Mufan Shi, revenues should remain stable in March, compared to the previous year, at an interval between 19 billion and 19.5 billion patacas.
Umansky is more optimistic by predicting a 5.3% homologous increase in March.
According to data from the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, casinos revenues totaled about 38 billion patacas in the first two months of 2025, noting an annual increase of 0.5% and a recovery of 75.5% compared to 2019.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Died President of Geocapital, Jorge Ferro Ribeiro</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/morreu-presidente-da-geocapital-jorge-ferro-ribeiro/</link><description>Jorge Ferro Ribeiro, chairman of the Board of Directors of the Geocapital Investment Company and Stanley Ho's historic partner, died on Saturday at Herdade in Mountain, according to the Jornal Económico. Investor and representative of the interests of Stanley Ho in Portugal, Jorge Ferro Ribeiro was president of the company Construções Technicals (which also operated in Macau) and Interfina, a group with various businesses, including consulting and management. Geocapital, based in Macau, is a company resulting from a partnership between Stanley Ho's heirs and businessman Jorge Ferro Ribeiro. Geocapital's role is to introduce Macau and its investors to companies from other countries, and also bring companies to each other from each other, using their specialized expertise and connections, the Jornal Económico says. In the early 1990s, Stanley Ho and Ferro Ribeiro established a consortium with three telecommunications giants in France, Germany and Hong Kong, and presented themselves to a contest to try to get one of the first licenses to operate a mobile phone in Portugal, but lost to TMN, which obtained the first, and for Telecel, which guaranteed the second, the same newspaper writes.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2352/</link><description>Metro registered in February second highest value
The average number of passengers who traveled daily in the light meter during February reached the second largest ever since that means of transportation went into operations. In the statistics released by the Light Metro Society, it can be seen that there were approximately 27,000 people who, per day, traveled in the subway last month, a number higher than in January (25,300). The passenger record is close to 33,000, accounted for in the first month of Metro operations in December 2019.
 
Vessels originated 34 accidents in 2024
The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) registered, in 2024, 34 accidents related to vessels in the Maritime area of ​​Macao. The cases involved strands, collision between boats and fires. Seven of the incidents implied passenger transport vessels. According to Dsama, authorities and boat companies discussed navigation precautions, with the aim of reducing the risk of accidents, also sharing experiences to the parties to be more sensitized to safe navigation. However, because of the fog, the companies yesterday suspended the connecting trips to Zhongshan and Shenzhen.
 
“Nova Águia” magazine honors Rocha Vieira
The Culture Magazine “Nova Águia” dedicated its 35th number to General Vasco Rocha Vieira, the last governor of Macao, who was an honorary partner of the Lusófono International Movement (one thousand). In a post scriptum inserted in the editorial, the direction of the “new eagle” also says that, in the next number, will evoke Rocha Vieira by the voice of Jorge Rangel, president of the International Institute of Macao. Rocha Vieira passed away last January 22, at the age of 85.
 
Association alert for hearing loss among young people
In an initiative for sensitization for hearing care, Lau Sut Man, secretary general of the Deaf Association, warned of the average age of hearing loss residents, observed in recent years, as well as to rise in the number of users of the association services that are people with acquired deafness. According to the Chinese language press, the associative leader suggested that, in the elaboration of action plans for the support services for the elderly and people rehabilitated in the next 10 years, the government ponders the creation of a hearing protection system that covers the entire life cycle, taking as reference the indicators of the World Health Organization.
 
Woman inhaled smoke on gas escape
A 53 -year -old woman was transported to the hospital after inhaling thick tobacco, following a fire in the kitchen of the fraction where she lives, near the San Ma Lo. According to the Fire Department, an oil gas leak was detected, which will have been in the cause of the accident. The case, which took place the night the day before yesterday, also caused the building of a dozen other residents of the building.</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Value and form of attribution of the still uncertain checks</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/valor-forma-de-atribuicao-dos-cheques-ainda-incertos/</link><description>The Chief Executive admits that there may be changes in the value and the distribution of pecuniary checks, a matter that is not yet closed. The budget for this year's pecuniary reimbursement plan is 7.48 billion of patacas. Sam Hou Fai also reiterated the attention that the government gives problems such as the aging of the population and the low birth rate. As for the viaduct between zones A and B, it assumed the intention to “improve” the proposal
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Admittedly, pecuniary checks will be distributed this year, but the government has not yet decided whether there will be changes in both the value and the form of attribution. “The budget for this year is 7.48 billion Patacas and, when they asked for my opinion at the time, I agreed to issue the checks. Currently, the global inflation rate is still low, so the measures for this year have to be implemented, ”began by telling Sam Hou Fai to journalists.
“If there is room for improvement, how much and how to distribute, the public must give opinions, to demonstrate more justice, accuracy and the connection to the MSAR. And in these ways we should ponder more, ”added the chief executive, on the sidelines of the Spring Dinner offered by the Macao Chinese Companies Association.
As I said, it is necessary to take into account "the global economic environment." “If they do not forget that monthly revenues of the game worth 20 billion patacas were used as a base, there is a small surplus. But see the month of December: there was only about 18 billion. The government will consider this question as a whole and will announce it to the public when a decision is made, ”he continued.
Admitting that the pecuniary reimbursement plan benefits residents and creates expectations in society, Sam Hou Fai recalled that it was implemented in 2008, as a temporary measure, and whose objective was to share with the population the result of economic development, if there were conditions in the public coffers. The leader of the MSAR also recalled that, so far, have been awarded 90 billion patacas in this context.
"The Government of MSar will continue to hear the opinions of the various sectors of society, hoping to improve and improve this measure," he said. Remember that in recent times there have been the voices to consider that the form of attribution of the checks must be changed, arguing, for example, that residents living abroad will no longer receive this benefit.
At the same time, Sam Hou Fai guaranteed, according to a statement from the Communication Office, that "the improvement of the well-being of the population and the support for vulnerable groups are the focus of governance actions." Regarding the rigid public expenses of the welfare of the population and occupying the highest proportion of overviews, ensured that the government "will continue to maintain close communication with the sectors of society, alarming more opinions and suggestions."
In this field, he said he hopes-under the assumption of safeguarding the basic needs of the welfare of the population and if the financial situation allows-"to fully consider the various factors and study the policy of adjusting various benefits."
It also underlined the “high attention that gives matters related to the elderly and children”, especially at a time when Macao is facing a double challenge: the aging of the population and the low rate of birth. The government “will, through a series of policies and services, provide support and affection to needy families, as well as encourage young families to have children,” he said.
 
Operators “have responsibility” in the case of satellite casinos
The three-year period of transition from the satellite casinos ends in late 2025 and, asked about the future of workers in those spaces, the chief executive recalled that "they are recruited by the operators, so they have the responsibility of taking appropriate action."
Sam Hou Fai added that the government is available to help if necessary. He also said he believed that game operators and satellite casinos managers will coordinate according to the contract entered into and proceed well to transition work. ”
There are 11 satellite casinos that can close, implying about 12,000 workers.
On the other hand, asked about the viaduct proposal between zones A and B, he pointed out that the government “has the need to proceed well to planning and complementary road facilities, linking it to several adjacent zones”, as zone A will become an important area of ​​education and housing ”.
Urbanists and deputies have warned that the viaduct can have impacts on world heritage. Recognizing that there are different opinions, Sam Hou Fai stated that the services will continue to collect opinions, "which will be studied and analyzed, to improve the respective proposal."
In relation to the flood protection work in Coloane -which environmentalists, urban planners and deputies also question, due to any impacts on the environment and protected animals -the chief executive stressed the “importance of the work to prevent flooding”. He stated that the work aims to favor “safeguarding the life of the population” and the “security of their goods”. In this sense, it ensured that the services “will plan the work well”.
Sam Hou Fai reiterates bet on science and technology
In a meeting with the Undersecretary-General of the United Nations, Tshilidzi Marwala, the Chief Executive stained that the government “gives high importance to the application of innovative science and technology in various areas” and has fostered growth of this type of industries. Sam Hou Fai also stressed that "there is a determination to boost the industrialization of innovative science and technology, which can also introduce new dynamics in local economic development." More specifically, he highlighted the incentive to “foreign universities and companies” to enjoy Macao and the deepened cooperation zone. Tshilidzi Marwala, who is also a rector of the United Nations University, was visiting Macau.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GDP grew 8.8% in 2024 after fifth quarterly deceleration</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pib-cresceu-88-em-2024-apos-quinta-desaceleracao-trimestral/</link><description>MSAR Gross Domestic Product increased by 8.8% in 2024, in annual and real terms, falling short of government projections and the international monetary fund. In the last three months of last year, homologous growth has reached only 3.4%, reflecting the fifth consecutive quarterly slowdown
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Calculated at current prices, the value of Macau's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) was 403.3 billion patacas by 2024, translating an annual growth of 8.8% in real terms and corresponding to 86.4% of the volume of 2019, before the pandemic, announced the direction of statistics and censuses (DSEC) services (DSEC). The performance of the local economy was thus short of the forecast made about a year ago by the then Secretary for Economics and Finance, Law Wai Nong, who pointed to a 10.3%growth, as well as the Projections of the International Monetary Fund (IMF), which started at 13.9%and were low magazines to 10.6%.
The per capita GDP, which reflects the average value of goods and services produced per person, grew 7.6% to 587,922 patacas compared to 2023, in a year when the implicit deflator of GDP, which measures global price variation, increased by 0.4%.
After increasing 75.1% in 2023 -considering the data reviewed by DSEC -GDP has followed a deceleration trajectory, in a context influenced by a relatively high comparative base and the slowdown or stabilization of the game's revenues. In the last three months of 2024, Macau's economy registered the fifth consecutive quarter of slowdown, growing only 3.4% in real terms, compared to 3.8% in the previous three months, 7.1% between April and June, 23.0% between January and March and 79.7% in the fourth quarter of 2023.
Between October and December, the GDP value equivalent to 88%of the economic volume of the same period of 2019. In the fourth quarter analysis, DSEC highlights homologous additions in internal demand (plus 2.8%) and service exports (plus 2.1%).
In the general calculation of last year, the economy was again driven by service exports, which grew by 9.2% compared to 2023, benefiting from the 23.8% increase in the number of visitors. In turn, the internal demand, which encompasses private consumer expense, the government's final consumer consumer expense and investment, advanced 2.3%.
According to official statistics, game service exports increased by 21.8%, contrary to the decline of 6.1%in exports of other tourist services, although they exceeded the 2019 level by 13%. In the field of foreign trade in goods, exports and imports of goods retreated 14.5% and 7.6%, in homologous terms, respectively.
 
Private compensates for breaking in public investment
Gross formation of fixed capital grew 4.6% between 2023 and 2024, thanks to the reinforcement of 12.6% in investment in the private sector, which plyed a descent of 8.4% in the public sphere. The investment in construction rose 5.1% in the private, however, lowered 10% in the public sector, due to the completion of several works of large wingspan.
In turn, the values ​​of equipment investment illustrate annual increase of 31.1% and 1.2% in the private and public sectors, respectively.
The contribution of investment to general economic growth in 2024 was estimated at 0.7 percentage points. In this chapter, the largest weight was again detained by exports of services (7.3 points), followed by imports of goods (2,9) and private consumer expense (1.5).
At the level of internal demand, there is a 4.9% increase in private consumer expense, which DSEC attributes “continuous recovery of economic activities” and “uninterrupted labor market stability”. Still, the final consumption expenses of families had different evolutions, with the rise to be more modest in the local market (more 3.8%) than abroad (11.1%more).
Among the main components of GDP expense, the government's final consumer consumer expense fell 5.1% last year, following the end of the measures adopted under the “Living Subsidy Plan”, the body says, noting that net purchases of goods and services lowered 11.2% and employees remuneration rose 0.2%.</description><pubDate>2025-03-03 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Anora” dominates Oscars in a historic gala for Brazil</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/anora-domina-oscares-em-gala-historica-para-brasil/</link><description>Director Sean Baker, Producers Alex Coco and Samantha Quan and Cast and Crew Members Win the Oscar for Best Picture For "Anora" During the Oscars Show at the 97th Academy Awards in Hollywood, Los Angeles, California, U.S., March 2, 2025. Reuters/Carlos Barria TPX Images of the Day



Sean Baker's movie “Anora” was the winner of the 97th edition of the Oscars, triumpting in five of the six categories to which he was appointed, followed by “The Brutalist” with three awards, while “Emilia Pérez” was limited to two and Brazil celebrated its first statuette.

"I'm Still Here" by Walter Salles, took the Portuguese language to the distinguished, winning the Oscar for best international film, surpassing Magnus von Horn (Denmark), "The Seed of the Sacred Fig", by Iranian Mohammad Rasoulof (Germany), Gints, "Flow" Zilbalodis (Latvia), which won the award for best animated feature film, and French Audiard's own “Emilia Pérez” itself.
Walter Salles's film, which was also nominated for better film and best main actress, by the interpretation of Fernanda Torres, already awarded the Golden Globes, refers to the period of Brazil's military dictatorship (1964-1985), recovering the story of politician Rubens Paiva, who was arrested, tortured and dead, and his wife, the resistant Eunice Paiva.
“Anora” beat the Oscars for Best Film, Best Actress (Mikey Madison), Best Director, Best Original Argument and Best Assembly, bringing together four of the main awards, giving only Yura Borisov's appointment for the best secondary actor to Kieran Culkin, distinguished by “Real Pain”.
Baker's movie tells the story of an American stripper who marries the son of a Russian oligarch. The base of the plot has allowed the Oscar presenter, comedian Connan O'Brien, to make the only obviously political joke of the night: "I think Americans are excited to see someone finally face a powerful Russian."
Mikey Madison, who won her first Oscar, defended sex workers and reinforced Baker's appeals in defense of independent cinema. Madison surpassed Demi Moore (“The Substance”), which criticism and betting houses were favorite, Fernanda Torres, who had already won the Golden Globe for the performance of “I'm Still”, Cynthia Erivo (“Wicked”) and Karla Sofa Gasco (“Emilia Pérez”), who dictated the final luck of the most named films in this edition, with 'Tweets' of yours of racist and xenophobic character.
The musical “Emilia Pérez”, which totaled 13 nominations -a record for a non -English language movie -awarded at the Cannes Festival, saw the popularity fall mainly because of the actress's messages, after being criticized by the way the trans community represented, telling the story of a mexican drug cartel who made a genre transition. “Emilia Pérez” was limited to two awards: Best Song (“El Mal”) and Best Secondary Actress, Zoe Saldaña.
“The Brutalist,” Brady Corbet's postwar drama, was in second place with three Oscars, including the second best actor for Adrien Brody, as well as the best photography and best soundtrack awards.
The Oscar for best documentary was for the Israelo-Palestinian movie “No other Land”, which, almost without budget and without the support of a US distributor, avenged in the academy vote. Gints Zilbalodis's “Flow” won the Oscar for best animated feature film, the first for a Latto movie, and “Wicked”, with 10 nominations, got two statuettes: best production design and best wardrobe, distinguishing Paul Tazewell, the first black man to win a ospa in this category.
“Dune: Part Two”, with better sound and best special effects, also added two Oscars, while “The Substance” only managed to gain the best characterization. “Conclave”, which totaled eight nominations, including better film, got an Oscar for Peter Straughan for the best adapted argument. “The Complete Unknown,” which reads Bob Dylan's early years, had eight nominations, including better film, and no Oscar.
The gala opened with Ariana Grande to sing “Somewhere Over the Rainbow” and honored Los Angeles firefighters, calling the stage representatives from different corporations because of the January fires. The tribute to the film professionals who died last year took place to the sound of Mozart's “Lacrimosa”, and brought to the faces like Gene Hackman, Gena Rowlands, Teri Garr, Roger Corman and Kris Kristofferson.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-03-04 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>