<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>André Cheong goes from government to the hemiciclo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/andre-cheong-passa-governo-para-hemiciclo/</link><description>In an unprecedented decision, André Cheong was appointed deputy, thus motivating a reconfiguration of the government itself. Wong Sio Chak will assume the position of Secretary for Administration and Justice, while Chan Tsz King, current prosecutor, will be in charge of the Security Folder. In turn, Chan will be replaced by Judge Tong Hio Fong, president of the second instance court. Of the seven deputies appointed by the Chief Executive, only Kou Kam Fai remains from the last legislature

Pedro Milheirão
André Cheong is one of the seven deputies appointed to the VIII Legislative Assembly (AL), according to an executive order published yesterday in an official bulletin. Pela primeira vez na história da RAEM, um Secretário deixará o Governo para integrar o Hemiciclo. Under proposal from the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai, the China State Council appointed Wong Sio Chak, a current secretary for security, to assume the protection of administration and justice in an equally unprecedented decision, in which a secretary in office will assume another portfolio in the same term. It is also the second time that a secretary has abandoned the position since 2006, when the then secretary for public works, to Man Long, was arrested in the context of a corruption scandal. Chan Tsz King, prosecutor (MP), will become the new secretary for security and will be replaced by the judge and president of the Second Instance Court (TSI), Tong Hio Fong.
André Cheong took office as Secretary for Administration and Justice in 2019, while Wong Sio Chak was chosen for Secretary for Security in 2014, having remained in office since then. Both were renamed in December, with the only two secretaries to move from the government of Ho Iat Seng.
Chan Tsz King, next Secretary for Security, was delegate of the MP Attorney between 1997 and 2000, and was then promoted to the Assistant Prosecutor. In 2019, he became a commissioner against corruption by 2024, the year he assumed the position of prosecutor. Tong Hio Fong served as Judge President of the Collective Court of First Instance Courts. He was later president of the lower court courts and judge of the second instance court. Since 2022, it has been holding the position of president of TSI.
The remaining named for al are rookie law wun Kong, Chao Ka Chong, Lam Fat Iam, Wong Ka Lon and Kou Ngon Seng, besides the only renamed, Kou Kam Fai. The appointments will be effective from October 16th.
Among the 33 deputies of VIII AL there are a total of 14 debutants. Chan Hao Wen, Lee Koi Ian, Loi I Weng and Chan Lai Kei, from direct suffrage, and Leong Pou U, Vong Hou Pi and Wong Chon Kit, of the indirect suffrage, are the new deputies to enter Hemiciclo, in addition to the six new deputies appointed by Sam Hou Fai.
 
Names leave promises
To the Chinese press, Kou Ngon Seng, director-general of the Macao Strategic Research Center for the development of Macao, assured that he will “work well, according to the Constitution and the Basic Law, and take advantage of his rich experience in the area of ​​Youth Affairs”. "The aim is to convey the expectations of young people in AL," Kou said, also promising to focus their work "in the formation of qualified staff and in the promotion of youth integration in the national development conjuncture." It will also pay “high attention” to the macao air transport port, on the west bank of Rio das Pérolas.
For its part, Chao Ka Chong, president of “Boardware Intelligence Technology” and Member of the Macao Science and Technology Council, has promised to “learn in a humble way and wide the opinions of different sectors of society, especially in the area of ​​science and technology. He also stressed that he will“ take advantage of his professional experience in the area ”so as to“ make contributions to society ”. Macao set in the in -depth cooperation zone of Hengqin ”.
Already Kou Kam Fai, director of the Pui Ching Secondary School, ensured “taking a broader view and a more pragmatic attitude”. In the next legislature, it will focus on several works, such as “the promotion of the development of long-term Macao education, the improvement of legal frameworks, the creation of a more effective mechanism for importing qualified frameworks, the improvement of the talent formation system and the active promotion of the in-depth cooperation zone”. He also added that he will pay attention to the employment and mental health issues of young people.
Law Wun Kong, chairman of the Superior Council of Law, is also a member of the Basic Law Commission of the Permanent Committee of the Popular Assembly. Lam Fat Iam, in turn, is director of the Faculty of Human and Social Sciences of the Polytechnic University of Macao and president of the Macao Cultural Education Publications Association. Finally, Wong Ka Lon is a member of the Youth Council and founding president of the Macao Live Transmission Association, according to the Social Communication Office.
MA Chin Seng and Ian Teng Pio remain in AL, but by the way of indirect suffrage, while other deputies appointed by Ho Iat SENG are leaving, namely Eddie Wu, Chan Hon Seng, Cheung Kin Chung and Pang Chuan, except Kou Kam Fai.
 
Relationship between Executive and Legislative “will be reinforced”, anticipates Sonny Lo
Sonny Lo Shiu-Hing believes that André Cheong's move to the Legislative Assembly (AL) is a "strategic move." "It's something unprecedented. I have never seen a secretary after 1999 be transferred to the AL," said the political commentator, in statements to Lusa. Sonny Lo also considers that “the relationship between the Executive and the Legislature in Macau will be reinforced”, with the existence of another deputy to “reduce the communication pit” between Hemiciclo and the Executive Council. This time becomes three deputies among the members who make up the Executive Council. In addition to André Cheong, they are also part of the Song Pek Kei Executive Council, the second most voted deputy of direct suffrage, and IP Sio Kai, deputy elected by the Indirect Way. Sonny Lo now hopes that the elected deputies have "a more supervisory role," recalling that the nominees play "a slightly different role," as the government advises as experts. In addition, the nominees "tend to be relatively younger and this can be a preparation, a kind of formation for more potential leaders in Macao," he added. For the political analyst, Wong Sio Chak will focus more on legal reforms in the courts. Sonny Lo also sees in Wong "a possible candidate for chief executive."</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rui Martins receives in Beijing the Friendship Medal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rui-martins-recebe-em-pequim-medalha-da-amizade/</link><description>The vice-rector of the University of Macao, Rui Martins, today receives in Beijing the medal of friendship of the Chinese government, in what is considered the largest award granted by the Popular Republic of China to foreign specialists who have made remarkable contributions to the economic and social progress of the country. distinguished
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The Friendship Medal, which is China's highest award attributed to foreign personalities who have been highlighted by “remarkable contributions” in various areas, will be delivered today to Rui Martins. The ceremony is scheduled for the Great Palace of the People in Beijing.
Other relief figures that contributed to the “socialist modernization of China, the promotion of exchange and cooperation between China and foreign countries and the protection of world peace” will be equally distinguished with medals and certificates. All the recipients “cooperated and actively participated in supporting China's social, cultural, economic and international development in varying degrees”, can be read in justification for the delivery of this award.
The “Friendship Award”, which in 2024 distinguished, among others, Dilma Rousseff, former president of Brazil and president, since 2023, from the New Development Bank, based in Shanghai (Banco do Brics), was initially created as a medal of Sino-Soviet friendship in 1951. At that time, she was granted to experts from the former Soviet Union and the then Prime Minister. Zhou Enlai and by the Minister of Foreign Affairs Chen Yi.
In 1955, the Chinese government decreed that each Soviet expert who departed would receive a medal, which presented the flags of China and the Soviet Union, along with the inscription “Long live the sino-soviet friendship”.
The Friendship Award was abolished with the sino-soviet rupture in the early 1960s. During the following period, in particular the cultural revolution, foreigners in China were often considered “spies” and very few remained in the country.
After China's reopening, a new Friendship Award was reintroduced in 1991. Since then, the winners have been selected by the state administration of foreign expert matters under the Council of State.
The prize, granted as part of the celebrations of the National Day of the Popular Republic of China, which are marked tomorrow, consists of a medal and a certificate. The medal is decorated with an image of the Great Wall and adopted various elements, such as a dove, followed by a handshake signal that symbolizes China's friendly attitude towards other countries. The medal plate is surrounded by lotus petals, a flower that represents purity, peace and harmony in traditional Chinese culture.
In addition to this national award, several local awards for foreign experts are also granted at the provincial, regional and municipal levels.
The first Friendship Medal in the new format was granted by President XI Jinping to Russian homologist Vladimir Putin on June 8, 2018.
This is the first award of the Popular Republic of China to Rui Martins, and the Portuguese academic has already been awarded Macao, notably with the professional merit medal awarded in 1999, the “Honorary Title of Value (2001) and Merit Medal in Education (2021). It also obtained the National Electric Engineering Prize (Portugal, 2024).
At 68 years old, he was born in São Jorge de Arraiolos, Lisbon, but grew up in Mozambique, where he graduated. It is known for its contributions to research in microelectronics and higher education, acting as vice-rector of the University of Macau (one) for global affairs, since 1997.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Border passages can reach six million on holidays</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/passagens-fronteiricas-podem-chegar-seis-milhoes-nos-feriados/</link><description>The authorities' predictions point between 5.6 million and six million entries and out of Macao borders on China National Day holidays. On the other hand, tourism services describe the situation of markings for Macau hotels as “satisfactory”, promising work on several fronts to receive visitors and ensure the quality of services
 
During the Golden Week Commemorative of China National Day, which begins tomorrow and ends on October 8, the borders of Macao will be able to count between 5.6 million and six million tickets, which translates an average of 700,000 to 750 thousand tickets and exits, yesterday anticipated the Public Security Police (CPSP). Authorities reiterated forecasts for 1.2 million visitors in the eight days.
At a press conference to present the measures to be implemented during the golden week, CPSP also estimated that October 3 and 4 should mark the peak of the flow of people on the borders. In addition to adopting, along with the Zhuhai and Hong Kong authorities, alert measures related to the flow of people and vehicles, the corporation will reinforce measures in the places commonly frequented by citizens to enjoy the full moon and at the sights. Opposure, you may implement multitudes control measures.
As for the flow of vehicles, customs services pointed to the border exits to today between 18h00 and 21h00, and the morning of October 1. On the other hand, they foresee a peak of entries on October 7, from 18h00 to 21h00.
At the Macao border post on the Delta Bridge, 14 thousand entries and vehicles are foreseen per day during the golden week. The Hengqin post and the border of the doors of the siege may register, per day, 12 thousand and 9,500 vehicle tickets, respectively.
On the other hand, according to the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), the markings for Macao hotels during the period of the Golden Week reflect a “satisfactory” situation. According to it, STD is working on several domains to receive visitors, including disclosure on multiple channels, reinforcement of communication with the sector and interdepartal inspections, in order to ensure the quality of tourist services.
According to the body, the Macao Grand Prix Museum will open free to the public on October 1st and will have doors open on October 7, original closing day.
In addition, STD highlighted cooperation with China's interior CTRip travel platform in the weekly disclosure of data on the continental tourists in Macao in this period of holidays, in order to allow the sector to better understand the trend and, consequently, to do the preparations well.
In turn, the Consumer Council (CC) will make a special service available on October 1.2, 4, 5 and 7, through which you will receive consultations and complaints from residents and tourists. In addition, the CC promised to provide suitable services to needy tourists through “close contact” with other government services based on a notification mechanism.
The direction of sea and water issues has been driving the removal of garbage from the bathing zones of Praia de Hac-Sá and repairing the premises damaged by the recent typhoon, in order to “do the possible so that most of the HAC-Sá beach zones return to normality before the national day”.
 
“Significant increase” of local mobility
In turn, the Directorate of Services for Traffic Affairs (DSAT) predicted that, due to the coincidence of the National Day holiday with the lunar cake festival, there will be a “significant increase” of the number of visitors to the territory and local mobility compared to previous years. In this sense, DSAT has ensured that it has reinforced the global traffic planning and established several plans and contingency.
According to DSAT, the two bus companies will increase the frequency of matches and, between October 1 and 8, will temporarily explore seasonal and special careers 3BX, 17T, 21at, 26Aat and 101xs, to reinforce transportation capacity and accelerate passenger flow. The surrounding road roads will be subject to provisional traffic conditioning.
Keeping the previous decongestation measures in the areas of East Square of the Cerco doors, Avenida de Almeida Ribeiro, Praia Grande, Zones adjacent to Rua dos Mercadores, Auto-Silo Pak Kong area, and in the old zapa zone, this time, will also use the ground floor area of ​​Auto-Silo Pak Kong for the installation of a provisional stoppage, which It will allow you to divert five careers from the “Ponte 16” stop, from October 1st to 8th, between 16h00 and 20h00.
In addition, in order to rationalize the situation of the stop “Ferreira Amaral Square”, at the same time and time, six careers will stop stopping at this stop, stopping at the stop of “Hotel Lisboa”.
In addition, the light meter will reinforce the services between October 1 and 8, the last match, during this period, uniformed to 11:59 pm.
From today or tomorrow, at all border stations the temporary stop zone and waiting queues for the "shuttle-bus" of hotels and casinos will also be extended. However, in the golden week, the "Shuttle-Bus" that connect the Delta Bridge border post to the outdoor port maritime terminal will operate on a direct point.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Travel agencies “won” 371 million in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/agencias-de-viagens-ganharam-371-milhoes-em-2024/</link><description>The gross surplus of Macau's travel agencies exceeded 370 million patacas in 2024, which represents an annual increase of about 44% and equals 72.5% of the level of 2019, indicates data from statistics and census services
 
The 183 Travel Agencies on the MSAR activity by 2024 (six more than 2023) registered, as a whole, a gross surplus of 371 million patacas, 43.6% more than the 258 million noted a year earlier, reported the direction of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC). This amount corresponds to 72.5% of the 512 million accounted for in 2019, the pre-pound year, when the highest level has been reached since the beginning of official statistical inquiries on this sector.
Between 2023 and 2024, the revenues of travel agencies grew 7.5% to 5.44 billion patacas. In turn, sector expenses rose 5.6% to 5.08 billion patacas, in a year when agencies had 3,818 workers (plus 16.8%).
According to DSEC, revenues from excursions (1.15 billion patacas) rose 33.3%, in annual terms, representing 21.1% of the total sector. Revenues from passenger transport tickets (1.13 billion) and driver's car rental (1.36 billion) increased 27.4% and 19.7%, respectively, and corresponded to 20.8% and 25.0% of the total. On the other hand, revenues derived from room reserve services fell 34.5% to 1.11 billion, or 20.4% of the total.
In the Chapter of Expenses, the value of purchases of goods/services and commissions descended 4.8% to 3.31 billion patacas, compared to 2023. DSEC highlights the decline of 35.1% in expenses in room reserve services (1.09 billion patacas), in contrast to the additions of 29.8% in passenger transport tickets (1,08 billions (1,08 billion tickets of Patacas) and 16.8% in excursions (807 million patacas).
On the other hand, exploration expenses (1.04 billion patacas) and personnel spending (726 million) registered homologous agencies of 29.4% and 37.8%, respectively. By justifying these high evolutions, DSEC stresses that vehicle expenses have increased and more drivers were recruited.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Festival promotes sea culture</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/festival-promove-cultura-maritima/</link><description>A lecture, a boat trip and a visit to the museum are highlights of the “Marítimo Festival” program, promoted in October for maritime and water services. The event aims to publicize the public culture and history of Macau to the public



















The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) will organize, during October, the “Marítimo 2025 Festival”, bringing various activities to the public opening, boat visits, boat trip, thematic exhibition visits, pedagogical material display, workshops and game tents.
On two consecutive weekends, on the 11th, 12th, 18th and 19th, the Guide Lighthouse and the Piloting School will be open to the public. At the same time, the “boat trip” is held, with guided tours of professionals, allowing participants to know the history and maritime culture of Macao, as well as the daily work of the staff and the professional knowledge of the maritime areas of Macao. Registration for the tour is now available through the “Single Account” and the draw to be held by Dsama will have 480 awards.
For the first time, the “Guide” tug ”and the“ hydrography 5 ”survey boat will be displayed on the Barra da Barra bridge. The first to 11 October and the second to October 18, allowing the visit to the facilities on board. From 12:00 pm on the 7th, the visit of the visit can be made on the “Maritime Festival” page of the Dsama Electronic page.
The program also includes the “Maritime Coexistence Day”, on the 11th and 12th, at Largo do Pagode da Barra, the Maritime Museum and the Pilot School, with several workshops on maritime pollution prevention, maritime beacons display, teaching of pedagogical materials, guided tours of a thematic exhibition, exploration of navigation and learning publications.
There will also be tendon of games subordinate to the theme “Maritime Safety”, with knowledge of the lighthouse, mini-lecture and games.
In a statement, Dsama states that these activities aim to “deepen participants' understanding of the body's work on the guarantee of maritime security, as well as increase marine and water knowledge”, adding that the program is “varied and fun, suitable for families”.
Participants, as long as they have completed the tasks indicated on site and online, will be qualified to a draw, including transfringe passenger transport tickets, electronic watches, supermarket coupons, among others.
The “Maritime Festival” has the collaboration of transportation and game operators, namely Turbojet, Cotai Water Jet, Passenger Transport Agency Yuet Tung, Galaxy Entertainment, Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment, MGM, SJM, Wynn that will offer tickets for transmitting passenger transport and “cruise travel From Macao ”, with prizes to draw. The event also has MGM, which gives in spaces for the organization of one of the activities.
 
Dsama coordinated post-tuff cleaning in HAC-Sá
The Directorate of Maritime and Water Affairs Services (DSAMA) and the Macao Environment Volunteers Association, coordinated with the Waste Systems Company, sent about 30 people to the Balnear areas of HAC-Sá beach to remove the trash dragged by the “Ragasa” typhoon. DSAMA also coordinated with the Institute for Municipal Affairs the reparations of damaged facilities, so that the beach “returns to normal before the National Day of the Popular Republic of China,” says a statement. The passage of the super tuffer dragged a large amount of trees and tree branches to the maritime areas, which forced Dsama to mobilize "more workers and vessels to prioritarily remove the waste on navigation channels to ensure navigation safety." Warning to the likelihood that there are dead fish and sharp objects, among others, Dsama appealed to the population "so as not to move to the beaches of Hás and Cheoc van for rest or water entry before cleaning, in order to avoid accidents."
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chief enhances business opportunities in the great bay</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/chefe-realca-oportunidades-de-negocio-na-grande-baia/</link><description>Sam Hou Fai appealed to companies to “invest and develop business in Macao, Hengqin and the Great Bay” in a speech rendered under the “world convention of Cantonese entrepreneurs”. Over the course of three days, Canton welcomed the initiative, and the chief executive took advantage of the moment to promote “the unique advantages of Macau”
 
Today the third and last day of the “World Convention of Cantonese entrepreneurs” ends in the city of Cantão. In a discourse held in a digital format, Sam Hou Fai called on entrepreneurs from “different sectors and around the world” to “inspect the industry development environment, invest and develop business in Macau, Hengqin and the Great Bay” for “new and greater development”, according to a statement of the media.
The chief executive took the opportunity to remember the "strong tenacity" of the economy, "the harmony and stability" of society, as well as the "increasingly clear" position of the principle "a center, a platform, a base", in the mashes. "The unique advantages of Macao, such as Porto Franco status, separate customs territory and low tax regime, have been continually consolidated," he noted.
The leader of the MGI also asserted that, "Macao is not only a charming city of mixture of Chinese and Western cultures, but it is also the vibrant locomotive of opening full of business opportunities." In addition, for Sam Hou Fai, "the function of Macau as a commercial service platform between China and the Portuguese -speaking countries has been deepened," while "the construction of the deepened cooperation zone between Guangdong and Macau in Hengqin is moving fully."
"The impulse of the development of the great bay" is "opening a new and magnificent journey for cooperation and mutual benefits between Guangdong and Macao," he said. The Government of MSA has attributes a “high importance” and participates “with all efforts” in the development of the region, actively promoting “the connection of infrastructure, the articulation of rules and mechanisms and the connection between the residents of the great bay”, reiterated Sam Hou Fai.
The chief executive again argued that Macao's prosperity counts “with active participation” of companies, hoping to “jointly expand the world market” and transmit “the spirit of boldness and pioneer of Cantonenses entrepreneurs in the New Age”. According to the official, the government "is uniting and leading all sectors of society." He also promised that the executive will commit to "optimizing, as always, the business environment, improving the efficiency of public services, reinforcing the guarantees of the rule of law, and protecting the legitimate rights and interests of investors."
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Several activities mark national day</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/varias-actividades-assinalam-dia-nacional/</link><description>The solemn ceremony of the flags and the reception of National Day are two of the main celebration activities of the 76th anniversary of the Implementation of the Popular Republic of China, scheduled for tomorrow. The test “Running in Commemoration of National Day”, as well as a fireworks show, for the population, also integrate the event program
 
The celebrations in Macao on the 76th anniversary of the Implementation of the Popular Republic of China (RPC) include the solemn ceremony of the flags and the reception of National Day, a road athletics competition, as well as a fireworks show.
According to a statement issued by the Social Communication Office, the RPC and MSA flags will take place at Flor de Lotus Square, tomorrow, October 1, at 08h00, being chaired by the Chief Executive, Sam Hou Fai. Representatives of the Central Government, the Ministry of Foreign Ministry, and the ELP garrison in Macau, as well as the legislative and judicial bodies and holders of the main positions of MSAR, as well as other individualities of various quadrants of society will also be present. The live transmission will be ensured by the TDM - Macao teledifusion.
At 9:30 am, in the auditorium of the Complex of the Commercial Cooperation Platform between China and the Portuguese-speaking countries, the official reception is allusive to the anniversary of the Implementation of the RPC.
However, several public services will organize a range of allusive commemorative activities, among which, stands out, after the Bandeiras, the test called “Running in Commemoration of National Day and World March 2025”, organized by the Institute of Sport.
The Directorate of Post and Telecommunications Services will install at the Central Station's Lilac Station, from 9 am to 2 pm tomorrow a temporary post office, with the commemorative stamp “celebration of the 76th anniversary of the implementation of the Popular Republic of China”. In the same place, will be for sale commemorative envelopes to the unit price of five patacas.
At the same time, the Grand Prix and Macao museums and the Center for Science Centro of Sciences will be open to the public on October 1st. The Museum of Communications and the basis of the education of love for the homeland and Macau for young people will also be open doors.
The commemorative program also includes the exhibitions of the 33rd Macao International Fire Competition (CIFAM), with the teams from China and Portugal, tomorrow, and Filipinas and Japan, on Thursday, with scheduled sessions for 21h00 and 21h40.
The iconic Arraial do Fogo-Artifice will take place, on October 1st and 2nd, from 5:30 pm to 10:30 pm, on the riverside tour of the Macao Science Center. Alongside this, the old neighborhood of Taipa and Rua de Nossa Senhora do Amparo will be made temporary pedestrian zones, from 1 to 7 October, daily from 12h00 to 19h00.
Meanwhile, today, at 8 pm, the Venetian Theater will promote the “Haojiang Moonlight Night - New Acrobatic Cisne Show”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macau repeats distinction in conferences and business</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-repete-distincao-em-conferencias-negocios/</link><description>Macao was distinguished in the “TTG Travel Awards 2025” as the “best city for conferences and business”. This is the fourth award that the MSAR receives this year in the sector of conventions and exhibitions
 
For the fourth time in 2025, Macau received a "best city for conferences and business" award. The award was delivered to the representative of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM), during the “TTG Travel Awards” ceremony, held in Bangcoque, the capital of Thailand.
This is the third consecutive year in which Macao guarantees the International Sector Award, as "Best Asian Convention Destination."
The local sector received several distinctions this year, such as “Five Star Prize of the Forbes 2025 Travel Guide” and “Best Integrated Resort (Conventions and Exhibitions)”, which, according to IPIM, confirms the international recognition of Macao's capabilities in the area of ​​conventions and exhibitions.
In addition to the awards delivery session, IPIM, together with the Tourism Services Directorate (STD), coordinated 12 local and deepened cooperation companies in Hengqin, including travel agencies, convention and exhibition service providers and integrated tourism and leisure companies, to participate in “Encouven Travel &amp; Conventions Meetings Asia 2025”.
The representation of the MSA has installed the “Macau-Hengqin Pavilion”, in which it promoted the environment and advantages of conventions and exhibitions of Macao and Hengqin, attracting more international events of the MICE sector, both to the territory and to the deepened cooperation zone. In the same place, an exchange session was also organized, resulting in 456 commercial meetings.
During the event, IPIM also coordinated the participation of exhibiting companies in the “Global Mice Collaborative Certification” convention and exhibitions course, organized by three international convention and exhibition bodies, “providing practical knowledge” about MICE, underlines the IPIM's statement.
In the first half of this year, Macau organized 918 convention and exhibition events, representing an increase of 29% compared to the same period of 2024. Throughout the second semester, several events will be held in Macao, including the 18th World Commercial Convention, the 25th “Asian Congress of Surgery”, the 50th Portuguese Travel Agencies Congress and Tourism Congress. 32nd “Asia-Pacific Software Engineering Conference”. “This series of successes fully demonstrates the Macao Single Charm as a destination for international conventions and exhibitions,” concludes IPIM.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chocolate car and modern art in symbiosis at the GPM Museum</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/carro-de-chocolate-arte-moderna-em-simbiose-museu-gpm/</link><description>A 2.9 -meter -long dual -length chocolate supercar with hand -made length, with the outside of the color -designed car, is the latest attraction of the Macao Grand Prix Museum. The author of the culinary sculpture joined a fashion artist for the creation of a modern art show
 
In a multidisciplinary collaboration between Bob Tay, internationally awarded culinary, and the popular Swiss fashion designer Saiff Vasarhelyi, the Macao Grand Prix (MGPM) museum inaugurated a thematic exhibition, which is based on a supercar made of chocolate. The initiative joins Creativity, Aesthetics, Confectionery and Speed ​​to create a supercar that brings another thematic exhibition to “publicize the culture of competition and reinforce the attraction of destination as a creative city of gastronomy”, according to a note from the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD).
After his MGPM debut in 2024, Bob Tay created a 2.9 -meter -long double -length double chocolate supercar. The outside of the car was conceived with colorful graffiti of fluid lines with vibrant colors and improved details, highlighting the dynamism of supercar and the possibilities of the art of confectionery.
Saiff Vasarhelyi is passionate about car culture and often incorporates elements of motorized sports in their works of art, having already collaborated with several international brands and exposed around the world.
“Allied to its influence on social networks, the exhibition of the artist's work on MGPM will effectively involve audiences of various origins and will help spread the museum and the great award,” says STD.
The show “Macao Grand Prix Museum x Wynn Chocolate Supercar Exhibition”, which will be evident to the public until November 16, was inaugurated at a ceremony attended by STD Director Maria Helena de Senna Fernandes, Sub Institute Sub Institute Director, Law Si Leng and Wynn Marketing Director Zoe Zou, and two artists.
In tune with the holidays of China National Day, MGPM will have free admission Wednesday, October 1, while the end of the space, scheduled for October 7, Tuesday, was canceled, so it will also be open to the public. The usual time of the museum is between 10h00 and 18h00. Ticket purchase is available on the MGPM page.
STD recalls that, after the completion of the expansion works in 2021, the museum reopened with a new face, having continued to increase multimedia interactive exposure items, the exhibition of the great award scenario, the running cars and the related objects, to provide visitors with “an experience of‘ education and fun ’, showing the diversity of“ Tourism +’and” and “Tourism +’ and ” contributing to raise the tourist attractiveness of the MSAR ”.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caligraphs and painters expose “Songs of Glory” to paint and brush</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caligrafas-pintoras-expoem-cancoes-da-gloria-tinta-pincel/</link><description>Half a hundred works of Caligrophes, painters and sculptors of Macao stamps make up the exhibition “Songs of Glory in Paint and Brush”, which will be inaugurated today at the Rui Cunha Foundation gallery. Participate in the show 30 local artists
 
The Rui Cunha Foundation (FRC) will inaugurate today, at 18:30, the annual collective exhibition “Songs of Glory to Tint and Brush - celebrating the 80th anniversary of the victory of the Chinese people in the war against Japan and the world victory against fascism”. The event, co-organized by the Association of Caligraphs, Painters and Sculptors of Macao Seals (Acpesm), brings together almost 50 works under the curatorship of President Hong San San Rodrigues.
The exhibited works were carried out by more than 30 local caps and painters that, joining efforts in the national purpose of celebrating the great official ephemerides of the Popular Republic of China, present their artistic interpretation in works of calligraphy, painting and engraving of sinetes, encompassing “historical scenes, patriotic poetry and peace themes, using the language of traditional art to revisit significant moments of the past past and transmitting belief in peace, ”can be read in a statement from the HRF.
Hong San San, as Acpesm's president, states that "artists of this association have always worked in close collaboration with the homeland." In this exhibition, members instill “their deep knowledge of history and sincere praise for peace in their creations of traditional Chinese culture”, using brush and paint as a container and notch knives as material.
Each work "carries with them the memory of martyrs and a deep affection for the country, and it is expected to serve as a bridge to unite the force that safeguards the prosperity of the homeland and the stability of Macao, writing a new chapter for peace and world development."
According to the manifesto of the curator, each piece of the exhibition is a "sincere confession" of the female artists of Macau: "In the powerful traits lies the adamant dorsal spine of our mountains and rivers; in the dark colors, the silhouettes of our martyrs wielding weapons; in deep engravings, the noble responsibility that the ascension and fall of a nation are the duty of each citizen."
Through the language of art, “we express our understanding of history and our admiration for peace”, while “we record our unshakable original intention of patriotic love by Macao”, the artists also highlight.
The exhibition will be evident to the public until October 11th.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Cultural Week exalts “mutual understanding”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/semana-cultural-exalta-entendimento-mutuo/</link><description>The Cultural Week of China and Portuguese-speaking countries will take place until Thursday in the fishermen's dock, presenting a program stuffed with various activities, such as musical performances, gastronomic performances and handicrafts. At the opening ceremony, the Secretary-General of the Macao Forum stressed that this initiative aims to “fully enhance the important role of masters in the promotion of cultural exchange and mutual understanding between peoples”



















Victor Rebelo
 
The Legend Boulevard Square of Doca dos Fishermen was the scene of the first events of this year's edition of China Cultural Week and Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP) in Macau, a event that will take place until October 2, Thursday, with emphasis on musical performances, gastronomic performances and handicrafts. For the first time, the event is extended to Zhongshan and Beijing.
At the inaugural ceremony, which was attended by more than a dozen guests, including Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin Yip, the Secretary-General of the Forum Permanent Secretariat for Economic and Commercial Cooperation between China and the PLP, which is responsible for the organization of the event, enhanced the role of the event, “allowing participating countries in the organization. of exchange activities of sino-illusopone cultures in the interior of China and, in particular, in the cities of the Great Bay ”.
Ji Xianzheng also stressed that “this initiative is intended to fully enhance the important role of Macao”, as a platform between China and the Lusophone nations, “fostering cultural exchange and mutual understanding between peoples”.
In addition, he stated that this edition of the Cultural Week brings together artists and artists of Beijing, Qinghai, Zhejiang and Zhuhai, as well as singers and programs from Macau, “congregating the traditional and media media, in order to expand their dissemination, which allows you to create conditions for a better knowledge of PLP artists about China”.
Prior to the opening ceremony, the guests visited the Craft Fair, as well as the exhibition, sale and live demonstrations of artisans. Then, the show “Artistic and Synusophone Sounds and Sounds-Dance and Music Sounds”, with artists from the Chinese province of Qinghai and the PLP, was held.
The main activities of the 17th Cultural Week to take place in Macau include a collective exhibition of audiovisual works at the University of Science and Technology, a handicraft show and gastronomic experiences, “fully highlighting the cultural charm of China and Lusophone countries,” according to the Forum.
For the performances of singular music and dance and works of art, there will be the participation of 72 performic artists and 12 artisans from the interior of China, Mashes and nine Portuguese -expression countries.
Also noteworthy is the gastronomic festival that brings together five renowned kitchen chefs from Brazil, Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea and Mozambique, in collaboration with local restoration professionals. The event “created a special menu that combines the typical flavors of Lusophone cuisine, offering a tasting of the delicacies of these countries, as well as a unique experience of the rich gastronomic culture,” says the Forum.
In addition, on October 24, a literary work of Angola, translated into Chinese language, entitled “Is this book a novel?” Will be launched? ” of writer João Melo. And, between October 25 and November 18, works of art will be exhibited from the PLP in the Institute Gallery for Municipal Affairs.
In Zhongshan, the activities of the Cultural Week will take place until October 12, integrating musical shows in Xingzhong Square and a fine arts exhibition at the Xiangshan Museum of Commercial Culture.
In Beijing, Big Shopping Park Square receives on October 3 and 4, Friday and Saturday, music and dance performances and other promotional events. “This strategy aims to reinforce the Macao Sino-Lusopone Platform and promote a broader cultural exchange, showing the Lusophone cultural diversity to a wider audience in China,” expresses the forum's permanent secretariat.
The organization of the cultural event has the collaboration of the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment, Tourism Services and the AMI, and the support of various Lusophone matrix associations.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal and Galaxy launch employment and training plan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsal-galaxy-lancam-plano-de-emprego-formacao-2/</link><description>Galaxy Macau Grand Opening_ Staff from Gaming Hall



The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) and Galaxy Entertainment (GEC) will launch a “GEC elite development plan”. Following the “first hiring, after training” model, the program will provide, for 12 months, training opportunities in a work context related to business inquiries and management of facilities to residents of Macao who intend to join the integrated leisure and tourism services sector. Interested parties can register until October 5th on the thematic page available on the DSAL website. The plan offers 12 job openings, including four for “inspectors” and eight for “engineering affairs”. Program content includes integrated training before employment, English conversation course at “Lingaskills General - Cambridge English Language Assessment”, Open Source Certification Course, Galaxy Basic Level Management Techniques, Equipment Management Safety Training and related to techniques testing certification. Trainees who demonstrate “good performance” will have the opportunity for progression to higher level inspectors or engineering technicians, still having a salary adjustment. Thus, it underlines DSAL, will be given “support for the development of the professional career and the upward mobility of Macao residents who are interested in integrating in the integrated tourism and leisure services sector”.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Drones illuminate “Toy Story” nights at Studio City</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/drones-iluminam-noites-de-toy-story-studio-city/</link><description>In celebration of the National Day of the People's Republic of China and the Fall Festival, Studio City will organize, on October 4th and 5th, Saturday and Sunday, a show where more than a thousand drones will illuminate the night of Macao. Toy Story Drone Carnival will take place at the Event Garden, located on the third floor of Studio City. In each night, the drones will have two sessions, at 20h00 and 9:45 pm, featuring images of Woody, Buzz Lightyear and other Toy Story characters, “turning the sky above Studio City into a light story that unfolds in light,” says Melco Resorts &amp; Entertainment. Emotion will continue on the ground with a selection of offers, including lively gaming booths, Toy Story themed beverages, among other amusements, where participants can interact to win awards or exchange memories. The guests who are registered with Melco (resorts) can take a guest under 18 years, with vacancies being limited and available in order of arrival. The Studio City Event Garden will be transformed into a “perfect outdoor scenario, offering a sparkling playground with immersive photographic moments,” including an inflatable six -meter -high Woody.</description><pubDate>2025-09-30 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Centenary doctor in Japan still exerts medicine with no intention of reforming</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/medica-centenaria-japao-ainda-exerce-medicina-sem-intencao-de-se-reformar/</link><description>A woman over 100 years old from Wakayama province in Japan continues to exercise medicine to support the health of local residents. Dr. Teru Kasamatsu, a doctor at Kasamatsu Hospital in Kainan, serves external patients three days a week, especially ordinary patients.
At the hospital facing Wakayama Bay, Kasamatsu wore a white gap and talked to patients with a kind smile while checking their medical records. "Your blood pressure is a little high," he told a patient. "Please bring your medicine registration book the next time."
The hospital was founded in 1909, and Kasamatsu examines and treats residents as a doctor for almost 80 years. Your belief as a doctor is very clear. "The best thing to do is hear what the sick means," he said.
Now, his second son, Dr. Satoshi, 68, is the director of the hospital, and his wife, Dr. Hitomi, 61, heads the Nursing Department. Kasamatsu has a great confidence of both.
Satoshi said, "She's great to create an atmosphere where it's easy to talk. Patients trust her."
Dr. Kasamatsu was born in 1925 where Kinokawa is today in Wakayama province, as the youngest of five brothers. He chose to become a doctor because the war intensified while still attending female secondary education. Seeing many women lose their husbands in the war, his father recommended that he learned to sustain himself, Kasamatsu said.
He studied a lot and became a doctor in 1948. He married Shigeru, an orthopedic surgeon at the age of 24. When Shigeru took over her father's Kasamatsu Hospital, she began working at the hospital unit with her husband.
The couple managed the hospital together as they raised three children. She said she sometimes served 120 patients a day. As the hospital used to receive urgent patients, it was not uncommon to stay up all night to attend surgeries.
“I did everything from examining the patients to dispense with medicines and accounting,” he recalled. When the hospital began to accept more hospitalized sick and needed a cook to provide meals, he decided to do so alone and got a cook license when he was over 30 years old.
Despite his busy and busy days, he continued to work with energy, even though he was hospitalized for cancer treatment. Dr. Kasamatsu states that the secret of his longevity and health is in his diet.
"Eat a lot of vegetables, such as spinach, broccoli, kale and okra. Eating vegetables helps keep blood sugar levels low, so it's good."
Shigero died in 2012 at the age of 91, and Kasamatsu is currently alone in the house, which is next to the hospital. Even at 100, it is still without cane. It receives support from people around it, however, remains healthy both physically and mentally.
Its daily routine is to resolve numerical puzzles, which, according to itself, is a way of preventing dementia. Spends one to two hours a day to solve them to keep the mind active.
Kasamatsu's hobby is the piano, which started playing at age 70, inspired by Shigeru, who had already begun to learn before her. Plays with skill as it traputes pieces like Moon River. It also has weekly classes and endeavored to dominate Für Elise, from Beethoven, even performing in a recital alongside young people.
It also tries to update your medical knowledge by reading medical association materials whenever you have time. She has no intention of reforming herself. “I'm not feeling bad,” he says.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-09-29 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>