<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Children's support center warns of “strained family relationships”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/centro-de-apoio-criancas-alerta-para-relacoes-familiares-tensas/</link><description>Boy in white shirt on the green background



The Macau Children's Protection Center dealt with 59 cases between January and September this year, registering a small increase in abuse situations. Four of the 11 suspected cases of mistreatment involved sexual abuse, revealed the director of the Center, also highlighting the increase in the age range of children supported by the institution this year. In the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, Bondy Li highlighted that the issue that should deserve more attention in the work to protect children is mental health within families, since “situations of mental instability among both parents and children have increased”
 
In the first nine months of this year, the Children's Protection Center of the Macau Association for the Fight Against Child Abuse handled a total of 59 cases. Eleven are suspected cases of ill-treatment.
According to the Center's director, Bondy Li, the total number of cases registered until the end of September is almost equivalent to that recorded in the same periods of 2024 and 2023. However, she noted that suspected cases of abuse have slightly increased, compared to the same period last year.
In an interview with TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, Bondy Li warned that tense family relationships, inadequate emotional management on the part of parents and the mental health problem of children about to enter puberty gave rise to many cases treated by the center.
According to the same person responsible, in the first nine months, physical violence continues to be the most frequent form of child abuse, as in recent years. Additionally, four of the 11 suspected cases of maltreatment involved sexual abuse of children. There was also one case of inadequate care and one in which the child witnessed domestic violence.
As for the remaining cases, Bondy Li described that, “although they are not as serious, the cases show relatively tense family relationships and long-term verbal conflicts within the family, which puts children in danger at any time”.
The center's director also highlighted a change. “The age range of victims registered this year is a little higher than last year and in 2023, with the majority being around 10 years old. Previously, children aged six to eight years old were more common”, he revealed. On the other hand, parents continue to be the main responsible for abuse.
Another phenomenon is that the perpetrators of the four cases of child sexual abuse are not family members, but other people in society, according to the center's director.
Regarding the common characteristics of families that could lead to child abuse, Bondy Li analyzed that couples who have conflicts between themselves “can gradually transform their problems into violence against children, whether physical or verbal”. Furthermore, he added, “acts [of maltreatment] can be carried out by some parents who have too high expectations for their children, or by those who suffer from too much pressure at work or economic conditions”.
On the other hand, he warned, families with children with special educational needs also face high risk. "Many parents do not understand or do not accept how their children are. Therefore, we need to make great efforts to make them understand the situation and use assessment services for their children. In fact, many parents do not have the courage to use this resource", he highlighted.
At this point, Bondy Li also pointed out that there have been, in the last two years, some cases in which the unemployment of a father or mother led to tensions in family relationships and outbursts with children.
In general, for the director of the Children's Protection Center, the issue that should deserve more attention in child protection work is the mental health of family members. This is because “situations of mental instability among both parents and children have increased”, he warned.
"Some parents are emotionally unstable and have no patience for children. They use intimidation methods, which causes fear and anxiety among children. On the other hand, many situations have recently arisen in which children who are almost puberty, who have tense relationships with their parents, have used threatening language during conflicts with their parents, such as 'if you take away my cell phone, I will get hurt'", said Bondy Li.
“In addition, [children almost at puberty] can also commit violent acts against their parents, and this type of situation has been gradually increasing recently,” he continued.
Bondy Li confessed that these types of problems surrounding mental health are beyond the treatment capabilities of an ordinary social worker. “Therefore, our colleagues must learn more to better understand these phenomena and be better able to discover risks in the mental state of parents or children, in order to be able to give them advice for psychological treatment”, he defended.
 
Increased awareness to ask for help
Regarding the sources of cases reported to the center this year, the person responsible noted that more than 50% are requests for help on their own initiative, which, in her opinion, reflects an increase in public awareness. "We are receiving more and more requests for support on our own initiative, especially related to problems at an early stage. They all know the law to prevent and combat domestic violence and do not want their problems to escalate to that level", said Bondy Li.
On the other hand, there are also cases uncovered by neighbors or friends who requested help from social workers, or referred by the Government or schools, especially those of a more serious nature, such as the 11 suspected cases of abuse.
However, ongoing intervention faces challenges arising from the complexity of fundamental family problem solving. "Some parents chose to communicate with us at the initial stage of their family problems. Later, we intended to carry out more in-depth work, however, they rejected our support because they thought the problem in question had already been resolved. However, a few years later, they asked for help again because they discovered the problem was getting worse", he pointed out.
In general, within the scope of child protection, Bondy Li stressed that there must be improvements in community awareness and professional training. "It is necessary to continually channel awareness-raising and community education resources about the law against domestic violence. Community education can play an alert role, and neighbors, family members and friends also have a very important protective role. They can make reports when the problem is not yet very serious", he stressed.
Furthermore, he highlighted that training must be continuous and extended to law enforcement personnel and all sectors that come into contact with children. “All people who work with children must be trained on how to protect children and the responsibility to notify their supervisor if they discover behavior that hurts children, so that the situation can be detected and treated as quickly as possible”, he emphasized.
Currently, the Child Protection Center provides a range of ongoing services to families in need, including education and emotional management, methods for raising children, adjusting expectations for children and supporting children with special educational needs. The center's services aim to help guardians to “change their mentality, be more patient with children and alleviate emotional pressure on the entire family”, described the director.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SMEs play a “fundamental role” in economic development</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/pme-desempenham-papel-fundamental-desenvolvimento-economico/</link><description>The role that small and medium-sized companies play in promoting innovation and economic development was analyzed at a Round Table, as part of the activities scheduled for the three fairs taking place at the Venetian's Cotai Expo. At the meeting, the Secretary for Economy and Finance highlighted the regular organization of training courses in Macau, which allow “to deepen investment opportunities in Mainland China and the needs of Portuguese-speaking markets”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
A Round Table aimed at small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) from China and Portuguese-speaking countries (PLP) focused on the cooperation and development of SMEs, with the aim of exchanging opinions “to create a pragmatic and efficient platform for sharing and dialogue”, according to the Secretary for Economy and Finance.
Tai Kin Ip said during the initiative, integrated into the activities of the three fairs that are taking place simultaneously for four days, at the Venetian's Cotai Expo, that SMEs play a “fundamental” role in promoting innovation and economic development”.
During the Round Table, in which graduates of the colloquiums on Capacity Building and Digital Economy between China and the PLP also participated, the minister highlighted that, “over the years, Mainland China, the Macao SAR and Portuguese-speaking countries have proactively promoted reinforced exchange between SMEs, either through holding, in different Portuguese-speaking countries, the Meeting of Entrepreneurs for Economic and Commercial Cooperation, or through the regular organization of various training courses in Macau”.
He highlighted that such initiatives allow participants to have a deeper understanding of investment opportunities in Mainland China, the needs of Portuguese-speaking markets and the unique advantages of Macau's role as a platform, “contributing to continuously raising Sino-Lusophone economic and commercial cooperation to broader and deeper levels”.
Earlier, at the joint inauguration ceremony of the three fairs, the 2nd China-Portuguese Speaking Countries (Macau) Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX), the 30th Macau International Fair (MIF) and the 2025 Macau Franchise Exhibition (MFE), Tai Kin Ip stressed that, with 30 years of existence, the MIF was developed “into a crucial platform” that promotes “the integration depth between industry and MICE (Conventions and Exhibitions) and establishes high-quality commercial contact channels”.
The three events and other conventions are held at the same time, which plays a role of “doubled effect”, meaning that “it will further reinforce the depth and breadth” of Macau as a platform for economic and commercial cooperation between China and the PLP, serving as a “broader” communication bridge for companies on both sides, “which will help produce the effect of doubling ‘MICE + the economy of the first store’”.
The Secretary believes that Macau will further strengthen contact with Mainland China and abroad and deepen the role of “super contact person” between China and the PLP, as well as publicize development opportunities within the scope of ‘Macau+ Hengqin’ and the joint construction of the “high-quality” Greater Bay Area.
At the same time, he assured that the Macao SAR will explore the potential for intersectoral cooperation, in order to expand the international “circle of friendship” and become an “important window for the country's high-quality opening to the outside world”.
The three fairs, also visited yesterday by the Chief Executive, will run until Saturday, presenting this year a total exhibition area of ​​almost 3,000 square meters, distributed in 19 zones and three pavilions. Together, they bring together more than 1,100 exhibitors, from more than 30 countries or regions. Lusophony alone has 320 “stands”, which represents an increase of 23% compared to 2024. In parallel, this year, for the first time, the China-PLP International Agricultural Expo will take place.
The three competitions are under the themes “Creating New Opportunities for Cooperation Based on the New Development Pattern”, “Macau, Gateway to Global Business” and “Brands without Borders, Shared Opportunities”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>2025 is the year with the most signs of tropical storms</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/2025-e-ano-mais-sinais-de-tempestade-tropical/</link><description>After the 13th tropical storm signal was raised in Macau during the passage of “Fengshen”, this year broke the record for the highest number of tropical storm signals issued in a single year since 1968
 
Due to the influence of the tropical storm “Fengshen”, the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG) issued the 13th tropical storm signal this year on Monday night, which set a new record for the highest number of tropical storm warnings issued in a single year since 1968, the year in which records began in the territory. As they recalled, the previous record was 12 warnings issued, set in 1974.
The SMG concluded that, in addition to breaking the aforementioned record, “Fengshen” also represents the fifth time in history that tropical storm signal 3 was directly emitted without signal 1 having been emitted.
On the other hand, according to the organization, due to the combined influence of a strong northeast monsoon and “Fengshen”, the wind in Macau began to blow from the north, relatively strong, on Monday. Due to the predominance of north and northeast winds and topographic barriers, the average wind strength was not particularly strong, but gusts repeatedly reached levels 7 or 8 on the “Beaufort” Scale.
"With the arrival of autumn, the northeast monsoon becomes more active, resulting in the frequent occurrence of autumn tropical cyclones (autumn typhoons) simultaneously with this monsoon. This increases uncertainty regarding the impact of the winds", warned the SMG.
Analyzing “Fengshen”, the SMG indicated that, due to the passage of a strong northeast monsoon that moved south, the pressure gradient in the coastal regions of South China increased, leading to an increase in intensity. Therefore, the signal of strong monsoon winds (black ball) was initially emitted.
As “Fengshen” crossed the central and/or northern part of the South China Sea, in combination with the influence of the northeast monsoon, the atmospheric pressure gradient on the coast of South China increased further, resulting in a strengthening of wind intensity. Consequently, the circulation associated with the tropical cyclone had an increased impact on Macau, leading the SMG to directly issue tropical storm signal 3. According to what they analyzed, with the removal of “Fengshen”, the atmospheric pressure gradient lost strength and intensity, which is why the “black ball” signal was raised again.
Regarding the following days, the organization predicted that the northeast monsoon will ease, while the sky will be less cloudy, with a slight increase in temperatures. However, he warned, during the mornings and evenings, the weather in the region will remain relatively cold. Yesterday, the minimum temperature dropped to 16.8 degrees Celsius, the lowest recorded in Macau since the start of autumn.
It should be remembered that, at the beginning of this month, Typhoon “Matmo” forced the 12th tropical storm signal to be raised in Macau this year. It was also the fourth time that the SMG issued tropical storm signal 8. Signal 8 has only been raised in the territory four times in the space of a year: in 1993, 2008 and 2022 and 2025.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Associations finalize preparations for another Lusofonia Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/associacoes-ultimam-preparativos-para-mais-um-festival-da-lusofonia/</link><description>澳門中葡文化藝術節 2024銀娛葡韻嘉年華



Starting tomorrow, Casas da Taipa will host another edition of the Lusofonia Festival. This year, the featured country is Angola, which will have a stand in the shape of an agricultural machine. Meanwhile, the “barraquinha” in Portugal will reproduce “Os Impérios do Divino Espírito Santo”, small religious constructions from the Azores. The event coordinator, António Machado, told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that he hopes that “people come back to the space, thus continuing the success that the festival has had since it was created”
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
Weather forecasts predict sun in the coming days, without rain, which is “excellent news” for those preparing to head to Casas da Taipa tomorrow, the opening day of this year's edition of the Lusofonia Festival.
The event coordinator told TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper that he hopes the predictions are confirmed, “so that people come back to the space, thus continuing the success that the festival has had since it was created”. António Machado emphasizes that “everything is ready for the party”, considering that the program “will certainly please the public, with a lot of musical diversity, gastronomy, traditional games and lots of interaction between people from the most varied cultures”.
The employee at the Cultural Institute responsible for the details of organizing the event emphasizes that “this spirit between communities, cultural exchange, has always been our first objective and I think we have managed to disseminate to the public the culture that has been rooted here for more than 400 years”.
He recalls that he was the president of the then Chamber of Islands, Madeira de Carvalho, in 1998, the great mentor of the Festival da Lusofonia. “At that time, the event was for just one day and was organized individually, that is, a party among friends, representing the Portuguese-speaking communities based here, as there were no associations yet”, he highlights.
This meeting point, he guarantees, “was the beginning of a popular festival, which lasted two days the following year and later three”. The idea that emerged 28 years ago has been a “great success”, because “everyone contributed to it, the associations, created in the meantime, the visitors, keeping unchanged the components that presided over the organization of the festival since its beginning, but with the improvements we want with regard to the quality of the artists present”, he points out.
The extension of the festival period to two consecutive weekends, since last year, “was the result of this success and we feel that the local population is hungry for this type of initiatives with great tradition in the territory”, he observes.
In recent days, the hustle and bustle of elements linked to the respective associations has increased to finalize details, with a view to completing the “stalls”.
 
From Angolan agriculture to Azorean symbols
The newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU had already published some of the themes of the stalls that will be lined up along the avenue where Casas da Taipa are located, such as Bossa Nova do Brasil and café de Moçambique, but all associations will have themed spaces to promote to visitors. Two examples come from Casa de Portugal, which presents as its main focus the “Empires of the Divine Holy Spirit” of the Azores, and Angola, which promotes agriculture, reproduced in a tractor, or agricultural machine.
The African country was given the spotlight in this year's edition of the Festival, which is why a cook and an artist are in Macau. “Chef Lisandra, from Luanda, will prepare typical Angolan dishes, while Armando Scott will be doing paintings and portraits of people,” the president of the Angola Macau Association, Anacleto Cabaça, told JTM, adding that Nelma Silvestre is responsible for all the artistic aspects of the tent.
As for Casa de Portugal, president Amélia António told our newspaper that the idea of ​​introducing the “Impérios do Divino Espírito Santo”, originally from the Azores, comes as a result of “trying to do something different, after so many years of participating”.
Present on all the Azorean islands, small religious buildings, generally colorful and decorated, occupy a central place in the life of the parishes. More than buildings, they are spaces for meeting, sharing and celebration, they become the stage for the Espírito Santo festivities, between April and June.
According to an explanatory panel that will be displayed in the “barraquinha” of Casa de Portugal, “these celebrations include symbolic coronations, processions and the generous distribution of food – bread, meat and the traditional Espírito Santo soup – offered free of charge to the community”. These are gestures that “reflect the values ​​of humility, fraternity and solidarity that define this devotion”, adds the text, informing that the tradition dates back to the 15th century, brought by the first Portuguese settlers.
“Over time, this tradition acquired a unique expression in the Azores, mixing Christian faith with community practices, having evolved from mobile and simple structures to fixed buildings, many of them decorated with crowns, doves and flags, symbols that enrich the spiritual and visual heritage of the islands”, describes the panel.
In addition to this central theme, Casa de Portugal will have gastronomy spaces next to Largo no Carmo, through food from the Lvsitanvs restaurant, and downstairs with coffee, sweets, savory snacks and snacks, but also crafts, ceramics, traditional games, led by Cândido de Azevedo, an entertainment area for children and the usual table football championship.
In addition to the associations mentioned above, representatives from Cape Verde, Guinea-Bissau, Equatorial Guinea, São Tomé and Príncipe, Timor-Leste, Goa, Daman and Diu, in addition to the Macanese community, also participate in the event.
 
Community shows start in Bairro Iao Hon
Some of the musical artists who will perform on the festival stage are starting to perform today in Bairro Iao Hon, as part of the program of shows in the community, with performances scheduled between 6:30 pm and 8:30 pm by bands Memu Sunhu, from Guinea-Bissau, and Rui Orlando, from Angola, as well as dance groups from China, Guangdong, Negros Unidos, Guinea Equatorial, and Carimbó Paidégua, from Brazil.
Throughout the weekend there will be other musical “shows”, including Kalema, on Saturday, at 8 pm, and there will be performances by other groups, singers and local bands during the afternoon of the three days.
For Amélia António, the Lusofonia Festival continues to justify itself more and more. “The Portuguese community has decreased, but participation and people's presence has not decreased, it has even increased, because the local population and visitors are interested and really enjoy this festival, which is perhaps the one that attracts the most people”, he admits.
Comparing the Lusofonia Festival with the Cultural Week, both dedicated to the traditions and cultures of Portuguese-speaking countries, the leader regrets that the Cultural Week has few people, “because they insist on not promoting it, repeating the same mistakes every year, in an event that involves effort and expense and that continues to not have the intended impact”.
On the contrary, the Lusophone Festival of Hengqin, which took place recently and in which Casa de Portugal made its contribution, resulted in “success”, says Amélia António, for whom the event “went very well and on the organization side they were extremely collaborative, making it a very positive experience”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China urges EU to support free trade</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-insta-ue-apoiar-livre-comercio/</link><description>China yesterday said it expected the European Union to “support free trade” and “oppose protectionism”, after Chinese Commerce Minister Wang Wentao and European Trade Commissioner Maros Sefcovic spoke by telephone.
Chinese Foreign Ministry spokesperson Guo Jiakun said at a press conference that “the essence of economic and trade relations between China and the EU lies in complementarity and mutual benefit”. Guo expressed the hope that “the EU will fulfill its commitment to support free trade and oppose trade protectionism, and provide a fair, transparent and non-discriminatory business environment for companies in all countries”.
According to him, China expects the 27 to “adopt concrete measures to defend the market economy and the standards of the World Trade Organization” and “persist in the adequate resolution of trade differences through dialogue”.
During the call, Sefcovic invited Chinese authorities to visit Brussels to seek “urgent solutions” to the export controls on rare earths imposed by Beijing. The commissioner explained that Wang accepted the invitation to address the issue in the “next few days” in the Belgian capital, a visit that has not yet been confirmed by Chinese authorities.
“We have no interest in escalation, but the situation casts a shadow on our relationship, so a quick resolution is essential,” said the European Commissioner.
Sefcovic, who classified the discussion as “constructive”, recalled that Brussels considers that the increase in Chinese controls on exports since April is “unjustified and harmful” and damages the bilateral relationship between both parties, while at the same time going against attempts to achieve more stable and reliable trade.
The commissioner discussed with Wang the ban on the company Nexperia from exporting semiconductors produced in its factory in China, following the decision by the Netherlands to intervene in the company to prevent the transfer of knowledge to China by the company, which was founded in the Netherlands, but in 2019 was acquired by a Chinese group. In this sense, he said that both parties have communicated to him their intention to “resolve the situation and work towards a practical agreement that restores supply chains, provides much-needed certainty and avoids global production stoppages”.
 
Von der Leyen warns against rare earth dependencies
In turn, the president of the European Commission yesterday asked the EU to avoid “new and dangerous dependencies” on rare earths from China, which could become “instruments of pressure”, after the tightening of controls on Chinese exports.
"The others are not standing still: China exports almost twice as much clean technology as we do and this represents a risk of pushing our industries out of strategic markets, including our own. We cannot allow ourselves to fall into new and dangerous dependencies", said Ursula von der Leyen, speaking in a debate at the plenary session of the European Parliament in Strasbourg.
In a discussion ahead of Thursday's European Council meeting, the leader of the community executive noted: "In recent years, we have all witnessed what happens when a single country gains control over the supply of an essential product or technology." “At any time, these dependencies can become instruments of pressure [as] restrictions on exports can be imposed from one day to the next”, which leads to “supply routes being interrupted”, he added.
Alluding to recent Chinese announcements, Ursula von der Leyen warned that “factories here in Europe may be forced to slow down or even close”. For this reason, he asked the EU to be “very vigilant” and “control the technologies that will shape our future”, in terms of critical raw materials.
Ursula von der Leyen assured that she was “ready to propose additional measures to guarantee Europe's economic security” and defended, as already proposed, a “made in Europe” criterion for public contracts.
The European Commission reported concerns from the EU industry, especially automotive, due to the tightening of controls on exports of rare earths by China, which could affect supply chains, and is in contact with the Chinese authorities.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>23% of illegal smokers detected in casinos</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/23-dos-fumadores-ilegais-detectados-nos-casinos/</link><description>Casinos accounted for 23% of illegal smokers until September, followed by restaurants, with 15%, according to the balance of violations of the Tobacco Control Law and the Alcohol Consumption Control Law. More than 3,700 people were caught smoking in prohibited places between January and September
 
Between January and September, the Health Services (SSM) carried out 179 thousand inspections of establishments, a daily average of 656 inspections, as part of the inspection in relation to the Tobacco Control Law and the Alcohol Consumption Control Law. In total, 4,054 infractions were detected.
Regarding tobacco control, 3,744 cases were detected of people smoking in places where it is prohibited, 196 cases of transporting electronic cigarettes when entering and leaving the Macao SAR, and 103 suspected cases of violation of other provisions of the Tobacco Control Law, namely the failure to display signs prohibiting smoking in places provided for by law and the failure to display notices prohibiting the sale of tobacco products to minors under 18 years of age. Inspection actions were carried out by the SSM, Public Security Police Corps, Institute for Municipal Affairs, Gaming Inspection and Coordination Directorate and Customs Services, among others.
Specifically, and according to the balance of the first nine months, the largest number of infractions was detected in casinos, with a total of 842 cases (22.5% of the total). Catering establishments followed, with 552 cases (14.7%) and parks/gardens and leisure areas, with 319 (8.5%).
Regarding the control of alcohol consumption, in the same period, 11 suspected cases of violation of the Alcohol Consumption Control Law were registered, of which three related to the sale or provision of alcoholic beverages to minors. The other eight are related, for example, to the fact that sellers do not display signs prohibiting the sale of alcohol to minors or that advertising does not present warnings in Chinese, Portuguese and English. According to the SSM, “all these cases have already been instructed for due monitoring”.
The organization also revealed other cases. For example, the SSM discovered that a minor entrusted an adult with the purchase of alcoholic beverages, demonstrating that, although the supermarket complies with the law, “there are those who violate the prohibition of making alcoholic beverages available to them”. Note that offenders can be punished with a fine of 1,500 to 20,000 patacas.
Another case mentioned concerns several stores that sell tobacco products and that display accessories related to tobacco brands or logos in their windows, which is prohibited by law. The public display of tobacco brands or logos constitutes an act of tobacco advertising, with the offender being punished with a fine of 20 thousand to 200 thousand patacas.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CESL Asia presents high-tech agriculture projects</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cesl-asia-apresenta-projectos-de-agricultura-de-alta-tecnologia/</link><description>Technology-based projects are being presented by CESL Asia at the China-Portuguese-Speaking Countries Economic and Trade Exhibition. Among the innovative solutions proposed, the local company will launch key initiatives, including an aerospace innovation applied in the area of ​​agriculture
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
CESL Asia presents at the 2nd China-Portuguese-Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX) a set of pioneering projects and partnerships that aim to highlight its commitment to technological innovation and sustainable development. According to the local company, key initiatives will be announced during the fair period that kicked off yesterday at the Venetian's Cotai Expo, including: AgroPV, aerospace innovation applied to high-tech agricultural solutions and systems and asset management platforms based on Artificial Intelligence (AI).
“These initiatives demonstrate advances in high-tech agriculture, renewable energy, energy management and artificial intelligence that are driving sustainability and operational excellence”, says a note from CESL Asia.
AgroPV, one of CESL Asia's flagship references, integrates modern agricultural practices with the production of renewable energy through photovoltaic (PV) technology. This innovative model reflects the company's vision for sustainable agriculture “through technological synergy”, combining clean energy production with improved animal welfare and ecological resilience.
The AgroPV pilot solar plant at Monte do Pasto, an agricultural holding owned by CESL Asia in the Alentejo region, in Portugal, has an installed capacity of 243 kWp and produces approximately 387 MWh of electricity per year. With a covered area of ​​1,170 square meters, “it contributes to reducing the heat stress of cattle and protecting their natural behavior”, highlights the document.
According to CESL Asia, the support of a battery storage system allows the farm and its feed factory to achieve almost energy self-sufficiency, meeting up to 97% of its energy needs. The next step, he says, “is to expand the AgroPV system to hundreds of megawatts, covering various agricultural applications”.
In partnership with Spin.Works, a Portuguese aerospace company founded in 2006 and specialized in Earth observation and missions to the Moon and Mars, the Macau company that operates in the areas of environmental infrastructure, energy and facilities management, is developing space-time forecasting systems for agricultural and livestock operations.
Through the integration of remote optical photonic sensors, computer vision and AI-based analyses, the system, already implemented at Monte do Pasto and the solar plant, “improves productivity, product quality and sustainability”.
Spin.Works intends to expand these solutions, in partnership with CESL Asia, in the agricultural sectors of the European and Chinese markets. “The collaboration with EREN, a strategic investor in innovative low-carbon technologies, and with DLEC, a start-up specialized in the energy transition in Mainland China, aims to develop AI technologies in the Greater Bay Area to optimize the energy systems and HVAC operations of buildings”, highlights the note.
In introducing the projects that will be presented at C-PLPEX, the company based in the territory since 1987 considers that these innovations were designed to “improve energy efficiency, reduce carbon emissions and accelerate the region's transition to a more intelligent, ecological and sustainable infrastructure”. The joint venture is introducing these solutions to the Macau and Asian markets.
Developed internally by CESL Asia, together with a local technology partner, ORTUX is an intelligent People, Asset and Resource Management platform that supports more efficient and productive asset management. “By integrating AI technologies, with CESL Asia’s more than 35 years of operational experience, ORTUX can increase efficiency by more than 35% and reduce installation maintenance costs by between 25% and 35%, promoting sustainability and profitability”, highlights the company chaired by Portuguese businessman António Trindade.
Through these innovative initiatives and partnerships, CESL Asia pursues the objective of combining cutting-edge technology with sustainability, strengthening collaboration between China and Portuguese-speaking countries. “CESL Asia's participation in C‐PLPEX reaffirms its commitment to the exchange of knowledge, sustainable economic growth and international cooperation, based on its business platform based in the Macao SAR”, he emphasizes.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Portuguese agricultural products having “difficulties” entering China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/produtos-agricolas-portugueses-dificuldades-para-entrar-na-china/</link><description>Portugal has excellent products and a “very significant interest” in the Chinese market, although it faces adversities that limit entry into the Asian country, said the Secretary of State for Agriculture, João Moura, yesterday.
“The difficulties are many, many times, in terms of diplomatic relations, exports, imports – some adjustments that need to be made”, admitted to journalists João Moura, who is in Macau representing the Government at the 30th Macau International Fair (MIF) and the 2nd China-Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition (C-PLPEX), which are taking place simultaneously.
In parallel, the China-Portuguese Speaking Countries International Agricultural Expo is organized for the first time.
These events, the person responsible highlighted, are “a great window of opportunity” to smooth out “some rough edges”.
“We are in an interpretation that is often differentiated between markets as different as Portugal and China, in which food analysis and control have their differences, have their valences and, therefore, there is nothing better than talking, sitting at the table to try to overcome some of these difficulties and adversities”, he added.
Portugal, said the Secretary of State, has “several ideas” and “several products with great potential”, namely dried fruits, pork, olive oil and wine. “We have a lot of opportunity for Portuguese products that are widely accepted in China,” he said.
“We have products with great export capacity, with great worldwide acceptance and, therefore, the Chinese market is a market that is of very significant interest to us”, he stated.
In the opposite direction, he declared that he felt in Macau “a great interest from China” in Portugal, not only in terms of exports, but also with regard to the “internationalization of some Chinese companies”.
Companies in the field of technology, machinery or equipment in the area of ​​agriculture, said João Moura, without providing additional details about these companies. “They are very interested in the development of some sectors of our agriculture and we are open to welcome them”, he concluded.
In a speech given during the Round Table of Small and Medium-Sized Enterprises in China and Portuguese-Speaking Countries, the Portuguese representative highlighted the “crucial role” of Macau as a connection platform, noting that the geographical and cultural position of the territory makes it “a point of convergence between East and West”, facilitating trade and investment.
"In turn, Portugal has, in the global context, a strategic position that connects the Eastern world and the American continent, without forgetting the African continent. These more agile and integrative platforms encourage and provide commercial exchanges and the growth of new companies", he said.
A survey published in May this year by the European Union Chamber of Commerce in China concluded that European companies are cutting costs and reducing investment plans in the Asian country, as the economy slows down and fierce competition drives down prices. “Faced with a series of challenges – including the persistence of regulatory and market access barriers, increased geopolitical tensions, price deflation, low domestic consumption and reduced margins – Chamber members’ optimism regarding short and medium-term prospects is now at a historically low level”, reads the report accompanying the results of the survey.
 
JTM with Lusa</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>National security without “margin for error”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/seguranca-nacional-sem-margem-para-erro/</link><description>In the first working meeting with the team, the new Secretary for Security, Chan Tsz King, stressed that “the defense of national security is the main mission in the area of ​​security” and said that “no margin for error is allowed” in this field
 
Chan Tsz King, who recently took office as Secretary for Security, replacing Wong Sio Chak, highlighted, at the first working meeting of the authority he heads, that “the defense of national security is the main mission in the area of ​​security, and no margin for error is allowed”. The Secretary noted that, “in view of the international situation, national security circumstances have become complex and there are many challenges”.
In this sense, he indicated that defending national security “means safeguarding the security of Macau and both are inseparable”. Furthermore, Chan Tsz King demanded that the security team be “fully aware of the meaning of the act of oath, deeply understanding the main idea of ​​the term of the oath, reviewing its initial objective of joining the security forces”. It must also strive to “safeguard the essential values ​​of the security forces, namely, love for the country, love for Macau, loyalty, obedience, honesty and integrity, as well as cultivating a positive, disciplined institutional image that dares to assume responsibilities and deserves the trust of citizens”.
At the same work meeting, the government official recognized the past efforts of the security team and praised “the excellent results achieved”. Furthermore, Chan Tsz King reiterated the importance of integrity and self-discipline, indicating that “the practice of criminal acts by law enforcers undermines public expectations about the legal order and seriously affects society's confidence in the rule of law”, according to a press release.
“When exercising authority powers, the police team must act in accordance with the law, in the interest of the population and in a prudent manner”, he stressed, emphasizing that it is “important” to create a mechanism to prevent corruption. “However, the most important thing is for the team to always have an awareness of integrity in mind, to ‘not dare, be powerful and be corrupt’”, he said, adding that directors and managers must “serve as an example, without ambiguity in this matter”.
At this meeting, the Secretary took stock of the work and results obtained over the previous years, conveyed the concept of governance and planned the future direction of the work.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Digital literacy at the 10th IPOR meeting on language teaching</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/literacia-digital-10o-encontro-ipor-sobre-ensino-de-linguas/</link><description>The next edition of the “Asia PLE Teaching Network Points Meeting” will take place between November 21st and 22nd, under the theme “Digital literacy and PLE teaching-learning through technology”
 
The Instituto Português do Oriente (IPOR) will hold the tenth “Meeting of Asian PLE Teaching Network Points” (EPR), on the 21st and 22nd of November. This year's theme will be “Digital literacy and PLE teaching-learning through technology”. The launch session will take place at 9am on November 21st, at the Dr. Stanley Ho Auditorium of the Consulate-General of Portugal in Macau and Hong Kong, according to a statement from IPOR.
This year's EPR will focus on “the transformative impact that new information and communication technologies, together with recent advances in artificial intelligence, have been having on language teaching in general and the Portuguese language in particular”. “Special attention will be given to technological tools that open up new educational possibilities, and, subsequently, to the way in which these changes have influenced pedagogical practices and the learning process”, says IPOR.
The institute believes that teaching and learning a foreign language “implies the development of multiple communicative skills”. The classroom thus constitutes “the privileged space to provide students with real opportunities for interaction and use of language in authentic contexts”, can be read on the IPOR website.
Furthermore, “New Information and Communication Technologies allow access to varied and authentic content, which exposes students to different cultures, values ​​and forms of communication, expanding their intercultural understanding”. Digital resources have been “revolutionizing the educational landscape”, allowing active methodologies that involve students in a dynamic way and contribute “to developing intercultural skills”. It is in this context that “digital literacy emerges as an essential competence”, argues IPOR.
Within the scope of this year's theme, three axes of work were outlined, namely “the importance of digital literacy in teaching and learning foreign languages”, “digital tools for teaching and learning PLE” and “pedagogical approaches for teaching PLE”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Lu Nan returns to Portugal with portraits of the human condition in Asia</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lu-nan-volta-portugal-retratos-da-condicao-humana-na-asia/</link><description>“Ocher Space”, in Lisbon, today marks the return of Chinese photographer Lu Nan to Portugal, in a presentation of 63 analogue photographs from the “Prisons of Northern Burma” project, according to a press release. For this series, the artist lived with prisoners affected by drug trafficking in the north of the country for three months. The images show "men chained, bodies marked by dependence, empty looks. But also moments of care, of sharing humanity." Coordinated and curated by João Miguel Barros, the exhibition also includes a 28-minute video of his project “Trilogia”, which was presented in 2018, at the Museu Colecção Berardo, in addition to the respective 225 photographs. Over the course of 15 years, Lu dedicated himself to this three-part work, which constitutes “a visual meditation on the human condition”. The 56 photographs of the “Forgotten People” portray mental illness in China. “On the Road” focuses on the presence of the Catholic Church in China, with 60 images. In “Four Seasons”, the 109 images constitute a portrait of the daily lives of Tibetan peasants. Lu has become an unavoidable figure in Chinese photography, with a work distinguished “not by quantity, but by density”. Each project is the result of years of coexistence, silence and attention. Your camera is neither a weapon nor a mirror, it is an extension of listening", the note reads. Until November 29th, the public will be able to visit the exhibition from 3:00 pm to 6:30 pm local time, between Wednesdays and Saturdays.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>DELTA BRIDGE WELCOMED 93 MILLION PASSENGERS IN SEVEN YEARS OF OPERATION</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ponte-delta-acolheu-93-milhoes-de-passageiros-em-sete-anos-de-operacao/</link><description>default



Since its official opening to traffic on October 24, 2018, the Hong Kong-Zhuhai-Macau Bridge has recorded more than 93.34 million people entering and leaving and 19.42 million vehicle crossings, as of 8am yesterday, according to data from the Zhuhai Border Inspection Station cited by the Xinhua agency. The volume of people crossing the Delta Bridge has already exceeded 25.1 million in 2025, reflecting an annual growth of 17%, while vehicle crossings increased by 25% to 5.46 million. At the same time, the mega infrastructure received 10.15 million residents from Mainland China this year, including 4.6 million with tourist visas for Hong Kong and Macau, with both numbers breaking records. On the other hand, the total number of foreign tourists who used the bridge has already exceeded 421 thousand this year, representing a year-on-year increase of 26.7%. Since January, there have been 14.36 million entries and exits of residents from Hong Kong and Macau and 3.09 million vehicle crossings from both regions. "With the continuous growth trend in the flow of passengers and vehicles, it is estimated that in the whole of 2025, the total number of passengers will exceed 30 million, and the number of vehicles will exceed six million," said Chen Faqiu, head of the bridge's Border Inspection Station, according to Xinhua. Officially opened on October 23, 2018, by President Xi Jinping, the bridge reduced travel time between Hong Kong and Zhuhai or Macau from around three hours to 45 minutes. In 2019, movement on the bridge involved 12.88 million passengers and 860 thousand vehicles. In 2024, the numbers rose to 27 million and 5.55 million, respectively. Statistical data points to the continued growth in the flow of visitors from Mainland China to Hong Kong and Macau as the main driving factor for this increase.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>BRIEF</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2490/</link><description>Court puts 16 properties linked to Alvin Chau up for sale
Properties belonging to former gambling magnate Alvin Chau are now listed as ready for judicial auction, according to information on the Macao SAR Courts website, reported “Macau News Agency”. In total, there are 16 properties, all offices and located on the 12th floor of the Dynasty Plaza China Civil Plaza building. The total price of the bid is 64.8 million patacas, according to the information provided. Remember that, in July last year, the Court of Final Instance confirmed the 18-year prison sentence for Alvin Chau. Both he and eight other people were ordered to pay the Government almost HK$24.87 billion in compensation for pocketing winnings from illegal gambling operations. The other eight offenders were sentenced to prison terms ranging from nine years to twelve and a half years.
 
DSSCU warns against installing metal cages
The Directorate of Land and Urban Construction Services (DSSCU) warned yesterday against the provision of installation services for metal cages, acts that are “manifestly illegal” and which have been publicized on various social networks and online platforms in recent days, through advertisements, as indicated. In this sense, he expressed “concern and rejection of such practices, reiterating that the Government has been continuously combating illegal works, including metal cages”. In a statement, the organization recalls that the “Legal Regime for Urban Construction” increased the fines applicable to offenders for carrying out illegal works and introduced additional sanctions. Among the cases dealt with by DSSCU in recent years, he said that illegal works, namely metal cages, have received special attention, with fines having been imposed reaching the amount of 180 thousand patacas, in one case, and 240 thousand patacas in another.</description><pubDate>2025-10-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>From threatening to “cool!”: How opinions about China changed in Vietnam</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/de-ameacador-fixe-como-opinioes-sobre-china-mudaram-vietname/</link><description>Dozens of young Vietnamese people lined up for hours in September to see “cool” troops march in a huge military parade in Hanoi. But it wasn't their own soldiers they were looking for. It was the Chinese contingent.
The scene reflects a shift in attitude toward China – amid trade tensions with the US – that has allowed Vietnamese leaders to launch sensitive projects such as high-speed rail links and special economic zones near China that could significantly boost bilateral ties.
Just a few years ago, with many Vietnamese wary of a powerful neighbor with which they had fought several wars, these projects were seen as too controversial and caused violent protests. But opinions are softening, as shown by social media posts, online surveys and data on language learning.
Nearly 75% of Vietnamese respondents prefer the US to China as a partner, but the share favoring China is increasing faster than anywhere else in Southeast Asia, bucking the regional trend, according to a survey conducted in early 2025 by the Singapore-based ISEAS – Yusof Ishak Institute.
Social media appears to be playing a crucial role in changing the mood in Vietnam – and in particular, TikTok, which is popular among young people and, in 2024, had 67 million users in Vietnam, the highest number after Facebook, according to the government. When users of the platform owned by Chinese technology giant ByteDance search for the Vietnamese word for China they get extremely positive results, some from 2023.
Among the popular videos suggested by TikTok are clips of Chinese soldiers performing synchronized dances and videos showing Chinese cities, with many viewers expressing admiration for China's rapid development.
TikTok users searching for the Vietnamese name of the South China Sea, a focus of frequent conflict between the two countries, often find clips about tropical storms or tensions between China and the Philippines, which also have claims to parts of the sea, according to tests carried out without user profiles to avoid algorithmic bias.
In September, crowds gathered in Hanoi to celebrate the 80th anniversary of Vietnam's declaration of independence from colonial rule. Tens of thousands crowded the streets, many to watch the Chinese parade. Troops march alongside Vietnamese soldiers - an unprecedented sight in the capital of a country that was last invaded by China in the late 1970s and where major streets are named after anti-Chinese heroes.
"It was worth the wait. Very cool. I admire their discipline," said Le Huyen My, a 22-year-old who traveled from Ho Chi Minh City in the south and camped overnight to secure a spot to watch the Chinese parade.
A video about the parade reached 3.3 million views on TikTok and attracted around 1,400 comments, many praising the “impeccable” march of Chinese soldiers. Similar videos on other platforms also generated positive reactions, although Facebook users were more skeptical about China and the US.
Young Vietnamese online “appear less strident toward China than before, but this is due more to the state's increasingly tighter grip on nationalism than to declining resentment,” said Nguyen Khac Giang of ISEAS.
Online campaigns against China are still rife in Vietnam and often target companies using maps of the South China Sea aligned with Beijing, but they tend to be short-lived.
This marks a change from 2018, when widespread anti-China protests forced the Vietnamese government to shelve a plan for Special Economic Zones seen as favorable to Chinese companies. Now, Vietnamese state media frequently report new plans for economic zones on the border with China, without generating protests.
“Economic interests are taking precedence over nationalism,” said Nguyen Hung, an academic at RMIT University in Vietnam, noting that Hanoi has promoted a pragmatic approach towards Beijing, especially as trade tensions with Washington escalate.
Vietnamese data shows that Chinese companies are now among Vietnam's top investors; leaders meet frequently; and interest in Chinese culture is growing. Chinese President Xi Jinping has traveled to Vietnam twice in the past two years, and Vietnamese leader To Lam visited Beijing on his first trip abroad, shortly after being named head of the Communist Party in 2024.
Online searches for China in Vietnam have increased, with a focus on Chinese films and the language, according to Google Trends. In the first quarter of 2025, Vietnam led global registrations for the HSK Chinese Proficiency Test, China's official exam for non-native speakers, according to Chinese state media.
But as China often lives in centuries of ambivalent ties, Vietnamese pride runs deep. “Chinese troops look fascinating, but our soldiers are still the best,” said student Nguyen Hue Van, 21, who attended the parade in Hanoi.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-21 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>