<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Inability to self -care “covers” domestic violence against the elderly</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/incapacidade-de-autocuidado-encobre-violencia-domestica-contra-idosos/</link><description>The report of implementation of the law against domestic violence related to 2024 points to a reduction of family crises, but warns of the “large increase” of cases of violence against the elderly. CPSP warns that some elderly people choose to tolerate violence for self -care inability and to pamper their children. It also assumes that “traditional social concepts” continue to make it difficult to discover these situations and prevention. Almost two thirds of the 125 processes of domestic violence were filed
 
In 2024, the Institute of Social Action (IAS) received 893 cases of family crisis (excluded repeated cases), which makes a monthly average of 74.4. The number dropped 9.8% compared to 2023, and the decrease was noted in two of the three parameters: “family dispute” (423 cases) and “family conflict” (385). Already in the category “Preliminary suspicion of domestic violence”, there were 85 cases, the equal number of 2023, notes the IAS, in the report to implement the Law for Prevention and Combating Domestic Violence for 2024.
Last year, 55 cases of domestic violence were confirmed to a monthly average of 4.6. Associating the reduction of cases of family crisis with “constant work of community awareness and long -term education”, IAS warns, however, for the “large increase” of cases of domestic violence against elderly (from zero to eight between 2023 and 2024) and for the rise of 45.5% in cases against children.
According to the report consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao, the Public Security Police (CPSP) notes that children and the elderly are vulnerable, and "some seniors may, due to their children and the lack of independent self-care capacity, normally choose to tolerate the acts of violence."
"Therefore, [elderly victims and children] really depend on foreign aid for discovery and denunciation [of cases], and allowing police authorities and social service equipment to intervene as early as possible," says CPSP, who received 127 cases suspected of domestic violence in 2024, all of physical abuse.
On the other hand, CPSP states that there are still suspicious cases whose victims - due to the influence on traditional social concepts or fear of pressure from public opinion - do not intend to reveal the family problem or the violence suffered, rejecting to ask police for help or social services. Sometimes they continue to live with the aggressors. This phenomenon “makes it difficult to discover and prevent cases of domestic violence,” says the corporation.
In addition to continuing to bet on courses and lectures, to raise knowledge, the forms of treatment and the ability to execute the law, CPSP intends to reinforce awareness actions, in order to encourage victims to seek help.
Generally speaking, IAS understands that "it is necessary to reinforce citizens 'knowledge of' zero domestic violence 'and raise the victims' awareness of self-protection and the reasons for helping help, especially to disclose, with people of different age groups, the means of requesting help." It also argues that "it is necessary to increase the sensitivity of the front line staff, in order to find out as soon as possible the risks of suffering from domestic violence and provide intervention and support timely."
In turn, the Judiciary Police (PJ) dealt with 133 cases of offensive behavior between family members, including 108 referred by CPSP. The PJ eventually referred 12 cases to the Public Prosecution Service (MP) for evident evidence of “domestic violence” after investigation, and registered two defendants indicted for the practice of domestic violence (out of flagrant offense). It also adopted 40 measures to protect victims to hospitals, homes or households, and in 55 cases, requested the intervention of social workers.
According to PJ, some attackers had violent acts against family members due to incapacity caused by mental illness and emotional problems, many rejecting medicines or medical consultation. Given these situations, "the family members of the attackers warned the police because they wanted the help of police and competent government services, rather than accusing the attackers," he said.
In this sense, when dealing with these cases, PJ promises to give priority to the urgent needs and needs of the victims, as well as try to convince the aggressors to accept hospital assessment and receive treatment.
 
The penalty of fine to the arrest of four years and six months
Regarding the cases targeted by judicial proceedings, among the 133 treated by the PJ, in addition to the 12 with evidence of domestic violence, 117 were a crime of offenses to physical integrity and one of threat.
Citing MP data, IAS reveals that in 2024, 125 cases of crime of domestic violence (16 more than 2023) were processed, and the MP deducted accusations in 24 cases (31 accused in 2023).
On the other hand, 78 cases were filed by the MP for several reasons. In 42, the victims ceased to investigate the responsibility, while in 31 there were not enough evidence. In addition, two cases were not a crime and three were filed for other reasons.
In 2024, IAS received nine judgments. The lightest penalty was a fine in a case, and the most severe four years and six months in prison (without suspended penalty) and payment of non -property damage to the victim. Moreover, prison sentences ranged from six months to two years and nine months; and the suspended between two years and four years. Except the case with lighter punishment, in all cases judged, the suspects were also sentenced to IAS applied evidence regime.
In addition, health services provided immediate treatment services to 167 suspicious victims last year, and health professionals helped in 57 suspected cases of violence against children.
The counseling services to students of the Directorate of Education and Youth Development Services (DSEDJ) treated 65 cases of preliminary suspicion of domestic violence, 60 being students, two with guardians and three involving both.
According to the DSEDJ, the sensitization of school staff has increased, however, the degree of acceptance of services by parents and students in question affects the monitoring of cases. In this sense, the report advocates a content review related to the subject in the school's operating guide.
For its part, services for labor affairs provided professional counseling in five cases linked to domestic violence and employment support services equally in five cases, two of whom got employment through conjugation and two by themselves.
 
Raised accommodation rate at centers for women
The report also indicates that the two shelter centers for women served 199 people by 2024, registering an average accommodation rate of 73.4%, plus 21.8 percentage points in annual terms. As for temporary residences, the rate rose 4.8 points to 39.6%.
The report associates the rise in the three strand accommodation rate: in the number of women who asked for help at their own initiative, in the proportion of cases in which they took minor children to the centers and in the number of cases suspected of violence against spouses. Alongside this, it is also attached to cases of family conflict and single pasting problems.
The Men's Retreat Center registered a 3.5%accommodation rate, a break of 14.9 percentage points.
In statistical terms, the report also states that the Family Support Services at risk, from Caritas, reported 2,375 communication cases, 1,567 of which on family issues (66%) and 808 (34%) related to suicide and community support. Except repeated cases, 893 family crisis were noted.
In concrete, the main reasons of the 423 cases of family dispute were separation of spouses (15.1%), emotional management problems (11.8%), mental illness or suspicion of mental illness (7.8%) and children's education (7.8%). As for the 385 family conflict, the three dominant causes were emotional management (22.9%), adultery or suspicion of adultery (15.3%) and mental illness or mental illness suspicion (8.1%).
The 85 cases of preliminary suspicions of domestic violence included 35 against wives, one against her husband, 34 against children and nine against the elderly. The five main factors of risk of violent behavior were children's education (22.4%), emotional management (15.3%), adultery or suspicion of adultery (12.9%), mental illness or suspicion of mental illness (10.6%) and alcohol abuse (8.2%). However, the largest number of victims were recorded in the age groups from seven to 12 years and 35 to 44 years, with the aggressors being mainly between 35 and 44 years and between 45 and 54.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial Park opens Centro Cultural dedicated to Chinese Medicine</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/parque-industrial-inaugura-centro-cultural-dedicado-a-medicina-chinesa/</link><description>The Center for Cultural Experience of Traditional Chinese Medicine was recently inaugurated in the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin. According to Tai Kin IP, Secretary for Economics and Finance, the project aims to integrate “cultural heritage, science education, interactive experiences and leisure tourism”

The Chinese Traditional Medicine Scientific and Industrial Park for Guangdong-Macau cooperation inaugurated the Center for Cultural Experience of Traditional Chinese Medicinal. According to a park statement, the new venture "merges the wisdom of traditional Chinese medicine (MTC) with the fascination of modern technology."
The center is based on an innovative concept of “themed organization for floors and flowing scenarios with each step” and has “the origin, inheritance, development, contribution and future perspectives” of the MTC. With the use of “intelligent technology” and an “international narrative”, visitors will be able to know and appreciate the culture of traditional medicine. In addition to being a “framework of‘ Macau-Hengqin cultural and tourist cooperation ””, the venture aims to “accelerate industrialization, modernization and internationalization of MTC”.
The project was conceived by “Weta Workshop”, a world -recognized studio in the field of film creativity and winner of five Oscars. The initiative injects a “new dynamism in the development of the park's 'Great Health + Tourism', helping MTC's culture to reach the world through 'China Stories, expressed to the world,'” says the statement.
Secretary for Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, described the center as "a key project of the" Great Health "sector of the park," which integrates "cultural heritage, science education, interactive experiences and leisure tourism." This works “not only as a window for the public to explore the MTC culture, but also as a strong momentum for the integrated development of 'Great Health + Tourism'”.
Tai Kin IP expects the center "to remain true to cultural dissemination" and "put the content first, telling the stories of MTC well." The secretary also intends to promote an “open cooperation” and that “exchange bridges” and “industrial synergies” are established that enable “a diverse development”. Sir Richard Taylor, co-founder of the Weta Workshop, described the center with an “extraordinary fusion of the aesthetics and wisdom of the East and West”.
The entity responsible for the park provides that, in the future, the Center should be associated with “deeply with the strategic position of the cooperation zone, binding itself closely to the industrial chain of the five spheres 'medicine, health, investigation, manufacture and services' of the park”.
 
Lecture addressed MTC use in athlete injuries
Health Services (SSM) gave a lecture on the “prevention and treatment of sports lesions with characteristic of traditional Chinese medicine” intended for Macao athletes. The objective was to give knowledge about the “exclusive advantages” of traditional Chinese medicine in health management, trauma prevention and post-injury rehabilitation. The session took place at the Institute of Sports athlete Training and Internship Center, having had more than 80 coaches and athletes. In the course of the lectures, the two ambassadors for the health promotion of traditional Chinese medicine spoke communications about “discovering clinical methods and mechanisms characteristic of traditional Chinese medicine after sports lesions” and “combination of traditional Chinese medicine with sports medicine - treatment of sports lesions with traditional Chinese medicine”. The lectures addressed the scientific mechanisms and clinical applications of traditional therapies such as acupuncture, Tuiná, Ventos therapy and Moxibustion, emphasizing the central concept of “prevention before sick” and combining modern medical research, can be read in a SSM statement.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>SSM point to “high” risk of “chikungunya” fever transmission</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ssm-apontam-para-elevado-risco-de-transmissao-de-febre-chikungunya/</link><description>Following the “Wipha” typhoon passage, health services warn that there is more likely to exist stagnant waters, which may result in greater proliferation of mosquitoes responsible for transmitting the “chikungunya” fever and dengue fever. In Foshan, almost 1,900 cases of "chikungunya" fever have already been confirmed. Given the frequent circulation of people between Guangdong and the MSAR, the authorities consider that “the risk of transmission to Macau is high”
 
Pedro Milheirão
Leong Iek Hou, head of the Health Services Disease Prevention and Control Center (SSM), warned that, following the “Wipha” typhoon, there is a greater likelihood that there are stagnant waters, creating conditions favorable to mosquito reproduction. At a press conference, Leong said yesterday that the SSM have reinforced the inspection and cleaning of mosquito proliferation sources, as well as the elimination of these insects, in order to avoid the transmission of the "chikungunya" fever and dengue fever.
At the same time, the SSM and the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) have made several awareness actions with the population, together with local associations. The objective is to “raise awareness of residents to reinforce stagnant water elimination and the adoption of anti-fulfillment measures”, both at home and at workplaces. AMI will even make three mosquito elimination actions per month, at the body's tutelage premises, according to Kenny Fong, head of the Environmental Hygiene and Licensing Department.
The prevention center official also noted that the mosquito proliferation rate is lower this year (62.6%) than 2024 (72%). Regarding cases of dengue fever, last year was the "most serious" of the last two decades, Leong recalled. Last year 39 cases were recorded, of which nine were places.
Until July 19, the city of Foshan reported a total of 1,873 confirmed cases of "chikungunya" fever. Of these, 1,790 were identified in Shunde district, 49 in the Chancheng district and 34 in the Nanhai district. However, Leong Iek has clarified that all cases in Guangdong were slight. Given the frequent circulation of people between Guangdong and MSAR, health authorities consider that "the risk of transmission to Macau is high."
SSM appeals to residents to take preventive measures, even if they stay in those places for a short time, in order to mitigate the risk of infection. Leong also appealed to health professionals to pay attention to "patients who have suspicious symptoms of these fevers." The public health laboratory of health services will freely make tests to both fevers to all medical institutions, he said.
In order to decentralize resources and promote a “healthy community”, the SSM, the AMI, the Benefent Association and the Mutual Assistance of the Verde Ilha neighborhood residents made a disclosure activity in the area of residence where the imported case of “chikungunya” fever took place. It is recalled that the first local dengue fever case was registered on July 5 and the first imported case of “Chikungunya” fever was reported last Friday.
The body also urged residents to adopt the "three strategies against mosquitoes", namely "avoid" proliferation "of mosquitoes at home", removing stagnant waters and larvae, "preventing" mosquito entry into interior spaces ", through mosquitoes and air conditioners, and" preventing "bite", wearing long and mosquito clothing.
Chikungunya fever is a viral disease whose clinical manifestations and disease prevention and control methods are similar to those of dengue fever, both transmitted by “aedes albopictus” mosquito bites. The incubation period may vary between two and 12 days, with initial signs of fever and joint pain. After two or three days there are rashes appear, and the entire course of the disease lasts about a week in slight cases. Some patients may experience joint pain up to three months after they are infected.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>1,115 TNT hiring authorization</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/revogadas-1-115-autorizacoes-de-contratacao-de-tnr/</link><description>In just over a year, more than 1,000 permission of non-resident workers were revoked for irregularities, the director of services for work matters revealed. Chan Un Tong also indicated that illegal work sanctions were applied to 856 people
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Between January last year and May this year, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) revoked 1,115 authorizations for hiring non-resident workers “for irregular use”. In response to a written interpellation of Deputy Leong Hong Sai, the director of the body, Chan Un Tong, says that, in the same period, 874 inspection operations were performed, and illegal work sanctions were applied to a total of 856 people.
The illegal work detected by the body was, for example, “exercise of duties in place/ for employer other than authorized”, “exercise of authorized functions”, illegal worker and work on their own, according to Chan Un Tong. In addition, it indicated that three employing entities were punished with “ancillary sanctions” which resulted in the revocation of 10 non -resident workers' hiring (TNR) authorizations. These employers were still deprived of the right to request new TNR hiring authorizations for six months.
The director of DSAL stresses that “to confirm the contracting situation of TNR by employers,” the body is attentive, making visits and verification of labor relations, “in order to ensure the reasonable use of hiring authorizations”.
"Whether 'false employment relationship situations' or 'irregular use of hiring authorization' are detected by DSAL within their skills or received by the transfer of other services, it is certain that DSSA will follow and investigate cases," says Chan Un Tong, in response to Leong Hong Sai.
In addition, it stresses that if the existence of illegal acts is verified after the investigation, "it is true that they will be treated so much, including the total or partial revocation of their hiring authorizations, as well as the referral of cases to the competent services for monitoring when these cases are involved in criminal acts, such as false statements or false documents."
It also ensures that, in the future, the government will continue to closely monitor the tendency of labor market development and the evolution of human resources demand and supply, taking more pragmatic and flexible adjustment and control measures according to changes, “dynamically adjusting and controlling the number of TNR”, ensuring the rights and priority interests in access to resident employment.
The deputy had also questioned the preparation of the part -time work regime. In the response, the director of DSAL recalled that, after the publication of the final report of the public consultation, in 2018, the representatives of the Labor and employer of the Permanent Social Concertation Council discussed the issue, but the consensus was not reached. "The Government of MSar will reconsider the matter according to the actual situation of society," he said.
On the other hand, in relation to the increase in the days of maternity and vacation license, Dsal has commissioned an inquiry and a study to a third entity. "Given that the revision of the law in the field of work involves several social factors, it will consider the general interests of Macao, in due course of a public consultation, in order to broadly collect the opinions of society and proceed to its discussion, under the law," read.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Caeal “supports” exclusion from lists that integrate a “non -patriot”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/caeal-apoia-exclusao-de-listas-integrem-um-nao-patriota/</link><description>The president of Caeal said yesterday that Caeal "supports and agrees" with the decision of the State Security Defense Commission to exclude all members of a list when a candidate is disqualified for "not being faithful to mashes" and "not defending the basic law"
 
Asked what is the legal provision that stipulates that, when a candidate for elections of the Legislative Assembly (AL) is excluded because the other members of the list is not equally considered “not defenders of the Basic Law” or “not faithful to the MSAR”, the chairman of the Electoral Affairs Commission (Caeal) pointed out that the MSAR State Security Defense Commission (CDSE) followed the criteria defined in stipulation 4 Article 33 of the Electoral Law. He also stated that he made the decision to verify according to the respective procedures and the known "facts".
"Regarding the opinion of the CDSe, Caeal supports and agrees, having made the decision to disqualify the respective people depending on this opinion," said Seng Ioi Man yesterday, after a meeting of Caeal.
On the other hand, urged to react on an alleged statement of an disqualified candidate that "he had been urged by Caeal to give up the candidacy," Seng Ioi Man said he had noticed this "news or comment." "What CAEAL wants to mention is that the respective statement does not correspond to the facts. Regarding the statements related to the elections and not corresponding to the truth, they can constitute defamation and slander to electoral work. Caeal censors it and reserves the possibility of demanding the legal responsibilities of these false statements," he said.
According to some local press agencies, this statement was issued by Alberto Wong, who suggests that it was approached by individuals with authority several times before July 15 - the day CAEAL announced disqualifying two lists with 12 candidates. In the brief statement, Wong stressed that he was pressured to abandon the race or face consequences.
It is recalled that, in addition to the candidacy led by Alberto Wong, the list whose main face was the current deputy Ron Lam was also disqualified.
However, Caeal said yesterday that he has already explained to the candidate lists the criteria for using and distribution of objects to the election campaign, which must be declared consonants the three existing categories. According to the judge, the first category is related to electoral propaganda objects to distribute to the public, who may have printed the designation, number and logo of the candidate lists. They can be leaflets, pamphlets, small dry or moistened packets, fans, hand flags and pens.
The second category includes objects that can be distributed to supporters during the meetings. These (for example, whistles, balloons, bright sticks, inflatable sticks and disposable raincoats) may have colors associated with lists, but cannot show the designation, number or logo.
As for the third category, which covers clothes and equipment used by the staff who participates in electoral activities, some types of objects, such as t-shirts, vests, hats and other work clothes, may have the name, number and logo of the lists. Ecological bags and umbrellas cannot display these three elements and can only have the colors of the teams.
Advertising objects can only be distributed to the public between August 30 and September 12, the election campaign period. In addition, it is not adequate that they are distributed in a package as if it were as a gift, clarified the president of Caeal. The candidate lists were urged to declare the three types of objects before August 27, having to clarify the list, number and prices. The costs of distributing campaign objects will be included in the election campaign expenses of the lists and the final election account.
Seng Ioi Man reiterated that campaign objects distributed to the public should avoid the nature of benefits, otherwise it may constitute electoral corruption.
On the other hand, it indicated that more than 770 voting booths will be installed for direct suffrage and the indirect, 80 more than in previous elections, to further accelerate the voting process, shortening the waiting time of voters.
Vote booths will contemplate the needs of voters with disabilities. On the other hand, they will be covered by translucent curtains to ensure the confidentiality of the vote and allow workers to see if there is any illegal situation at a relatively long distance. At this point, he stressed that it is forbidden to take photographs from the voter policeman with mobile phones. Seng Ioi Man also said he believes in the effective prevention of this type of occurrences, and also the "very fast and simple" voting process.
 
Almost 3,000 employees working in the elections
In addition, it revealed that in the 38 voting assemblies for direct suffrage and the five intended for indirect suffrage, there will be 1,300 employees responsible for electoral work, who will be selected from a total of 2,200 who have been recruited to various public services.
Seng Ioi Man indicated that he intends that all electoral officials perform all electoral work according to the law, in an orderly and rigorous manner, helping voters to vote without starter and concluding the counting of high efficiency votes.
In addition, there will be 1,500 employees at voting places to provide support and maintain order.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Alerted beauty salons to comply with the law</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/saloes-de-beleza-alertados-para-cumprimento-da-lei/</link><description>At a meeting with the Macao Beauty Industry Business Association, the Institute for Pharmaceutical Supervision and Administration (Isaf) addressed the implementation of the law on medical devices, the supervision of beauty services and products, among other topics. Isaf president Choi Peng Cheong recalled from the outset that the “supervision and administration regime of medical devices” was approved in the specialty by the Legislative Assembly on July 14, which will take effect on July 1 next year.
Choi Peng Cheong stressed that "beauty services are related to the health and safety of residents, and that their quality is closely related to public health." Thus, he warned that medical devices are classified according to the risk, and beauty salons can acquire and store low -risk class I (such as medicinal cotton and medicinal cotton swab), as well as medium -risk class II for non -medical purposes.
However, he warned that "beauty salons cannot use these medical devices to perform medical procedures, and medical acts, which are medical acts, are performed by health professionals in medical institutions should be performed. Choi Peng Cheong has stated that health services have a “clear definition” of medical acts and supervise under the law.
At the same time, it indicated that high -risk class III medical devices can only be provided to health institutions such as hospitals and clinics, and scientific research units, and beauty salons cannot have these types of medical devices.
In addition, the same person assured that Isaf will continue to disclose the new law to the sector, as well as launch an online electronic classification system to help the sector adapt to the new regime. Through a “transparent supervision”, the body expects to “promote compliance with the law”.
The president of the Beauty Industry Business Association, Lou Iok NGO, in turn, said that the association has actively communicated with public services. He also stated that, through the meeting, it became better known the devices and beauty products that can be used in beauty salons, hoping that government services "define clearer work orientations about the content of services that beauty salons can provide."</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game can grow 9% in the second half</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-pode-crescer-9-segundo-semestre/</link><description>Consultant Seport Research Partners reviewed the projections on the game's revenues in Macao, now predicting a 9% homologous rise in the second half and an increase of 7% in the 2025 overall calculation
 
Given the fact that “growth has reaches in recent months”, gross revenues of Macau casinos could increase about 9% in the second half of this year, compared to the same period of 2024, the consultant Seaport Research Partners foresees, in a new report with more optimistic projections about the sector.
“In Macao, we now foresee a 7% growth in the game's gross gross revenues” for the year 2025, indicates the Vitaly Umansky analyst, who had previously anticipated 5.6% increase compared to 2024, which ended with a record of 226.78 billion.
According to data released by the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, the game's revenues were headed at 118.77 billion in the first half of this year, which translates a 4.4% increase compared to 113.75 billion noted between January and June 2024 and corresponds to 79.4% of 2019. 61.12 billion, a growth that several analysts partially associated with the impact of shows on game operators enterprises.
"Although 2025 has begun softly in Macao, our expectation of summer recovery and strengthening in the second half is bearing fruit, and we continue to see Macau as a long -term secular growth market," Vitaly Umnsky stressed, also predicting a 7% increase in casinos revenues in the coming years. In this scenario, EBITDA set of game operators (results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation) may register a composite annual growth rate (CAGR, in the English acronym) of 9%.
In a long -term view, the analyst considers that "changes in market quotas will benefit Sands and Galaxy, while smaller operators should suffer quota losses," something that may be more notorious "if the recovery of the mass market is stronger than the currently planned." In this case, the game sector would benefit from a “higher global growth”.
Although he acknowledges that "concerns about Chinese macroeconomics and the US game sector's deceleration remain obstacles," Vitaly Umnsky maintains that these fears "are probably being overcome by improving feeling and stimuli." In addition, it understands that the actions of various game operators in the capital market remain undervalued.
In this sense, Seport Research Partners raised its target prices to all actions, except for MGM Resorts and MGM China, in the first case due to the slowdown in Las Vegas and the announced reinforcement of investment in New York and Japan. Regarding MGM China, the consultant argues that the price of actions will now have reached fair value, after the recent Hong Performance Kong.
The consultant thus recommends buying Las Vegas Sands at a target price of 58 dollars, Melco Resorts ($ 11), Wynn Resorts ($ 125), Galaxy (45 dollars of Hong Kong), Hong Kong's 23 dollars) and Wynn Macau (8 dollars of Hong Kong).
“Our game thesis is widely driven by long -term secular growth in the Macao and Singapore markets, and for Wynn for the opportunity in the United Arab Emirates,” said Vitaly Umansky.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTM prepares future of the digital economy</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctm-prepara-futuro-da-economia-digital/</link><description>Throughout this year, the Macau Telecommunications Company aims to further develop its fiber optic network to leverage a set of services and technologies, such as artificial intelligence, 5.5g, 'Big Data' and 'clouds' services, which, according to the operator, will be able to boost the Economy of thecep
 
Pedro Milheirão
In response to the 10 Gbps Optical Network Program, launched by the China Ministry of Information and Information Technology, the Macao Telecommunications Company (CTM) aims to develop the “10 GBPS” and “10 GBPs campus” pilot projects, according to the company's annual report.
The implementation of “an optical network with higher speed and lower latency” aims to support “high -speed artificial intelligence computing capacity, cloud computing services, state -of -the -art network services”, among others. Terri Kuan, vice president of the financial sector, believes that enterprises will position Macau as "leader city of "10 Gbps" in the region. "
Operator Director-General Vandy Poon ensures that “by 2025 CTM will continue to be fully committed to cooperating with the Government of MSAR and supporting its policies to promote economic diversification through technology, cultivating AI talents, expanding our Zhuhai software development center and following the latest national communication trends”.
At the same time, Vandy Poon states that the company will further reinforce its role “as a communication platform between Macao and Portuguese -speaking countries” and it will be “the facilitating element that leads the 'Digital Macao' to a new phase of development”.
“Taking advantage of our network and our technology strengths, we intend to establish smarter solutions for local businesses, government and other companies,” says Ebel Cham, vice president of the company's commercial area. Ebel Cham also states that pilot projects will allow to continue "to popularize services 5.5g and" fiber-to-the-room ". The goal is to "establish smarter solutions for local businesses, government, and other companies." In addition to the 5.5g private network, the company has been focused on the development of “5G voice”.
The launch of “Roaming 5G” in the Great Bay was another of the efforts made by CTM in 2024 to “provide a better communication experience to residents” and facilitate the development of a “low altitude economy” in the region. Last year, together with the Macao Education Association, CTM also brought “the 5G National Intelligent Education Station” to various primary and secondary schools, presenting the 5G, Big Data projects and “smart cities” projects to over 350 students.
 
Bet on “Wi-Fi 7”, I was and “Great Data”
Parallel to investment in network expansion and optimization of services, CTM also aims to expand “Wi-Fi 7” access points to provide “a better service experienceless service experience to citizens, tourists and business sector”, explains Thomas NG, vice president of the operator's network services. The company has also worked on the integration of “Wi-Fi 7” technology with “360º fiber service”.
Another CTM outbreaks has been the combination of AI with cloud applications. The company assumes that investment in “ia + great data” will tend to grow and therefore intend to “improve local capabilities”. For this purpose, it plans to create “more innovative smart applications and complete digital transformation solutions for various sectors,” explains Terri Kuan. It is recalled that the operator had already introduced the “Baidu Ai” platform in 2024 to “improve local AI” capabilities, as well as the “Ai Macau Smart Tourism Service” application.
“We will actively support MSAR government policies and enable intelligent transformation with 'Ia + Great Data' to create examples of more accurate and efficient applications for small and medium -sized businesses (SMEs), and collaborate with all sectors to support the moderate diversification of Macao's economy,” says Ebel Cham.
In turn, Aguinaldo Wahnon, Vice President of CTM's legal and regulatory affairs, hopes that this year the “new telecommunications law can promote greater development and innovation of the sector” and provide operators “a more efficient legal and regulatory framework”. The “Holistic Approach”, which integrates, ‘Big Data’, Cloud, Data and Electronic Trade Centers, will modernize internal processes and enrich the company's service supply, defends Wahnon.
For Macao Post and Telecommunications Director, Derby Lau Wai Meng, “AI is remodeling economic and social life standards at an unprecedented rhythm. As a central engine of a digital economy, telecommunications operators perform a vital mission in establishing a solid technological base that allows various sectors to release their potential”. Last year, the operator participated in the “Employment for Young Employment” of the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs, “to demonstrate various intelligent AI solutions”.
Lau also hopes that the CTM "follows its philosophy" and "remains committed to collaborating with the different sectors of society", promoting "a better view in building a smart city in Macao." In the same vein, Luo XI Cheng, president of Citic Telecom International Holdings, a group of 99% of CTM actions, believes that the operator's efforts “continually improve the intelligent city's ecosystem 'Digital', contributing to the development of society and the economy.
 
Thousands of workers and hundreds of formations
At the end of last year, CTM had 1,025 workers, and 60.5% works in network services or information technology areas and 23.7% were responsible for sales or customer service. In addition, 22.6% of workers had been at the company for over 15 years and 27.8% less than five years ago. More than half have a professional or higher course (51.9%).
CTM organized 207 training courses, including 52 in “Management and Corporate Development”, in order to offer opportunities for professional progression. In 2024, the operator donated a total of 324 thousand patacas to 13 organizations, under the “Bonus Point Donation Program” that aims to support social assistance services.
The company's volunteer team also organized 14 sessions of sharing information on fraud prevention with more than 700 seniors. “Given the widespread fraud in telecommunications, CTM actively promotes the popularization of information technology”, having collaborated with different social organizations, ”can be read in the report.
The CTM was constituted in October 1981 and is today the main supplier of telecommunications services at MSAR. The operator has more than half of the mobile telecommunications market.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>MGM's “Open House” in August</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/open-house-da-mgm-em-agosto/</link><description>During the first three days of August, MGM China will organize the “Celebration Open House”, which will provide interested parties the opportunity to know the event spaces of the two resorts of the company

MGM will hold the “Celebration Open House” at MGM Macau and MGM Cotai, between 1 and 3 August, to present the “Personalized Locations and Services for Events,” according to a note from the operator. Visitors will have the opportunity to know the great party halls, multifunctional rooms and other exclusive spaces for private events or meetings. Guests who make reservations during the three days will benefit from exclusive discounts and other limited time offers.
MGM Macau will be decorated with a Korean wedding theme, "evoking a refined and romantic environment." At the same time, MGM Cotai will present a scenario of French inspiration that will refer to "the dream charm of European celebrations." "The decorations on site will plunge the guests in a world of creative marriage configurations, designed to show the unique beauty of different styles," can be read.
According to the operator, both resorts are available "a magnificent interior and exterior space by the pool for about 300 guests." MGM Macau "offers a panoramic view of 180 ° to the sea from the coast of the Macao Peninsula." MGM Cotai, in turn, "is ideal for all types of events." Both stand out for the “refined design”, with capabilities to receive up to a thousand guests. MGM ensures that all the events it holds have menus cured by its kitchen team, sommelier services and “high level” decorations.
For the occasion, MGM invited 15 traders to offer free consulting services on site, focused on thematic celebrations, event planning, decorative cakes, photography and entertainment, among others. The operator will also offer free guided tours to the various spaces for events, suites and rooms of both properties.
Under promotions, Chinese wedding packages will have a 15%discount, while Western ceremonies will have a 10%price reduction. In addition, guests who make purchases through designated payment services will receive a Sweet Corner from MGM's kitchen team, valued at five thousand patacas.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>40 creative brands promoted in Hong Kong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/40-marcas-criativas-promovidas-em-hong-kong/</link><description>Forty creative brands in the territory had the opportunity to show and sell their products at the “Macao Craft Fair in the Great Bay Zone”, organized by the Cultural Institute (IC) at the Hong Kong Convention and Exhibition Center (HKCEC), between July 16 and 22. This was the first time that IC promoted products from Macao cultural and creative entities in Hong Kong through this “Craft Fair”.

Previously held in Canton, Foshan and Shenzhen, “the event was well received by both the sector professionals and the public, contributing to increase the visibility of Macao's cultural and creative brands and expand their market range in the large bay zone,” said the IC.
According to the same statement, the 40 brands presented and marketed, at two times, "a diversified range of cultural and creative products." The offer included “products inspired by Macau characters, lifestyle products, clothing and accessories, handicrafts, handcrafted natural products and many other products that incorporate typical cultural elements of Macau”.
At the same time, this year, the Cultural Institute and the Macau Foundation made efforts to participate in the 35th Hong Kong Book Fair, which took place at the same place and dates, “presenting a careful selection of high quality Macao publications to readers of Hong Kong and other stops”.
The head of the IC, Ho Hong Pan Cultural and Creative Promotion Department and the head of the Cultural Institute's Division of Studies and Publications, Lo Chi Keong, visited the event's venue, whose tickets cost 30 dollars from Hong Kong for adults and 10 HKD for children.</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Brief</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/breves-2438/</link><description>Three burlads in over 14 million Patacas
At least three more residents were the target of sloping, having lost more than 14 million patacas in total. The Judicial Police (PJ) received complaints about two more cases of investment -related circumvents. Two residents, a man and a middle-aged woman, will have fallen into an investment trap in actions, undergoing losses of 12 million and 1.05 million patacas. The PJ is investigating whether the two victims were circumvented by the same criminal group. According to the investigation, they lost the money after opening accounts in an application allegedly intended for investment in actions. In another case, a young woman lost a million patacas after being deceived by a false police officer in the interior of China. According to PJ, the burlão claimed that the victim was associated with cases of slopping and it eventually shared information from the mobile phone screen with the alleged agent. The next day, he realized that a million patacas had been transferred from his account.
 
Building in the Patio do Espinho will be the target of demolition
The construction located at 10 10 of the Espinho Patio, which was unoccupied and collapsed on Monday morning, will be the target of demolition, confirmed the Cultural Institute (IC) to the Chinese language press, noting that the building was at risk, being necessary to "urgently proceed to urgent demolition". The decision arose after an inspection to the place of staff of the Directorate of Soil Services and Urban Construction (DSSCU), which was notified for the case by the Fire Department. According to preliminary inspection, they collapsed the roof and part of the outer walls of the construction concerned. In addition, the other outer walls recorded a slight inclination and there was a risk of collapse. The authorities did not indicate when the building will be demolished.
 
Iran, Lebanon and Syria with maximum travel alert
The number of destinations covered by the MSAR travel alert system was extended to 110. New countries include Iran, Lebanon and Syria, which are now classified at travel alert level 3, which means “the level of threat to personal safety is extreme”; As well as Pakistan, classified as Level 2. In this case, according to the Directorate of Tourism Services (STD), it is worth reconsider non -essential trips, as there is a threat to security. The travel alert system is not prohibitive, and each individual is responsible for traveling or adjusting the travel plan according to the information provided. In case of need for assistance, residents may contact the open line for tourism (+853 2833 3000), embassies and consulates of the Popular Republic of China in the places or the 24 -hour Open Emergency Open line of protective and consular assistance from the RPC Ministry of Foreign Affairs (+86 10308).</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Only three sectors benefited “significantly” from visitors</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/apenas-tres-sectores-beneficiaram-significativamente-dos-visitantes/</link><description>Over the past two years, economic recovery driven by external demand "has not effectively spread by more than half of the sectors," concluded a study of elements from the monetary authority's investigation and statistical department. The game sectors, hotels and restaurants were the ones that “benefited significantly” from the arrival of more visitors to the territory. In this sense, the authors argue that “although efforts to boost external demand remain crucial, equal attention should be paid to the stimulus of internal demand” to ensure “a balanced economic recovery”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
More than half of Macao sectors have not rendered the result of tourism recovery in the last two years. A study by three elements from the Macao's monetary authority and statistics department reveals that only three areas benefited “significantly” from the increase in the number of visitors.
The analysis by C. K. Leong, C. K. IO and H. Y. Huang about the unequal economic resum in the territory points out that “the asymmetrical economic recovery of Macao stems from imbalances between external and internal demand”.
Despite the “excellent overall performance” of the local economy in the last two years, the authors note that “only three sectors: game and junkets activities; hotels and similar activities; and similar restaurants and activities have benefited significantly from the resurgence of visitors.” "This suggests that an economic recovery prevailed predominantly by external demand has not effectively spread to more than half of the industries," they marked in the document, consulted by the Jornal Tribuna de Macao.
The banking sector, insurance and pension funds, real estate activities, construction, education, health and social assistance, as well as the transforming industry, “did not benefit significantly from tourism growth”. "Coincidentally they have a significant positive relationship with the median monthly employment income, suggesting that the growth of these sectors is driven by internal demand," they observe.
In this sense, they consider that "although efforts to boost external demand remain crucial, equal attention should be paid to the stimulus of internal demand, accompanied by continuous analysis of the determinants of growth in all sectors in order to ensure a balanced economic recovery."
In the case of the retail trade sector, it is stated that “despite the rapid recovery in the number of visitors and the local economy in aggregate terms, double pressures to decrease per capita spending on visitors not related to the game and the environment of high interest rates are weighing on the prospects of small and medium -sized businesses (SME)”.
In other words, "SME's performance is more sensitive to the per capita spending of visitors not linked to the game than to the number of visitors." Thus, it is necessary to “look beyond the numbers of visitors arrivals”, so that examining the preferences of constantly evolving consumers in the postpandeia era would help to elaborate “effective policies” and directed to support small local companies in adapting to these changes.
"Our analysis (…) reveals that there is a substantial heterogeneity in the sectoral dynamics of Macao. Notably, an economic recovery predominantly driven by external demand did not effectively spread over half of the sectors," the trio reiterates.
Given that Macao is “a small open economy, where the integrated industry of tourism and leisure is a fundamental pillar”, the authors say that it is natural that the evolution of external demand raises more attention, but underline that it is necessary to “evaluate the short and long term dynamics of different economic variables and their specific implications for each sector”.
The study also underlines the importance of “promoting synergies between external and internal demand to solve growth disparities, which would help guide Macau's economy to a more sustainable development path in the context of adequate economic diversification”, it can read.
It should be noted that service exports represented about 80% of the contribution to actual GDP growth in 2024, and Macao's economic recovery was mostly driven by external demand.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sign 10 had never been issued anytime soon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sinal-10-nunca-tinha-sido-emitido-tao-cedo/</link><description>Sign 10 Due to the “Wipha” typhoon became the earlier since there are records in 1968. This was, moreover, the fifth tropical cyclone since 2017 that forced the issuance of the highest tropical storm signal, according to meteorological and geophysical services. For the next few days it is expected "unstable" time, despite the removal of "Wipha". The Secretary for Security praised the “efficient” cooperation and the response “timely”

Catarina Pereira
 
Typhoon “Wipha” has been the fifth tropical cyclone in the last nine years since 2017, forcing signal 10 in Macao, observed the Meteorological and Geophysical Services (SMG). Moreover, since there are records in 1968 that the highest sign of tropical storm had not been lifted anytime soon. It is necessary to retreat on July 24, 1991, when the “Brendon” passage to find the record of a 10 sign at this time of year.
In a balance over the typhoon, the SMG report that, after entering the Southern Sea of China, the "Wipha" went directly to the coast of the Pearl River estuary with typhoon intensity, eventually passing about 30 kilometers southwest of Macao.
"The sustained 10 -minute sustained winds recorded in the four bridges reached level 12, with maximum gusts of 14, during the validity of Tropical Storm signal 10," says the body.
After entering the northern part of the Southern Sea of China, the development of the typhoon "accelerated significantly", even resulting in the formation of the phenomenon known as "Hot Tower" as it approached the coast of the Pérola river estuary. “In the satellite image, an upward cloud appears like a tower at the top of a cloud,” the SMG indicates.
The body says the phenomenon represents "a sudden movement" near the eye wall of a tropical storm. "The height of the cloud summit can reach the top of the troposphere, accompanied by lightning, which means that the tropical storm is intensifying rapidly," he adds.
Although the “Wipha” typhoon has gradually removed and weakened, time in the region will remain “unstable” in the coming days, with thunder and thunderstorms due to the influence of associated cloud bands. “Squirers are expected to decrease and the sky will be not cloudy later this week,” says the SMG, appealing to the population to pay attention to the latest meteorological information.
 
Compliments to the civil protection structure
In a balance sheet, the secretary for security and joint action commander, Wong Sio Chak, considered that all members of the civil protection structure "fulfilled their duty, performed their duties and, according to emergency plans, were able to warn and prevent in time." He also praised “efficient” cooperation, under the coordination of the Civil Protection Operations Center.
Wong Sio Chak recalled that Macau is still at the time of typhoons and said he hopes that members of the civil protection structure will not lower the guard, continuing to perform and optimize all tasks based on this response, "in order to ensure the safety of citizens' lives and goods."
According to him, around 6:30 pm on Sunday, the forces and security services sent personnel to all areas of the territory to remove fallen trees and obstacles on the roads, "ensuring the fluidity of traffic in the main arteries of Macao."
The “state of immediate prevention” in the territory was declared extinguished from 10:30 pm on Sunday, when signal 3 was lifted. Thus, the circulation of public transport was resumed and the maritime bridges of the territory reopened. The border posts that connect Macau and Zhuhai had already reopened at 17:00, when the tropical storm signal dropped to 8.
The passage of “Wipha” left five slight injuries in the territory and 139 people rode to the shelter centers. In addition, hundreds of occurrences were recorded.
Specifically, during the passage of the typhoon there were 163 occurrences, involving 98 cases of “removal of plaster, complaint, window, awning or other objects with risk of fall/overthrow” and 54 cases of “construction/lamp/tree removal with risk of fall/overthrow”. There were also nine situations involving “removal of scaffolding or other facilities in workshops with risk of falling/overthrowing”, a case of “retention in the elevator” and another of “fire”.
The Institute for Municipal Affairs indicated that after cleaning and safety assessment, more than 80% of parks, 90% of leisure zones and all dog ride zones were reopened yesterday afternoon.
The telephone support line, in turn, received 123 calls. The Public Security Police Corps also carried out an operation, having intercepted two cases of taxi drivers and four cases of unlicensed vehicles.</description><pubDate>2025-07-22 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Japanese children join Portugal to protect the oceans</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/criancas-japonesas-juntam-se-portugal-para-proteger-os-oceanos-vitor-quinta/</link><description>Vitor Quintã*
Dozens of Japanese children joined yesterday at Expo2025 in Osaka, an appeal to protect the seas, which the Lisbon Oceanarium wants to take the UN summit on climate change in November, Brazil.

“Do you want to be ocean ambassadors here in Japan?” Asked at the Portugal Pavilion, Marine Biologist Natacha Moreira, from the Blue Ocean Foundation, to the students of two classes of an Osaka school.
The positive response came in a 40 -voices unison chorus, the first Japanese young people to sign the mini 30x30, “a wave” launched by the blue ocean and the oceanarium, in support of the world goal to protect 30% from the ocean by 2030.
Oceanaria's director of education, Diogo Geraldes, told Lusa that a first letter was delivered during the third UN Ocean conference, which took place in Nice, France, in June.
A new version of the document will be delivered to the United Nations Conference on Climate Changes (COP30), which will take place in November in Belém, the state capital of Pará, northern Brazil.
The appeal has already gathered the support of 9,500 young people from 27 countries, but in Asia still had contributions from Malaysian and Timor-Leste schools.
The Oceanarium prepared materials on the Mini 30x30 in Japanese especially for Expo, which already existed in Portuguese, Spanish, French and English.
Before they vote unanimously in favor of the appeal, the young Japanese tested the interactive experiences of the Oceanarium in one of the two multi -articles of the Portugal Pavilion, whose theme is “Ocean: Blue Dialogue”.
"The Lisbon Oceanarium is, in Portugal, the institution with more scrolls and experience in Blue Literacy. For over 25 years that has been teaching teachers and students to have a more sustainable relationship with the sea," Blue Ocean Executive Administrator Tiago Pitta and Cunha told Lusa.
An experiment that led the Oceanarium and the Blue Ocean, with the support of the Directorate-General for Education, to develop the Educar Program for a Blue Generation, which promotes ocean literacy among students from 6 to 10 years.
Diogo Geraldes explained that they started in the first cycle because "it is easier to form teachers, who are often the same from the first to fourth year."
For five years, the project has been training to 1,300 teachers at a pilot phase that took place in the municipalities of Albufeira, Cascais, Mafra, Moura, Nazaré, Peniche, Silves, Sintra and the Autonomous Region of the Azores.
After the end of this phase, in May 2024, the Ministry of Education, Science and Innovation decided to extend the program to all primary schools in the country and to include the ocean in the curriculum.
Tiago Pitta and Cunha said the goal is to "educate the most conscious generation of the entire European Union regarding the connection of humans with the ocean." "We could, in the end, be a little, as the Nordicas went to the environment [terrestrial] from the 1970s, the Portuguese citizens would be for blue," explained the expert.
Created in 2017 by the Francisco Manuel dos Santos Society, which includes in its heritage the Lisbon Oceanarium, the Blue Ocean is a non -profit entity, which aims to contribute to the conservation and sustainable use of the oceans.
 
*Journalist of the Lusa Agency traveled at the invitation of the Blue Ocean Foundation</description><pubDate>2025-07-23 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>