<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Canteen for the elderly could be a pioneering project by Fu Hong</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cantina-para-idosos-podera-ser-projecto-pioneiro-da-fu-hong/</link><description>The project to create a canteen with more appropriate food for the elderly may see developments this year. This is an “old dream” of the Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association, whose president of the general assembly wants the space to help resolve the issue of meals that elderly people often purchase in restaurants. Fátima Santos Ferreira will soon start contacts with the Housing Institute to find out if there are stores available to install the cafeteria
 
VÍTOR REBELO
 
A canteen that serves the interests of the elderly, in terms of a daily diet that is more appropriate for their age, could be the next project of the Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association.
“We found that elderly people sometimes have difficulty eating,” the president of the general assembly of the institution dedicated to supporting disabled and vulnerable people began to tell the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, adding that “the meals they pick up or order for take-away are not prepared in the best way, are not properly cut, and sometimes, as many have teething problems, they need meals edible and healthy.”
The project, which, if it becomes reality, will be pioneering, “since there is nothing like this in Macau”, should see some developments within a short time, after the first contacts are made with the responsible entities. “We haven’t presented the plan yet, but we would like to be able to provide this response to the elderly, because it is a necessity”, says Fátima dos Santos Ferreira.
“First we have to contact and negotiate with the Housing Institute to find out if there are available stores that they can rent to us and only after that will we move forward with this dream of ours, which is already old, trying to make it happen as quickly as possible”, he highlights, believing that by the end of the year “there could be some news on the subject”.
Even though nothing has been officially discussed yet, the director emphasizes that the idea is to find a space “in an area where there is a greater population density of elderly people”. As for the dimensions of the canteen, “it will all depend on the place we find, but it cannot be too big, as we have to start small”, he emphasizes.
Fátima dos Santos Ferreira also spoke of another “old dream”, but this one has already been made public, which is the construction of a building that houses social enterprises. “This canteen could even be part of that”, he admits.
The building “would help to solve several problems, because associations that want to organize a social enterprise face difficulties with space and rental contracts, always subject to increased rents”, he mentions.
“If we have a building for social enterprises, then the various associations will be able to apply based on a project accepted by the Government and then Macau will be able to have more social enterprises”, he says.
The president of the general assembly of Fu Hong states that she has been trying to “sell” the project since the previous Executive. “But, sometimes, I think there is not a lot of sensitivity, because when they hear about a social enterprise they immediately think that it is a business, which is wrong”, he laments.
A social enterprise “is created to facilitate employment for the needy section of the population, the disabled, the mentally ill, various types”, he emphasizes, recalling that the Fu Hong Rehabilitation Association has two social enterprises, a laundry and another selling second-hand products.
In addition, the institution has a restaurant serving Portuguese and Macanese food, “which has been in high demand since Macanese cuisine entered the list of China's intangible heritage, opening up the possibility for people to come and try Macanese food, because it is the first fusion cuisine”, he says.
The restaurant operates as an occupational center, located in Fai Chi Kei, for mentally ill patients in recovery. “Because the ‘mentally ill’ are different from the ‘mentally disabled’, since the former have crises and with treatment they recover, but then they need to be inserted into the community”. Therefore, “the association thought about creating this occupational center”, he explains.
Last weekend, Fu Hong promoted another fundraising campaign for its activities, which took place in various locations in Macau and Taipa, with the sale of flags, stamps and products related to the National Games, which involved several volunteers, including families who took their children to participate. “It’s good, from a young age, to have the possibility of helping with these types of causes”, concludes Fátima Santos Ferreira.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM brings together champions from several FR and F4 series</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/gpm-junta-campeoes-de-varias-series-de-fr-f4/</link><description>Well-known faces from the main Macau Grand Prix races in recent years return to the Guia Circuit for another edition of the event, between 13 and 16 November. Mortara, Borkovic, Michelisz, Slater and Todd are some of the leading figures in their categories, in cars and motorcycles. Formula Regional is once again in the spotlight, being one of the two single-seater races, alongside F4, bringing to Macau the best of the year in the various championships. Both promote young pilots. In terms of teams, Mercedes is the big absentee in the GT Cup. Tickets for the four days went on sale yesterday

VÍTOR REBELO
 
Macau already feels the atmosphere of another Grand Prix (GPM), and one month before the start of the competition you can see the metal barriers set up along the circuit. Some time in advance, the organization also begins to prepare the structures of the stands that will house speed lovers, who can, since yesterday, purchase tickets for the four days of racing.
In competitive terms, the biggest international sports event in the Macao SAR officially revealed the names of most of the teams and pilots, after the announcement made by the Organizing Committee, in a press conference held yesterday morning at the Science Center.
From the outset, the Formula Regional (FR) will occupy a prominent place, as happened in 2024, when it debuted on the Guia asphalt replacing the “missed” Formula 3. The FR is once again one of the races with the greatest impact and one of the two races involving single-seaters.
In the entry list, which has not yet been fully released, it is known that the R-ace GP team, owned by last year's champion – the North American Ugo Ugochukwu – is participating with three drivers who made their debut in the territory in 2024: the Italian Matteo De Palo, the Frenchman Enzo Deligny, fourth in the main race of the previous edition of the GPM, and Jin Nakamura, a Toyota protégé.
British rider Freddie Slater, leader of the European championship (FRECA), remains at Prema Racing and leads the contingent attacking the title. Slatter, fourth in last year's qualifying race, will once again be alongside his season-long teammate, Rashid Al Dhaheri, from the United Arab Emirates, in a line-up where there is still room for local driver Charles Leong Hon Chio.
Leong first participated in the F3 GPM in 2018, and won when the race was held with Formula 4 (F4) cars in 2020 and 2021, during the pandemic years. He was second in the F4 race in 2023 and, this season, he has just been crowned champion of the Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia.
More F3 talents join the FR race, namely Spaniard Mari Boya, who finished seventh last year and fourth in 2023, and Frenchman Théophile Naël, representing Pinnacle Motosport.
The Eurocup-3 contingent continues with newly crowned champion Mattia Colnaghi, who will race alongside China's Enzo Yeh and Mexico's José Garfias. Van Amersfoort Racing has entered Euroformula Open champion Tymek Kucharczyk of Poland, Japanese championship leader Kiyoshi Umegaki and Chinese Zhenrui Chi.
 
Japanese among the candidates in the Formula 4 race
With regard to Formula 4, which returns to the GPM program, it now has the title of World Cup and once again attracts a wide list of promising young people. From the very competitive Italian championship come Kean Nakamura-Berta, recently crowned champion, the Italian Emanuele Olivieri and the North American Sebastian Wheldon, son of the late Indianapolis 500 winner, Dan Wheldon.
Rintaro Sato, son of 2001 GPM F3 winner and two-time Indianapolis 500 champion Takuma Sato, will make his second visit to Macau, joining a strong delegation from the French series, which also includes Alexandre Munoz, Jules Roussel and Rayan Caretti.
British F4 champion and Red Bull Junior driver Fionn McLaughlin will be joined by another winner of that trophy, Thomas Bearman, younger brother of Haas' new Formula 1 star Ollie Bearman. The youngest driver in the field also comes from the UK championship, Indian Ary Bansal, who will turn 16 before his debut in the Macao SAR.
Argentine Genaro Trappa will also come from the European F4 scene, while Ethan Nobels will participate from the Brazilian Championship. Meanwhile, two champions of the series from China are registered: the Portuguese Tiago Rodrigues, winner on the Mainland in 2023, and this season's champion, Zhang Shimo. Marcus Cheong Man Hei is another representative from Macau.
 
Elite line-up in the FIA ​​GT Cup
The Macau GT Cup – FIA GT World Cup will feature a line-up of world elite drivers, from six of the most prestigious names in the automotive industry, such as Audi, BMW, Ferrari, Lamborghini, McLaren and Porsche.
“Mr. Macau”, Edoardo Mortara, returns to the Guia Circuit in a Lamborghini Huracán, looking for his fifth victory, which will allow him to regain his status as the record holder for the most victories in the race. The Italian-Swiss will be accompanied at Absolute Corse by Luca Engstler.
Raffaele Marciello, two-time winner, is another well-known name among Macau motorsport lovers who is present, behind the wheel of a ROWE Racing BMW M4.
For Porsche, Laurens Vanthoor, Alessio Picariello, Ayhancan Guven, Laurin Heinrich and Dorian Boccolacci will be on the grid, while for Ferrari the Italian Antonio Fuoco and the Chinese Deng Yi and Ye Yifei will be on the grid.
One of the new features, in terms of regulations for this year, is the fact that the ten fastest drivers in the regular 30-minute qualifying session will then have the opportunity to compete in the “Super Pole” for Saturday's 12-lap qualifying race.
In this GT competition, Mercedes is the big absentee, since the sensors of the vehicles normally used are not allowed in the GPM, supposedly because they limit the power of the rear wheels.
The Guia Macau-Kumbo FIA TCR World Tour race once again features names with extensive experience in the GPM, including five winners: Swede Thed Björk, Chinese star Ma Qing Hua, Argentine Esteban Guerrieri, Hungarian Norbert Michelisz and Dušan Borković, who last year became the first Serbian to win the competition.
Ten full-time World Tour drivers will be on the starting grid, with championship leader Yann Ehrlacher the driver to beat in the fight for his third FIA Touring Car title with Lynk &amp; Co, where he is joined by Ma, Björk and Santiago Urrutia.
On two wheels, veteran Michael Rutter, with several victories in Guia, is the big absentee. For the rest, we will have Peter Hickman, five-time champion, and Davey Todd, who won last year's race, but who had to wait for training due to rain.
Finnish Erno Kostamo, second behind Todd, returns in an attempt to repeat his 2022 triumph. There are also, among others, David Johnson, Rob Hodson, Michael Evans, Marcus Simpson, Ryan Whitehall, Sam West, Paul Jordan, Michael Sweeney, Laurent Hoffman and Almaric Blanc.
In support races, the GPM will this year include the GT Cup – Great Bay Race (GT4), with eight manufacturers and names such as Wang Hao, Lu Wenlong, Han Lichao, Darryl O’Young. Macau will be represented by several drivers, including Leong Ian Veng, Lei Kit Meng, Wong Cheng Tou and Wong Wai.
In the Roadsport Challenge, the winner of the 2024 edition of the Macao SAR Establishment Cup, Damon Chan Tat Man, returns accompanied by Cheang Kin Sang and Ivan Szeto Wing Shun, who also reached the podium last year. The runner-up in the 2024 Macau Roadsport Challenge, Jerónimo Badaraco, will seek to improve his result, after having been second in 2024, behind Lei Kit Meng, and is part of the group of local drivers, which will once again include Macanese Rui Valente.
This year's GPM budget is 160 million patacas, 40 million of which are borne by the Government and the rest by the six operators, in equal parts of 20 million.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Folk dance and custard tarts elevated to intangible heritage</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/danca-folclorica-pasteis-de-nata-elevados-patrimonio-intangivel/</link><description>After broad support from participants in the public consultation, the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture has now included the 12 manifestations proposed by the Cultural Institute on the List of Intangible Cultural Heritage. Highlights include Portuguese Folk Dance and the Making of Pastel de Nata, as well as Dragon and Lion Dances and the Belief and Customs of Tou Tei

The Portuguese Folk Dance, the Making of Pastéis de Nata and 10 other events were inscribed on the List of Intangible Cultural Heritage, according to an order signed by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, O Lam, and published yesterday in the Official Bulletin. Overall, the 12 demonstrations proposed to be part of this list “obtained around 70% or more agreement, indicating broad social support”, considered the Cultural Institute (IC), when it released the results of the public consultation.
Originating in rural areas of Portugal, it is believed that folk dance was introduced to Macau with the arrival of the Portuguese and was spread here as part of their community activities. But it was only in the early 70s and 80s of the last century that this type of dance became “more popular” and developed into activities with other local communities. “Portuguese folk dance has continuously acquired characteristics of Macau, and currently involves artists from the Portuguese, Macanese and Chinese communities, among others”, according to what was mentioned when presenting the recommended events.
For the IC, “local Portuguese folk dance reflects the value of Macau's multiculturalism, as well as the integration and friendship between Chinese and Portuguese cultures, being a relevant cultural manifestation of the typical culture” of the territory.
As for the Making of Pastéis de Nata, it was argued that it evolved in Macau from the Portuguese sweet. “At the end of the last century, a bakery in Coloane started selling its own interpretation of characteristic egg tarts, based on the Portuguese recipe, with some influences from Hong Kong and Macau cooking techniques, which was a great success”, said the organization.
“Nowadays, custard tarts have not only evolved to include new flavors, but have also led to the creation of other types of sweets”, he stressed, adding that they have “characteristics specific to Macau” and a “deep cultural significance”.
In this list, the Belief and Customs of Tou Tei, the Dragon Dance and the Lion Dance also stand out, which received 90% support in the public consultation. According to the IC, the Belief and Customs of Tou Tei is “an important demonstration of the legacy of the traditional culture of the Chinese nation” in the territory, which is reflected, for example, in the Tou Tei Festival, which takes place on the second day of the second month of the lunar calendar.
The Dragon Dance, in turn, represents “an important symbol of the richness of traditional Chinese culture in Macau”, being of “great value for the investigation of popular culture”, while the Lion Dance “has been representing and promoting traditional Chinese culture in the international sporting arena, promoting exchange and dialogue between Chinese and foreign cultures”.
The Spring Festival is another event now on the list, which “also plays an important role in consolidating family relationships, promoting community support and maintaining social ethics, thus having a significant historical and cultural identity value”. The Dragon Boat Festival is also one of the “most important and with the longest history” in the territory, “reflecting a unique national spirit and a rich culture that Macau continues to celebrate”, while the Dragon Boat Regatta constitutes “an important representation of the transmission and continuity of traditional Chinese culture”.
On the other hand, tai chi martial arts is a modality with many practitioners, “reflecting the continuity of traditional Chinese culture in the territory”. For the IC, “its cultural significance and different forms of practice have been enriched, highlighting human creativity, and assuming an important historical and social value”. The making of almond cookies, traditional Chinese wedding cakes and jook-sing noodles are also three manifestations that are now part of the intangible cultural heritage due to their significance.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Chef António, “great figure” of Portuguese gastronomy, has died</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/morreu-chef-antonio-grande-figura-da-gastronomia-portuguesa/</link><description>Chef António passed away in Macau, aged 77. Considered a “great figure” of Portuguese gastronomy, he is remembered as an “affable”, “joking” person, sometimes “a little controversial in his opinions”. António Neves Coelho was awarded the tourist merit medal by the Macao SAR Government in 2013 and also received the Portuguese communities merit medal from the Portuguese Government
 
Catarina Pereira*
 
António Neves Coelho, better known as chef António, passed away at the age of 77, in Macau. An unavoidable figure in Portuguese gastronomy in the territory, he arrived in Macau for the first time in 1970, where he completed mandatory military service for two years. Decades later, in 1997, he decided to start a new chapter in the East. An “authentic artist” and “joker”, an “affable” person, sometimes “a little controversial in his opinions”, chef António is remembered as having made “great contributions” in the area of ​​gastronomy.
Vera Alcobia worked, for around five years, as António Coelho's assistant in the restaurant that bore his name, in a space that projected the quality of the food he prepared. “He was a genuine artist, in addition to being a great friend, always very playful with everyone who worked with him and very concerned about his employees”, he began by referring to the newspaper TRIBUNA DE MACAU, who was at the chef's side in many moments of his personal and professional life in Macau, and who considered him “almost like a father or grandfather”.
For Vera Alcobia, also involved in the restaurant and hotel industry, “he had that way of opening bottles with a sword and always did his demonstrations”, adding that António “always used the motto that you don’t need to scold to teach people well”.
Even though “loved by some and hated by others”, chef António Coelho “was a figure who managed to maintain the quality of Portuguese food, manufacturing everything in the restaurant itself, including the bread, the patties, everything, striving for quality”, he considered, adding that “even today there are many employees spread across Macau who continue with his approach to cooking”.
The chef’s most recent project was Angela’s Café and Lounge, at the Hotel Lisboeta. “He was loving the new challenge, seeing customers again and serving the things he loved to do.” For Vera Alcobia, her friend “left” at a time when she was also leaving the territory. “It’s sad,” he concludes.
It was also with “great sadness” that Santos Pinto, owner of the restaurant “O Santos”, received the news. “Another friend who left… He came here many times [to the restaurant], I always followed him very closely”, he said in statements to this newspaper, recalling all the steps taken by António in professional terms.
"We were close friends. Then when he opened 'António' here in Taipa, he became much busier, we didn't have as much time anymore, but there was always that hug, with a lot of friendship", he added. Santos Pinto highlighted that António “made many contributions to Macau, specifically to Portuguese and Macanese gastronomy”.
Carlos Cabral, president of the Confraria da Gastronomia Macaense – of which António Coelho was a member -, said that “it is a great sadness to lose a great figure in Portuguese gastronomy here in Macau”. For years, highlighted Carlos Cabral, the chef “practiced and developed his work, always serving the Portuguese and Macanese community, as well as tourists from various corners of the world”.
Pedro Lobo also remembers António's “unavoidable figure” in the kitchen in Macau: “It's a huge loss in the gastronomy scene. He was someone who put his touch, his personal stamp on Portuguese food, in the way he served his customers, in the way he respected his customers”.
As he said, “chef António was one of the people who knew Portuguese gastronomy in depth”. “At times, he was a little controversial in the opinions he expressed, but in any case he was someone who had value and who will always be marked in the history of Macau's gastronomy, particularly in the area of ​​Portuguese food”, continued Pedro Lobo.
Pointing out that the chef sometimes liked to “provoke discussions, in a good way”, Pedro Lobo highlighted that “he was always an affable, impeccable person”. “He was a very friendly person, with whom we lived and played, so he will always be someone who will be remembered with great nostalgia”, he pointed out.
Awarded the tourist merit medal by the Macao SAR Government in 2013, António Neves Coelho also received the Portuguese communities merit medal from the Portuguese Government.
When he arrived in the territory for the second time, already close to the transfer of sovereignty, he worked in several restaurants, having been chef at Clube Militar and at the “Espaço Lisboa” restaurant. He also had a brief stay in Hong Kong.
In 2007, he opened the restaurant bearing his name, in Taipa Velha, which received several international accolades. It was also highlighted, for 12 consecutive years, in the “Michelin Guide Hong Kong and Macau”.
In addition to being a member of the Macau Gastronomy Confraternity and member of the Macau Culinary Association, António Neves Coelho was also “Maitre Rotisseur” of the Association Mondiale de la Gastronomie, in France.
 
*With Vítor Rebelo</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rivungo, royal blessings and wildlife on the border banks of the Cuando River</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/actual/rivungo-bencaos-reais-fauna-selvagem-nas-margens-da-fronteira-rio-cuando/</link><description>King Golden Mangisi Kaputungo VIII (2-E), eighth descendant of a lineage dating back to the 19th century, during a presentation and blessing ceremony, in Embala, Rivungo municipality, Angola, October 10, 2025. Situated on the bank of the Cuando River, which marks Angola's natural border with Zambia, the remote municipality of Rivungo is about 1,600 kilometers from Luanda wants to abandon isolation, investing in ecological tourism and the traditions of his small kingdom. (FOLLOWS TEXT FROM LUSA ON OCTOBER 11, 2025). AMPE ROGÉRIO/LUSA




RAQUEL RIO*
Located on the bank of the Cuando River, which marks the natural border between Angola and Zambia, the remote municipality of Rivungo, around 1,600 kilometers from Luanda, wants to abandon isolation, focusing on ecological tourism and the traditions of its small kingdom.
In Angola, maps are deceiving. The distance from Mavinga, capital of Cuando, to Rivungo – 223 kilometers as the crow flies – translates into 16 hours of travel through almost invisible trails, between dense forest and soft sand trails that challenge the engines and the patience of travelers. The caravan that included Lusa reporters arrived at dawn, after a night on the road interrupted by flat tires, forced breaks, a lot of tension and accumulated fatigue.
The village, located in the extreme east-south of the country and now integrated into the new province of Cuando, tries to take advantage of the benefits of the recent administrative division and attract visitors interested in getting to know the wildlife, local rituals and receiving the blessing of King Kaputungo VIII.
Mateus Alfredo Malita, deputy municipal administrator, believes that investing in tourism and traditions can be a path to development: "Rivungo is one of the nine municipalities in Cuando. It is undergoing rapid development, taking into account the infrastructure that the State is building, such as the new municipal hospital, with a capacity of 30 beds, schools and projects to combat poverty", he lists.
Access remains the main obstacle. "We know about the difficulties of road connections, but the State is working to take the municipality out of isolation. Machines can already be seen on the Cuito Cuanavale–Mavinga section, and we hope that they will soon reach here. This will change everything", he told Lusa.
Rivungo, highlights the official, has a rare advantage: its proximity to Zambia, which opens up prospects for cross-border trade and tourism. “Our relationship with neighboring Zambia is good”, he stated, adding that there is cooperation and security, with no record of crimes associated with fuel smuggling, a scarce commodity in the locality and which is mandatory to transport given the absence of fueling stations.
“We want to attract investors to install a fuel pump here, something that would make life much easier for residents and the private sector”, he highlights.
Alongside the administration of the Angolan State, traditional authorities also continue to hold symbolic and effective power and it is almost obligatory for visitors to stop at the royal “embala” (village).
At the entrance, a group of women dance to the beat of royal drums before the king's guards lead visitors into the labyrinthine Embala Fumu Kaputungo, the heart of the ancient kingdom of Cuando. It is here that the sovereign Golden Mangisi Kaputungo VIII resides, the eighth descendant of a lineage that dates back to the 19th century.
The king receives the entourage seated on a high throne, with a carved alligator under his feet – “the king of the earth over the king of the river”, as explained by governor Eduardo Chicote Dandula, grand chief of the municipality and royal advisor. “Here there is only King Kaputungo”, repeats the sovereign during the blessing.
One by one, visitors kneel in front of the throne, after following the protocol: giving advance notice, bringing complimentary gifts (usually wine) and placing offerings in baskets (baskets) to obtain the blessing and protection of the ancestors.
Between the sound of drums and the chirping of birds, we are immersed in the spirit of our ancestors and in the almost untouched landscape of Rivungo, dotted with rivers and waterholes among forests and grass where the fauna that circulates through the Luengue-Luiana National Park, part of the Okavango-Zambezi transfrontier project, one of the largest ecological corridors in Southern Africa, hides. “The municipality is within the park and that is an advantage”, said Mateus Malita, who foresees the creation of small jobs for young people and opportunities in commerce and hotels.
Tourism is still timid, but promising, maintains the deputy administrator. "Even with difficult access, we have already received visitors interested in getting to know the local reality and our fauna. Rivungo is fertile, has arable land and lots of water. It has everything to attract those who want to invest, whether in agriculture or tourism."
Despite the lack of hotels and restaurants, Mateus Malita thinks that they will soon be built by inhabitants who believe in a future presence of visitors. "We still don't have the infrastructure we want, but we're starting. One day, who knows, we'll have a five-star hotel here to welcome tourists and visitors", the deputy administrator dreams.
The Rivungo region is part of the ancestral territory of the Kingdom of Cuando, founded by the Kwamashi people, a riverside group originating from the current Democratic Republic of Congo, who migrated south centuries ago in search of fertile land.
The Kaputungu royal lineage has continued to this day, with the current king being the guardian of this spiritual and cultural heritage.
The name Rivungo – derived from the Muvunguvungu tree – was adopted by Catholic missionaries who founded the Santa Cruz do Cuando Mission here in 1936, one of the first colonial centers in the region.
Rivungo is today the portrait of a deep Angola, which has changed little in recent decades and where the future emerges at a slow pace.
 
*Journalist at Lusa agency</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Study started for pedestrian system in Mong Há</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iniciado-estudo-para-sistema-pedonal-em-mong-ha/</link><description>Study and planning work has already begun for the pedestrian system to be included in the Municipal Park of Colina de Mong Há, assured the president of IAM, however, no details regarding the project's timing have been announced. Chao Wai Ieng stressed that it is necessary to carry out a prudent analysis, since Mong Há Hill is part of the Classified Real Estate
 
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) “has already started study and planning work” for the pedestrian system that aims to facilitate residents' access to the Mong Há Hill Municipal Park, said the chairman of the organization's Board of Directors, Chao Wai Ieng, in response to a written question from Nick Lei.
The deputy had noted that years ago the organization had organized, with associations and architects, a competition for the barrier-free pedestrian system in that area, however, “several years have passed since the conclusion of the competition and the authorities still do not have any concrete projects to move forward”.
He also noted that the Colina de Mong-Ha Municipal Park has four entrances and exits that are made up of stairs or ramps, “which does not favor access for the elderly and people with reduced mobility, constituting, above all, an obstacle for people who use wheelchairs”. Furthermore, on the sidewalk there are also “stairs in several places, which affects the desire of residents to climb the Hill and use the respective facilities”.
In the reply, Chao Wai Ieng highlighted that that location “is an important hill in Macau and involves Classified Real Estate and respective Protection Zones”, so the IAM “needs to study prudently and consult the opinions of competent services, in order to find a balance between the conditions of the site, the protection of world heritage and ecological conservation, among other factors, in order to prepare an appropriate project”. Details about the timeline for this project were not provided by the organization's leader.
On the other hand, Nick Lei pointed out that several facilities in the Mong-Ha Hill Municipal Park “are deteriorated or their design no longer meets current needs”. "As for this problem that is related to facilities, in terms of the short term, will the appropriate improvement be carried out as soon as possible to satisfy the real needs of use? In terms of the long term, under the assumption of compliance with the Law on Safeguarding Cultural Heritage, we must study the global reorganization of the Mong-Ha Hill Municipal Park, with the aim of its design better corresponding to the needs inherent to social development", he stressed, questioning whether this will be done.
In this context, the president of the IAM said that the organization “continues to listen to the opinions of society, to optimize the facilities of parks, gardens and leisure areas”. And he recalled that in July this year, stair handrails and fences were installed in places that meet the conditions for this purpose, in the Colina de Mong Há Municipal Park.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coutinho once again leads the single list for the ATFPM</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coutinho-volta-liderar-lista-unica-para-atfpm/</link><description>On October 26th, the ATFPM goes to the vote. The list presented by José Pereira Coutinho was the only one to apply, as he himself confirmed to this newspaper. In the program presented, Coutinho lists a series of priorities
 
The Association of Public Service Workers of Macau (ATFPM) will hold elections for management bodies (three-year period 2025-2028) on October 26th, which will take place between 10 am and 7 pm. The program on José Pereira Coutinho's list was the only one to reach the association's secretariat, as he himself confirmed to the TRIBUNA DE MACAU newspaper, so the deputy should therefore advance to a new term.
According to information disseminated by ATFPM, Coutinho is once again the president of the Board, while Rita Santos continues as president of the Board of the General Assembly. Maria Leong Madalena also remains president of the Supervisory Board.
José Pereira Coutinho – who sits in the Legislative Assembly, together with Chan Hao Weng and Che Sai Wang – listed, in a statement, some of his priorities as the main candidate on the list for the association's managing bodies. From the outset, he guaranteed that they will continue “fighting to ensure that the rights and interests of all public administration workers are respected”, namely proposing the salary update of three points in the index table, as well as the update of subsidies.
The president of ATFPM also said that he will insist “on the retroactive payment of the 7 thousand patacas for the remaining three years in a total amount of 21 thousand patacas, as well as increasing survival pensions by 100% and granting the residence allowance”.
“We will propose the granting of an electronic consumer card worth ten thousand patacas and that the economic contribution be increased to fifteen thousand patacas”, he added. On the other hand, he mentioned his intention to insist that concessionaires create more jobs for young people and that the Government “grant public housing expressly for young people as a way of increasing the number of births”.
According to José Pereira Coutinho, his list also intends to remain attentive to improving support for the disabled, single-parent families, informal caregivers, and bedridden elderly people. Full-time mothers who “face career abandonment, difficulty in relocation, salary inequality, lack of work flexibility and the stigma of being seen as less productive or committed” were also mentioned.
Furthermore, Coutinho assured that the ATFPM, under his command, will continue to “insist on the granting of residence allowances to Caixa Geral de Aposentações pensioners who reside in Macau”, as well as “on more support for members including their children who are unemployed through paid internships in services and public entities”.
 
CP.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Coffee and bakery gain strength at Franchise Expo</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/cafe-padaria-ganham-forca-na-expo-de-franquia/</link><description>This year's edition of the Macau Franchise Exhibition will pay special attention to intellectual property and synergies between coffee and bakery. The event will take place in parallel with the MIF and the China–Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition
 
More than a hundred exhibitors, including franchises and intellectual property (IP) licensing agents, from Mainland China, Southeast Asia, Hong Kong, Macau and other regions, will participate in the Macau Franchise Exhibition (MFE), co-organized by the Macao SAR Trade and Investment Promotion Institute (IPIM), “Macau Chain Stores and Franchise Association” and “Macao International Brand Enterprise Commercial Association” (MIBA). The exhibition will take place between the 22nd and 25th of October, at the Cotai Expo at the Venetian Macau, where three zones will be created: Brands, the Macau International Coffee Festival and IP Licensing, aiming to support the exploration of new business opportunities.
According to IPIM, the International Coffee Festival Zone will have a “significantly larger dimension” in this edition. In addition to collaborating with “Informa Markets”, a globally known exhibition company, in holding the World Coffee Extraction Championship – China Selection Competition (Macao Regional Competition), this Zone will be part of the Macau Intersectoral Bread Festival for the first time. More than 60 national and international coffee and bakery brands will be present at the event, which will include competitions, exhibitions and forums, to foster partnerships between the two sectors.
The Brand Zone will bring together “nationally and internationally recognized” brands, covering franchise companies and diversified chains in the bakery, catering, light meals sectors, among others, functioning as a professional platform for presenting products and holding contact exchanges. In addition, “on-site” visits to exhibitors will be organized, encouraging the introduction of transregional brands and the establishment of the first store in Macau.
In turn, the IP Licensing Zone will have an area 2.5 times larger than in 2024, highlighting several brands, such as Tahilalats and Meowlove, from the Indonesian studio MindBlowon; UGLYMEWS and GAEGUNEEZ, from South Korea; Zootopia, from Disney; and original IP from Macau and Greater Bay Area, such as Mr.Bubbles, WANAB. Sports IP will also be presented, including the “15th edition of the National Games, 12th edition of the National Games for People with Disabilities and 9th edition of the National Special Olympic Games”, the “Bicycle Tour of Italy” and the popular “Chinese Eight-Ball Billiards”.
The MFE will take place simultaneously with the 2nd China–Portuguese Speaking Countries Economic and Commercial Exhibition and the 30th Macau International Fair, in the same place and period. IPIM believes that holding events simultaneously will allow for an “efficient combination of resources and the maximization of benefits for all participants”.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IAM presented two new community projects</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/iam-apresentou-dois-novos-projectos-comunitarios/</link><description>The renovation project for the Tamagnini Barbosa Market was presented yesterday, which involves updating the facilities and equipment and reorganizing the sales stalls. The Institute for Municipal Affairs also took the opportunity to present the proposal for the construction of a new children's pavilion

PEDRO MILHEIRÃO
The Institute for Municipal Affairs (IAM) yesterday presented its plan to revitalize the Tamagnini Barbosa Market and the project for a children's exploration pavilion, which will be built in the Service Center on Avenida de Venceslau de Morais. IAM expects the market to resume normal operation in 2027 and for the pavilion works to be completed in the last quarter of 2028.
Regarding the Tamagnini Barbosa Market revitalization plan, the project foresees an adjustment of existing public spaces and the reorganization of stalls “by sales type” and the “separation of wet areas and dry areas”, as well as the creation of a food center on the first floor with more than 150 seats and 16 stalls. Three elevators will also be added, lighting and wastewater drainage and ventilation systems will be improved.
In addition to the construction of a corridor connecting to the Toi Fai Building's self-silo, spaces will be reserved to connect the market to the future “Sports Park for Citizens”.
According to Lao Sio Fun, head of IAM's markets division, “currently, the stalls are relatively small and the layout is not very good and is cramped”. "This market has been in operation for over 20 years. The lighting system is aged and the environment is quite humid. The aisles are small and the plumbing is out of date", he pointed out. This “new market model” will provide citizens with a “new shopping experience”.
Lao also guaranteed that “all seven entrances and exits to the market will be maintained” and that the “flow of people will be separated from the logistical flow of the market, in order to keep the floor dry”, similar to what happens with the Horta Mitra Market.
The head of the markets division stated that the plan has already been presented to the Advisory Council for Municipal Affairs and the Advisory Council for Community Services in the North Zone and that the organization has maintained “close communication with sellers to listen to their opinions and concerns”. In addition to the existing stalls, seven others will be available for public tender.
Preparatory work has already started, and the Government expects the first phase of work, on the first floor, to begin in the first three months of 2026, ensuring that all stalls continue to operate on the ground floor. During the second phase, planned for the third quarter of next year, fresh and live food stall sellers will be able to temporarily suspend their activities or transfer them to a temporary stall area.
The authorities also predict that the food center could open between July and September of next year and that the fresh and live produce stalls on the ground floor could resume activity in the first quarter of 2027.
 
Large leisure facility
Regarding the children's pavilion, Leong Ho Teng, senior technician at the IAM projects division, highlighted that people have expressed the “need for more community facilities” and that “the entire social sector wants to have more large-scale leisure facilities”.
The new complex will be organized into different areas, depending on the age group, since “all children have different experiences growing up”, highlighted Leong. The facilities will be aimed at young people up to the age of 18, based on the concept of a “playful exploratory supermarket”, with interactive games and a multi-themed modular design.
The first floor, measuring three thousand square meters, will be divided into six areas for children up to 12 years old. Slides, a wall and climbing net will be installed, and a creative challenge zone and a play area for early childhood children will be created. There will also be a multifunctional room, where workshops will be held for children and parents, a board games room, a toy library and a dining and rest area.
On the second floor, covering approximately 3,500 square meters, the five areas aimed at young people aged six to 18 will have a trampoline park, a hammock trail, sporting challenges, an “innovative sports space” and a games room.
Taking into account factors such as the “safety of children's facilities” and the “needs and demands of parents”, the organization hopes to be able to carry out public tender work for the pavilion in 2027.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Industrial sector closed 2024 with a surplus of 3.6 billion</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-industrial-fechou-2024-excedente-de-36-mil-milhoes/</link><description>In 2024, the Macao SAR industrial sector “earned” 3.6 billion patacas, 5.4% less than in the previous year. The data indicates that there was a general increase in expenses, both for energy and water production and distribution establishments and for manufacturing industries
 
Last year, the gross surplus of Macau's industrial sector amounted to 3.65 billion patacas, 5.4% less than in 2023, official data indicates. Revenues were 12.23 billion, corresponding to an annual increase of 1%. However, this growth was mitigated by higher expenses, as they reached 8.58 billion patacas, translating into a year-on-year increase of 4%.
In particular, manufacturing industries recorded a positive balance of 1.03 billion patacas, an annual drop of 21.4%. The sector's revenues were 7.6 billion, an annual decrease of 5.1%, while expenses fell 1.9%, to 6.56 billion, according to the Industrial Survey of the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC).
In 2024, the gross surplus of companies in the food and beverage industries fell by 36% to 523 million patacas. Revenues were 3.53 billion and expenses were 3.01 billion, corresponding to year-on-year increases of 0.2% and 11.2%, respectively.
In turn, the manufacture of cement and ready-mixed concrete was affected by a drop in demand for products in construction works, as noted by DSEC. This branch recorded “gains” of 348 million patacas, 10.2% below the value recorded in 2023. Revenue and expenses decreased by 19.9% ​​and 22.3%, respectively, to 1.55 billion and 1.21 billion patacas.
On the other hand, the production and distribution of electricity, gas and water recorded a surplus of 2.62 billion patacas, 2.9% more year-on-year. Expenses in this sector increased by 28.8%, from 2023 to 2024, reaching 2.02 billion. Revenues grew 12.8%, to a total of 4.64 billion.
Last year, the industry's production value amounted to 11.93 billion patacas, while the added value amounted to 6.55 billion patacas.
According to DSEC, the industrial sector had 888 establishments, 26 more than in 2023. Of these, five operated in the production and distribution of energy and water and 883 in manufacturing industries.
On the other hand, there were 247 fewer workers than in the previous year, making a total of 10,118 workers. In the energy and water sector, 1,095 people worked, 13 more than in 2023, while the manufacturing industries had 9,023 people working, 260 fewer than a year before.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Diversity and vitality” at the Autumn Salon</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/diversidade-vitalidade-salao-de-outono/</link><description>Around 100 works by more than 50 local artists will be on display at Casa Garden, as part of the 16th edition of the Salão de Outono. At the same time, the exhibitions “Exhibition within the Exhibition” and “Surrealistic Chinoiserie: Golden City of Seres” will also be on display.
 
“Homecoming: A Reunion between the Light and Shadow of History” will be the theme of the 16th edition of the “Art for All Society” (AFA) Autumn Salon, co-organized with Fundação Oriente. More than 50 local artists will present around a hundred works, which include Chinese painting, oil painting, watercolor, sculpture, photography, ceramics, installations, video and digital art. The opening ceremony will take place at 6:30 pm on October 24th, at Casa Garden, according to a press release from the organization.
The works of the artists who responded to the open call and were invited by Fundação Oriente will showcase “the diversity and vitality” of the local contemporary art scene as well as “the heritage and energy of Macau’s artistic ecosystem”. In addition, two other exhibits will also be on display, AFA said.
In the special area “Exhibition within the Exhibition”, the public will find the solo ceramic exhibition “The Caprichos of Creation” by Lio Pou I, winner of the Fundação Oriente 2024 Art Prize. Curated by Julia Lam Tsz Kwan and Leong Kit Man, Lio's “cloud and body forms” will explore “the deep meaning of life and existence”.
The two-year AFA project “Surrealistic Chinoiserie: Golden City of Seres”, by curator Alice Kok, will also be presented, an interdisciplinary collaboration that brings together “visual art, dance, music and costume design to present an artistic dialogue where Eastern and Western cultures intertwine, and the classic meets the futuristic”, it can be read. The project debuted in June in Antwerp, Belgium, and has now arrived in Macau, where it will remain until December 6th.
In this exhibition, the public will encounter the work of Leong Chi Mou, a visual exploration of the idea of ​​a “new type of silk”, with acrylic paintings on brass and steel. The performances, co-performed and choreographed by Jay Zhang and Tina Kan, will integrate Dunhuang-inspired forms with contemporary ballet, echoing “the cultural reconstruction of Leong’s work.”
Inspired by crystalline structures and cyborg shapes, designer Mandy Cheuk's futuristic helmets will imagine “the interplay between body and technology”, while the music by composer Faye Choi and flutist Iris Lo will mix “ethereal Eastern tones with Western electronic textures to complete a sensorial and immersive experience”.
The project had the initial guidance of Belgian artistic director Dirk Decloedt and production support from Florence Fong. According to AFA, the work aims to create “new artistic vocabularies” and spaces for reflection, establishing a bridge between the surrealism inspired by Magritte and Macau’s cultural identity.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Halftone exhibition presents more than 20 photographs</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/mostra-da-halftone-apresenta-mais-de-20-de-fotografias/</link><description>A collective exhibition that opens today at the Rui Cunha Foundation will showcase the photographic works of 23 members of Halftone – Macau Photographic Association. The exhibition is curated by Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro and Francisco Ricarte

























The photographic works of 23 amateur and professional artists who are part of Halftone – Macau Photographic Association will be presented today at the Rui Cunha Foundation Gallery (FRC), in a collective exhibition curated by Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro and Francisco Ricarte. The opening of the exhibition is scheduled for 6:30 pm.
The joint exhibition, entitled “Halftone’ 25”, reveals more than two dozen works, “ranging from documentary photography to artistic expression, including landscape, human, studio, conceptual, street photography”, in color or black and white. These photographs can be seen by the public until October 25th.
As in previous years, images were selected – some already known and others new – by the authors, mentioned here in alphabetical order: André Carvalhosa, António Mil-Homens, António Sotero, António Bessa Almeida, Cássia Schutt, Catarina Cortesão Terra, Carmen Serejo, Cristiana Figueiredo, David Lopo, Elói Scarva, Francisco Ricarte, Gonçalo Lobo Pinheiro, Inela Kovacevic, Joana Freitas, João Miguel Barros, João M. Rato, João Palla Martins, Jorge Veiga Alves, José das Neves, José Sales Marques, Kuok Hou Tang, Nélson Silva and Nuno Calçada Bastos.
Entry is free, to this exhibition that has the support of the FRC and Banco Nacional Ultramarino.
Created in 2021, Halftone is a non-profit cultural association that aims to promote contemporary photography in all its aspects. Founded in an inclusive and comprehensive way, it is open to all those who are interested in photography as an artistic or documentary expression, regardless of their experience or practice, says a statement from the FRC.
In addition to boosting the photographic work of its members, Halftone also aims to organize exhibitions, publish a magazine, books and monographs, organize debates and develop pedagogical and educational projects.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao SAR support plan is a “great opportunity” for Portuguese stores</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/plano-de-apoio-da-raem-e-grande-oportunidade-para-lojas-portuguesas/</link><description>The subsidy program of up to one million patacas to attract international companies to Macau is “a great opportunity for Portuguese stores”, said the secretary general of the Luso-Chinese Chamber of Commerce and Industry yesterday. "It's a great opportunity for Portuguese stores that want to internationalize in Asia; Macau is a showcase for China and a place where tourists look for entertainment and shopping", said Bernardo Mendia, adding that "a good experience in Macau is a safe step towards later entering China". Speaking to Lusa on the eve of the presentation of the program that will come into force in November, Mendia explained that the support given by Macau is for international companies that want to expand their presence in the territory, subject to certain conditions, which in the case of Portuguese and Spanish brands are mitigated. “If the companies are from Portuguese or Spanish-speaking countries, the requirements of the regulation are less stringent, as long as they are recommended by a chamber of commerce”, said the businessman, highlighting that, although the authorities' objective is to attract world-renowned brands to Macau, in the case of Portuguese and Spanish companies “the criteria for obtaining the subsidy is easier to comply with”. Furthermore, he highlighted, “in Macau there are Portuguese banks, legal services, accountants and other professional service providers essential to the internationalization of Portuguese brands”. The initiative will be presented today in Lisbon and, later, also in Porto, Madrid and Barcelona during this week, with the presence of officials from the Macau Trade and Investment Promotion Institute.</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Rome will show the influence of great masters in Dalí’s work</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/roma-vai-apresentar-influencia-de-grandes-mestres-na-obra-de-dali/</link><description>Revolution and tradition in the work of Salvador Dalí will meet next Friday in a major exhibition in Rome. Coinciding with the centenary of the Spanish artist's first solo exhibition, the exhibition will explore the influences of great names in painting, such as Velázquez, Rafael and Picasso.

Entitled “Dalí, Revolution and Tradition”, the exhibition will be on display between October 17th and February 1st, 2026, at “Palazzo Cipolla”, in the Italian capital. The public will have the opportunity to appreciate more than 60 works by Salvador Dalí, including paintings and drawings, as well as photographic and audiovisual material, thus immersing themselves in his complex creative universe.
The works belong to the collection of the Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation, as well as prestigious international institutions such as the Museu Nacional Centro de Arte Reina Sofía, the Museu Nacional Thyssen-Bornemisza, the Picasso Museum in Barcelona and the Uffizi Galleries in Florence, the organizers explained.
Under the scientific direction of Montse Aguer, director of the Dalí Museums, and curated by Carme Ruiz González and Lucia Moni, the exhibition offers a unique journey focused on Dalí's relationship with four great figures: three historical masters – the Dutch Johannes Vermeer, the Spanish Diego Velázquez and the Italian Rafael – and a contemporary, Pablo Picasso.
"Dalí always felt a deep admiration for Italy. The Renaissance masters represented a reference point on his horizon. This exhibition aims to go beyond the individual and reveal the critical thinking that defines his creative universe", explained Fèlix Roca Batllori, general director of the Gala-Salvador Dalí Foundation, during the presentation of the exhibition.
In the late 1930s, Dalí openly expressed his desire to “become a classic” and recognized Velázquez, Vermeer and Rafael as his great role models. He even dedicated his studies and citations to them, reaching their peak in the “Comparative Table of Values”, included in the treatise “50 Magical Secrets of Painting”, where he exalts the technical and compositional values ​​of classical painting.
The exhibition in Rome will allow us to observe how the Spanish painter transitioned from an academic style of painting to constant experimentation with the European avant-garde, ultimately developing his own unique language.
“We have prepared a unique and innovative exhibition for Rome, which explores the alternation between two apparently opposite poles – revolution and tradition – in Salvador Dalí’s artistic production”, said Lucia Moni, curator of the Fundació Gala-Salvador Dalí, cited by the EFE agency.
The exhibition will be divided into four sections, each dedicated to one of the great masters who inspired the painter. In these sections, Dalí will be portrayed not only as the great surrealist of the 20th century, but also as an intellectual capable of reformulating the codes of modern art.
The new Roma Foundation project thus continues the dialogue started with Pablo Picasso, a figure with whom Dalí maintained a complex relationship throughout his career and whose exhibition, recently closed, was visited by more than 80 thousand people.
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-10-14 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>