<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Students will have a platform for mental health consultation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/alunos-vao-ter-plataforma-para-consulta-de-saude-mental/</link><description>A 24 -hour online consultation platform for students will be launched in the scope of mental health. The tool will allow risk cases to be forwarded to “timely” support through the Verde of Health Services
 
Catarina Pereira
 
To intervene early on mental health problems, the government will “reinforce psychological support in community neighborhoods and schools”. In particular, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) will launch “a 24 -hour online consultation platform for all students”, in the context of mental health.
This tool will allow, “in view of the risks detected and the hidden cases of students”, directly forward students to “timely support”, through the Verde Verde provided by health services (SSM), revealed the body's director, Alvis Lo.
At the same time, “the size of students' counseling services teams will be increased, reinforcing their functions in identifying, supporting and monitoring students with needs”. This is through “Chat with U-Open Line Program for Students and Support through the Internet”, which provides an immediate open line and online emotional support services to students with needs, can be read to respond to a Song Pek Kei interpellation.
The deputy was concerned about the issue of suicide, asking for a monitoring mechanism to reinforce support and intervention. According to information released by the authorities, 84 suicide attempts were reported in the first quarter of this year, "which reflects the high risk of suicide in Macao," he noted.
In this context, he argued that all age groups face different pressures and challenges, and it is difficult to count only on the strength of a single public service or a professional aspect to deal effectively, with psychological pressure and emotional problems. Specifically, he pointed out that emotional problems need to be detected at an early stage.
Alvis Lo pointed out that the SSM, the DSEDJ and the Institute of Social Action (IAS) have maintained a close communication with community institutions, realizing the joint mechanism of “joint four level prevention” on mental health. He also said that DSEDJ promoted the creation of the “Working Group on Physical and Mental Health at School” in all schools, and the students 'mental health identification table and their work guidelines so that schools can identify, in due time, the students' needs and support them taking into account the corresponding level.
In turn, Si Ka Lon also expressed concern about this issue. The deputy recalled that in recent years, the number of suicide deaths has been increasing in Macao, with 91 cases in 2024, "the highest number of the last 10 years." In view of the international suicide rate, "which is 9 to 10 per 100,000 people, the Macao rate is 30% higher, which shows that mental health has already become a major challenge for public health," he warned.
In the response also signed by the SSM director, it is said that there are currently more than 7,000 people who have accepted the formation of being “guardian of life”-people who engage in promoting mental health and community well-being, being encouraged to pay attention to the psychological health of those around them.
In the future, says Alvis Lo, IAS will cooperate with different institutions and associations to continually disclose the idea of ​​“affectionate people”, dedicated to forming more “life guardians”.
It also underlines that “in the face of possible psychological or emotional disturbances”, SSM, “in addition to providing psychological support measures, also appeals to residents to develop a healthy lifestyle, namely regular exercise, balanced diet and enough rest”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao Catholic churches were erected with innovative techniques</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/igrejas-catolicas-de-macau-foram-erguidas-tecnicas-inovadoras/</link><description>The first bamboo reinforced concrete techniques will have been used in the Catholic churches of Macao in the 16th century. One study stresses that the architecture of the churches influenced the urban development of the city and the Lingnan region. It also points out that “the process of building the modern Catholic churches in Macao deeply reflects the double trajectory of colonial expansion and cultural adaptation”
 
Pedro Milheirão
 
The construction of the 16th century Catholic churches in Macao will have launched the foundations for the city's urban development and influenced the architectural evolution in the Lingnan region, indicates an investigation published in the Journal of Asian Architecture and Building Engineering ”. According to the article entitled “A Study on Architectural Characteristics and the Value of Modern Catholic Churches in Macao”, the churches have become spaces that allowed the expression of new techniques in religious architecture.
The use of bark powder and straw to reinforce the strength and durability of buildings, for example, were innovative methods, according to the researchers group composed by Francisco Vizeu Pinheiro, from the Faculty of Arts and Humanities of the University of St. Joseph, and the Academics Yao Wu, Yonglan Wu and Mingrui Miao, from Suzhou University.
Researchers suggest that at that time the first bamboo reinforced concrete techniques were used in European architectural constructions. The "choice of the place, the layout, the unique style and the structural requirements" reflected "a deep architectural wisdom."
The modern Catholic churches of Macao, "with new materials and elements," contrasting "strongly with Lingnan's architecture", and exhibited "various well -defined spatial styles and functions." Construction materials and decorative patterns typical of Lingnan's traditional culture, in turn, were also incorporated, "reflecting respect and continuation of local culture." Constructions gave rise to “distinct and attractive” urban landscapes, as well as provided “essential” support for the sustainable development of the city.
For the conduct of this study, the group of researchers analyzed 12 churches -such as the São Francisco Xavier Church, Sé, St. Augustine, São Lourenço or Penha -from four dimensions: Layout, style evolution, construction technology and cultural value. According to the authors, Macao became a “unique stage for the intersection and integration of oriental and western architectural art, religious thinking and even social culture”.
The article describes the “influence of the diffusion of western culture”, but also the “adaptation” to what was local. “As an architectural product of a special historical context, the process of building modern Catholic churches in Macao deeply reflects the double trajectory of colonial expansion and cultural adaptation,” says the study.
Events such as the discovery of commercial routes in southeastern China by the Portuguese, the attempted Dutch invasion of Macao and the British occupation of Hong Kong will have influenced the development of Catholic churches in the territory.
These events would eventually introduce classic elements of the West into local architecture, such as baroque and gothic styles. Ties with Portugal, Southeast Asia and Islamic Religious Culture also shaped Macao's architecture, “enriching the cultural diversity and uniqueness” of the churches, can read.
More concretely, as regards the plant of churches, it is said that they have three types - the convex symmetrical plant, which “inherits the tradition of European basilicas and reinforces the sacredity of ritual space”; the parallel rectangular plant, which adapts “to the dense urban texture of Macao with a single compact main hall”; and the symmetrical curved plant, which "reaches acoustic optimization and the translation of maritime cultural symbols through curved walls."
For the authors, "this type of differentiation shows that by transplanting western spatial paradigms, the architecture of the churches of Macau has developed a local adaptation logic based on the geographical environment and functional needs."
The façade of the churches, in turn, also shows that style has undergone four phases of transformation: the proportional law of Renaissance classicism, the dynamic composition of baroque aesthetics, the simplified form of neoclassicism and the local experience of gothic rebirth. In the study, it is noted that "the styles of each phase are not simply copied, but cultural translation is achieved through the local transformation of crafts."
By way of example, researchers point out “the reduction of the depth of relief in the baroque gerine of the Rosary Church [São Domingos Church]” and “the elevation of the classic base of the Saint Joseph Seminary column”. “This double mechanism of 'imitation of the form-formal form' confirms the essential attributes of colonial architecture as a field of cultural negotiation,” they continue.
 
Social changes and cultural exchanges
In addition, research offers a perspective for understanding the social changes and cultural exchanges of Macao and the entire coastal area of ​​China. The connection of churches to the Silk Maritime Route, for example, contributed to a free economic flow, greater integration and cooperation between markets, as well as an improvement in cultural exchanges between civilizations and connectivity between Asia, Europe and Africa.
The arrival of Catholicism also reconfigured religious practice, which involved, above all, the worship of the sea gods and a reverence for natural forces. The Catholic Church brought rooted ideals in justice and ethics, and the new churches served as instruments of social control and cultural reproduction.
Through “a comprehensive analysis of the intersection, merger and coexistence of oriental and western cultural influences”, this investigation provides ideas for the conservation of Macao's architecture and heritage, consider the authors of the study.
"In part of the cross analysis of space, technology and culture, it reveals the complexity of the churches of Macau as 'intercultural construction products'. The study confirms that the 'local nature' of colonial architecture is not only reflected in the imitation of form, but also exists in the multifaceted interaction of material translation, adaptation of the process and symbolic reorganization," they reiterate. Investigators also point out that "the continuous use of the church to this day makes it in a typical case of living cultural heritage protection."</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities bet on creating “sustainable” AI system</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-apostadas-em-criar-sistema-de-ia-sustentavel/</link><description>Continue to develop studies on artificial intelligence technology, as well as formations for civil service workers are some of the government's objectives, which is betting on creating a “sustainable” AI platform for public services. One of the aspects the executive wants to explore is the use of AI in the treatment of official documents, "namely in the wording, review and translation." On the other hand, I intend to introduce new elements into the single account, offering an “innovative experience”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The executive intends to establish “a sustainable artificial intelligence platform for use of public services” and, for this, will reinforce the results of AI support work, namely “through training in possible scenarios and practical experience”. The idea is to contribute to “the general and detailed planning of the IMA's practical application” in the future, including, for example, the space of machine rooms, computing resources, knowledge training, the development platform, indicated the substitute director of administration and public function services (SAFP), Joana Maria Noronha, in response to an interpellation of deputy Wong Kit Cheng.
Stressing that the government “pay attention” to AI development trends, “proactively exploring its development space within the scope of services provided to citizens and the internal operation of public services”, the SAFP substitute director pointed out that this technology is currently used mainly as an auxiliary means. The SAFP public information center, for example, has applied AI in telephone service services, “increasing the efficiency of service and treatment of complaints presented”.
On the other hand, according to Joana Maria Noronha, 11 services “related to the life of the population from various areas” were selected to organize the information of these services and to the IMA training, “which will be gradually extended to other services according to their results”.
In relation to the application of AI on government electronic platforms, authorities plan to promote the work of updating the single account, introducing “new elements” and “changing the more passive service model to a more active model”. By way of example, the substitute director indicates that, according to the age of the use, the new model may send information from services that will be useful, or the user may interact with the AI ​​helper through voice or writing messages, "offering him an innovative experience."
At the same time, the government intends to explore the use of AI tools to assist public services workers in the treatment of official documents, "namely in the wording, revision and translation, in order to increase administrative efficiency."
"With the continuous development of AI technologies and the promotion of MSAR government's experimental studies and works, SAFP plan to provide training actions to workers at different levels, from management to basic practice, in order to increase personnel knowledge about AI development trends and their technical application," adds the answer to Wong Kit Cheng.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal pay attention to salaries offered to TNR</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsal-atenta-salarios-oferecidos-tnr/</link><description>Given complaints of restoration and construction workers who arrived at Deputy Leong Sun IOK, about worse employment opportunities for residents in the face of TNR, the management of services for labor affairs says it is attentive and authorizing TNR hiring requests depending on the law. It also wins that it will not authorize TNR requests from companies that submit “an unreasonable salary level”
 
The Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) ensures that it is aware of the requests for hiring non -resident workers (TNR) and the compensation offered by companies following a written interpellation of Leong Sun IOK. The deputy was reported to have received complaints from restoration and construction workers, that TNR could work full time and local workers are “mostly part-time workers or short-term”, faced with “underemployment” and “income insufficient” situations.
First of all, the body's director, Chan Un Tong, stresses that the importation of labor “aims only to temporarily supply the insufficiency of local human resources”, so companies should “always” give priority to places, provided that there are jobs in which residents are interested and for which require the requirements. Companies cannot allow, by no means, that the importation of TNR impairs employment opportunities and residents' rights and labor interests, ”he says.
Regarding the treatment of requests for hiring TNR, the DSAL director indicates that, under the law, several factors such as the general socioeconomic development, the offer and demand for labor in the employment market, the size and exploration situation of the requesting companies, the situation of hiring existing workers and working conditions, among others. The body “has been assessed and authorized by each case of request, pursuant to the law and according to its concrete situation”, it may be read.
Regarding the compensation offered by companies to TNR, “DSAL has proceeded to the global consideration of various factors”: the salary level of the economic activity and jobs in the employment market; the salary level of the workfold recruited and registered with DSSA; as well as the size of companies, “in order to guarantee the paying equality paid between equal or equal value provided by resident and TNR workers”. “If a company intends to hire TNR with an unreasonable salary level, DSAL will not authorize its request,” says Chan Un Tong.
In response to Leong Sun IOK, the body states that it will continue to closely follow the evolution of the employment market and dynamically adjust the number of TNR, "striving to coordinate the balance between supply and demand for labor." DSAL also ensures that it will “seriously hear” the opinions of the company about the appreciation and authorization of the requests for hiring TNR.
 
Labor import maintains a trend of slowing down
Macao had 183,783 non-resident workers (TNR) at the end of May, representing a monthly rise of 0.1% or 215 individuals, confirming the softening trend in 2025, according to data from the Public Security Police body released by services for labor affairs. The number of TNR increased only 0.6%, or 1,241 workers, compared to the end of December. On the other hand, imported labor rose 1.7% (plus 3,006) compared to the same month of 2024 and corresponds to 93.5% of the total recorded at the end of December 2019, the pre-pound year. In late May this year, workers from the interior of China (121,155) remained the main non-resident work force, followed by the Philippines (31,472), Vietnam (8,111), Indonesia (7,858), Myanmar (4,569), Nepal (3,884), Hong Kong (2,191) and Tailândia and Tailândia and Tailândia (904). The branch of hotels, restaurants and the like dominates labor imports, with 54,569 TNR, or 29.7% of the total, followed by families with domestic employees (27,972).
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Former JTM director competes for the Municipal Assembly of Mira</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ex-director-jtm-concorre-a-assembleia-municipal-de-mira/</link><description>José Firmino da Rocha Diniz, co-founder, former director and former administrator of the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, will be the candidate of the Socialist Party (PS) to the presidency of the Mira Municipal Assembly, in the next local elections, which will take place in September or October this year.
"It is a choice of high symbolism and quality, which projects a clear ambition: it reinforces the prestige and demand in the democratic life of the municipality of Mira. The decision of Francisco Reigota, candidate of the PS to the City Hall, is seen as a certain and consistent choice, bringing to Mirense civic life a huge national and international prestige. underlines a note from the PS of that municipality of the district of Coimbra.
Journalist, teacher of higher education, man of culture, letters and history, José Rocha Diniz is seen as “a born communicator, respected and listened to in the decision centers, both in Portugal and abroad”. He lived and worked in various parts of the world-namely in Macau-and was distinguished with important awards, such as the Macao Government Cultural Merit and the Grand Officer of the Order of Merit, awarded by the President of the Republic Jorge Sampaio.
After a career “marked by excellence and public service, he returned to aim and now accepts this challenge: helping the county reaching a new level of development,” says the same note, adding that the candidate “affirms himself as a coherent man, knowledgeable of local reality and deeply committed to improving collective life”.
Rocha Diniz intends to be a president of the “active, participatory and demanding Municipal Assembly, raising the role of this body that must be, by nature, the main guarantee of political stability and good governance”. "It rejects the decorative role that is sometimes attributed to it, and it is proposed to lead a new phase of institutional appreciation, democratic dialogue and accountability of the elected," emphasizes the PS, convinced that it is a "clear", "safe" and "time-to give the future it deserves, raising the level".
“José Rocha Diniz represents integrity, knowledge and vision. It is undoubtedly an exception figure that will bring enormous value to the project led by Francisco Reigota and the future governance of the county,” says Mira PS, assuming the purpose of “doing what has not yet been done”, with “courage” and “competence”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Colo-Rectal tracking lowered to the age of 50</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/rastreio-colo-rectal-baixou-para-os-50-anos/</link><description>The minimum age of participation in the Color-Rectal cancer screening program becomes 50 years. After adjustment, residents up to 69 may take the exam. The marking is available through the single account
 
Health services (SSM) have dropped to 50 years the minimum age so that residents can participate for free in the colo-recrectal cancer screening program, launched in 2016. After adjustment, those interested in performing the examination between 50 and 69 years, therefore born between 1956 and 1975, can participate in the program.
Residents who gather the conditions can mark online, in the “my health” function of the Single Account, on the SSM page, or go to the corresponding residence area health center to mark the evaluation or request information. Other conditions to be eligible include not having had any colonoscopy in the last five years, nor hidden blood test in the last two, as well as not suffering or suffered from colo-rectal cancer.
The SSM predict that 39,000 people will benefit from the program after adjustment and said that in the future they will continue to extend the age of access and may increase the maximum age of participants.
According to data from the body, in the last 10 years 2,999 residents have performed a colonoscopy, with 312 high -risk polyps were found. Meanwhile, in 168 patients was diagnosed with colo-rectal cancer. Specifically, 50% of these patients were in the early phase of the disease.
In the last five years the mortality rate of this type of cancer has decreased 12.6% in Macao compared to the registered rate before the launch of the tracking program. On the other hand, the survival rate, in that time space, of patients with colo-rectal cancer also registered an increase of 8%, which “shows the effectiveness of implementing the measure”, pointed out the SSM, for whom the program “should have continuity and even more optimized”.
It was also revealed that by June this year a total of 31,000 residents, aged 55 to 69, participated in the program, representing about 17% of people in this age group. In addition, 50% performed screening tests at Kiang Wu Hospital, 30% did so at the University Hospital and 20% on Yinkui. Authorities believe that vacancies are sufficient, however, they are discussing with the Islands Hospital the possibility of being established a transfer cooperation of some participants in the program.
Underlining that Colo-Rectal cancer is one of the most common cancer in Macao, occupying second place among the first 10 more incidence cancers and cause of cancer death, SSM predicts that the number of cases continue to increase due to population aging and unbalanced diet.
Colo-rectal cancer may develop in anyone, occurring more often in people aged 60 years or over, due to the entry in the period when the colo-recrectal mucosa cells become polyps, and later become carcinogenic, which may take up to 10 years. In this sense, the maintenance of a balanced diet, exercise practice frequently and regularly performing regular colorectal screening may prevent the manifestation of colo-rectal cancer.
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Crucial digital economy for diversification</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/economia-digital-crucial-para-diversificacao/</link><description>The digital economy was highlighted as a new engine for the diversification of Macao's economy by the secretary for the economy and finance in launching a series of activities of the “25th anniversary celebration of the Macao Commercial Association Commission - Women in Business &amp; Economics Forum”. In his speech, Tai Kin IP stated that at a time when globalization and technological revolution are “deeply integrated”, the digital economy “is not only a product of technological evolution, but also a key driving force to remodel the economic structure and increase competitiveness”.
The ruler indicated that, in recent years, the development of the digital economy has been "a fundamental force" in the reorganization of global elements and resources, the remodeling of economic structure and the restructuring of competition. " QR. This is a “significant growth that has not been reached immediately, being a progress that all present can see and is strictly related to all of us,” he said.
With a good use of data elements, “it is possible to activate the potential of traditional industries and provide SMEs with an innovative low -cost and high efficiency path,” said Tai Kin IP, for whom “this is why the digital economy is an indispensable engine for the reconversion of Macao, which is an unavoidable path to the territory”.
Despite support plans for more than 1,600 companies to perform digital counterpart, the secretary admits that "Macau is still too late in terms of digital reconversion pace compared to other advanced economies."
In his intervention in the Forum organized by the Commercial Association, Tai Kin IP stressed that "the benefits of digitization for society are undeniable." Faced with the current world geopolitical and economic situation, “complex and steep”, Macau as an autonomous customs zone and Porto Franco, became an important bridge head for the opening of the country to the world ”.
He concluded, hoping that more Macao entrepreneurs "give wide to their wisdom and dare to be the first to lead their companies to intelligent adaptation and digitization", encouraging more young women to participate in technological innovation, "in order to help Macau achieve the proper diversification of the economy."
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Unemployment rate remains at 1.9%</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/taxa-de-desemprego-permanece-em-19/</link><description>For the third consecutive period, the general unemployment rate in Macau has not changed, remaining 1.9% between March and May, according to official data
 
The global unemployment rate at MSAR was estimated at 1.9% between March and May this year, thus equating the same level registered in the previous period (February to April), the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) said yesterday. The unemployment rate of the residents remained at 2.5%, and the two indicators did not change for the third consecutive period.
On the other hand, the global (1.6%) and underemployment subsidiary rates of residents (2.1%), which encompass cases of unpaid licenses, advanced 0.2 and 0.3 percentage points, respectively, compared to those of the past period.
Between March and May, the active population living in Macau descended 0.1% to 380,200, in sequential terms. The employed population (373,000 individuals) decreased 0.1% (200 people), compared to the immediately preceding period, however, residents employed (282,200) rose 0.1% (plus 300), with the increase of jobs in the construction sector to compensate for a decrease in the branch of financial activities.
In general terms, compared to the previous period, workers of the station sectors and other betting games (about 69,300), thick trade and retail (45,400) and construction (22,400) grew 0.7%, 1.0%and 4.6%, respectively. In the opposite direction, labor in hotel (30,000 employees) and restoration (20,900) fell 0.2% and 0.9%, respectively.
Unemployed residents (7,200) went down 2.1% (200 people), compared to the previous period. Among the unemployed looking for a new job, most previously worked in retail, construction and game sectors.
According to DSEC, individuals looking for the first job equivalent to 8.4% of unemployed residents, less than 1.8 points than in the period between February and April.
In turn, the number of underemployed residents (6,000) rose 13.8% (plus 800 people) in relation to the previous period. Most of the undereased construction sector and the industry of real estate and services provided to companies.
When compared to the period between March and May 2024, global (66.6%) and resident activity rates (61.3%) lowered 0.8 and 0.7 percentage points, respectively.
Employment survey excluded residents and non -residents who, despite working in Macao, live abroad, whose average number was calculated at about 106,400 in the period under analysis. Including this group, the total labor encompassed 486,500 people.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Dili Declaration” results from the union of Luso-Asian</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/declaracao-de-dili-resulta-da-uniao-de-luso-asiaticos/</link><description>The 4th edition of the Luso-Asian Communities Conference, which took place for three days in Timor-Leste, ended with the signing of the “Dili Declaration”, a document that aims to create an association, towards cooperation and joint solidarity work for the benefit of Portuguese-speaking communities in Asia.
The text, prepared by representatives of the delegations of the eight countries or regions present, presents a “strictly cultural, dialogue and mutual respect, united by the richness of a legacy inherited over centuries and which we want to convey to future generations”.
Signatories assume the “shared will to look for solutions that translate into concrete benefits for each community, serving and valuing their specificities”.
The “declaration of dili” is part of the spirit that presides over the conference of the Luso-Asian communities, so it is considered “essential to consubstantiation of this event in an association”, to host in the Timorese capital, which will constitute “a link between these communities”, but also provides a “meeting point”, linking them to partner entities, investigators and academics, movements and cultural associations, and cultural associations and associations Solidarity, among others, “in a joint effort of defense of the human and cultural heritage they represent”.
Macao was represented by Miguel de Senna Fernandes, through the Macanese Association and Promoter Association of Macanese Instruction, and José Sales Marques, from the Macanese Council of Communities. Also present communities of Malaca (Malaysia), Tugu and Flores (Indonesia), Burgher (Sri Lanka), Goa (India), Kudichin (Thailand), Bayingyi (Myanmar) and Oedusse (Timor-Leste), totaling more than a hundred people.
Miguel de Senna Fernandes told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that this is “a noble idea”, in the sense that “we have a common legacy, a belonging, which is something that unites us and, deep down, has to do with the Portuguese presence itself”.
In his intervention at the Forum, Macaense talked about the effort to promote the maquista through theater and choir in Patuá by the Dóci Papiaçá Di Macau and, before him, by Adé dos Santos Ferreira and others. “The highlight of the day was the video of our version of‘ Macau Sami ’on Youtube,” he said.
The next conference in 2027 is expected to take place in Lisbon. "It is good that this happens, because it is important that Portugal has a sense of its decisive influence on the formation of these peoples, at a time when the historical overseas vocation seems to have been converted into a malaise, but even in a feeling of shame and" mea guilt "among the Portuguese," he emphasized, adding that this feeling "must be eradicated".
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Vandilion Zone at IAO Hon Optimized from September</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/zona-de-vendilhoes-iao-hon-optimizada-partir-de-setembro/</link><description>From September, the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMI) will carry out optimization works in the Iao Hon market vendin zone, divided into four phases. The idea is to comprehensively reshape the facilities of the banks, reinforce fire prevention measures, raise the level of safety in the use of electricity, increasing leisure space and improving the operating environment. It is recalled that that zone was affected by a fire in April this year. According to the AMI, during the works, the operations of the vendins will not be affected and they will not need to suspend the business. At the same time, AMI will maintain “close communication” with the sailings to try to transfer the current 32 newsstands to new newsstands before next New Year Lunar. The first three phases of the project consist of a comprehensive update of the stalls facilities and equipment, including the installation of independent electricity counters, separating the newsstands by brick walls, and equip each bank with fire roller and transparent roller line. The following premise is to keep the current north-south layout of the vendin zone being unchanged the area of ​​each bank. In addition, the function of turning off the electricity automatically will be added, and when the vendon closes the roll shutter, the electricity supply in the bank will stop. In addition, the distance between the newsstands and the Kat Cheong building will be extended from five to six meters. Already in the 4th phase of the works, will be built a small leisure square on the south side of the vendin area. On the other hand, in an open session of AI, President Chao Wai Ieng revealed that a proposal for optimization for the Tamagnini Barbosa Municipal Market will be prepared.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Couto leaves in China and Leong wins in Japan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/couto-abandona-na-china-leong-vence-japao/</link><description>Macau pilot André Couto was not happy to return to the competition, having abandoned the second race of the third round of the China Tourism Car Championship at the Zhejiang circuit. After being ranked eighth in the initial weekend race, Couto started in front of the grid as a result of the reversal of race positions, but was ranked on the first lap and abandoned. This was not, therefore, the best return to the tracks of the representative of the Macao MacPro Racing Team team. "It was quite confident for both races in China, but unfortunately the car sport is like this and we can't control when we have accidents caused by opponents," he told the Journal Tribuna de Macao. André Couto, who trimmed a Honda, stressed that "the car walked well in training and qualification", where it was a fourth positioned, but already in the first race suffered a touch, "that destabilized the car, even though it was able to end." For the driver, "the team bet everything in the second race in Zhejiang and we had the mission to win, since it was the first time this year I ran in this championship." In turn, another local pilot, Charles Leong, leads the absolute classification in Lamborghini Super Trofeo Asia's Pro Lamboghini class, pairing with Irishman Alex Denning at SJM Theodore Racing. Charles won the second race of the third round of the time, in Fuji, Japan, after being second the day before. The next day is scheduled for Inje, South Korea, between July 18 and 20. It is recalled that Charles Leong triumphed in Formula 4 of the Macao Grand Prix in 2020 and 2021.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IC looks for “exclusive” products for “Hush!” Festival</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ic-procura-produtos-exclusivos-para-festival-hush/</link><description>The “Hush! Concerts on Praia 2025”, scheduled for mid -October and organized by the Cultural Institute (IC), is inviting local cultural and creative entities to develop exclusive products for the “Hush!” Brands Project. In addition to using the brand “Hush!” In design, this year is added the mascot “Hush!” as a new intersection element to “promote the fusion between music and creative culture”. Proposals can be delivered until 5 pm on July 9. The annual event of the cultural brand “Hush! Concerts on the Beach” includes concerts and thematic shows, as well as bazaars with stalls, music workshops, experiences with musical instruments, installation art, online music contests, among other activities. Under this project now launched, the selected entities will be allowed to use the registered brand “Hush!” or the “Hush!” Mascot, as a “joint partner”, to launch and sell melting products, but assuming the exclusive responsibility for profits and losses, says the IC. According to the body, the integration of music with culture and creativity will be promoted through interaction between musical brands and associated entities, "allowing them to be recognized by broader audiences." Selected entities will also be able to set up the newsstands to sell their own brand and hush! in a designated area, in the places of the concerts. Application regulations can be consulted and unloaded on the IC website or on the “Hush Full Music” page on Facebook. Selected candidates will be notified individually.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mishes maintains prohibition on importation of Japanese products despite change from China</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-mantem-proibicao-de-importacao-de-produtos-japoneses-apesar-de-mudanca-da-china/</link><description>Macao continues to ban the importation of Japan food products, although China's general administration has announced the conditional resuming the importation of water products from some regions of Japan, except 10 municipalities, including Fukushima. According to the Institute for Municipal Affairs (AMIs), the importation of fresh and living food products, of animals, salt and seaweed, vegetables, fruits, milk and dairy products, water and derivatives, poultry eggs, etc., from 10 municipalities (Fukushima, Chiba, Tchigi, Ibaraki, Gunma, Gunma, Gunma Miyagi, Niigata, Nagano, Saitama and Tokyo Metropolis) due to the need to “ensure food safety and citizens' health”. The ban began in August 2023 and since then AMI and Customs have been inspecting to prevent the entry of these products in the territory. In addition, food samples are collected at various retail venues. Until June 22, at the level of import and sale in the market, tests with portable radiation detector have already been performed at about 193,000 samples, and about 3,700 was collected for radionuclide tests, "without any anomaly." In turn, the Hong Kong government said it will “act prudence”, since “the duration and scale” of Fukushima Central eviction “are unprecedented”, and asked the Japanese authorities more “scientific evidence” to “evaluate if there are conditions to relax” restrictions. Japan began in 2023 progressively releasing the Pacific Ocean the wastewater treated from Fukushima in an operation that was approved by the International Atomic Energy Agency, but raised strong criticism from Beijing. According to the General Administration of China Customs, the samples collected under the long -term monitoring of the contaminated water in Fukushima “did not reveal anomalies”, so they decided to resume I imports from seafood. Japan described the decision as "positive". "The Japanese government continues to work with China to remove the other import controls," said Japanese government deputy spokesman Kazhiko Aoki.</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Teachers' arrests for sharing pictures from under the skirts shock Japan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/detencoes-de-professores-por-partilharem-fotos-de-baixo-das-saias-chocam-japao/</link><description>Japan's Minister of Education reacted with outrage on Friday, after the arrest of two teachers who allegedly shared photographs showing girls' interior clothing in a chat group that allegedly included almost 10 basic and secondary school teachers.
The case shocked the country. If they are convicted, the teachers-a 42-year-old and one 37-could face up to three years in prison or a fine of up to three million yen (almost 170,000 patacas), a police spokesman said to AFP, explaining that they were detained separately last week for taking photographs in which girls' underpants were visible and send them to the chat group. Men allegedly knew that girls “were under 13,” said the spokesman, adding that the detainees admitted the accusations.
Police sources said they believed that the group, led by the 42 -year -old teacher, had “almost 10” teachers, including the two detainees, according to NHK.
About 70 photographs and videos were shared in the group, including those apparently taken at school or in extracurricular activities, with some showing girls changing clothes.
"I'm really angry. This can never be tolerated," Education Minister Toshiko Abe told journalists.
The ministry plans to hold an online meeting with local education councils to avoid similar incidents.
The central school of Nagoya, where one of the teachers worked, held a meeting with more than 270 parents concerned, said NHK.
"It's scary and chilling," one mother told her 30 -year -old. "I would like to know if my daughter was one of the victims," ​​he added. For now, the school suspended physical education classes.
The mayor of Nagoya, Ichiro Hirosawa, classified the alleged crimes of "unthinkable". "They created a national group and were sharing the images ... I apologize and at the same time, I'm full of anger," he said.
Japan is preparing to launch its own version of the British Disclosure and Exclusion Service (DBS) next year to protect children from sexual assault. The DBS system will require those looking for jobs involving working with children to be subjected to verification of background for sexual crimes.
Little by little more data are known. The two suspects are 42 -year -old Yuji Moriyama, a teacher at Kosaka Primary School in the Tenpaku neighborhood, Nagoya; and Fumiya Kosemura, 37, a teacher at Hongodai Primary School in the Totsuka neighborhood of Yokohama.
Police said Moriyama took photographs to a student in underwear at an institution in Aichi province around September 2024, and Kosemura did the same at a institution in Kanagawa province in January 2025. They will then have shared indecent photos with members of an online chat group.
Moriyama is the administrator of the chat group and, according to police, had about 70 photos and videos of girls changing clothes and images inside their skirts.
Aichi police are investigating the case under the presumption that the chat group is composed of teachers whose hobby is photographic and video voicurism.
The criminal acts were detected in March 2025, when another teacher was arrested on suspicion of placing body fluid in a backpack that a girl held on the platform of a Nagoya train station. Through the investigation of the man, who was arrested on suspicion of property destruction, Aichi police discovered the existence of the online chat group and was investigating it.
It was found that nearly 10 people in the group had shared indecent photographs and videos, according to sources of the investigation.
Aichi police analyzed the content published in the Chat group and concluded that all members could be teachers. Authorities are checking how the group was formed.
According to sources, analyzes made by the province police to the confiscated smartphones revealed that the group members shared their impressions of the photographs and videos they published. One answer said "this is so good," while another said "I can't stop looking at them."
The publications were made with fictitious names, and other details, such as the names of the schools, were not disclosed. But there were posts like "the closing ceremony is today" and "It's tomorrow at my school."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-01 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>