<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Coutinho says that "maintaining a place" in the hemiciclo would already be "very good"</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/coutinho-diz-manter-um-lugar-hemiciclo-ja-seria-muito-bom/</link><description>By this time, it is still uncertain what will be the strategy of the new hope in the elections for the Legislative Assembly. José Pereira Coutinho referred the decision on the names to join the list to the ATFPM management, when asked if theist head will keep or can be Rita Santos. The deputy said he was also “reticent” about the conquest of two seats, pointing out that maintaining a place would be “very good”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
Getting a seat at the Legislative Assembly (AL) in the next elections would already be “an excellent result” for the New Hope list, says José Pereira Coutinho, who said yesterday that he is still open who could head the list. "[The place will be] for whom the Directorate of the Association of Public Function Workers (ATFPM) decides," he said, when asked whether to be for his own or Rita Santos, that he twice suspended his mandate as counselor of Portuguese communities, justifying the decision with the realization of the elections.
The deputy proved to be “quite reticent” as to the results of the elections, pointing out, without specifying, that “there is already movements in society in terms of offerings, tours, gifts”. "I already have some experience, in election time everything changes overnight and I must say, frankly and honestly, that keeping a place on the new hope list is already very good," he said, adding that it would be "important" have in the hemiciclo “a voice that dominates the Portuguese language and the Chinese language”.
As for Rita Santos, she noted that "she is a public figure, a person capable of performing any public office, both in public administration and in the Assembly." "It is committed, it is a good picture, valid," said the deputy, reiterating that "it will all depend on what the direction of ATFPM understands" and even the opinions of the Portuguese communities counselors.
It is recalled that in 1996, Rita Santos was a candidate for deputy of AL, having failed to enter the hemiciclo. In October last year, it temporarily suspended the mandate as an advisor to the Portuguese communities of the Circle of China, justifying the decision with the preparation of the election of the Chief Executive and with the participation in the elections for AL in 2025. Already in January this year, He extended the suspension for another 60 days.
Pereira Coutinho, in AL since 2005, recalled that he is already fulfilling the fifth term, being "one of the deputies with the most seniority". "We need to sacrifice ourselves, it is not easy to be elected deputy by the way," he said. "Having an examination of conscience in the last five years, I have fulfilled the role it should fulfill, serve the population, serve the Portuguese community, I am at this moment the only one that is expressed in Portuguese," he defended.
Claiming to be “confident” of the work and commitment they are dedicating to the preparation of the elections, he stressed: “We need the support of the entire population of Macao, especially the Portuguese community”. In the last elections, the New Hope got two seats.
As for Marcelo Rebelo de Sousa's visit to Macau to mark June 10, the deputy said that “it is pleasant news”, pointing out that the Portuguese school will be a subject to be on the table, since it worries the Portuguese community .
 
Policies to “revive” the economy of the
On the other hand, he said he noted "a notorious difference in the executive's attitude" regarding the period of elections for the position, "when it was much easier to have access to him." "Now it's becoming increasingly difficult," he said, although he says "the most important thing is that there is work and implementation of policies that can solve problems."
He said, he has "high expectations" about the lines of government action, hoping that there may be policies to "revive Macao's economy." “Macao's economy is not in good health. It takes measures that can increase jobs, ”he said. "There are many unemployed people, inflation is firing, the inflation rate does not correspond to reality and it is increasingly difficult to find a job," he said.
In addition, he said, "we have a big problem with satellite casinos that has to be solved because, otherwise, if they are extinguished, it involves tens of thousands of jobs." The only solution, he argued, "is to extend the deadline for another three years to try to find long -term solutions."</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Kou Hoi in anticipating “even more intense” works in the</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/kou-hoi-anteve-trabalhos-ainda-mais-intensos-na-al/</link><description>In what is the last legislative session of the current legislature, Kou Hoi In anticipates that the works of the hemiciclo are “even more intense”, also because the sixth mandate of the government begins and will be presented the lines of government action. The president of AL assured that the agency will "optimize" the mechanism of legislative production. On the other hand, he said that the review of several laws related to national security gives “guarantees of a disciplinary framework applicable to the next elections” of AL, which are held this year
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The President of the Legislative Assembly (AL) foresees that the work of the “in the near future” agency is “even more intense”, since this year is the last legislative session of the current legislature, and the sixth mandate of the government begins . At the spring lunch offered by Al to the media, Kou Hoi In also took a balance of the work so far done.
Regarding legislative initiatives, he said that they were already approved by the plenary, being appreciated in the specialty in the three permanent commissions, nine proposals of law and a project of resolution. "On the other hand, the presentation of the first report of the government lines by the new government will also be presented, followed by the debate," he recalled.
In this sense, it has ensured that the hemiciclo will make “all efforts to be completed before the legislative session.” Kou Hoi In also stressed that the legislative body “will continue to work for the welfare of the population, to vigorously promote the glorious tradition of love for the homeland and Macau, and to accurately adhere to the new mission and the new tasks attributed to Macao on the new journey of the new age of the country. ” "We will perform the functions entrusted to us, working together in improving diverse legislation, promoting the reform of public administration and optimizing the legislative production mechanism, in coordination with the government," he added.
For the future, he has ensured that Hemiciclo will “persist, as always, in the beginning of 'a country' and enhance the advantages of 'two systems', ensuring stable and lasting implementation of the 'country, two systems' principle in Macao, and raising the level and effectiveness of the governance of MSAR by the exercise of supervisory competence ”. In concrete, he stated that the commitment will be evidenced in the “improvement of the construction of the institutional system” and the promotion of the “high quality development of the works” of AL, “seeking to progress in a stable way”.
“We are going to work towards a new mandate leap in the conquest of new development milestones in all its enterprises, thus contributing to the successful practice of the 'a country, two systems' with Macao characteristics to be projected to a new level, ”said Kou Hoi In.
According to this legislature, "2024 was the year when the AL had the most overwhelmed agenda." Nevertheless, he pointed out Kou Hoi In, “all deputies, sharing an active and pragmatic attitude in the performance of their functions, have fulfilled their attributions under the law, with a high sense of mission and responsibility”, in cooperation with the government. In your opinion, this has allowed improvements in the “efficiency” and “effectiveness” of the hemiciclo, “ensuring that all works are developed and completed in a solid, orderly and stable way”.
With regard to national security, said Kou Hoi In, "we have always taken the defense of national sovereignty, and the safety and interests of state development as guiding principles of legislative work developed by the hemiciclo." In this field, and to “better” implement “Macau governed by Patriots”, recalled that Al concluded, in 2023, the review of the electoral law for the Chief Executive and, in 2024, of the Electoral Law to the AL and the Law of Oaths on the occasion of the act of inauguration.
“The approval of these three legislative initiatives was essential, to ensure, on the one hand, that the election of the sixth chief executive had been successfully completed under the law in 2024, offering, on the other, the guarantees of applicable disciplinary framework To the next 8th al elections, to take place this year, ”he said.
Kou Hoi In also mentioned President Xi Jinping's “important speeches” on the occasion of the anniversary of the masters.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Defended 90 days of maternity leave</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/defendidos-90-dias-de-licenca-de-maternidade/</link><description>Wong Kit Cheng considers that one of the most important incentives to foster birth would be to extend the maternity leave to 90 days, with the government to finance the additional 20 days
 
In view of the low birth rate, Deputy Wong Kit Cheng expects the government to adopt, through administrative regulation, the increase in maternity leave from 70 to 90 days to all Macao women. At the same time, it suggests a subsidy plan for the compensation paid in the maternity leave, and the value of this support is equivalent to 20 days of the maturity of the workers.
Note that, for the implementation of 90 days of maternity leave, it is necessary to review the Law of Labor Relations, Wong noted that no mechanism has not yet been activated, although “the possibility of the matter being addressed in the future by the Permanent Council of Social Concertation ”.
In this regard, the deputy understands that “a measure of provisional benefit”, through an administrative regulation, would be more viable to motivate companies to launch that “friend” measure of the family. In their opinion, the authorities will be financially capable of encouraging birth in this way.
“I hope that, in the coming lines of government action (LAG), birth incentive policies will be separated from any laws, being regarded as beneficial measures for the population. In addition, in monetary terms, the increase in birth allowance and the launch of a subsidy for child care would also contribute to relieve the financial pressure of families after the birth of babies. In the long run, improving child and child care services can also make Macau environment more favorable to children's growth, ”he suggested.
"If the government does not grant subsidies under maternity, paternity, company to sick family and child care, companies will remain hesitant," he said.
On the other hand, Wong proposed a new housing policy that allows families with newborns to replace their fractions with larger ones.
Still on LAG, the subdirector of the Association of Women has exhorted the government to reinforce measures to support the population, so that "residents can effectively enjoy the fruits of economic diversification." In addition to expecting “more concrete economic measures that also serve to solve resident employment and entrepreneurship problems,” the deputy wants to see mirrored in the LAG the “interaction” of mashes with the development of hengqin.
In addition, Wong warned of increasing requests for help to the Women's Association Psychotherapy Center. Therefore, it considers that resources in the area of ​​mental health should be reinforced, as well as support to institutions that provide psychological counseling services in the community and the number of vacancies for consultations in the psychotherapy centers, among other measures.
Wong also indicated that his team expects to "keep up" in the Legislative Assembly after this year's elections, so that "there are more deputies who speak to children and their families." Stressing that the defense of the rights and interests of women and children is a “priority work” of deputies linked to the Women's Association, the desire to see more deputies in the greater participation of young people and women in politics.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Buses in breaking in the evaluation of passengers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autocarros-em-quebra-na-avaliacao-dos-passageiros/</link><description>The numbers of the latest assessment of passenger satisfaction in Macau's public bus service show that users are less satisfied. In statistics released by services for traffic issues, regarding the service offered directly by the companies, TCM remains at the head of Transmac
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The results of the assessment of bus services in the first half of 2024 reveal that passengers felt less satisfied compared to previous periods. According to data from the Directorate of Traffic Services (DSAT), 27 points were assigned, from a total of 40, a break from the first half of 2023 (28.8 points) and the second semester of the same year (28.1 points ). According to official data, as long as the score is made at the base of a total of 40 points, this was the lowest assessment.
Regarding the degree of passenger satisfaction regarding bus companies, the numbers maintain the indications provided at the end of the same period last year, ie, TCM got a better score, having received 27.4 points, against 26, 3 of Transmac. The TCM score is, however, lower than that that was reached in the second half of 2023, when the values ​​reached 28.3.
In the data now provided by DSAT, TCM has maintained the hegemony of satisfaction for several years, specifically since the second half of 2020, after the period before Transmac has obtained, a favorable score of a few tenths above its rival.
Despite the positive numbers now revealed and regarding the second half of 2024, the TCM this time received the lowest grade of the last six reviews.
Transmac has progressively descended from quotation in the opinion of people who use buses and this second semester assessment of 2024 is the worst of its last five semiannual reviews.
On the other hand, DSAT has attributed the C+ level to the performance of Transmac, as has been the case since the first half of 2021. The values ​​mean that, if there is a scale stipulated from 0 to 100 points, Transmac would obtain a score between 77 and 80.
The TCM received B-, that is, between 80 and 83 points, worsening its installment, since in previous statistics, first and second semesters of 2023, had been quoted with C+. It should be noted that between 2015 and 2020 the maximum score was 10 and from 2021 became 40.
Other data provided by DSAT include improvement measures by bus operators. Concretely regarding the repetition of security problems or services, such as breach of safety or driving rules, as well as accidents, there is a possibility for drivers involved to be “persuaded” to dismiss or be dismissed.
The 2024 data show that 25 bus drivers were “persuaded” to fire, while 30 said goodbye to a total of 55 drivers. The number is equivalent to a climb compared to 2023, since this year only 32 were under these circumstances.
It is recalled that pursuant to the new bus agreement, which entered into force on 1 January 2021, the service evaluation regime indicators were adjusted for service and management indicator (30%), transportation means and equipment and security (30%) and passenger satisfaction (40%).</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public libraries record high use rates</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/bibliotecas-publicas-registam-elevadas-taxas-de-utilizacao/</link><description>An inquiry into the Macao Public Library shows that 80% of respondents are satisfied with the global services provided. The study, commissioned by the Cultural Institute to the Polytechnic University, also revealed that 73% of respondents said they had used public library services, which means a relatively high use rate. In terms of electronic reading, about 70% have this habit
 
Victor Rebelo
 
Residents in general, students, parents and children, and non -resident workers answered 1,200 questionnaires about the Macao Public Library. The results obtained in this study commissioned by the Cultural Institute (IC) from Macau Polytechnic University (UPM) show that the average score of the degree of satisfaction attributed by respondents was almost four points, on a scale up to five, and about 80% are satisfied or very pleased with the services provided by public libraries.
The positive responses of the participants in the inquiry were directed at the time of service, the distribution sites, attitude and efficiency of the service, among others.
In addition, the surveys of the survey reveal that 73% of respondents said they had used public library services, which means a relatively high use rate.
In terms of electronic reading, about 70% expressed that they have a habit of reading electronic books or other electronic resources. These data reflect that reading through electronic means is becoming increasingly popular in Macao.
The results of the inquiry conducted by the UPM, in which 1,006 valid questionnaires were obtained, showed that resident reading interests are mainly leisure and relaxation, as well as obtaining information. Almost 80% read books last year, with the annual volume and time spent on reading it was at an average level.
These data illustrate a relatively high rate of participation in the reading of Macao residents, constituting a good basis for the promotion of the construction of Macau as a “reading city”, considers the IC. On the other hand, the people who participated in the investigation generally recognized the important role of public libraries in promoting reading culture.
According to the IC, public libraries will in the future "optimize their development around diversification and digitization." Given the results of the inquiry, the body will continue to reinforce the promotion of the concept of the “reading city”, “increasing the public awareness and participation in reading and developing a promotional strategy that differentiates various groups, such as local residents, workers not residents, and students. ”
At the same time, the IC ensures libraries will enrich the resources of the collection, especially electronic books and electronic resources, improving digital services for public convenience and optimizing the experience of using library resources through the combination of technology and innovation .
“Diversified and international reading activities will be performed, facilitating cultural exchange and cooperation, creating an inclusive reading environment and promoting the transformation of Macau into an“ influential reading ”, reinforces the body.
The final report of the inquiry is published on the Electronic Page of the Public Library of Macao do IC, and can be consulted and discharged by residents.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Santa Casa provider proposed birth subsidy of 30 thousand patacas</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/provedor-da-santa-casa-propos-subsidio-de-nascimento-de-30-mil-patacas/</link><description>In a meeting with the secretary for social affairs and culture, the provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia proposed several measures related to birth and population aging. One of them was the increase in the birth allowance of current 5,418 Patacas, a value that considers “derisory” to 30,000 patacas. As for aging, he gave the idea of ​​turning the lower floors of the residence into an elderly
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The provider of the Santa Casa da Misericórdia proposed a series of births and aging measures to the secretary for social and culture affairs, Lam. Increased birth allowance, free day care and use of residence for the elderly to create a home were the ideas transmitted By António José de Freitas, who expressed concern with the phenomena of the low birth rate and the aging of the population in an interview with the Jornal Tribuna de Macau.
“I proposed that the Macao government should increase monetary support to encourage the birth rate. In Hong Kong there are 20 thousand for every child born and it is good not to forget that there are over seven million inhabitants. Macao doesn't even have 10%. Macao gives 5,418 patacas, which is derisory. Last year, only 3,000 children were born, ”noted António José de Freitas.
In this sense, in a meeting with LAM, where members of the social sector of the Electoral Commission of the Chief Executive were present, the Holy House provider made a proposal in this context: “I suggested the secretary that the value, at least, should be 30 thousand Patacas. Every 1,000 children who are born only represent 30 million patacas. ” "It's nothing," he said, pointing to the revenues of 6,300 million from MSAR.
In the same field, he noted that “it is a luck for children” to be 15 years of free education in the territory, “something that does not happen everywhere”, however, argues that it takes more. “The government should also exempt children who need preschool, that is, the day care. Because whether families have money or not, they have to pay a monthly fee, ”he said.
As for the reaction of the secretary, António José de Freitas said it was “good”: “I think that, by her reaction, this will move forward. The birth subsidy will not be 5,000 Patacas for sure, ”he said in a preview of the government lines.
With the low birth rate in the territory, day care centers are already impacting. With two day care centers -one in Nape, subsidized by the government, and another on Avenida da República, the Lara Reis day care center -the Santa Casa was also affected, with these two spaces accounted for “losses” last year, due to decreased number of babies.
The oldest daycare in Nape has a capacity of 258 children, currently counting less than 200. “And according to the numbers of the Social Action Institute, our day care is one of the highest occupancy rate. There were day care centers that had to close rooms, ”said the provider. The Lara Reis day care center, with space for 70 children, welcomes, at the moment, 24. "All this is derived from the low birth rate," he noted.
Recently, the Deputy Director of Health Services (SSM), Kuok Cheong U, predicted that the MSAR should register less than 3,500 births in 2025, a number that would be the lowest since 2004. After visiting the first babies born in the lunar year of the serpent, He said he hopes that the birth rate "continues to fall" and added that "it will be good" if the number of births reaches 3,500.
If Kuok's forecast is accurate, this will be the least fertile year since 2004, when Macau registered 3,308 births. According to official data, 3,712 births were 43.5% than 10 years (6,571) and out of a maximum of 7,913 set in 1988, which was a lunar year of the dragon.
 
Residence for the elderly must host home
On the other hand, the tendency of aging of the population that will only be aggravated in the coming years also worries António José de Freitas. For this reason, it was also one of the topics he addressed with the secretary for social affairs and culture. The provider took official data from the Institute of Social Action, according to which 1,800 people were waiting to enter the homes of the elderly.
As this newspaper reported in January, there were only about five hundred hundred homes in elderly homes, and the waiting list was quite extensive. Vago places did not even cover a third of the people who were waiting to enter these spaces, which totaled about 1,800.
“I said 1,800 are many beds. Doing the math, a home with a capacity of 100 beds is already a very good home, has to have some space. We need 18 homes to be able to satisfy these requests. This is now, but in some time it will be worse, because the aging of the population gradually worsens, ”he said.
Stating that there is always talk of the home that is being built in zone A of the new landfills, the provider argued that it cannot be expected. “Why not enjoy the residence for the elderly, whose occupancy rate is too low? This has 37 floors, each floor has nine autonomous fractions… ”, he continued, saying that the idea would be to“ enjoy the lower floors ”.
In your opinion, taking advantage of that space to create a home would be "a perfect idea," because "when they enter the residence for the elderly, people have no guarantee about the future." According to the rules, people who can live in those fractions have to be independent. “The elderly who enter now have total independence, but in 10 or 15 years from now they are dependent, it is the law of nature. And then? They have to go back to the place of origin and have no guarantee of taking place in the elderly homes, ”he lamented.
Thus, the idea would be that, after being dependent, these seniors will pay, instead of the income of the residence for the elderly, the tuition of the home - which would be on the lower floors of that building. "It is a quick, effective solution and we enjoy the space that is already created," he said.
Home of Misericórdias, of Santa Casa, has 129 beds, currently welcoming 95 elderly. The space never fills because the third floor is dedicated to independent people, and 98% of the elderly who are admitted are bedridden and dependent.
Asked if it believes that in the lines of government action will be announced measures in this context, António José de Freitas said that there will be "a major revision regarding the distribution of benefits to the needy people." "And I think the consumer card will be an announced thing," he added.
 
Santa Casa with positive balance of 34.5 million
The Santa Casa da Misericórdia de Macao ended 2024 with a positive balance of 34.5 million patacas, “thanks to rigorous management,” said the provider, António José de Freitas, to the Jornal Tribuna de Macau, indicating that Last year, all tenants of commercial spaces again paid the incomes, after several years of pandemic in which the amounts were cut, resulting from the economic situation that lived. The revenues “collected” by the Brotherhood ascended 102 million Patacas, a 6% increase in 2023. Most of the lace earnings of stores (42% of the total), in a value of 43.7 million; Following the subsidies of the Institute of Social Action and Health Services, of 17.6 million (17.4%), and interest on time deposits and the Order was worth 17.6 million (17.2%). As for the expenses, they totaled 67.6 million, and the spending on the staff were the ones who had the most “weight”, a total of 50 million patacas. Asked if this year there will be an increase in salaries, António José de Freitas said that no now, but "probably next year." In 2023, Santa Casa rose the salaries of employees by 5%.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Real estate sector wants land auctions to invert crisis</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sector-imobiliario-quer-leiloes-de-terras-para-inverter-crise/</link><description>The president of the Macao Real Estate Entrepreneurs Association considers that the sector is living the “worst scenario in the last 40 years”, having recorded only an average of 3,000 transactions of housing fractions in the last three years. To inject vitality to the sector, Ung Choi Kun suggested, for example, that the government has been auctions of land to erect housing for exchange in urban renewal
 
The real estate sector of the territory is experiencing the “worst scenario in the last 40 years,” warned Ung Choi Kun, president of the Macao Real Estate Entrepreneurs Association, pointing out that, according to data from the Finance Services Directorate, 3,057 were registered. Transactions of housing fractions at MSAR last year. The average number of house transactions has reached only about 3,000 in the last three years, it has accentuated.
On the sidelines of the Spring Lunch organized by the Association, Ung Choi Kun also pointed to the constant increase in old buildings built over four decades in Macao. Given this context, he suggested to the authorities to advance with land auctions to build housing for exchange in urban renewal, in order to give more opportunities to the real estate sector.
According to the Chinese language press, the associative leader hopes to see various measures to counteract the crisis panorama, including the “deep integration” between the “1+4” industries and the real estate sector. In this respect, it has exemplified that the development of traditional Chinese medicine and Big Health requires modern industrial parks, laboratories and advanced equipment, as well as cold chain storage and logistics facilities. However, he warned that the current conditions of factories in Macao "can no longer meet the requirements for the development of modern industry."
In addition, Ung Choi Kun proposed to the government to take the initiative to erect a “complex with the nature of former libris”, encouraging the financial and banking sectors to support the participation of real estate industry in this project.
On the other hand, it stressed that small and medium -sized SME (SME) currently face “multiple challenges” related to capital, technical and market. Therefore, it expects a “high-tech industry incubation center to be built, which provides“ One-Stop ”SME services including offices, technical support and financing services. In your opinion, this solution will not only strengthen the competitiveness of SMEs, but will also foster more leases and investments for the real estate sector.
At the same time, Ung Choi Kun asked the authorities to launch “favorable and facilitating measures for the population” as a “one-stop” measure to open commercial establishments to stimulate internal demand and strengthen investor confidence .</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Dsal has recorded 1,333 minors to work in recent years</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dsal-registou-1-333-menores-trabalhar-nos-ultimos-anos/</link><description>Between 2022 and 2024, 667 cases of hiring of minors were reported, involving 1,333 minors, according to data from the Directorate of Services for Laboral Affairs. Most work on hotel and restoration sectors, as well as thick and retail trade. According to the body's director, Wong Chi Hong, 21 lawsuits were instructed in the same period
 
Between 2022 and 2024, the Directorate of Services for Labor Affairs (DSAL) was notified to 667 cases of hiring minors, involving 1,333 minors. The information was advanced by the director of the body, Wong Chi Hong, in response to an interpellation of Deputy Lei Chan U.
Employers were mainly dedicated to “hotel and restoration” and “thick trade and retail”, while smaller workers in question was mainly “table employee” and “retail sales employee,” said Wong Chi Hong.
In the same period, 21 processes related to minors were instructed. According to the director of the government organism, they were "mainly related to the violation of minor admission requirements and the disqualification of employers' duty to communicate." The DSSA proceeded, in accordance with the law, “the monitoring of the offenses committed”, and Wong Chi Hong advanced details.
According to the Labor Relations Law, the minor who works must have completed the minimum age of admission, to have the physical and psychic capabilities appropriate to perform the functions to be performed, proven by written medical certificate, as well as the written authorization of their legal representatives.
In addition, the employer must communicate the hiring of the minor to DSAL within 15 days of the conclusion of the contract, and the copy of the contract, the medical certificate and the written authorization of its legal representatives, except in the situation of Hiring to work during the summer school holidays.
The director of DSAL also recalls that, in the current law, special guarantees related to the minor worker are plasma, and for example there are “prohibited and conditioned works”. In addition, there are also requirements regarding health protection, among others.
To increase public knowledge about the labor rights and interests of minors, DSAL has been conducting disclosure actions in various formats, as well as conducting exclusive clarification sessions in schools. Surveillance actions and special inspection actions are also carried out during summer school holidays.
“Dsal will, in articulation with the needs of socioeconomic development, continue with the attention given to the situation of law enforcement, as well as to continue to hear from the various quadrants of society the opinions and suggestions regarding a more adequate protection of rights and interests Workers, ”said Wong Chi Hong.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Game in the phase of “stabilization”</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/jogo-em-fase-de-estabilizacao/</link><description>Casinos' results after Chinese New Year holidays were “better” than they were feared, when they hit an average of 725 million patacas, according to the investment bank JP Morgan
 
Gross Macao game revenues totaled about 7.4 billion patacas in the first nine days of this month, which is equivalent to a daily average of 822 million, the JP Morgan investment bank said, stressing that “solid” demand At the end of this period it helped compensate for the “weakness” of the results achieved on Chinese New Year holidays. The recipes “stabilized after the Lunar New Year,” said DS Kim, Mufan Shi and Selina Li analysts.
Between February 1 and 5, the casinos raised 900 million patacas a day, but were a little short of the expectations of analysts and investors.
After the golden week, which took place between January 28 and February 4, the billing has been “better than it was”, translating an average of 725 million patacas, JP Morgan experts revealed. In general, monthly performance “remains within expectations, although it is at the lower end”, they noted, noticing that the daily average until February 9 is in line with its previous predictions (between 800 million and 850 million patacas) .
In estimates for the general taxpayer, the trio of analysts opt for caution, pointing to a wide margin, between 18.3 billion and 19.4 billion of patacas. In annual terms, this interval oscillates between a 1% break and a 5% increase.
As the first two months of 2025 may reflect an annual decrease of 2% or a growth of 2%. “This implies that gross game revenues in 2025 can grow only in a low digit, about +1% to +4% in annual terms,” says the report, stiving that the “consensus” of initial projections perspective an increase in about 5% compared to 2024.
This week, Citigroup has already reduced its forecast on the growth of macao casinos revenues in 2025, now anticipating an annual rise of 3%compared to the previous projection of 7%.
According to the Game Inspection and Coordination Directorate, the game's revenues were on 18.25 billion Patacas in January, translating an annual break of 5.6% and equivalent to 73.2% of the same month of 2019. On the other hand, 0.3% grew in monthly terms.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sporting “repsched” remains in the Elite League</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/sporting-repescado-mantem-se-na-liga-de-elite/</link><description>The new season of the 1st Macao Football Division starts on the 19th and will rely on Sporting's participation. Leonine formation ended the past season in the penultimate place, so it was unpromped, but it turned out to be “repaired” due to the withdrawal of Mount Carlo. The decision was made by the soccer association, which thus confirmed the presence of the “white green” in the draw that takes place today. The associative leaders also revealed that women's football will have a championship of the eleven variant
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The 2025 season of the Macau Football League will start on February 19, with the first rounds to be held on the pitch of the Canidromo Campo. The race will feature 10 teams, as last season and in the same system, that is, a single turn of “all-Contra”, followed by two with the first five classifieds to play the title and the remaining to fight for maintenance in the main level.
This year's race will not have Monte Carlo, as the Jornal Tribuna de Macao had already advanced, which represents a loss of enormous meaning, as it is a historic club in the territory. To fill the vacancy left open by the “blue and yellow” club, the Macao Football Association (AFM) decided to “reply” Sporting, which finished the 2024 elite league in the penultimate position, ahead of Ka I. Decision arose following the same policy used in similar cases, according to this newspaper the secretary general of AFM told.
"When these situations happen, we have always given priority to the teams that would come down, thus providing them with permanence, which I think it makes perfect sense," said Chan Keng Hou during the traditional Spring Lunch, in which AFM gathers with the media and promotes the program for another time of football.
The leader reported that the elite league draw will take place today in the late afternoon, knowing the departure of the matches for the first hours of the competition, which will take place, not on the lawn of the Taipa stadium, as it would be desired of the clubs and intention of AFM, but in the field of the canhy.
 
Unavailable stadium “takes” games to the canidrome
Chan Keng has regrets that the floor of the Taipa Stadium is not at this time in condition, requiring some time so that there can be held back games of the championship. "We don't have great alternatives, so the Canidromo field is again our only option at this time," he said, hoping that "within perhaps a month or two the Taipa stadium can already host the elite league challenges." .
In addition to the absence of Mount Carlo in the Elite League, because it does not intend to continue the senior football project, the descent of the II Ka I division, another prestigious club at the local level, also stands out. Ka I and Monte Carlo have titles won throughout their history and have already been part of their plants of good quality players, not only from Macau but abroad, with emphasis on Brazilian professionals.
Unlike previous years, in which two teams were unpromped, this time only Ka I descends from division. In the opposite direction, the League of Elite is the champion of the 2nd Division of 2024, Shao Jiang, who promises to bet on "high flights" after the superiority manifested in the last year's race, and Ivo Chiba, a club that is given great importance to the development of young players.
In this sense, the elite league that is about to start generates some expectation, trying to compensate for the important absences of Monte Carlo and Ka I.
 
Women's football will have proof in the eleven variant
AFM, which has been represented by virtually its entire staff, including the coaches of the selections, released the activities plan for 2025, where a Women's Football Championship of the 11 variant will be charged for the first time, when the race will until now the test It was held in the D. Bosco field with seven athletes.
“This is a strong bet we intend to make,” said Chan Keng Hou, for those who “have been time to give women's football the dimension that deserves through this world and to provide women to play 11 elements games on the field , which so far had not yet happened at a local level and did not allow them to develop that it is necessary to implement. ”
Macau has been organizing a championship for at least six teams for several years, but in the variant of five players on each side and the synthetic floor of the D. Bosco field. This has created difficulties when the Macao female selection moves to international competitions to carry out Asian findings.
“The progress of women's football can be much greater,” expresses the leader. About the Women's Championship system, Chan Keng Hou has not given details, because "we are still discussing the best model."
"We will probably have to reduce the number of participating teams, as there are not so many athletes available, but the intention is to make a league with several laps so that they can compete as much as possible," he says.
According to the planning of AFM, the female football team will be able to hold friendly meetings in April, May, July, October and November, which will confirm will give the team a greater competitiveness.
 
Higher training frequency for the main selection
The year of Macao football will also bring a project of “greater intensity” regarding the frequency of the work of the selections, especially in the main formation. For this, AFM has a plan already stipulated by the new Kenneth Kwok coach, which points to more training periods.
The coach, born in Hong Kong, who has been responsible for some teams from the 1st neighboring territory and directed Raehk's main selection at the Jakarta Asian Games in 2018, told the Tribuna de Macao newspaper that “young players in the territory They have a lot of potential. ” "And that is what I intend to enjoy, giving them the possibility of training in the field, but also in theoretical sessions outside the lawn," he said.
Kenneth Kwok considers it "indispensable" that the main selection of MSAR is progressively assimilating the arrival of young elements, so that "there is a renewal and Macao football can ensure higher quality."
The representative team of MSAR has scheduled some international challenges of preparation, about four or five throughout the year, but not yet established or chosen opponents.
For the month of March, the first friendly challenge of the year is planned, but it will have to be out of Macao, as the Taipa stadium should not yet be in a position. “Later, yes, we will have our selection to receive some opponents in games included in the so -called FIFA window and scheduled for June, October and November,” said Chan Keng Hou.
However, in September, the under-23 Macao selection will participate in the Asia Championship qualification phase of the category. The respective draw will be held in June, so the adversaries are not yet known, knowing that, in principle, they will leave the geographical zone of East Asia and ranking similar to the MSAR.
Another aspect that the association intends to develop is the arbitration area. The president of the AFM Board said yesterday that a campaign was launched in schools and along with young people with soccer, so that there is an interest in attending referee courses. Thus, after the first attempt, AFM has already had the registration of nine students for arbitration sessions that will begin soon.
Lao Pak Leng also emphasized other courses, such as coaches, following the plan presented by the Kenneth Kwok coach, which aims for greater contact and joint learning, through various local stages with technicians not only of the selections, but also with those of the teams of the Elite League.
 
Disciplinary punishment Stephen Chow can be “some games”
The Disciplinary Commission of the Macao Football Association (AFM) has not yet made any decision regarding the punishment that should be applied to Stephen Chow, former President of Must CPK, following aggressions recorded at the end of a sub-sub-championship challenge 16. According to Chan Keng Hou, AFM Secretary-General, "the process is underway and has been longer because there have been many incidents and aggressions after the challenge is over." However, "as the images released on video are not fully enlightening whether or not there was aggression from the then CPK responsible, as stated in the police report, the punishment is likely to be summed up to some suspension games," said the manager. It is known, however, that the parents of Benfica's 15-year-old, apparently assaulted by Stephen Chow, did not file a complaint to the authorities. The former CPK president has already been replaced in office.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Green Island residents deliver petition to the Chief Executive</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/moradores-da-ilha-verde-entregam-peticao-ao-chefe-executivo/</link><description>In order to request the government changes to the new planning plan of the Green Island and the improvement of fire prevention measures, a group of residents of that city zone yesterday submitted a petition to the Chief Executive.
 
At the government headquarters, a group of residents of Verde Island yesterday handed a petition to the chief executive. In the document, they ask for changes to the new planning plan of Ilha Verde and the improvement of fire protection measures in that area of ​​the territory.
Regarding the new urban planning plan, residents began to regret that, although the government has underlined the importance of safeguarding the Green Island Hill and the maintenance and restoration of the convent, “there was no effective advance ”In this regard.
Fiting the planning of the green island as “challenging”, the petitioners appealed to the executive to create an exclusive interdepportional group to properly treat procedures for the expropriation of the Green Island Hill and the respective compensation. They argue in particular that the "real realization of the planning plan" will only be possible "if land throughout the hill are actually controlled by the government."
On the other hand, the plan expects to download the maximum height ceilings of the buildings in the lots influenced by the view of the visual corridor on the south side of the hill. According to the group of residents, the new top limit of height will affect the Fok Tak San Chuen building where several five -floor blocks have no elevators.
In this sense, residents are concerned about the risk that the reconstructed buildings are unable to welcome elevators due to height restrictions, because they are not foreseen, in the planning plan, measures to lodge affected residents. In the petition, the government also installed the restrictions to the height of the constructions in the lots influenced by the visual corridor, to enable the construction of buildings equipped with elevators.
Regarding the issue of fire safety, according to the Chinese language press, a petitioner pointed to the recent occurrence of a fire in a shipyard on the new road of Ilha Verde, where “after the fire, no prevention measures have not yet been taken measures. fires ”.
As there are many obsolete vehicles parked on Verde Island, residents are afraid that inappropriate treatment of these vehicles causes fires. In addition, they warned of the number of old trees in the area due to the impact of termites and for landslide signs on the slopes of some roads. Therefore, the petitioners have asked the government to optimize fire prevention measures, so that the safety of old and residents is better protected.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>CTT resumed sending orders to the US</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ctt-retomaram-envio-de-encomendas-para-os-eua/</link><description>The post office of Macao and Hong Kong announced the recovery of small packages and orders to the US after five days of suspension. In a statement, Macao's Post Office and Telecommunications Directorate says that it is already accepting “all mail objects” for the US.
The CTT recalled that the suspension "may have originated a correspondence, which will possibly result in delays in the delivery of shipments to the US." "Additionally, the possibility of any changes in the Postal Services of the United States cannot be excluded at any time," they warned.
Hours earlier, Hong Kong's post office had said they were "formally notified" by the US Postal Service (USPS) that US authorities "currently do not impose additional fees on postal articles with goods."
On January 5, the company said it had been notified by USPS that it could only send packages or orders that customers had registered with customs and the protection of US borders (CBP). The registration would require “the necessary import documents and the payment of fees made through a customs dispatcher,” added the Hong Kong Post Office. After the suspension of shipping, the company "continued to negotiate" with USPS.
On the 4th, USPS announced that it would temporarily stop accepting orders from China and Hong Kong (without any reference to Macao) “until new order”. But hours later, USPS reversed the decision, without justifying, just stating that it was going to work with the CBP to implement a collection process for the new rates imposed on Chinese goods in order to avoid interruptions in delivery.
The new US president has increased customs rates on imports from China by 10%after retreating in plans to charge tariffs to Canada and Mexico. The vast majority of goods sent from China arrives outside the mail system, but Donald Trump's order has eliminated exemption for low value products, acquired directly by consumers and sent through postal service. This exemption encompassed articles of less than $ 800. The USPS measurement could block or delay orders made through Chinese Electronic Trade platforms Shein and Temu.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Housing credit suffers third consecutive break</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/credito-a-habitacao-sofre-terceira-quebra-consecutiva/</link><description>The value of new mortgage loans for housing approved by Macao banks was 1.01 billion patacas in December, marking a monthly decrease of 17.9%, although it risen 8.8% in annual terms, indicate monetary authority data (AMCM). In December, the loans granted to residents (1.18 billion) corresponded to 96.6% of the total.
This was the third consecutive monthly break in housing credit, after the 57% descents in October and 5.3% in November, which had contradicted the 142.1% increase between August and September.
Between October and December, the monthly average of new mortgage loans for housing reached 1.18 billion patacas, less 36.5% than in the previous period (September to November).
According to AMCM data, at the end of December, the debt ratio unpaid on housing credit, which involves delays over three months in interest and or capital payments, rose 0.1 points to 3.5% , compared to the previous month, and 2.7 percentage points compared to last year's same period.
Already the gross balance of mortgage loans for housing was located at 218.14 billion in late 2024, reflecting decreases of 0.5% and 4.9%, compared to the previous month and the same period of 2023, respectively. Of these loans, 96.6% were granted to residents.
For its part, the new commercial loans for real estate activities totaled 685.51 million patacas, an amount that translates a monthly decrease of 22.7% and an annual decline of 21.1%. Between October and December, the monthly average of these loans retreated 13.6% to 738.25 million, in relation to the previous three months.
In the credit segment for real estate activities, the unpaid debt ratio (5.3%) advanced 0.5 points in a month and 2.3 points within one year. The gross balance of commercial loans for real estate activities (149.92 billion) fell 0.7% compared to the previous month and 5.5% in the annual variation.</description><pubDate>2025-02-12 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>‘Kinda Pregnant’ is quite good</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/kinda-pregnant-e-bastante-bom-jake-coyle/</link><description>Jake Coyle*
We have already used how some movie characters are able to do to maintain a good comedy story. But it is still a special achievement when Amy Schumer, playing a single woman crazy about babies who fits a pregnant belly in "Kinda Pregnant", is so desperate for maintaining fiction that stuffs a roasted turkey in the dress.
It may be thinking: this is very ridiculous. The filling, alone. But if we appreciated the "Some Like It Hot" or "Mrs. Doubtfire ”, I see no reason to question the structure of“ Kinda Pregnant ”, a funny and often insightful satire about motherhood, both real and imaginary.
"Kinda Pregnant", which debuted last week on Netflix, is a kind of retro comedy. Like “40-Year-Old Virgin” and “Wedding Crashers”, one can basically understand the film only by the title.
But, like any good high concept comedy, "Kinda Pregnant" is predominantly a far-fetched form of its star and co-argumentist, Schumer, talk frankly about his theme of election. Here, this is the wide range of pregnancy experiences - body changes, sex revelation parties, personal jealousy - all mixed with a healthy amount of pseudo pregnancy falls.
It has been a decade since Schumer was essentially released as a 2015 film star in “Trainwreck” by Judd Apatow. But "Kinda Pregnant", which Schumer wrote with Julie Paiva, almost as skillfully channels Schumer's comic voice - the one that made Sketches series "Inside Amy Schumer" excellent.
The opening of the movie recalls Lainy (Schumer) in a child playing with dolls and imagining a future mother. As middle-aged, however, Lainy, a high school teacher in Brooklyn, is nowhere near to realize this dream. At dinner, where she suspects that her longtime boyfriend (Damon Wayans Jr.) will make the proposal, he invites her to a throes to Trois. Back at school, Lainy's class about “Romeo and Juliet” becomes darkly cynical.
Things get even worse when Lainy's best married friend (Jillian Bell) reveals that she is pregnant. "Get rid of him!" Lainy lets out before apologizing. Later, when the couple go shopping in clothes, Lainy tries a disorder in the belly. The saleswoman is immediately friendly to her, offering a burrito and a foot massage. "Who is the father?" she asks. "Doordesh," Lainy replies before adding, "driver."
Much of the fun in "Kinda Pregnant" is to see Lainy inventing increasingly ridiculous lies while trying to pretend to be pregnant. (After accidentally choosing thanksgiving as the moment of its conception, Lainy Cava has an even deeper hole in suggesting that it happened in a “selling Black Friday's eve”.)
But the stratagem becomes more difficult when she, during a pregnant gymnastics class, meets a woman (Brianne Howey) who really likes and wants to be a friend. Even more complicated: Lainy begins to fall in love with another boy she knows in a cafeteria (Forte Will).
In a movie full of funny people (others include Urzila Carlson as an educational advisor and Alex Moffat as future idiot father), strong is an especially good presence in "Kinda Pregnant". For an actor of such a crazy nonsense, strongly fits in a remarkably natural way in a more romantic comedy scenario. It also has a wonderfully ridiculous occupation, even to the standards of the romantic comedy, leading a Zamboni in the Central Park.
Probably from here, you can imagine what Kinda Pregnant ”will be like. The director Tyler Spindel, nephew of Adam Sandler (producer of the film), does nothing to promote film comedy, a proposal failed in recent years, except rare exceptions in the great screen. But he gives artists a lot of space to be themselves, and Lainy's desperate desire to have a family looks exaggerated and genuine. If "Knocked Up" captured the comedy of unexpectedly pregnant, "Kinda Pregnant" personifies the pain of wishing it.
 
*Coyle has been a film critic for the Associated Press since 2013. He has lived in New York City.</description><pubDate>2025-02-11 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>