<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Airport expansion requires more traffic controllers</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/expansao-aeroporto-requer-mais-controladores-de-trafego/</link><description>Integrating 28 licensed professionals, the team of air traffic controllers at MSA will be reinforced with four new elements, all young people, who are being trained and will be able to start working later this year, said the president of the Air Traffic Controllers Association to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao. Raymond Tam Tek Hong described that the team has been “very stable”, but needs more labor because of the expansion of the airport and also because in 2026, the minimum duration of annual training will triple to 12 hours
 
Macao currently has 28 licensed air traffic controllers. Almost all are residents, except a "Blue Card holder," said Raymond Tam Tek Hong, president of the Macao Air Traffic Controllers Association (Matca, in the English acronym), describing the team as "very stable".
Speaking to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao about the Human Resources situation point, the associative leader assured that "there is usually no problem." But he also noticed that the controllers face some pressure when Macau registers bad weather, such as the passage of tuffons. This is because, during the typhoons, it is not possible to change shifts, and the controllers usually have to rigorously follow the time defined by the civil aviation authority to finish their work and rest, and the maximum working time per day is not allowed.
Currently, 50% of air traffic controllers in Macau are men. "People have always been about two dozen," said Raymond Tam Tek Hong.
He said, after three decades of the association's creation, the controllers team will face an evolution due to the expansion of Macau International Airport, that is, there will be a reinforcement of the team.
“Currently, we have four new colleagues who are being formed, taking into account the need to develop the airport and landfill work, already ongoing to expand. During the landfill process, some changes in the airport and heaven. Therefore, we need to start preparing our staff two to three years before completion and we need some time for this reinforcement, so that they familiarize the operations on the site Airport, ”explained Raymond Tam Tek Hong.
The four graduates, all young men, began to receive training at the beginning of this year and will be subject to exams between September and October, so they could work from the end of the year.
The president of MATCA argued that the air traffic control team should integrate more personal, "also because they have increased the hours of annual training, and the duration of training will only increase in the future," he explained. He also added that shifts will be tighter when training, because in this case the professional will have to leave the job for a full day or several consecutive days.
Currently, air traffic controllers in the territory need to receive a total of four hours of formation per year. However, the minimum duration of the annual training required for this group of professionals next year was elevated by the authorities for 12 hours.
 
Emergency situations target training
According to Raymond Tam Tek Hong, the main content of the annual formation of controllers is to update the work requirements in relation to “land personnel” and the computational simulation of airport situations, including some emergency situations.
On the other hand, the associative leader revealed that, taking advantage of the 30th anniversary of the Association and the Airport, Matca will organize in Macao the 41st Regional Conference of Asia Pacific Association of Air Traffic Operators, between October 20 this year, with the participation of air traffic controllers, aviation specialists, industry leaders, among more 100 professionals, who will discuss the advancement of safety of the safety Aviation, operational efficiency and regional collaboration, under the theme: “Operations in all weather conditions in the aerodrome”.
Founded in 1995, Matca is a non -profit organization dedicated to the “promotion of professional excellence in air traffic management”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Sands profit fell again in the second quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/lucro-da-sands-voltou-cair-segundo-trimestre/</link><description>Sands China saw net profits fall 13% in the second quarter of this year to $ 214 million, after having already registered results considered “weak” earlier this year. In a scenario where the operator admits not to perform as good as expected in Macao, CEO of Las Vegas Sands recognized flaws and revealed that the group changed its strategy. Grant Chum, president of Sands China, explained that, since the end of April, they began to implement “a more aggressive client reinvestment program”, which has already started to bear fruit
 
Catarina Pereira
 
After a first trimester with “weak” results, Sands China profit fell again in the three months finished in June. In a context where the game operator has not had as "performance" as good as he would like -as he already admitted Robert Goldstein, CEO of the Las Vegas Sands (LVS) group -, the president of Sands China, Grant Chum, revealed, in the presentation of the results, that the group is already adopting a strategic change to recover lost ground.
Sands China ended the second quarter of 2025 with net profits of US $ 214 million (about 1.7 billion patacas), translating a break of 13% compared to the 246 million noted in the same period last year. In the period under analysis, the results before interest, taxes, amortization and depreciation (EBITDA) had a slight annual increase from 0.9% to $ 566 million.
“We performed below expectations in this market,” said Rob Goldstein. “We didn't approach enough customer reinvesting. We believed our enterprises would be enough [to attract more customers]. We were wrong. And so, throughout the quarter, we changed our approach to allow us to increase our market share and EBITDA (…)“ Now we've entered the wave. We are not leading the market - we are simply in the dispute now, and that's good, ”he added in a video conferencing about the group's results.
Grant Chum stated that "around April, we started implementing a more aggressive client reinvestment program." "We are seeing some encouraging initial results with these growing reinvestment levels. As we advanced to May and June, Sands China's performance has improved and we will continue to adjust to market conditions as needed," he said.
Data also reveals that Sands China net revenues were just below $ 1.80 billion, an increase of 2.5% in homologous terms.
Between April and June, the operator's casinos revenues in Macau were about 1.35 billion, when last year they had been 1.33 billion. However, only Londoner's casino revenues increased from the previous year to 495 million (+56%). In the remaining Sands China developments, casinos' revenues decreased from the previous year.
According to Chum, Sands China is also looking for opportunities to “improve performance” of Parisian and Sands. As for Londoner, the performance is different: "In general, the reception to The Londoner has been phenomenal. We are receiving exceptional feedback from customers."
The adjusted EBITDA of Parisian fell 47% in homologous terms to $ 44 million, while net revenue decreased 26.8% to 194 million. At Sands Macao, adjusted EBITDA suffered a decrease from 10% to 9 million, while net revenue fell 10.1% to $ 71 million.
Patrick Dumont, director of operations at Las Vegas Sands and future leader of the group, added: "We are not where we want to be in Macau. We feel we made a great investment, we have a great product and we believe we can increase Ebitda from here."
Despite the challenges in Macao, the LVS recorded a net result of $ 519 million in the second quarter, over 424 million from the previous year (+22.4%), while Ebitda grew 24.3% to 1.33 billion. The scenario was mainly due to Marina Bay Sands. Singapore operations saw net revenues rise 36.6%to 1.39 billion, with EBITDA adjusted to grow 50%to 768 million.
Goldstein destacou o desempenho recorde da propriedade, atribuindo-o à conclusão de uma renovação de 1,75 mil milhões de dólares. "Marina Bay Sands has returned to record a record financial and operational performance," he said, adding: "Our new high products and services position us for additional growth."
In general, LVS casinos revenue increased by 18.7% in homologous terms for just under 2.42 billion. Game -related revenues - including hotel, food and beverage services, shopping centers, conventions and retail operations - totaled $ 760 million, an increase of 4.7% over the previous year's 726 million.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Francis Lui donated 30 million to UTM that inaugurated yiu tung building</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/francis-lui-doou-30-milhoes-a-utm-inaugurou-edificio-yiu-tung/</link><description>UTM has already inaugurated the Yiu Tung building, which will be the main teaching site of the undergraduate courses next school year. Francis Lui Yiu Tung, vice president of UTM and president of the Galaxy Enternainment Group, donated 30 million patacas to the institution. The dean, Fanny Vong, thanked the gesture and pointed out that the amount “means greater flexibility in the future”
 
Catarina Pereira
 
The new building of the University of Tourism of Macau (UTM), called the Yiu Tung building, is ready for the start of the school 2025/2026, becoming the main teaching site of the undergraduate courses. The space has the capacity to host more than 2,000 students simultaneously for both theoretical and practical classes. "It is not only an infrastructure for teaching and practice, but also a symbolic milestone that represents the public good and inspires the dedication of teachers and students," said Fanny Vong, dean of the institution, at the building's presentation ceremony.
Fanny Vong also thanked the donation of 30 million Patacas made by Francis Lui Yiu Tung, president of the UTM development foundation and vice president of UTM, as well as president of Galaxy Entertainment Group. "As a public higher education institution, this was the first time UTM has opened a new source of financial revenue, which means greater flexibility in the future," said the dean.
Francis Lui, in turn, thanked the Government of MSAR and the UTM "for the trust and support in the attribution of the name" Yiu Tung Building to the New Building. " Noting that since he has assumed functions in the UTM he has “profoundly meaning the commitment and dedication of all its members in the formation of future sector talents”, Lui said he hoped, with this donation, “further support” the institution “in the advancement of quality and innovative teaching and research, as well as the connection between academic results and the evolving needs of industry”.
He also stressed that he hopes to work closely with UTM and all sectors of society to reinforce Macau's development as a “World Tourism and Leisure City”, wishing the Yiu Tung building “Materialize this vision, inspiring, connecting and enabling young people to contribute to the future of Macao”.
At the time, Cheung Kin Chung, chairman of the UTM Foundation's Executive Committee, thanked Francis Lui and explained that the 30 million Patacas will “support the university's academic development, including the creation of excellence in education prizes, highlights for outstanding articles and the promotion of exchange and collaboration programs,” according to a note from the institution.
The educational building has 14 floors and a total area of approximately 16,000 square meters, with 58 theoretical classrooms, 54 academic cabinets, four pedagogical kitchens, simulated reception rooms and governance practices.
The ceremony, chaired by the Secretary for Social Affairs and Culture, LAM, was attended by members of the Central Popular Government's Cabinet in the MSAR and the Ministry of Foreign Ministry of RPC, the Director of Youth Education and Development Services, Kong Chi Meng, among other personalities.
Fanny Vong also assured that UTM “will continue to take over the mission entrusted to it in this new era, taking advantage of its skills to form multidisciplinary talents within the scope of 'Tourism+', introducing new elements and vitality in the synergatic development of the tourist sector and other sectors, thus contributing to the development of high quality Macau and the country”.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Camões” brand debut of Victor Marreiros in Portugal</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/camoes-marca-estreia-de-victor-marreiros-em-portugal/</link><description>Victor Hugo Marreiros's “Camões Five Zero Zero” exhibition will be inaugurated tomorrow in Lisbon. It will be the first time the Macaense artist has an individual work in Portugal. The project marks the five centuries of the Portuguese poet



















The Galeria Passavite, in Lisbon, will open this Saturday, at 18:30 (Portuguese time), the show “Camões five Zero Zero”, by Victor Hugo Marreiros. This is the first time that the artist from Macao has had a solo project in Portugal. The work will be evident in the Portuguese capital until August 30 and will follow later to Macao, according to a statement.
The exhibition celebrates the 500th anniversary of Luís de Camões and proposes “a contemporary and symbolic reading of the poet figure”, using June 10 commemorative posters in Macau, which Victor Hugo Marreiros has created over 30 years. In his various productions, Marreiros has attributed a tone of modernity to Camões, bringing him “to our time and to the time of Macao”, can be read in a note of intent.
The project was born from an original idea by graphic designer Henrique Silva and presents a reinterpretation of Camões "with graphic freedom, humor and critical spirit, in a series that is, simultaneously, memory and creation." The challenge that the designer proposed to the poster author was "isolate the figure of the poet without kings or queens, presidents or ministers, without Benfica, Sporting or Porto." Deep down, "without context other than Camões himself."
Victor Hugo Marreiros's trait “is simple but never neutral” and demonstrates “a rare balance between symbolic and popular, between drawing and idea, between seriousness and smile”, argues Henrique Silva. The series demonstrates the meaning that makes “a Camões that does not only come from national memory, but from the world. And in this case it comes from Macao”, with “a contaminated look, in the best sense of the word, for centuries of encounters, exchanges and cultural coexistence”. “Portuguese identity is not only ours, nor exclusive,” says Henrique Silva.
For the director of the Portuguese Institute of the East (IPOR), Patrícia Quaresma, the work of Victor Hugo Marreiros crosses “with sensitivity and intelligence, references from the East and the West”. The head of IPOR believes that “this exhibition will inspire, raising meetings, readings and shares and continuing this construction of scripts that unite Macau and Portugal”.
Victor Hugo Marreiros takes more than 45 years dedicated to the visual arts, scenography and graphic design, having been recognized and awarded, local and internationally, on more than 200 occasions. Your work includes hundreds of book covers, magazines and posters. In addition, he participated in exhibitions by over 20 countries, such as Portugal, Japan, Brazil and the USA, among others.
He headed the graphic sector of the Cultural Institute for more than two decades and, between 1984 and 1989, was the artistic director of TDM - Macao teledifusion. He is currently artistic director of the “Victor Hugo Design” studio, where he developed “an unmistakable graphic language”.
“Passavite” is a non -profit cultural association, founded in 2014 by Henrique Silva, Paulo Robalo, Mathieu Sodore, Daniel Nascimento and Rui Lourenço. Monthly, it presents events inserted “in the most diverse languages and artistic genres”.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>China and EU want to mitigate divergences</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/ultimas/china-ue-querem-atenuar-divergencias/</link><description>EPA12257687 Chinese President XI Jinping (2-L), Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi (L), European Council President Antonio Costa (6-R) and European Commission President Ursula von der Leyen (5-R) Along with Opening Remarks of the 25th Eu-China Summit at the Great Hall of the People in Beijing, China, 24 July 2025. The Summit, Marking the 50th Anniversary of Eu-China Bilateral Relations, Focuses on the State of thee Relations and Global Geopolitical Challenges.  EPA / MAHESH KUMAR A. / POOL



Chinese President Xi Jinping yesterday called for a strategic renewal in relations with the European Union (EU), while the president of the European Commission (CE), Ursula von der Leyen, warned that bilateral relations reached a “inflection point”, requiring solutions for commercial imbalance, and the president of the European council, António Costa, reiterated the Appeal to his user to use his to use to use his Influence to end the war in Ukraine, installing China to play "an active role for peace and international stability."
In a Beijing Summit marked by growing commercial, technological and geopolitical tensions between the two blocks, Chinese Prime Minister I read Qiang, defended, in turn, that cooperation should be “the predominant tone”, pointing “The Partnership” as “the correct definition of China-UE relations”.
According to Xi Jinping, over the last five decades, Sino-European ties have produced “fruitful results” and benefited both parties and the world. Faced with “a more challenging and more complex international situation,” China and EU should reinforce communication, foster confidence and deepen cooperation, contributing more stability and predictability to the world, defended. "We should seek convergences, even maintaining disagreements, and persist in the opening and mutual benefit," he said, stressing the importance of promoting a bilateral relationship "that continues to grow in the right direction" and that can project for the next 50 years "even brighter".
Accompanied by Costa, von der Leyen noted that, to “rebalance” the relationship, it is necessary to take steps to “increase market access to European companies in China, limit the external impact of excess capacity and reduce export controls”.
According to the Chinese Foreign Ministry, Li stated that China and the EU "have no fundamental conflicts" and insisted that "cooperation is a natural option," even in an international environment "in transformation". He also pointed out that if both parties “defend free trade and firmly practice multilateralism,” global economic dynamism will be maintained and the tendency for a multipolar world will advance.
For its part, von der Leyen stressed that Europe believes in free trade, "but also in loyal competition" and warned that when its concerns are not met, "European industry and citizens will demand that their interests be defended." "EU and China are important business partners, but the current imbalance is serious, with a commercial deficit that reaches 305 billion euros," said CE, in the statement released after the meetings. Brussels expressed concern about “persistent systemic distortions” and the “excess of industrial capacity” of China, which considers aggravating inequalities in market access.
The European bloc has again demanded progress on long -term commercial issues, recalling that Chinese investments in Europe can benefit competitiveness, technological progress and quality job creation as long as reciprocity exists. "The EU is still willing to participate in a constructive dialogue to find negotiated solutions. But as long as it does not happen, it will adopt proportional measures and in accordance with international law to protect your legitimate interests," war.
Brussels also asked China to take concrete measures to improve European companies to the Chinese market in priority sectors such as meat, cosmetics and pharmaceuticals.
The community executive also demanded the end of the “reprisals” against European exports of brandy, pork and dairy products, as well as the raising restrictions on rare land export, which he considers to have a “negative impact” on European industrial sectors. The official note also underlines the need to promote reciprocity in the digital area, noting that European companies face significant obstacles to operate in China.
The EU also expressed concerns about the lack of clarity in Chinese data security and transfronheous flows, as well as denouncing “malicious cyber activities” originating from China.
On the other hand, China and EU pledged to reinforce joint efforts to combat climate change. Both parties agreed to reinforce cooperation in areas such as energy transition, climate change adaptation, methane emissions control, carbon markets and green and low carbon technologies.
 
JTM with Lusa and International Agencies</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Continent visitors grow above average</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/visitantes-continente-crescem-acima-da-media/</link><description>The number of visitors in Macau increased 14.9% to about 19.22 million in the first half of 2025, in annual terms, with the Chinese continent market representing 71.6% of the total, according to data released yesterday by the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC), which include 11.18 million tourists (+25.8%) and almost 8.04 million tourists (+2.6%). The average accumulated period of permanence of visitors was estimated at 1.1 days, less 0.1 days than in the first half of 2024, due to the increase in the proportion of tour.
According to DSEC, between January and June, visitors from the interior of China grew 19.3% to about 13.77 million, compared to the same period of 2024, with emphasis on the 25.7% increase in nine cities of the Greater Bay River Delta (7.02 million), stimulated by the growth of 57% among Zhuhai coming. In the case of individual visitors (7.41 million), the climb reached 24.6%, and official data also integrates visitors with “one entry per week” (867,492), “multiple entry visa” (241,257) and “group entries and exits” (72.149).
In turn, visitors from Hong Kong (3.65 million) and Taiwan (461,735) increased by 1.1% and 14.0%, respectively, compared to the first half of last year.
Official data also show that Macau welcomed, in the set of six months, 1.34 million international visitors, a number that illustrates an annual rise of 14.8%. With regard to Southeast Asia, DSEC stresses that the visitors of the Philippines (273,715), Indonesia (104,608), Malaysia (90,259) and Thailand (80,932) grew 16.8%, 13.8%, 6.0%and 8.8%, respectively, offsetting 0.7%in the Singapore. (54,543).
Among other markets in Asia, the organism highlights India (58,309), South Korea (282,151) and Japan (76,435), with homologous increase of 6.2%, 21.7%and 23.5%, respectively. On the other hand, compared to long -distance visitors, it stood out for a 9.9% rise from the US (76,457).
In the first semester, the entrances of visitors by land (15.78 million) increased by 20.4% and corresponded to 82.1% of the total. On the other hand, those arrivals on the sea (1.98 million) and air (1.46 million) decreased 5.2% and 4.1%, respectively.
In June alone, Macao accounted for 2.89 million visitors, plus 13.3%, in annual terms, with tour (1.61 million) and tourists (1.28 million) to grow 22.5%and 3.6%, respectively.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Mando de negceia aerial agreement with Saudi Arabia</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/raem-negoceia-acordo-aereo-arabia-saudita/</link><description>The MSAR is negotiating an air agreement with Saudi Arabia's civil aviation authority, with the aim of establishing regular flights. This year is foreseen for formal meetings, the president of the civil aviation authority revealed
 
Pun Wa Kin, president of the Civil Aviation Authority (AACM), revealed that the MSAR is in negotiations with the Saudi Arabia homologous organism. The intention is the “celebration of a bilateral air transport agreement, providing for formal meetings later this year, with the objective of brevity to establish a legal framework for the opening of regular flights between the two parties”.
Currently, air agreements celebrated between Macao and 50 countries include the United Arab Emirates, Oman, Israel, Turkey and Qatar, “establishing a legal framework for air transport between Macau and five of the main Middle East countries,” he said. The information arises in response to a written interpellation of Deputy Lam Lon Wai about the use of air traffic rights and the expansion of the air network and emerging markets.
"Although there are no direct passenger flights between Macao and Middle East countries, air load operators, such as Turkish Airlines and Qatar Airways, have appealed to Quinta Freedom traffic rights, established in the respective air agreement, to operate cargo transportation services in Macao," explained Pun Wa Kin.
He stressed, to attract more foreign airlines to settle in Macao, the International Airport Society (CAM) continues to launch incentive plans, “actively negotiating with business opportunities for the exploration of routes to Macau and supporting the existing airlines in increasing frequency and destinations for their flights”.
On the other hand, it indicated that Cam has “actively enjoyed” the “Express Link” service and existing direct flights that connect the main tourist cities of the Southeast and Northeast Asia. "Passengers can resort to local and foreign airlines operating in Macao, starting from Macao and scale in cities such as Beijing, Kuala Lumpur, Bangkok, Singapore, Tokyo and Taipeé da China, to various parts of the world, benefiting from the luggage convenience to the final destination with a single ticket," he noticed.
Pun Wa Kin also indicated that airlines based in Macau can, by sharing code with the mother company on the Beijing route, facilitate passenger connection between Macau and Frankfurt, and vice versa. "The number of users on this route has been increasing, gradually becoming one of the viable options for the connection between Macao and Europe," he noted.
 
C.p.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Inflation rate continues to slow down</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/taxa-de-inflacao-continua-desacelerar/</link><description>In line with the situation experienced since August 2024, the Annual Inflation rate in the MSAR registered new slowdown in June, by setting at 0.34%, indicates official statistical data
 
During the annual cycle ended in June, Macau registered a 0.34% rise in the Consumer Average General General Index (IPC) compared to the immediately previous 12 months (July 2023 to June 2024), falling short of 0.38% noted in May, according to the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services. The percentage of IPC increase in this comparative base, the most used by economists to calculate the annual inflation rate, has continually decreased since August 2024.
In the same time window closed in June, the IPC rose 0.31% in level A, which encompasses about 50% of family aggregates with monthly expenses between 11,000 and 35,999 patacas, and 0.36% in category B, which encompasses 30% of families with average spending between 36,000 and 71,999 Patacas. In general, increases in the index rates of various products and services (+2.37%), education (+1.60%) and health (+1.29%) and decreases in transport (-2.66%) and information and communication (-1.60%).
On the other hand, the General IPC grew 0.25%compared to June 2024, with the largest variation to be focused on the leisure, recreation, sport and culture section (+3.42%), contrary to the descents in information and communication (-3.12%) and clothing and footwear (-2.26%). Price rates of food products and non-alcoholic beverages and housing and fuels advanced 0.20% and 0.18%, respectively, due to the increase of meals acquired away from home and take-away and home rents.
In addition, the CPI rose 0.04%in the monthly comparison, with DSEC highlighting variations in clothing and footwear (+0.66%) and various products and services (+0.45%), which include personal care, insurance, jewelery, goldsmiths and watches, among others. Already the index of food products and non-alcoholic beverages increased only 0.01%compared to May, registering, on the other, descents in the leisure section, recreation, sport and culture (-0.58%) and alcoholic beverages and tobacco (-0.45%).
Between April and June, the average General IPC grew 0.22%, compared to the homologous quarter of 2024 and rose 0.02% compared to the first three months of this year. In the first half of this year, the average General IPC increased by 0.19%, in relation to the period between January and June 2024, and the increase of 0.49% in the price index of food products and non -alcoholic beverages is highlighted.
IPC-A and IPC-B, both average indices, rose 0.14% and 0.22%, respectively, compared to the first half of 2024.
 
S.t.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>400 companies at the Guangdong and Macau Fair</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/400-empresas-na-feira-de-guangdong-macau/</link><description>The Guangdong and Macau Province Products Fair runs until Sunday, in which hundreds of companies have more than five thousand products at Venetian. The program also includes games, raffles and an original play
 
Yesterday the Guangdong and Macau Province Products Fair (GMBPF, in the English), co-organized by the Institute for the Promotion of Commerce and Investment (IPIM) and the Guangdong Province Trade Services, was started yesterday. In the nearly 13,000 square meters, located in Venetian, more than 400 national and international companies, with more than five thousand products of “excellence”, according to IPIM. The event, divided into five sections, takes place until Sunday and involves a series of activities, including the debut of an original play.
This year, the GMBPF focuses on "in the silver economy and the national trend industry." In the healthy life exposure zone for the elderly, innovative products are presented, such as “wearable exoskeletons, lift chairs, among other assistance equipment”. As part of the theme “Technologies in the service of the elderly, creating friendly spaces for the elderly”, will be recreated “real scenarios of domestic life”, at the “Intelligent House Exhibition Pavilion” and the “exoskeletal zone”, in order to “ensure the safety of elderly at home”.
In the exposure zone of national trend products, the dialogue focuses on the “essence of the culture of Xiguan”, through an interactive experience in recreated scenarios. These include a “Xiguan cultural corridor in the‘ Lichia Canal ’section” and “Beco No. 72 of Guangdong and Macau”. The products presented merge “tradition and modernity” and include “Chinese costumes, cultural and creative products, incense art and national style jewelery”, according to the IPIM statement.
In addition, “Masters of Intangible Cultural Heritage of National Level” of Lingnan Culture were also invited. During the event will be presented techniques from Porcelain Cantonense, Guangzhou embroidery, bone, clay and wood sculptures and the ceramic of the Xicun oven.
The fair also features an original theatrical production, with actors of the television series “Seventy and two tenants”. The “Luz da Moon on Macau” is held on “Beco No. 72” and revives “The Charm of Classic Characters”. Also available are artistic facilities, such as “The Third Prince, Nezha x Bear Cosmos” and the “Dimond” brand space. In the latter, “10 flash shows will be held per day” by members of the Cantonense opera.
Throughout the event, more discounts and offers will be launched, including “traditional gastronomic souvenirs such as chiffon pandan, crab sauce with Singapore pepper accompanied by fried dumplings and“ Bak Kut Teh ”, among others. In addition, there will be more than 100,000 exclusive gifts, as well as raffles and games with various prizes.
The GMBPF also intends to enhance the "cooperation between Macao and Hengqin". In the MSa will be held four thematic forums, on “silver economy and intelligent care” and “economic cooperation”. In Hengqin, the Forum on "Innovation in the Silver Economy and 'Big Health'" will take place. Interested parties can visit the enclosure between 10h00 and 20h00, free of charge.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao “Crusga” Raehk in the hockey Asian</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-esmaga-raehk-asiatico-de-hoquei/</link><description>The male macao skate hockey selection won at the Asia-Camania championship, which runs in the South Korean city of Jecheon. The formation of the territory "crushed" Hong Kong for 71-0. On the other hand, the masters tied with New Zealand under-19 and was defeated by Japan and Australia in the female sector

Victor Rebelo
 
Macao began all the gas another edition of the Asia-Camania Championship of Roller Hockey, applying a very heavy defeat to Hong Kong. Nuno Antunes' “five” scored 71 goals to the opponent and conceded none, which gives her encouragement to the other challenges.
It was known beforehand that Raehk would be one of the latest selections present in the competition, along with the People's Republic of China, but it was not expected that the difference was so high and the result reached such a high level, worthy of the Guinness Book.
Helder Alhada Ricardo, who left Macau about two years ago to return to Portugal, was invited again by the skating association to represent the masters, having been in a prominent plan, pointing 31 goals. The former player/coach of the selection of the territory, who last seasoned the veterans of Hockey Club of Caldas da Rainha, showed, despite his 41 years, the good technique he still has and the scorching vein that noted it in Macao and Asia.
With the goals pointed out, it became the second most realized worldwide in official competitions. Totalizes now 422, against 399 of Portuguese António Livramento, considered one of the best hoots of all time.
Interestingly, at the top of the list of the best markers in the history of the modality at the international level, according to known data, is Alberto Lisboa, also a former player in Portugal and Macau, as well as being also responsible for the selection of the MSAR, with 481 goals in world and Asian.
Nuno Antunes oriented training again playing today against New Zealand, followed by matches with China, India, Japan and Taiwan.
The coach told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that Hong Kong's selection is "really very weak", and that Macau had the "unhappiness" of being the first game. "We do not know tomorrow, nor can we make it easier to tell that the selections that follow golee too, otherwise we will be dependent," he said.
The coach recognizes that there will be very uneven results. "Is it ugly? Is it actually, but uglier is to facilitate and lose championships in the difference in goals," he says.
"The ideal was to win the games all without depending on it, but we have had bad experiences precisely in this context," he concludes.
Also in the first round of the men's championship, India surpassed China (32-0) and the Japanese beat New Zealand (8-4).
The MSar entourage participates in two more categories, female seniors and under-19. The women's team, directed by José Sousa, lost in his debut with Japan 7-0. In the second challenge, one more Desaire, now against Australia (10-0). Today, the confrontation is with New Zealand, which in the inaugural round beat China 8-0. In another result of the female class, India thrashed Hong Kong by 62-0.
In the young level, Macao's first game was with the New Zealandes, yesterday morning, having tied (5-5). On Friday's journey, he will find India.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>60 secondary students learn Camões language in Portugal and Shanghai</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/60-alunos-secundario-aprendem-lingua-de-camoes-em-portugal-xangai/</link><description>On summer holidays, DSEDJ launched this year two courses focused on Portuguese learning, one in Portugal lasting three weeks and the other in Shanghai that will last two weeks. The objective is to improve the integrated Portuguese language skills of the 60 participating students from 22 local secondary schools

Between this month and August, the Directorate of Youth Education and Development Services (DSEDJ) will organize two summer courses for learning Portuguese, having selected a total of 60 students from 22 secondary schools in Macao, to participate in a course in Portugal or another in Shanghai.
According to DSEDJ, students who participate in the course in Portugal, lasting three weeks, will visit Lisbon, Coimbra and Porto, where they will take intensive Portuguese courses in higher education institutions. In this course, designated by “Summer Language and Culture Study Travel - Study Program in Portugal”, students will experience the academic environment closely and know the rich history and local culture, which will deepen the knowledge of these young people about Portugal and help them plan the continuation of studies, said the DSEDJ.
During the three weeks, students will also participate in various study activities outside the classrooms. They will know those three large Portuguese cities and gain more abilities in terms of linguistic practice and intercultural communication, through interaction with local residents.
Already in Shanghai, participants in the “Summer Initiation Course 2025” will have two weeks to take systematic courses taught by higher education institutions, in order to strengthen their techniques for learning Portuguese and to increase their confidence in studying the language of Camões.
In the same line, this group of students will also have linguistic and cultural exchanges with secondary education students who study Portuguese language in Shanghai, with whom they will exchange learning methods. According to DSEDJ, in addition, the course in Shanghai is covered by the meaning of widening the horizon and the interpersonal network of students in the Portuguese area.
“The two Portuguese -holidays field activities on summer holidays will not only improve students' integrated Portuguese skills, but they will also be beneficial for students to demonstrate the excellent style and quality of Macau young people with friends in China and International, promoting humanistic exchanges between China and Portugal,” said DSEDJ.
In a statement, the body also stressed that the DSEDJ is committed, through systematic education, to form, from childhood, students interested in learning the Portuguese language, so that they can hear, speak, read and write in Portuguese. At the same time, it promised the “continuous deepening” of the establishment of Portuguese-language official schools that make all levels of teaching and development of Chinese-Portuguese bilingual classes available, as well as the organization of various study plans, phased Portuguese courses and diverse learning activities, with a view to consolidating the linguistic base for students interested in continuing studies in Portugal.
In addition, DSEDJ highlighted the creation of prizes at levels, in order to increase opportunities for students to study Portuguese language abroad.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>IC promotes books exchange in the three lamps</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/ic-promove-troca-de-livros-nos-tres-candeeiros/</link><description>The activity “exchange one book for another”, launched by the Cultural Institute, will be held this weekend in the area of the three lamps. Each person can exchange a maximum of 20 books
 
The Cultural Institute (IC) again promotes the activity “exchange one book for another”, this time, in the roundabout of Carlos da Maia. Next Saturday and Sunday, a book exchange counter will be set up in the three lamps, and the goal is to “increase the circulation and sharing of reading resources in the community by building a convenient book exchange platform”, as well as “encouraging residents to cultivate reading habit”.
Participants only need to take their books that comply with the exchange rules, selecting the favorite books and exchanging them for a number equal to their own books, explains the IC. Each person can exchange a maximum of 20 books during the event.
The body led by Leong Wai Man warns that magazines, leaflets, guides to enter a higher degree school, textbooks, event catalogs, children's cloth books, not locally published yearbooks, legal books, exam guides. Outside are also published science and engineering books for over five years, computer books edited for over three years, tour guides edited for over two years, periodic publications with pornographic and/or violent content, religious publications, books without publication or with infringements to copyright.
In addition, damaged or dirty books, collections and incomplete pages, poorly bound books, with easy -to -separated pages, torn books, and books with more than five copies, to ensure the quality and applicability of exchange books.
In addition, on site, panels will be placed on the services provided by the Macao Public Library to present various resources and services, "in order to facilitate the understanding of residents, increase their interest in reading and promote reading culture in the community." The activity “Changing one book for another” is released in a unique month from May to November.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Grand Lisboa Palace welcomes shows about Picasso</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/grand-lisboa-palace-acolhe-mostra-sobre-picasso/</link><description>The SJM inaugurated the exhibition “Picasso: Beauty and Drama”, under the Macao International Biennial Program. The operator's “special exhibition” brings together more than a hundred Pablo Picasso work at the Grand Lisboa Palace until October



















Grand Lisboa Palace welcomed over 140 original works by Pablo Picasso. SJM's “Special Exhibition”, “Picasso: Beauty and Drama” is one of the highlights of the Macao International Art Biennial. Co-organized by the operator and the “Museo Casa Natal Picasso”, the show will be evident until October 26 and features paintings, impressions, ceramics, illustrations and manuscripts of the Spanish artist, says SJM.
The exhibition explores the artist's perspectives “About the beauty and emotional drama of his personal life” and offers “an intimate glimpse of one of the greatest artistic minds of the 20th century,” according to a press release. On display stands out the painting “Figure in Brook to Strues”, the portrait of his daughter, “Paloma with Doll, Black Background” and the play “Knight and Horse”, among other works.
Divided into seven thematic galleries, the exhibition “draws the evolution of the artist through various phases of his career”, offering “a rare view of his emotional landscape” and his connection to Andalusia. In the “Beauty” section, the author challenges and redefines “classic ideals”. In "myths", Picasso reinterprets ancient narratives through a modern lens. In the “Bulls” gallery, “the symbolic role of bullfighting in Spanish identity” and the “emotional response of the artist to his homeland” are explored.
In "Women", Picasso pays tribute to women who "shaped their creative and emotional journeys." “Ceramics” enhances its late exploitation with this art form, where worldly containers are transformed. His "tireless experimentation" in mixed engravings and techniques is represented in "techniques."
Finally, the last gallery presents 10 "quintessential" works that illustrate "artistic genius, devotion to the family, love for tradition and irreverent ingenuity" by Pablo Picasso. The exhibition culminates in an interactive area, which includes a mirror room and the installation "where are you going?", Where visitors are challenged to "follow their passions."
The president of the Cultural Institute, Leong Wai Man, highlighted “SJM's longtime commitment to the arts and culture”, which “enriched Macao's urban landscape with an international view and creative curatorship, raising the city's artistic reputation”.
Daisy Ho, executive director of the operator, said that SJM "prides itself on continuing to support" Macau Art "and work with the Government of MSAR." "This exhibition exemplifies an important multicultural collaboration and resonates with our longtime efforts to promote Chinese cultural heritage."
Daily, during the exhibition period, there will also be a series of workshops from the “Picasso: Beauty and Drama” learning studio. In addition, Grand Lisbon Palace guests will be able to experience, for a limited period, menus inspired by the Spanish artist.
The exhibition is open to the public from 11h00 to 19h00, Monday to Thursday, between 11h00 and 21h00 from Friday and from 10h00 to 21h00, on the weekends. Guided tours are available in English, Cantonese and Mandarin, and the price for each adult is 298 patacas.
 
P.M.</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>“Sucata Museum” in Maputo gives new life to the old iron and the community</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/museu-da-sucata-em-maputo-da-nova-vida-ao-ferro-velho-a-comunidade/</link><description>Rui Paulino, 54, manager of the company Limetal and mentor of the project of the “Museum of Sucata”, in an interview with Lusa in the neighborhood of Flaculo, a former garden of the Vulcano Football Club, in the rear of the limetal company, where Iron Velho is reinvented in art and instrument of social transformation, in Maputo, Mozambique, July 2, 2025. Vulcano ", but visitors dubbed him from" Sucata Museum ", where Iron Velho is recreated with creativity, inclusion and hope. (Accompanies Lusa text on July 21, 2025). Luísa Nhantumbo/Lusa



Luísa Nhantumbo*

 
In the neighborhood of Flagenculo, in Maputo, a former garden of the Vulcano Football Club, in the rear of the limetal company shipyard, has gained new identity as a “scrap museum”, where Iron Velho is reinvented in art and instrument of social transformation.
The space is known on social networks as “Vulcano Sucarte”, but visitors dubbed him “scrap museum”, where Iron Velho is recreated with creativity, inclusion and hope.
"It's the name given by the people coming here and it was because it's a museum," Lusa Rui Paulino, 54, a manager of the Limetal company and mentor of the project that "gives life to the scrap".
The goal is to “show that there is life of the scrap after being transformed,” says Rui, in the midst of several sculptures made of recycled metals, spread across almost the entire backyard of the “museum”.
In the "scratch" there are several works exposed on the floor, on trees, from tights, tables, chairs, animals, musical instruments, there are sea-inspired sculptures, such as seahors and turtles, made from scrap or purchased locally.
The artistic and cultural space emerged “in play”, around 2000, when Rui and his former mechanic welled small sculptures from unusable pieces, in a craft that the architect and businessman inherited from his father, who founded the company in 1950.
Today, besides giving life to the scrap, Rui Paulino also dreams of giving a better life to the Vulcan club, turning him into a multipurpose structure that integrates cycling, football and athletics.
"The club is the driver of this project because it is the organization of people, it is the responsibility that each one has to have things to be well presented. I think without the club this would not be what it is ... The idea is to set up something that does not stop, a serious club (…) to set up sports schools, a gym," says the enthusiastic businessman.
The shipyard transformed into a gallery hostels 90 people involved in the various activities of the project, most of the old and current athletes of the Vulcano Football Club, so much so that the team's equipment hanged at Estendal is at the bottom of the backyard.
The works of the “Museum” are made of cars scrap, appliances, office supplies, dishes, beverage production factories and all metallic to imagine.
“Baths, pans, machines, engines, metal structures, everything that has played its role of structure and is already discarded, because iron has a useful life time, then is transformed into scrap and everything that is scrap we process,” says the difficulties of obtaining the raw material.
The pieces were also created from scrap purchased in small quantities in local markets, but supply instability led the company to change the strategy.
“We created a lot of problems, so we now only work with serious contracts, with large companies, but we still buy scrap from individuals, on the condition of being well organized things,” he clarifies, also mentioning financial difficulties that reduced the number of employees from 120 to 90.
Despite the difficulties, ambition remains firm: “Developing the community through club and art”, also portrayed in a building whose three floors, except the base, are made of metal.
In the summit of the building, which acts as the club's social center, there is a dragon made based on recycled metal, which signals the "museum" in the distance and is used as a point of reference of space, located in the suburb of Maputo.
“The biggest dream is to be able to go here and see my athletes and my friends enjoying a club that works well,” says Rui, who has already opened a second gallery on Mao Tsé Tung Avenue, in the city of Maputo, with pieces available to the public.
Metal sculptures are also spread in various parts of the Mozambican capital, as well as the Call of the Call.
The businessman complains about the lack of market for works in Mozambique, a situation that delays his dream of “developing the Community of the Callmill” and the Vulcan club through the life that gives the scrap. "A club requires many services around you that can be transformed into support for society and the community around us," says the official, for whom "everything has value now" and the "scrap looks like gold."
 
*From the Lusa Agency</description><pubDate>2025-07-25 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>