<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/</link><description>Jornal TRIBUNA DE MACAU EN RSS</description><item><title>Authorities reported 55 cases of domestic violence in 2024</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-registaram-55-casos-de-violencia-domestica-em-2024/</link><description>The central registration system shows that, in the last year, 55 suspected cases of domestic violence were confirmed in Macao, involving 56 victims. The number illustrates an annual increase of 37.5% and a continuous climbing trend since 2022. According to the report, 30.9% of attackers and 13.3% of victims live without income. In addition, in 40% of cases, in addition to the victim, episodes of violence were witnessed by children
 
Between January and December last year, the MSAR authorities received 2,375 communications about cases suspected of domestic violence, of which 1,697 were considered as suspicious cases after the exclusion of repeated situations. After the analysis, only 55 were confirmed as suspected cases of domestic violence, involving 55 attackers who will have attacked 56 victims, reveals the summary of the 2024 annual report, prepared by the Institute of Social Action, related to the Central Case Registration System of Domestic Violence.
Regarding the types of cases, 30 (54.5% of the total) concerns situations of violence with spouses and 16 against children (29.1%). There were also eight cases against the elderly (14.5%) and one of violence against family members.
Compared to the 2023 data, it appears that the number of suspected cases of domestic violence in Macau increased by 37.5%. Specifically, cases of violence against children rose nearly 45.5% in annual terms, while cases that implied spouses increased about 15.4%.
After breaks in the numbers of all types of domestic violence in 2022, official data show that this phenomenon has continuously climbed, as regards the total of cases and occurrences against spouses. Over the past four years, 2024 has been the year with more cases of domestic violence against the elderly, taking into account the records every six in 2021, three in 2022 and zero in 2023.
Generally speaking, the report reveals that the average number of cases of domestic violence per month registered a continuous decrease between 2016 (October to December) and 2020, having dropped from 10.3 to 3.2. Subsequently, it increased to 6.8 cases per month by 2021, fell by 2022 again, remained unchanged by 2023 and rose to an average of 4.6 by 2024.
Last year, the types of offense were mainly translated into physical violence, corresponding to a total of 44 cases (80%). There are also six cases of psychic offense (10.9%), one of sexual violence being a child, one of inadequate care, also to a child, and three related to violence or multiple offenses, involving spouses.
In general, 69.6% of victims are women and 78.2% of attackers are male.
On the other hand, according to the central registration system, in 40% of cases confirmed in 2024, beyond the victim, there were other children who witnessed violence against parents, siblings or grandparents.
Regarding the income of victims who were attacked by the spouses, in addition to 26.7% whose performance was unknown, 49.9% earn less than 20 thousand patacas per month. In concrete, 13.3% had no income and 13.3% earned monthly between 15,001 and 20,000 patacas. As for the elderly victims, 88.9% lived without income last year.
In another respect, 39.3% of victims of domestic violence completed primary education and 19.6% completed complementary secondary education. Only eight victims, 14.3% of the total, have a degree or higher. On the other hand, 32.1% of victims work full time, 39.3% live in the north and 12.5% ​​reside in the mud. Among the victims of marital violence, there are employees of office, inactive, counter employees, table employees, public relations workers in casinos and croupiers.
With regard to aggressors, 29.1% were registered with unknown yield and 30.9% without income. In general, 50.8% of attackers earn less than 20,000 patacas per month.
Still in the field of employment, 47.3% of attackers work full time and 16.4% were unemployed when they practiced domestic violence. As for the profession, in addition to 32.7% of inactive attackers, several drivers, office employees and cooks.
According to the same data, 27.3% of attackers completed general secondary education, while 25.5% are licensed or with higher academic degree.
The most common age groups among the victims last year are between 35 and 44 years old, between seven and 12th years and from 25 to 34 years. Among the aggressors, 38.2% and 30.9% were in the 35 to 44 age group and in the 25-34 range, respectively. On the other hand, 55.4% of victims and 65.5% of attackers are married. In addition, victims (89.3%) and aggressors (89.1%) are mostly permanent residents.
 
Emotional disorders as dominant causes
In cases of marital violence, most victims (83.3%) are female and 50% were born within China. In this type of cases, the main factors that cause violence are the “disorders or uncontrolled emotions” (60%), the “drunkenness” (26.7%) and “agreement with the use of violence” (20%). In addition, the main factors regarding family relationships are associated with “difficulties in communication with spouses” (50%) and “adultery or adultery suspicion” (43.3%).
Regarding cases against children, 56.3% of victims are boys aged seven to 12 years. In this sphere, causes also include “disorders or uncontrolled emotions” (62.5%) and “agreement with the use of violence” (43.8%). In addition, 43.8% of aggressors against children justified violent acts for "irrational expectations to their children" and 31.3% admitted their "strong belief in body punishment."
Also in the origin of cases of violence against children, factors such as the “appearance of difficulties in the education of children” (56.3%), “difficulties in communication between spouses” (50%) and the “appearance of obstacles in communication between parents and children” (43.8%) were found.
Regarding nine old -age victims (six women and three men recorded in a total of eight cases), seven suffered physical violence and psychic offense. In addition to the factors that were also at the source of cases of violence against spouses and children, it is observed that 62.5% of the aggressors against the elderly will be with mental disabilities. According to the report, 37.5% of people who committed violence to the elderly attributed behavior to “family care pressure”, and 37.5% pointed to “problems in communication”.
 
Most sought after individual counseling
The report also reveals that “individual or family counseling” was the most necessary route after the occurrence of violence (used by 87.3% of victims). In addition, 34.5% of the victims needed the “urgent host service”, and 29.1% sought “school counseling”.
Of the rest, 23.6%, 21.8% and 16.4% of people who suffered domestic violence needed “medical services”, “home for children and young people” and “clinical psychological service”, respectively. “Legal counseling” and “financial assistance” were used for 14.5% and 10.9% of the victims, respectively.
As for the case source, 41.8% were discovered following requests for aid made by victims, on their own initiative. At the same time, non -governmental institutions or associations helped detect 14.5% of cases of domestic violence.
On the other hand, 12.7% of cases first reached the knowledge of the Public Security Police, while 12.7% of occurrences were released with the help of schools or student counseling services.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Macao without “Poule” in the League of Volleyball Nations</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/macau-sem-poule-na-liga-das-nacoes-de-voleibol/</link><description>With some surprise, Macau was left out of this year's edition of the Women's League League, specifically the qualification phase, in “Poule”, contrary to what had been happening for several editions. Hong Kong will host China's tournament and selection, as of June 4th. The President of the Institute of Sports revealed to the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that "a multiplicity of reasons" led the mand to "take a break." Luís Gomes is, however, optimistic regarding the return of the competition to the territory “at the right time”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The start of the 2025 edition of the Female Volleyball League is scheduled for June 4, however, Macau is not included in the "Pouches" of qualification, contrary to what had been happening about two decades ago. In 2001 and 2011, Macau even organized the final phase of the so -called World Women's Volleyball Grand Prix, which would be replaced by the current League of Nations.
Asked about the reasons for the absence of masters in the prestigious tournament organized by the International Federation of Modality (FIVB), the president of the Sports Institute (ID) told the Jornal Tribuna de Macao that a "multiplicity of reasons made us take a break." However, Luís Gomes believes that the competition returns to Macau soon. "I am optimistic about the return of the League of Nations to Macau at the right time," he said.
The leader stressed that there has been a “good partnership” with FIVB in organizing the event for several years, implying that this will not mean that it has to be in all editions. "The test is organized in different places worldwide," he recalls, adding that the federation "takes into account the promotion of volleyball in different regions, in order to increase the influence of sport."
The promotion of marketing and the period of the event “are always issues that concern FIVB,” said Luís Gomes, without any use whether the decision was up to Macau or the International Federation.
Created in 2018, the League of Nations returned to Macau in 2024, after being last held in 2019. Because of the pandemic, the "poule" of the territory was suspended, having resumed last year with a different format, with more games, which aroused greater interest and enthusiasm. Brazil won the territory series, which hosted the Galaxy Arena for the first time, with a capacity of 16,000 spectators.
Unlike Macao, Hong Kong will organize this year one of the “Poules”, between June 18, at the Kai Tak Arena, receiving selections from China, Thailand, Japan, Italy, Bulgaria and Czech Republic. The remaining teams are Brazil, South Korea, Türkiye, the United States, Germany, the Baixes, Poland, Serbia and the Dominican Republic.
The qualification phase will also be held in the cities of Beijing (China), Otava (Canada), Rio de Janeiro (Brazil), Istanbul (Turkey), Belgrade (Serbia), Apeldoorn (Netherlands), Arlington (United States) and Chiba (Japan. The final phase, for the attribution of the title, will take place in Lodz, Poland, between 23 and 27 July.
 
“Sport and Health” post attracted numerous elderly
According to the Institute of Sport (ID), the activity of “Sport and Health: Service and Information Post”, held at the government's residence for the elderly, was well-received by the many elderly who participated. The ID, in collaboration with the Institute of Social Action, provided a free physical condition assessment service and performed a session under the monthly theme “Increased muscle mass for fall prevention”, with the participation of a nutritionist. The ID service and information post will be available at the side space of Jardim Cidade das Flores, between 08:00 and 11:30 next Sunday.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Prices and sales of houses fell for the third consecutive quarter</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/precos-vendas-de-casas-cairam-pelo-terceiro-trimestre-consecutivo/</link><description>The real estate market of the MSAR continued to cool in the first quarter of this year, registering new sequential breaks in sales of housing fractions, offices and industrial units. According to official data, the average price of houses sold retreated 5.5% in three months and 15.5% within one year, driven by coloane descent
 
Sérgio Terra
 
Real estate business regressed in the first three months of this year in general reveals data from the Statistics and Census Services Directorate (DSEC), which point to a break from 1.5% to 1,348 in the number of sales of autonomous fractions and parking places, compared to the previous three months. The total amount of transactions, based on the seal tax charged, suffered an even more pronounced decline by retreating 28.4% to 5.33 billion patacas in the same temporal interval.
In the housing chapter, the number of transactions rose 31.6% in annual terms, however, descended 14.7% over the fourth quarter of 2024. According to official statistics, it is the third consecutive quarterly descent.
Between January and March, 754 housing autonomous fractions (less 130, in quarterly terms) were transacted by the global amount of 3.69 billion patacas (less 27.4%). Sealed businesses included 644 housing fractions of built buildings (less 17.6%), for a total value of 3.2 billion (less 29%) and 110 in construction estate (plus eight), by 488 million (less 15.2%).
The average price per square meter (service area) of housing fractions sold 5.5% to 71,859 patacas, compared to the fourth quarter of 2024, and lowered 15.5% in annual homologous terms. In this domain, the third successive and seventh quarterly descent was recorded in the annual comparison.
In the period under analysis, Coloane was no longer the zone with the most expensive houses, the result of a quarterly descent from 24.5% to 76,441 patacas in the average price of transacted fractions. On the other hand, on the Macau Peninsula (68,043 patacas) and the mud (78,547 patacas) average prices lowered 2.6% and 3.6%, respectively.
In the case of housing fractions of built buildings, the average price fell 5.7% to 70,768 patacas, compared to the last three months of 2024. On the other hand, in buildings under construction, it was decreased from 31.2% to 81,448 patacas.
The largest number of house transactions occurred in Baixa da Taipa (99), new landfills of Black Sand - Natap (83) and in Black Areia and Iao Hon (55), with average prices per square meter of 77.141, 92.192 and 63,791 patacas, respectively. The Pac On and Taipa Grande zone stood out as the most expensive, with the average price to be set at 98,271 patacas.
 
More stores sold by lower values
In turn, the number of transacted stores grew 12% to 112, compared to the preceding three months, however, the respective total amount lowered 59.6% to 712 million patacas. The Nape Zone stands out in this segment, with 48 stores sold for a total amount of 59 million patacas.
In the first three months of 2025, there were also 18 offices, 17 industrial fractions and 441 parking places, numbers that illustrate quarterly descents of 40% and 5.65% and an increase of 33.6, respectively. The total value of office sales (62 million) descended 38.4%, while those of industrial fractions (169 million) and parking spaces (323 million) increased 11.6%and 14.4%, respectively.
The average price per square meter of autonomous fractions for offices (58,652 patacas) decreased 10.1%, in relation to the previous quarter. On the other hand, industrial autonomous fractions made 5.5%more, to 34,361 patacas.
At the end of March, 5,174 housing autonomous fractions were in the project phase, 1,785 under construction and 104 in survey. In addition, licenses were issued for 212 fractions, all located on the Macao Peninsula and the studio type. There were also 32 housing autonomous fractions with permission of execution issued (all on the peninsula), of which 43.7% were studio type and 56.3% had a quarter.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Jockey land included in the use plan</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/terreno-jockey-incluido-em-plano-de-aproveitamento/</link><description>default



The land where the Jockey Club operated is included in the reserve of spaces for future planning and use, according to the secretary for transport and public works. Raymond Tam also said that the respective land, as well as the originally affecting the construction of the “ocean world”, will be used according to the “concrete needs of society's development”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The use of state land, such as the one that housed the facilities of the former Jockey Club, was approached by the secretary for transport and public works in response to an oral interpellation of Deputy Ma Io Fong. In the statements made at the Legislative Assembly (AL), Raymond Tam said that "regarding the land originally affected to the construction of the Hippodrome and also the" ocean world ", both are included in reserve for future planning and use of the concrete needs of society's development."
It is recalled that the space that served for horsepower runs by Macau Jockey Club was recovered by the government, after the lease of the Macao Horse Race Company was declared in late March last year.
In response to the deputy, Raymond Tam stated that in the future, when elaborating the detail plans of each Planning and Management Operative Unit (UOPG), the current situation and specific needs of each UOPG will be taken, so as to “progressively improve the global disposition of space, optimize public facilities and the environmental environment, thus responding to the needs of the resident population recreational and sports facilities, among others ”.
As for the land integrated in the land reserve whose definitive purpose has not yet been attributed, "its provisional use will be considered, taking into account the different needs of society."
The secretary for transport and public works highlighted in AL that the government has already taken advantage of some land recovered, "turning them into public and public leisure spaces or into children's parks." In the first phase, the B13 lot of zone A of the new urban landfills, the C8 lot of Lake Nam Van and the BT7 batch of the Taipa were selected to be used provisionally as open fields open to the public and schools.
Regarding land adjacent to Olympic Avenue, as well as the lot initially intended for the construction of the so-called Park of Tire, they are integrated into the Central Taipa-2 UOPG, whose planning “is currently underway”. According to the ruler, "efforts are being taught for their conclusion as fast as possible, with a view to subsequent public consultation intended for the collection of suggestions."
Referring to the Seac Pai Van Zone, where the Institute for Municipal Affairs has created, more recently, a new leisure area in Alameda da Harmonia, Raymond Tam stressed that the direction of soil and urban construction services is “optimizing and adjusting the land yet to develop” in the community neighborhood, in the sense of “building a more comfortable, accessible and gifted community”, with the objective of “effectively improving the housing conditions of the resident population”.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Journey “Improper for Cardiac” decides title in the Portuguese League</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/desporto/jornada-impropria-para-cardiacos-decide-titulo-na-liga-portuguesa/</link><description>Sporting or Benfica, one of them will celebrate the title on Saturday in the Portuguese Football League. The "lions" depart as favorites, as they depend only on themselves to celebrate the two -time championship. The Jornal Tribuna de Macao has heard some fans on both sides for the preview of a round that will decide, and so it will be “improper to cardiac”
 
Victor Rebelo
 
The draw between Benfica and Sporting postponed the issue of the title in the Portuguese Football League for the last day, with the challenges in which they act the two candidates scheduled for this Saturday, starting at 18h00 (01h00 at dawn in Macau).
With the two formations tied at points (79), but with Sporting in advantage in direct confrontation, the last day is a little more comfortable for the "lions", which depend only on themselves. However, football is prodigal in surprises, hence the fans of both clubs are reserved and expecting, ready to “explode” the emotions as soon as the referees bear the end of the games.
Sporting will guarantee the title if the Fifth Classifieds Vitória de Vitória de Alvalade is exceeded in Alvalade. However, it can also become champion if tied or losing as long as this is the same result obtained by Benfica in Braga.
The Jornal Tribuna de Macao recorded the opinion of some fans of the two clubs resident in Macau.
Amâncio Goitia, Leonino aficioned, begins by saying that
"This season, Sporting has undoubtedly demonstrated that it is the best team in the championship," adding that "even facing a significant number of injuries, the team managed to stay first in most journeys, which emphasizes the quality of the squad."
“Winning this game is essential to solidify the hard work done throughout the season,” says the Macaense. The “resilience” demonstrated by the team, coupled with the “unconditional support of the fans”, creates an environment “conducive to achieving this great goal”.
The Macao Elite League player, which curiously wears Benfica's nightgown, is "anxious" to see Sporting lift the trophy. “May the two -time championship come,” he concludes.
On the other hand, Duarte Alves recognizes that it is "an improper journey to cardiac." The “incarnate” sympathizer points out that there are interesting statistics: “70 years since Sporting has celebrated a two -time championship, but it will have no easy life by fighting a victory that needs to secure a place in Europe”.
Already Benfica, "to counteract this, will have to overthrow another impressive statistic -since 2000, no team that has entered the last day left the title -and plays out against a Braga with a mission almost impossible to return to the places of the League podium."
Moreover, the president of Benfica de Macao addresses other struggles. "FC Porto plays mainly to avoid another installment below average, having practically the third place guaranteed," he notes. Meanwhile, "in the shadow of the big ones," Santa Clara, coming from the 2nd League, "tries another historical achievement" in the year of the elite return, that is, "becoming the first Azorean team on the top-5, betting on solid football that has as its secret weapon the emotional strength of its stadium, a decisive factor that few analysts have highlighted."
In short, Duarte Alves stresses that it will be “one last day where there is not only football, but decades of history, unlikely statistics and unpublished European destinations in the Portuguese League”.
Also with connection with local football, Filipe Duarte states that, "as a Benfica fan, not being a great fanatic, as it is obvious to make me sad to be champion this year," as the team "had everything" to win the title. “It made it easier for some games that it would be supposed to be easy, it cost the championship,” he says.
Although the league is not over yet, Benfica de Macau's central defense thinks it is “it will be difficult” for its colors. However, as Guimarães needs to win to go to European competitions, "it may be that the game against Sporting" becomes interesting "for the last day, not forgetting that Benfica" also has to win. "He recognizes that" there will be a lot of nerves on the skin "but expects to fall to Benfica's side.
 
Quality of the squad is not enough to win
Filipe Duarte states that it was a championship that did not start the best way for the "incarnated", but was improving over time. "In my opinion, Benfica's squad has more quality, even if it sometimes does not arrive," he says.
Sportinguista Paulo Ferreira also left his opinion about tomorrow's emotions in Portuguese football, believing that Sporting and Benfica will win their games. “Sporting with more difficulty meeting with Vitória de Guimarães, but will eventually triumph and be champion,” he says, considering that the Vimaranenses, despite the defeat, will ensure the conference league.
As for the influence of certain players, it foresees that "once again Gyokeres will be decisive."
On the opposite side of the table, "I believe Farense will ensure direct maintenance after beating Santa Clara." Amadora's star “will go to the Maintenance Play-Off with Vizela, eventually going down the AVS and Boavista division”.
Frederico Cordeiro sees a large part of Benfica's games live on television, despite late times. From his perspective, "the last six hours have practically decided that the title would either Sporting or Benfica." In fact, he comments, "if Benfica had not tied with Arouca, when he was in advantage of two balls, he could now say he was one step away from being champion." This game "was fatal" for Benfica. Moreover, he says, "it is quite visible that some clubs have shown that they can face the teams that occupy the first three places."
Finally Tiago Assunção, Leonino Adept, begins by analyzing Alvalade's challenge. "The atmosphere around the game, as it was possible to see after the final whistle in Derby, with the apotheotic reception to the team, is special," justifying with the fact that the Sportinguists "feel that only a small step for final consecration and the team is close to making history."
The possibility of Sporting becoming champion “three times in the last five years, especially considering that the team six years ago started a dark period after the incidents in Alcochete, makes the expected achievement even more impressive,” he says.
The opponent is strong, he says, "but it also comes in with the pressure of needing a victory to secure a place in European competitions, which makes an open game anticipated, where both teams will look for the only result that guarantees them their goal: victory."
The sympathizer acknowledges that there will be much "nervous" in field players, the bench and between assistance. "
With all these ingredients, "I anticipate a Sporting to carry offensively since the start of the game, through players such as Trincão, Pot and, of course, Swedish Gyokeres Bomber, which will certainly want to increase its already impressive Goaller Peculius."
In conclusion, Tiago Assunção stresses that "no early party, but also without fear, that it is a great game and that, in the end, Sporting comes out victorious, thus winning the long -awaited two -time championship."</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Demonry building in ruin on theater street</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/demolido-edificio-em-ruina-na-rua-teatro/</link><description>default



Authorities demolished a ruined building on Theater Street, in order to eliminate risks to public safety, the soil services and urban construction (DSSCU) directed. Owners “have undeclable responsibility and duty to periodically proceed to the conservation and repair of their buildings in order to keep them in good condition,” the body reiterated, by stressing that “their degradation may cause death or property losses to others and further result in public safety risks”.
The demolished building whose coverage had collapsed was in advanced state of degradation. Following a survey, the DSSCU survey committee confirmed the state of ruin, thus publishing a notice to demand from the owners to demolish, however, it received no response. Therefore, DSSCU has advanced to its demolition, and the resulting costs is the responsibility of the owners.
As a rule, through ordinary inspection, the presentation of complaints from citizens or the transfer of cases made by other services, DSSCU sends personnel to the inspection of the building, in order to evaluate its state and follow up on the case. If there are signs of lack of conservation of the building, the body notifies the owners to hire qualified professionals within the fixed period, in order to inspect the building and the preparation of the “report on the state of the building” to register the parties in poor repair and conservation and present solutions.
If the building is in poor reparation and conservation or in a state of ruin, DSSCU may unable to order a prior survey to the building, then drawing up the inspection notice, notifying the owners of its results. Owners will have to comply with the Order of DSSCU and hire qualified professionals within the deadline stipulated to prepare the projects of work and make the repair, consolidation, partial or total demolition of the building.
In addition, when there is an imminent risk of collapse or situation that constitutes a serious danger to public health or people's safety, DSSCU may immediately require owners to proceed to the necessary works. If they do not deal with the matter as soon as possible, taking into account public interests, demolition work will be performed by the Administration and the respective expenses supported by the owners, which will still be subject to any sanctions.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Hengqin leader resigned</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/dirigente-de-hengqin-apresentou-demissao/</link><description>Claiming “personal motives”, Su Kun resigned as Deputy Chief of the Executive Committee of the Deepened Cooperation Zone, as well as the function of Advisor to the Secretary's Office for the Economy and Finance of Macau
 
The Macao government announced yesterday that a leader of the deepened cooperation zone in Hengqin called for the resignation "for personal reasons." According to a note, Su Kun is no longer one of the six assistants of the executive committee of the in-depth cooperation zone.
According to the Macao Government portal, this commission “assumes the functions of promoting international dissemination, business and investment capture, industry introduction, land exploitation, construction of specific projects and management of subjects concerning the life of the population”.
The Secretary's Office for Macao Economics and Finance, Tai Kin IP, indicated in the statement, with only one sentence, that Su Kun also resigned as the secretary's advisor, a request that was approved, with effects since yesterday.
Su Kun's resignation takes place a day after the Guangdong neighboring neighboring commission announced the beginning of an investigation to the former president of the state company responsible for the development of the Hengqin Special Zone. In a statement, Guangdong's Provincial Disciplinary Inspection Commission said the former president of Hengqin's Zhuhai Group, Hu Jia, “is suspected of serious disciplinary violations,” a phrase that usually refers to corruption.
The note, also with only one sentence, says Hu is being the subject of “disciplinary review and investigation” by Zhuhai's Municipal Inspection and Disciplinary Supervision Commission.
Lusa asked the Macao government if Su Kun's resignation is related to corruption investigation against Hu Jia, but did not report any response until the closing of this edition.
The Hengqin Zhuhai Group was created in 2009 by the municipality of Zhuhai for the construction and development of the special hengqin economic zone. This area includes the in -depth cooperation zone, a project launched by Beijing in 2021 and jointly managed by Guangdong province and Macau.
The Macao government has defended a greater bet on integration with Hengqin. The development of the neighboring island “is our main task,” the executive chief told journalists on Tuesday at a six-day visit to Macao from the Chinese Communist Party's leading Macao for Macao and Hong Kong, Xia Baolong.
On Monday, the director of the Hong Kong and Macao affairs office, under the tutelage of the Council of State, said that "the construction of hengqin should be treated as a priority of Macao."
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Authorities “LIMAM ORGES” against money laundering</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/autoridades-limam-arestas-contra-lavagem-de-dinheiro/</link><description>The interdepportal working group against capital laundering and terrorism financing continues to evaluate the eventual need to review the legislation on this matter, the SPU said
 
Sixty representatives of 13 services, including leaders, bosses and their workers, attended this year's first plenary meeting of the Interdepartal Working Group against capital laundering and terrorism financing. According to Unit Police Services (SPU), the meeting aimed to discuss and monitor the latest changes and recommendations on international standards of the International Financial Action Group (FATF in the English acronym), so that participating members can “prepare in advance work for mutual evaluation”.
In addition, “members continue to study the need to review current legislation and international standards, in order to improve the legal system of the MSAR and its execution,” says the same note, without any details.
According to the SPU, the Working Group coordinates public and private entities and applies the resources of international organizations with a view to combating the bleaching of capital and the preceding crimes associated, in order to “play an active and effective role in the execution of the law, supervision and implementation of policies”.
In order to articulate with government policies and “ensure that Macao's financial system is not used by criminals to practice capital bleaching or other illicit financial activities”, the working group holds periodic meetings to analyze the trends and development of this type of crime.
Coordinated by the SPU Financial Information Office (GIF), this group integral representatives of the Public Prosecution Service, Commissioner against Corruption, Customs Services, Directorate of Justice Services, Monetary Authority, Directorate of Inspection and Coordination of Games, Directorate of Technological Economics and Development Services, Directorate of Finance Services, Judiciary Police, Public Security Police, Housing Institute and Disciplinary Commission on the disciplinary power the solicitors.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Guangdong circulation “materialized” later this year</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/circulacao-para-guangdong-materializada-ainda-este-ano/</link><description>The operational issues of circulation to other regions of Guangdong Province of “Vehicles with single registration circulating between Macau and Hengqin” are already basically resolved, according to the Secretary for Administration and Justice. André Cheong revealed that “after conversation with their ministries and commissions”, the procedures of appreciation and approval are underway.
In parallel, in response to an oral interpellation of Deputy Nick Lei, he stressed that, “in articulation with the implementation of this policy, it is necessary to proceed to the complementary work, such as the revision of the single -registration vehicle management method and the creation of the second line border information system, among others”. If all goes well, the government “expects politics to be materialized later this year,” he said.
Taking into account the maximum road capacity of the border post and the respective roads to leave Hengqin Island in the early phase of the circulation policy to other regions of Guangdong Province of “unique enrollment vehicles circulating between Macau and Hengqin”, only the owners of “unique enrollment” who live, reside, work and entrepreneurs in the deepen cooperation zone can require circulation to other regions of Guangdong Province.
André Cheong recalled that since January 24 this year, hengqin is already installed in exclusive channels in the Security Inspection Zone located at the Hengqin border post towards Macao, intended for MSAR residents, multiple tourists and exits, elderly over 60 years old, children under 3 years old, pregnant and other mobility difficulties.
The secretary assured that the government has maintained a dialogue with the competent services in the interior of China, "to facilitate the displacement between Macau and Hengqin of the living territory residents, study, work and seek entrepreneurship in the in -depth cooperation zone."
 
V.R.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Public revenues dropped 5% until April</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/receitas-publicas-baixaram-5-ate-abril/</link><description>MSAR CURRENT REVENUE fell 4.95% in the first four months of the year, compared to the same period of 2024, especially due to a drop in financial revenues. Between January and April, current revenue was 34 billion patacas, according to data published on the Electronic Page of the Directorate of Finance Services (DSF).
The main reason for the decrease resided in financial revenues, which went from billion in the first four months of 2024 to only six thousand patacas this year. This heading corresponds to the results of the Monetary Authority of Macao, and includes investment and interest and dividends revenues.
In addition, the data also reveals a drop of 0.06%, to 29.8 billion patacas in tax revenues, which still represented 84.7% of the total. The six city game operators pay a 35% direct tax on game revenues, 2.4% for the Macao Social Security Fund and urban and tourist development, and 1.6% delivered to the Macao Foundation for cultural, educational, scientific, academics and philanthropic purposes.
Taxes on the game fell, although Macao casinos registered total revenues of 76.5 billion patacas in the first four months of the year, more 0.8% than in the same period of 2024. Between January and April, Macau collected 30.2% of current revenue projected for 2025 in the budget, which is 112.6 billion.
Globally, including capital revenues, administration received 34.37 billion patacas, 4.8% less than in the first four months of 2024.
On the contrary, public expense rose 2.6%to 24 billion patacas), due to an expense of 874.7 million patacas in “actions and other participation”.
Macao ended April with a public account surplus of 10.3 billion patacas, less 18.5% than in the same period last year. Still, this value is already higher than the government's forecast for the year 2025: 6.83 billion patacas.
Macao closed 2024 with an surplus of 15.8 billion patacas, more than twice the one recorded the previous year.
On April 15, the chief executive, Sam Hou Fai, admitted to fear a budgetary deficit in 2025, due to the slowdown in the game's recipes.
 
JTM WITH LUSA</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Trainees rose 17% in language courses</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/formandos-subiram-17-nos-cursos-de-linguas/</link><description>In 2024, nearly 1,800 vocational training courses were held with more than 76,000 participants, numbers that reflect annual breaks. However, trainees in language courses grew 16.8%, according to official data
 
Over the past year, 67 institutions (more than in 2023) took 1,777 vocational training courses, with the participation of 76,385 trainees, representing 7.2% and 21.8%, respectively, compared to the previous year, the Directorate of Statistics and Census Services (DSEC) (DSEC) said yesterday. According to the body, these annual breaks derive mainly from the end of some temporary training plans, which had been implemented in response to the pandemic.
The most trainee areas continued to be “Trade and Administration” courses (17,898 participants; 27.3% less than in 2023) and “health” (10,343, more 8.1%), representing 23.4% and 13.5% of the total of graduates, respectively. However, the highest progress occurred in the “languages” courses, with the number of trainees increasing 16.8% to 6,818 within one year, corresponding to 8.9% of the total.
In “Occupational Security” (6,534 graduates) there was an increase of 9.4%, while in the field of “Information and Communication Technologies” the number of participants fell 27.9% to 6,004. The courses related to “Education” (4,898), “Tourism and Leisure” (3,842), “Engineering and Construction” (3580) and “Hotels and Restoration Services” (2,751) and “Arts and Design” (2,521) also suffered sharp decreases of 27.7%, 38.9%, 26.5%, 53.2%, respectively.
According to DSEC data, the number of courses for the public (896) and the trainees (35,140) fell 12.5%and 30.6%, respectively, compared to 2023. The courses intended for companies/institutions/organs (881) lowered 1.1%, in annual terms, and the number of graduates (41,245) decreased 12.3%.
At the end of last year, institutions that promoted vocational courses employed 1,885 people (another 51 in one year), of which 1,138 (54) were teaching staff (including full and partial time staff).
The DSEC survey covered public, private and higher education institutions in Macao who took vocational training courses as a main activity and were in activity in the year 2024.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>GPM Museum gains more animation on the birthday of remodeling</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/museu-gpm-ganha-mais-animacao-aniversario-da-remodelacao/</link><description>On June 1st, the Macau Grand Prix Museum will organize a set of activities to mark the fourth anniversary of the museum's reopening. The magic shows, guided tours and workshops aim to make known the “singular charm” of the Macau Motorized Sport event

The Macao Grand Prix Museum will hold a series of special activities to celebrate the fourth anniversary since its reopening, the Tourism Services (STD) directed, inviting interested parties to “feel the singular charm of the Grand Prix”. The public will have the opportunity to experience the elements of “Tourism + Sport” and “to know closely the development of this great Macao motor sport event”, says the statement, noting that the museum has interactive facilities and a “large amount of precious objects” that show the “glorious history” of the event.
Throughout June 1st, the entrance will be free and visitors will be able to participate in workshops, watch magic shows and find discounts at the souvenir store. The shows will take place at 10:30, at 1:30 pm and 4:00 pm, during which professional magicians will distribute thematic balloons of the Grand Prix, in a limited number.
On the same day, the museum will organize the workshop “Creative Running and Mosaic Camp”, which combines the “History of the Great Award” with “Artistic Creation” so that participants can learn about the culture of the sports event.
According to STD, the activity consists of a professional guided tour and a production experience, both 45 minutes. First will be presented the historical origin of the Macao Grand Prix and knowledge about the event. Later, participants will be able to learn about the uniqueness and history of the culture of the great award, through exhibitions, historical photographs and explanatory texts,
There will be a “experimentation session” under the theme “Triumph Tr2”, the winning car of the first edition of the event. For an hour and a half, participants will be guided by professional instructors “in a production process that connects the history of the Macao Grand Prix to the cars on display of the museum”.
The workshop will be free and will take place in three sessions, at 11:00, at 14:00 and 4:30 pm, whose pre-regret is open until 18:00 on May 21, and the names will be drawn. The activity is intended for young people, between six and 12 years, and they can be accompanied by their carers, to a limit of 15 pairs per session.
In order to make known the culture of the “emblematic event” in an innovative way and emphasizing an experience of “fun education”, the museum has continually introduced new elements “to enrich the experience of residents and visitors”, according to STD.
The Grand Prix Museum is open daily between 10:00 and 18:00, ending on Tuesdays.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>Preventive arrest for false police suspected of violation</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/local/prisao-preventiva-para-falso-policia-suspeito-de-violacao/</link><description>Following the first judicial interrogation and under the promotion of the Public Prosecution Service (MP), the Criminal Instruction Judge applied to him the measure of coercion of custody to an individual suspected of undergoing police and violation. According to the MP, defendant was involved in several cases in which he falsely frightened the police quality, having served a sentence for the crime of usurpation of duties. Recently, “it will have been going through police once again and will have embarrassed the offended to perform sexual act with him using acts of violence,” says the MP's statement. Subsequently, the defendant also required the victim to pledge his mobile phone and raise the money from the mobile phone payment account, but failed to do what he wanted. The judge considered there to be strong evidence of the crimes of violation and usurpation of functions, as well as the attempted practice of the crime of extortion. Under the provisions of the Criminal Procedure Code, the MP will continue to direct the further investigation procedure.</description><pubDate>2025-05-16 00:00:00</pubDate></item><item><title>New Cannes Clothing Code forces Halle Berry to change clothes</title><link>https://jtm.com.mo/lazer/novo-codigo-de-vestuario-de-cannes-obriga-halle-berry-trocar-de-roupa/</link><description>EPA12096429 JUY MEMBERS South Korean Director Hong Sang-Soo (L) and US ACTOR HALLE BERRY (R) ATTEND A Press Conference Ahead of the Opening of the 78th Annual Cannes Film Festival, In Cannes, France, 13 May 2025. The Film Festival Runes from 13 to 24 May 2025. EPA / TRISTAN Fewings / Pool *** Local Caption ***



Halle Berry, an Óscar-winning actress, was caught by surprise by the new Cannes Festival clothing code and had to change her choice of clothes at the last minute, told reporters on Tuesday.
According to the rules, nudity is not allowed on the red treadmill, and “bulky clothes, in particular those of Grande tail”, which block the way of other guests and complicate the places in the theater, are no longer allowed. The organizers warned that they could deny access to the red treadmill to those who did not respect the rules.
"I had an amazing Gupta dress to wear tonight, and I can't wear it because the tail is too big," Halle Berry, who is a member of the festival jury this year at a press conference.
"I had to change ideas. But I think the part of nudity is also a good rule," added the American star who won an Oscar for the 2001 movie Monster's Ball.
In recent years, guests and celebrities on the red treadmill have challenged the boundaries of the festival's clothing code with giant tails, transparent dresses and clothes that leave the nipples on display.
Kanye West and his wife, Bianca Censori, caused the Grammy Awards red treadmill in February, when Censori took a huge coat to reveal a transparent dress with nothing underneath.
 
Cinema stars denounce “silence” before “genocide” in Gaza
Several world film stars, including Pedro Almodóvar, Susan Sarandon and Richard Gere, denounced the "silence" of the world of culture in the face of "genocide" in Gaza, in a statement published in the French newspaper "Liberio", coinciding with the opening of the Cannes Film Festival. "We, artists and actors/actors of the cultural scope, we cannot remain silent while a genocide in Gaza is held," says the about 380 signatories of the text, which pays tribute to Fatima Hassouna, a deceased photojournalist in Israeli bombardment in April and protagonist of a documentary programmed in Cannes. The manifesto was published in printed version on the morning of opening the largest film festival in the world, a ceremony marked by the delivery of the Honorary Golden Palm to Robert de Niro, legend of the cinema and declared opponent of US President Donald Trump. Two filmmakers awarded the golden palm, Justine Triet and Ruben Östlund, as well as numerous actors and actors (Javier Bardem, Ralph Fiennes, etc.) signed the text. "What is our profession, if not to learn from history, from engaged movies, if we are not present to protect the oppressed voices?" Asks the signatories, who ask "in the name of all those who die in indifference."
 
JTM with international agencies</description><pubDate>2025-05-15 00:00:00</pubDate></item></channel></rss>